<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167802</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Self-Perceived work disability in a school of children with special  needs</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims. Increased psychosocial and physical demands of the Special Education Centers (SEC) workers can also lead to intense involvement, triggering stressful and to trigger stress situations and potentially work disability. The objective of this study was to assess the self-perceived occupational disability and its relation with socio-demographic, occupational and health variables with in a sample of this these workers. Methods. Cross-sectional study with of 40 SEC workers of in Murcia (Spain) (n = 40). The Spanish WRFQ version was used to measure self-perceived work ability. A structured self-administered questionnaire was used for to collect sociodemographic, occupational, and health variables. A descriptive analysis of the studied variables was performed. Differences between groups were studied using the Mann-Whitney U test, Student's T test and Kruskal-Wallis test. Results.The mean age of the sample was 40.15 ± 10.53 years; 82.5% were women, 60% were computer users and 92.50% were directly attending children. The subscales of production requirements and physical demands had the worst results. Workers &lt;40 years presented lower scores in for the time management subscales (p = 0.002) and production requirements (p = 0.01); Computer computer users in time management (p &lt;0.001), production requirements (p &lt;0.001) and psychological requirements (p = 0.005); as well as among those working as managers and healthcare employeesthe employment status of executive and sanitary. Conclusions.The level of self-perceived occupational disability is was low in this collective, with the subscales of production requirements and physical requirements being the worst evaluated. The working conditions related to a higher degree of self-perceived occupational disability are were the use of of a computer, the employment status and the manual materials handling (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Gracia, María Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramada Rodilla, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seguí Crespo, María del Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina Torres, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Las elevadas exigencias psicosociales y físicas de los trabajadores de los Centros de Educación Especial (CEE), conllevan una  alta implicación y pueden desencadenar situaciones de estrés y discapacidad laboral. El objetivo de este estudio es evaluar la discapacidad laboral auto-percibida y su relación con variables sociodemográficas, laborales y de salud, en una muestra de trabajadores de este colectivo. Métodos. Estudio transversal realizado con trabajadores (n=40) de un CEE de Murcia (España). Se utilizó la versión en castellano del WRFQ para medir la capacidad laboral auto-percibida, y un cuestionario ad hoc para variables sociodemográficas, laborales y de salud. Se realizó un análisis descriptivo de las variables estudiadas. Las diferencias entre grupos se estudiaron mediante las pruebas U de Mann-Whitney, T de Student y Kruskal-Wallis. Resultados. La edad media de los participantes fue 40,15 ± 10,53 años, el 82,5% fueron mujeres, el 60% usuarios de ordenador y el 92,50% realizaba atención directa a niños. Las subescalas de exigencias de la producción y exigencias físicas obtuvieron los peores resultados. Presentaron puntuaciones inferiores los trabajadores &lt;40 años en las subescalas de gestión del tiempo (p=0,002) y exigencias de producción (p=0,01); los que empleaban ordenador en gestión del tiempo (p&lt;0,001), exigencias de la producción (p&lt;0,001) y exigencias psicológicas (p=0,005); así como la categoría laboral de directivo y sanitario. Conclusiones. El nivel de discapacidad laboral auto-percibida es bajo, siendo las subescalas exigencias de la producción y exigencias físicas las peor valoradas. Las condiciones de trabajo relacionadas con un mayor grado de discapacidad laboral auto-percibida son el uso de ordenador, la categoría laboral y el manejo de cargas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. prev. riesgos labor. (Ed. impr.);20(4): 203-213, oct.-dic. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167802</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Discapacidad laboral auto-percibida en trabajadores de un centro de educación especial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54263^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15336</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32027^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
