<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89173</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of osteoporosis as assessed by "os calcaneus" ultrasonography among a working population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Osteoporosis ranks among the diseases having increased their prevalence over the last years because of the increase in life expectancy. Prevention can be achieved as from the middle ages of life through early diagnosis and lifestyle modifications. Objective: To assess the prevalence of osteoporosis among workers of a local management enterprise. Methods: Cross-sectional, descriptive, disease-prevalence study. Within a company encompassing 1,500 workers, volunteer ultrasound bone densitometry assessments were performed. The following variables were analyzed: age, gender, weight, height, BMI, BUA (broad-band ultrasound attenuation), proportion (%) to the normal population, Z-score and T-score. The Statgraphics Plus software was used for the statistical calculations.Results: The overall prevalence of osteoporosis was  21.83%, with a clear predominance of the male gender (42.5% vs. 17.46% in females). Conclusions: There was a high prevalence of osteoporosis among the males in the studied population (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ares Camerino, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sainz Vera, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez Collantes, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La osteoporosis es una de las enfermedades que han aumentado su prevalencia en los últimos años debido al aumento de la esperanza de vida. Su prevención se puede realizar desde la edad media de la vida realizando un diagnóstico precoz y modificando estilos de vida. Objetivo: Conocer la prevalencia de la osteoporosis entre los trabajadores de una empresa de administración local. Metodología: Estudio transversal descriptivo de prevalencia de enfermedad. En una empresa de 1.500 trabajadores se realizó, de forma voluntaria, una densitometría ósea ultrasónica. Se analizaron las siguientes variables: edad, sexo, peso, talla, IMC, BUA (broadband ultrasound attenuation), porcentaje en comparación con la población normal, Z-score, T-score. Los cálculos estadísticos se analizaron con el programa Statgraphics Plus. Resultados: La prevalencia de la osteoporosis fue del 21,83%, con un claro predominio en el sexo masculino (42,5%) y con un 17,46% en mujeres. Conclusiones: Alta prevalencia de la osteoporosis entre la población masculina estudiada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;17(1): 30-35, abr. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89173</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de la osteoporosis determinada por ultrasonografía de calcáneo en una población laboral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23176^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32334^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
