<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-66121</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Self-medication is the situation in which patients obtained and use drugs that are not prescribed or recommended by the doctor and in which the treatment is not supervised. It represents a part of the self-cares and should be taken into account because of its frequency and its repercussions since these may be both negative and positive. Self-medication is based on the patient&#146;s own decision. However, this initiative is modulated by several factors, primarily related with the patient, the condition, social setting pharmacists and the professionals. This should be considered from a multifactorial and multidisciplinary approach with the active participation of different groups and institutions. As principal measures to be established, health care education on self-medication can be mentioned both in positive terms about its benefits and the negative ones about its risks, the rational use of drugs in the daily clinical practice and a firm attitude regarding demand for medications to the doctors and pharmacists</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Calcerrada, R. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orueta, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La automedicación es la situación en la que los pacientes consiguen y utilizan medicamentos sin participación del médico ni en la prescripción ni en la supervisión del tratamiento. Representa una parte de los autocuidados y debe ser tenida en cuenta tanto por su frecuencia como por sus repercusiones, ya que estas pueden ser positivas o negativas. La automedicación se basa en la propia decisión del paciente, pero dicha iniciativa está modulada por diversos factores relacionados principalmente con el propio paciente, con el proceso, con el entorno social, con los farmacéuticos y con los profesionales. Su abordaje debe realizarse desde un enfoque multifactorial y multidisciplinar con la participación activa de diferentes colectivos e instituciones. Como medidas principales a implementar pueden citarse la educación sanitaria sobre la automedicación tanto en términos positivos de sus beneficios como negativos de sus riesgos, el uso racional de medicamentos en la práctica clínica diaria y la actitud de firmeza frente a la demanda de medicamentos de los médicos y de los farmacéuticos</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);34(3): 133-137, mar. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-66121</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4422^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13037^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13031^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
