<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159572</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The need of a new integral approach to the care of patient with severe mental disorder thirty years after the psychiatric reform</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">More than thirty years have passed since the beginning of the psychiatric reform, a period of intense and relevant social, scientific and cultural changes which have directly impacted on mental disorders and their management. Improvement in psychopharmacological treatment, a new model of physician-patient relationship, patient´s empowerment as a key issue and the fight against social stigma related to mental health disorders, changes in clinical governance and health policy, the assistential burden derived from the treatment of less severe pathology in mental health community centers, improvements in teamwork and coordination with other resources involved&#133; are some of the relevant changes which determine the scene of community-based mental health assistance. We think this is a right time to check the state of the community-based care programmes for severe mental disorders, and the role of mental health center. We propose to have a reflexion about two relevant topics: where we are and where we are heading (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ballesteros Martín, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Yagüe, Ernesto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leira Sanmartín, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Madoz-Gúrpide, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Han pasado más de 30 años desde el inicio de los procesos de reforma psiquiátrica, periodo además de importantes e intensos cambios sociales, científicos y culturales que afectan de manera directa a la enfermedad mental grave y a su manejo. Las mejoras del tratamiento farmacológico, un nuevo modelo de relación médico-paciente, el empoderamiento del paciente como elemento clave y la lucha contra el estigma social de la enfermedad, los cambios en la gestión de los recursos, el incremento de la carga que suponen los pacientes con patología menor en los centros de salud mental, las mejoras en el trabajo en equipo y en la coordinación de los recursos implicados&#133; son algunas de las modificaciones importantes que condicionan el escenario de la atención en salud mental comunitaria. Se nos antoja, por tanto, como un buen momento para revisar el estado de los programas de gestión del trastorno mental grave en el adulto y de los centros de salud mental, y plantear dos cuestiones sencillas a la par que relevantes: dónde estamos y hacia dónde nos dirigimos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;91: 0-0, 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159572</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Necesidad de un nuevo enfoque en la atención integral a los pacientes con trastorno mental grave treinta años después de la reforma psiquiátrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31424^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3188^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3285^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3188^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3285^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53395^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3188^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3190^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3222^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3222^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54298</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
