<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85752</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Radial Head Arthroplasty using metallic prosthesis in unreconstructible fractures. Our experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze the outcomes using metallic prosthesis in unreconstructible radial head fractures. Materials and methods: Nine patients with conminuted radial head fractures in which metallic prosthetic arthroplasty was performed were retrospectively evaluated using the Mayo Elbow Performance Index (MEPI) and the DASH questionnaire. The mean follow-up were eighteen (5-42) months. Pain, mobility, X-Rays outcomes and complications were also evaluated. Results: there were four excellent results, three good, one fair and one bad using the MEP score . The average range of motion was 110º of flexo-extension, (60º-145º), 64º of pronation (50º-70º) and 72º of supination (35º-80º). Five complications were observed. Conclusion: The use of radial head metallic prosthesis is an option for the treatment of conminuted radial head fractures in selected cases with a high rate of complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morales Muñoz, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano Egea, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerra Vélez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Rodríguez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Fernández, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar los resultados obtenidos con la atroplastia de cabeza radial mediante prótesis metálicas en fracturas no reconstruibles. Material y métodos: Estudio observacional en 9 pacientes con fractura conminuta de la cabeza radial tratadas con prótesis metálicas. Se evaluaron retrospectivamente mediante el Mayo Elbow Performance Index (MEPI) y el cuestionario DASH. También evaluamos la presencia de dolor, los arcos de movilidad, los hallazgos radiográficos y la aparición de complicaciones. El seguimiento medio fue de dieciocho (5-42) meses. Resultados: Tras un seguimiento medio de dieciocho meses (5-42) se obtuvieron cuatro resultados excelentes, tres buenos, uno regular y uno malo según la escala MEPI. El arco de movilidad fue de 110º de flexo-extensión (60º- 145º), 64º de pronación (50º-70º) y 72º de supinación (35º-80º). Aparecen complicaciones en cinco pacientes. Conclusiones: El uso de prótesis metálicas de cabeza radial es una opción terapéutica para casos seleccionados de fracturas conminutas de cabeza radial con una elevada tasa de complicaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);21(4): 200-206, oct.-dic. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85752</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Artroplastia de cabeza radial mediante prótesis metálicas en fracturas no reconstruibles. Nuestra experiencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33576^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12319^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33576^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33576^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11916^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12319^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4624^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4624^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
