<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116656</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patient with testosterone deficit syndrome after radical prostatectomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Testosterone Deficiency Syndrome is associated with age. Recent studies advocate for the safety of hormonal treatment with testosterone in patients with history of Prostate Cancer (PC), once disease-free survival is confirmed. A total of five publications describe 110 patients treated with testosterone replacement therapy, having a history of PC, who had undergone radical prostatectomy (RP). Only one patient had biochemical recurrence during replacement therapy. Testosterone replacement therapy must be indicated in selected patients with history of low risk localized prostate cancer treated satisfactorily who are symptomatic and have good oncological control. The testosterone levels to achieve should be the minimum effective to obtain a symptomatic response. Adequate information on the benefits and potential risks must be understood and accepted by the patient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Portillo, Luis del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morgentaler, Abraham</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carballido, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Linares Espinós, Estefanía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Salamanca, Juan I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Areche, Jennifer</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moncada, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Izquierdo, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de déficit de testosterona (SDT) define un cuadro clínico y bioquímico asociado a la edad que produce un detrimento en la calidad de vida de estos pacientes. Estudios recientes abogan por la seguridad del tratamiento hormonal con testosterona en pacientes con historia de cáncer de próstata (CP) al no haberse demostrado inducción de este tumor. Un total de cinco publicaciones presentan resultados de 110 pacientes tratados con testosterona con historia de CP intervenidos mediante prostatectomía radical (PR). Solo un paciente presentó recidiva bioquímica durante el tratamiento sustitutivo. La terapia de reemplazamiento con testosterona ha de ser indicada en pacientes seleccionados que se encuentren sintomáticos y con historia de cáncer localizado de bajo riesgo tratado de manera satisfactoria y buen control oncológico. Las cifras de testosterona a alcanzar y mantener serán las mínimas eficaces que permitan obtener una respuesta sintomática. Una correcta y adecuada información de los beneficios y potenciales riesgos han de ser entendidos y aceptados por el paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;66(7): 663-668, sept. 2013. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116656</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Paciente con SDT tras prostatectomía radical</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14118^s22015</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
