<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88369</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Chronic unipolar mania. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Bipolar disorder is a phasic mental disorder characterized by the presence of (hypo) maniac, depressive and/or mixed episodes during the course of the disease. Clinical case. A middle-age man, with no prior history of depressive episodes, began to suffer a picture of manic characteristics as an adolescent that has lasted for 18 years. Despite the numerous drug treatments prescribed, there has been no improvement, and the disorder has followed a torpid and chronic course. Conclusions. Chronic unipolar mania is a clinical entity appearing as a residual characteristic in the current psychiatric nosology. Its low prevalence makes it difficult to carry out research aimed at elucidating whether it has a subordinate or independent relationship with the bipolar disorder. A systematic assessment of the effectiveness of electroconvulsive therapy is needed in these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Frías-Ibáñez, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Carrera, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cervera-Elegido, Noelia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero-Cervera, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El trastorno bipolar es una patología mental de naturaleza fásica, caracterizada por la presencia de episodios (hipo) maníacos, depresivos y/o mixtos que se suceden a lo largo del curso de la enfermedad. Caso clínico. Se expone el caso de un varón de mediana edad, sin antecedentes de episodios depresivos, que inició en la adolescencia un cuadro de características maniformes de 18 años de evolución. A pesar de los numerosos tratamientos farmacológicos prescritos, no se apreció mejoría alguna, presentando un curso tórpido, tendente a la cronicidad. Conclusiones. La manía unipolar crónica es una entidad clínica representada de una manera residual en la nosología psiquiátrica actual. Su ínfima prevalencia dificulta la investigación orientada a dilucidar su naturaleza subordinada o independiente del trastorno bipolar. Se hace necesaria una evaluación sistematizada de la efectividad de la terapia electroconvulsiva con estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;39(2): 143-146, mar.-abr. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88369</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manía unipolar crónica. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4637^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
