<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163589</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Lifestyles, overweight and obesity. empirical evidence for the urban population in Argentina. 2005-2009</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Rationale: In Argentina adult overweight and obesity increased more than 4% between 2005 and 2009 exceeding 50% of total adults living in urban areas. The objective of this work is to estimate the relationship between adult overweight and constituent characteristics, habits, family composition and socioeconomic factors. Methods: We estimate conditional probability models with and without correction for possible sample selection bias. Estimations are based on microdata bases from National Risk Factor Survey 2005 and 2009. Results: Constituent factors (gender, age) are relevant predictors of overweight. However, lifestyles, habits and socioeconomic factor are important Conclusions: The design of policies to reduce excess weight should take into account the lifestyles and socioeconomic conditions of the target population to improve their effectiveness (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Temporelli Braun, Karina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viego Mediavilla, Valentina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: En Argentina los adultos con sobrepeso y obesidad aumentaron más de un 4% entre 2005 y 2009, superando el 50% del total de la población adulta urbana. El objetivo de este trabajo es estimar la probabilidad de que un adulto registre sobrepeso en función de sus características constitutivas, hábitos, conformación familiar y factores socioeconómicos. Método: Se estimaron modelos de probabilidad condicional con y sin corrección por posible sesgo de selección muestral. Se utilizan las bases de microdatos de la Encuesta Nacional de Factores de Riesgo 2005 y 2009. Resultados: Los factores constitutivos (género, edad) son relevantes como predictores de problemas de sobrepeso. No obstante, los estilos de vida, los hábitos que ellos implican y los factores socioeconómicos también son importantes. Conclusión: El diseño de políticas tendientes a disminuir el exceso de peso deben tener en cuenta los estilos de vida y condiciones socioeconómicas de la población objetivo a fin de mejorar su efectividad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;21(3): 10-17, jul.-sept. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163589</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estilos de vida, sobrepeso y obesidad. Evidencia empírica para la población urbana adulta argentina. 2005-2009</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d16571^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1121^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14904^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
