<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040087</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6709</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Application of molecular nucleic acid-based techniques for the study of microbial communities in monuments and artworks</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Microorganisms play critical roles in every kind of habitat on Earth, including those constructed by humans. Thus, our cultural heritage is affected by microbial colonization. While classical microbiological methods based on culturing procedures have provided important, but limited information on the microbial diversity of natural samples, novel molecular techniques have been extremely valuable in unraveling the diversity of microbiota involved in the biodeterioration of our monuments and artworks. The knowledge gained from these approaches has allowed the design of strategies for conserving and protecting monuments for the benefit of future generations. This review describes the state-of-the-art of the application of molecular methods to the analysis of cultural assets, and provides near-future perspectives on the subject (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González, Juan M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saiz-Jiménez, Cesáreo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los microorganismos desempeñan papeles críticos en todo tipo de hábitat de la Tierra, incluso en los que han sido construidos por los humanos. Así, el patrimonio cultural también se ve afectado por la colonización de microorganismos. Mientras los métodos clásicos de microbiología basados en procedimientos de cultivo han proporcionado información importante, pero limitada, de las muestras naturales, las nuevas técnicas moleculares son muy valiosas para descubrir la diversidad de la microbiota causante del biodeterioro de monumentos y obras de arte. El conocimiento alcanzado con estos métodos ha permitido diseñar estrategias adecuadas para la conservación y protección de monumentos, en beneficio de generaciones futuras. Esta revisión describe la situación actual de la aplicación de métodos moleculares al análisis de bienes culturales y aporta perspectivas para un futuro próximo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int Microbiol;8(3): 189-194, sept. 2005. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040087</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicación de técnicas moleculares basadas en ácidos nucleicos al estudio de comunidades microbianas en monumentos y obras de arte</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35408^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12994</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28913</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32430</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3359</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32433</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28047</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
