<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058908</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0973</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cloninger&#146;s psychobiological model in opiate dependent individuals</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive. To study the relationship    between Cloninger&#146;s personality dimensions and    drug misuse in opiate dependents sample.    Material and methods. Cross-sectional study. 196    subjects were obtained from consecutive sampling    among opiate dependents that were admitted in a    detoxification unit in a General Hospital. The sample    was analysed by a Drug Abuse Questionnaire    and the Temperament and Character Inventory. After    the descriptive analysis of variables, mean differences    tests were used for the Cloninger&#146;s dimensions    comparing multiple-substance dependents with single-substance ones, and between different    groups attending to the consumption pattern. Also,    the correlation between Cloninger&#146;s dimensions and    the number of substance dependences were analysed,    and a lineal regression model was obtained to    evaluate how those dimensions of personality could    predict the number of substances for dependence.    Results. Results suggest that substance&#146;s type    could be influenced by temperament variables,    while the addiction&#146;s severity, mainly the dependence    to one or more substances, could be influenced    more by character ones.    Conclusions. More studies are needed, mainly    longitudinal, to confirm the relationship between    personality dimensions and substances dependence,    because the results of this study suggest that the    personality and the substances dependence are    etio-pathologically inter-related</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cervera Martínez, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Abolafio, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orengo Caus, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballester Sánchez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Haro Cortés, Y. G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benito Delegido, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Estudiar las relaciones entre    las dimensiones de personalidad de Cloninger y el    consumo de sustancias en una muestra de drogodependientes.    Material y métodos. Estudio transversal. Los 196    sujetos del estudio se obtuvieron por muestreo consecutivo    entre los pacientes dependientes de opiáceos    que ingresaban en una Unidad de Desintoxicación    Hospitalaria. A los sujetos se les evaluó con un    Cuestionario de Consumo de Sustancias y el Temperament    and Character Inventory. Tras el estudio    descriptivo de las variables, se realizaron pruebas    de diferencia de medias en las dimensiones de Cloninger    comparando por un lado el grupo de politoxicómanos    y el grupo de los que dependían de una    sola sustancia, y por otro, varios grupos con diferentes    patrones de consumo. También se estudió la    correlación entre las dimensiones de Cloninger y el    número de sustancias de las que dependían los sujetos    y se creó un modelo de regresión lineal para    evaluar si las dimensiones de personalidad permitían    predecir el número de sustancias de las que    dependían los sujetos.    Resultados. Los resultados sugieren que la elección    de las sustancias de abuso podría estar influida    por variables temperamentales, mientras que la    gravedad de la adicción, en concreto, el hecho de    depender de una o más sustancias estaría más relacionado    con variables caracteriales.    Conclusiones. Recomendar la realización de más    estudios, especialmente longitudinales, para confirmar    las relaciones entre las dimensiones de la personalidad    y la dependencia de sustancias, pues,    atendiendo a los resultados expuestos, la personalidad    y el abuso de sustancias están etiopatogénicamente    interrelacionados</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trastor. adict;9(2): 108-115, abr. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058908</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El modelo psicobiológico de Cloninger en dependientes de opiáceos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10742^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9488^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
