<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136823</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Historical development of MDMA use and abuse</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">MDMA (ecstasy) has undoubtedly been the most popular recreational drug during the last decade. In spite of its having been synthesised in 1912 it was not employed as a drug by different groups in the United States until the end of the seventies (students, yuppies, gays, and new agers). In 1985 it was included in List I of the Amercican Comprehensive Substances Act, and in 1986, the WHO included it in List I of the Psychotropic Convention. Its greater spread on a worldwide bases has been associated with specific musical and recreational subcultures. In Spain, its spread has been over 5 different phases: previous phase (1978-1986), initial phase (1987-1989), popularity phase (1990-1991), phase of common use and masive consumption (1992-1996), and routine and end of cycle or stabilisation phase (1997-). During the last few years a considerable interest has been shown by international and national organisations to begin joint actions in order to know the real epidemiological magnitud of the phenomenon, its consequences on health, and the development of preventive actions to ameliorate the potential risks associated with its consumption (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bobes García, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáiz Martínez, Pilar A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paredes Ojanguren, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Portilla González, Paz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La MDMA (éxtasis), es sin duda, la droga que mayor popularidad ha alcanzado durante la última década. A pesar de haber sido sintetizada en 1912, no es hasta finales de los años 70 cuando comienza a ser utilizada por diversos grupos poblacionales en Estados Unidos (estudiantes, yuppies, gays y new agers). En el año 1985 es incluida en la Lista I de la Comprehensive Substances Act americana y en el año 1986, la OMS la incluye en la Lista I del Convenio sobre Psicotrópicos. Su posterior gran expansión a escala mundial se ha asociado a determinadas subculturas musicales y de ocio. En España, su difusión ha pasado por cinco fases diferentes: fase previa (1978-1986), fase inicial (1987-1989), fase de popularización (1990-1991), fase de vulgarización y consumo masivo (1992-1996) y fase de rutina y agotamiento del ciclo o fase de estabilización (1997-). Durante los últimos años existe cada vez mayor interés por parte de organismos internacionales y nacionales en la puesta en marcha de acciones conjuntas dirigidas a conocer la verdadera magnitud epidemiológica del fenómeno, sus consecuencias sobre la salud y en la puesta en marcha de acciones dirigidas a aminorar los potenciales daños asociados a su consumo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);15(supl.2): 35-49, 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136823</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución histórica del uso y abuso de MDMA</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32121^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23605^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12055^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200300</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
