<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149442</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Meeting on Palliative Care Education in Latin America Recommendations for teaching undergraduates and primary care health professionals</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In many Latin American countries Palliative Care development is still in the initial stages. A key reason is that the training of health professionals in this discipline, although intense and gradually increasing, is still insufficient, and with variable quality. The different institutions and organizations involved in the promotion and implementation of Palliative Care sponsored the first regional meeting on technical aspects of Palliative Care teaching to undergraduates and primary care health professionals. The meeting was held in Buenos Aires, Argentina in November 2012, and was attended by 60 professionals from diverse disciplines with teaching activity in Palliative Care from 11 different Latin American countries. Key issues in basic education in Palliative Care were identified and analyzed, challenges were identified, and recommendations were made overcome them. All the participants were in agreement that palliative care should be available and accessible for the majority of the patient population with life threatening conditions. Also, with the evidence that indicates that more patients may be able to receive appropriate care provided by primary care health care professionals, as long as they have the basic palliative care knowledge, skills and attitudes. This report describes the design and organization of the meeting and presents the results and recommendations related to teaching at the undergraduate and the primary care level (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lima, Liliana de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Wenk, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Centeno, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mutto, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berenguel, María del Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En muchos países de Latinoamérica el desarrollo del cuidado paliativo es aún incipiente. Una razón fundamental es que la formación de los profesionales de la salud en esta disciplina, aunque intensa y progresivamente mayor, es todavía insuficiente y de calidad variable. Diferentes instituciones y organizaciones relacionadas con la promoción e implementación del cuidado paliativo promovieron un primer encuentro regional sobre aspectos técnicos de la enseñanza de cuidado paliativo en el pregrado y el primer nivel de atención. La reunión se celebró en Buenos Aires, Argentina, en noviembre de 2012 y contó con la participación de 60 profesionales de diversas disciplinas con actividad docente en cuidado paliativo procedentes de 11 diferentes países latinoamericanos. Se identificaron y analizaron temas centrales en la enseñanza básica de cuidado paliativo, se identificaron aspectos que deben ser optimizados y se efectuaron recomendaciones para hacerlo. Todo el grupo estuvo de acuerdo con que el cuidado paliativo debería estar disponible y ser accesible para la mayor cantidad posible de pacientes con enfermedades de riesgo vital en estadios avanzados. También con la evidencia que muestra que más pacientes pueden recibir atención adecuada provista por profesionales del primer nivel de atención de salud, si adquieren los conocimientos, habilidades y actitudes básicas del cuidado paliativo. Este reporte describe el diseño y la organización del encuentro y se presentan los resultados y recomendaciones relacionadas con la docencia en el pregrado y el primer nivel de asistencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;23(1): 42-48, ene.-mar. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149442</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Encuentro sobre educación de cuidado paliativo en Latinoamérica. Recomendaciones sobre enseñanza en el pregrado y en el primer nivel de atención de salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55759^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
