<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75193</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4603</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The assessment of communicative and linguistic interaction related to language acquisition. Review of observational studies and rating scales</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">From the moment that sociocultural and ecofunctionaloriented authors started researching childdevelopment the amount of empirical studiesabout adult-child interaction in everyday contextsincreased dramatically. This is not surprising giventhe importance those researchers attach to theadult-child interaction in the psychological developmentof the child.In this paper we review studies that analyze earlyadult-child interaction that relates, in all or in part,to communication and language development ineveryday contexts. Most of them are observationalstudies that help specify the role every partnerplays during interactive communication, and at the same time try to identify reciprocal actions that,according to the theory expressed in the presentarticle, may affect child language development .We will analize observational studies that tookplace in spanish and catalan speaking culturalareas while the rating scales are of an internationalscopeWith this survey the authors pretend to review thepresent state of knowledge and establish the basisfor future instruments to be used in the assessmentof early daily interactions, mainly those processesthat are essential for the development of thechild's means to communicate and use language.We believe that the identification and assessmentof those processes will be of great help to speechtherapists and others involved in early interventionin language development and language disorders.Our final goal is to present the state of the art andfind future challenges thus promoting research inthis area that results in better and more preciseassessment and intervention practices with languageimpaired children and their families of ourown culture...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Galván-Bovaira, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rio, M. J. del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los estudios empíricos sobre la interacción adultoniñoen entornos cotidianos se multiplicaron a partirdel momento en que los autores de tendencia socioculturalse interesaron por el desarrollo infantil, locual no es de extrañar dado el papel relevante quedicha interacción puede desempeñar en la evoluciónpsicológica general del niño según dicho enfoque.En este trabajo se revisan una serie de estudios yescalas de evaluación que analizan y valoran la interaccióntemprana adulto-niño relacionada total o parcialmentecon el desarrollo comunicativo y lingüísticoy sus contextos cotidianos. Se trata de estudios que sehan llevado a cabo en entornos de lengua española ocatalana; las escalas, sin embargo, son de ámbitointernacional.El interés de las autoras al realizar esta revisión esconocer los antecedentes y sentar las bases de futurosinstrumentos que permitan evaluar la calidad deaquellos procesos interactivos cotidianos que másespecíficamente ayudan al niño a desarrollar sus propiosrecursos para comunicarse y usar el lenguaje.Facilitar la evaluación de dichos procesos contribuiríaa la labor de los profesionales dedicados al diagnósticoy a la intervención temprana en el área del lenguajey su patología.Se pretende como objetivo último analizar el estadode la cuestión así como establecer los retos pendientesen este ámbito de investigación que redunden enprocesos diagnósticos y de intervención cada vez másajustados a las necesidades de niños con dificultadesen la adquisición del lenguaje y de sus familias ennuestro entorno.La revisión constata el esfuerzo realizado para dotarde herramientas conceptuales y soporte metodológicoal estudio de la interacción comunicativa y lingüísticaen un entorno natural y para tratar de identificaractuaciones diádicas que impulsen eldesarrollo del lenguaje(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. logop. foniatr. audiol. (Ed. impr.);29(4): 225-236, oct.-dic.2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75193</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La evaluación de la interacción comunicativa y lingüística en relación a la adquisición del lenguaje infantil. Revisión de estudios observacionales y escalas de estimación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7982</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3487</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2713</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
