<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049932</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9744</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Elder abuse</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of this article is to analyze thedifferent kind of the maltreatment and the riskfactors of the elder abuse. Although we can findthis problem in the articles written in the last yearsof the nineteenth century where the way of lifein the Asylums was shown, it is in the eightiethdecade when the study of the elder abuse hashad an important impulse. Anyway we have to investigateprofoundly because now we know thatculture and social factors may condition even thedefinition of the elder abuse. In other way, it isvery important to study all the fields around violence:since the child abuse going through domesticviolence and sponce/intimate partner toelder abuse</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Picó Casanova, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este artículo es analizar los tiposde maltrato a las personas mayores que podemosencontrar, así como delimitar los factoresde riesgo de los mismos. Se trata de un temaque, aunque ya lo podemos encontrar en la literaturaa finales del siglo XIX con la denuncia delas condiciones de vida en los Hospicios y Asilos,no ha sido hasta la década de los 80 cuandose ha ampliado el campo de estudio del maltratoal mayor. Es un problema pendiente de investigaciónmás en profundidad ya que los condicionamientossociales y culturales de las distintaspartes del mundo influyen, incluso, en la definiciónde maltrato. Por otro lado el estudio de lallamada &#147;espiral de violencia&#148; será imprescindibleen el futuro</dc:description>
<dc:source>Geriátrika (Madr.);22(4): 128-132, abr. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049932</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Maltrato en el anciano</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6863</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4626</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38400</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
