<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139001</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Homework and academic achievement in Primary Education</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper analyzes the relationship between homework behavior and academic achievement using a sample of students from the last three years of primary education. The variables associated with student involvement in homework were the amount of homework completed, the time spent on homework, and homework time optimization, while academic achievement was estimated based on the grades in mathematics and foreign language (english). The possible effect of the course and gender when calculating the level of predictive variables concerning the homework on academic achievement was analyzed. The results indicated that the amount of homework done and the optimization of the time dedicated at homework significantly and positively predicted academic performance in both subjects. However, the amount of time spent on homework was not relevant. Finally, while gender was not statistically significant in predicting academic achievement, the course itself was statistically significant: as the course advances the mathematics achievement tends to diminish (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Núñez, José C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pan, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valle, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosário, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Regueiro, Bibiana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se analiza la relación entre la realización de deberes escolares y el rendimiento académico en una muestra de estudiantes de los tres últimos cursos de Educación Primaria. Las variables vinculadas con la implicación de los alumnos en los deberes escolares fueron el número de deberes realizados, el tiempo dedicado a los deberes y el aprovechamiento del tiempo dedicado a los deberes; mientras que el rendimiento académico fue estimado en base a las notas en matemáticas y lengua extranjera (inglés). Se ha tenido en cuenta el posible efecto del curso y del género a la hora de calcular el nivel predictivo de las variables relativas a los deberes sobre el rendimiento académico. Los resultados obtenidos indican que la cantidad de deberes realizados de los prescritos y el aprovechamiento del tiempo predicen positiva y significativamente el rendimiento académico en ambas asignaturas, mientras que la cantidad de tiempo dedicado a la realización de los deberes no es relevante. Finalmente, mientras que el género no resultó significativo en la predicción del rendimiento académico, el curso sí predijo negativamente el rendimiento en matemáticas: a medida que se asciende de curso el rendimiento en matemáticas tiende a disminuir (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;31(2): 562-569, mayo 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139001</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Deberes escolares y rendimiento académico en Educación Primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35173</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8037</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29745</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14876</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
