<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125042</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dislocation of the hip in a patient with von Recklinghausen disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Neurofibromatosis type 1 (NF-1) is one of the most common autosomal dominant disorders affecting humans. Patients with NF-1 may present with characteristic orthopaedic manifestations such as scoliosis, congenital pseudoarthrosis and limb hyperttrophy. Dislocation of the hip associated with NF-1 is a rare occurrence. There is a relative paucity of reported cases of pathological hip dislocation in patients with NF-1, with 13 documented cases found in the published literature. Seven dislocations occurred following trivial trauma and 6 cases were deemed atraumatic. We report a case of hip dislocation in a 26 years old male with NF-1 and scoliosis, that was treated successfully by closed reduction and skin traction (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bosque-Herrero, A. del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ezquerra-Herrando, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albareda-Albareda, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La neurofibromatosis tipo I (NF-1) es una de las enfermedades autosómicas dominantes más comunes que afecta a los humanos. Los pacientes con NF-1 pueden presentar características manifestaciones clínicas ortopédicas como son la escoliosis, pseudoartrosis congénita y la hipertrofia de la extremidad. La luxación de cadera asociada a la NF-1 es muy poco frecuente. Hay muy pocos casos publicados de luxación de cadera en pacientes con NF-1, encontrando 13 casos documentados en la bibliografía. Siete luxaciones ocurrieron tras un traumatismo leve y 6 fueron atraumáticas. Presentamosun caso de una luxación de cadera en un varón de 26 años con NF-1 y escoliosis que fue tratado satisfactoriamente con reducción cerrada y tracción blanda (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);58(4): 246-248, jul.-ago. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125042</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Luxación de cadera en un paciente con enfermedad de von Recklinghausen</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10577^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6776^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7163^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6776^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30295^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23397^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6776^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23397^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6776^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6776^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9647^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10577^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30295^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6776^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10581^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
