<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89031</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sclerosis physical intraluminal in safena veins. Surgical treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION. Varicose veins constitute a health problem, one in five women suffers from varicose veins, there are many and differents medical and surgical treatments, but now none has been ideal. OBJETIVES. Implement and evaluate the surgical technique of physical sclerosis intraluminal in patients with valvular veins safenas failure varicose veins carriers. Determine the complications introduced with the realization of this surgical technique and determine presented recurrences. PATIENTS AND METHODS. Research is clinical, experimental, applied, field, and longitudinal. Studied patients had varicose veins with valvular insufficiency of the safenas. The surgical technique consisted of ambulatory physical sclerosis intraluminal with spinal  anaesthesia. These results were compared with the surgical technique of safenectomy by classical methods results. RESULTS. This technique do not touch or piercing communicating. Postoperative complications were few like the recurrence. It can do in any kind of patient independent of their age and varicose veins state. This technique is better than other classical  surgical procedures performed on the service. CONCLUSIONS. The advantages of physical sclerosis intraluminal are: there is no necessary to paint the varicose veins before to operate. Do not use elastic bandages. The operating time is lower as local complications and recurrence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vega García, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernádez Cañete, C. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">INTRODUCCIÓN. Las várices constituyen un problema de salud, una de cada cinco mujeres padecen de várices, existen muchos tratamientos tanto médicos como quirúrgicos, pero en la actualidad ninguno ha resultado ideal. OBJETIVOS. Aplicar y evaluar la técnica quirúrgica de safenoesclerosis física intraluminal en enfermos portadores de várices con insuficiencia valvular  de las venas safenas. Determinar las complicaciones presentadas con la realización de esta técnica quirúrgica y determinar las recidivas presentadas. PACIENTES Y MÉTODOS. La investigación es clínica, experimental, de campo, aplicada y longitudinal. Los enfermos estudiados tenían várices con insuficiencia valvular de las safenas. La técnica quirúrgica consistió en una safenoesclerosis física intraluminal de forma ambulatoria y con anestesia espinal. Se compararon estos resultados con la técnica quirúrgica de safenectomía, por métodos clásicos. RESULTADOS. Con esta técnica no se tocan las comunicantes ni perforantes.INTRODUCTION. Varicose veins constitute a health problem, one in five women suffers from varicose veins, there are many and Las complicaciones postoperatorias fueron pocas al igual que las recidivas. Se puede realizar en cualquier tipo deenfermo independiente de su edad y estado varicoso. Esta técnica resulta superior a otros procederes quirúrgicos clásicos realizados en el servicio. CONCLUSIONES. Las ventajas de la safenoesclerosis física intraluminal son: no hay necesidad de dibujar las várices antes de operar. No se usan vendajes elásticos. El tiempo quirúrgico es menor así como las complicaciones locales y las recidivas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;13(2): 59-63, abr.-jun. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89031</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Safenoesclerosis física intraluminal en el tratamiento quirúrgico de las várices</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12978^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29897^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15051^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12878^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
