<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041301</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of somatostatin in five neonates with chylothorax</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. The addition of somatostatin to the conventional treatment of neonatal chylothorax has been described in isolated cases.         Objective. To describe the results obtained in a series of five patients with neonatal chylothorax treated with somatostatin. Patients. Five neonates (gestational age range: 29-39 weeks) diagnosed with chylothorax of various etiologies were included. Chylothorax was congenital in two neonates, secondary to congenital diaphragmatic hernia repair in two neonates and secondary to thrombosis in the superior vein cava in one neonate. All the neonates were started on conservative therapy and intravenous somatostatin in distinct doses ranging from a bolus of 2 &amp;#956;g/kg/12 h to continuous perfusion at 10 &amp;#956;g/kg/h.         Results. In all patients the chylous drainage was stopped. No adverse effects were observed.         Conclusions. Somatostatin can be a safe and effective option in the treatment of both primary and secondary neonatal chylothorax refractory to conservative treatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Álvarez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tarazona Fargueta, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mira Navarro, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Santacruz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Cobo, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. En pacientes aislados se ha descrito el uso de la somatostatina como una opción terapéutica adicional al tratamiento convencional del quilotórax neonatal.         Objetivo. Describir nuestros resultados en una serie de 5 pacientes con quilotórax neonatal tratados con somatostatina.         Pacientes. Se incluyeron 5 recién nacidos (29-39 semanas de edad gestacional) diagnosticados de quilotórax de diferentes etiologías: dos congénitos, dos secundarios a cirugía reparadora de hernias diafragmáticas congénitas, y uno secundario a trombosis venosa de la vena cava. Tras la confirmación diagnóstica se inició en todos los niños tratamiento conservador y somatostatina intravenosa en diferentes pautas, desde bolos de 2 &amp;#956;g/kg/12 h, hasta perfusión continua de 10 &amp;#956;g/kg/h.         Resultados. En todos los pacientes se logró el cese del drenaje linfático y no se observaron efectos secundarios.         Conclusiones. La somatostatina puede ser una opción terapéutica eficaz y segura en el tratamiento del quilotórax, tanto primario como secundario, refractario al tratamiento conservador</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);63(3): 244-248, sept. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041301</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento con somastotina en cinco recién nacidos con quilotórax de diferentes etiologías</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2941^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7410^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22676^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22228</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2941^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
