<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148650</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Proposed alternative to standard apomorphine challenge test</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Subcutaneous apomorphine injection is used as a rescue treatment in the off periods in moderate and advanced Parkinson&#146;s disease and also when required to assess the dopaminergic response. It is not recommended as a diagnostic tool in Parkinson&#146;s disease because it has more side effects and is less specific than chronic response to levodopa. To calculate the dosage, an apomorphine challenge test is performed, generally taking quite time and testing several doses. We propose an alternative apomorphine challenge test, with a single injection and a higher initial dosage of 2-4 mg, as well as to schedule treatment according to the obtained response at that dosage. This procedure saves time and also allows a better planning of medical attention (AU</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Castrillo, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burguera, Juan Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La apomorfina en inyecciones subcutáneas intermitentes se emplea como tratamiento de rescate de los períodos off en la enfermedad de Parkinson moderada-avanzada y para cuando se requiera evaluar la respuesta dopaminérgica. No es recomendable como prueba diagnóstica en la enfermedad de Parkinson, porque tiene más efectos adversos y es inferior a la respuesta crónica con levodopa. Para calcular la dosis se hace un test con apomorfina, que, en general, conlleva bastante tiempo y pruebas con dosis diversas. Proponemos un test alternativo, con una sola inyección, con una dosis inicial mayor, de entre 2-4 mg, y pautar el tratamiento según la respuesta obtenida a esta dosis. Con ello se gana tiempo y, además, se pueden preestablecer mucho mejor los tiempos de atención (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;55(supl.1): s11-s13, 31 dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148650</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Propuesta alternativa al test de apomorfina habitual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d938</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24230^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23948^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7453</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23948^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4365</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24230^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23948^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32276^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4354^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23960^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23960^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d982^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d982^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d982^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32276^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32276^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
