<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162819</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Subcutaneous lymphoid follicular hyperplasia secondary to vaccination: correlation of ultrasound findings with clinical and histological findings</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In recent years, the use of vaccines has been standardized within vaccination programs. Adverse effects at the puncture site are usually mild and transient. Nevertheless, in some cases, persistence subcutaneous nodules can develop; these are often underdiagnosed because they are so rare and because of the long time that can transpire between the vaccination and their appearance. Histologically, they consist of a lymphoid follicular hyperplasia that occurs as a reaction to the aluminum particles usually used as an adjuvant in some vaccines. We were unable to find any reference in the radiological literature to these soft-tissue nodules secondary to vaccination. We report the characteristic ultrasound findings that will enable radiologists to identify or strongly suspect these lesions and thereby avoid unnecessary imaging tests that might lead to confusion and inadequate management of these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez García, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo Martínez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro Copete, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calbo Maiques, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos años, el uso de vacunas se encuentra estandarizado dentro de los programas de vacunación. Los efectos adversos en el sitio de punción suelen ser leves y transitorios. Sin embargo, en algunos casos se pueden desarrollar nódulos subcutáneos persistentes, los cuales son a menudo infradiagnosticados debido a su rareza y al largo periodo de tiempo que puede transcurrir entre la vacunación y su aparición. Histológicamente, consisten en una hiperplasia folicular linfoide reactiva a partículas de aluminio usadas normalmente como adyuvante en algunas vacunas. No hemos encontrado bibliografía radiológica que haga referencia a estos nódulos de partes blandas secundarios a vacunas. Describimos los hallazgos ecográficos característicos de estas lesiones, que permitirán al radiólogo su reconocimiento y elaborar un diagnóstico de alta sospecha, evitando la realización de pruebas de imagen innecesarias que podrían llevar a confusión y por tanto a un manejo inadecuado de estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);59(3): 264-269, mayo-jun. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162819</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hiperplasia folicular linfoide subcutánea secundaria a vacunas: descripción de los hallazgos ecográficos y correlación clínico-patológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29411^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32953^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23123^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29411^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
