<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131597</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Differential effectiveness of two anxiety induction procedures in youth and older adult populations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this study, we tested in older and younger adults the efficacy of two well-known procedures to experimentally induce anxiety: a) Velten self-statements combined with music; b) film scenes. We extended the previous findings in this field to the understudied area of mood induction in older adults. Fifty-seven older adults and 94 college students were randomly assigned to one of the experimental conditions or to a control group. Results indicated that both procedures were effective, according to a series of ANOVAs for several self-report, physiological, and behavioral measures. Likewise, the highest effect sizes were observed for the Velten procedure (g = .81 vs. g = .71), and the effects were significantly higher in younger (g = 1.0 in the Velten condition) than in older adults (g = .62), Q = 4.25, &amp;#967;2(1), P = .0392. Both procedures were effective to induce inducting anxiety in both age groups, especially the Velten procedure in younger adults. Therefore, Velten self-statements combined with music may be very useful anxiety induction procedure for further research in controlled situations of emotions across the life-span (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Márquez, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nuevo, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrera, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montorio, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izal, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este estudio se comparó la eficacia en personas mayores y jóvenes de dos procedimientos habituales para inducir experimentalmente ansiedad: a) frases auto-referenciales Velten combinadas con música; b) escenas de películas. Así, este trabajo extendió hallazgos previos en este campo a la poca estudiada área de la inducción de estados de ánimo en la edad avanzada. Se asignó aleatoriamente a 57 personas mayores y 94 estudiantes universitarios a una de las dos condiciones experimentales o aun grupo control. Los resultados mostraron que ambos procedimientos eran efectivos, de acuerdo con el cambio en varios ANOVAs para diferentes autoinformes y medidas fisiológicas y conductuales. Asimismo, los tamaños del efecto más elevados se encontraron en el procedimiento Velten (g = .81 vs. g = .71) y los efectos fueron significativamente mayores en jóvenes que en personas mayores (g = 1.0 vs. g = .62 en la condición Velten; Q=4.25, &amp;#967;2(1), p = .0392). Los dos procedimientos fueron efectivos para inducir ansiedad en ambos grupos de edad, aunque especialmente en el caso del procedimiento Velten en los jóvenes. Por tanto, el uso de frases Velten combinadas con música parece un procedimiento útil para inducir ansiedad en investigaciones en situaciones controladas sobre las emociones a lo largo del ciclo vital (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;31(1): 28-36, ene. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131597</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia diferencial de dos procedimientos de inducción de la ansiedad en poblaciones de jóvenes y adultos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33140</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3102</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8776</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
