<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114150</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spontaneous resolution of macular detachment associated with optic disc coloboma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report: A 24-year-old male presented with visual acuity loss of the right eye. Examination of the right eye fundus showed a serous detachment of the posterior pole associated with optic disc coloboma. The patient refused surgical treatment. After six months an improvement in visual acuity was observed with the disappearance of macular subretinal fluid. Discussion: The macular detachment is a known complication of the optic disc coloboma. Different therapeutic options have been used, although spontaneous re-attachment may also occur as shown in this case (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castaño, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Poyales, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Paciente varón de 24 años que acude por disminución de agudeza visual del ojo derecho. La exploración oftalmológica de dicho ojo mostraba un desprendimiento seroso del polo posterior asociado a coloboma del nervio óptico. Se propuso tratamiento quirúrgico que el paciente rechazó. A los 6 meses se objetivó una mejoría de la agudeza visual con desaparición del líquido subretiniano a nivel macular. Discusión: El desprendimiento del polo posterior es una complicación conocida del coloboma del nervio óptico. Se han utilizado distintas opciones terapéuticas, aunque como demuestra este caso también puede acontecer una resolución espontánea (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;88(7): 279-282, jul. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114150</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resolución espontánea de desprendimiento macular asociado a coloboma del disco óptico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d20181^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27963^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10080^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20181^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20181^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4669^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10080^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27963^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24366^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20181^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
