<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127105</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The assurance of the quality of a service rendered by a member of the dental profession is an essential feature of any system of peer review in dentistry. This document addresses twoe essential elements: (i) appropriateness of treatment modality and (ii) quality or level of treatment rendered. In revising these guidelines the European Society of Endodontology is responding to a public and professional need. In receiving care a specialized nature such as endodontic treatment, patients need and deserve treatment that meets the standard of care generally given by competent practitioners. The European Society of Endodontology has the expertise and professional responsibility necessary to assist the dental profession by instituting guidelines on the standard of care in the special area of Endodontics. In accepting this responsibility the European of Endodontology formulated treatment guidelines that are intended to represent current good practice. This document is the revised version of an earlier consensus report (International Endodontic Journal (1994) 27, 115-24). As there is not one single way of performing treatment, these guidelines have been formulated in broad terms (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sociedad Europea de Endodoncia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Asegurar la calidad de un servicio realizado por un miembro de la profesión dental es una característica esencial de cualquier sistema de peer review en odontología. Este documetno trata dos cuestiones esenciales: (i) la adecuación del tipo de tratamiento i (ii) la calidad o nivel de tratamiento realizado. Al revisar estas guías, la Sociedad Europea de Endodoncia responde a una necesidad pública y profesional. Al recibir tratamiento de tipo especializado como es el tratamiento endodóncico, los pacientes requieren y merecen el tratamiento que cumple los estándares dados generalmente por profesionales competentes. La Sociedad Europea de Endodoncia tiene la responsabilidad experta  profesional necesaria para ayudar a la profesión dental presentando estas guías sobre el estándar de tratamiento en el área especial de la Endodoncia. Al aceptar esta responsabilidad, La Sociedad Europea de Endodoncia formuló unas guías de tratamiento que pretenden representar la correcta práctica actual. Este documento es la versión revisada de un informe de consenso previo (International Endodontic Jouranl (1994), 27, 115-124). Como no hay una única manera de tratar un paciente, estas guías se han formulado en términos amplios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);25(4): 253-263, oct.-dic. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127105</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Directrices para la calidad del tratamiento endodóncico: informe sobre el consenso de la Sociedad Europea de Endodoncia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33208</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12765^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3803^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29368^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4790^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
