<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82617</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">High dynamic risk cystoceles</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: To assess the bladder compliance in a series of cystoceles referred for urodynamic study.METHODS: Retrospective study of a series of patients with cystocele undergoing medical history, videurodynamic study, pelvic MRI and lower urinary tract, urological ultrasound and cystoscopy. We Excluded cases with neurogenic dysfunction and urinary infection. The terminology followed the criteria of the ICS, if not specified otherwise. The series includes 3333 cases of cystocele 616 of which are grade III cystocele. There were 3 cases with low bladder compliance; this is 0.0009% of total (1:1000) and 0.5% of grade III cystocele (1:200)RESULTS: All cases of cystocele whit low compliance were associated with feeling of a bulk in the vagina and functional symptoms of lower urinary tract (LUTS). No urinary incontinence was related to cough. These patients also showed urodynamic alterations in the voiding phase, type hypo / acontractile detrusor and postvoid residual. The patients were subjected to various techniques of abdominal and transvaginal cystocele repair (with preventive anti-incontinence surgery), getting a vagina bulk disappearance, improvement of symptoms of lower urinary tract function, normalization of bladder compliance and detrusor contractility, with elimination of the postvoid residual.CONCLUSIONS: Although they are not frequent, high-risk cystoceles should be discarded in high-grade cystocele that apart from low bladder accommodation, have a hipo/acontractile detrusor and postvoid residual. Surgical correction of cystocele not only reduces the bulk and LUTS, but normalizes urodynamic alterations(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Silmi Moyano, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez Rubio, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pelaquim, Humberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salinas Casado, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Virseda Chamorro, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Comprobar la acomodación vesical de una serie de cistoceles remitidos para estudio urodinámico.MÉTODOS: Se realizó un estudio retrospectivo de una serie de pacientes con cistocele, sometidos a historia clínica, estudio vídeo-urodinámico, RMN del suelo pélvico y tracto urinario inferior, ecografía urológica y cistoscopia. Se excluyeron los casos con disfunción neurógena e infección urinaria. La terminología siguió los criterios de la ICS, cuando no se especifica lo contrario. La serie comprende a 3.333 casos de cistocele de los que 616 casos corresponden a cistoceles grado III. Los casos con acomodación vesical disminuida correspondieron a 3 casos, esto es el 0,009 % del total (1 por mil) y el 0,5 % de los cistoceles grado III (1 por 200)RESULTADOS: Todos los casos de cistocele de baja acomodación, se asociaron a sensación de bulto en vagina y síntomas funcionales del tracto urinario inferior. Ninguna refería incontinencia urinaria a la tos. En estas pacientes también se demostraron alteraciones urodinámicas de la fase miccional tipo hipo/acontractilidad del detrusor y residuo postmiccional. Las pacientes fueron sometidas a distintas técnicas vaginales y abdominales de corrección del cistocele (con cirugía anti-incontinencia preventiva), obteniendo una desaparición del bulto en vagina, mejoría de los síntomas funcionales del tracto urinario inferior, con normalización de la acomodación vesical y contractilidad del detrusor, y con desaparición del residuo postmiccional.CONCLUSIONES: Aunque no son frecuentes los cistoceles de alto riesgo, habrá que descartarlos ante cistoceles de alto grado, que aparte de la baja acomodación vesical, presentan un detrusor hipo/acontráctil y residuo postmiccional. La cirugía correctora del cistocele, no sólo reduce el prolapso y mejora los síntomas funcionales del tracto urinario inferior, sino que normaliza las alteraciones urodinámicas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;63(5): 355-361, jun. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82617</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cistocele de alto riesgo urodinámico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14963</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52128^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52128^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
