<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136104</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Activity of micafungin against Candida biofilms</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Most recalcitrant infections are associated to colonization and microbial biofilm development. These biofilms are difficult to eliminate by the immune response mechanisms and the current antimicrobial therapy. Aim: To describe the antifungal of micafungin against fungal biofilms based in the scientific and medical literature of recent years. Methods: We have done a bibliographic retrieval using the scientific terms &#147;micafungin&#148;, &#147;activity&#148;, &#147;biofilm&#148;, &#147;Candida&#148;, &#147;Aspergillus&#148;, &#147;fungi&#148;, &#147;mycos&#148;*, susceptibility, in PubMed/Medline from the National Library of Medicine from 2006 to 2009. Results: Most current antifungal agents (amphotericin B and fluconazole) and the new azole antifungals have no activity against fungal biofilms. However, micafungin and the rest of echinocandins are very active against Candida albicans, Candida dubliniensis, Candida glabrata, and Candida krusei biofilms but their activities are variable and less strong against Candida tropicalis and Candida parapsilosis biofilms. Moreover, they have not activities against the biofilms of Cryptococcus y Trichosporon. Conclusions: The activity of micafungin against Candida biofilms gives more strength to its therapeutic indication for candidaemia and invasive candidiasis associated to catheter, prosthesis and other biomedical devices (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Eraso, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quindós, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villar-Vidal, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: Muchas de las micosis más recalcitrantes al tratamiento se asocian a la colonización y la formación de biopelículas que son difíciles de eliminar por parte de los mecanismos defensivos inmunológicos y con el tratamiento antimicrobiano habitual. Objetivo: Describir la utilidad de la micafungina en las biopelículas fúngicas a partir de los datos publicados en los últimos años. Métodos: Se ha realizado una búsqueda bibliográfica mediante el empleo de los términos &#147;micafungin&#148;, &#147;activity&#148;, &#147;biofilm&#148;, &#147;Candida&#148;, &#147;Aspergillus&#148;, &#147;fungi&#148;, &#147;mycos*&#148;, &#147;susceptibility&#148;, en la base de datos PubMed/Medline de la National Library of Medicine de Estados Unidos desde enero de 2006 hasta enero de 2009. Resultados: La mayoría de los antifúngicos convencionales (anfotericina B y fluconazol) y los nuevos azoles no tienen actividad en las biopelículas fúngicas. Sin embargo, la micafungina y las otras equinocandinas son muy activas en las biopelículas de Candida albicans, Candida dubliniensis, Candida glabrata y Candida krusei, mientras que su actividad es variable con las de Candida parapsilosis y Candida tropicalis. Sin embar- go, su actividad es prácticamente nula contra las biopelículas de Cryptococcus y Trichosporon. Conclusiones: La actividad antifúngica de la micafungina en las biopelículas de Candida refuerza su indicación terapéutica en el tratamiento de las candidemias y candidiasis invasoras asociadas a catéteres, prótesis y otros implantes biomédicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;26(1): 49-55, mar. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136104</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actividad de la micafungina contra las biopelículas de Candida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32342^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52786^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4414</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52786^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29867^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1237^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53122^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53122^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2209^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2207^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36324</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36325</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
