<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140374</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dyslipidemias in school-age chilean children: prevalence and associated factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Dyslipidemias are a key cardiovascular risk factor, and are increased since early childhood. The objective of this study was to describe the prevalence, characteristics of dyslipidemias and associated factors in a population of Chilean children. Methods: Cross-sectional study done in school-age children from Santiago, Chile (2009-2011). Parents answered questions about family medical history and children answered questions about physical activity. Anthropometry was performed and in a blood sample (12 hours fast) lipid profile, glycemia and insulinemia were measured. Results: We recruited 2900 euglycemic children, 11.4±0.97 years old, 52% girls. According to BMI, 22.5% were overweight and 15,3% had obesity. Considering recommended cut-off points for lipids, 69.3% were in acceptable range, 19.2% at risk and 11.5% at high cardiovascular risk. In total, 32% of the population had any clinical form of dyslipidemia: Isolated hypertriglyceridemia (9.4%), low HDL-C (7.6%), isolated hypercholesterolemia (4.9%), atherogenic dyslipidemia (6.24%) and mixed dyslipidemia (3.9%). Except for isolated hypercholesterolemia, dyslipidemias were more frequent in girls (globally 36.2% vs. 27.4%, p&lt;0.0001). Low HDL-C was associated with sedentary lifestyle. In multiple logistic regression analysis, nutritional status was the most important associated factor, with less influence of age, sex, central obesity, insulin resistance and history of parental cardiovascular risk factors. Conclusions: In this population of Chilean school-age children, we found a high prevalence of dyslipidemia, and the principal determinant was weight excess (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Farías Jofré, Marcelo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barja Yáñez, Salesa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arnaiz Gómez, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo Valenzuela, Oscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez de Landa, Angélica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mardones Santander, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villarroel Del Pino, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las dislipidemias son un factor de riesgo cardiovascular clave, en aumento ya desde la niñez. El objetivo de este estudio fue describir la prevalencia, tipo de dislipidemias y factores asociados, en una población de niños chilenos. Métodos: Estudio transversal en escolares de Santiago de Chile (2009-2011). Se realizó antropometría, encuesta de antecedentes familiares a los padres y de actividad fí- sica a los niños. En muestra sanguínea de ayunas se midió perfil lipídico, glicemia e insulinemia. Resultados: Se reclutaron 2900 escolares de 11,42±0,97 años de edad, 52% mujeres, todos euglicémicos. Según IMC, 22,5% tenía sobrepeso y 15,3% obesidad. Al considerar los límites recomendados para cada lípido, 69,3% se encontraba en rango aceptable, 19,2% en riesgo y 11,5% en alto riesgo cardiovascular. En total, 32% de la población presentó alguna forma clínica de dislipidemia: Hipertrigliceridemia aislada (9,4%), Bajo C-HDL (7,6%), Hipercolesterolemia aislada (4,9%), Dislipidemia aterogénica (6,24%) y Dislipidemia mixta (3,9%). Excepto la hipercolesterolemia aislada, las demás dislipidemias fueron más frecuentes en las niñas (36,2% vs. 27,4%, p&lt;0,0001). El menor C-HDL se asoció al sedentarismo y a la menor frecuencia de actividad física. En regresión logística múltiple, el estado nutricional fue el factor asociado más gravitante, con menor influencia de: edad, sexo, obesidad central, resistencia insulínica y antecedente de factores de riesgo parental cardiovascular. Conclusiones: En esta muestra poblacional de escolares chilenos se encontró una alta prevalencia de dislipidemias asociadas principalmente al exceso de peso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(5): 2079-2087, mayo 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140374</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dislipidemias en escolares chilenos: prevalencia y factores asociados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8230^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1812^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28461</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50514^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
