<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78421</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment with rituximab for thrombocytopenia due to systemic lupus erythematosus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Some patients with thrombocytopenia due SLE fail to respond to conventional therapies. Rituximab has been reported to be an alternative for patient treatment.ObjectiveTo evaluate the response of thrombocytopenia due to Systemic Lupus Erythematosus to the use of Rituximab and patient relapse time at our hospital.Patients and methodsWe analyzed patients with SLE than received a 2 gram rituximab treatment for thrombocytopenia. We analyzed the rate of patients that achieved complete remission (CR), defined as a platelet count over 100mil/mm3, partial remission (PR) described as platelets within 50&#150;100mil/mm3 and no response (NR) if platelets remained unchanged and the time the remission was sustained.Results16 treatments were applied to 13 patients, aged 28±9 years of age and SLE mean duration time of 68±44 months with a mean platelet count of 38±29mil. In 14 treatments (87%) remission was achieved after 5±2 weeks where 2 patients (12.5%) were non respondent. One of them died due to a massive hemorrhage. The mean response time without relapse was 15.6±6 months. Follow up of three patients was not possible and 3 other died due to infections.ConclusionsRituximab is an alternative for treatment of thrombocytopenia due to Systemic Lupus Erythematosus(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Maia Becerra Márquez, Ariana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Sánchez, María Azucena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mejía Holguín, Yadhira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aranda Baca, Laura Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sauza del Pozo, María Josefina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calderón Saldierna, Rosa Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En algunos casos la trombocitopenia secundaria a lupus eritematoso sistémico (LES) no responde al tratamiento convencional. En los últimos años se ha reportado que el rituximab es una alternativa para estos pacientes.ObjetivoEvaluar la respuesta de la trombocitopenia (T) secundaria a LES con el uso de rituximab y determinar el tiempo que se mantiene el efecto libre de recaída.Material y métodosSe revisaron los expedientes de los pacientes con diagnóstico de LES con T que recibieron tratamiento con rituximab (2g) para conocer la proporción de pacientes que lograron remisión completa (RC): definida como una cuenta plaquetaria &gt;100.000/mm3; remisión parcial (RP): cuenta plaquetaria entre 50.000 y 100.000/mm3 y los no respondedores (NR); así como el tiempo que se mantiene el paciente sin recaída.ResultadosSe aplicaron 16 tratamientos en 13 pacientes, en una paciente 3 y en otra 2 ciclos. Fueron 12 mujeres y 1 hombre con edad media de 28±9 años y tiempo medio de duración del LES de 68±44 meses, con una cuenta media plaquetaria de 38.000±29.000. En 14 tratamientos (87%) se logró RC después de 5±2 semanas y 2 pacientes (12.5%) fueron NR. Una de ellas murió por hemorragia masiva. El tiempo medio de respuesta sin recaída fue de 15,6±6 meses. Tres pacientes perdieron el seguimiento y 3 murieron de infecciones.ConclusionesEl rituximab es una alternativa de tratamiento en pacientes con T secundaria a LES(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);6(2): 82-85, mar.-abr.2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78421</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento con rituximab para la trombocitopenia secundaria a lupus eritematoso sistémico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14306^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11406^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8356^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
