<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88081</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Unwanted pregnancy in teenagers in a health area</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Detection of the cases duly coded as abortion, unwanted pregnancy and emergency contraception in teenagers, between 13 and 18 years of age in Primary Health Care, who were treated on demand in a primary health care clinic in Cartagena (Murcia). Material and method. A retrospective, longitudinal, quantitative study carried out on the cases coded in OMI-AP software of the health centres, in Area II Primary Care Management of Cartagena (2003-2008 inclusive) conducted on teenagers between 13 and 18 years old, inclusive, seen in clinics from January 2003 to December 2008. Variables studied were: age and birth origin. Results. The study included 227 cases of abortion; 235 unwanted pregnancies and 151 cases of emergency contraception, accounting for over 50% of all cases of teenagers treated, and teenagers from Murcia in all range ages as regards abortion, and UP between 17 and 18 years, and 15 and 16 years. It is worth noting that emergency contraception has the highest rate sample in the community of Murcia between 15 and 16 year-olds, with statistical significance. Conclusions. Abortion is treated equally in all communities, as it is offered by the public health system. In unwanted pregnancy cases, improving conditions for maternity is highly recommended and the prevention of pregnancy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Luquín Martínez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piñana López, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso García, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cánovas Inglés, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piñana López, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Ureña, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Detección de los casos atendidos, debidamente codificados en atención primaria de interrupción voluntaria del embarazo (IVE), embarazo no deseado (END) y anticoncepción de emergencia (AE) en adolescentes entre 13 y 18 años, atendidas en consulta a demanda en el Área de Salud de Cartagena. Material y método. Estudio cuantitativo, longitudinal retrospectivo realizado con las codificaciones en OMI-AP de los Centros de Salud del Área II de la Gerencia de Atención Primaria de Cartagena (2003-2008, ambos inclusive) participando las adolescentes atendidas en consulta entre 13 y 18 años ambos inclusive, desde enero de 2003 a diciembre de 2008. Se estudiaron las variables por edad y origen de procedencia. Resultados. El estudio incluye 227 casos de IVE, 235 de END, y 151 casos de AE, suponiendo más del 50% de los casos atendidas, adolescentes murcianas en todos los rangos de edad, con respecto al IVE y END entre 17 y 18 años y 15 y 16 años. Aunque en AE la muestra presenta el mayor porcentaje procedente de la comunidad de la Región de Murcia entre 15 y 16 años con significación estadística. Conclusiones. La IVE sería atendida en igualdad de condiciones en todas las comunidades al ser ofertado desde el sistema público de salud. En los casos de END mejorar las condiciones actuales de la maternidad, así como las medidas de prevención del embarazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);37(5): 227-232, mayo 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88081</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Embarazo no deseado en adolescente en un área de salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11709^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3286^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38863^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d299^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30280^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11709^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201105</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
