<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-62202</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Postural treatment with active cast for adults with motor cerebral disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">People with motor cerebral disease suffer alterations that produce movement and posture abnormalities, thus making adequate sitting posture difficult or impossible.Our objective is to show the effectiveness of a postural treatment with active moulds in adults, which is usually applied in children. We present the case of an adult with motor cerebral disease involving incorrect sitting posture with inadequate support and scarce trunk control.The previous physical therapy reeducation treatment prior to the use of the mould and the subsequent combination of both treatments are described.The results are analyzed, comparing the measures taken from the preestablished anatomical points in free sitting and in the moulded seat. Improvement in posture and increased trunk control was observed.Adults with multiply deficiencies need to receive physical therapy treatment continuously and child protocols need to be adapted to make them effective in adults(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz Esteban, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velasco Arias, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las personas con enfermedad motriz cerebral (EMC) sufren alteraciones en el movimiento y la postura que hacen difícil o imposible una sedestación adecuada.Nuestro objetivo es mostrar la utilidad en el adulto de la técnica Le Métayer de reeducación postural mediante asientos moldeados activos para niños pequeños. Para ello, se presenta el caso de un adulto con EMC y su sedestación con apoyos inadecuados y escaso control de tronco. Se describe el tratamiento de reeducación previo a la realización del molde y la posterior combinación de ambos tratamientos.El análisis de los resultados se realiza comparando las medidas tomadas desde puntos anatómicos preestablecidos en sedestación libre y en el asiento moldeado, constatando la mejoría de la postura y el aumento del control de tronco.Se plantea la necesidad del plurideficiente adulto de recibir tratamiento fisioterápico de forma crónica y de adaptar los protocolos infantiles para hacerlos eficaces en adultos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);31(3): 115-119, mayo 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-62202</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento postural con molde activo en el adulto con enfermedad motriz cerebral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9322^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33528^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200905</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
