<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142026</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1582</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Role of breast magnetic resonance imaging in assessing response to neoadjuvant therapy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Molecular classification of breast cancer has allowed us to predict its biological behaviour, providing important diagnostic and therapeutic information. The development of specific treatments in primary systemic therapy has increased the percentage of conservative surgery, with disease-free survival and overall survival rates equivalent to adjuvant therapy. In this setting, breast magnetic resonance imaging has become the imaging modality of choice to evaluate the response of breast cancer treated with primary systemic therapy. This technique has a good radiologic-pathologic correlation and allows discrimination of different types of response according to the molecular profile (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Mur, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castán Senar, Alba</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz Ciria, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La clasificación molecular del cáncer de mama ha permitido predecir su comportamiento biológico, proporcionando información de importancia diagnóstica y terapéutica. El desarrollo de esquemas específicos en terapia primaria sistémica ha aumentado el porcentaje de cirugías conservadoras, manteniendo unas tasas de supervivencia libre de enfermedad y supervivencia global equivalentes a las de la terapia adyuvante. En este ámbito, la resonancia magnética mamaria se ha consolidado como la técnica de imagen de elección para la valoración de la respuesta del cáncer de mama tratado con terapia primaria sistémica, presentando una buena correlación radiopatológica y con capacidad para discriminar diferentes niveles de respuesta en función del perfil molecular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. senol. patol. mamar. (Ed. impr.);28(4): 181-187, oct.-dic. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142026</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papel de la resonancia magnética de mama en la valoración de la respuesta a la neoadyuvancia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9157^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
