<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039897</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hepatitis B virus genotypes in chronic carriers on the island of Gran Canaria. Clinical and epidemiological characteristics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To investigate the prevalence of hepatitis B virus (HBV) genotypes in Spanish hepatitis B carriers, and to study the differences in epidemiological characteristics, e antigen (HBeAg) seroconversion, serum DNA viral levels (VL) and liver function alterations. Methods. This study included 108 patients. Genotyping was carried out in 84 with the INNO-LiPA HBV genotyping assay (Innogenetics).Results. There were 41 women and 67 men, with a mean age of 44.1 years. The source of transmission was family contact in 26 patients (24.1%); transfusions in 10 (9.3%); sexual promiscuity in 9 (8.3%), intravenous drug use in 3 (2.8%), health care accident in 2 (1.8%); and unknown causes in 58 (53.7%). Forty patients had chronic hepatitis and 68 (63%) were healthy carriers. The time of evolution of the infection was known in only in 45 patients, and was over 10 years in 42 of them. One hundred patients (92.6%) were HbeAg-negative and 90 (83.3%) had detectable viral DNA. Genotype A was present in 46 (54.8%), D in 20 (23.8%), F in 2 (2,4%), C in 1 (1.2%), A-G coinfection in 7 (8.3%), A-D in 4 (4.8%), D-G in 2 (2,4%), A-C in 1 (1.2%), and A-D-G in 1 (1.2%). There were no significant differences between genotypes. A trend towards an association was found between VL &amp;#8804; 10 5 copies/mL and the presence of chronic hepatitis in genotype A (28.9%) as opposed to genotype D (7.7%) (p non significant). Conclusions. HBV genotypes A and D, and coinfections with G are predominant in our area. Genotype A showed a tendency to produce greater inflammatory activity when VL was &amp;#8804; 10 5 copies/ml (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Bardeci, Diana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lafarga-Capuz, Bernardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-San Román, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez-Bordón, Pino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pena-López, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-González, María Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer la distribución de genotipos del virus de la hepatitis B (VHB) de pacientes españoles portadores crónicos y su relación con las características epidemiológicas, la presencia de antígeno e, el nivel sérico del ADN viral (CV) y la alteración de la función hepática. Métodos. Se estudiaron 108 pacientes. El genotipo se realizó en 84 mediante INNO-LiPA HBV Genotyping-Innogenetics. Resultados. De los pacientes, 41 fueron mujeres y 67 hombres, con una edad media de 44,1 años. Las fuentes de transmisión fueron: contacto familiar, 26 pacientes (24,1%); transfusiones, 10 (9,3%); promiscuidad sexual, 9 (8,3%); adicción a drogas parenterales, 3 (2,8%); accidente sanitario, 2 (1,8%) y en 58 (53,7%) se desconocía. Cuarenta pacientes (37%) presentaron una hepatitis crónica (HC) y 68 (63%) eran portadores asintomáticos. Sólo en 45 pacientes se conocía el tiempo de evolución de la infección y en 42 fue mayor de 10 años. Cien pacientes (92,6%) presentaron antígeno e-negativo y 90 (83,3%) tuvieron ADN viral detectable. La distribución de genotipos fue: A, 46 (54,8%); D, 20 (23,8%); F, 2 (2,4%); C, 1 (1,2%), coinfección A-G, 7 (8,3%); A-D, 4 (4,8%); D-G, 2 (2,4%); A-C, 1 (1,2%) y A-D-G, 1 (1,2%). No se observaron diferencias significativas entre genotipos. Se observó una tendencia en el genotipo A a presentar HC cuando la CV &amp;#8804; 10 5 copias/ml (28,9% de los casos) frente al genotipo D (7,7%) (p no significativa). Conclusiones. En nuestra área predomina el genotipo A, D y las coinfecciones con G. Observamos una tendencia del genotipo A a producir una mayor actividad inflamatoria cuando la CV &amp;#8804; 10 5 copias/ml (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;23(7): 415-418, ago. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039897</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Genotipos del virus de la hepatitis B en portadores crónicos en la isla de Gran Canaria. Características clinicoepidemiológicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1274^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33343^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33343^s32386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6668^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5974</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33123</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28093^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28093^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
