<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133438</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mechanisms used by inulin-type fructans to improve the lipid profile</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims: The consumption of prebiotics has been associated with improvement in the lipid profile. Thus, this review aims to describe the main mechanisms by which inulin-type fructans improve the lipid profile and thereby reduce the cardiovascular risk.  ata synthesis: Inulin-type fructans have been demonstrated to improve the lipid profile through a number of mechanisms. These mechanisms include: decrease in gene expression of hepatic enzymes responsible for de novo synthesis of lipids; increase of muscle lipoprotein lipase enzyme activity, enhancing the production of short-chain fatty acids; altered production of polyamines which increases the production of satiogenic peptide; altered blood glucose and insulinemia; increase of fecal excretion of bile salts and cholesterol and increase of the Bifidobacterium population. Conclusions: The consumption of inulin-type fructans enhances lipid profile. Generally, the mechanisms vary according to the physiologic state of the individual and the type of diet to which the inulin-type fructans are added. Thus, inulin may be used for the prevention and/or treatment of cardiovascular diseases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Conceicao, Lisiane Lopes da</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dias, Mancela Maciel dos Santos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peluzio, Maria do Carmo Gouveia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosa, Damiana Diniz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reis, Sandra Aparecida dos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: El consumo de prebióticos ha sido asociado con el mejoramiento del perfil lipídico. Por tanto, esta revisión tiene como objetivo describir los principales mecanismos por los cuales fructanos tipo inulina, mejoran el perfil lipídico reduciendo el riesgo cardivascular. Síntesis de los datos: Los fructanos tipo inulina, han demostrado una mejora del perfil lipídico, a través de varios mecanismos, incluyendo: disminución de la expresión génica de las enzimas hepáticas responsables por la síntesis de novo de lípidos; aumento de la actividad enzimática del lipoproteína lipasa muscular; aumento de la producción de ácidos grasos de cadena corta; producción alterada de poliaminas que aumentan la producción del peptido Satiogen; alteración de la glicemia e insulinemia; aumento de la populación de Bifidobacterium y el incremento de la excreción fecal de las sales biliares y el colesterol. Conclusiones: El consumo de los fructanos tipo inulina mejora el perfil lipídico. Generalmente, los mecanismos varian de acuerdo com el estado fisiológico del individuo y el tipo de dieta, en la que son adicionados los fructanos tipo inulina. Por tanto, la inulina puede ser utilizada para la prevención y/o tratamiento de enfermedades cardiovasculares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(2): 528-536, feb. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133438</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mecanismos utilizados por los fructanos tipo inclina para mejorar el perfil lipídico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5766^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8230^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55394</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7605^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
