<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88821</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Body composition and energy metabolism in women with excess weight</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. The objective of this paper is to evaluatebody composition and energy expenditure in womenwith excess body weight.Methods. There was a non-randomized, cross-sectionalstudy with 40 women, [26 with excess weight (G1) and14 eutrophic (G2)]. The following evaluations weremade: dietetic, anthropometric and body composition(electrical bioimpedance), physical activity (threedimensionalaccelerometer) and energy expenditure,basal and resting (indirect calorimetry).Results. The energy intake and physical activity did notdiffer between groups. The parameters of body compositionwere higher in G1, except total body water. Therewas a relationship between energy expenditure andbody composition. The lean mass was the biggest determinantof energy expenditure. There was no differencein metabolic parameters between groups, but lowernutrient oxidation and increased metabolic efficiency inG1 was suggested.Conclusion. Excess weight was associated with bodycomposition and energy expenditure changes that justifythe accumulation of body fat(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lopes Rosado, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bressan, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>D&#146;Andrea, C. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vogel, C. E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos. El objetivo de presente trabajo es evaluarla composición corporal y el metabolismo energéticoen mujeres con exceso de peso corporal.Material y métodos. Estudio transversal de intervenciónno randomizado con 40 mujeres [26 con excesode peso (G1) y 14 eutróficas (G2)]. Fueron realizadasevaluaciones dietéticas, antropométricas y de la composicióncorporal (bioimpedancia eléctrica), actividadfísica (acelerómetro tridimensional) y metabolismoenergético (calorimetría indirecta).Resultados. No hubo diferencia en la ingesta energéticay en la actividad física entre los grupos. Los parámetrosde composición corporal fueron superiores en G1,excepto el agua corporal total. Hubo asociación entreel gasto energético y la composición corporal. La masacorporal magra fue el principal determinante del gastoenergético. No hubo diferencia de los parámetros metabólicosentre los grupos, pero se sugiere menor velocidadde oxidación de los nutrientes y mayor eficienciametabólica en G1.Conclusiones. El exceso de peso corporal se asoció concambios en la composición corporal y en el metabolismoenergético que justifican la acumulación de grasacorporal(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;33(2): 155-165, mayo-ago. 2010. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88821</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Composición corporal y metabolismo energético en mujeres con exceso de peso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2185^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1860^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4813^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4813^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4067^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4813^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
