<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100300</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Carbon dioxide vs. air insufflation in ileo-colonoscopy and in gastroscopy plus ileo-colonoscopy: a comparative study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: insufflation with carbon dioxide (CO2) during endoscopies compared to air is associated with a decrease in abdominal discomfort after the examination, because CO2 is readily absorbed through the small intestine and eliminated by the lungs. Aim: the objective of this randomized clinical trial was to assess the effect of CO2 insufflation on pain and abdominal distension after an ileo-colonoscopy (I) and after an ileo-colonoscopy plus gastroscopy (I+G). Material and methods: we included a total of 309 patients in the study and all endoscopies were performed under sedation with propofol. Two hundred fourteen patients underwent an I (132 with CO2 / 82 with air) and 95 underwent an I+G (53 with CO2 / 42 with air). Abdominal pain was studied at 10, 30 and 120 minutes of exploration and abdominal perimeter difference before and after the procedure. Results: both in group I and in group I+G, the use of CO2 translated into an average of abdominal pain significantly lower (p &lt; 0.05). Similarly, a smaller increase in waist circumference was found among group I and group I+G, in patients where CO2 was used (p &lt; 0.05). Conclusion: the insufflation of CO2 instead of air during the performance of endoscopy significantly reduces the discomfort and abdominal pain after an ileo-colonoscopy and after a gastroscopy + ileo-colonoscopy(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Prieto de Frías, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herráiz Bayod, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riva, Susana de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrascosa Gil, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carretero Ribón, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Calderón, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Navas, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Betés Ibáñez, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la insuflación con dióxido de carbono (CO2) durante las endoscopias digestivas comparado con el aire, se asocia a una disminución de las molestias abdominales después de la exploración, ya que el CO2 es fácilmente absorbido por el intestino delgado y eliminado por los pulmones. Objetivo: el objetivo de este ensayo clínico aleatorizado fue valorar el efecto de la insuflación de CO2 sobre el dolor y la distensión abdominal después de una ileo-colonoscopia (I) y después de una íleo-colonoscopia + gastroscopia (I+G). Material y métodos: se incluyeron un total de 309 pacientes en el estudio y todas las endoscopias fueron realizadas bajo sedación con propofol. A 214 pacientes se les realizó una I (132 con CO2 / 82 con aire) y a 95 se les realizó una I+G (53 con CO2 / 42 con aire). Se estudió el dolor abdominal a los 10, 30 y 120 min de la exploración y la diferencia de perímetro abdominal antes y después del procedimiento. Resultados: tanto en el grupo I como en el grupo I+G, se objetivó una media de dolor abdominal en los pacientes en los que se utilizó CO2 significativamente menor que en los que se utilizó aire (p &lt; 0,05). Y de igual modo se objetivó un menor incremento en el perímetro abdominal para el grupo I y para el I+G en los pacientes en que se utilizó CO2 frente a los que se utilizó aire (p &lt; 0,05). Conclusión: la insuflación de CO2 en vez de aire durante la realización de la exploración endoscópica, reduce significativamente el disconfort y el dolor abdominal después de una íleo-colonoscopia y después de una íleo-colonoscopia + gastroscopia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;104(5): 237-241, mayo 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100300</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Insuflación de CO2 vs. aire en íleo-colonoscopia y en gastroscopia más íleo-colonoscopia: estudio comparativo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29396^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29396^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2284</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29341^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29341^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23322^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7260^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7265^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2284^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7265^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23322^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23322^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7265^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7260^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
