<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60753</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-6266</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OOBJETIVES: To validate home poligraphy in patients with vascular comorbidity and suspicion of obstructive sleep apnea syndrome (OSAS), and to determine in patients with is chemicheart disease if treatment with CPAP influences in their control.  PATIENTS AND METHODS: Forty-two patients were included (29 men and 13 women; Age: 53 ± 7.8 years; BMI: 33 ± 5.2)who were made home sleep study and conventional polysomnography. Sixteen patients with ischemic heart disease were evaluate dafter CPAP treatment. Diagnosis of OSAS was stablished when apnea-hypoapnea index (AHI) was &gt; 5 in polysomnography and treatment with CPAP was indicated when AHI &gt; 15. RESULTS: A significative correlation and concordance (p&lt;0.01)were observed between the polysomnography and polygraphy in the AHI (36 ± 19.9 vs 32 ± 17.4), r = 0.903 and CCI = 0.938, and the desaturation index (33 ± 23.5 vs 35 ± 22.1), r = 0.896 and CCI = 0.948.When AHI &gt;5 in polysomnography, the polygraphy obtained an are aunder the ROC curve = 1 and for IAH &gt;15 the area under the ROC curve was 0.945. After CPAP treatment, patients with ischemic heart disease went less frequently to the hospital. CONCLUSIONS: Poligraphy is valid for diagnosis and treatment indication. Patients with ischemic heart disease, CPAP improves their control and reduces visits to the hospital (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jurado Gámez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Cabrera, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cosano Povedano,  A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Calero, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cobos, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arenas, M. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Marín, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVOS: Validar la poligrafía domiciliaria en pacientes con comorbilidad vascular y sospecha de un síndrome de apneas hipopneas del sueño (SAHS) y determinar, en aquellos enfermos con cardiopatía isquémica, si el tratamiento con CPAP influye en el control de esta enfermedad. PACIENTES Y MÉTODOS: Fueron incluidos 42 enfermos (29 hombres y 13 mujeres, edad: 53 ± 7,8 años, IMC: 33 ± 5,2). Se les realizó poligrafía domiciliaria y polisomnografía convencional. Dieciséis pacientes con cardiopatía isquémica fueron evaluados tras el tratamiento con CPAP. El diagnóstico de SAHS se estableció ante un índice de apnea-hipopnea (IAH), en la polisomnografía&gt; 5 y se indicó tratamiento con CPAP si el IAH fue &gt; 15. RESULTADOS: Se observa una correlación y concordancia significativa (p &lt; 0,01) entre la polisomnografía y poligrafía, en el IAH (36 ± 19,9 frente a 32 ± 17,4), r = 0,903 y CCI = 0,938, y en el índice de saturación (33 ± 23,5 frente a 35 ± 22,1), r = 0,896 y CCI = 0,948. Respecto a un IAH &gt; 5 en la polisomnografía, la poligrafía obtiene un área bajo la curva ROC = 1 y para un IAH &gt; 15el área bajo la curva ROC fue de 0,945. Tras el tratamiento con CPAP, los enfermos con cardiopatía isquémica acudieron menos frecuentemente al servicio de urgencias. CONCLUSIONES: La poligrafía domiciliaria es válida para el diagnóstico e indicación de tratamiento. En pacientes con cardiopatía isquémica, la CPAP mejora su control, descendiendo el número de consultas al servicio de urgencias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neumosur (Sevilla);20(4): 185-190, oct.-dic. 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60753</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Poligrafía domiciliaria en pacientes con patología cardiovascular y sospecha de un SAHS</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13273^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32137^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30611^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13273^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
