<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129082</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Experimental study of the consequences of resection of the flexor retinaculum on the stability of the scaphoids</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To analyze the consequences of flexor retinaculum (FR) section on the kinetic behavior of the scaphoid, triquetrum and capitate bones under axial load. Material and method. A 6 degree-of-freedom electromagnetic motion tracking device with sensors attached to the scaphoid, triquetrumcapitate and radius was used to monitor spatial changes in carpal bone alignment as a result of isometrically loading the main motor writs muscles. Six wrists from fresh cadavers were used, in which the principal motor tendons were subjected to loads proportional to physiological cross sectional area of each muscle. The experiment was carried out with the wrist in the neutral position, before and after the FR section. Results. After FR section, the scaphoid showed less flexion (P = .05) and a higher degree of radial inclination (P = .03) compared to the same experiment with the FR intact. The kinetic behavior of the triquetrum did not change significantly. Discussion. According to the results of this study, the isolated section of the FR did not produce greater instability of the scaphoid. If so, the scaphoid should have a higher degree of flexion, but exactly the opposite movement happens. Conclusion. Resection of the FR alters the kinetic behavior of the scaphoid under axial load, but does not produce greater instability in the carpus. Pillar syndrome may not be as a result of scaphoid instability, but due to another type of dysfunction that needs to be determined in future studies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Elías, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llusá Pérez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvà Coll, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Baeza, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Valorar de forma experimental las consecuencias de la sección del retináculo flexor (RF) en el comportamiento cinético del escafoides, piramidal y hueso grande, bajo carga axial. Material y método. Utilizando sensores de posición y orientación, tipo Fastrak&#153;, se realizó un registro de los cambios de orientación espacial del escafoides y piramidal en relación al radio, al aplicar una carga axial. Para ello se utilizaron 6 muñecas de cadáver fresco, cuyos principales tendones motores fueron sujetos a cargas proporcionales al área seccional fisiológica de cada músculo. El experimento se llevó a cabo en condiciones de carga isométrica, con la muñeca en posición neutra, antes y después de seccionar el RF. Resultados. Tras la sección del RF, el escafoides manifestó una menor flexión (p=0,05) y una mayor inclinación radial (p=0,03) que cuando la misma carga se aplicó en la muñeca con RF íntegro. El comportamiento cinético del piramidal no cambió significativamente. Discusión. Según los resultados de este trabajo, la sección aislada del RF no genera una mayor inestabilidad del escafoides. Si fuese así, el escafoides debería presentar un mayor grado de flexión y en cambio ocurre todo lo contrario. Conclusión. La sección del RF modifica el comportamiento cinético del escafoides bajo carga axial, pero no genera mayor inestabilidad carpiana. El síndrome del pilar, no debería ser entendido como la consecuencia de la desestabilización del escafoides, sino de otro tipo de disfunción a determinar en futuros estudios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);55(3): 224-230, mayo-jun. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129082</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio experimental de las consecuencias de la sección del retináculo flexor sobre la estabilidad del escafoides</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52102^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2391^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2136</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35257^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15351^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35257^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35257^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15351</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
