<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049200</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-6585</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Inmediate implant loading in mandible edentulous patients. Technique of Maló</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The aim of this study was to assess the clinical outcome of immediate loading in the treatment with osseointegrated implants of edentulous mandible. Methods. Edentulous patients were treated with Microdent® sandblasted-etched surface implants for rehabilitation of mandible by insertion of 4 implants in anterior area with immediate loading. A follow-up were of 12 months. Results. 10 patients (6 men and 4 women) were treated with 40 implants (20 straight and 20 inclined) with a length of 14-16 mm and were loaded immediately with a acrylic screw full denture. Clinical findings showed a survival and success rate of implants of 100%. No implants were lost during the follow-up period. Conclusions. This study indicate that immediate loading of implants in the treatment of edentulous mandible constitute a dental treatment treatment with a high success rate success (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Méndez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velasco Ortega, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Frías, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segura Egea, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medel Soteras, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El objetivo del presente estudio era valorar los resultados clínicos de la carga inmediata en el tratamiento con implantes oseointegrados de la mandíbula edéntula. Pacientes y métodos. Los pacientes edéntulos completos fueron tratados con implantes Microdent® con superficie con chorreado de arena y grabada con ácidos para la rehabilitación de la mandíbula edéntula mediante la colocación de 4 implantes en el sector anterior con carga funcional inmediata. Los implantes fueron evaluados durante 1 año. Resultados. 10 pacientes (6 varones y 4 mujeres) fueron tratados con 40 implantes (20 rectos y 20 inclinados) de 14-16 mm de longitud y fueron cargados de forma inmediata con una prótesis completa de resina atornillada. Los hallazgos clínicos indican una supervivencia y éxito de los implantes del 100% ya que ningún implante se ha perdido durante el año de seguimiento clínico. Conclusiones. Este estudio indica que la carga inmediata de los implantes en el tratamiento de la mandíbula edéntula constituye un tratamiento odontológico con una elevada tasa de éxito (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. periodoncia implantol. oral;18(3): 127-134, dic. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049200</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La carga funcional inmediata con implantes en pacientes edéntulos mandibulares. Técnica de Maló</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24600^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24600^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33384^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d783^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3843^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32808^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32808^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3843^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3843^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8506^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23440^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1888^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1888^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
