<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163636</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The relevance of psychological flexibility in the context of cancer: a review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Psychological flexibility has been related to a wide number of positive outcomes among individuals with mental health problems and chronic illnesses, and it has been identified as an important mechanism of change in psychotherapy. However, the attention given to psychological flexibility within psycho-oncology has been quite limited, even though it may offer new alternatives in the treatment of cancer-related distress. The objective of the present descriptive review was to bring together the studies that have examined the association between psychological flexibility and outcomes among cancer patients, or have carried out interventions aiming to increase the level of psychological flexibility among cancer patients. Even though the research base in this area is still small, the findings consistently show that higher levels of psychological flexibility are associated with increased levels of wellbeing among cancer patients, even in the presence of health deterioration. Implications for clinical practice in psycho-oncology are discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aguirre-Camacho, Aldo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Jiménez, Bernardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La flexibilidad psicológica ha sido relacionada con diversos indicadores positivos en individuos con problemas de salud mental y enfermedades crónicas, y ha sido identificada como un importante mecanismo de cambio psicoterapéutico. Sin embargo, la atención prestada a la flexibilidad psicológica en la psicooncología ha sido limitada, a pesar de su potencial relación con el distrés relacionado con el cáncer. El objetivo de la presente revisión descriptiva fue reunir los estudios que han examinado la asociación entre la flexibilidad psicológica y distintos indicadores de bienestar en pacientes con cáncer, o evaluado el impacto de intervenciones destinadas a incrementar el nivel de flexibilidad psicológica en pacientes con cáncer. A pesar del bajo número de estudios, los resultados demuestran de forma consistente que la flexibilidad psicológica está asociada a altos niveles de bienestar en pacientes con cáncer, incluso en presencia de deterioro físico. Para finalizar, se presentan algunas implicaciones para la práctica clínica en psico-oncología (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);14(1): 11-22, ene.-jun. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163636</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La relevancia de la flexibilidad psicológica en el contexto del cáncer: una revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
