<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147097</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Development of the Seminar</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The current issue of REUMATOLOGÍA CLÍNICA is devoted to the method of teaching clinical anatomy as it applies to rheumatology. This method was developed as a response to a perceived need. It is our belief that rheumatologists are at present insufficiently trained in clinical anatomy. As a result, our diagnostic skills may fall short of their potential. Recent rheumatologic literature shows a vertiginous growth of musculoskeletal ultrasonography. In contrast to ultrasound, however, skilled, anatomy-based inspection and palpation can be mastered by all and applied in the care of all patients. It is our hope that clinical musculoskeletal anatomy will one day be a basic component in rheumatology training programs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Canoso, Juan J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kalish, Robert A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este número de REUMATOLOGÍA CLÍNICA se dedica a la difusión de un método de enseñanza de la anatomía clínica para reumatólogos. No se trata de una propuesta sino más bien de una respuesta a una carencia que percibimos, a través de muchos años y hasta el presente, en reumatólogos de distintos países y continentes. La ultrasonografía musculoesquelética, a pesar de su extraordinaria importancia y creciente difusión, impactará poco en esta carencia. Es más, a menos que hagamos un esfuerzo consciente de educación puede llegar a agravarla por atrofia por desuso de nuestros músculos clínicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);8(supl.2): 10-12, dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147097</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desarrollo del seminario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4571^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4571^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29870</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9334^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4570^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12630^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4570^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d727^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11241</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32065</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
