<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040919</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8799</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">What do we really know about exercise in childhood? (I)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Concerning the adaptation of children to exercise, we accept concepts which support our theories about physical work in childhood; but    most of them are lacking of experimental basis.    So, considering ethical, technical or methodological difficulties inherent to any experimental work with children, easily we found not contrasted relations established between some observations and growth process.    We must add methodological mistakes common to experimental works, such as: most works has no control group, the training protocols are not well described or are inappropriate, statistical procedures are wrong, population sample are insufficient, often not contrasted observations are used as starting point. It is surprising that only a half of works talking about growth include the maturing stage of the sample.    In this situation, we present a critical analysis of the accepted concepts about exercise in children through a wide bibliographic review.    We conclude that most of these concepts are not proved and must be reviewed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Naranjo Orellana, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerrero Almeida, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">No disponible</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. med. deporte;22(108): 311-317, jul.-ago. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040919</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Qué sabemos realmente acerca del trabajo físico en los niños? (I)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5178^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5178^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5178^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5180^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5178^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11240^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32868^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9324^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8837^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4813^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6493^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6278^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27866^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
