<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156921</identifier>
<setSpec>0556-6177</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Transperineal Pd-103 brachytherapy as the sole treatment modality for good prognostic prostate cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article reports the 6-year experience of The Ohio State University in the management of adenocarcinoma of the prostate Gleason&#145;s score &lt;7 and PSA&lt;10 with permanent Pd&#151;103 brachytherapy as the only treatment modality. Material and Methods: From May 1990 to December, 1996, 125 patients underwent Pd-103 permanent brachytherapy at The Ohio State University. Of these, 54 presented with Gleason&#146;s score of 6 or less, pre-implant PSA level of less than 10 and had not received any prior radiation therapy or androgen blockade. These 54 patients form the basis of this report. Median age at the time of the implant was 66 years (range 45&#151;90). The prostate volume was obtained from a preimplant CT scan. Treatment planning was performed interactively, in real-time, on-line, in the operating room. The Pd-103 seeds were implanted using a Mick TP&#151;200 applicator. We implanted a median of 100 (range 70-130) Pd-103 seeds per patient, with a median total activity of 150 mCi (range 99-221) to deliver a minimum peripheral dose (MPD) of 110 Gy (range 80-140 Gy). Results: Only 3 out of 53 evaluable patients had a biochemical failure (5.6%). The average time to bio-chemical control was 13.5 months. The 6-year actuarial freedom from biochemical relapse (FFBR) was 91%, with a median follow-up of 2.7 years (range 0.6&#151;6.8). The cancer-specific survival patient was 98%, with an overall survival of 92%. Eighty percent of the patients experienced acute temporary dysuria. Of these, 15% needed temporary bladder catheterization due to urinary blockage. Only one patient had severe urinary incontinence. Five patients reported minor rectal bleeding, but only 4% of the cases appear to be radiation&#151;related. Conclusions: Patients with low&#151;risk cancer of the prostate, as defined by a Gleason score pattern of less than 7 and an initial PSA of less than 10 can be successfully treated with Pd-103 permanent brachytherapy as the sole treatment modality with an actuarial 6-year FFBR of 91%. Most patients required medical management for symptomatic postimplant dysuria, with a 15% urinary obstruction rate. Rectal morbidity was mild and occurred infrequently (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernandes, PS</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Monge, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nag, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El trabajo expone la experiencia (de seis años) en la Universidad del Estado de Ohio, en el tratamiento del adenocarcinoma prostatico grado &lt; 7 de Gleason y PSA&lt;10, con brachiterapla Pd-103 permanente como Unica modaliad de tratamiento. Material y métodos: 125 pacientes (entre mayo 1990 y diciembre 1996) recibieron brachiterapia Pd-103 permanente. 54 presentaban un grado 6 de Gleason o menor y un nivel PSA menor de 10 antes del implante y no habían sido tratados previamente con radioterapia ni bloqueo de andrégenos. Estos 54 pacrentes son los que constituyen la base de la presente relación. Su edad media, al realizarse el implante, era de 66 años (range 45-90). El tamaño de la prostata antes del implante se determine mediante TC. Los granulos Pd-103 fueron implantados mediante un aplicador Mick TP&#151;200. Fueron implantados una media de 100 (rango 70-130), con una media de actividad total de 150 m Ci (rango 99-121), que permitia liberar una dosis periférica de 110 Gy (rango 80-140 Gy). Resultados: Solamente 3 de los 53 pacrentes presentaron un tallo bioquimico (5,6%). El tiempo promedio de control bioquímico fue de 13,5 meses. Las 6 años libres de liberación bioquímica fue de 95% con un seguimiento medio de 2,7 a&amp;#64257;os (tango O,6&#151;6,8). La supervivencia oncológica fue del 98% y la total del 92%. El 80% de los pacientes experimentó una disuria aguda temporal. De ellos, el 15% necesitó una cateterización vesical mientras hubo bloqueo miccional. Solamente un paciente padeció incontinencia importante. Cinco pacientes refirieron hemorragia rectal de escasa-importancia, pero solo el 4% era imputable a la radiación. Conclusiones: Pacientes con cancer prostatico de bajo riesgo (grado Gleason de 7 o menos y con un PSA inicial menor de 10) pueden ser tratados con éxito mediante la implantacién permanente braquioterápica Pd&#151;.104. como único tratamiento (6 años FFBR de 91%). La mayor parte de los pacientes requirieron tratamlento médico a cause de la disuria posimplante, con un 15% de bloqueo urinario. La afectación rectal fue ligera y se presentó en muy pocos casos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Med Univ Navarra;44(2): 12-20, 2000. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156921</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Braquiterapia Pd-103 transperineal como único tratamiento en el cáncer de próstata de buen pronóstico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52157^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52157^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1944^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1944^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23183^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11913^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23183^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30596^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
