<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85738</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Lack of motivation in Nursing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The lack of motivation in professionals seriously affects many professions,including nursing, due to its inherent characteristics which make it sensitiveto this phenomenon. Nursing is basically very emotionally taxing, as itrequires frequently addressing traumatic experiences in patients&#146; lives. Inorder to get a clear view of this problem a study was developed with the aimof identifying nurses&#146; needs in their daily practice and determining whatmeans or actions are most adequate to counteract decreased motivation. Itconsists of a descriptive exploratory study with a qualitative methodologicalapproach. A Health Care Centre was selected and the case study methodwas selected as the research method, the semi-structured interviewbeing the nuclear technique for data collection and observation and documentalanalysis being complementary techniques. After performing a firstanalysis, it was observed that all interviewed nurses reported liking theirprofession, for two main reasons: &#147;feeling good&#148; and &#147;helping&#148;. In termsof the difficulties of their profession, the lack of human and material resources,integration in services and the relationship with colleagues andother nurses are emphasised. In regards to coping strategies for decreasedmotivation, nurses concur in their opinion, claiming that interpersonal relationshipsand the integration in services are adequate policies, but deemingperiodic assessments and rotation of positions to be flawed policies.There are differing opinions in terms of the continued education strategy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferrera Picado, Jesús Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La desmotivación profesional afecta gravemente a muchas profesiones y, entreellas, a las enfermeras, debido a que tienen unas características propiasque las hacen más sensible a este fenómeno. Fundamentalmente, exige undesgaste emocional muy grande, debido a que es frecuente tener que afrontarsituaciones traumáticas en la vida de los pacientes. Para enfocar esteproblema se desarrolló un estudio con los objetivos de identificar las necesidadesde los enfermeros en el desempeño diario y determinar qué medioso acciones son los más adecuados para contrarrestar la desmotivación. Setrata de un estudio descriptivo y exploratorio, con un abordaje metodológicocualitativo. Se seleccionó un Centro de Salud y se escogió el estudio decaso como método de investigación, considerando la entrevista semi-estructuradacomo técnica nuclear de recogida de datos y la observación y elanálisis documental como técnicas complementarias. Realizando un primeranálisis, sobresale que todos los enfermeros entrevistados manifiestan queles gusta la profesión que ejercen, fundamentalmente por dos motivos: &#147;sentirsebien&#148; y &#147;ayudar&#148;. En relación a las dificultades del desempeño profesional,se destaca la falta de recursos humanos y materiales, la integraciónen los servicios y la relación con compañeros y enfermos. En las estrategiasde afrontamiento de la desmotivación, la opinión de los entrevistados esunánime, afirmando que las relaciones interpersonales y la integración enlos servicios son políticas adecuadas, pero considerando la evaluación periódicay la rotación de puestos como políticas erradas. Sobre la estrategiade formación continuada existe división de opiniones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;13(3): 14-18, abr. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85738</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La desmotivación en enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24419</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
