<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058989</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cold chain maintenance in vaccines: a systematic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: Systematic immunization programmes mostly depend on the correct maintenance and manipulation of the vaccines to be used, i.e. perfect maintenance of the cold chain. Therefore, we decided to carry out a systematic review of the literature on the cold chain and vaccines, to identify daily practices in vaccine sites.                 Methods: A literature search was performed in the main medical databases for documents published between 1990 and 2005, including those performed by means of a survey and/or inspection of vaccine sites that provided the following data: a designated health officer, availability of a thermometer with maximums and minimums, refrigerator temperature at the time of the visit, and temperature control and registration. For all the variables, the mean prevalence was calculated with a 95% confidence interval.                 Results: Three hundred seventy-seven articles were found; 31 were initially selected and 13 were finally included. In 72.21% of the vaccine points, there was an officer responsible for the vaccines, but only 61.43% knew the optimal temperature range. Fifty-five percent of these points had a thermometer with maximums and minimums and only 26.88% carried out temperature controls and registrations at least once per day.                 Conclusion: Important shortfalls were detected in cold chain maintenance in all selected articles, jeopardizing the effectiveness and efficiency of immunization programs</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Albaladejo Vicente, Romana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pilar Arrazola Martínez, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Molina, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villanueva Orbáiz, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Astasio Arbiza, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juanes Pardo, José Ramón de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Los programas de inmunización sistemática dependen en gran medida del correcto mantenimiento y la manipulación de las vacunas que se aplican, es decir, del perfecto mantenimiento de la cadena del frío. Por ello, nos propusimos realizar una revisión sistemática de la literatura médica sobre la cadena del frío y las vacunas, con el objetivo de conocer las prácticas diarias en los puntos de vacunación.                 Métodos: Se efectuó una búsqueda bibliográfica en las principales bases médicas entre 1990 y 2005. Se incluyeron los estudios que, mediante encuesta y/o inspección a puntos de vacunación, aportaban datos sobre: designación de responsable sanitario, existencia de termómetro de máximas y mínimas, temperatura del frigorífico en el momento de la visita y control y registro de la temperatura. Para todas las variables se calculó la prevalencia media con su intervalo de confianza del 95%.                 Resultados: Se localizaron 377 artículos, se seleccionaron inicialmente 31 y se incluyeron 13 de ellos. El 72,21% de los puntos de vacunación tenía un responsable de vacunas, pero sólo el 61,43% de ellos conocían el rango óptimo de temperaturas. Por otro lado, el 55% de estos puntos tenía un termómetro de máxima y mínima y sólo el 26,88% realizaba controles y registros de temperaturas al menos una vez al día.                 Conclusión: En las publicaciones incluidas en el estudio se detectan deficiencias importantes en el mantenimiento de la cadena del frío de las vacunas, que ponen en riesgo la efectividad y la eficiencia de los programas de inmunización</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;21(4): 343-348, jul.2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058989</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mantenimiento de la cadena del frío para las vacunas: una revisión sistemática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12456^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11744^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4415</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4416^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23123</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200707</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
