<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044959</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveEducate in the responsible knowledge and in the rationaluse of the medicines concerning the persons who benefitfrom the social programs of home assistant.MethodPersonal home interviews of SAD users, reporting oncertified documents the medicine used, if they are knownor not, if they move back or not. Any medical incidents willalso be reported, for a better education, integration,or derivation, if needed. ResultsEach patient takes an average of 6,4 medicines. An averageof 27,3% of the cases is derived to the doctor. 25,5% ofthe cases are derived to the social services. They withdraw23,9 % of all the medicines checked are withdrawn bythe social services, with big differences between knowntherapeutic groups. 31,6% of all the checked medicinesremain unknown; with also big differences between thesegroups. The most important are groups R. (respiratoryapparatus) with 56,5% of ignorance, J. (antiinfectioustherapy) with 67% and S. (organs of the senses) with 75%</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villafaina Barroso, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias Torrecilla, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salgado Morcillo, Rosa M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoEducar en el conocimiento responsable y en el usoracional de los medicamentos por parte de las personasbeneficiarias de los programas sociales de ayuda adomicilio (SAD).MétodoEntrevista personal en visita domiciliaria a los usuariosdel SAD, haciendo constar en documento escrito losmedicamentos revisados, si se conocen o no, si se retirano no y las distintas incidencias registradas. Intentandoeducar, integrar y derivar si fuese el caso.ResultadosCada paciente toma una media de 6,4 medicamentos.Se derivan al médico una media del 27,3% de los casos.Se derivan a los servicios sociales un 25,5% de los casos.Se retiran el 23,9% de todos los medicamentos revisadoscon grandes diferencias entre distintos grupos terapéuticos.Se desconoce 31,6% de todos los medicamentosrevisados; grandes diferencias entre grupos los másdesconocidos R. (aparato respiratorio) con un 56,5% dedesconocimiento, J. (terapia antiinfecciosa) con un 67%y S. (órganos de los sentidos) con un 75%</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;7(1): 32-40, ene.-mar. 2005. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044959</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión de botiquines domésticos de personas incluidas en ayuda domiciliaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4416^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13037</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12535^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4424</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32694^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
