<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165241</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analytical performance of the Alere(TM) i Influenza A&amp;B assay for the rapid detection of influenza viruses</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The analytical performance of the new Alere(TM) i Influenza A&amp;B kit (AL-Flu) assay, based on isothermal nucleic acids amplification, was evaluated and compared with an antigen detection method, SD Bioline Influenza Virus Antigen Test (SDB), and an automated real-time RT-PCR, Simplexa(TM) Flu A/B &amp; VRS Direct assay (SPX), for detection of influenza viruses. An &#145;in-house&#146; RT-PCR was used as the reference method. Sensitivity of AL-Flu, SDB, and SPX was 71.7%, 34.8%, and 100%, respectively. Specificity was 100% for all techniques. The turnaround time was 13min for AL-Flu, 15min for SDB, and 75min for SPX. The Alere(TM) i Influenza A&amp;B assay is an optimal point-of-care assay for influenza diagnosis in clinical emergency settings, and is more sensitive and specific than antigen detection methods (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Ruiz, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Marí, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riazzo, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedrosa Corral, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanbonmatsu Gámez, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Fernández, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se evaluó el nuevo ensayo Alere(TM) i Influenza A&amp;B kit (AL-Flu), basado en la amplificación isotérmica de ácidos nucleicos, y se comparó con un método de detección de antígeno, SD Bioline Influenza Virus Antigen Test (SDB), y con una RT-PCR en tiempo real automática, Simplexa(TM) Flu A/B &amp; VRS Direct assay (SPX), para la detección de virus de la gripe. Se utilizó una RT-PCR en tiempo real casera como método de referencia. La sensibilidad de AL-Flu, SDB y SPX fue del 71,7%, del 34,8% y del 100%, respectivamente. Se obtuvo una especificidad del 100% con todos los métodos. El tiempo de realización fue de 13min para AL-Flu, de 15min para SDB y de 75min para SPX. El ensayo Alere(TM) i Influenza A&amp;B es óptimo para el diagnóstico de gripe en unidades de urgencias, al ser más sensible y específico que las técnicas de detección de antígeno (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;35(7): 438-440, ago.-sept. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165241</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación del sistema Alere(TM) i Influenza A&amp;B para la detección rápida de virus de la gripe</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12561^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35623^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35624^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
