<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74699</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The PRESCAP project has presented up to the present date two cross-sectional and multicenter studies conducted in the years 2002 and 2006 with the same methodology and in similar populations attended in Primary Care (PC). They included patients of &amp;#8805; 18 years diagnosed of arterial hypertension(AHT) from the entire Spanish territory who received antihypertensive drug treatment. The degree of blood pressure (BP) control found in these two samples, the largest performed up to now in our country, was 36.1% in 2002 and 41.4% in 2006. These percentages were, respectively, 33.5% and 38.2% in hypertensive subjects of 65 years or older and 9.1% and 15.1% in diabetic patients. A total of 51.9% of the hypertensive subjects had high-very high added cardiovascular risk (CVR). BP control decreases as the CVR increases. It was found that 27.4% of hypertensive subjects had high added CVR and 6.8% had very high added CVR. The PC physician changed the treatment of the poorly controlled hypertensive subjects in 18.3%of the cases in 2002 and in 30.4% in 2006. In the PRESCAP2002, 44.0% of the hypertensive subjects received combined antihypertensive therapy and in the PRESCAP 2006, this percentage reached 55.6%. Although the control of AHT has noticeably improved in Spain in recent years, the percentage of optimally controlled patients continues to be extremely deficient, especially in the diabetic population, in elderly hypertensive subjects and in those who have added high or very high CVR (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grupo de Trabajo de Hipertensión Arterial de la Sociedad Española de Médicos de Atención Primaria (Grupo HTA/SEMERGEN) y de los investigadores del estudio PRESCAP 2006</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El proyecto PRESCAP presenta, hasta el momento, dos estudios transversales y multicéntricos que se realizaron en los años 2002 y 2006 con la misma metodología y en poblaciones similares asistidas en Atención Primaria (AP). Incluyeron pacientes &amp;#8805; 18 años diagnosticados de hipertensión arterial (HTA) de todo el territorio español que recibían tratamiento farmacológico antihipertensivo. El grado de control de la presión arterial (PA) que se ha encontrado en estas dos muestras, las más amplias de las realizadas hasta ahora en nuestro país, fue del 36,1% en2002 y del 41,4% en 2006; estos porcentajes fueron respectivamente del 33,5% y 38,2% en los hipertensos de 65 o más años de edad, y del 9,1% y 15,1% en pacientes diabéticos. El51,9% de los hipertensos presentaba riesgo cardiovascular(RCV) añadido alto o muy alto. El control de la PA disminuía conforme aumentaba el RCV: resultaba del 27,4% en los hipertensos que tenían RCV añadido alto y del 6,8% en los que mostraban RCV añadido muy alto. El médico de AP modificó el tratamiento de los hipertensos mal controlados en el18,3% de los casos en 2002 y en el 30,4% en 2006. En el PRESCAP 2002 el 44,0% de los hipertensos recibía terapia combinada antihipertensiva y en el PRESCAP 2006 ese porcentaje ascendía al 55,6%. Aunque el control de la HTA ha mejorado ostensiblemente en España en los últimos años, el porcentaje de pacientes controlados óptimamente sigue siendo todavía a todas luces deficitario, especialmente en la población diabética, en los hipertensos de mayor edad y en aquellos que tienen un RCV añadido alto o muy alto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);35(9): 450-456, nov. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74699</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aportaciones del estudio PRESCAP al conocimiento de la hipertensión arterial en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200911</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
