<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109416</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Molecular markers for ischemia, do we have something better than creatinine and glomerular filtration rate?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Acute kidney injury (AKI) can occur spontaneously or iatrogenically, and rates of AKI continue to rise over the last two decades despite improvements in clinical care and development of preventive strategies. Serum creatinine (sCr) is the current gold standard for measuring changes in kidney function and identifying AKI. Detection of AKI by sCr, however, is delayed and small rises connote significantly increased morbidity and mortality. Diagnosis of AKI by sCr is therefore likely too late to prevent some of the early structural changes that characterize renal injury. Several urinary biomarkers including neutrophil gelatinase-associated lipocal in (NGAL), N-acetyl-beta-D-glucosaminidase (NAG), Interleukin-18 (IL-18), kidney injury molecule-1 (KIM-1), liver fatty-acid-binding protein (L-FABP), and cystatin-C, have shown an ability to predict AKI days before an elevation in sCr, and a few even seem to predict AKI-related morbidity and mortality better than sCr alone. A review of the current literature regarding these biomarkers reveals that they individually have unique strengths and weaknesses that can provide different types of information about patients. Currently, NGAL is the urine biomarker with the most promise as an individual marker. However, combining multiple markers to form a &#145;biomarker panel&#146; along with sCr is an improvement over current clinical risk prediction models alone, and may be able to provide more individualized detail about the type and location of renal injury(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Russo, Paul</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sprenkle, Preston</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La lesión renal aguda puede ocurrir espontáneamente o iatrogénicamente; las tasas de lesión renal aguda han continuado creciendo durante las dos últimas décadas a pesar de las mejoras en los cuidados clínicos y el desarrollo de estrategias preventivas. La creatinina sérica (Crs) es el patrón oro de referencia para medir los cambios de la función renal e identificar una lesión renal aguda. Sin embargo, la detección de lesión renal aguda mediante Crs se retrasa, y pequeños incrementos conllevan aumentos significativos de la morbilidad y mortalidad. Diagnosticar la lesión renal aguda por medio de la Crs será por lo tanto probablemente demasiado tarde para evitar algunos de los cambios estructurales tempranos que caracterizan la lesión renal. Varios biomarcadores urinarios incluyendo la lipocalinaneutrofílica asociada a gelatinasa (NGAL), N-acetil beta-D-glucosaminidasa (NAG), Interleukina-18 (IL-18), La molécula de lesión renal 1 (KIM 1), la proteína hepática de unión de ácidos grasos y las cistatina-C, han demostrado la capacidad de predecir la lesión renal aguda días antes de la elevación de la Crs, y unos pocos incluso parecen predecir la morbilidad y mortalidad asociadas con la lesión renal aguda mejor que la Crs sola. Una revisión de la literatura actual sobre estos biomarcadores revela que individualmente tienen fortalezas y debilidades singulares que pueden ofrecer diferentes tipos de información sobre los pacientes. Actualmente el NGAL es el biomarcador urinario más prometedor como marcador individual. Sin embargo, la combinación de múltiples marcadores para formar un panel de biomarcadores junto con la Crs es una mejora sobre los modelos clínicos de predicción de riesgo solos, y pueden ser capaces de ofrecer información más detallada sobre el tipo y localización de la lesión renal(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;66(1): 99-114, ene.-feb. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109416</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Marcadores moleculares en la isquemia, ¿no hay nada mejor que la creatinina y la tasa de filtración glomerular?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7678^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3421^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54416^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6063^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7855^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7678^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
