<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122496</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-8831</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychological problems in children of families served at a primary pediatric care clinic and their association with demographic variables</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Mental health disorders during childhood and adolescence have short and long-term consequences on development. There is evidence of the benefits of early detection of these disorders; however, most children suffering mental health problems do not receive proper care. Objective. To identify the main psychological problems affecting children attending a primary clinic of the public health care system. Method. The sample was selected from the control group of a study investigating exposure to domestic violence. Eighty-five children 4 to 15-years-old not exposed to domestic violence pertaining to 54 families served at two primary care centers of the Valles region were selected for participation in the study. Psychopathology was assessed using a semi-structured diagnostic interview following the DSM-IV criteria. Results. The most frequent disorders diagnosed were: specific phobia (11.8%) and stereotyped movement disorders (11.8%), enuresis (7.1%), attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (4.7%), tic disorders (4.7%), generalized anxiety (4.7%), oppositional defiant disorder (3.5%), social phobia (3.5%) and separation anxiety (2.4%). Age increased the odds of presenting anxiety disorders  (OR=1.2; IC 95%: 1,02-1,41; p=0.026). Familial socioeconomic status was not associated with the presence of disorders.Conclusions. Psychological problems are frequent among children being seen at primary pediatric health care clinics. Early detection during childhood is important for intervention. The pediatrician is key for identifying those disorders and referring the children to a mental health professional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sansa, Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Clará, Immaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coronado, Ricard</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puente, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ezpeleta, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Granero, Roser</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. Los trastornos de salud mental en la infancia y la adolescencia tienen consecuencias a corto y largo plazo sobre el desarrollo. Hay evidencias de los beneficios de detectar tempranamente estos problemas. A pesar de ello, la mayoría de los niños que los padecen no reciben la atención requerida. Objetivo. Identificar y cuantificar los principales problemas psicológicos que presentan los niños que acuden a consultas pediátricas ambulatorias de la red pública de salud. Método. La muestra procede del grupo control de un estudio sobre la exposición a violencia doméstica. Participan 85 niños de entre 4 y 15 años que no han estado expuestos a violencia doméstica de 54 familias que acuden a consulta pediátrica en dos centros de  asistencia primaria del área del Vallès. Se evalúa la psicopatologíamediante una entrevista diagnóstica semiestructurada siguiendo  los criterios del DSM-IV. Resultados. Los trastornos más frecuentes son la fobia específica (11,8%) y los movimientos estereotipados (11,8%), seguidos de la enuresis (7,1%), el déficit de atención con hiperactividad (4,7%), los tics (4,7%), la ansiedad generalizada (4,7%), el negativismo desafiante (3,5%), la fobia social (3,5%) y la ansiedad de separación (2,4%). La edad de los niños incrementa la posibilidad de presentar algún trastorno de ansiedad (OR=1,2; IC 95%: 1,02-1,41; p=0,026). El nivel socioeconómico de la familia no está relacionado con la presencia de trastornos. Conclusiones. Los problemas psicológicos en los niños atendidos en pediatría primaria son frecuentes. La detección temprana en la infancia es importante para la intervención. El pediatra es un  elemento clave para la detección y derivación de los niños que lo necesiten a un profesional especializado en salud mental (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. catalan;74(1): 8-13, ene.-mar. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122496</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Problemas psicológicos en niños de familias que acuden a consulta pediátrica y asociación con variables demográficas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10222^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2710^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
