<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142075</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A flow cytometry method for testing the susceptibility of Cryptococcus spp. to amphotericin B</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Human fungal infections have increased at an alarming rate in recent years, particularly in immunocompromised individuals. Cryptococcosis is the second most prevalent systemic fungal infection worldwide, and the most prevalent systemic infection in immunocompromised individuals, representing more than 70% of cases. The incidence of cryptococcosis is high in people with HIV/acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS), with recent estimates indicating that there are one million cases of cryptococcal meningitis globally per year in AIDS patients. Aims. The aim of this research was to develop a rapid flow cytometric antifungal susceptibility test and to compare the results with the standard methods. Methods. A reference strain and clinical isolates of Cryptococcus neoformans and Cryptococcus gattii were tested for susceptibility to amphotericin B by flow cytometry using propidium iodide as indicator of viability. Flow cytometry (FC) results were compared with the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) values determined by microdilution. Results. The antifungal activity of amphotericin B ranged from MICs of 0.06 to 2 &amp;#956;g/ml for the 11 isolates studied. The same results were found by FC. Conclusions. The FC method allows same-day results, assisting in the selection of appropriate antifungal therapies. These results demonstrate an excellent correlation between FC and the classic methods of testing for susceptibility to antifungal agents. This rapid diagnosis method makes it possible to quickly administer effective therapeutic interventions, often saving lives (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fusco-Almeida, Ana Marisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soares Mendes-Giannini, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benaducci, Tatiane</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cássia Orlandi Sardi, Janaina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Teruyuki Matsumoto, Marcelo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. En los últimos años, las infecciones por hongos en el ser humano, particularmente en individuos inmunodeprimidos, han aumentado a un ritmo alarmante. La criptococosis es la segunda infección fúngica sistémica más frecuente en todo el mundo, y también la infección sistémica más frecuente en personas inmunodeprimidas, lo que representa más del 70% de los casos. La incidencia de la criptococosis es alta en las personas con VIH/síndrome de inmunodeficiencia adquirida. Estudios recientes indican que hay un millón de casos de meningitis criptocócica en pacientes con síndrome de inmunodeficiencia adquirida por año en todo el mundo. Objetivos. El objetivo de esta investigación fue desarrollar una prueba rápida de sensibilidad antifúngica por citometría de flujo (CF) y comparar los resultados con los métodos estándar. Métodos. Se estudió la sensibilidad a la anfotericina B por CF, con yoduro de propidio como indicador de la viabilidad, de una cepa de referencia y varios aislamientos clínicos de Cryptococcus neoformans y Cryptococcus gattii. Resultados. La actividad antifúngica de la anfotericina B varió de una concentración mínima inhibitoria de 0,06 a 2 &amp;#956;g/ml para los 11 aislamientos estudiados. Los mismos resultados fueron encontrados por CF. Conclusiones. El método de la CF permite resultados el mismo día, lo que hace posible una rápida selección de los tratamientos antifúngicos adecuados. Estos resultados demuestran una excelente correlación entre el método de la CF y los procedimientos clásicos de pruebas de sensibilidad a los agentes antifúngicos. Este método de rastreo ágil hace que sea posible realizar rápidamente intervenciones terapéuticas eficaces y, a menudo, salvar vidas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;32(3): 159-163, jul.-sept. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142075</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">/ Un método de citometría de flujo para determinar la sensibilidad de Cryptococcus spp. a la anfotericina B</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3471^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27953^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24244^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5567^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53451^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3470^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3471^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3472^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
