<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-70682</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-6266</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION: The principal goal of this study has been to describe the spectrum and frequency of diseases presenting as unexplained dyspnea in our area by means of performing graded cardiopulmonary exercise test and demonstrate its utility in the diagnosis of chronic dyspnea, so much to clear up its etiology as to guide further tests. METHODS: A descriptive study has been performed for five years based in the patients referred to our service with chronic explained dyspnea. All of them presented clinical history, physical examination and basic complementary tests that didn&#146;t clear up its etiology. A graded cardiopulmonary exercise test was performed, recording a series of functional parameters and yielding finally an ergometric diagnosis following the algorithm by Wasserman et al.1RESULTS: 178 patients were entered (92 male; mean age 42,5± 16,7 years). Obtained diagnosis in order or frequency were: normal or psichogenic dyspnea (71,9%), bronchial hyper reactivity (8,4%), pulmonary limitation (6,7%), overweight and deconditioning(3,9%), hypertensive crisis (3,9%), cardiocirculatory limitation(3,4%) and pulmonary vascular alterations (1,7%). We didn&#146;t found significant differences between both sexs or between different groups of age as for the ergometric diagnosis. CONCLUSIONS: After assessing all the results of our study, we saw that in most of cases a normal diagnosis could reject the existence of a significant disease. Some patients whose results were pathological needed the performing of new tests, however, the cardiopulmonary exercise test, thanks to guiding the diagnosis, allowed a more correct selection of them, with the consequent savingsin time, money and bothers to the patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Linde de Luna, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidal Díaz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosales Jaldo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández de Rota García, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Lafuente Gémar, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cadavid Rodríguez, B. E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">FUNDAMENTO: El objetivo principal de este trabajo ha sido describir el espectro y frecuencia de causas que provocan disnea de origen desconocido en nuestro medio mediante la realización de la prueba de esfuerzo cardiopulmonar y demostrar su utilidad en el diagnóstico de la disnea crónica, tanto para esclarecer su etiología como para orientar las pruebas posteriores. MÉTODOS: Se ha realizado un estudio descriptivo durante cinco años de los enfermos remitidos a nuestro servicio por disnea crónica de origen desconocido. Todos presentaban una historia clínica, exploración física y pruebas complementarias básicas que no aclaraban su etiología. Se les realizó una prueba de esfuerzo cardiopulmonar, registrándose una serie de parámetros funcionales y arrojando finalmente un diagnóstico ergométrico siguiendo el algoritmo de Wasserman et al.1 RESULTADOS: Fueron incluidos 178 pacientes (92 hombres; edad media 42,5 ± 16,7 años). Por orden de frecuencia los diagnósticos obtenidos fueron: normal o disnea psicógena (71,9%), hiperreactividad bronquial (8,4%), limitación ventilatoria (6,7%),sobrepeso y sedentarismo (3,9%), crisis de HTA (3,9%), limitación cardiocirculatoria (3,4%) y alteración vascular pulmonar (1,7%).No encontramos diferencias entre sexos o entre distintos grupos de edad en cuanto a los diagnósticos ergométricos. CONCLUSIONES: Hemos comprobado que en la mayoría delos casos un diagnóstico de normalidad ha permitido excluir la existencia de enfermedad significativa. Algunos pacientes cuyos resultados fueron patológicos precisaron la realización de nuevas pruebas, sin embargo, al orientar el diagnóstico, el test de esfuerzo permitió hacer una selección más precisa de las mismas, con los consiguientes ahorros en tiempo, dinero y molestias a los pacientes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neumosur (Sevilla);19(2): 65-72, abr.-jun. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-70682</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5178</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30118^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4479^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4479^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1969</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
