<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116777</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidemiological studies on the poliomyelitis in Spain before the vaccination</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The eradication of polio in Spain is one of the most important health milestones of the twentieth century, not only for public health but also for the effect it had on scientific knowledge in our country, in the medical field. Knowledge of international literature by our epidemiologists and virologists, was important, as reflected in the studies of outbreaks, virological studies and clinical studies. For public health represented, throughout the twentieth century, an effort geared to make decisions based on scientific knowledge. For epidemiology represented the application of new ways of working and, therefore, its modernization (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Navarro, J. Ferrán</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La erradicación de la poliomielitis en España es uno de los hitos sanitarios más importantes del siglo XX, no solo para la salud pública sino también por el efecto que su conocimiento científico tuvo en en el ámbito médico de nuestro país. El conocimiento de la literatura internacional por nuestros epidemiólogos y virólogos fue importante, como reflejan los estudios de los brotes epidémicos, los estudios virológicos y, lógicamente, los estudios clínicos. Para la salud pública representó, a lo largo de todo el siglo XX, un esfuerzo orientado a tomar decisiones basadas en el conocimiento científico. Para la epidemiología representó la aplicación de nuevas formas de trabajo y, por tanto, su modernización (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;87(5): 429-441, sept.-oct. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116777</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los estudios epidemiológicos sobre la poliomielitis en España antes de la vacunación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23146^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11483^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38882</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11483^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38889</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23146^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38897</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38885</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23146^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
