<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93458</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of fat intake on body composition, lipemia and glycemia of type 1 diabetics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Diabetes mellitus is a metabolic disorder characterized by chronic hyperglycemia and body composition is important in the disease control. The nutritional intervention has relevance in the improvement of glycemia and lipemia in diabetic patients. Aim: Evaluate the influence of fat intake on body composition, lipemia and glycemia on patients with type 1 diabetes mellitus. Methods: 19 patients were evaluated by anthropometric (body mass index and waist circumference), body composition (fat mass, lean body mass and total body water by bioelectrical impedance) and biochemical variables, after 8 hours of fasting. Dietary assessment was performed using the dietary records for 3 days, analyzed for nutritional software DietPró 5i. The groups were formed according to the usual intake of saturated fatty acids (SFA) (G1 &lt; 10% of total energy expenditure (TEE) of SFA and G2 &amp;#8805; 10% of TEE of SFA). Statistical analysis was performed in SPSS 16.0, considering p &lt; 0.05. Results: There was no difference in anthropometric and biochemical variables between groups, but G1 presented higher fat mass (FM) and G2 high SFA and adequate mounsaturated fatty acids (MUFA) intake. The lipemia and glycemia were not affected by high SFA intake, but adequate MUFA intake may have influenced the results of these variables. No found relation between type of fat ingested and biochemistry variables.  Conclusion: Body composition can be influenced by type of fat ingested. Lipemia and glycemia were not influenced by high SFA intake, perhaps due to MUFA intake adequate (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lopes Rosado, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mansur Leal, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lopes Souto, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lima, E dos Santos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miranda, M Paes de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La diabetes mellitus es una enfermedad metabólica caracterizada por hiperglucemia crónica y la composición corporal es importante en el control de la enfermedad. La intervención nutricional tiene relevancia en la mejora de la glucemia y lipemia en pacientes diabéticos. Objetivo: Evaluar la influencia de la ingesta de grasa en la composición corporal, lipemia y glucemia en pacientes con diabetes mellitus tipo 1. Métodos: 19 pacientes fueron evaluados por parámetros antropométricos (índice de masa corporal y circunferencia de la cintura), composición corporal (masa grasa, masa corporal magra y agua corporal total por impedancia bioeléctrica) y bioquímicos, después de 8 horas de ayuno. La evaluación dietética se realizó mediante registros dietéticos de 3 días, analizados en el software nutricional DietPró 5i. Los grupos se formaron según la ingesta habitual de ácidos grasos saturados (AGS) (G1 &lt; 10% del gasto energético total (GET) de AGS y G2 &amp;#8805; 10% del GET de AGS). El análisis estadístico se realizó en SPSS 16.0, con p &lt; 0,05. Resultados: No hubo diferencia en los parámetros antropométricos y bioquímicos entre los grupos, pero G1 presentó mayor masa grasa (MG) y G2 mayor ingesta de AGS y adecuada de ácidos grasos monoinsaturados (AGMI). La lipemia y glucemia no fueron afectadas por la elevada ingesta de AGS, pero la ingesta adecuada de AGMI puede influenciar en los resultados de estos parámetros. No fueron verificadas relaciones entre el tipo de grasa y los parámetros bioquímicos. Conclusión: La composición corporal puede ser influenciada por el tipo de grasa ingerida. La lipemia y la glucemia no fueron influenciadas por la alta ingesta de AGS, tal vez debido a la adecuada ingesta de AGMI (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;26(5): 1110-1114, sept.-oct. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93458</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de la ingesta de grasas en la composición corporal, respuesta inflamatoria y metabolismo de los lipidios de la glucosa en los diabéticos tipo 1</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51213</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8230^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23101^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37656</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
