<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123912</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-7546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characterization of the physical condition and cardiovascular risk of highway police officers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The aim of this study was to assess the physical fitness, body composition and blood pressure of highway police officers in the state of Paraná, Brazil. Method. The sample consisted of 52 male (38.3 ± 6.3 years old, 89.6 ± 18.4 kg) where the following determinations were performed: body mass index (BMI); waist circumference (WC); waist/hip ratio (WHR);  body composition (skinfold thickness); aerobic power (indirectly estimated in a treadmill test); muscle strength of the upper limbs was measured by the number of push-ups and abdominal strength by the number of crunches (ES) and blood pressure (measured by auscultatory method). Results. The highway police officers had a BMI classified as mild obesity (28.6 ± 4.8 kg/m2), and a higher cardiovascular risk as determined by WC (95.4 ± 10.8 cm) and WHR (0.92 ± 0.05). The percentage of body fat was above the recommended values (23.6 ± 4.3 %) but the aerobic power was considered good (34.8 ± 1.1 ml/kg/min). Mean ES upper body (21 ± 8 repetitions) and abdomen (28 ± 8 repetitions) were qualified as fair but mean blood pressure was considered high in 23 % of the police officers. Conclusion. Based on our results it was possible to conclude that although the police officers presented good levels of aerobic power and muscle strength, they are overweight and showed a higher cardiovascular risk (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Andrade, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andreato, L. V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gealh, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frazói de Moraes, S. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esteves, J. V. D. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Evaluar los niveles de aptitud, composición corporal y de la presión arterial de la policía de carreteras en el estado de Paraná, Brasil. Método. Se analizó a 52 oficiales del sexo masculino (38,3 ± 6,3 años, y 89,6 ± 18,4 kg). Fueron realizadas diferentes mediciones para la obtención del índice de masa corporal (IMC); la circunferencia de cintura (CC); el índice cintura/cadera (ICC). La composición corporal se midió por medio del espesor del pliegue cutáneo; la potencia aeróbica se estimó indirectamente mediante una prueba de esfuerzo en una cinta ergométrica; la fuerza muscular de los miembros superiores se midió mediante el número de flexiones y la del abdomen por el número de abdominales y la presión arterial fue medida por auscultación. Resultados. Los policías presentaban un IMC clasificado como obesidad leve (28,6 ± 4,8 kg/m2); la CC de alto riesgo (95,4 ± 10,8 cm); el ICC alto (0,92 ± 0,05); el porcentaje de grasa corporal por encima de los valores recomendados (23,6 ± 4,3 %); la potencia aeróbica buena (34,8 ± 1,1 ml/kg/min); la RM de los miembros superiores (21 ± 8 repeticiones) y del abdomen (28 ± 8 repeticiones) medias, y una proporción significativa (23 %) de los policías presentaron niveles de presión arterial alterada.  Conclusión. En base a estos resultados, fue posible verificar que aunque la policía ha mantenido buenos niveles de potencia aeróbica y fuerza muscular, presentaron exceso de peso e índices que indican alto riesgo cardiovascular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. andal. med. deporte;7(2): 66-71, jun. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123912</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Caracterización de la condición física y factores del riesgo cardiovascular de la policía de carreteras</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51214</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29881</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
