<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-62684</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Neurologic complications of infective endocarditis (IE) are frequent. In many cases, they are the initial feature and considerably impair the prognosis of the disease. The most common neurologic manifestation is embolic stroke, but other many neurologic events have been described, ranged from cerebral hemorrhage due to rupture of mycotic aneurysm to the exceptional aseptic meningitis with a cellular cerebrospinal fluid. We describe 3 cases that represent this wide spectrum of presentation. Ischemic stroke in the first patient and cerebral hemorrhage in the second were respectively documented several days before the diagnosis of IE. In the third case, a cellular meningitis was the unusual clinical debut of aortic IE. Cerebral infarct or hemorrhage are exceptionally caused byan underlying IE, so a high level of suspicious is needed to recognize these complications. The best management to improve the prognosis has to be based on a rapid diagnosis and on set of antibiotic treatment, considering valve replacement in the adequate timing</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Varona, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las complicaciones neurológicas de la endocarditis infecciosa (EI) son en ocasiones la primera manifestación clínica de la enfermedad y están asociadas con un importante incremento en su mortalidad. La principal forma de presentación es el ictus embólico, pero se han descrito otras muchas que abarcan desde la hemorragia cerebral hasta la excepcionalmente descrita meningitis aséptica acelular. Presentamos 3 casos ilustrativos de este amplio espectro clínico. El diagnóstico de ictus isquémico cerebral en el primer paciente y de hemorragia intraparenquimatosa en el segundo precedió en varios días a la documentación de la EI. En el tercer caso un cuadro de meningitis aguda acelular fue la inusual formade debut de EI. Debido a que muy raramente la EI es la causa subyacentea un infarto o a una hemorragia cerebral, es fundamental tener un alto grado de alerta para reconocer precozmente estas complicaciones y así establecer el diagnóstico de EI, iniciando rápidamente el tratamiento antibiótico y planteando el recambio valvular y el momento adecuado del mismo, para disminuir el riesgo de deterioro neurológico y evitar el desarrollo de nuevas complicaciones que empeoren el pronóstico</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;24(9): 439-441, sept. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-62684</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d2585^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2585^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4777^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4777^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4777^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8752^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2582^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8752^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
