<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101757</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spirometry in collaborating child</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Lung function test are the methods used to understand the functioning of the airways and lung. There are different methods or techniques for assessing lung function in collaborators children. The test most frequently used in clinical practice are forced spirometry with bronchodilator test, Test bronchodynamic and peak expiratory flow (PEF). The technique of choice is forced spirometry with bronchodilator test. It is the most useful test for the diagnosis and monitoring of asthma. It is important to know that spirometry with bronchodilator test. It is the most useful test for the diagnosis and monitoring of asthma. It is important to know that spirometry is the &#147;gold standard&#148; for measuring lung function in children. To classify obstructive lung diseases, restrictive and mixed. Moreover, spirometry with bronchodilator test is required to diagnose obstruction of the airway, demonstrating reversibility, assess response to treatment and monitor the evolution. Symptomatology, spirometry and bronchodilation test analyzed jointly will establish the diagnosis and institute the appropriate treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Callejón Callejón, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliva Hernández, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los tests de función pulmonar son los métodos que se utilizan para conocer el funcionamiento de las vías aéreas y los pulmones. Existen diferentes métodos o técnicas para valorar la función pulmonar en niños colaboradores. Los test más frecuentemente utilizados en la práctica clínica son: la espirometría forzada con prueba brocodilatadora, tests broncodinámicos y flujo respiratorio máximo (FEM). La técnica de elección es la espirometría forzada con prueba broncodilatadora. Es la prueba más útil para el diagnóstico y seguimiento del asma. Es importante conocer que la espirometría forzada es el &#147;patrón oro&#148; para la medición de la función pulmonar en el niño. Permite clasificar las enfermedades pulmonares en obstructivas, restrictivas y mixtas. Por otro lado, la espirometría con prueba brocodilatadora es obligada para diagnosticar la obstrucción de la vía aérea, demostrar su reversibilidad, valorar la respuesta al tratamiento y monotorizar la evolución. La sintomatología, la espirometría forzada y la prueba de broncodilatación analizadas conjuntamente, permitirán establecer el diagnóstico e instaurar el tratamiento adecuado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;68(2): 131-138, mar.-abr. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101757</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Espirometría en el niño colaborador</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13530^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12560^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
