<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81487</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Naming speed and phonological awareness in early reading learning</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The ability to read is a basic acquisition that conditions children&#146;s social integration and it is an important factor in school success. It is considered a complex activity in which different levels of cognitive processes are involved. The relationship between phonological awareness, naming speed and learning to read has been widely studied. Research on this topic has previously been carried out with different training procedures, or with children with reading and writing learning disabilities, or children with phonological awareness problems. The innovative aspect of this research is that it presents a longitudinal study of the influence of phonological awareness and naming speed on reading with no training procedure. 85 kindergarten children were assessed with Rapid Automatized Naming Test, The Phonological Knowledge Test (PECO) and the Reading Test (PROLEC-R) at two development points: at 5,6 and at 6.5 years old. A correlational comparison and a hierarchical regression analysis were calculated in order to determine the explicit variance for phonological awareness and naming speed in reading. Results showed that phonological awareness and naming speed differentially explain variance in reading. The discrepancies found are a consequence of the different measurement techniques for phonological awareness and naming speed used by the diverse authors(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aguilar Villagrán, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marchena Consejero, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Menacho Jiménez, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcale Cuevas, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Guzmán, José I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramiro Olivier, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se estima que existe relación entre conciencia fonológica y la velocidad de nombrar en el aprendizaje de la lectura. Los estudios se han realizado a través de procedimientos de intervención, o bien con alumnos con dificultades de aprendizaje de lectoescritura o con escasa conciencia fonológica. Se presenta un estudio longitudinal sin intervención como elemento innovador para conocer la influencia de la conciencia fonológica y la velocidad de nombrar sobre la lectura. 85 alumnos fueron evaluados con el Rapid Automatized Naming Test, la Prueba de Evaluación del Conocimiento Fonológico y el test de evaluación de lectura PROLEC-R en dos momentos evolutivos: a los 5,6 y a los 6,5 años. Se realizó un cálculo correlacional, así como un análisis de regresión jerárquica para conocer la varianza explícita de las variables conciencia fonológica y velocidad de nombrar en la lectura. Los resultados mostraron que la conciencia fonológica y la velocidad de nombrar contribuyen de manera distinta a la decodificación lectora. Las discrepancias encontradas con estudios previos en este campo pueden derivarse de las distintas medidas utilizadas en conciencia fonológica y velocidad de nombrar(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);22(3): 436-442, 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81487</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Velocidad de nombrar y conciencia fonológica en el aprendizaje inicial de la lectura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3262</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11813^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11813^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15334</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12366</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37623^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7981^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29986^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29986^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
