<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052891</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perinatal diagnosis and treatment of giant lymphangioma of the neck</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">With the advances in prenatal ultrasound, most congenital malformations can be diagnosed prior to birth, allowing for the planning of early treatment. Lymphangiomas are the most common benign congenital lesions observed with this technique. In some cases, they are associated with other malformations or chromosomal anomalies. The seriousness of a lymphangioma depends on the type, location, extension and whether or not others structures are involved. The most widespread therapeutic option is surgery, the objective of which is the complete resection of the lesion without damaging adjacent structures. Although there are other treatment options, we think that the choice of the approach depends on each patient, on the site of the lymphangioma and on the involvement of other structures. We discuss these aspects in the present review</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Rabago, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereira Díaz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Archundia, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Anaya Reyes, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín del Campo, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tinajero Iriarte, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Con el avance de la ecografía prenatal, se diagnostican muchas anomalías congénitas, lo que permite planificar un tratamiento temprano. Las linfagiomas son la lesión cogénita benigna más común de todas las malformaciones encontradas por ecografía prenatal, en algunas ocasiones asociadas a otras malformaciones y/o con cariotipo anormal. La gravedad de los linfangiomas se basa en el tipo, la localización, la extensión y la infiltración a otras estructuras. El tratamiento quirúrgico es el más aceptado, con el objetivo principal de lograr la resección completa, sin causar daño a las estructuras anexas y, aunque hay otras alternativas de tratamiento, creemos que se debe individualizar la mejor opción según la localización e infiltración del linfangioma a otras estructuras, motivo de nuestra revisión</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;65(1): 32-35, ene. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052891</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico y manejo perinatal del linfangioma gigante de cuello</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8379^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8379^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9524^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13895^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11731^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9524^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6409^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6409^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32092^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6409^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31993^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31993^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31994^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8379^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32092^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
