<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131809</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-7615</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The objective of this study is to compare the constructive thinking, a measure of emotional intelligence, between a clinical sample of adult patients diagnosed with dual diagnosis and a non-clinical sample. Method: By means of a comparative design of investigation, a not clinical sample of 835 subjects was compared with a sample of 180 subjects diagnosed of dual diagnosis: 78 with clinical disorders or of the Axix I and 102 with disorders of the personality or of the Axis II, according to DSM-TR-IV. Results: The results indicate a constructive thinking greater than in the non-clinical sample, as well as a destructive thinking higher in the sample with dual diagnosis. There were no differences between clinical disorders and personality. Conclusions: The clinic sample presents a destructive pattern of coping or no adaptative compared with non-clinical population, which in the case of patients with personality disorders is increased by illusions and superstitions and esoteric thoughts that contribute to their coping deficit (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López García, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albalat Alcaraz, Caridad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Ros, Encarna</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El objetivo de este estudio es comparar el pensamiento constructivo, una medida de inteligencia emocional, entre una muestra clínica de pacientes adultos diagnosticados de patología dual y una muestra no clínica. Método: Mediante un diseño de investigación comparativo, una muestra no clínica de 835 sujetos se comparó con una muestra de 180 sujetos diagnosticados de patología dual: 78 con trastornos clínicos o del Eje I y102 con trastornos de la personalidad o del Eje II, según criterios DSM-IV-TR. Resultados: Los resultados indican un pensamiento constructivo superior en la muestra no clínica, así como un pensamiento destructivo superior en la muestra con patología dual. No se apreciaron diferencias entre trastornos clínicos y de personalidad. Conclusiones: La muestra clínica presenta un patrón destructivo o desadaptativo de afrontamiento en comparación con población no clínica, que en el caso de pacientes con trastornos de personalidad se ve incrementado por ilusiones, supersticiones y pensamientos esotéricos que contribuyen a su afrontamiento deficitario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. drogodepend;39(4): 47-58, oct.-dic. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131809</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pensamiento constructivo como medida de inteligencia emocional en patología dual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31511^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31511^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31511^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7272^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31511^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53742^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13870^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31511^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14230</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
