<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78898</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Expression of matrix metalloproteinase-9 in prostate cancer. Preliminary experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: To study the validity of Matrix Metalloproteinase 9 as a complementary marker to PSA for the diagnosis and prognosis of Prostate Cancer.METHODS: Prospective study structured as a hospital-based cohort of 100 consecutive patients undergoing prostate biopsy. Serum determination of MMP-9 was carried out by means of inmunoassay . Statistical analysis was performed using the Stata/SE 8.2 software.RESULTS: 32 patients were diagnosed with prostate cancer and 52% had a Gleason score equal to or greater than 7. The values of serum MMP-9 varied between 225.7 and 1932.3 ng/ml, without significant differences among patients with benign, malignant and uncertain histology (p=0.429). The differences approached statistical significance in the subgroup of patients with PSA at 4-10 ng/ml (p=0.058), and significant differences were observed in the subgroup with free PSA to total PSA coefficient of less than 15% (p=0.037). No relationship between the Gleason score and the level of MMP-9 was shown (p=0.739). The levels of PSA and MMP-9 were shown to be independent (Pearson coefficient of correlation -0.1).CONCLUSIONS: It was not possible to show the efficacy of MMP-9 in predicting the result of the biopsy. In the group of patients with slightly increased levels of PSA (between 4 and 10 ng/ml) all the descriptive variables were higher in the group with malignant histology, though they did not reach statistical significance, they did reach significance when the coefficient of free PSA over total PSA was less than 15%, but this finding is not relevant clinically, as these patients already have a clear indication for biopsy. Neither was the relationship with the prognosis shown as there are no differences of MMP-9 expression at varying Gleason scores(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gonzalez Rodriguez, Iván</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gonzalez Arriaga, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernandez Samoano, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muruamendiaraz Fernandez, Valentín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Ugarteburu, Rodrigo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tardon, Adonina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivas del Fresno, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernandez García, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perez-Carral, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lopez Cima, Felicitas</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Estudiar la validez de la metaloproteasa 9 (MMP-9) como marcador complementario al PSA en el diagnóstico y el pronóstico del carcinoma de próstata.MÉTODO: Estudio prospectivo estructurado como cohorte de base hospitalaria. Fueron incluidos 100 pacientes consecutivos a los que se iba a practicar una biopsia prostática. La determinación sérica de MMP-9 se realizó mediante inmunoensayo, y el análisis estadístico con el programa informático stata/SE 8.2.RESULTADOS: 32 pacientes fueron diagnosticados de carcinoma prostático y el 52% de ellos con grado Gleason mayor o igual a 7. Los valores de MMP-9 sérica oscilaron entre 225,7 y 1932,3 nanogramos por mililitro, sin encontrar diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre los pacientes con histología benigna, maligna e incierta (p=0,429). Las diferencias se acercaron a la significación estadística en el subgrupo de pacientes con PSA 4-10 ng/ml (p=0,058) y en el subgrupo PSA libre/total menor de 15% se observaron diferencias significativas (p=0,037). No se encontró relación entre el grado Gleason y el nivel de MMP-9 (p=0,739). Los niveles de PSA y MMP-9 demostraron ser independientes (Coeficiente de correlación de Pearson -0,1).CONCLUSIONES: No fue posible demostrar la eficacia de la MMP-9 para predecir el resultado de la biopsia. En el grupo de pacientes con elevaciones discretas del PSA (entre 4 y 10 ng/ml) todas las variables descriptivas fueron superiores en el grupo con histología maligna, sin alcanzar la significación estadística. Sí se alcanzó la significación cuando el cociente de PSA libre entre PSA total fue menor del 15%, pero este hallazgo no tiene relevancia en la práctica clínica, pues estos pacientes ya tienen indicación clara de biopsia. Tampoco se demuestra relación con el pronóstico al no existir diferencias de expresión de MMP-9 entre diferentes grados Gleason(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;63(2): 119-124, mar. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78898</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Expresión de metaloproteasa de matriz 9 en el cáncer de próstata. Experiencia preliminar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38178</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24016^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38178^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38178^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
