<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165298</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Correlation between physical activity and self-efficacy in Chinese university students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Physical inactivity is becoming increasingly prevalent in Chinese university students. This study aims to assess the leisure-time physical activity level of the Chinese university students and to examine the correlation between the physical activity level and the self-efficacy to overcome barriers to physical activity. Five hundred and thirty Chinese university students participated in the study voluntarily. The International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ, Chinese Short version) and the Self-Efficacy to Overcome Barriers to Physical Activity Scale (SOBPAS) are adopted. The results suggested: (1) the level of leisure-time physical activity in Chinese University students is relatively low; (2) self-efficacy to overcome barriers to physical activity is significantly correlated with the physical activity, it can be used as a predictor of university students&#146; leisure time physical activity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Liu, Hao</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dai, Xia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La inactividad física es cada vez más frecuente en los estudiantes universitarios chinos. Este estudio tiene como objetivo evaluar el nivel de actividad física de los estudiantes universitarios chinos y examinar la correlación entre el nivel de actividad física y la autoeficacia para superar las barreras a la actividad física. Quinientos treinta estudiantes universitarios chinos participaron voluntariamente en el estudio. Se aprueban el Cuestionario Internacional de Actividad Física (IPAQ, Versión Corta Chino) y la Autoeficacia para Superar Barreras a la Escala de Actividad Física (SOBPAS). Los resultados sugieren: 1) que el nivel de actividad física en los estudiantes universitarios chinos es relativamente bajo; (2) la autoeficacia para superar las barreras a la actividad física está significativamente correlacionada con la actividad física, puede ser utilizado como predictor de la actividad física de los estudiantes universitarios de tiempo libre (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;26(supl.4): 110-114, 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165298</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Correlación entre la actividad física y la autoeficacia en estudiantes universitarios chinos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2727</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33883</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8076</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
