<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84421</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4008</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Monitoring of management indicators that link hospital emergecy activity and laboratory workload</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This aim of this study is to monitor the activity carried out in the emergency laboratory of Son Dureta University Hospital during the years 2000&#150;2004 and to discuss the variations. This work is based on the the graphical comparison between the trends of indicators of analytical demand (tests/requests), (URV/requests), and (URV/tests) that represent the productivity of laboratory and also other indicators that associate emergency activities of the hospital with the laboratory (laboratory requests/emergencies), (tests/emergencies), and (URV/emergencies). The results show an inverse relationship between the hospital emergencies and laboratory. The hospital emergencies have decreased as there is a new hospital in Palma, on the other hand, the activity of the urgent laboratory has increased. The reason is due to the increase inpatient activity in new hospital areas: heart surgery, a significant increase of critical care, psychiatry, toxicology, etc. A trend to complexity is observed, that is due to the increase in indices: URV/tests, tests/emergencies, and URV/emergencies; that have arisen from the new diagnostic criteria for myocardial infarction. This has caused a large increase tropinin assays, the use of CRP as a sepsis marker and drug abuse testing to confirm the suspicion of drug taking(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Parera Rosselló, María Magdalena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuster Fuster, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guix Aguado, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Escribano, Herminio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Raja, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonnín Tomas, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo es monitorizar la actividad realizada por el laboratorio de urgencias del Hospital Universitario Son Dureta durante el período 2000-2004 y tratar de justificar las variaciones. El estudio se basa en la comparación gráfica de la tendencia mostrada por los indicadores de demanda analítica (magnitudes/peticiones, unidades relativas de valor (URV)/peticiones y URV/magnitudes), que representan la productividad del laboratorio, y la de los indicadores que relacionan la actividad de urgencias del hospital y la del laboratorio (peticiones laboratorio/urgencias, magnitudes/urgencias, URV/urgencias). Los resultados demuestran una relación inversa entre las urgencias del hospital y las del laboratorio. Las urgencias hospitalarias han disminuido por la apertura de un segundo hospital en Palma; en cambio, la actividad del laboratorio de urgencias ha aumentado. El motivo es el incremento de las urgencias de hospitalización derivadas fundamentalmente de áreas relacionadas con nuevas acciones hospitalarias: cirugía cardíaca, unidad de reanimación, psiquiatría, desintoxicación, toxicología, hemodinámica intervencionista 24 h, etc. Se observa una tendencia hacia la complejidad por el incremento de los índices URV/magnitudes, magnitudes/urgencias y URV/urgencias; a ello han contribuido, sobre todo, los nuevos criterios diagnósticos del infarto de miocardio que conllevan realizar muchas más determinaciones de troponina, el uso de proteína C reactiva como marcador de sepsis y las determinaciones de drogas de abuso para confirmar la sospecha de ingestión en las urgencias hospitalarias(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. lab. clín;1(1): 24-28, mar. 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84421</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Monitorización de indicadores de gestión que relacionan la actividad de urgencias del hospital y la del laboratorio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29563^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29563^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51711^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33124^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25665</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51711^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33124^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28416^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33124^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28416^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
