<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60096</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interposed abdominal compression in cardiopulmonary arrest: a literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine whether interposed abdominal compression during cardiopulmonary resuscitation is a technique worth considering on the basis of published evidence. Method: A literature search was performed on PubMed for the period January through December 2007 using the keywords: interposed abdominal compression alone or in combination with chest compression or cardiopulmonary resuscitation. We selected only those studies that evaluated interposed abdominal compression. A total of 42 articles were found; 17 were reviews of the literature or articles on the history of the technique and 25 were clinical studies of different types and measuring a number of variables: blood pressure, cardiac output, survival, etc. These clinical studies were grouped according to the variable measured in order to compare results. Results: Some of the studies point to the advantages of interposed abdominal compression while others cast doubt on its utility; very few presented statistically significant evidence in favor of interposed abdominal compression, and benefits involved very specific measures. According to the studies reviewed, interposed abdominal compression increases venous return, improving cardiac filling and, hence, cardiac output during cardiopulmonary resuscitation. It increases diastolic pressure in the thoracic aorta, favoring coronary artery perfusion during the phase of chest relaxation. It therefore increases survival among patients who require cardiopulmonary resuscitation. Conclusions: None of the studies reviewed found interposed abdominal compression to offer a statistically significant advantage in comparison with standard cardiopulmonary resuscitation. However, the outcome measures in many of those studies suggest that this technique could actually be effective, justifying a trial to determine whether it is really useful (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Noval de la Torre, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galván Sasía, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Intentar determinar en base a los artículos revisados si la compresión abdominal interpuesta (CAI) es una técnica a tener en cuenta en las maniobras de reanimación cardiopulmonar (RCP).Método: Se realizó una búsqueda bibliográfica vía internet por medio de PubMed® entre los meses de enero y diciembre de 2007 utilizando como palabra clave &#147;compresión abdominal interpuesta&#148; sola o asociada a &#147;masaje torácico&#148; o &#147;reanimación cardiopulmonar&#148;. Se seleccionaron sólo aquellos estudios en los que la CAI estaba implicada directamente en el estudio. Se encontraron un total 42 artículos, de los cuales17 eran revisiones bibliográficas o históricas y 25 eran ensayos clínicos de distintos tipos en los que a su vez se medían diferentes variables (presión arterial, gasto cardiaco, supervivencia,&#133;). Posteriormente, se dividieron según el parámetro medido con el fin de comparar los resultados obtenidos en cada estudio. Resultados: Entre los estudios encontrados algunos muestran de las ventajas de la CAI y otros ponen en duda su utilidad, muy pocos con evidencia estadísticamente significativa a favor de la CAI y siempre con respecto a parámetros muy concretos. Según los estudios revisados, la compresión abdominal interpuesta aumenta el retorno venoso mejorando el llenado de las cavidades cardiacas durantes la RCP y por tanto mejora el gasto cardiaco; causa un aumento de la presión diastólica de la aorta torácica lo que favorece la perfusión coronaria en la fase de relajación torácica; y por tanto aumenta la supervivencia de los pacientes que sufren una parada cardiorrespiratoria (PCR) (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);21(1): 17-22, feb. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60096</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Compresión abdominal interpuesta en la parada cardiorrespiratoria: revisión crítica de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30213^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6475^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
