<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106799</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0973</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A survey about the satisfaction of heroin ¿dependent patients from Valencia region (Spain) with methadone treatment centres</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To multidimensionally assess heroin¿dependent patients' satisfaction with methadone treatment centres from Valencia Region (Spain). Method. An independent interviewer recruited 278 consecutively arriving patients from 12 randomly selected centres (9 conventional centres and 3 mobile methadone clinics) to participate in a survey that included the Verona Service Satisfaction Scale for Methadone Treatment (VSSS¿MT). Results. One hundred sixty¿six (59.7%) patients agreed to participate. Mean overall VSSS¿MT score was 3.5 (SD = 0.6), on a 1¿5 point scale (1 = terrible; 5 = excellent). The percentage of patients who felt satisfied (VSSS¿MT scores &gt; 3) was, by category: overall satisfaction, 82.4%; basic interventions, 80.6%; specific interventions, 59.2%; social worker skills, 66.3%; psychologist skills, 71.6%. In a multiple regression analysis, methadone take¿home privileges, lower number of days from the last dose adjustment, and being treated in a conventional (not mobile) methadone clinic appeared as independent predictors of satisfaction with methadone maintenance treatment. This regression model accounted for 9% of the variance in VSSS¿MT overall scores. Conclusions. The survey results show that heroin¿dependent patients from Valencia Region are slightly satisfied with methadone treatment centres. The variables most strongly related to this satisfaction accounted for only a limited amount of the variance in VSSS¿MT overall scores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Trujols, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valderrama, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gich, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez de los Cobos, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valero, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Valorar multidimensionalmente la satisfacción de los pacientes dependientes de heroína con los centros de tratamiento con metadona de la Comunidad de Valencia. Método. Se solicitó a 278 pacientes que llegaron consecutivamente a los 12 centros (9 convencionales y 3 unidades móviles) seleccionados aleatoriamente, su participación en una encuesta que incluía la Escala de Verona para valorar la Satisfacción con los Servicios en los centros de Tratamiento con Metadona (VSSS¿MT). Resultados. Ciento sesenta y seis (59,7%) pacientes aceptaron participar. La media global de las puntuaciones en la VSSS¿MT fue 3,5 (DT = 0,6), siendo el rango de puntuaciones de dicha escala 1¿5 (1: malísima y 5: excelente). El porcentaje de pacientes que se sintió satisfecho (VSSS¿MT &gt; 3) fue, por categorías, el siguiente: valoración global, 82,4%; intervenciones básicas 80,6%; intervenciones específi cas 59,3%; habilidades de los trabajadores sociales 66,3%; habilidades de los psicólogos 71,7%. En un análisis de regresión múltiple, los predictores independientes de la satisfacción con el tratamiento de mantenimiento con metadona (TMM) fueron: hallarse en régimen de take¿home o dosis para llevar a casa, un menor número de días desde el último ajuste de dosis, y recibir el TMM en un centro convencional &#151;y no en unidad móvil&#151;. Este modelo de regresión explicó el 9% de la varianza de las puntuaciones totales de la VSSS¿MT. Conclusiones. Los pacientes dependientes de opioides de la Comunidad de Valencia se sienten ligeramente satisfechos con los centros de tratamiento con metadona. Las variables más intensamente asociadas con tal satisfacción explican un limitado porcentaje de la varianza de la puntuación global de la VSSS¿MT (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trastor. adict;14(3): 66-72, jul.-dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106799</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Encuesta sobre la satisfacción de los pacientes dependientes de heroína de la Comunidad de Valencia con los centros de tratamiento con metadona</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23920^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23920^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6715^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6715^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8866^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
