<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165290</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Maintaining and managing athletic identity among elite athletes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Researchers have studied athletic identity (AI) and explored the impact that having a strong AI can have on an athlete. Additionally, researchers have explored the maintenance of AI, but only among very specific athletic populations. Little is known about how different athletes manage their AI at various stages in their career (i.e., still competing versus retired). Therefore, the purpose of this study was to explore how both retired and non-retired elite athletes from a range of sports maintain and perpetuate their AI. Five male and eight female elite athletes were individually interviewed on two separate occasions. Participants were asked questions regarding their AI, their successes and failures in sport, and how their feelings of self-worth were related to their athletic achievements. An inductive data analysis process was used, and relevant themes were identified. It was also found that there are things athletes do, or that occur in their environment that maintain and perpetuate their AI. The current findings expand this body of literature by exploring the various strategies elite athletes use to support their AI (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arts Poucher, Zoe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tamminen, Katherine A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los investigadores han estudiado la identidad atlética (AI) y han explorado el impacto que puede generar tener una AI fuerte en un atleta. Además, los investigadores han explorado el mantenimiento de la AI, pero sólo entre las poblaciones atléticas muy específicas. Poco se sabe acerca de cómo los diferentes atletas manejan su AI en varias etapas de su carrera (es decir, siguen compitiendo contra jubilados). Por lo tanto, el propósito de este estudio fue explorar cómo los atletas de elite jubilados y no retirados de una variedad de deportes mantienen y perpetúan su AI. Cinco atletas de élite masculinos y ocho femeninos fueron entrevistados individualmente en dos ocasiones. Se les preguntó a los participantes acerca de su AI, sus éxitos y fracasos en el deporte, y cómo sus sentimientos de autoestima estaban relacionados con sus logros atléticos. Se utilizó un proceso inductivo de análisis de datos y se identificaron temas relevantes. También se encontró que hay cosas que los atletas hacen, o que ocurren en su entorno que mantienen y perpetúan su AI. Los hallazgos actuales amplían este cuerpo de literatura explorando las diversas estrategias que los atletas de élite usan para apoyar su AI (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;26(supl.4): 63-67, 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165290</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mantenimiento y gestión de la identidad atlética entre atletas de élite</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7244</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12594^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
