<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60214</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Infantile hemangioendothelioma of the liver</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Infantile hemangioendothelioma of the liver is a benign tumor composed of anastomosed vascular channels. Usually they cause symptoms during the first 6 months of life which occasionally may be serious, above all in cases of congestive heart failure or coagulopathy. In many cases it may be provided by imaging techniques (ultrasound, computed tomography and magnetic resonance imaging) sufficient information to diagnose and to plan for adequate treatment. We present a case of a newborn with congestive heart failure and hepatomegaly due to hemangioendothelioma of the liver. We review the presentation, diagnostic and treatment of it, as soon as the principal differential diagnoses to take into account in the presence of aneounatal hepatic neoplasm (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Díez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ornia Rodríguez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Catañón Hevia, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meana Morís, A. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solís Sánchez, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García González, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El hemangionedotelioma hepático infantil es un tumor benigno compuesto de canales vasculares anastomosados. Lo más frecuente es que se produzcan síntomas en los 6 primeros meses de vida, que en ocasiones pueden ser graves, sobre todo en casos de fallo cardiaco congestivo o coagulopatía. En muchos casos se puede obtener con técnicas de imagen (ultrasonidos, tomografía computarizada y resonancia magnética) suficiente información para el diagnóstico y planificación del tratamiento adecuado. Presentamos el caso de un neonato con fallo cardiaco congestivo y hepatomegalia debido a hemangioendotelioma hepático. Se revisa la presentación, diagnóstico y tratamiento del mismo así como los principales diagnósticos diferenciales a tener en cuenta ante una neoplasia hepática neonatal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;63(6): 508-510, nov.-dic. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60214</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hemangioendotelioma hepático infantil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31421^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8287^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8287^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31421^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
