<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051999</identifier>
<setSpec>0556-6177</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidemiology of thyroid gland disorders in Galicia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Thyroid diseases are one of the most common endocrine disorders.Epidemiological data on different alterations normally come from a rangeof areas. Here we present many aspects of thyroid disorders, in thesame area over a twenty-year period (1984-2004).We show that residents of Galicia were not affected by endemic goiter.Iodine intake in the school population in this area was adequate beforethe promotion of consumption of iodized salt.An increase in iodine intake induces a significant increase in the incidenceof clinical hyperthyroidism in the adult population.A long-term benefit has been observed in the young population afterpromotion of iodized salt consumption.However, despite the campaign, an elevated percentage of pregnantwomen or women of fertile age have an insufficient iodine intake.We show that gestation or postpartum-related thyroid disorders are mainlysubclinical. In addition, prevalence of postpartum thyroiditis increasessix months after delivery. Postpartum depression was not related tothyroid dysfunction</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Mayor, R. V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galofré, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ríos, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los estudios epidemiológicos realizados por nuestro grupo en la comunidadgallega en el periodo 1984-2004 han demostrado:1. La población del sur de Galicia no padecía de bocio endémico y queel consumo de yodo de la población pediátrica en nuestra área erasuficiente antes de la campaña de promoción del consumo de sal yodada.2. El aumento del consumo de yodo en nuestra población indujo unaumento significativo en la incidencia de hipertiroidismo clínico en lapoblación adulta.3. Que la campaña de promoción del consumo de sal yodada ha sidobeneficiosa a largo plazo sobre la población infantil.4. Que pese a la existencia de la citada campaña, un porcentaje elevadode las mujeres gestantes y aquellas en edad fértil tienen un consumodeficiente de yodo dietético.5. Poseemos en nuestra comunidad datos sobre la prevalencia de lasdistintas formas y grados de disfunción tiroidea.6. Demostramos que la disfunción tiroidea asociada a la gestación o alperiodo posparto es fundamentalmente del tipo subclínico y que la prevalenciade tiroiditis posparto es mayor a partir de los 6 meses. Tambiénque las anomalías psíquicas que presentan algunas mujeres en elposparto no se asocian con disfunción tiroidea o tiroiditis posparto</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Med Univ Navarra;50(1): 11-16, ene. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051999</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Epidemiología de las enfermedades de la glándula tiroides en Galicia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12080^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7619^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19366^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6187^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14354^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14347^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d651^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
