<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150750</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Motivation for practice of recreational physical activity and physical inactivity in population of Chihuahua (Mexico)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The reasons for the general population practiced recreational physical activity or inactivity remain are diverse and vary according to age and sex, in populations with high levels of Chronic Noncom - municable Diseases (NCDs), these grounds should be studied to design appropriate strategies to achieve population increasing participation in adequate physical activity (exercise) to promote health. Objective: To identify the reasons why people engage/not engage in sports or recreational physical activity in Chihuahua city and it&#146;s relationship with age and gender. Methods: 655 subjects were recruited, including 335 6-to-90-year-old women, and 320 men among 6 and 91 years old. They were classified by age into five groups, and a questionnaire was applied to them during the months of May and June 2014, about the type of physical activity they were engaged in and the reasons behind this activity or inactivity. Results: The main motivations behind the practice of physical exercise were: pleasure (22.8% of the little girls and 36.6% of the little boys, 15.3% of the adolescent girls and 33% of the adolescent boys); and health (27.3% of the young women adults, 37.1% of the women mature adults, and 28.4% of the elderly woman. Among the masculine gender: 32.3% of young men, 52.2% of mature adults, and 21.9% of senior men). The reasons for inactivity were: lack of health - among the elderly people-; and lack of time -among the other age groups of the masculine gender-; among the femenine gender little girls referred to lack of motivation as the reason for not doing exercise, adolescent girls said they don&#146;t like to work out, and young and mature adult women said they don&#146;t have time to exercise. Discussion: The reasons why people realize or not exercise vary in relation to age and sex, it is remarkable that women do not exercise as much as men, children and youth prefer moderate to vigorous physical activity, the school children there are a higher proportion of those engaged in physical exercise than those who do not practice, however upon reaching the adolescence age and until age 60 or more, it is evident that there is a greater part of the population that does not perform physical exercise, encouraging the development of NCDs. Conclusion: The main reasons why exercise is performed are: to improve the health and taste corresponding to walking, football and dance, while the reasons for not exercise is lack of time, dislike and discouragement and in the case elderly for advanced disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hinojos-Seáñez, Elsa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Duarte, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>De La Torre-Díaz, María de Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo-Rentería, José Buenaventura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Daw, María de Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los motivos por los cuales la población general practica actividad física recreativa o permanecen en la inactividad son diversos y varían de acuerdo a la edad y el sexo, en poblaciones donde hay una alta prevalencia de Enfermedades Crónicas No Transmisibles (ECNT), estos motivos deben ser estudiados para diseñar estrategias adecuadas a la población que logren incrementar la práctica de Actividad física adecuada (ejercicio físico) para promover la salud. Objetivo: Identificar los motivos por los que las personas realizan o no actividad física recreativa o deportiva en la ciudad de Chihuahua y su relación con el sexo y la edad. Material y Métodos: En 655 sujetos, 355 mujeres con edades entre 6 y 90 años; y 320 hombres con edades entre 6 y 91 años, que fueron divididos en 5 grupos por edad, se aplicó un cuestionario de creación propia durante los meses de mayo a junio del 2014, sobre los motivos por los cuales realizan o no actividad física. Resultados: Los principales motivos por los que rea lizan ejercicio son: por gusto 22.8% de las niñas y el 36.6% de los niños, 15.3% de las adolescentes y 33% de los adolescentes; por salud el 27.3% de los mujeres adultas jóvenes, 37.1% de mujeres adultas maduras y 28.4% de las mujeres adultas mayores; en contraste con el sexo masculino 32.3% adultos jóvenes, 52.2% adultos maduros y 21.9% adultos mayores. Los motivos por los que no la realizan en los adultos mayores son por enfermedad incapacitante, los demás grupos de edad y sexo masculino son por falta de tiempo, en el sexo femenino las niñas refieren por desmotivación, a las adolescentes no les gusta y las mujeres adultas jóvenes y maduras por falta de tiempo. Discusión: Los motivos por los que la población rea - liza o no ejercicio físico varían en relación a la edad y el sexo, es notable que las mujeres realizan menos actividad física que los hombres; en los niños y en los jóvenes se prefieren las actividades físicas de moderadas a vigorosas, en los escolares la proporción de quienes realizan ejercicio físico es mayor que quienes no lo practican. Sin embargo, al llegar a la edad de la adolescencia hasta la edad de 60 o más años, es evidente que es mayor la población que no realiza ejercicio físico, favoreciendo el desarrollo de las ENT. Conclusión: Los principales motivos por los que se realiza ejercicio son: por mejorar la salud y por gusto correspondiendo a caminar, futbol y bailar, mientras que los motivos por los que no realizan ejercicio son por falta de tiempo, disgusto y desmotivación y en el caso de adultos mayores por enfermedad avanzada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;36(1): 10-16, 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150750</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Motivos para la práctica de actividad física recreativa e inactividad en la población de Chihuahua (México)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53696^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
