<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74717</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Postoperative complications in a man with San Filippo syndrome anesthetized for multiple tooth extraction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">San Filippo syndrome is a hereditary lysosomaldisorder resulting in the accumulation ofmucopolysaccharides (mucopolysaccharidosis type III). Adeficit in the enzyme required to break down heparansulfate leads to its deposition in the connective tissue ofmany organs, particularly the brain, liver, heart, andspleen. The first symptoms&#151;including mentaldeterioration, dimorphism, and behavioral changes suchas hyperkinesis and aggressivity&#151;present in childhood.Because this rare disorder has many anestheticimplications, we report the case of a 20-year-old man withSan Filippo syndrome who underwent multiple toothextraction under general combined anesthesia and a blockof the second and third branches of the trigeminal nerve.This anesthetic combination provided satisfactory surgicalconditions and recovery from anesthesia was rapid.Following surgery the patient developed a respiratoryinfection that led to severe respiratory failure and death(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Palazón, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Navarro, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuentes-García, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de San Filippo es una enfermedad hereditariade almacenamiento lisosomal perteneciente algrupo de las mucopolisacaridosis (mucopolisacaridosistipo III). Existe un déficit enzimático necesario para ladegradación del heparán sulfato que hace que se depositeen el tejido conectivo de múltiples órganos, sobre todoen cerebro, hígado, corazón y bazo. Los primeros síntomasde la enfermedad aparecen en la infancia presentandoun deterioro mental, dimorfismo y alteracionesdel comportamiento con hiperquinesia y agresividad.Por las múltiples implicaciones anestésicas de estarara enfermedad, presentamos el caso clínico de unpaciente de 20 años de edad con síndrome de San Filippo,que fue intervenido para exodoncia múltiple bajoanestesia general combinada con bloqueo troncular de lasegunda y tercera rama del nervio trigémino, que proporcionócondiciones quirúrgicas satisfactorias y unarecuperación de la anestesia rápida. Durante el periodopostoperatorio presentó una infección respiratoria que leprovocó una insuficiencia respiratoria grave y posteriorfallecimiento del paciente(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;56(8): 503-506, oct. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74717</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conducta perioperatoria en un paciente con síndrome de San Filippo sometido a exodoncia múltiple</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30389^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12561^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33572^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20180^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30000^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
