<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141228</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A surgical safety checklist implementation: experience of a start-up phase of a collaborative project in hospitals of Catalonia, Spai</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Surgical patient safety is a priority in the national and international quality healthcare improvement strategies. The objective of the study was to implement a collaborative intervention with multiple components and to evaluate the impact of the patient surgical safety checklist (SSC) application. This is a prospective, longitudinal multicenter study with a 7-month follow-up period in 2009 based on a collaborative intervention for the implementation of a 24 item-SSC distributed in 3 different stages (sign in, time out, sign out) for its application to the surgical patient. A total number of 27 hospitals participated in the strategy. The global implementation rate was 48% (95%CI, 47.6%-48.4%) during the evaluation period. The overall compliance with all the items of the SSC included in each stage (sign in, time out, sign out) was 75,1% (95%CI, 73.5%-76.7%) for the sign in, 77.1% (95%CI, 75.5%-78.6%) for the time out and 88.3% (95%CI, 87.2%-89.5%) for the sign out respectively. The individual compliance with each item of the SSC has remained above 85%, except for the surgical site marking with an adherence of 67.4% (95%CI, 65.7%-69.1%)] and 71.2% (95%CI, 69.6%-72.9%)] in the sign in and time out respectively. The SSC was successfully implemented to 48% of the surgeries performed to the participating hospitals. The global compliance with the SSC was elevated and the intervention trend was stable during the evaluation period. Strategies were identified to allow of a higher number of surgeries with application of the SSC and more professional involvement in measures compliance such as surgical site marking (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mora, Núria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vila, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oller, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallverdú, Helena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orrego, Carola</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bañeres, Joaquim</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Secanell, Mariona</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La seguridad en el paciente quirúrgico es un tema de alta prioridad en las estrategias de mejora de la calidad en atención sanitaria en los ámbitos nacional e internacional. El objetivo fue implementar una inte rvención colaborativa de múltiples componentes y evaluar su impacto en la aplicación de un listado de verificación quirúrgico (LVQ) de prácticas seguras en el paciente. Estudio prospectivo, longitudinal, multicéntrico, basado en la aplicación y seguimiento durante 7 meses en el año 2009 de una intervención colaborativa, para facilitar la implementación de un LVQ de 24 ítems distribuidos en 3 momentos de aplicación en el paciente quirúrgico, siendo estos los momentos de verificación preoperatoria (VP), pausa preoperatoria (PP) y verificación a la salida de quirófano (VS). Se adhirieron 27 hospitales a la estrategia. La implementación global fue del 48% (intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 47,6-48,4). El cumplimiento de todos los ítems del LVQ para cada momento de aplicación fue de un 75,1% (IC del 95%, 73,5-76,7), un 77,1% (IC del 95%, 75,5-78,6) y un 88,3% (IC del 95%, 87,2-89,5) para la VP, la PP y la VS, respectivamente. El cumplimiento individual de cada ítem del LVQ se mantuvo por encima del 85%, excepto en la realización del marcaje, con un 67,4% (IC del 95%, 65,7-69,1) y un 71,2% (IC del 95%, 9,6-72,9) en la VP y PP, respectivamente. Se consiguió implementar el LVQ en el 48% de las cirugías en los hospitales participantes. El cumplimiento fue elevado y se mantuvo estable en el tiempo. Se identificaron estrategias para aumentar el alcance en el número de cirugías con aplicación del LVQ y más implicación de los profesionales en el cumplimiento de medidas tales como la realización del marcaje (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);143(supl.1): 17-24, jul. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141228</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implementación de un listado de verificación de prácticas seguras en cirugía: experiencia de la fase inicial de la puesta en marcha de un proyecto colaborativo en hospitales de Catalunya</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7541</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3320</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53822</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33121^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20180^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6935^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31061^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28984^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23802</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10549^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10055^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201407</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
