<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123820</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-7615</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Drug abuse is currently a complex phenomenon with negative consequences for the individual, family, and society in Mexico. Merida, Yucatan, is no exception, so the local government and several organisations are addressing this problem through different social programmes; these programmes lack evaluations, however. The alternative that considers evaluating social programmes is gaining ground over more traditionalist methodologies and policies (Mercado-Martínez, Bosi y Hernández-Ibarra, 2010), as it helps to makeappropriate decisions to develop relevant actions. This paper focuses on the evaluation of the perceived utility of a social programme revolving around the medical-psychiatric, psychological and social therapeutic management of individuals who use drugs,  conducted by Centros de Integración Juvenil Unincorporated Association based on the participants&#146; experience, in Merida, Yucatan, Mexico. The methodology used in the study was phenomenological - qualitative, with participant observation, semi-structured interviews, and document analysis as techniques. The participants were six assistants, two ex-assistants, the organisation&#146;s director, the coordinators, and the programme manager. The results show the socio-familiar and labour developments of the attendees, addressing aspects involving the quality of their relationships, the role of communication, the use of free time, and the insertion of new socio-educational activities. Additionally, several other programme aspects are analysed, such as meeting objectives and the role of the individuals in charge, which helped to identify successes and failures in the programme in order to favour decision-making processes to generate improvement (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Echeverría Echeverría, Rebelín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serhant Cobos, Stephany Abraham</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Actualmente, en México el abuso de las drogas constituye un complejo fenómeno con consecuencias negativas a nivel individual, familiar y social. Mérida (Yucatán) no es la excepción, por lo que distintas organizaciones y el gobierno local atienden dicha problemática a través de diversos programas sociales, sin embargo se carece de evaluaciones a éstos. Plantearse la posibilidad de evaluar los programas sociales es una alternativa que intenta ganar terreno, suplantando políticas y metodologías tradicionalistas (Mercado-Martínez, Bosi y Hernández-Ibarra, 2010), ya que contribuye a tomar decisiones adecuadas para desarrollar acciones pertinentes. Este trabajo se centra en la evaluación de la percepción de utilidad a nivel individual de un programa social centrado en el manejo terapéutico médico-psiquiátrico, psicológico y social, en personas que consumen drogas; implementado por Centros de Integración Juvenil Asociación Civil, en Mérida, Yucatán, México, desde la experiencia de sus involucrados. La metodología utilizada fue de corte cualitativo fenomenológico con técnicas de observación participativa, entrevista semi-estructurada y análisis documental. Participaron seis asistentes, dos exasistentes, el director de la organización, los  coordinadores y la responsable del programa. Los resultados discuten la evolución sociofamiliar y laboral de los asistentes, abordando aspectos relacionados con la calidad de sus relaciones, el papel de la comunicación, el uso del tiempo libre y la inserción a nuevas actividades socioeducativas. Adicionalmente se analizan diferentes aspectos del programa como el cumplimiento de los objetivos y el papel de los responsables,  situación que permitió reconocer aciertos y desaciertos en el programa con miras a favorecer procesos de toma de decisión encaminados a la mejora (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. drogodepend;39(2): 31-45, abr.-jun. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123820</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la percepción de utilidad de un programa social dirigido a consumidores de drogas en Mérida, Yucatán, México</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54376^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3675</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16836</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
