<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160337</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Minimally invasive PCNL-MIP</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Miniaturized percutaneous nephrolithotomy (mini-PCNL) has increased in popularity in recent years and is now widely used to overcome the therapeutic gap between conventional PCNL and less-invasive procedures such as shock wave lithotripsy (SWL) or flexible ureterorenoscopy (URS) for the treatment of renal stones. However, despite its minimally invasive nature, the superiority in terms of safety, as well as the similar efficacy of mini-PCNL compared to conventional procedures, is still under debate. The aim of this chapter is to present one of the most recent advancements in terms of mini-PCNL: the Karl Storz &#145;minimally invasive PCNL&#146; (MIP). A literature search for original and review articles either published or e-published up to December 2016 was performed using Google and the PubMed database. Keywords included: minimally invasive PCNL; MIP. The retrieved articles were gathered and examined. The complete MIP set is composed of different sized rigid metallic fiber-optic nephroscopes and different sized metallic operating sheaths, according to which the MIP is categorized into extra-small (XS), small (S), medium (M) and large (L). Dilation can be performed either in one-step or with a progressive technique, as needed. The reusable devices of the MIP and vacuum cleaner efect make PCNL with this set a cheap procedure. The possibility to shift from a small to a larger instrument within the same set (Matrioska technique) makes MIP a very versatile technique suitable for the treatment of almost any stone. Studies in the literature have shown that MIP is equally effective, with comparable rates of post-operative complications, as conventional PCNL, independently from stone size. MIP does not represent a new technique, but rather a combination of the last ten years of PCNL improvements in a single system that can transversally cover all available techniques in the panorama of percutaneous stone treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montanari, Emanuele</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boeri, Luca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Talso, Michele</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zanetti, Stefano Paolo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallioli, Andrea</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Nefrolitotomía percutánea miniaturizada (mini-NLPC) ha aumentado de popularidad en años recientes y ahora se utiliza ampliamente en el tratamiento de la litiasis renal para superar la brecha entre la NLPC convencional y los procedimientos menos invasivos como litotricia extracorpórea por ondas de choque (LEOC) o ureterorrenoscopia flexible (URS). Sin embargo, a pesar de su naturaleza mínimamente invasiva, la superioridad en términos de seguridad, así cómo la similar eficacia de la mini-NLPC comparada con los procedimientos convencionales está todavía en debate. El objetivo de este capítulo es presentar uno de los avances más recientes en términos de mini-NLPC: La NLPC mínimamente invasiva de Karl Storz. Se realizó una búsqueda bibliográfica de artículos originales y revisiones publicados o e-publicados hasta diciembre del 2016 utilizando Google y la base de datos PubMed. Las palabras clave incluían: NLPC mínimamente invasiva; MIP. Los artículos obtenidos fueron recogidos y examinados. El equipo completo de MIP se compone de nefroscopios rígidos metálicos de fibra óptica de diferentes tamaños y vainas operatorias de diferentes calibres, conforme a lo cual la MIP se clasifica como extra pequeña (XS), pequeña (S), mediana (M) y grande (L). La dilatación se puede realizar en un paso o con una técnica progresiva, según las necesidades. Los aparatos de la MIP y el aspirador de vacío reutilizables hacen que la NLPC sea barata con este equipo. La posibilidad de cambiar de un instrumento pequeño a otro más grande dentro del mismo equipo (técnica Matrioska) hace que la MIP sea una técnica muy versátil adecuada para el tratamiento casi de cualquier piedra. Los estudios de la literatura han demostrado que la MIP es igualmente eficaz, con tasas de complicaciones postoperatorias comparables a la NLPC convencional, independientemente del tamaño de la piedra. La MIP no representa una técnica nueva, si no más una combinación de las mejoras de la NLPC de los últimos 10 años en un único sistema que puede cubrir transversalmente todas las técnicas disponibles en el panorama del tratamiento percutáneo de la litiasis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;70(1): 226-234, ene.-feb. 2017. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160337</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">NLPC minimamente invasiva-MIP</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19608^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52133^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24371^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52124^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
