<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049356</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sarcomatoid renal carcinoma with malignant heterologous elements: case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: The sarcomatoid pattern    represents the histological type of renal carcinoma with the poorest prognosis, receiving the grade 4 of the Furhman classification consistently.    METHODS: We report the case of a 80-year-old male who underwent nephroureterectomy with the pathologic diagnosis of sarcomatoid renal carcinoma with areas of chondro and osteosarcoma, as well as squamous cell differentiation. It is an exceptional case because it is rare to find all these elements in the same tumor.    RESULTS: The study of the surgical specimen enables in most cases the identification of some of the classic    histological patterns of renal carcinoma, nevertheless an immunohistochemical study is of great value for proper classification of the neoplasia and differential diagnosis with other renal lesions, mainly sarcomas.    CONCLUSIONS: The presence of malignant heterologous elements, as in our case, will confirm the.prognosis of these neoplasias, which really don&#146;t have an effective treatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torres Olivera, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Gómez, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: El patrón sarcomatoide representa    el tipo histológico de carcinoma renal con peor pronóstico    asignándosele un grado 4 de Furhman de manera sistemática.    MÉTODOS: Presentamos el caso de un paciente de 80 años al que se le realiza una nefroureterectomía con el subsiguiente    diagnóstico histológico de carcinoma renal con patrón sarcomatoide con áreas de condro y osteosarcoma así como diferenciación escamosa. Se trata de un caso excepcional en cuanto que es muy infrecuente encontrar todos estos elementos en un mismo tumor.    RESULTADOS: El estudio seriado de la pieza quirúrgica permite identificar en la mayoría de las ocasiones alguno de los patrones histológicos clásicos del carcinoma renal si bien el estudio inmunohistoquímico será de gran utilidad en la correcta catalogación de tal neoplasia y en el diagnóstico    diferencial con otras lesiones renale s, principalmente    sarcomatosas. CONCLUSIONES: La presencia de elementos heterólogos malignos, como en nuestro caso ratificará el mal pronostico de estas neoplasias para las que no existe un tratamiento verdaderamente efectivo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;59(6): 621-624, jul.-ago. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049356</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Carcinoma sarcomatoide renal con elementos heterológicos malignos. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7855^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12888^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12888^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7855^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
