<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76518</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-1375</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparative study of the efficacy of two online HDF techniques</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There are two online haemodiafiltration (HDF) techniques: pre-dilutional and post-dilutional, the latter being the most frequently used. Our study compares the efficacy of two HDF techniques, post-dilutional and mixed, analysing the frequency of cases in which there was an increase in trans-membrane pressure, preventing continuation of the treatment. The study consisted of two phases, in the first phase, (post-dilutional online HDF), we reduced the infusion rate (Qi) every time the trans-membrane pressure (TMP) was &gt;= 350 mmHg and we moved on to conventional haemodialysis if Qi was 30 ml/min. In the second phase, (mixed online HDF), we changed to pre-dilutional during the last hour and every time the TMP was &gt;= 350 mmHg. In phase 1 haemo-concentration (HC) appeared in 38.83% of sessions and in phase 2 in 18.06%. During the last hour of treatment, HC appeared in 119cases in phase 1 and in 15 cases in phase 2. Coagulation of the system occurred on 24 occasions during phase 1 and on 2 occasions during phase 2. Hypotension occurred on 80 occasions in phase 1 and on69 in phase 2.In light of the increase in TMP during post-dilutional HDF, the mixed technique proved more efficient than continuing in post-dilutional with a reduction of Qi. With the mixed method the elimination of de Beta2 microglobulin was greater and the efficacy of the technique was not reduced (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Terry Osset, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Párraga Díaz, MAteo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Belchí Rosique, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cárceles Legáz, Eulalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Melero Rubio, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Astorga Pérez, Felicidad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chica Arellano, Josefina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Existen dos técnicas Hemodiafiltración (HDF) on line: predilucional y posdilucional, siendo esta última la más utilizada. Nuestro estudio compara la eficacia dedos técnicas de HDF, posdilucional y mixta, analizando la frecuencia de casos en los que existió un aumento de la presión transmembrana, hecho que impidió continuar con el tratamiento. El estudio constó de dos fases, en la primera fase, (HDF on line posdilucional), reducíamos la tasa de infusión (Qi) cada vez que la presión transmembrana (PTM) era &gt;= 350 mmHg. y pasábamos a hemodiálisis convencional si Qi era 30 ml/min. En la segunda fase, (HDF on line mixta), cambiábamos a predilucional durante la última hora y cada vez que la PTM era 350mmHg.En la fase 1 apareció hemoconcentración (HC) en un 38.83% de las sesiones y en la fase 2 en un 18.06%.En la última hora de tratamiento, la HC apareció en119 casos en la fase 1 y en 15 casos en la fase 2. Se produjo la coagulación del sistema en 24 ocasiones durante la fase 1 y en 2 ocasiones durante la fase 2. Se produjeron hipotensiones en 80 ocasiones en la fase 1 y en 69 en la fase 2. Ante el aumento de PTM durante la HDF on line posdilucional la técnica mixta resultó más eficaz que continuaren posdilucional con disminución del Qi. Con el método mixto fue mayor la eliminación de Beta2 microglobulina y no disminuyó la eficacia de la técnica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Enferm. Nefrol;9(4): 249-253, oct.-dic. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76518</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio comparativo de la eficacia de dos técnicas de HDF on line</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1821^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22965^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31418^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
