<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116498</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness of a stretching program on anxiety levels of workers in a logistic platform: a randomized controlled study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To study the influence of a short programme of stretching exercises on anxiety levels of workers in a Spanish logistic company. Method: A controlled clinical trial was carried out by means of an inter-subject design of random homogeneous blocks. Participants were assigned to the experimental group (n = 67), treated with a programme of stretching exercises of 10-minute duration after working hours for a period of 3 months, or to the untreated control group (n = 67). The primary result variable was anxiety, and the secondary variables were burnout syndrome, quality of life and flexibility. An analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) by intention to treat was performed on each of the result variables by controlling the baseline scores, the age and the practice of introjective activities outside the program, with the size effect calculated by means of the partial eta-squared value (&amp;#951;2). Results: The results of the ANCOVA showed a moderate effect of the stretching exercise programme on the levels of anxiety (&amp;#951;2 = 0,06; P = 0.004). Other effects found were substantial for flexibility (&amp;#951;2 = 0,13; P &lt; .001); moderately high for bodily pain (&amp;#951;2 = 0,08; P =0 .001), and moderate for vitality (&amp;#951;2 = 0,05; P = .016); mental health (&amp;#951;2 = 0,05; P =0 .017); general health (&amp;#951;2 = 0,04; P =0 .028) and exhaustion (&amp;#951;2 = 0,04; P = 0.025). Conclusions: The implementation of a short programme of stretching exercises in the work place was effective for reducing levels of anxiety, bodily pain and exhaustion, and for raising levels of vitality, mental health, general health and flexibility. This type of intervention could be seen as a low-cost strategy for improving the well-being of workers (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montero-Marín, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Asún, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estrada-Marcén, Nerea</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Asún, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la efectividad de un programa abreviado de estiramientos sobre los niveles de ansiedad de los trabajadores de una empresa logística española. Método: Se llevó adelante un ensayo clínico controlado, con un diseño inter-sujetos, aleatorizado mediante conglomerados. Los participantes fueron asignados al grupo experimental (n = 67), tratado con un programa de estiramientos, de 10&amp;#8242; de duración tras la jornada laboral, durante 3 meses, o al grupo control (n = 67), no tratado. La variable resultado principal fue la ansiedad estado y las variables secundarias el burnout, la calidad de vida y la flexibilidad. Se llevó a cabo un análisis de covarianza (ANCOVA) por intención de tratar sobre las variables resultado, controlando las puntuaciones basales, la edad y la práctica de actividades introyectivas fuera del programa, calculando el tamaño del efecto mediante eta cuadrado parcial (&amp;#951;2). Resultados: Los resultados del ANCOVA señalaron un efecto moderado del programa de estiramientos sobre la ansiedad (&amp;#951;2 = 0,06; p = 0,004). También se encontraron efectos elevados en flexibilidad (&amp;#951;2 = 0,13; p &lt; 0,001), moderadamente altos en dolor corporal (&amp;#951;2 = 0,08; p = 0,001), moderados en vitalidad (&amp;#951;2 = 0,05; p = 0,016), salud mental (&amp;#951;2 = 0,05; p = 0,017), salud general (&amp;#951;2 = 0,04; p = 0,028) y agotamiento (&amp;#951;2 = 0,04; p = 0,025). Conclusiones: La implementación de un programa de estiramientos en el lugar de trabajo resultó eficaz para disminuir los niveles de ansiedad, dolor corporal y agotamiento, así como para aumentar la vitalidad, salud mental, salud general y flexibilidad. Este tipo de intervención podría constituir una estrategia de bajo coste para la mejora del bienestar de los trabajadores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;45(7): 376-383, ago.-sept. 2013. geaf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116498</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad de un programa de estiramientos sobre los niveles de ansiedad de los trabajadores de una plataforma logística: un estudio controlado aleatorizado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52426^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16735</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
