<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110170</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of a nutritional screening tool for hospitalized pediatric patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Malnutrition among hospitalized patients has clinical implications, and interest has arisen to find screening tools able to identify subjects under risk. At present, there is no consensus about the most suitable nutrition screening tool for pediatric patients. Aim: To validate STAMP (Screening Tool for the Assessment of Malnutrition in Pediatrics) pediatric screening tool in Spain. Methods: Descriptive cross-sectional study of patients admitted to a 3rd level children's hospital with both medical and surgical specialities. During the first 24 hours of admission, STAMP screening tool was applied. For its validation, results were compared with those obtained from a nutritional assessment performed by specialist staff, which included clinical, anthropometric and body composition data. Results: A sample of 250 children was studied. Nutritional assessment identified 64 patients (25.6%) under risk, 40 of whom were malnourished (16%). STAMP classified 48.4% of the patients as being under nutritional risk. This tool showed 75% sensitivity and 60.8% specificity when identifying patients under risk according to nutritional assessment. It showed 90% sensitivity and 59.5% specificity when identifying malnourished patients. Comments: Malnutrition was less frequent than that reported in other European countries, although diagnosis technique was different. STAMP is a simple and useful tool for nutritional screening, avoiding the need to assess all patients on admission in order to identify those under nutritional risk (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Ruzafa, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moráis López, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrero Álvarez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivero de la Rosa, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caraballo Chicano, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mano Hernández, A de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Martínez, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lama More, RA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galera Martínez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La malnutrición en los pacientes hospitalizados tiene implicaciones clínicas y evolutivas, por lo que existe interés en desarrollar métodos de cribado que identifiquen los individuos de riesgo. En la actualidad no existe consenso acerca de la herramienta de cribado nutricional más apropiada para aplicar en población pediátrica. Objetivo: Validar en España la herramienta de cribado nutricional pediátrico STAMP (Screening Tool for the Assessment of Malnutrition in Pediatrics). Métodos: Estudio descriptivo transversal en pacientes ingresados en un hospital pediátrico de tercer nivel con diferentes especialidades médicas y quirúrgicas. En las primeras 24 horas de ingreso se aplicó el método de cribado nutricional STAMP. Para la validación de sus resultados se llevó a cabo una valoración del estado nutricional que incluyó datos clínicos, antropométricos y de composición corporal realizada por personal especializado en nutrición. Resultados: Fueron estudiados 250 niños. La valoración nutricional detectó 64 pacientes (25,6%) considerados de riesgo, de los cuales 40 (16%) estaban ya malnutridos. STAMP clasificó un 48,4% de la muestra como de riesgo nutricional elevado. Dicho método mostró una sensibilidad del 75% y una especificidad del 60,8% para identificar los pacientes considerados de riesgo en la valoración nutricional, y una sensibilidad del 90% y especificidad del 59,5% para detectar los malnutridos. Comentarios: La frecuencia de malnutrición fue algo inferior a la de otros países de nuestro entorno, aunque el método diagnóstico fue diferente. El método STAMP es una herramienta sencilla y útil para el cribado nutricional, que evitaría la necesidad de valorar a todos los pacientes al ingreso para detectar los sujetos de riesgo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;27(5): 1429-1436, sept.-oct. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110170</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación de una herramienta de cribado nutricional para pacientes pediátricos hospitalizados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23583^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2711^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
