<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058091</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cardiovascular magnetic resonance evaluation of left-to-right shunts due to cardiac septal defects in patients with pulmonary arterial hypertension</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objetives. As cardiac septal defects are frequently associated with pulmonary arterial hypertension, hemodynamic assessment is essential before deciding on surgery. The aim of this study was to evaluate the use of cardiovascular magnetic resonance imaging for assessing cardiac shunts and for quantifying pulmonary artery systolic pressure in patients with cardiac septal defects. Methods. This cross-sectional study involved patients with cardiac septal defects and clinically suspected severe pulmonary arterial hypertension who had an indication for cardiac catheterization and in whom magnetic resonance imaging was not contraindicated. Each test's results were evaluated independently by two expert radiologists and interventional cardiologists who were blinded to the results of the other test. The procedures were compared using confidence limits and intraclass correlation coefficients. Results. The study involved 29 patients (18 female and 11 male) aged from 30 days to 18 years; seven had an atrial septal defect, 14 had a ventricular septal defect, and eight had an atrioventricular septal defect. The correlation coefficients for measurements made using the two procedures were 0.80, 0.75, 0.81 and 0.58 for pulmonary output, systemic output, flow ratio, and systolic pressure in the pulmonary artery, respectively. Cardiovascular magnetic resonance tended to underestimate systemic output by 0.80 L/min, pulmonary output by 1.35 L/min, left-to-right shunt flow by 0.12 L/min, and systolic pressure in the pulmonary artery by 16.5 mmHg. The complication rate with cardiac catheterization was 31% compared with 3.4% with cardiovascular magnetic resonance imaging. Conclusions. The evaluation of patients with cardiac septal defects and pulmonary arterial hypertension should initially be performed using noninvasive diagnostic techniques (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Valenzuela, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-González, Martha A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solorio, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Malacara-Hernández, Juan M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz de León, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jarquin, Víctor M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espínola-Zavaleta, Nilda</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Los defectos septales cardiacos con frecuencia se asocian con hipertensión arterial pulmonar, por lo que es indispensable su evaluación hemodinámica previa a la decisión quirúrgica. Llevamos a cabo un estudio para comparar la cuantificación del cortocircuito y de la presión sistólica de la arteria pulmonar mediante resonancia magnética cardiovascular en pacientes con defectos septales cardiacos. Métodos. Se diseñó un estudio transversal en pacientes con defectos septales cardiacos y sospecha clínica de hipertensión arterial pulmonar grave, con indicación de cateterismo cardiaco, sin contraindicación de resonancia magnética. La valoración de los resultados de cada prueba fue realizada por dos expertos radiólogos y hemodinamistas, de manera independiente y que desconocían los hallazgos en la otra prueba. La comparación entre los procedimientos se llevó a cabo mediante los límites de concordancia y el coeficiente de correlación intraclase. Resultados. Se incluyó a 29 pacientes, 18 mujeres y 11 varones, de 30 días a 18 años de edad, 7 con comunicación interauricular, 14 con comunicación interventricular y 8 con canal auriculoventricular completo. La correlación intraclase entre ambos procedimientos fue 0,80; 0,75; 0,81 y 0,58 para el gasto pulmonar, el gasto sistémico, la relación de flujos y la presión sistólica de la arteria pulmonar, respectivamente. La resonancia tiende a subestimar en 0,80 l/min el gasto sistémico, 1,35 l/min el gasto pulmonar, 0,12 l/min el desvío de flujo QP:QS y 16,5 mmHg la presión sistólica de la arteria pulmonar. La incidencia de complicaciones inherentes al cateterismo fue del 31% y de la resonancia del 3,4%. Conclusiones. La evaluación de los pacientes con defectos septales cardiacos e hipertensión pulmonar deberá realizarse, en primera instancia, con métodos de diagnóstico no invasivos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;60(9): 907-913, sept. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058091</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resonancia magnética cardiovascular en la cuantificación de los cortocircuitos de izquierda a derecha en los defectos septales cardiacos con hipertensión arterial pulmonar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7155^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23275^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6496^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
