<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75026</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anidulafungin: a new therapeutic approach in antifungal therapy. Pharmacology of anidulafungin</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Anidulafungin is a new echinocandin antifungal agent which inhibitsß-1,3-D-glucan synthase and disrupts fungal cell-wall synthesis. It has markedantifungal activity against Candida spp. and Aspergillus spp., includingamphotericin B and triazole resistant strains. Due to the limited oral availability,anidulafungin in clinical use is available for parenteral administration only.Elimination of anidulafungin takes place via slow non-enzymatic degradation toinactive metabolites. Less than 10% and 1% of the initially administered drugis excreted unchanged into feces and urine, respectively. It does not requiredosage adjustment in subjects with hepatic or renal impairment established.Anidulafungin is generally well tolerated. Adverse events appear not to bedose or infusion related. The most common treatment related adverse eventsare phlebitis, headache, nausea, vomiting and pyrexia. The lack of interactionswith tacrolimus, cyclosporine and corticosteroids and its limited toxicity profileplaces anidulafungin as an attractive new option for the treatment of invasivefungal infections especially in transplant patients(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montejo González, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Catalán González, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La anidulafungina es una nueva equinocandina que inhibe la síntesis deß-1,3-D-glucano sintasa e interrumpe la síntesis de la pared célular del hongo.Presenta una marcada actividad frente a Candida spp. y Aspergillus spp.,incluyendo las especies resistentes a anfotericina B y triazoles. Debido a sulimitada biodisponibilidad oral únicamente se administra en la clínica por víaparenteral. La anidulafungina sufre un proceso de degradación espontánea enla sangre, no precisando de metabolización hepática y siendo eliminada porvía fecal en su mayoría como metabolitos inactivos. La eliminación urinaria delfármaco es inferior al 1%. No precisa ajuste de dosis en insuficiencia hepáticani renal. La anidulafungina es generalmente bien tolerada. Los efectosadversos notificados no se relacionan ni con la dosis ni con el tipo deinfusión. La mayoría de los efectos adversos son flebitis, cefalea, nauseas,vómitos y fiebre. El limitado perfil de toxicidad y las mínimas interaccionescon otros fármacos (ciclosporina, tacrólimus y corticoesteroides) hacen de laanidulafungina una nueva opción terapéutica para las infecciones fúngicasinvasoras, especialmente en pacientes receptoras de trasplantes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;25(2): 92-100, 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75026</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nueva aportación en terapia antifúngica: Anidulafungina. Aspectos farmacológicos de la anidulafungina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2209^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52786^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30095^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29074^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1235^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5794^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200800</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
