<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140562</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The concept of care throughout history</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Etymologically care concept comes from the term 'll take care / curare.' The word care has different meanings in our language. The most immediate and popular works as a warning of impending danger; This is one of the words a child learns first and now, for the elderly, we use it as profusion throughout life. Objectives: It is proposed to review the scientific literature to analyze the evolution of the concept of 'Care' throughout history. Methods: Systematic review in the following databases: Medline, Pubmed Scopus, CUIDEN, Google Scholar. Results: Items with high relevance ranging from 1947 to 2012 were selected after analysis of 51 complete articles, we selected 13 articles and added 10 referential and intuitive search Google Scholar. Conclusions: The term care affects all human life, mind and body. Thus, a healthy mind is the assumption of a good life. Several scientists and researchers have used this term in their studies from different perspectives but coinciding in its importance to humanity in general and in the field of health professionals, in particular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alba Martín, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Etimológicamente el concepto de cuidado proviene del término 'cuidare/ curare'. La palabra cuidado tiene diversos significados en nuestra lengua. El más inmediato y popular funciona como un aviso ante un peligro inminente; Se trata de una de las palabras que aprende primero un niño y ya, de mayores, la usamos como profusión durante toda la vida. Objetivos: Se plantea revisar la literatura científica para analizar la evolución del concepto de 'Cuidado' a lo largo de la historia. Metodología: Revisión sistemática en las siguientes bases de datos: Medline, Pubmed Scopus, CUIDEN, Google Scholar. Resultados principales: Se seleccionaron artículos con alto nivel de relevancia que abarcan desde el año 1947 al año 2012. Tras el análisis de 51 artículos completos, hemos seleccionado 13 y hemos añadido 10 artículos de búsqueda referencial e intuitiva en Google Scholar. Conclusiones: La palabra cuidado afecta a toda la vida humana, a la mente y al cuerpo. Así, una mente sana es el supuesto de una buena vida. Diversos científicos e investigadores han hecho uso de este término en sus estudios desde diferentes perspectivas pero coincidiendo en la importancia del mismo para la humanidad, en general y, en el campo de la salud y los profesionales, en particular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;19(41): 101-105, ene.-abr. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140562</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El Concepto de cuidado a lo largo de la Historia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6835</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
