<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053071</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Group closure and needs identification in blood and organ donation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Three moral values are within the blood and organ donation with therapeutical purpose: giving without obligation, altruism and solidarity. It seems than for donors unselfishness is something transcendental: blood save lives. Altruism and solidarity are present, but spending is under the pattern of reciprocity. Recruiting and keeping blood and organ spenders is an uncertain and complex process. How spenders live reciprocity can help us to understand rejections to donation. The research work is based on personal interviews and on the analyses of the material used in recruitment actions of blood and organ donors. Two kinds of reciprocity were discovered: focused and fuzzy reciprocity (according to how the community is conceived and which is its target). Focused reciprocity is characteristic of social systems based on tight personal relationships. Fuzzy reciprocity is characteristic of individualistic and anonymity based societies. This is a main point in spending, thus focused reciprocity is not compatible with donations with therapeutical purpose which are voluntary, altruist and anonymous. That what obstruct donation is the restricted exchange due to focused reciprocity. Having a common blood relation o biological heritage is not a main basis to reject donation, as it could be thought</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casado-Neira, David</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La acción de dar sin compromiso, el altruismo y la solidaridad están en el centro de la donación de sangre y órganos con fines terapéuticos. Según se hace ver las personas hacen una entrega desinteresada y transcendental: &#145;la sangre salva vidas&#146;. El altruismo y la solidaridad son aquí ineludibles, pero la donación está sometida a los principios de la reciprocidad. La captación y fidelización de donantes se enfrenta a veces a crisis o dificultades que se pueden explicar en parte por cómo los donantes interpretan la reciprocidad. Recurriendo a entrevistas y al análisis de contenido de campañas de captación de donantes de sangre y órganos identificamos dos tipos de reciprocidad (según sea el tipo de destino y concepción de la comunidad): focalizada o difusa. La focalizada es característica de sistemas sociales basados en relaciones personales estrechas (reales o virtuales). La difusa responde a una concepción individualista y anónima de la vida social. En la donación esto va a ser fundamental porque la reciprocidad focalizada es difícilmente compatible con la donación terapéutica, que es voluntaria, altruista y anónima. Lo que dificulta la donación es el intercambio restrictivo de la reciprocidad focalizada, no que este grupo comparta sangre o herencia biológica común que deseen preservar</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;14(51): 45-49, mar. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053071</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Clausura grupal e identificación de necesidades en las donaciones de sangre y órganos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d533</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1809^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14408^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
