<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160751</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The concerns of Spanish patients with inflammatory bowel disease as measured by the RFIPC questionnaire</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: Concerns impact the quality of life for patients with inflammatory bowel disease (IBD). We attempted to identify the concerns of IBD patients in our practice, and to assess the applicability of the Rating Form of IBD Patients Concerns (RFIPC) questionnaire to Spanish patients. Patients and methods: One hundred and thirty-one patients seen in our practice filled out the Spanish version of RFIPC. The questionnaire&#146;s reliability, validity, and discriminating power were analyzed. Results: The total score was 46.93, with a standard deviation (SD) of 21.475. Primary concerns included: 'having an ostomy bag', 'effects of medication', 'developing cancer', 'energy level', and 'uncertain nature of disease'. Female patients scored higher on total RFIPC and on most items. Cronbach&#146;s alpha was 0.924. A good correlation was seen between two consecutive answers for 37 patients; the Spearman&#146;s coefficient was 0.842 (p &lt; 0.001), and the intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC) was 0.775 (p &lt; 0.001). Correlation was also found between RFIPC and both the IBDQ-32 emotional domain (0.413, p &lt; 0.001) and anxiety scale (0.543, p &lt; 0.001). Conclusions: The RFIPC questionnaire may be administered to Spanish patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Berroa de la Rosa, Edel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Salazar, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora Cuadrado, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes y objetivos: las preocupaciones influyen en la calidad de vida de los pacientes con enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal (EII). Pretendemos identificar las preocupaciones de los pacientes con EII que atendemos en nuestra consulta y comprobar si el Rating Form of IBD Patients Concerns (RFIPC) es un cuestionario aplicable a los pacientes españoles. Pacientes y métodos: ciento treinta y un pacientes atendidos en la consulta contestaron la versión española del RFIPC. Se ha estudiado la fiabilidad, validez y capacidad discriminadora del cuestionario. Resultados: la puntuación total fue 46,93 con desviación estándar (DS) de 21,475. Las preocupaciones principales fueron: 'que me coloquen una bolsa', 'reacciones a medicamentos', 'padecer cáncer', 'vitalidad' y 'situación incierta de la enfermedad'. Los pacientes de sexo femenino puntuaron más alto en el RFIPC y en la mayoría de los ítems. El valor alfa de Cronbach fue 0,924. Se comprobó una buena correlación entre dos respuestas consecutivas de 37 pacientes, Spearman 0,842 (p &lt; 0,001) y coeficiente de correlación intraclase (CCI) 0,775 (p &lt; 0,001). También hubo correlación entre el RFIPC y el dominio emocional del Inflammatoy Bowel Disease Questionnarie (IBDQ) 32 0,413 (p &lt; 0,001) y la escala de ansiedad 0,543 (p &lt; 0,001). Conclusiones: el cuestionario RFIPC puede aplicarse a los pacientes españoles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;109(3): 196-201, mar. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160751</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las preocupaciones de los pacientes españoles con enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal medidas con el cuestionario RFIPC</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23971^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23971^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
