<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045979</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Predictive value of metabolic syndrome in pregnancy for the development of diabetes mellitus and factors of short-term vascular risk for mother and child after birth (gestaMET)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To evaluate the presence of diabetes mellitus (DM) or short-term alterations in glucose metabolism, obesity and vascular risk factors after birth in women with pregnancy metabolic syndrome (PMS). To evaluate the incidence of obesity, lipaemia, glucaemia disorder, blood pressure (BP), or lipid figures in the period after birth in children of women with PMS.         Design. Cohort study.         Setting. Forty two primary care centres.         Participants. Study cohort (SC): women with PMS and their children. Control cohort (CC): women without primary criteria of PMS and their children. Sample size: SC, 980 women and CC, also 980. Consecutive sampling.         Measurements. Mother: basic data, 75 g oral overload, lipid profile, insulinaemia, toxic habits, nutrition survey, and physical activity. Child: weight, height, BP, nutrition survey, glucaemia, insulinaemia, and lipid profile. Father: basic data, BP, glucaemia, lipid profile, insulinaemia, toxic habits, nutrition survey, and physical activity. We will study genes related to insulin resistance in all subjects.         Statistical analysis. Comparison of proportions with *2 test; ANOVA to measure means. Evaluation of effect of intra-uteral exposure through logistical regression and COX regression, whilst controlling potentially confusing and interactive variables.         Discussion. This study will contribute to locating the moment when diabetes and vascular risk start and to finding the optimum moment for starting prevention strategies</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Fernández, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual de la Pisa, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Evaluar la presencia de diabetes mellitus (DM) o alteraciones en el metabolismo de la glucosa, la presencia de obesidad y los factores de riesgo vascular a corto plazo tras el parto en mujeres con síndrome metabólico gestacional (SMG). Evaluar la incidencia de obesidad, dislipidemia, alteraciones en las cifras de glucemia, presión arterial (PA) o lípidos, a corto plazo tras el parto, en los hijos de mujeres con SMG.         Diseño. Estudio de cohortes.         Emplazamiento. En total, 42 centros de atención primaria.         Participantes. Cohorte de estudio (CE): mujeres con SMG y sus hijos. Cohorte control (CC): mujeres sin criterios primarios de SMG y sus hijos. Tamaño muestral: CE: 980 mujeres y CC: 980 mujeres. Muestreo consecutivo.         Mediciones. Madre: antropometría, sobrecarga oral de 75 g, perfil lipídico, insulinemia, PA, hábitos tóxicos, encuesta nutricional y actividad física. Niño: peso, talla, PA, encuesta nutricional, determinaciones de glucemia, insulinemia y perfil lipídico. Padre: antropometría, PA, glucemia, perfil lipídico, insulinemia, hábitos tóxicos, encuesta nutricional y actividad física. Estudiaremos genes relacionados con la resistencia insulínica en todos los sujetos.         Análisis estadístico. Comparación de proporciones mediante el test de la *2, diferencias de medias mediante el ANOVA. Evaluación del efecto de la exposición intraútero mediante análisis de regresión logística y de regresión de COX, controlando las potenciales variables de confusión y de interacción.         Discusión. Con este estudio podremos contribuir al conocimiento sobre el momento de inicio de la diabetes y el riesgo vascular, y sobre el momento óptimo de iniciar estrategias de prevención</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;37(9): 517-521, mayo 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045979</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valor predictivo del síndrome metabólico en la gestación para el desarrollo de diabetes mellitus</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30157^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
