<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72699</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">High-density lipoprotein cholesterol and cardiovascular disease in Spanish hypertensive women. The RIMHA Study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. To determine the prevalence of a low high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL-C) concentration in 11 042 hypertensive Spanish women aged &amp;#8805;55 years, to identify factors associated with a low concentration, and to evaluate its relationship with cardiovascular disease (CVD). Methods. Analysis of RIMHA cross-sectional study findings. Data on demographic, biochemical and clinical variables were obtained. Relationships between a low HDL-C concentration ( &lt;46 mg dl and cvd between the hdl-c concentration in quintiles were studied by multivariate logistic regression modeling results prevalence of a low was 24 3 95 confidence interval ci 23 5 minus 25 1 higher women with diabetes or independently associated excess weight smoking presence inversely age 7 vs 18 4 those normal p &lt;.001). There was an independent association between a low HDL-C concentration and CVD after adjustment for other risk factors (odds ratio [OR]=1.42; 95% CI, 1.26&amp;#8722;1.60; P&lt;.001) and with silent target organ damage (OR=1.31; 95% CI, 1.15&amp;#8722;1.49; P&lt;.001). Similarly, there was an independent inverse association between the HDL-C concentration (in quintiles) and the prevalence of CVD, particularly for HDL-C concentrations &lt;58 mg dl conclusions one in 4 hypertensive women aged ge 55 years had a low hdl-c concentration which was independently associated with the presence of cvd moreover there an inverse association between and prevalence even at normal concentrations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grupo de los investigadores del estudio RIMHA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Evaluar la prevalencia de concentración baja de colesterol de las lipoproteínas de alta densidad (cHDL), los factores asociados y la relación con la enfermedad cardiovascular (ECV), en 11.042 mujeres hipertensas de 55 o más años de edad. Métodos. Análisis del estudio transversal RIMHA. Se recogieron datos demográficos, bioquímicos, y clínicos. Se analizó la relación entre cHDL bajo ( &lt; 46 mg/dl) y ECV, y entre concentración de cHDL (quintiles) y ECV mediante modelos multivariables de regresión logística. Resultados. La prevalencia de cHDL bajo fue del 24,3% (intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 23,5-25,1), y fue mayor en mujeres diabéticas o con ECV. El cHDL bajo se asoció a exceso de peso, tabaquismo, diabetes y ECV, e inversamente con la edad. La prevalencia de ECV fue mayor en mujeres con cHDL bajo (el 24,7 frente al 18,4% con cHDL normal; p &lt; 0,001). Se observó una asociación independiente entre cHDL bajo y ECV tras ajustar por otros factores de riesgo (odds ratio [OR] = 1,42; IC del 95%, 1,26-1,60; p &lt; 0,001) y por la lesión asintomática de órgano diana (OR = 1,31; IC del 95%, 1,15-1,49; p &lt; 0,001). Del mismo modo, se observó una asociación independiente e inversa entre la concentración de cHDL (quintiles) y la presencia de ECV, en especial para concentraciones de cHDL &lt; 58 mg/dl. Conclusiones. En esta muestra de mujeres hipertensas de 55 años o más, una de cada 4 tenía cHDL bajo, y esto se relacionó independientemente con la presencia de ECV. Además, encontramos una asociación inversa entre la concentración de cHDL y la prevalencia de ECV también en cifras de cHDL consideradas normales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;62(9): 1022-1031, sept. 2009. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72699</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Colesterol HDL y enfermedad cardiovascular en mujeres hipertensas de España. Estudio RIMHA</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8250^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4634</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14679^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24811</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8248^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
