<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117392</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficiency of oncologic treatments for solid tumours in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To provide estimates of the efficiency for chemotherapy strategies used in Spain. Methods: Published reports of the phase-Ill clinical trials for chemotherapies used for the most prevalent solid tumours in Spain were retrieved. The incremental cost-effectiveness ratio (ICER) was calculated for each strategy compared to the control group in the clinical trial, with the National Health System perspective. The total cost (&#128;, 2012) including only drug cost (ex-factory price) was estimated based on the total units of each drug required for administration (no vial wastage), with the dosification and number of cycles specified in the publication for each treatment arm. Effectiveness was measured as month of overall survival (OS) and/or month of progression free survival (PFS). Results: A total of 40 chemotherapies for 13 different advanced or metastatic tumours were assessed. OS ranged from 5.3 to 33.3 months for the 34 therapies that included the information with hazard ratios (HR) values from 0.49 to 1.15 when compared with its control group. PFS ranged, from 39 therapies with these data, between 1.5 to 12.4 months, with HR from 0.33 to 1.52. ICERs were between &#128;2,142.57 and &#128;60,996.37 per each OS month gained, and from &#128;2,102.54 to &#128;661,845.27 per PFS month gained. Conclusion: The variety and heterogenicity of survival and ICERs results, suggest disparity of criteria in the price and reimbursement process of drugs in Spain. The continuous advances in oncology seem to require economic revaluations of drugs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Seguí, M. Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Queralt Gorgas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oyagüez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Barrera, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casado, M. Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frías, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Proporcionar estimadores de la eficiencia de esquemas oncológicos empleados en España. Métodos: Se seleccionaron las publicaciones de ensayos clínicos en fase III usados para indicación de las terapias oncológicas de alto impacto empleadas para tratamiento de tumores sólidos en estadíos III-IV. Para cada esquema se calculó la relación coste-eficacia incremental (RCEI) respecto al comparador del ensayo, con la perspectiva del Sistema Nacional de Salud. El coste (&#128;, 2012) farmacológico, en PVL, de cada esquema y comparador se estimó con las unidades de medicamento requeridas en cada administración (aprovechamiento máximo de viales) considerando la posología y el número de ciclos especificado en el ensayo para cada una de las ramas. La efectividad se expresó en meses de supervivencia global (SG) y/o supervivencia libre de progresión (SLP). Resultados: Se analizaron 40 esquemas oncológicos para trece tumores metastásicos. La SG osciló entre 5,3 y 33,3 meses para las 34 terapias que incluían esa información, con valores de hazard ratio (HR) respecto a sus comparadores de 0,49 a 1,15. La SLP osciló entre 1,5 y 12,4 meses para las 39 terapias con este dato, con HR de 0,33 a 1,52. Los valores de RCEI oscilaron entre 2.142,57 &#128;-60.996,37 &#128;/mes de SG adicional y entre 2.102,54 &#128;-661.845,27 &#128;/mes de SLP adicional. Conclusión: La dispersión y heterogeneidad de la supervivencia y RCEI estimadas, sugieren disparidad de criterios en la decisión de precio y financiación de las terapias, en España. Los continuos avances en terapias oncológicas parecen requerir reevaluaciones económicas de los medicamentos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;37(3): 240-259, mayo-jun. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117392</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficiencia de tratamientos oncológicos para tumores sólidos en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32281</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50249</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50303</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30152^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d974^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
