<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161723</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Infiltration of botulinum toxin type A in a post-surgical vulvar neuroma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present the case of a 54-year-old woman with a diagnosis of vulvar lichen sclerosus. She was treated by resection of the lichen sclerosus and subsequent flap reconstruction of the perineum. Months later, the patient developed perineal and vulvar burning and spontaneous pain with proctalgia and coitalgia. She was diagnosed with vestibulodynia with clinical suspicion of painful vulvar neuroma in the scar tissue by palpation of the induration and we decided to start pharmacological treatment. Oral analgesics followed by local anaesthetic infiltration plus steroid therapy and pudendal nerve radiofrequency were unsuccessful. Therefore, local infiltration of botulinum toxin A (BOTOX ®) into trigger point and introitus was administered as compassionate treatment. Botulinum toxin type A, is used compassionately for anal sphincter dyssynergy, chronic anal fissure, vestibulodynia and pelvic pain caused by muscle spasm. Its 2 main effects are relaxation of muscle fibre, and analgesia that is specific to the toxin (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo Aguirre, RM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canos Verdecho, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fenollosa Vazquez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casasempere, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos el caso de una paciente mujer de 54 años, diagnosticada de liquen escleroso vulvar y tratada en Ginecología mediante resección de liquen escleroso y posterior reconstrucción del periné mediante colgajo. Meses después, la paciente consulta por dolor perineal y vulvar tipo urente y espontáneo con coitalgia y proctalgia. Diagnosticada de vestibulodinia provocada y con sospecha clínica de neuroma vulvar pericicatricial por palpación dolorosa de punto indurado, se decide iniciar tratamiento farmacológico. Tras el fracaso analgésico con tratamiento oral, infiltraciones locales con anestésico local más corticoides y radiofrecuencia del nervio pudendo, se decidió tratamiento compasivo con infiltraciones locales de toxina botulínica en punto doloroso de introito vaginal izquierdo. La toxina botulínica A (BOTOX ®), se emplea de forma compasiva para la disinergia esfinteriana anal, para la fisura anal crónica, la vestibulodinia provocada y el dolor pélvico por espasmo muscular. Presenta principalmente 2 efectos: la relajación de la fibra muscular y la analgesia, que es propiedad específica de la toxina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);44(2): 93-96, abr.-jun. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161723</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infiltración de toxina botulínica tipo A en neuroma vulvar posquirúrgico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9655^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1930^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1267^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53533^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9655^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
