<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88121</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-5962</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Do structured selection interviews produce gender adverse impact?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Previous studies have demonstrated the validity and reliability of structured interviews for personnel selection. However, results have been contradictory on whether this method produces adverse impact against women. This study is a meta-analysis to determine if structured interviews produce adverse impact by gender of the interviewee. Findings indicate no differences in scores for men and women for any of the modalities of the structured interview. Finally, implications of these results are discussed for research and for practice in personnel selection(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso, Pamela</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Estudios anteriores han demostrado la validez y la fiabilidad de las entrevistas estructuradas de selección. Sin embargo, se han obtenido resultados contradictorios sobre si este método produce impacto adverso hacia las mujeres. Este estudio es un meta-análisis que tiene como objetivo determinar si las entrevistas estructuradas producen impacto adverso según el sexo del entrevistado. Los resultados indican que no hay diferencias en las puntuaciones para hombres y mujeres en ninguna de las modalidades de la entrevista estructurada. Finalmente, se discuten las implicaciones de estos resultados, tanto para la investigación como para la práctica en selección de personal(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. trab. organ. (1999);27(1): 43-53, 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88121</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Producen resultado adverso de género las entrevistas estructuradas de selección de personal?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10752^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5924</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7569^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7569^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10752^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10752^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201100</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
