<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144435</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation and criteria for use of the teaching material by Physiotherapy students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. When using teaching materials, university professors know the aims they seek and the role these materials have. However, the use given to them by the students appears to be different from that pursued by their professors. Objective. This paper aims to look into the viewpoints of Physiotherapy students regarding the utility of the teaching materials, in order to determine the main dimensions related to their usage. Material and method. A prospective type survey study was performed in 183 students with a Physiotherapy Degree from the University of Valencia. A 17-item questionnaire was developed ad hoc for this purpose in the University. A descriptive study and analysis of the principal component analysis were performed. Results. The highest rated items were: to be up to date with the subject (4.46 ± 0.83), to study the professor's presentation (4.43 ± 0.87) and note-taking in class (4.29 ± 1). The multivariate analysis resulted in 4 dimensions: Going deeply into the contents, The professor's presentation, Essential resources and Independent study habits. Conclusions. The students of Physiotherapy consider that the teaching materials are very helpful to remain up to date on the subject in the individual work habit. The teacher's presentation is the main source of information to complete their notes. Other materials, which are positively evaluated, are used to go deeper into the contents. These results could serve as a guide and to help the Physiotherapy professors from this university and others in the elaboration and selection of teaching materials (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Espí-López, GV</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Sánchez, ML</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruescas-Nicolau, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. A la hora de utilizar los materiales docentes, los profesores universitarios son conscientes de los objetivos que persiguen y de la función que estos deben desempeñar. Ahora, el uso que los estudiantes realizan de los mismos parece distante de la utilidad conferida por el profesor. Objetivo. Recoger la opinión de estudiantes de Fisioterapia sobre la utilidad del material docente para, posteriormente, determinar las principales dimensiones relacionadas con su uso. Material y método. Se realizó un estudio prospectivo tipo encuesta a 183 estudiantes del Grado de Fisioterapia de la Universitat de València, donde se elaboró ad hoc un cuestionario compuesto por 17 ítems. Se realizó un estudio descriptivo de los ítems y un análisis de componentes principales. Resultados. Los ítems mejor valorados fueron: llevar al día la asignatura (4,46 ± 0,83), estudiar de la presentación del profesor (4,43 ± 0,87) y tomar también apuntes en clase (4,29 ± 1). El resultado del análisis multivariante mostró 4 dimensiones: Profundizar en los contenidos, Presentación del profesor, Recursos considerados necesarios y Hábitos de trabajo individual. Conclusiones. Los estudiantes de Fisioterapia encuentran que el material docente es de gran utilidad para llevar al día la asignatura en su hábito de trabajo individual. La presentación del profesor es la principal fuente de información para completar sus anotaciones. Valorados positivamente, otros materiales son usados para profundizar en los contenidos. Estos resultados podrían orientar y ayudar a profesores de Fisioterapia, de esta y otras universidades, en la elaboración y selección de material docente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);37(6): 262-270, nov.-dic. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144435</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración y criterios de uso del material docente por parte de los estudiantes de Fisioterapia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1301^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14043^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4562^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36319^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4562^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4562^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1301^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36319^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
