<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111458</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adverse events related to the medication informed by primary care patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To identify the frequency of adverse events reported by primary care patients and determine their consequences on patients&#146; assessment of care. Patients and methods: Observational study based with a sample of randomly primary care patients. A total of 1,952 patients were surveyed (sample defined to a maximum error of 4%, Confidence Interval of 95%), 1,514 from general practices and 438 from pediatrics. In 612 cases began a new treatment. Results: In 38 (6.2%) cases were reported an AE; of these, 25 (4.1%) experienced drug-related AE. Among older we found increased frequency of AE. In 14 of these 25 patients (56%) requested a second query. The frequency of medication-related AE was associated with ineffective treatment. Those who suffered drug-related AE but received information about this episode rated a favorable view of health care received. Conclusion: We need safer practices in primary care. Patients can provide relevant information about patient safety. Even in the event of serious harm from treatment prescribed by a doctor, trust in professional remains (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Navarro, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guilabert, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mira, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aranaz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Identificar la frecuencia de eventos adversos (EA) según informe de los pacientes en atención primaria (AP) y determinar si sufrir EA incide negativamente en la valoración de la atención recibida. Pacientes y metodología: Estudio observacional, basado en entrevistas estructuradas a una muestra de pacientes de AP seleccionada aleatoriamente. Se encuestó a 1.952 pacientes, de 1.514 de consultas de medicina general y 438 de pediatría. En 612 casos se inició un nuevo tratamiento. Escogimos una muestra aleatoria definida para un error máximo del 4%, nivel de confianza del 95%. Resultados: En 38 (6,2%) casos se informó de EA; de estos, 25 (4,1%) sufrieron EA relacionados con la medicación. A mayor edad encontramos mayor frecuencia de EA. En 14 de estos 25 pacientes (56%) se solicitó una segunda consulta. La frecuencia de EA relacionado con la medicación se asoció a ineficacia del tratamiento. Quienes sufrieron EA relacionados con la medicación pero recibieron información sobre este episodio valoraron de forma positiva las atenciones sanitarias recibidas. Conclusión: Se precisan prácticas más seguras en AP y recurrir a los pacientes para conocer la frecuencia de EA tiene menor coste y aporta información relevante. Incluso en el caso de sufrir complicaciones derivadas del tratamiento indicado por el médico, la confianza en el profesional de AP se mantiene (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);24(1): 48-53, ene.-mar. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111458</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eventos adversos relacionados con la medicación informados por los pacientes en atención primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
