<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96244</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8799</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Applying a mathematical model to taper in young swimmers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Before an important competition, the training dose should be reduced with the intention of improving the performance. This study aims to determine the impact of the implementation of a mathematical model during the non-linear, progressive reduction of the training load or taper in young swimmers. Ten swimmers were tested before and after the taper. The control variables measured during the training were the volume, the relationship between the volume and the mean intensity of training season (MITS) and the frequency of training. The decrease in the volume of training after applying the mathematical model was of 30.9% in the first week, and of 71.2% in the second week. The decrease in MITS after applying the mathematical model was of 30.8% in the first week, and of 71.1% in the second week. The training frequency was decreased by 10% in the first week, and up to 40% in the second week. The records obtained between the first and the second tests were significantly better (p &lt; 0.05). The maximum lactate production also increased significantly (p &lt; 0.05), unlike the speed of lactate clarifying that it did not. The correlation between lactate and the maximum mark obtained was significant (p &lt; 0.05). The value SPE (subjective perception of effort)after applying the mathematical model decreased, but not significantly (p &gt; 0.05). These data indicate that the taper proposed does not cause loss of sensation or training, since the records improved significantly, as did the maximum production of lactate, showing a high correlation between maximum lactate and record (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lara Padilla, Eleazar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berral de la Rosa, Carlos J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berral de la Rosa, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Bies, Elizabeth C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Baños, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Ante una competición importante, la dosis de entrenamiento debe reducirse con la intención de mejorar el rendimiento. El presente estudio tiene por objetivo determinar los efectos de la aplicación de un modelo matemático durante la reducción progresiva no lineal de la carga de entrenamientoo taper en jóvenes nadadores. Diez nadadores fueron testados antes y después del taper. Las variables utilizadas para el control fueron el volumen de entrenamiento, la relación entre volumen e intensidad media de entrenamiento en una temporada (MITS) y la frecuencia de entrenamiento. La disminución del volumen de entrenamiento tras aplicar el modelo matemático resultó en la primera semana del 30,9%, y en la segunda semana del 71,2%. La disminución de los MITS tras aplicar el modelo matemático tuvo un resultado en la primera semana del 30,8%, y en la segunda semana del 71,1%. La frecuencia de entrenamiento se disminuyó un 10% en la primera semana, y hasta el 40% en la segunda semana. Las marcas obtenidas entre el primer y el segundo tests fueron significativamente mejores para el segundo (p &lt; 0,05). El lactato máximo también se modificó de manera significativa (p &lt; 0,05), a diferencia del lactato mínimo, en el que no se detectaron diferencias. La correlación entre lactato máximo y la marca obtenida resultó significativa (p &lt; 0,05). El valor de la percepción subjetivo del esfuerzo (RPE), tras aplicar el modelo matemático, disminuyó, aunque no significativamente(p &gt; 0,05). Estos datos indican que el taper propuesto no provoca pérdidas de sensaciones ni de entrenamiento, pues las marcas obtenidas mejoraron de forma significativa, al igual que lo hizo el lactato máximo, lo que demuestra una clara correlación entre lactato máximo y marca (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. med. deporte;26(133): 355-363, sept.-oct. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96244</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicación de un modelo matemático al taper en jóvenes nadadores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d133</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5180^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13931^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
