<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047766</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: when a patient has an incurable cancer and requirescare by another person during the final stages of his or her life, theassigned caregiver experiences emotional distress and suffering.Objective: to evaluate the severity and causes of emotional distress incaregivers supporting patients with end-stage cancer, measurements wereobtained of the severity and causes of their suffering, of their perception ofpatient symptom control, of their emotional and practical difficulties, andof their satisfaction with the caring task.Methods: fifty caregivers of patients with advanced cancer undergoingpalliative care were evaluated. Information was collected during two interviews(initial and final), with a suffering scale being completed in eachinterview, and from patient clinical records.Results: seventy-two percent of caregivers were women with a medianage of 44.8 ± 14.5 years; 56% had illnesses that required treatment, andmost of them devoted more than 12 hours a day to patient care. The sufferingof caregivers was high throughout therapy (initial 7.5 ± 2.8; final8.4 ± 1.8). They had the perception that symptom control for theirpatients was moderate (initial 5.3 ± 3.3; final 5.7 ± 2.7). They reported lowpractical difficulties (2.3 ± 3.5), moderate emotional difficulties (5.7 ±3.8), and great satisfaction with their task (8.9 ± 1.6).It is necessary that difficulties experienced by caregivers be identified,and that education as well as adequate emotional and material support beoffered them in order to optimize their caring capacity and to reduce theirsuffering</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Wenk, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monti, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La enfermedad incurable de un paciente, y la tarea de asistirlo durante el período final, provocan sufrimiento en el cuidador responsable. Objetivo: Evaluar en los cuidadores responsables la intensidad y causasde sufrimiento, la percepción del control de los síntomas del paciente, las dificultades prácticas y emocionales, y la satisfacción con la tarea. Métodos: Se evaluaron a los cuidadores responsables de 50 pacientes consecutivos con cáncer avanzado en cuidado paliativo. Los datos se obtuvieron en dos entrevistas (inicial y final), con una escala de sufrimiento completada en cada entrevista, y con datos de la historia clínica del paciente. Resultados: 72% de los cuidadores responsables eran mujeres, de edad media 44,8 años ± 14,5; 56% tenía enfermedades que requerían tratamiento y la mayoría dedicaron más de 12 horas por día a la asistencia del paciente. El sufrimiento de los cuidadores responsables fue elevado durante todo el tratamiento (inicial 7,5 ± 2,8, final 8,4 ± 1,8), y tuvieron la percepción de que el control de síntomas fue moderado (inicial 5,3 ± 3,3, final 5,7 ± 2,7). Reportaron baja dificultad práctica (2,3 ± 3,5); dificultad emocional moderada (5,7 ± 3,8) y gran satisfacción con su tarea (8,9 ± 1,6). Es necesario identificar las dificultades de los CR, brindarles instrucción y apoyo emocional y material adecuados para optimizar su capacidad de asistencia y reducir su sufrimiento</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;13(2): 64-68, feb. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047766</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación del sufrimiento de los cuidadores esponsables de pacientes con cáncer asistidos en un centro de cuidados paliativos en Argentina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6858^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
