<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166105</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Importance of omega-3 fatty acids in the secondary prevention of acute myocardial infarction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Since the 1970s, general observations of dietary habits in both animal models and humans have suggested that omega-3 polyunsaturated fatty acids might be beneficial in preventing cardiovascular disease. Their most apparent and direct action appears to be their antiarrhythmic effect, which involves the stabilization of cardiac electrophysiological activity. However, subsequent investigations into other actions have revealed that there may be numerous mechanisms of action affecting multiple cellular targets. In fact, it has been shown that these molecules are able to modulate many cellular and tissular processes, such as inflammation, and cell proliferation, migration and apoptosis. Consequently, several hypothesis have been proposed to explain these observations, with the result that better targeted preclinical and clinical studies have been designed. Today, a large body of evidence, from epidemiological, laboratory and clinical studies, is gradually expanding the rational basis for using these compounds in the treatment of cardiovascular disease, particularly for secondary prevention. The aim of this review was to summarize the range of findings that underlies our understanding of the effects of omega-3 polyunsaturated fatty acids, from epidemiological observations to the results of clinical trials, and including laboratory findings. Although recommendations on the use of these fatty acids are already included in international guidelines, it is important that their risk&#150;benefit profile and mechanisms of action in various clinical conditions continue to be investigated, as is being done in many ongoing clinical studies, which should provide new data in coming years (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lonardo, Giuseppe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ceseri, Martina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maggioni, Aldo P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde la década de los sesenta, las simples observaciones de los hábitos alimentarios indicaban que los ácidos grasos poliinsaturados (AGPI) omega-3 podían ser beneficiosos para la prevención cardiovascular, tanto en los modelos animales como humanos. El efecto más evidente y directo parecía ser el antiarrítmico, al estabilizar la electrofisiología cardiaca. Sin embargo, con posterioridad se han investigado otros muchos efectos que han revelado otros posibles, y múltiples mecanismos de acción sobre diferentes objetivos celulares. De hecho, se ha demostrado la capacidad de estas moléculas para modular muchos de los procesos celulares y tisulares, como la inflamación, la proliferación celular, la migración, la apoptosis, etc. Por consiguiente, se plantearon diversas hipótesis para explicar los resultados observados y se diseñaron más estudios preclínicos y clínicos al respecto. En la actualidad disponemos de una gran cantidad de datos (epidemiológicos, experimentales y de ensayos clínicos) que han ido proporcionando gradualmente la base racional para el uso de estos compuestos en las enfermedades cardiovasculares, sobre todo en la prevención secundaria. Esta revisión pretende resumir las bases principales del conocimiento sobre los efectos de los AGPI omega-3, desde las observaciones epidemiológicas a los resultados de los ensayos clínicos, a través de los datos experimentales. Aunque ya hay una recomendación en las guías internacionales para el uso de los AGPI omega-3, aún se necesitan más investigaciones sobre su perfil de riesgo/beneficio y sus mecanismos de acción en diversos trastornos clínicos, como lo demuestra la existencia de muchos estudios clínicos en curso que aportarán nuevos datos en los próximos años (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);6(supl.D): 62d-71d, 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166105</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Importancia de los ácidos grasos omega-3 en la prevención secundaria del infarto agudo de miocardio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3662^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5334^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32808</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30163^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30163^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24651^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3662^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53393^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53393^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
