<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90115</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Guidelines for the non-invasive follow-up of abdominal aortic aneurysm treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Endovascular aneurysm repair (EVAR) is one of the greatest advances in vascular surgery over the past 50 years. In contrast to conventional aneurysm repair, EVAR requires stringent posoperative surveillance. Imaging of the graft and aneurysm is of utmost importance during follow-up to identify patients in need of secondary intervention. This has led to rigorous follow-up protocols based on regular CT examinations. The use of these intense follow-up protocols has recently been questioned due to the high radiation doses and the frequent use of nephrotoxic contrast agents. Less intensive follow-up based on ultrasound examination appears to be safe in the vast majority of patients. We suggest an EVAR surveillance regimen that regulates the frequency and intensity of postoperative imaging based on the outcomes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fontcuberta, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino Mairal, O. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aracil Sanus, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vila i Coll, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leal, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riera Vázquez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tratamiento endovascular del aneurisma de aorta abdominal (EVAR) representa uno de los grandes avances de la cirugía vascular en los últimos 50 años. A diferencia del tratamiento abierto, el EVAR precisa un seguimiento postoperatorio estricto. Durante el seguimiento, la imagen del dispositivo y del aneurisma son de extrema importancia para identificar pacientes en riesgo que precisan una intervención secundaria. Ello ha conducido a protocolos de seguimiento rigurosos basados en estudios con angio-TC. El empleo de estos protocolos de seguimiento tan intensivos son criticados actualmente tanto por la alta radiación administrada al paciente como por el empleo de medios de contraste nefrotóxicos. Los programas de seguimiento postoperatorios menos intensivos y basados en ultrasonidos parecen ser seguros en la mayoría de los pacientes. Proponemos un régimen de seguimiento postoperatorio del EVAR que varía la intensidad y frecuencia de los estudios de imagen postoperatorios en función de los hallazgos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;63(2): 65-74, mar.-abr. 2011. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90115</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Guía de seguimiento no invasivo del tratamiento endovascular del aneurisma de aorta abdominal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31994^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30853^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30853^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24885^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24885^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30829^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30853^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
