<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144452</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Estimation of hospital costs of colorectal cancer in Catalonia (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the hospital cost associated with colorectal cancer (CRC) treatment by stage at diagnosis, type of cost and disease phase in a public hospital. Methods: A retrospective analysis was conducted of the hospital costs associated with a cohort of 699 patients diagnosed with CRC and treated for this disease between 2000 and 2006 in a teaching hospital and who had a 5-year follow-up from the time of diagnosis. Data were collected from clinical-administrative databases. Mean costs per patient were analysed by stage at diagnosis, cost type and disease phase. Results: The mean cost per patient ranged from 6,573 Euros for patients with a diagnosis of CRC in situto 36,894 &#128; in those diagnosed in stage III. The main cost components were surgery-inpatient care (59.2%) and chemotherapy (19.4%). Advanced disease stages were associated with a decrease in the relative weight of surgical and inpatient care costs and an increase in chemotherapy costs. Conclusions: This study provides the costs of CRC treatment based on clinical practice, with chemotherapy and surgery accounting for the major cost components. This cost analysis is a baseline study that will provide a useful source of information for future studies on cost-effectiveness and on the budget impact of different therapeutic innovations in Spain (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Corral, Julieta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macià, Francesc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borràs, Josep Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antonio, Javier Mateu de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castells, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cots, Francesc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Alzorriz, Enric</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chiarello, Pietro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reig, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estimar el coste hospitalario del tratamiento del cáncer colorrectal (CCR) según estadio, tipo de coste y fase de evolución de la enfermedad en un hospital público. Métodos: Se realizó un estudio retrospectivo de costes de la atención hospitalaria del CCR de una cohorte de 699 pacientes con diagnóstico y tratamiento de CCR entre los años 2000 y 2006 en el Hospital del Mar, con seguimiento de hasta 5 años desde el diagnóstico de la enfermedad, a partir de bases de datos clínico-administrativas. Se analizó el coste medio por estadio, tipo de coste y fase de evolución de la enfermedad. Resultados: El coste medio por paciente en casos con diagnóstico in situ fue de 6573 &#128;. Este coste aumentó en estadios más avanzados y llegó a los 36.894 &#128; en el estadio III. Los principales componentes del coste fueron la cirugía-hospitalización (59,2%) y la quimioterapia (19,4%). En estadios más avanzados, el peso de la cirugía-hospitalización disminuyó, mientras que el de la quimioterapia aumentó. Conclusión: Este estudio proporciona el coste hospitalario del tratamiento del CCR calculado a partir de la práctica clínica habitual. La cirugía y el tratamiento quimioterápico son los principales componentes del coste. Los resultados obtenidos aportarán la información necesaria para los análisis de coste-efectividad de distintas iniciativas preventivas e innovaciones terapéuticas en nuestro entorno (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;29(6): 437-444, nov.-dic. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144452</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estimación del coste hospitalario del cáncer colorrectal en Cataluña</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30057^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50303</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13886^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
