<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131725</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relation ship between hypoalbuminemia and amputation free survival in patients undergoing revascularization due tolower limb critical ischemia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Hypoalbuminemia is a marker of poor prognosis in multiple clinical settings; however, has not yet been convincingly established its involvement in the results after arterial surgery of the lower limb. This paper evaluates the impact of hypoalbuminemia in patients undergoing revascularization for critical ischemia of the lower limb. Material and Methods. A retrospective observational study of patients who underwent revascularization for critical limb ischemia in the University Hospital of Valladolid was designed. We classified the patients into two groups according to the presence of calcinosis or not when assessing the ankle-brachial index. Both groups were compared to estimate differences in major amputation, exitus, major amputation free survival, hospital stay and complications. Results. Of the 529 patients included in the study, 61 (11,5%) had arterial hypoalbuminemia; these group had a 30 days higher major amputation rate (33,3% versus 19,5%), and a year higher mortality (34% versus 13,8%) and major amputation rate (28,6% versus 17,3%). One year amputation free survival was worse in patients with hypoalbuminemia(45%, 37%, 33%, 33% y 22% versus 70%, 64%, 58%, 51% y 48% at 1, 2, 3, 4 y 5 years), as well as the rate of respiratory postoperative complications (23% versus 6.4%). Conclusion. Preoperative hypoalbuminemia in patients revascularized by critical lower limb ischemia is associated with worse short and medium term clinical outcomes in terms of exitus and major amputation, as well as a higher rate of post operatory respiratory complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Fajardo, J A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brizuela Sanz, J A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero Puerta, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La hipoalbuminemia es un marcador de mal pronóstico en múltiples situaciones clínicas; sin embargo, aún no se ha establecido fehacientemente su implicación en los resultados tras cirugía arterial de la extremidad inferior. Este trabajo evalúa el impacto de la hipoalbuminemia en pacientes sometidos a revascularización por isquemia crítica de la extremidad inferior. Material y métodos. Se diseñó un estudio restrospectivo observacional de pacientes revascularizados por isquemia crítica en el Hospital Clínico Universitario de Valladolid. Se clasificó a los pacientes en dos grupos según la presencia de hipo o normo albuminemia en la analítica de sangre periférica preoperatoria. Se compararon ambos grupos para estimar diferencias en cuanto a amputación mayor, exitus, supervivencia libre de amputación mayor, estancia postoperatoria y complicaciones. Resultados. De los 529 pacientes incluidos en el trabajo, 61 (11,5%) presentaron hipoalbuminemia; este grupo presentó a 30 días mayor tasa de amputación mayor (33,3% versus 19,5%), y al año mayor mortalidad (34% versus 13,8%) y mayor tasa de amputación (28,6% versus 17,3%). La supervivencia libre de amputación mayor fue peor en pacientes con hipoalbuminemia (45%, 37%, 33%, 33% y 22% versus 70%, 64%, 58%, 51% y 48% a 1, 2, 3, 4 y 5 años), así como la tasas de complicaciones postoperatorias respiratorias (23% versus 6,4%). Conclusión. La hipoalbuminemia preoperatoria en pacientes revascularizados por isquemia crítica de la extremidad inferior se asocia a peores resultados clínicos en términos de muerte y amputación mayor a corto y medio plazo, así como a mayor tasa de complicaciones respiratorias postoperatorias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;17(4): 153-157, oct.-dic. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131725</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Realización entre la hipoalbuminemia y la supervivencia libre de amputación mayor en pacientes revascularizados por isquemia crítica de la extremidad inferior</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37287^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7678^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20180^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d686^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d686^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37287^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13915</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36500^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36500^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d421^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d421^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
