<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039624</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of sweat collection patches for the drug analysis in a group of inmates in the penal population in Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Ascertaining the usefulness and acceptance of sweat collection systems in order to establish the use of drugs in prison populations. Comparing the results of sweat and urine sample analyses.        Methodology: Observational cross-sectional study in a sample of 51 Grade-Three inmates or on parole involving an analysis of opiate and cocaine use on the basis of patches and urine samples.        Results: 82.35% of the sample considered that sweat collection systems are a good procedure in determining drug use. 81.75% of the patches were found completely adhered to the skin at removal, whereas 22.7% were partially or completely unstuck. Of the 170 patches which were analysed, cocaine was detected in 14.12% of them, opiates in 0.59%, and both substances were detected in 2.94% patches. An association was found when comparing these results with those from the urine analyses ( p &lt; 0.0001).        Discussion: Patches are easy to apply and, when they detach easy to detect. It is possible that unstuck patches have become spontaneously detached as a result of the excessive perspiration found in patients receiving high doses of methadone or from high summer temperatures. However, the possibility that the patches have been voluntarily detached cannot be excluded</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sternberg, Fabio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, Mario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vegue, Milagros</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvaro, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer la utilidad y la aceptación de los sistemas recolectores de sudor para la determinación de drogas en población penitenciaria. Comparar los resultados de los análisis de muestras de sudor y orina.        Material y método: Estudio descriptivo de tipo trasversal en una muestra de 51 personas en situación de Tercer Grado penitenciario o libertad condicional en las que se analizó el consumo de opiáceos y cocaína en parches y muestras de orina.        Resultados: El 82,35% de la muestra consideraba que los sistemas recolectores de sudor son un buen procedimiento para determinar el consumo de drogas. El 81,65% de los parches se encontraban totalmente adheridos a la piel al retirarlos, mientras que el 18,35% estaban parcialmente o totalmente despegados. De los 170 parches analizados en el 14,12% se detectó cocaína, en el 0,59% opiáceos y en el 2,94% las 2 sustancias, encontrando asociación entre estos resultados y los de los análisis de orina (p &lt; 0,0001).        Discusión: Resulta sencillo aplicar los parches y cuando se despegan se descubre fácilmente. Es posible que los parches despegados se desprendan espontáneamente como consecuencia de la sudoración abundante que aparece en sujetos que reciben altas dosis de metadona o que se produce por las altas temperaturas del verano. Aunque tampoco es posible excluir que los parches hayan sido voluntariamente desprendidos ya que su estado se asocia con la mala aceptación previa del procedimiento</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);17(2): 139-144, abr. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039624</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de los parches para el análisis de drogas en sudor en un grupo de reclusos de Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3070^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13927^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22604^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8866</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13923^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9488^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11766^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11766^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14956^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
