<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167277</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The hypertrophy of autonomy in the bioethical debate</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the current bioethical debate personal autonomy is frequently used as an argument to justify the legalization of new options for the subject. This is the case, for instance, of the controversies around surrogated motherhood, organ free market, euthanasia or egg freezing in order to postpone motherhood. This paper aims to show how legalizing certain options can be harmful to people, and would justify and perpetuate situations of domination of some human beings over others. In this regard, the importance of recognizing the unavailability of certain goods and human rights is underlined (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Otero, Juan María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el actual debate bioético se recurre frecuentemente al argumento de la autonomía personal para justificar la legalización de nuevas opciones para el sujeto, como la maternidad subrogada, la venta de órganos, la eutanasia o la congelación de gametos para posponer la paternidad. El presente artículo trata de mostrar cómo legalizar determinadas opciones puede resultar perjudicial para las personas afectadas, así como justificar y perpetuar situaciones de dominio de unos seres humanos sobre otros. En este sentido, se subraya la importancia de reconocer la indisponibilidad de determinados bienes y derechos humanos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad Bioet;28(94): 329-340, sept.-dic. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167277</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La hipertrofia del principio de autonomía en el debate bioético</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30490^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33877^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36316</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7381</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27859</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36358</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55428^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29871</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36433</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28008^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
