<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116152</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Scorpion sting in Lebanon. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Scorpion stings are frequent injuries, especially during the summer, ocasionally severe and produced by different mechanisms. Clinical manifestations vary with species and venom type, and include local, which vary from pain to necrosis, and general effects, with pulmonary, cardiovascular and neurological manifestations and coagulopathy, among others. Standard treatment protocol is still lacking. First aid include basic initial evaluation. If there are criteria of severity two large-bore cannulae should be inserted, and complementary exams such as complete blood analysis, X-ray study and electrocardiogram should be performed. Local treatment is mandatory to reduce the risk of infection. We present a case of double scorpion bite in the right low extremity suffered during the «Libre Hidalgo» XIV mission in Lebanon. The patient was discharged from ROLE 1 24 hours after admission and remained asymptomatic during his stay (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garijo Álvarez, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jie, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gascón Hove, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Herrero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las picaduras por escorpión son lesiones frecuentes, especialmente durante el verano, ocasionalmente graves y producidas por diferentes mecanismos. La clínica varía según la especie y la clase de veneno, e incluye efectos locales, como dolor y necrosis, y generales, entre las que encontramos manifestaciones pulmonares, cardiovasculares, neurológicas y coagulopatía, entre otras. Aún no existe un protocolo de actuación estandarizado. Las primeras medidas incluyen una evaluación inicial básica. Ante la existencia de criterios de severidad deberían colocarse dos vías de grueso calibre y deberían ser realizados exámenes complementarios como análisis de sangre, estudios radiológicos y un electrocardiograma (ECG). El tratamiento local es obligado para reducir el riesgo de infección. Presentamos a continuación un caso de una picadura doble por escorpión en la pierna derecha durante la misión «Libre Hidalgo» XIV en Líbano. El paciente abandonó el ROLE 1 24 horas después de su ingreso y permaneció asintomático durante éste (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;69(3): 203-205, sept. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116152</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Picadura por escorpión en Líbano. Presentación de un caso y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12984^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28021^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1758^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23121^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9077</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
