<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045116</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5665</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neuronal transdifferentiation of human bone marrow mesenchymal stem cells</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study describes the possibility to obtain neuronaltransdifferentiation of human mesenchymal stem cells, obtainedfrom the bone marrow stroma. Our present resultsconfirm previous experiences showing that these cells expressmarkers of neuronal differentiation when they arecultured with certain chemical factors. On the other hand,the present study demonstrates that a neuronal transdifferentiationof these cells can also be obtained by means of aco-culture with Schwann cells. In co-culture, transdifferentiationbegins later, although nestin expression is first observed4 hours after beginning the co-culture, it decreasedbetween 24 and 72 hours, and at this time, a clear increasein the number of NSE, NF and beta-tubulin-positive cells,can be seen</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zurita, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguayo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oya, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente estudio se muestra la posibilidad de lograruna transdiferenciación de células madre mesenquimales humanas,obtenidas del estroma de médula ósea, hacia neuronasadultas. Los resultados obtenidos confirman experiencias previasacerca de que las células madre del estroma de la médulaósea experimentan cambios fenotípicos y expresan marcadoresde diferenciación neuronal cuando se cultivan in vitrocon determinadas sustancias químicas. Por otra parte, el presenteestudio demuestra que la transdiferenciación neuronalde estas células puede ser obtenida también por medio de unco-cultivo con células de Schwann. La transdiferenciación enco-cultivo comienza más tardíamente, y aunque la expresiónde nestina, como primer marcador neural, se observa ya a las4 horas del co-cultivo, esta expresión disminuye entre las 24 y72 horas, momento en que comienzan a observarse células conexpresión de marcadores de diferenciación neuronal, aumentandoprogresivamente el número de células que expresanEnolasa específica neuronal, Proteína de neurofilamentos yBeta-tubulina</dc:description>
<dc:source>MAPFRE med;16(3): 167-173, jul. 2005. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045116</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Transdiferenciación neuronal de células madre mesenquimales de médula ósea humana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14806^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2489^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24016^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29931^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10944^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54432^s22071</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12964</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1878^s22071</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
