<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125520</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment compliance in chronic illness: current situation and future perspectives</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Long-term chronic diseases have a high mortality rate around the world, affecting both genders equally. Despite improvements in the diagnosis and treatment of various health problems, lack of treatment compliance remains an obstacle to improving health and patient quality of life, and it carries a high associated socio-healthcare cost. The objectives of this study were to develop the concept of «therapeutic adherence», which includes both pharmacological compliance as well as non-pharmacological (level of agreement and patient involvement, lifestyle changes, etc.) treatments. The study also aimed to establish the clinical and socio-health impact of non-compliance, the reasons for non-compliance, and methods and strategies to improve compliance. The results of this study support therapeutic adherence as an essential goal of the healthcare system that encompasses all stakeholders involved in patient health (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aliaga Pérez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinto, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barragán García, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Jurado, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ollero Baturone, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández de Cano Martín, M. N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conthe, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez Contreras, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las enfermedades crónicas de larga duración poseen una elevada mortalidad y afectan por igual a ambos sexos. La falta de adherencia a las recomendaciones terapéuticas continúa siendo un obstáculo para mejorar la salud y la calidad de vida de los pacientes, además de conllevar un elevado coste sociosanitario. En este trabajo se desarrolla el concepto «adherencia terapéutica» que engloba tratamientos farmacológicos (cumplimiento terapéutico) y no farmacológicos (grado de coincidencia entre las recomendaciones ofrecidas, como pueden ser cambios en los hábitos de vida y su implantación por el paciente). También se analiza el impacto clínico y sociosanitario de la «adherencia terapéutica», así como las causas de la falta de adherencia y métodos y estrategias para mejorarla. Concluimos que la adherencia terapéutica debe ser un objetivo esencial del sistema sanitario, englobando todos los agentes implicados en la salud del paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;214(6): 336-344, ago.-sept. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125520</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adherencia terapéutica en la enfermedad crónica: estado de la situación y perspectiva de futuro</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10546^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10546^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3380^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
