<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132271</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Noninvasive Mechanical Ventilation in Patients with Obesity Hypoventilation Syndrome. Long-term Outcome and Prognostic Factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Obesity is associated with 2 closely related respiratory diseases: obesity hypoventilation syndrome (OHS) and obstructive sleep apnea-hypopnea syndrome (OSAHS). It has been shown that noninvasive ventilation during sleep produces clinical and functional improvement in these patients. The long-term survival rate with this treatment, and the difference in clinical progress in OHS patients with and without OSAHS are analyzed. Methodology: Longitudinal, observational study with a cohort of patients diagnosed with OHS, included in a home ventilation program over a period of 12 years, divided into 2 groups: pure OHS and OSAHS associated OHS. Bi-level positive airway pressure ventilation was administered. During the follow-up period, symptoms, exacerbations and hospitalizations, blood gas tests and pulmonary function tests, and survival rates were monitored and compared Results: Eighty-three patients were eligible for analysis, 60 women (72.3%) and 23 men (27.7%), with a mean survival time of 8.47 years. Fifty patients (60.2%) were included in the group without OSAHS (OHS) and 33 (39.8%) in the OSAHS-associated OHS group (OHS-OSAHS). PaCO2 in the OHS group was significantly higher than in the OHS-OSAHS group (P &lt; .01). OHS patients also had a higher hospitalization rate (P &lt; .05). There was a significant improvement in both groups in FEV1 and FVC, and no differences between groups in PaCO2 and PaO2 values. There were no differences in mortality between the 2 groups, but low FVC values were predictive of mortality. Conclusions: The use of mechanical ventilation in patients with OHS, with or without OSAHS, is an effective treatment for the correction of blood gases and functional alterations and can achieve prolonged survival rates (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morán Caicedo, Liliana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Resano Barrios, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodriguez Gonzalez-Moro, José Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Martin, Soledad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Rodríguez, Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ojeda Castillejo, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bellón Cano, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lucas Ramos, Pilar de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Desde el punto de vista respiratorio, la obesidad se asocia con 2 enfermedades muy relacionadas: el síndrome de obesidad-hipoventilación (SOH) y el síndrome de apnea-hipopnea del sueño (SAHS). Se ha demostrado que el tratamiento con ventilación mecánica no invasiva durante el sueño produce una mejoría clínica y funcional en estos pacientes. Analizamos a largo plazo la supervivencia con este tratamiento, y la diferencia en la evolución entre pacientes con SOH con y sin SAHS asociado. Metodología: Estudio longitudinal, observacional, de una cohorte de pacientes diagnosticados de SOH e incluidos en un programa de ventilación domiciliaria a lo largo de 12 años, distribuidos en 2 grupos: SOH puro y SOH asociado a SAHS. La ventilación se llevó a cabo con ventiladores de presión positiva continua binivel. Durante el tiempo de seguimiento se monitorizó y comparó su situación clínica (síntomas, exacerbaciones e ingresos), gasométrica y funcional, así como su supervivencia. Resultados: Ochenta y tres pacientes fueron válidos para el análisis, 60 mujeres (72,3%) y 23 hombres (27,7%), con una media de supervivencia de 8,47 años.  Cincuenta pacientes (60,2%) fueron incluidos en el grupo sin SAHS (SOH) y 33 (39,8%) en el grupo con SAHS (SOH-SAHS). La PaCO2 del grupo SOH era significativamente mayor que la del grupo SOH-SAHS (p &lt; 0,01), y también presentaban más hospitalizaciones (p &lt; 0,05). Existió una mejoría significativa en ambos grupos en FEV1 y FVC, y en los valores de PaCO2 y PaO2, sin diferencias entre los grupos. Mientras que no se apreciaron diferencias en la supervivencia relacionadas con el subgrupo diagnóstico, valores bajos de FVC sí constituían un factor predictivo de mortalidad. Conclusiones: El uso de ventilación domiciliaria en pacientes con SOH con o sin SAHS es un tratamiento eficaz que corrige las alteraciones gasométricas y funcionales y permite alcanzar tiempos prolongados de supervivencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;51(2): 61-68, feb. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132271</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ventilación mecánica no invasiva en pacientes con síndrome de obesidad-hipoventilación. Evolución a largo plazo y factores pronósticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24890</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51716^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13273^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55022^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7220^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
