<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045168</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality improvement of filling medication tolleys process for an unit-dose drug distribution system</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the quality of filling medication trolleysprocess for an unit-dose drug distribution system, after the implantationof a protocol.Method: Five criteria were defined: four were related to themedication given to the patient, and one criterion was related tothe patient&#146;s identification. At the same time, it was designed astandardized protocol of filling medication trolleys process and itwas evaluated the degree of compliance with the criteria on all thehospitalized patients&#146; medication drawers in two clinical units. Thefulfilment of the criteria was measured both before and after theimplantation of the protocol, for fourteen and seven days respectively.Results: In the first evaluation the number of errors was0.84/medication drawer. After the implantation of the protocol,the total number of errors after correction for sample size decreasedat 0.22/medication drawer. The degree of compliance improvedfor all the criteria, and differences were statistically significantfor the criteria with most errors.Conclusions: The implantation of a protocol significantlyimproved two of the five quality criteria studied in the filling medicationtrolleys process. The patient's identification has been revealedas a fundamental aspect of intervention in the dispensationquality</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Espuny, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bovaira, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorente, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la calidad del proceso de llenado de carrosen un sistema de distribución en dosis unitarias tras la implantaciónde un protocolo.Método: Se definieron cinco criterios de calidad: cuatro relativosa la medicación dispensada al paciente y uno relativo a laidentificación del mismo. Paralelamente, se diseñó un protocolode trabajo estandarizado y se evaluó el cumplimiento de los criteriossobre todos los cajetines de medicación de los pacientes hospitalizadosen dos unidades clínicas. El cumplimiento de los criteriosse midió antes y después de la implantación del protocolo,durante catorce y siete días consecutivos respectivamente.Resultados: En la primera evaluación el número de incumplimientosfue 0,84/cajetín. Tras la implantación del protocolo, eltotal de incumplimientos tras ajuste por tamaño de muestra seredujo a 0,22/cajetín. El nivel de cumplimiento mejoró para todoslos criterios y las diferencias fueron significativas para los dos criteriosmás incumplidos.Conclusiones: La implantación de un protocolo ha supuestouna mejora significativa en dos de los cinco criterios estudiados enel proceso llenado de carros de medicación. La identificación delpaciente se ha revelado como un aspecto fundamental de intervenciónen la calidad de la dispensación</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;29(6): 359-363, nov.-dic. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045168</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mejora de la calidad del proceso de llenado de carros de medicación en un sistema de distribución de medicamentos en dosis unitarias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8675</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26452^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10797^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4411^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4422^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
