<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159472</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">«The anthropocene», ecosystem management, and environmental virtue</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this article I consider contrasting views on the implications of rapid, macroscale anthropogenic change for environmental ethics, particularly ecosystem management, species conservation, and environmental virtue. I begin by reviewing the Anthropocene debate, which has become a primary point of discourse on whether we ought to embrace a more interventionist stance regarding ecosystem management and species conservation. I then discuss the challenges posed by rapid ecological change to predominant ecosystem management and species conservation practices. I argue that these challenges not withstanding, we ought not go all in on interventionist management, even as novel conservation and management techniques can be justified in particular cases. It is possible to adopt a more forward looking normative stance, without licensing robust interventionism. Finally, I discuss the implications of this for some environmental virtues (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sandler, Ronald</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo considero puntos de vista contrastantes sobre las implicaciones del rápido cambio  antropogénico en macroescala de la ética ambiental, con particular referencia a la gestión de los ecosistemas, la conservación de especies, y la virtud ambiental. Comienzo por revisar el debate sobre el &#147;Antropoceno&#148;, que se ha convertido en un punto fundamental del discurso sobre nuestra opción de tomar una postura más intervencionista respecto a la gestión de los ecosistemas y la conservación de especies. Finalmente, abordo los desafíos que plantea el rápido cambio ecológico a las prácticas predominantes de gestión de los ecosistemas y de conservación de las especies. Argumento que, no obstante estos desafíos, no debemos apoyar totalmente la gestión intervencionista, ya que nuevas técnicas de conservación y de gestión pueden justificarse en casos particulares. Es posible adoptar una postura normativa más hacia el futuro, sin una caer en el intervencionismo radical. Por último, discuto las implicaciones de esto para algunas virtudes ambientales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad Bioet;27(91): 357-368, sept.-dic. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159472</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">«El antropoceno», la gestión de los ecosistemas y la virtud ambiental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1698^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32479</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3266</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51600^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16274^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32447^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31494</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
