<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74792</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Susceptibility to antimicrobial agents of rapidly growing mycobacteria</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Rapidly growing mycobacteria are often associated with human diseases. We investigated the in vitro susceptibilities of 40 isolates to six antimicrobialagents: 17 Mycobacterium fortuitum, 11 M. chelonae and 12 M. abscessus isolated from several human sources: 29 respiratorysecretions, 5 cutaneous abscesses, 4 corneal ulcers and 2 urine samples of patients treated at &#147;Hospital Puerta del Mar&#148; (Cádiz). Susceptibilitystudies were determined by the broth microdilution method for amikacin, clarithromycin, ciprofloxacin, levofloxacin, imipenem and cefoxitin.Results suggest that amikacin is the most effective antimicrobial agent for treating infections due to rapidly growing mycobacteria.Clarithromycin and imipenem show good activity against M. fortuitum and M. abscessus, but not against M. chelonae. Quinolones are onlyeffective against M. fortuitum. It&#146;s important to identify, in rapidly growing mycobacteria infections, the etiologic agent to determine correcttreatment(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Agudo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Aragón, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Martos, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flores, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las micobacterias de crecimiento rápido no cromógenas se asocian con frecuencia a infecciones humanas diseminadas y localizadas. Hemosdeterminado la sensibilidad in vitro a seis antimicrobianos de uso habitual de 40 cepas (17 Mycobacterium fortuitum, 11 M. chelonae y 12M. abscessus) aisladas de diversas fuentes clínicas: 29 secreciones respiratorias, cinco abscesos cutáneos, cuatro úlceras corneales y dos orinas,de pacientes atendidos en el Hospital Puerta del Mar, de Cádiz. El estudio de sensibilidad se realizó por el método de microdilución encaldo frente a amikacina, claritromicina, ciprofloxacino, levofloxacino, imipenem y cefoxitina. Los resultados sugieren que la amikacina es elantimicrobiano más efectivo para el tratamiento de las infecciones producidas por micobacterias de crecimiento rápido no cromógenas. Laclaritromicina y el imipenem presentan buena actividad frente a M. fortuitum y M. abscessus, pero no frente a M. chelonae. Las quinolonassolamente son efectivas frente a M. fortuitum. En las infecciones por micobacterias de crecimiento rápido es importante identificar el agenteetiológico para determinar el tratamiento más apropiado(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;20(4): 429-432, sep.2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74792</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sensibilidad a los antimicrobianos de micobacterias de crecimiento rápido</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24244^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9357^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9353^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9354^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
