<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130662</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gender activation in transparent and opaque words</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Two reaction time experiments were carried out to examine the morphological gender processing of Spanish words that were either transparent -that is, ending in o/a (e.g., banco - bank)-or opaque- that is, without superficial gender marking (e.g., virtud - virtue). In Experiment 1, participants categorized the gender of a transparent gender target preceded by a derived word of the same gender  (e.g., banquillo-dock, masculine) or of different gender (e.g., banqueta-stool, feminine). A negative priming gender effect indicates the use of strategic-attentional mechanisms to decide the gender of the target, but also automatic computation of the prime gender. Experiment 2 used a lexical decision task with the stimuli of Experiment 1 in addition to opaque gender words. The results show longer reaction times for transparent gender words with regard to opaque items. This effect was possibly due to thelexical requirements of the task: lexical decision, and also because transparent words are morphologically more complex than opaque words. Finally, in both experiments, there was negative priming: when prime and target were of the same gender, reaction times were longer. This effect indicates that participants cannot ignore the gender of the prime when they respond to the target (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alvarez, Carlos J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urrutia, Mabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Dos experimentos de tiempo de reacción se realizaron para evaluar el procesamiento del género en palabras del español con género transparente, terminadas en -o/-a (e.g., banco) y palabras opacas, terminadas en consonantes (e.g., virtud). En el experimento 1 los participantes efectuaron una tarea de categorización de género en la que debían decidir el género de un target precedido por una palabra del mismo género (e.g., banquillo-BANCO) o de diferente género (e.g., banqueta-BANCO). Los resultados indicaron un efecto de priming negativo, estoindica el uso de una estrategia atencional para decidir el género del target, pero también un cálculo automático del género del prime. En el experimento 2 se realizó una tarea de decisión léxica con los mismos estímulos del experimento 1, añadiéndose estímulos de género opaco. Los resultados mostrarontiempos de reacción más largos para palabras de género transparente con respecto a las opacas, esto porque las primeras son morfológicamente más complejas que las segundas y también a que se trata de tareas léxicas distintas. En ambos experimentos encontramos un efecto de priming negativo cuando prime y target correspondían al mismo género. Este efecto podría indicar que los participantes no pueden ignorar el género del prime cuando responden al target (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);21(1): 1-8, ene.-mar. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130662</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Activación de género en palabras transparentes y opacas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7980</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15334</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7985</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55087</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5924</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
