<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051153</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gender differences in early reperfusion treatment after myocardial infarction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Clinical variability in myocardial infarction (MI) regarding age, comorbidities and atypical symptoms could determine gender differences in inhospital care. This study analyzes the magnitude and determinants of differences between men and women in early reperfusion therapy in people hospitalized after MI. Patients and method: 2,836 patients who arrived to hospital with MI were studied (IBERICA-Basque Country study). The relative risk (RR) of receiving early reperfusion for men versus women, adjusted by age, clinical characteristics, risk factors, and pre-hospital delay was estimated. The effect decomposition methodology and the log binomial regression were applied. Results: 29% of patients were women with a median age of 77 years. The RR of revascularization in men compared to women was different according to age. When factors such as hypertension diabetes, Killip III-IV at admission and atypical symptoms were taken into account, statistically significant differences between sexes were not detected at 45 years old (RR = 0.91; 95% CI = 0.77-1.07). However, for 64 years old and over, the RR of reperfusion was 1.24 (95% CI = 1.05-1.47). Both the differences by sex and the sex-age interaction were no longer statistically significant after adjusting by pre-hospital delay. Conclusions: The delay to receive medical care in elderly women is responsible of gender differences in early reperfusion. It is necessary to analyze the reasons for treatment-seeking delay</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hurtado de Caracho, Iraida</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esnaola, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arós, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Audicana, Covadonga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lecuona, Iñaki</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arteagoitia, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Basterretxea, Mikel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo, Montse</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aldasoro, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marrugat, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Diferencias en la presentación clínica del infarto agudo de miocardio (IAM), como la edad, la comorbilidad y la frecuencia de síntomas atípicos, podrían condicionar un proceso de cuidados hospitalarios distinto según el sexo. Este estudio analiza la magnitud y los determinantes de las diferencias entre sexos en la revascularización precoz en personas ingresadas por IAM. Pacientes y método: Se estudió a 2.836 pacientes con IAM que accedieron a cuidados hospitalarios (IBERICA-País Vasco). Se estimó el riesgo relativo (RR) de revascularización precoz en los varones respecto a las mujeres teniendo en cuenta la edad, la presentación clínica, los antecedentes y la demora extrahospitalaria. Se aplicó la metodología de descomposición de efectos y el análisis de regresión log-binomial. Resultados: El 29% de los pacientes eran mujeres y su edad mediana, de 77 años. El RR de revascularización de los varones respecto a las mujeres fue distinto según la edad. Tras ajustar por hipertensión arterial, diabetes, Killip III-IV al ingreso y síntomas atípicos, no se apreciaban diferencias significativas a los 45 años (RR = 0,91; intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 0,77-1,07), mientras que para los mayores de 64 años, el RR de revascularización fue de 1,24 (IC del 95%, 1,05-1,47). Al ajustar por la demora extrahospitalaria, las diferencias por sexo y la interacción del sexo con la edad no eran significativas. Conclusiones: El retraso en el acceso a la atención sanitaria de las mujeres mayores es causa de las diferencias por sexo en la revascularización precoz. Es necesario analizar las razones de esta demora</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);128(3): 81-85, ene. 2007. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051153</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias de género en el tratamiento de revascularización precoz del infarto agudo de miocardio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9396^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28634</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28842</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
