<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138482</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Primary cerebral lymphoma in an immunocompetent patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Primary lymphoma of the central nervous system PLCNS) was a very uncommon disease until a few decades ago. However, its incidence has increased in recent years, mainly in immunocompetent patients. Thus, some authors suggest that PLCNS may become the most frequent tumor. The final diagnosis is based on the pathology study of the samples obtained with stereotaxic biopsy or with surgery, but X-ray studies may be very useful in the orientation of this disease. The typical finding in immunocompetent subjects is the appearance of single supratentorial lesions with homogeneous uptake of contrast and scarce edema, without edema, necrosis nor bleeding. Survival has increased thanks to the new treatments applied, although there is still controversy regarding frequency, dose and administration form of many of them. We present the case of an immunocompetent male patient with progressive dyplopia and vertigo caused by a primary lymphoma of the central nervous system and a review the literature (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García García, AM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Catalán, MI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García García, ME</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El linfoma primario del sistema nervioso central (LPSNC) era una entidad de escasa frecuencia hasta hace unas décadas, pero su incidencia se ha incrementado en los últimos años, principalmente en pacientes inmunocompetentes, por lo que algunos autores sugieren que podría llegar a ser el tumor más frecuente. El diagnóstico definitivo se basa en el estudio anatomopatológico de las muestras obtenidas con biopsia estereotáxica o con cirugía, pero las pruebas radiológicas pueden ser de gran utilidad en la orientación de esta entidad. El hallazgo típico en inmunocompetentes es la aparición de lesiones únicas supratentoriales, con captación homogénea de contraste y escaso edema, sin necrosis ni hemorragia. La supervivencia se ha incrementado gracias a los nuevos tratamientos aplicados, aunque existen controversias con respecto a la frecuencia, dosis y forma de administración de muchos de ellos. Presentamos el caso de un hombre, inmunocompetente, con cuadro de 1 mes de evolución de diplopía, vértigo y cefalea como forma de presentación de LPSNC y revisamos la literatura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;23(2): 122-125, mar. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138482</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Linfoma primario cerebral en un paciente inmunocompetente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1958^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7304</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1958^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1958^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8398^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27888^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4229^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31474</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8398^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8398^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
