<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143679</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Food consumption pattern at a family level of urban areas of Anzoátegui, Venezuela</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In order to assess the qualitative pattern of food consumption in urban families of Anzoátegui, Venezuela, 300 domestic groups that combined a total of 1  163 people were studied. The domestic dietary pattern was addressed by the method of qualitative frequency of food consumption, which applied a structured survey that yielded the usual frequency of intake of a food or food group over a given period. The information was obtained through an interview with the person responsible for the procurement of food in every home, and included basic data for the socioeconomic and nutritional profile of the families studied. The qualitative analysis of the diet was obtained by comparing the different food groups that constitute the actual consumption pattern of the population studied, with official feeding guidelines suggested for the Venezuelan population. The present study showed that the qualitative pattern of food consumption in the urban population evaluated is characterized by slightly adjusted to the promotion of health and control of diet-related diseases. The family food proved to be far from the guidelines established by the dietary guidelines for Venezuela and consumption patterns are fairly homogeneous in the different socioeconomic strata. The foods most consumed daily were salt, coffee, dressing and precooked corn flour as well as beef, chicken and the higher weekly food consumption pastas. 90% of the food consumed daily is technologically processed. The results contribute to increase knowledge about the food situation of the Venezuelan population, and technically could direct the efforts of the authorities to reconcile the development of the productive sector and food supply, whereas a pattern qualitatively inadequate intake directly affects the individual biological functioning, and results in the collective conditioning of unfavorable health states (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Lorenzo, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cámara Martos, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Rojas, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ekmeiro Salvador, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Con el objeto de evaluar el patrón cualitativo de consumo de alimentos en familias de zonas urbanas del estado de Anzoátegui, Venezuela, se estudiaron 300 grupos domésticos que aglutinaban un total de 1.163 personas. El patrón dietético intrafamiliar se abordó a través del método de frecuencia cualitativa de consumo de alimentos, el cual aplicó una encuesta estructurada que permitió obtener la frecuencia habitual de ingesta de un alimento o grupo de alimentos durante un período determinado. La información fue obtenida mediante una entrevista con la persona responsable de la adquisición de los alimentos en cada hogar, e incluía datos básicos para elaborar el perfil socioeconómico y alimentario de las familias estudiadas. El análisis cualitativo de la dieta se obtuvo comparando los diferentes grupos de alimentos que constituyen el patrón real de consumo de la población evaluada, con las guías de alimentación oficiales sugeridas para la población venezolana. El presente estudio reveló que el patrón de consumo cualitativo de alimentos en la población urbana evaluada se caracteriza por prácticas alimentarias poco ajustadas a la promoción de la salud y al control de las enfermedades relacionadas con la dieta. La alimentación familiar demostró estar muy apartada de los lineamientos establecidos por las guías de alimentación para Venezuela y que los patrones de consumo son bastante homogéneos en los diferentes estratos socioeconómicos. Los alimentos más consumidos diariamente fueron sal, café, adobo y harina de maíz precocida; así como la carne de bovino, el pollo y las pastas alimenticias los de mayor consumo semanal. El 90% de los alimentos más consumidos diariamente son tecnológicamente procesados. Los resultados obtenidos contribuyen a incrementar el conocimiento sobre la situación alimentaria de la población venezolana; y técnicamente podrían dirigir los esfuerzos de las autoridades para conciliar el desarrollo del sector productivo y de abastecimiento de alimentos, considerando que un patrón de consumo cualitativamente inadecuado afecta directamente al funcionamiento biológico individual y se traduce en el condicionamiento colectivo de estados de salud desfavorables (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(4): 1758-1765, oct. 2015. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143679</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patrón de consumo de alimentos a nivel familiar en zonas urbanas de Anzoátegui, Venezuela</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23905</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28084</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14904^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5350</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55398</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
