<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-20000</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Griscelli syndrome in mexico. Description of a case with neurological manifestations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Griscelli syndrome is a pathological condition with immunodeficiency and is characterised by hepatosplenomegaly, silvery hair, progressive neurological deterioration, hypogammaglobulinemia and pancytopenia. It is inherited by autosomal recessive transmission and is diagnosed using the histopathological findings from a skin biopsy, characterised by hyperpigmentation with accumulations of melanin, associated to the manifestations described. Case report. We report on the first case identified in Mexico: the patient, who presented silvery hair, hepatosplenomegaly and pancytopenia, was a member of a family with two children and had no noteworthy antecedents. From the ninth month onwards there was a fast progression of the neurological deterioration, which was characterised by epileptic seizures and flaccid quadriparesis that progressed quickly to a state of coma. Magnetic resonance imaging revealed demyelination of the white matter, mainly in the bilateral frontotemporal area; skin biopsy showed hyperpigmentation with accumulations of melanin. Conclusions. Immunodeficiencies are serious problems, but associated with dermatological, haematological and neurological data, accompanied by findings obtained by paraclinical haematological explorations, by neuroimaging and skin biopsies, it is possible to establish the proper diagnosis in order to improve quality of life and the progress of the disease. This can be achieved by bone marrow transplant (until now the only therapy available) but it must be performed early and not when the disease is at an advanced stage, when the possibility of recovery becomes more remote (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El síndrome de Griscelli es una patología con inmunodeficiencia y se caracteriza por hepatoesplenomegalia, cabello plateado, deterioro neurológico progresivo, hipogammaglobulinemia y pancitopenia. Se transmite con carácter autosómico recesivo y su diagnóstico se realiza con los hallazgos histopatológicos de la biopsia de piel, caracterizado por hiperpigmentación con cúmulos de melanina, asociado a las manifestaciones descritas. Caso clínico. Se presenta el primer caso identificado en México, que presentó cabello plateado, hepatoesplenomegalia y pancitopenia; integrante de una familia de dos hijos y sin ningún antecedente de importancia. A partir de los nueve meses aparece una progresión rápida del deterioro neurológico, caracterizado por crisis epilépticas, y cuadriparesia flácida que evolucionó rápidamente al estado de coma. En la resonancia magnética se observó una desmielinización de sustancia blanca de predominio frontotemporal bilateral; la biopsia de piel mostró una hiperpigmentación con cúmulos de melanina. Conclusiones. Las inmunodeficiencias son problemas graves, pero asociados a datos fenotípicos dermatológicos, hematológicos y neurológicos, acompañados de hallazgos paraclínicos hematológicos, de neuroimagen y complementado con la biopsia de piel es posible establecer el diagnóstico oportuno para mejorar la calidad de vida y la progresión de la enfermedad, mediante el procedimiento de trasplante de médula ósea, hasta el momento único recurso terapéutico, pero realizado de forma temprana y no en estadio avanzado, en donde la posible recuperación es más difícil (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;36(4): 347-350, feb. 2003. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Griscelli en México. Descripción de un caso con manifestaciones neurológicas</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Pérez Casillas, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro Tarín, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alva Moncayo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-20000</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6354</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7334</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6686</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13957</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13546</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10385</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14065</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
