<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156412</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Structural synaptic plasticity in the hippocampus induced by spatial experience and its implications in information processing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Long-lasting memory formation requires that groups of neurons processing new information develop the ability to reproduce the patterns of neural activity acquired by experience. Development: Changes in synaptic efficiency let neurons organise to form ensembles that repeat certain activity patterns again and again. Among other changes in synaptic plasticity, structural modifications tend to be long-lasting which suggests that they underlie long-term memory. There is a large body of evidence supporting that experience promotes changes in the synaptic structure, particularly in the hippocampus. Conclusion: Structural changes to the hippocampus may be functionally implicated in stabilising acquired memories and encoding new information (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carasatorre, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Cintra, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez-Amaya, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Para formar memorias perdurables, es necesario que los grupos de neuronas encargados de procesar la información que adquirimos desarrollen la capacidad de reproducir los patrones de actividad que se forman a través de la experiencia. Desarrollo: Los cambios en la eficiencia sináptica permiten que las neuronas se organicen en «ensambles» y reproduzcan una y otra vez estos patrones de actividad. Entre los cambios en la eficiencia sináptica están las modificaciones en la estructura, las cuales tienden a perdurar por mucho tiempo y por ello se les vincula con la memoria a largo plazo. En la literatura existe amplia evidencia de que la experiencia promueve modificaciones en la estructura sináptica, particularmente en regiones como el hipocampo. Conclusión: Las implicaciones funcionales de estos cambios en el hipocampo incluyen un posible papel en la estabilización de los recuerdos adquiridos y en la codificación de nueva información (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;31(8): 543-549, oct. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156412</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Plasticidad sináptica estructural en el hipocampo inducida por la experiencia espacial y sus implicaciones en el procesamiento de información</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9665^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8776^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13409^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6783^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
