<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60562</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Methods for determining viral tropism: genotype and phenotype tests</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The recent approval of the first CCR5 antagonist,Maraviroc (MVC, Celsentri®), with specific antiviral activityagainst R5-tropic virus variants has generated the need forstudies to determine the viral tropism in all those patientcandidates for starting treatment with this new drug.Although genotyping methods appear to be the mostuseful tool due to its speed and simplicity, in the case ofviral tropism, phenotyping techniques are currentlyconsidered the most reliable. In the last few years, different phenotyping assays have been developed todetermine the use of the co-receptor. However, the TrofileTMphenotype assay is currently the one most used for thedetermination of tropism, since it is the only one that hasbeen clinically validated. Given that the presence of X4-tropic variants in the viral population has been associatedwith virological failure to MVC, the main challenge of bothgenotyping and phenotyping tools is to optimise theirsensitivity for detecting X4-tropic variants present in aminority of the viral population. At the same time, thecorrelation between genotyping/phenotyping methods isbeing evaluated to determine whether genotyping tools canbe useful to make therapeutic decisions(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Poveda, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perez-Olmeda, Mayte</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La reciente aprobación del primer antagonista de CCR5,maraviroc (MVC, Celsentri®), con una actividad antiviralespecífica frente a variantes virales R5-trópicas hagenerado la necesidad de disponer de ensayos para ladeterminación del tropismo viral en todos los pacientescandidatos a iniciar tratamiento con este nuevo fármaco.Aunque los métodos genotípicos parecen ser laherramienta más útil por su rapidez y sencillez, en el casodel tropismo viral, las técnicas fenotípicas son actualmenteconsideradas las más fiables. En los últimos años, se handesarrollado diferentes ensayos fenotípicos para ladeterminación del uso del correceptor. Sin embargo, elensayo fenotípico de TrofileTM es el ensayo utilizadoactualmente para la determinación de tropismo, ya que esel único que cuenta con validación clínica. Dado que lapresencia de variantes X4-trópicas en la población viral seha asociado con fracaso virológico a MVC, el principal retode las herramientas tanto genotípicas como fenotípicas esoptimizar su sensibilidad para la detección de variantesX4-trópicas presentes de forma minoritaria en la poblaciónviral. Al mismo tiempo, se está evaluando la correlaciónentre métodos genotípicos y fenotípicos para determinarsi las herramientas genotípicas pueden utilizarse paratomar decisiones terapéuticas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;26(supl.11): 40-48, oct. 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60562</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Métodos de determinación del tropismo viral: tests genotípicos y fenotípicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36265^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29416^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29416^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27890^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10833</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5974</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31996</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33499^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33498^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
