<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80114</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of differences between indication and prescription of gastroprotection in patients with risk factors treated with nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory agents: The GAP study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">AbstractPreventive measures in patients treated with nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDS) have been reported to be underused. The aim of the present study was to analyze differences between the indication and prescription of gastroprotection with proton pump inhibitors (PPI) in patients treated with NSAIDS and with risk factors for gastrointestinal complications.MethodsWe performed an observational, cross-sectional, multicenter study. Data were gathered retrospectively from medical records and from a questionnaire on risk factors and indication for gastroprotection.ResultsA total of 432 physicians gathered data from 2,160 patients treated with NSAIDs. Nearly all (90.4%) of the patients were prescribed gastroprotection with a PPI. Long-term versus short-term (&lt;1 month) NSAID treatment was associated with gastroprotection (OR=2.37; 95% CI 1.779&#150;3.171). The mean number of risk factors per patient was 2±0.16 (range 0&#150;7), and a significant association was found between the number of risk factors and the percentage of patients receiving gastroprotection. Nevertheless, the proportion of patients with risk factors not receiving gastroprotection was 3% for those with a prior history of ulcer and/or gastrointestinal bleeding due to NSAIDS and 7&#150;10% for the remaining factors. Differences were found between the indication for gastroprotection and the gastroprotection prescribed among the various specialties. The specialists prescribing gastroprotection the least were radiotherapy specialists.ConclusionsThese results demonstrate that, in daily clinical practice, differences between the indication and prescription of gastroprotection in patients treated with NSAIDS and with risk factors are small in Spain(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Jiménez, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lanas, Angel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero Correa, Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ResumenSe ha señalado que las medidas de prevención en pacientes tratados con antiinflamatorios no esteroideos (AINE) estan infrautilizadas. El objetivo de este estudio es analizar las diferencias entre indicación y prescripción real de gastroprotección con inhibidores de bomba de protones en pacientes con factores de riesgo para complicaciones gastrointestinales en tratamiento con AINE.MétodosEstudio observacional, transversal y multicéntrico. Recogida retrospectiva de datos a partir de historias clínicas y cumplimentación de un cuestionario sobre factores de riesgo e indicación de gastroprotección.ResultadosUn total de 432 facultativos recogieron datos de 2.160 pacientes tratados con AINE. Un 90,4% de pacientes recibían prescripción de gastroprotección con inhibidores de bomba de protones. El tratamiento con AINE a largo plazo frente a corto plazo (&lt;1 mes) mostraba una asociación con gastroprotección (odds ratio=2,37; intervalo de confianza del 95%: 1,779&#150;3,171). La media de factores de riesgo por paciente fue de 2±0,16 (rango: 0&#150;7), se observó una asociación significativa entre número de factores de riesgo y porcentaje de pacientes en gastroprotección. Aun así, la proporción de pacientes con factores de riesgo sin gastroprotección fue del 3% para historia previa de enfermedad ulcerosa o hemorragia digestiva por AINE y del 7&#150;10% para los demás factores. Se observaron diferencias entre indicación y gastroprotección prescrita entre las diferentes especialidades, los especialistas de radioterapia son los que presentaron menor grado de gastroprotección.ConclusionesEstos resultados reflejan que en la práctica clínica diaria las diferencias entre indicación y prescripción real de gastroprotección en pacientes con factores de riesgo tratados con AINE son pequeñas en nuestro país(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;33(2): 80-91, feb. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80114</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de las diferencias entre indicación y prescripción de gastroprotección en pacientes con factores de riesgo tratados con antiinflamatorios no esteroideos: estudio GAP</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5908^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52844^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29962^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27938^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27938^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d908^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
