<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112438</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-7279</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Given the growing life expectancy of the population in Catalonia and the incidence of cognitive deterioration as from age 65, the home care services, such as housing with services for older people, must implement preventive practices that provide a quality assistance to those who may be suffering from a cognitive deterioration and, at the same time, to their informal caregivers in order to ensure personalized attention. This research aims to highlight the profile of the person who might be suffering from an incipient cognitive deterioration, as well as that of the caregivers, and the risk factors which have been observed, such as solitude and/or insufficient observation of the professionals who assist them (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Canal Chavero, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Dado el aumento de la esperanza de vida de la población en Cataluña y la incidencia de deterioro cognitivo a partir de los 65 años, los servicios de atención domiciliaria como las viviendas con servicios para personas mayores deben ir poniendo en práctica acciones preventivas que brinden una atención de calidad a las personas que podrían estar sufriendo un deterioro cognitivo y, al mismo tiempo, a sus cuidadores informales, para garantizar de esta forma una atención personalizada. Mediante este estudio se pretende dar a conocer el perfil de persona con posible deterioro cognitivo incipiente y el de los cuidadores y los factores de riesgo que se han desprendido de dicha investigación, como pueden ser la soledad y/o la observación insuficiente de los profesionales que les atienden (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Inf. psiquiátr;(212): 235-253, abr.-jun. 2013. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112438</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Atención domiciliaria a personas mayores con posible deterioro cognitivo y a sus cuidadores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28940</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37737^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
