<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72920</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Premedication with oral fentanil (CFOT) in paedriatic surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The surgery in the paedriatic population represents a sourceof disconfort for the patient and his familiar surroundingsthat often are infravalued, so much by these as by the professionals.Still there is much to make to diminish this impact andto provide to the children emotional conditions adapted to facethe surgery and the postoperative period. The objective ofthis work was to demonstrate the utility of fentanyl oral (CFOT)to provide ansiolityc and postoperative analgesia. 10 ug/Kg ofCFOT was administered previous to intervention to a group of45 children submissive for amigdalectomy and the behavior wasvalued, the collaboration and the analgesia obtained in the immediatepostoperative period. The obtained results was comparedwith those of a similar placebo group. Student andANOVA, obtaining themselves significant differences as far asthe collaboration degree, ansiolityc and analgesia in favor ofgroup CFOT. We maintain that this method is in addition safe,simple and enjoys a great acceptance on the part of the parentsand professionals implied in the welfare process(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Bustamante, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moguel, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Guerrero, A. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres, L. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Collado, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La cirugía en la población infantil representa una fuentede disconfort para el paciente y su entorno familiar que a menudoes infravalorado tanto por éstos como por los profesionales.Aún hay mucho por hacer para disminuir este impactoy proporcionar a los niños unas condiciones emocionales adecuadaspara enfrentarse a la cirugía y al postoperatorio. El objetivode este trabajo era demostrar la utilidad del citrato defentanilo oral transmucosa (CFOT) como medio de ansiolisispreoperatorio y analgesia postoperatoria. Para ello se administróprevio a la intervención 10 ug/Kg de CFOT a un grupode 45 niños sometidos a adenoamigdalectomía y se valoróel comportamiento, la colaboración y la analgesia obtenida enel antequirófano y postoperatorio inmediato. Los resultadosobtenidos se compararon con los de un grupo control similarutilizando para ello la T de student y ANOVA, obteniéndosediferencias significativas en cuanto al grado de colaboración,ansiolisis y analgesia a favor del grupo CFOT. Nosotros sostenemosque este método es además seguro, sencillo y gozade una gran aceptación por parte de los padres y profesionalesimplicados en el proceso asistencial(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;15(2): 69-74, mar.2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72920</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad del citrato fentanilo oral transmucosa (CFOT) para procurar ansiolisis preoperatoria y analgesia postoperatoria en cirugía pediátrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28846^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14458^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14458^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11729^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52865^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11729^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d715^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28037^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11621^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11621^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6590^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
