<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74709</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The pharmacists and the health care team: a new paradigm of interprofesional relations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The work of different health care assistants is directed towards the well being of the patient, mainly the prevention and cure of diseases. Nevertheless, the relations among the different healthcare professionals have not always been well defined. This has caused disagreements among them, with the result of prejudgment for the patients. At present, precisely one of the fundamental challenges of the health care field is to achieve a real integration of all the assistants who are in charge of health care, forming real teams wherein every professional can contribute in a coordinated manner their knowledge and skills. This is the proposal presented in this text, that is, the need for a change in the present paradigm of the relations among the different members of the healthcare team (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Guzmán, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La labor de los distintos agentes sanitarios está dirigida al bien del paciente, principalmente a la prevención de enfermedades y la curación de enfermos. No obstante, las relaciones entre los profesionales de la salud no siempre han estado bien definidas. Ello ha dado lugar a discrepancias entre ellos, con el consiguiente perjuicio para los pacientes. Precisamente, en la actualidad, uno de los retos fundamentales en el ámbito sanitario es conseguir una verdadera integración de todos los agentes que tienen a su cargo el cuidado de la salud, los cuales constituyen auténticos equipos, en los que cada profesional pueda aportar, de manera coordinada, sus conocimientos y habilidades. Ésta es la propuesta que se presenta en el texto, la cual remite, en definitiva, a la necesidad de plantear un cambio en el actual paradigma de las relaciones entre los miembros del equipo sanitario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;11(2): 85-89, abr.-jun. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74709</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El farmacéutico y el equipo de salud: un nuevo paradigma de relaciones interprofesionales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7564</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10749^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10786^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10542^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50249</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36316</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
