<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121568</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pharmacovigilance of calcineurin inhibitors in pediatric kidney and liver transplantation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To develop a pharmacovigilance program of calcineurin inhibitors used in pediatric renal and liver transplant patients at Hospital de Pediatría JP Garrahan, Argentina. Methods: Adverse drug reactions (ADRs) of pediatric patients with kidney and liver transplantation treated with calcineurin inhibitors (cyclosporine and tacrolimus) were evaluated by retrospective review of medical records of patients transplanted between 2010 and 2011. In addition, we carried out active pharmacovigilance since March, 2011. ADRs were reported to the National Health Authority. Results: A total of 59 patients, 28 kidney transplant and 31 liver tarnsplant patients were analyzed. In both transplants, 60 ADRs to cyclosporine were reported including (number of cases), hypertension (19) and nephrotoxicity (6). In addition, 46 ADRs to tacrolimus were registered as hypomagnesemia (25), hypertension (7) and nephrotoxicity (5). A total of 95% and 96% of the adverse events to cyclosporine and tacrolimus, respectively, were defined as probable or definitive. Lastly, 70% and 98% of the events to cyclosporine and tacrolimus respectively, have been moderately severe or severe. Conclusions: This is the first study in Latin America that developed an intensive qualitative and quantitative analysis of the ADRs to calcineruin inhibitors in pediatric kidney and liver transplant patients. Spontaneous reporting should be motivated as well as monitoring ADRs should continue in the medium and long term for improving patient's quality of life (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Monteverde, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rousseau, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schaiquevich, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Imventarza, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dip, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cáceres Guido, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riva, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mato, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Desarrollar un programa de farmacovigilancia de pacientes pediátricos trasplantados hepáticos y renales centrado en inmunosupresores calcineurínicos del Hospital de Pediatría JP Garrahan de Argentina. Métodos: Se evaluaron las reacciones adversas a medicamentos (RAM) de los pacientes pediátricos trasplantados renales y hepáticos de nuestro hospital tratados con inhibidores de calcineurina (ciclosporina y tacrolimus) por revisión retrospectiva de historias clínicas de pacientes trasplantados en 2010-2011, y análisis prospectivo por farmacovigilancia activa de trasplantados fuera de dicho período, cuyas complicaciones se hayan presentado en los ateneos semanales del Servicio de Trasplante desde marzo de 2011. Las RAM se notificaron a la autoridad sanitaria nacional. Resultados: Se analizaron un total de 59 pacientes, 28 trasplantados renales y 31 hepáticos. Se notificaron, en ambos trasplantes, 60 RAM a ciclosporina destacándose (número de casos) hipertensión arterial (19) y nefrotoxicidad (6). Asimismo, se registraron 46 RAM a tacrolimus, incluyendo hipomagnesemia (25), hipertensión (7) y nefrotoxicidad (5). El 95% y 96% de los eventos adversos a ciclosporina y a tacrolimus, respectivamente, han sido agrupados como probables o definitivos. El 70% y 98% de los eventos adversos a ciclosporina y a tacrolimus respectivamente, han sido de severidad moderada o grave. Conclusiones: Este es el primer proyecto en América Latina que propone y desarrolla el estudio cuali-cuantitativo intensivo de RAM a inhibidores de calcineurina en trasplante pediátrico renal y hepático. Es necesario estimular la notificación espontánea así como continuar el seguimiento de RAM a mediano y largo plazo para mejorar la calidad de vida del paciente trasplantado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;37(6): 441-449, nov.-dic. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121568</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Farmacovigilancia de inhibidores de calcineurina en trasplante renal y hepático pediátrico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30103^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52955</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54726</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29476</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33429^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7344^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30164^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
