<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108555</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9572</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sleep deprivation as diagnostic methodo in adult sleepwalkers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Sleepwalking is considered a benign sleep disturbance in children, although when present in adults can result in injury to the sleeper and to others. This sleep disorder is more difficult to detect in the laboratory of sleep that in the patient&#146;s normal environment, making it difficult to establish the diagnosis through polysomnographie. The group Montplaisir (Neurology 2002) based on the knowledge that sleepwalking presented less control or consolidation of slow sleep studied the effect of sleep deprivation in patients sleepwalking and compared with controls, finding that sleep deprivation for 38 hours before the study PSG increased the frequency and complexity of episodes of sleepwalking in the registry. Case Report: It is presented a case studied by PSG night preceded by 38 hours of sleep deprivation of a man 29year old with episodes of sleepwalking with a frequency of three or more episodes per week for 8 months. The medical history revealed insufficient sleep and poor sleep hygiene due to his work as a musician band. Other sleep disorders and diseases weren&#146;t detected. There were two episodes of sudden waking from slow sleep with movements compatible with a diagnosis of sleepwalking in the adult. Conclusion: The sleep deprivation is a tool to be taken into account in the study of sleepwalking in the laboratories of sleep disorders&#146;studies facilitating the diagnosis for inducing somnambulistic episodes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Canet, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: : El sonambulismo es considerado como una alteración del sueño benigna en niños, si bien, cuando se presenta en adultos puede producir algún daño en el que lo padece o en los otros. Este trastorno del sueño es más difícil de detectar en los laboratorios del sueño que en el ambiente habitual del paciente, lo cual hace difícil establecer el diagnóstico mediante polisomnografía. El grupo de Montplaisir (Neurology 2002) basándose en el conocimiento de que los sonámbulos presentan un menor control o consolidación del sueño lento estudiaron el efecto que la privación del sueño producía en pacientes sonámbulos y los compararon con controles encontrando que una privación del sueño de 38 horas antes del estudio polisomnográfico nocturno aumentaba la frecuencia y complejidad de los episodios de sonambulismo en el registro. Caso clínico: Se presenta un caso estudiado mediante PSG nocturna precedido de 38 horas de privación de sueño de un varón de 29 años con episodios de sonambulismo con una periocidad de tres episodios o más a la semana desde hace 8 meses. La historia clínica reveló sueño insuficiente y mala higiene del sueño debido a su trabajo como músico de banda. No se detectaron otras alteraciones del sueño ni otras patologías. Se registraron dos episodios de despertares bruscos acompañados de movimientos desde sueño lento compatibles con el diagnóstico de sonambulismo en al adulto. Conclusión: La privación del sueño es una herramienta a tener en cuenta en el estudio del sonambulismo en los laboratorios de estudios de trastornos del sueño facilitando el diagnóstico al inducir episodios registrables (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Vigilia sueño;21(1): 2-10, ene.-jun. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108555</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La privación del sueño como método de estudio en el sonambulismo en adultos. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13274^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13274^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13274^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13274^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13274^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30611^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13274^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13392^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30611^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30611^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30611^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13392^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
