<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94971</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neuropsychological aspects of acquired iffuse brain injury in paediatric childhood</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Summary. Introduction and development. Acquired brain injury is one of the most common causes of long-term disability in childhood and traumatisms are the most prevalent cause. Diffuse axonal injury is associated with poor neuropsychological outcome. In contrast to early focal lesions, young age confers no advantage in the outcome of severe diffuse brain injury. Plasticity is incomplete for structural and functional deficits in children. The traditional view of enhanced reorganization of function after localized brain injury it can&#146;t be applied in early severe diffuse brain injury. In the paediatric population where the central nervous system is in a rapid state of growth, developmental factors may mask the difficulties and deficits in certain  skills may not be evident until that skill is expected to emerge at a certain age. Conclusion. Like in adults the neuropsychological domains more affected in childhood are psychomotor speed, memory, attention and executive functioning. Inchildhood neuropsychological deficits will affect learning and adaptive behaviour. Sometimes deficits will be cumulative over time (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Colomé, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Sala, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sans, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>boix, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen. Introducción y desarrollo. El daño cerebral adquirido (DCA) es causa de discapacidad en la edad pediátrica. El traumatismo craneoencefálico grave constituye la causa más frecuente de DCA. El pronóstico vital del DCA es más favorable en el niño que en el adulto. No sucede así con el pronóstico neuropsicológico, que es más desfavorable cuanto menor es la edad en el momento de producirse la lesión. En el daño cerebral difuso la plasticidad y capacidad de reorganización cerebral  tienen un efecto limitado en la compensación de los déficit cognitivos y conductuales. Debido al proceso de desarrollo del sistema nervioso del niño, la repercusión del DCA puede tardar años en ser evidente. Las demandas crecientes en la escuela, de autonomía y de adaptación social, harán que las dificultades puedan ser progresivas con la edad. Conclusión. Las funciones neuropsicológicas más afectadas, igual que en la edad adulta, son la velocidad psicomotora, memoria, funciones ejecutivas y atencionales. El proceso de desarrollo y aprendizaje del niño hará que la repercusión sea mucho mayor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;48(supl.2): 23-26, feb. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94971</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aspectos neuropsicológicos del daño cerebral difuso adquirido en la edad pediátrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34242^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34226^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2699^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
