<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166113</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perfectionism and «adaptative alarm» to anxiety in sports figthing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The description of the characteristics of personality in sports has been one of the most popular topics for Sport Psychology, there are different lines of investigation. However, they have been smaller studies especially in combat sports. This study addresses the analysis of how the indicators of perfectionism relate to the vulnerability and sensitivity to anxiety symptoms. The sample consists of 110 athletes of combat, of which 78 men and 32 women. Different questionnaires were used to measure the study&#146;s variables, all of them adapted to Spanish population. We used different questionnaires adapted to Spanish population for the measurement of perfectionism (FMPS) and anxiety sensitivity (ASI-3). Results suggest that the lack of consistency between personal standards and own organization for sport (personal routines in training, rest, preparation of competitions, etc.) relate significantly with cognitive confusion and discrepancies. Differentiation by gender, women report significant differences in personal standards and vulnerability to social anxiety. Are doubts about actions and perceptions of parental expectations, the dimensions of perfectionism that more reactivity to alter social and physical anxiety. It can be said that although the existence of sensitivity symptoms of anxiety states, lack of resources for understanding and intervention will allow the development of the pathology of anxiety, early detection of key elements in their relationship with the personality allow anticipate and prepare for the athlete before his appearance through integrated strategies and psychological training to convert negative signals «adaptive alarms» sports practice and implementation resources (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Hernández, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Reyes, Aldo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La descripción de las relaciones diferenciales entre la personalidad y la respuesta deportiva ha permitido ofrecer explicación sobre el comportamiento psicológico de las personas cuando practican deporte. Por otra parte, han sido más reducidos los estudios realizados en particular en los deportes de combate. El presente estudio se dirige al análisis de cómo los indicadores de perfeccionismo se relacionan con la vulnerabilidad y sensibilidad a la sintomatología de ansiedad. La muestra consta de 110 deportistas de combate, de los cuales 78 hombres y 32 mujeres. Se han utilizado diferentes cuestionarios adaptados a población española para la medición del perfeccionismo (FMPS) y sensibilidad a la ansiedad (ASI-3). Los resultados sugieren que la falta de coherencia entre las exigencias personales y la organización propia para el deporte (rutinas personales en entrenamientos, descansos, preparación de competiciones, etc.) se relacionan de forma significativa con confusión y discrepancias cognitivas. En la diferenciación por género, las mujeres señalan diferencias de significación en normas personales y vulnerabilidad a la ansiedad social. Son las dudas sobre acciones y percepción de las expectativas paternas, las dimensiones del perfeccionismo que más alteran la reactividad a la ansiedad social y física. Es posible afirmar, que si bien se afirma la existencia de sensibilidad a la sintomatología de ansiedad, la falta de recursos para su entendimiento e intervención permitirán el desarrollo de la patología de ansiedad, la detección precoz de elementos claves en su relación con la personalidad permitirá anticipar y preparar al deportista ante su aparición, a través de estrategias y recursos integrados en el entrenamiento psicológico que convierta señales negativas en «alarmas adaptativas» para la práctica y ejecución deportiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;26(supl.2): 15-23, 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166113</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfeccionismo y «alarma adaptativa» a la ansiedad en deportes de combate</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54747^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15350^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14111</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13601</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
