<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044869</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and aimThe prevalence of hospital malnutrition togetherwith advanced age makes elderly patients undergoingmajor surgery a high-risk population withan adverse clinical evolution and greater associatedmortality. The aim of this study was to assessthe nutritional supply provided by a hospital dietplus supplements in elderly patients at risk of malnutritionduring seven days of hospitalization.Material and methodsTwo groups were studied: A) hospitalized patientswho were undernourished or at risk ofmalnutrition (n=74) with a mean age of74.8±12.2 years (53% men) and B) a controlgroup (n=70) with a mean age of 60.8±10.8 years(50% men). Macronutrients were prescribedand quantified according to the nomenclature ofthe hospital diet code. Ingestion was estimatedqualitatively following an interview with the patient,and quantitative results were estimatedusing the DietSource software (1.2). The nutrientsprovided by the nutritional supplementadministered (1-3 times per day) were added tothis calculation. The following diets were administered:baseline (n=20), bland III (n=19), liquid(n=14), bland II (n=6), diabetic (n=6), hyperproteic(n=5) and progression diets (n=4).ResultsThe supplement most frequently used was ClinutrenDessert® (n=48). In the baseline comparisonof the nutritional contribution between groupsA and B, lower levels were observed in the hospitalizedpatients, with significant differences in allthe variables except carbohydrates. The increasein energy supply following supplementation showedwide individual variability (6.9%-84.1%), but itincreased the supply of all the nutrients (correlationcoefficients: r=0.926 to r=0.984; P&lt;0.05).ConclusionsIn elderly hospitalized patients the nutritionalsupply provided by the diet is inferior to that definedin the international RDA. Nevertheless,with administration of dietary supplements, nutritionimproves and approaches the theoreticalrequirements</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Farriol, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roca, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pons, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">FundamentosLa prevalencia de la malnutrición hospitalariay la edad hace que los pacientes ancianossometidos a cirugía mayor sea un colectivo dealto riesgo con una evolución clínica adversaasociada a una mayor mortalidad. El objetivodel estudio es valorar el aporte nutricional dela dieta hospitalaria más suplementos, en pacientesancianos con riesgo de desnutrición,durante siete días de ingreso en el hospital.Material y métodosSe estudiaron dos grupos: A, pacienteshospitalizados desnutridos o en riesgo dedesnutrición (n=74) con una edad media de74,8±12,2 años (varones 53%) y B, un grupocontrol (n=70) con una edad media de60,8±10,8 años (50% varones). Los macronutrientesse prescribieron y contabilizaron delnomenclator del Código de dietas del hospital.La ingesta real se estimó cualitativamentedespués de la entrevista con el paciente y losresultados cuantitativos se estimaron medianteel software DietSource 1.2. Al cálculo obtenidose le añadió el aporte proveniente del suplementonutricional administrado (1-3 veces/día). Las dietas administradas fueron: basal(n=20), blanda III (n=19), líquida (n=14),blanda II (n=6), diabética (n=6), hiperproteica(n=5) y dietas de progresión (n=4).ResultadosEl suplemento más utilizado fue ClinutrenDessert® (n=48). Basalmente la comparacióndel aporte nutricional entre los grupos A y B,mostró niveles inferiores en los pacientes ingresados,con diferencias significativas en todaslas variables excepto los carbohidratos. Elincremento del aporte energético después dedar suplementos presentó una gran variabilidadindividual (6.9-84.1%) pero incrementó elaporte de todos los nutrientes (coeficientes decorrelación: r=0.926 a r=0.984; p&lt;0.05).ConclusionesEn pacientes ancianos hospitalizados, elaporte de nutrientes provenientes de la dietaes inferior al definido en las RDA internacionalespero con la administración de suplementosse consigue mejorar el aporte nutricionaly aproximarse a los requerimientos teóricos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;26(2): 56-64, mar.-abr. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044869</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aporte dietético de suplementos en pacientes ancianos hospitalizados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5661</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33546</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
