<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72943</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pritnarp spndrotnes of diffuse muscle-eskeletical pain. Descriptive study and versus to the conventional fibromialgia disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Study and contrast of primary clinical syndromes, similar to the Fibromyalgia (F.M.) but without important presence of Patient painful points. Methods: Design type cases and controls. Patient&#146;s clinical cases with generalized and persistent diffuse muscle-eskeletical pain/(&gt;6 months), but with&lt;5 F.M points. and exclusión of forceful pathologies. Controls. Diagnosed patients of F.M. by the criteria of Wolfe of 1994.Studied variables. A) Clinical characteristics. A questionnaire goes over 46 variants of the symptoms. Two samples: of 26 wo-men in cases and 32 women incontrols. B) Painful exploratory data and evolution. F.M points. Stress, anxiety and depression, semi quantitative evaluation. Muscular tensión, by semiobjective evaluation. And evolution by autoevaluation to the 6 months. Statistical Tests Student-Fisher Tests for the comparison of ages and number of painful points, and those of chi square for the comparison of frequencies. Results: Average of painful points in cases = 1.36 and controls (10,32 P&lt; 0,0001) very similar clinical profile in cases and controls, including the evolution. Differences: alive pain but and in rest, cases (P&lt; 0,005); muscular tensión but frequents in controls (P&lt; 0,01). Conclusion: These results relativist the importance diagnose and foretell of the painful points (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guitart Boixader, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudio y contrastación de unos cuadros clínicos primarios, similares a la Fibromiálgia (F.M.) pero sin presencia importante de puntos dolorosos. Pacientes y métodos: Diseño tipo casos y controles. Casos Pacientes con dolor musculo esquelético difuso/generalizado y persistente (&gt;6 meses), pero con &lt;5puntos de F.M. y exclusión de patologías contundentes. Controles Pacientes diagnosticados de F.M. por los criterios de Wolfe de 1994.Variables estudiadas A) Características clínicas. Se pasa un cuestionario sobre 46 variantes de la sintomatología. Dos muestras: de 26 mujeres en casos y 32mujeres en controles. B) Datos exploratorios y evolución. Puntos dolorosos de F.M. Estrés, ansiedad y depresión, por evaluación semicuantitativa. Tensión muscular, por evaluación semiobjetiva. Y evolución por autoevaluación a los 6 meses. Pruebas estadísticas Pruebas de Student-Fisher para la comparación de edades y número de puntos dolorosos, y las del chi cuadrado para la comparación de frecuencias. Resultados: Media de puntos dolorosos en casos=1.36 y en controles 10.32 (P&lt;0.0001). Perfil clínico muy similar en casos y controles, incluida la evolución. Diferencias: dolor más vivo y en reposo, en casos (P&lt;0.005); tensión muscular más frecuente en controles (P&lt;0.01). Conclusión: Estos resultados relativizan la importancia diagnóstica y pronóstica de los puntos dolorosos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;15(5): 284-290, jun.-jul. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72943</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuadros primarios de dolor musculoesquelético difuso. Estudio descriptivo y analítico frente a la fibromialgia convencional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13700^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13700^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9334^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9334^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9323^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200807</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
