<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164610</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Musculoskeletal disorders/pain in undergraduate nursing students in a community university in southern Brazil</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Goal: To describe the academic profile and assess the prevalence of musculoskeletal disorders/pain in undergraduate nursing students in a Community University in Southern Brazil. Method: It has been a descriptive quantitative study with a survey approach, and has been conducted with 149 nursing students, through the employment of an instrument with questions regarding sociodemographic variables, life, and health habits, as for Standardized Nordic Questionnaire. Results: Most participants were female, age ranging from 18 to 25, unmarried, living with the family, with no children, not receiving government support or family aid, and working for hospitals. The prevalence of musculoskeletal was in the dorsal and lumbar region and shoulders. Conclusions: The prevalence of such symptoms amongst the students leads to the need of implementing preventive and health promotion actions, in order to contribute for the improvement of life quality in both the academic scope and in the future as professionals (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martins-Machado, Letícia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosa-dos-Santos, Renan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bosi-de-Souza-Magnago, Tânia Solange</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bitencourt Toscani-Greco, Patrícia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antochevis-de-Oliveira, Matheus</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cassol-Prestes, Francine</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir el perfil académico y evaluar la prevalencia de trastornos/dolor musculoesquelético en estudiantes de graduación en Enfermería de una universidad comunitaria del sur brasileño. Método: Estudio descriptivo, cuantitativo, del tipo encuesta, con 149 estudiantes de enfermería a través del instrumento compuesto por preguntas referentes a las variables sociodemográficas, hábitos de vida y salud, así como por la versión brasileña Standardized Nordic Questionnaire. Resultados: La mayoría era del sexo femenino, con 18 y 25 años de edad, soltera, vive con la familia, no tiene hijos, no recibe beca o ayuda de la familia y trabaja en hospitales. Prevalencia de síntomas musculoesqueléticos en la región dorsal y baja de la espalda y hombros. Conclusiones: La prevalencia de estos síntomas entre los estudiantes señala la necesidad de implementar acciones preventivas y de promoción de la salud para contribuir a una mejor calidad de vida y salud, en el ámbito académico y en el futuro como profesionales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;16(47): 128-143, jul. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164610</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos/dolor músculoesquelético en estudiantes de enfermería de una universidad comunitaria del sur del Brasil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54520^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54520^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22981^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22981^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24960^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201707</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
