<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79198</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-0921</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Delirium or Síndrome Acute Confusional has an important incidence, especially in geriatrical patients and during hospitable income, that in spite of having an organic aetiology exist factors prearrangers like the environmental ones, between that include the social ones. Also, we must be conscious that previous the social situation goes to influence in the patient and the treatment, that is going to have an important influence for its evolution. The precise patient measured environmental and to its nearer relatives like reference, which will reduce to the level of confusion and its associate complications or upheavals. For it, at the same time as the facultative intervention and of infirmary, the social worker will have to realise a social and familiar intervention, that gives an interdisciplinary character to the intervention and improves the welfare quality(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gracia Merle, Ana M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El delirium o síndrome confusional agudo tiene una importante incidencia, especialmente en pacientes geriátricos y durante ingresos hospitalarios, que a pesar de tener una etiología orgánica existen factores predisponentes como los ambientales, entre los que se incluyen los sociales. Así mismo, debemos ser conscientes de que la situación social previa va influir en el paciente y en el tratamiento, que va a tener una influencia importante para su evolución. El paciente precisa medidas ambientales y a sus familiares más cercanos como referencia, lo que reducirá el nivel de confusión y sus complicaciones o trastornos asociados. Para ello, simultáneamente a la intervención facultativa y de enfermería, el trabajador social deberá realizar una intervención social y familiar, que dé un carácter interdisciplinar a la intervención y mejore la calidad asistencial(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. multidiscip. gerontol;20(1): 18-22, ene.-mar. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79198</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervención social en el delirium del anciano</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d20174^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3707^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3245^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
