<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049567</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1780</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">ACT and the importance of personal values in the context of psychological therapy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ACT and the Importance of Personal Values in the Context of Psychological Therapy. The aims of the article are to show the importance of personal values in the context of psychological treatment. The advantages of an explicit approach to values during the therapeutic process are examined. We analyse the values involved in Clinical Psychology, and how different clinical perspectives address them. Besides the importance of client&#146;svalues, the role of the therapist&#146;s values as an incentive for effective clinical work or as a barrier in the therapeutic change is analysed. All these points are considered in the context of the Acceptance and Commitment Therapy (ACT), as a therapy explicitly centred in client&#146;s personal values</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Luciano-Soriano, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valdivia-Salas, Sonsoles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Páez-Blarrina, Marisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Martínez, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente artículo expone la relevancia que tienen los valores personales como componente necesario del tratamiento psicológico y las ventajas que se derivan del abordaje de los valores de forma explícita a lo largo del proceso terapéutico. Se muestra la importancia de analizar los valores del cliente implicados en la práctica de la Psicología Clínica y se describe el lugar que dan a los valores las terapias más relevantes. Se discute además del rol de los valores del cliente, el papel de los valores del terapeuta y la necesidad de que éste aprenda a discriminar cuándo sus propios valores funcionan como barreras en el proceso clínico. En este contexto, se expone la Terapia de Aceptación y Compromiso (ACT) como terapia centrada explícitamente en los valores personales del cliente</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int. j. psychol. psychol. ther. (Ed. impr.);6(1): 1-20, ene. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049567</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Terapia de Aceptación y Compromiso (ACT) y la importancia de los valores personales en el contexto de la terapia psicológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11798</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13329</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12023^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
