<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164595</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-0618</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Historical perspective of antimalarials of natural origin</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Today, many diseases are treated thanks to the discovery of compounds from plants, which shows that they play a significant role in the discovery and development of new drugs. One of the alternatives for the control of malaria morbidity and mortality is chemotherapy, which has been made possible by the discovery of compounds from plants. At present, about half of the available antimalarials drugs are naturally occurring compounds or are related to them. This review provides a historical account of the origin and development of the main antimalarials as an instrument of architectural facts, which maintains a close relationship with the antimalarials referents, which serve as models to deepen the search for new natural chemical substances that could contribute to the Control of a devastating disease like malaria, where resistant strains of Plasmodium are being presented to the main treatments, therapeutic failure, in addition to poor access to medicines, among other factors; which complicate their prevention and  treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mesa, Ana María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Hoy, muchas enfermedades son tratadas gracias al descubrimiento de compuestos a partir de las plantas, lo que evidencia que estas juegan un papel significativo en el descubrimiento y desarrollo de nuevos fármacos. Una de las alternativas para el control de la morbi-mortalidad por malaria es la quimioterapia, la cual ha sido posible gracias al descubrimiento de compuestos a partir de las plantas. En la actualidad, cerca de la mitad de los fármacos antimaláricos disponibles son compuestos naturales o están relacionados con ellos. En esta revisión se hace un recuento histórico del origen y desarrollo de los principales antimaláricos como instrumento de hechos arquitectónicos, que mantienen una estrecha relación con los referentes antimaláricos, que sirven de modelos para profundizar en la búsqueda de nuevas sustancias químicas naturales que podrían contribuir al control de una devastadora enfermedad como la malaria, donde se están presentando cepas resistentes de Plasmodium a los principales tratamientos, falla terapéutica, además de un escaso acceso a los medicamentos, entre otros factores; que complican su prevención y tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Real Acad Farm;83(2): 167-174, 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164595</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perspectiva histórica de antimaláricos de origen natural</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12240^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8462^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54858^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3651^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37305^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23138^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d965^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11394^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7480^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
