<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103868</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The scientific entertainer in primary health care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The scientific method is capable of being applied in primary care. In this article we defend the role of the &#147;scientific entertainer &#147;as strategic and necessary in achieving this goal. The task has to include playful and light-hearted content. We explore some words in English that may help us to understand the concept of &#147;scientific entertainer&#148; from a semantic point of view (showman, master of ceremonies, entrepreneur, go-between) also in Spanish language (counsellor, mediator, methodologist) and finally in Latin and Greek (tripalium, negotium, chronos, kairos). We define the clinical, manager or research health-worker who is skilled in primary care as a &#147;primarylogist&#148;(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lapetra, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega-Calvo, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El método científico es susceptible de ser aplicado en atención primaria. Nosotros defendemos en este artículo la figura del «animador científico» como estratégica y necesaria. Su trabajo ha de tener un contenido «lúdico». Exploramos algunos términos en lengua inglesa que nos ayudan a comprender el concepto de «animador científico» desde un punto de vista semántico (showman, master of ceremony, entrepeneur, go-between), analizamos otros en lengua castellana (consejero, mediador, metodólogo) y otros en latín y griego (tripalium, negotium, chronos, kairos). Definimos como primariólogo al sanitario clínico, gestor o investigador que sea experto en atención primaria(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;44(9): 549-554, sept. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103868</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La animación científica en atención primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d25561</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8901</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12529</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13042</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
