<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96528</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Primary hip replacement: first year results and predictive factors of poor outcome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To evaluate the results of total hip arthroplasty in patients with osteoarthritis and to identify predictors of poor functional outcome. Material and methods. A prospective observational study in patients operated on in 2006 with total hip arthroplasty in 4 hospitals in Guipúzcoa, followed up for 1 year. Outcome variables: pain, physical function, complications, mortality, quality of life by WOMAC and SF-12 (at 0, 3, 6 and 12 months) and «Poor functional outcome» at one year (last quartile of the WOMAC in function area). Logistic regression was performed to examine predictors of poor functional outcome. Results. A total of 166 patients were followed up. The incidence of systemic and local complications was 6.3% and 14.5%, respectively, 4.3% readmissions and no deaths related to surgery. Close to 40 points improvement in pain, stiffness and WOMAC functional limitation, mainly in the first 3 months after surgery. A similar trend was seen, but lower in the physical and mental component of the SF12 (12 and 8 points, respectively). The previous score on the WOMAC function area and the physical component of SF-12, and the existence of any complications, are predictors of poor functional recovery. Discussion. The improvement experienced after the surgery is already very important before the third month. The functional and physical status before surgery and possible complications of surgery are significant determinants of the results (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Azcárate, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escobar, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Etxebarria-Foronda, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arrieta, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aizpuru, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Linertová, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarasqueta, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Evaluar los resultados del primer año en la artroplastia total de cadera de pacientes con osteoartritis e identificar los factores predictores de mala evolución funcional. Material y método. Estudio observacional, prospectivo en pacientes intervenidos en 2006 con artroplastia total de cadera en 4 hospitales de Guipúzcoa, seguidos durante un año. Variables de resultado: dolor, función física, complicaciones, mortalidad, calidad de vida mediante WOMAC y SF-12 (a 0, 3, 6 y 12 meses) y «mal resultado funcional» al año (último cuartil del WOMAC en área de función). Mediante regresión logística se estudiaron los factores predictores de mal resultado funcional. Resultados. Se incluyeron 166 pacientes. La incidencia de complicaciones sistémicas y locales fue de 6,3 y 14,5%, respectivamente, con 4,3% de reingresos y sin fallecimientos relacionados con la cirugía. Mejoría cercana a 40 puntos en dolor, rigidez y limitación funcional del WOMAC, principalmente en los primeros tres meses postintervención. Evolución similar, pero inferior en el componente físico y mental del SF12 (12 y 8 puntos respectivamente). La puntuación previa en el área de función de WOMAC y en el componente físico del SF-12, así como la existencia de alguna complicación, son factores predictores de la mala recuperación funcional. Discusión. La mejoría experimentada tras la intervención es ya muy relevante antes del tercer mes. La situación funcional y física previa a la intervención y las posibles complicaciones de la cirugía son factores determinantes de los resultados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);56(1): 3-10, ene.-feb. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96528</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Artroplastia primaria de cadera: resultados en el primer año y factores predictores de mala evolución</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
