<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83689</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Folic acid intake from diet and supplements in a population of pregnant women in Valencia, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: We examined the dietary intake and the use of supplements of folic acid (FA) in a cohort of pregnant women. We also explored the factors associated with non-compliance of both the recommended intake (RI) of 600&amp;#956;g/day and the supplement use of 400&amp;#956;g/day provided to prevent neural tube defects (NTD). Pacients and methods: We studied 782 pregnant women from the INMA-Valencia cohort. The dietary intake was estimated using a food frequency questionnaire in two periods of pregnancy; from preconception to the second month and from the 3rd to the 7th month. Information on supplement use was also collected which allowed us to estimate the total FA intake (diet+supplements). We explored factors associated with non-compliance of the recommendations by logistic regression. Results: The periconceptional mean daily FA intake was 304&amp;#956;g/day. FA supplements were taken by 19.2, 30.2 and 66.2% of women in preconception, first and second month of pregnancy, respectively. Among women using supplements in periconception, 30% exceeded the tolerable upper intake level (UL) of 1.000&amp;#956;g/day. Non-compliance with RI was more common among women of foreign origin, of low educational level, who smoked, with unplanned pregnancy, who did not visit a private gynaecologist, who had had children or without previous medical illness. Conclusions: Diet by itself is not sufficient to reach RI for FA during pregnanc and many women initiate supplement use after the recommended period and inadequately. The youngest women, with lowest educational attainment and unplanned pregnancies are more likely not to comply (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García de La Hera, Manuela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giménez Monzó, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iñiguez, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarrete Muñoz, Eva María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Climent, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rebagliato, Marisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramón, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vioque, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murcia, Mario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballester, Ferrán</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivos: Analizar la ingesta dietética y de suplementos de ácido fólico (AF) durante el embarazo y los factores asociados al incumplimiento de la ingesta recomendada (IR) de 600&amp;#956;g/d y al incumplimiento de 400&amp;#956;g/d de suplementos para prevenir los defectos del tubo neural. Pacientes y método: Se incluyeron a 782 embarazadas de la cohorte INMA-Valencia. La ingesta dietética se estimó mediante un cuestionario de frecuencia alimentaria en 2 períodos de embarazo, desde preconcepción al mes 2 y desde el mes 3&#150;7. También se recogió información de la suplementación y se estimó la ingesta total de AF (dieta+suplementos). Usando regresión logística múltiple se exploraron los factores asociados al incumplimiento de las recomendaciones. Resultados: La ingesta dietética media periconcepcional de AF fue de 304&amp;#956;g/d. Un 19,2%, 30,2% y 66,2% de embarazadas tomaron suplementos de AF en preconcepción, primer y segundo mes, respectivamente. Por otra parte, alrededor del 30% de las mujeres que tomaban suplementos de AF en periconcepción superó el límite superior tolerable de 1.000&amp;#956;g/d. El ser no española, de bajo nivel de estudios, fumadora, no planificar el embarazo, no haber visitado a ginecólogo privado, haber tenido hijos y no haber tenido antecedentes médicos previos, se asoció al incumplimiento de la IR. Conclusiones:  La dieta sola es insuficiente para alcanzar las IR de AF, puesto que la suplementación se hace tarde y mal. La situación se agrava en mujeres jóvenes, de menor nivel educativo y embarazo no planificado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);135(14): 637-643, nov. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83689</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ingesta dietética y de suplementos de ácido fólico en mujeres embarazadas de Valencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33546</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5631^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5631^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52506</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5629^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9629^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5629^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201011</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
