<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043165</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tensión free monofilament polypropylene mesh in cystocele and rectocele concomitant repair</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: We presented our experience in the concomitant correction of cystocele and rectocele with polypropylene monofilament mesh (Gynemesh PS), with transvaginal free tension technique. Method: During 2004 correction was made in 7 patients, Urogynecologic and Vaginal Surgery Unit of Gynecology and Obstetrics Department, Las Condes Clinic. Medium age 54 years old, weight 64 kgs. In four patients we used a third mesh for correction of urinary incontinence by TVT-O. Results: They don&#146;t present intraoperative complications, neither in immediate or delayed postoperative time. We not observed hematoma, infection, erosion or exposition mesh. Cure of cystocele and rectocele was in the 100% of patients. Complications have not appeared, 4 cases completed three months of observation, 2 cases two months and 1 case one month. Discussion: The use of protesic polypropylene multifilament macropore mesh in the concomitant correction of cistocele and rectocele, by transvaginal route with tension free technique seems to be a safe and effective surgery procedure (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pardo Schanz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solá Dalenz, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ricci Arriola, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guiloff Fische, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Presentamos nuestra experiencia en la corrección de cistocele y rectocele concomitante, con malla de polipropileno monofilamento (Gynemesh PS), con técnica libre de tensión transvaginal. Método: Entre noviembre 2004 y enero 2005 se realizó corrección 7 pacientes, de la Unidad de Uroginecología y Cirugía Vaginal del Departamento de Ginecología y Obstetricia, de la Clínica Las Condes. Mediana de edad 54 años, peso 64 kg. En cuatro pacientes además se asoció una tercera malla para corrección de incontinencia de orina de esfuerzo, con técnica de TVT-O. Resultado: No se presentaron complicaciones intraoperatorias, ni en el postoperatorio inmediato ni tardío. No se observó hematoma, infección, ni exposición de la malla. Se obtuvo curación del cistoceley del rectocele en el 100% de las pacientes. No se han presentado a la fecha actual, completando3 meses de observación 4 casos, 2 meses 2 casos, y 1 mes un caso. Discusión: La utilización de mallas protésicas, de polipropileno monofilamento con macroporo en la corrección concomitante del cistocele y del rectocele, por vía transvaginal, con técnica libre de tensión, parece ser un procedimiento seguro y eficaz (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;29(10): 977-980, nov.-dic. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043165</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Malla de polipropileno monofilamento libre de tensión en la reparación concomitante de cistocele y rectocele</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1770^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33761^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14950^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13907^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
