<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049979</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Drugs, plants, toxins, diseases and breastfeeding: ana aid in Spanish on the Internet</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The benefits of breast feedingf or the infant, the mother, the family, the health care system and society in general are well documented in numerous scientific publications. The medical advice for weaning a child without a justified reason is an act of irresponsibility from an ethical point of view. Moret han 90% of women might need to take some type of medication while breastfeeding their babies at any time, this being a commonly alleged reason for weaning. However, only a few drugs have been shown to represent a real hazard: phenindione, amiodarone, ergot derivatives, antineoplastic agents, iodides and drugs of abuse. Seemingly, only six maternal diseases are considered to contraindicate breast feeding or make it nearly impossible. By exercising common sense, applying basic knowledge of Pharmacology and Pediatrics and using up dated guidelines (e.g. books, journals and web resources), we should be able to adequately advise those lactating mothers who require medication. Therefore, healthcare givers are committed to offering them proper assistance since mothers will ultimately reject misin formation or recommendations based on prejudice so rreleased by the industry, like that contained in the Physician's Desk Reference. A website, www.e-lactancia.org, an easy-touse resource in both Spanish and English, will help us make appropriate decisions concerning more than 1.400 options that a lactating mother may have to confront</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Benlloch Muncharaz, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos Serrano, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beseler Soto, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mengual Sendra, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paricio Talayero, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferriol Camacho, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Palomares, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Landa Rivera, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los beneficios de la lactancia materna, para el niño y la madre, su familia, el sistema sanitario y la sociedad en general, están muy bien documentados en múltiples publicaciones. Suprimir una lactancia sin un motivo de peso es una grave irresponsabilidad desde el punto de vista sanitario. Más del 90% de las mujeres pueden tener que tomar medicamentos o productos de fitoterapia durante el periodo de lactancia, lo que constituye un motivo clásico de cese de la lactancia, pese a no estar demostrado su peligro real más que en un pequeñísimo porcentaje de productos: fenindiona, amiodarona, derivados del ergot, antineoplásicos, y oduros y psicodrogas de abuso. Del mismo modo, sólo 6 enfermedades de la madre contraindican o hacen prácticamente imposible la lactancia. Con sentido común, unos conocimientos básicos de farmacología y pediatría y buenas guías (libros, revistas y páginas web), podemos asesorar a las mujeres que lactan, deben tomar remedios para alguna dolencia o sufren una enfermedad. Las madres huirán de informaciones erróneas, basadas sólo en prejuicios o en el Vademécum. Una página web(www.e-lactancia.org), en español y de sencillo manejo, nos ayudará a tomar decisiones acertadas antemás de 1.400 opciones diferentes implicadas en la lactancia materna</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;64(7): 337-344, jul. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049979</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Medicamentos, plantas, tóxicos, enfermedades y lactancia: una ayuda en español en Internet</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4421</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9082^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
