<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91032</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Lymphangioleiomyomatosis Treatment with Sirolimus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Lymphangioleiomyomatosis (LAM) is a rare lung disease, that predominantly affects young females andgenerally progresses to respiratory failure. There is not sufficient evidence to support the routine useof any treatment in LAM. The only treatment for severe LAM is currently lung transplantation. Activationof mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR) signalling pathway has been observed in LAM. LAM isoften associated with angiomyolipoma in the kidneys. mTOR inhibitor sirolimus reduces angymiolipomavolumes. Some reports have shown improvement in lung function with sirolimus in LAM.We report 3 women with LAM, with a rapid decline in lung function and symptoms and who weretreated with sirolimus (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Acosta, Orlando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casanova, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valenzuela, Claudia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ancochea, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Girón, Rosa María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrón, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La linfangioleiomiomatosis (LAM) es una enfermedad pulmonar rara que afecta a mujeres jóvenes yque suele progresar hacia el fracaso del sistema respiratorio. No existe evidencia científica suficienteque justifique el uso de ningún fármaco en la LAM. El único tratamiento efectivo en los casos graves esel trasplante pulmonar. En la LAM se ha observado una activación de mammalian target of rapamycin(mTOR). La administración de sirolimus, un inhibidor de mTOR, parece reducir los angiomiolipomasrenales que se asocian a la LAM. Además, algunos trabajos sugieren una mejoría de la función pulmonarcon este fármaco. Presentamos tres mujeres con LAM que manifestaron un deterioro clínico y funcionalrespiratorio rápidamente progresivo y que fueron tratadas con sirolimus (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;47(9): 470-472, sept. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91032</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de la linfangioleiomiomatosis con sirolimus</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31329^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31654^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33809^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31329^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31329^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29477</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11807^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33809^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14804^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
