<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112971</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A case of diarrhoea by Clostridium difficile</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present a patient who developed a pseudomembranous colitis due to Clostridium difficile with a prolonged course. The diarrhoea symptoms worsened after two hospitalisations, but there was an improvement with outpatient treatment. The first diagnosis was made in Primary Care. We summarise the preventive measures, and present the severity criteria of this condition, as well as the failure antibiotic treatment with metronidazole and the possible aggravation by the use of other antibiotics in these patients. The patient recovered from the diarrhoea episodes after prolonged treatment. As with this case, the family doctor should note that, sometimes after hospital admissions of frail patients, there may be diarrhoea caused by this microorganism. An early diagnosis, outpatient treatment with appropriate antibiotics, and the implementation of preventive measures can be used in the Primary Care setting (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández Díaz, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos el caso de una paciente que presentó una colitis seudomembranosa por Clostridium difficile con una evolución prolongada, empeoramiento de su cuadro diarreico tras 2 ingresos hospitalarios y mejoría con tratamiento ambulatorio. El primer diagnóstico se realizó en atención primaria. Resumimos las medidas preventivas, exponemos los criterios de gravedad de este cuadro, el fracaso del tratamiento antibiótico con metronidazol y la posibilidad de agravamiento por el uso de otros antibióticos en estos pacientes. Tras un prolongado tratamiento, la paciente logró recuperarse de este proceso diarreico. Con este caso clínico, el médico de familia puede observar que, en ocasiones, tras los ingresos hospitalarios de los pacientes más frágiles, se pueden presentar diarreas producidas por este microorganismo. Un diagnóstico precoz, el tratamiento ambulatorio con los antibióticos adecuados y la puesta en práctica de las medidas preventivas pueden ser utilizadas en el ámbito de atención primaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);39(4): 222-225, mayo-jun. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112971</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Un caso de diarrea por Clostridium difficile</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23504^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5908^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8985^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28890^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5908^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5908^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3041^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29341^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22442^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28890^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5574^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22442^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3994^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22442^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
