<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134024</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Difficulties with the prescription and administration of antibiotics in routine hospital emergency department care: a survey study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To detect the problems hospital emergency room staff have when prescribing and administering antibiotics. Methods. A 14-item questionnaire was designed to assess staff members&#146; knowledge of the importance of starting antibiotic treatment promptly, assigning appropriate dosing intervals, adjusting for renal function, and switching to oral therapy. Agreement with each item was expressed on a 5-point Likert scale. Items with a rate of appropriate response of less than 75% were targeted for specific attention. Results. Two hundred questionnaires were distributed to the staff and 150 were returned completed (response rate,75%). The following items were targeted for attention based on rates of appropriate response of less than 75%: clear medical orders (65%), understanding the implication of early empirical antibiotic therapy on prognosis in serious infections(67%), estimation of the prevalence of renal insufficiency (42%), assumption that a creatinine serum level under&lt; 1.6 mg/dL is safe (33%), use of glomerular filtration rate to adjust dose according to renal function (47%), and an understanding of switching from intravenous to oral treatment (60%).Conclusions. This study revealed the difficulties medical and nursing staff have in prescribing and administering antibiotics in a hospital emergency department. The results can facilitate improvements in antibiotic therapy by pinpointing areas to target for specific training interventions or the design of electronic prescribing aids (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nicolás Ocejo, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monclús Cols, Ester</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Romero, Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Sánchez, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Detectar las barreras con las que se encuentra el personal sanitario en la prescripción y administración de antibióticos en un servicio de urgencias hospitalario (SUH).Método. Se diseñó una encuesta con 14 ítems para valorar el grado de conocimiento de la importancia de la precocidad en el inicio de tratamiento antibiótico, los intervalos de dosificación adecuados, el ajuste a la función renal y la terapia secuencial. Las respuestas a cada ítem fueron cualitativas con 5 categorías. Se consideró que los ítems que obtuvieron una respuesta correcta menor del 75% precisaban de una intervención específica. Resultados. Se recogieron 150 encuestas cumplimentadas de las 200 repartidas entre el personal sanitario (tasa de respuesta del 75%). Los ítems con una respuesta correcta menor del 75% y que por tanto se consideró que requerían de una intervención específica fueron: la claridad en la órdenes médicas (65%), el conocimiento de la implicación del tratamiento antibiótico empírico precoz en el pronóstico de las infecciones graves (67%), la estimación de la prevalencia de la insuficiencia renal (42%), un valor de creatinina sérica inferior a 1,6 mg/dl considerado como seguro(33%), el filtrado glomerular como parámetro que se debe utilizar para ajustar la dosis a la función renal (47%) y el conocimiento de la terapia secuencial (60%).Conclusión. Este estudio permite conocer las dificultades con las que se encuentra el personal sanitario a la hora de prescribir y administrar antibióticos en un SUH y facilita el diseño de estrategias de mejora que incluyan desde formación específica a técnicas de prescripción electrónica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);27(1): 50-54, feb. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134024</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Detección mediante encuesta de las dificultades con las que se encuentra el personal sanitario en la prescripción y administración de antibióticos en la práctica clínica diaria de un servicio de urgencias hospitalario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4422^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11742^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10749^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
