<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107282</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bean or blue rubber bleb nevus syndrome.  Presentation of 6 patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction/Aims. Bean or Blue Rubber Bleb Nevus Syndrome(BRBNS) is an uncommon disease characterized by multifocal venous malformations that predominantly affect the skin, soft tissues and gastrointestinal tract. Our objective is to familiarize the pediatric surgeon with this condition, promoting early diagnosis and seriated surgical treatment as therapeutic options. We have reviewed the diagnosis and treatment of 6 patients treated from 1993 to 2009.  Material and methods. All the patients had a venous malformation (&gt; 10 cm) that acted as a marker. After, characteristic skin lesions appeared as well as chronic anemia due to digestive bleeding associated to hypofibrinogenemia. Age of appearance of the anemic picturevaried from 6 months to 7 years, it being more aggressive the earlier its appearance. The diagnosis of the disease was made by endoscopically. All the patients required transfusion with blood derivatives 5 to 25 times (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miguel, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre Ramos, C.A. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Gutiérrez, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tovar, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrena, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soto, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ros, Z</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción/objetivos. El síndrome de Bean o Blue Rubber BlebNevus Syndrome es una enfermedad poco frecuente caracterizada por malformaciones venosas multifocales que afectan predominantemente a la piel, tejidos blandos y tracto gastroinestinal. Nuestro objetivo es familiarizar al cirujano pediátrico con esta entidad, fomentar el diagnóstico precoz y el tratamiento quirúrgico seriado como opción terapeútica. Revisamos el diagnóstico y tratamiento de seis pacientes tratados desde 1993 a 2009.Material y mótodos. Todos los pacientes presentaron una malformación venosa (&gt; 10 cm) que actuó como marcador. Posteriormente, aparecieron lesiones cutáneas características, así como anemia crónica por sangrado digestivo asociado a hipofibrinogenemia. La edad de aparición del cuadro anémico varía entre los 6 meses y los 7 años siendo más agresivo cuanto más temprano es. El diagnóstico de la enfermedad se realizó por medios endoscópicos. Todos precisaron trasfusión de hemoderivados entre 5 y 25 ocasiones al año. El tratamiento fue multidisciplinar; tasfusiones periódicas en todos los casos, esclerosis endoscópica en lesiones que afectan a colon o a estómago y tratamiento quirúrgico de las del yeyuno e ileon, en dos de estos pacientes extirpando (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;23(4): 241-244, oct. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107282</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Bean o Blue rubber bleb nevus syndrome. Presentación de 6 pacientes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52606^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23785^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52606^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19157^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24871^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6542^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19157^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
