<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-64584</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The recommendations included in this document will be part a series of updated reviews of the literature on respiratory support in the newborn infant. These recommendations are structured into twelve modules, with the first three modules being developed in this work. Each module it is the result of a consensus process amongst all members of the Surfactant and Respiratory Group of the Spanish Society of Neonatology. They represent a summary of the published papers on each specific topic and of the clinical experience of each one of the members of the group. Each module includes a summary of the scientific evidence available, graded into four levels of recommendations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grupo Respiratorio y Surfactante de la Sociedad Española de Neonatología</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las recomendaciones incluidas en este documento forman parte de una revisión actualizada de la asistencia respiratoria en el recién nacido. Están estructuradas en 12 módulos, y en este trabajo se presentan los primeros tres módulos. El contenido de cada módulo es el resultado del consenso de los miembros del Grupo Respiratorio y Surfactante de la Sociedad Española de Neonatología. Representan una síntesis de los trabajos publicados y de la experiencia clínica de cada uno de los miembros del grupo. Cada módulo se acompaña de un resumen de la evidencia científica con cuatro grados de recomendaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);68(5): 516-524, mayo 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-64584</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d12552^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32868^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10269^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12552^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25823</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7601^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200805</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
