<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132311</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Longitudinal study of the evolution (from birth to 8 years of age) of anthropometric variables in a cohort of very low birth weight infants</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Descriptive anthropometric survey in a cohort of very low birth weight infants (VLBWI) newborns from birth to age 8 years, analyzing the growth characteristics in these patients. Material and Methods: Retrospective registration of weight and height at birth and age 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 6 and 8 years in a cohort of 170 VLBWI (&lt; 1500 g). Patients were separated into appropriate for gestational age (AGA, n=101) and low birth weight or small for gestational age (SGA, n=69) according to the charts from Carrascosa  et al. Anthropometric variables were compared with those from a control group. Results: Gestational age was 30.4±3.1 weeks. Weight and height at birth were 1182.1± 228.4 g and 38.2± 3.2 cm, respectively. Weight, height and body mass index in both sexes and every considered age were higher (p&lt;0.05) within the control group with respect to VLBWI (AGA and SGA). At age 2, 81.2% and 71% of AGA and SGA (p&lt;0.05) respectively, presented with normal height. At age 8, the height of 8.95% of AGA and 17.4% of SGA infants did not exceed the 2 SD below the average of the  control group. Conclusions: VLBWI have a catch-up growth which allows the acquisition of normal height in 87.1% and 78.3% of patients in groups AGA and SGA, respectively, at age 4. Only 8.9% of patients in group AGA did not present catch-up growth at age 8, being the possibility (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Durá Travé, TeodoroUniversidad de Navarra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chueca Guindelain, María Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Martín García, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berrade Zubiri, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudio descriptivo antropométrico en una cohorte de recién nacidos de muy bajo peso (RNMBP) desde el nacimiento hasta los 8 años de edad, analizándose las características del crecimiento en estos pacientes. Material y Métodos: Registro retrospectivo del peso y talla al nacimiento y a los 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 6 y 8 años de edad de una cohorte de 170 RNMBP (&lt;1.500g). Se dividieron en recién nacidos con peso adecuado para la edad gestacional (AEG, n=101) y recién nacidos con bajo peso  para la edad gestacional (PEG, n=69), según las tablas de Carrascosa et al. Las variables antropométricas se compararon con un grupo control. Resultados: La edad gestacional era de 30,4±3,1 semanas. El peso y la talla al nacer eran de 1.182,1±228,4 g y de 38,2±3,2 cm, respectivamente. En ambos sexos y en todas las edades consideradas los pesos, tallas e IMC eran superiores (p&lt;0,05) en el grupo control. A los 2 años de edad el 81,2% y el 71% de los AEG y PEG (p&lt;0,05), respectivamente, tenían una talla normal. A los 8 años de edad la talla del 8,9% de AEG y del 17,4% de PEG no habían experimentado un crecimiento recuperador. Conclusiones: Los RNMBP tienen un crecimiento recuperador que permite alcanzar a los 4 años de edad una talla normal al 87,1% y 78,3% de AEG y PEG, respectivamente.  A los 8 años de edad el 8,9% de AEG no presentaban crecimiento recuperador, sin contemplarse laposibilidad de tratamiento con hormona de crecimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;30(5): 1063-1070, nov. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132311</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio evolutivo longitudinal (desde el nacimiento hasta los 8 años) de las variables antropométricas en una cohorte de recién nacidos de muy bajo peso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32719^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201411</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
