<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99920</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Long-term mortality and hospital readmission after acute myocardial infarction: an eight-year follow-up study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. Acute myocardial infarction is responsible for most of the deaths in developed countries and for a very large number of hospital admissions. Specifically in Spain, each year about 140 000 deaths and 5 million hospital stays are due to acute myocardial infarction, corresponding to health care costs reaching 15% of total expenditure. Therefore, this paper presents an exhaustive analysis of acute myocardial infarction and the related prognosis, such as recurrence and mortality. Methods. This observational study was carried out in Spain. Data were obtained using the Hospital Discharge Administrative Database from 2000 through 2007, inclusive. Specifically, 12 096 cases of acute myocardial infarction (8606 women and 3490 men) were reported during this period, with 2395 readmissions for this diagnosis. Readmissions were analyzed for frequency and duration using logistic regression and the Wang survival model. Mortality was analyzed using logistic regression. Results. Readmission rates were 50% for patients younger than 45 years and 38% for those older than 75 years (P&lt;.001). Men were readmitted more frequently than women throughout the follow-up period. Variables related to hospital mortality from acute myocardial infarction were the presence of diabetes, previous ischemic heart disease, and cerebrovascular disease. Conclusions. Mid-term hospital readmissions are highly frequent in acute myocardial infarction survivors. Male sex, previous coronary heart disease, and the number of classical cardiovascular risk factors are the major risk predictors of this readmission. Our results highlight the need for improved medical care during acute myocardial infarction admission, integrated into secondary prevention programs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alegría, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrés, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cordero, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Ortiz, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Magán, Purificación</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luengo, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Magallón Botaya, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casasnovas, José A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. El infarto agudo de miocardio es en los países desarrollados la causa más importante de mortalidad, así como de un gran número de ingresos hospitalarios. Concretamente, en España cada año se producen alrededor de 140.000 muertes y 5 millones de hospitalizaciones a causa de infarto agudo de miocardio, lo cual corresponde a unos costes de asistencia sanitaria que suponen un 15% de los gastos totales. En este artículo se presenta, pues, un análisis exhaustivo del infarto agudo de miocardio y el pronóstico que comporta en cuanto a recurrencia y mortalidad. Métodos. Este estudio observacional se llevó a cabo en España. Los datos se obtuvieron de la Base de Datos Administrativa de Altas Hospitalarias para el periodo comprendido entre 2000 y 2007, ambos inclusive. Concretamente, se registraron 12.096 casos de infarto agudo de miocardio (8.606 mujeres y 3.490 varones) durante ese periodo, con un total de 2.395 reingresos por ese diagnóstico. Se analizó la frecuencia y la duración de los reingresos mediante regresión logística y con el modelo de supervivencia de Wang. La mortalidad se analizó mediante una regresión logística. Resultados. Las tasas de reingreso fueron del 50% en los pacientes de menos de 45 años y del 38% en los de más de 75 años (p&lt;0,001). Los varones reingresaron con mayor frecuencia que las mujeres durante todo el periodo de seguimiento. Las variables relacionadas con la mortalidad hospitalaria por infarto agudo de miocardio fueron diabetes mellitus, antecedentes de cardiopatía isquémica y enfermedad cerebrovascular. Conclusiones. Los reingresos hospitalarios a medio plazo son muy frecuentes en los pacientes que sobreviven a un infarto agudo de miocardio. El sexo masculino, los antecedentes de enfermedad coronaria y el número de factores de riesgo cardiovascular clásicos son factores predictivos importantes del riesgo de reingreso. Nuestros resultados resaltan la necesidad de una mejora de la asistencia médica durante el ingreso por infarto agudo de miocardio, de manera integrada en los programas de prevención secundaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;65(5): 414-420, mayo 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99920</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mortalidad a largo plazo y reingreso hospitalario tras infarto agudo de miocardio: un estudio de seguimiento de ocho años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13915</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53393^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53393^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
