<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81465</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">How do we use hypnotics in primary care?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To describe the use of hypnotics and the consumer profile. Material and methods. A descriptive cross-sectional multicenter study conducted in primary care in a Health Area of Toledo. Population: non-terminal patients &gt;=18 years with prescription of hypnotics in 2007. Results. A hypnotic drug was prescribed to 8.2% of the population in 2007. The most frequent active principle used was lorazepam (58.5%), followed by lormetazepam (13%). We studied 639 patients, 68.2% women with a mean age of 64.2±16.7 years and a median attendance of 29 visits per year (RI 23 consultations/year). A total of 19.4% (SD 3.1) patients took 2 or 3 different active ingredients. Median treatment duration was 78.4 weeks (RI 88.5). According to the clinical records, 26.6% had 2 or more chronic disorders, in 30.9% (SD 3.6). The associated diagnosis (8.4% insomnia, 69.4% depression-anxiety) was stated in 30.9% (SD 3.6), 73.8% (SD 3.4) took drugs with potential interactions with hypnotics, treatment was revised in 15%, 1.9% (SD 1.06) suffered adverse reactions, 4.9% (SD 0.9) had fallen during the treatment, 12.5% (SD 2.3) of treatments exceeded the maximum permitted dose. Conclusions. The consumer of hypnotics in our area is a woman of 64, who lives in rural areas, is a frequent visitor to the doctor, with anxiety and depression and with high risk of drug interactions, who receive chronic treatment with hypnotic drugs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Perales, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acín Gericó, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Aguado, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alejandre Lázaro, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Adán Valero, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Describir la utilización de hipnóticos y el perfil del consumidor. Material y métodos. Estudio descriptivo transversal multicéntrico, realizado en atención primaria del área de salud de Toledo. Población: pacientes &gt;=18 años con prescripción de hipnóticos en el año 2007, no terminales. Resultados. Al 8,2% de la población en 2007 se le prescribió algún hipnótico. El principio activo más frecuente fue el lorazepam (58,5%), seguido de lormetazepam (13%). Hemos estudiado 639 pacientes, 68,2% mujeres, con una edad media de 64,2±16,7 años y una mediana de frecuentación de 29 consultas/año (R.I. 23 consultas/año). El 19,4% (DE 3,1) de los pacientes tomaron 2&#150;3 principios activos distintos. Duración del tratamiento mediana de 78,4 semanas (R.I. 88,5). Según historia clínica: el 26,6% tienen 2 o más patologías crónicas, en el 30,9% (DE 3,6) constaba el diagnóstico asociado (8,4% insomnio, 69,4% depresión-ansiedad), tomaban fármacos con posibles interacciones con los hipnóticos 73,8% (DE 3,4), al 15% se revisa el tratamiento, 1,9% (DE 1,06) sufrieron reacciones adversas, 4,9% (DE 0,9) tuvieron caídas durante el tratamiento, el 12,5% (DE 2,3) de los tratamientos superaban la dosis máxima permitida. Conclusiones. El consumidor de hipnóticos de nuestro área es una mujer de 64 años, que vive en el medio rural, hiperfrecuentadora, con depresión, ansiedad y riesgo elevado de interacciones medicamentosas, que toma el hipnótico de forma crónica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);36(7): 372-376, ago.-sept. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81465</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Cómo utilizamos los hipnóticos en atención primaria?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7170^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7170^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
