<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59960</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of carotid intima-media thickness in familial hypercholesterolemia in childhood</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Familial hypercholesterolemia (FH) is characterized by exposure to severely elevated LDL-cholesterol from birth, which produces lipid deposits, which can be measured by means of intima-media thickness (IMT). Subjects and methods: The IMT and concentrations of cholesterol and its fractions, triglycerides, alipoproteins Apo-A1, Apo-B and endothelial risk factors (homocysteine and high sensitivity protein C ) were determined in 89 patients (44 males) from 2 to 19 years (9.54±3.91 years). IMT was measured by ultrasound using a 12MHz linear array transducer in both carotids to 1cm of the bulb. The IMT mean was compared with age, sex and analytical parameters using multiple regression analysis. Results: The mean values were: IMT 0.334±0.088mm, total cholesterol 273.62±91.93mg/dl, LDL-cholesterol 204.21±86.16mg/dl, LDL/HDL 3.83±1.45, apoprotein A1 134.61±26.49mg/dl, apoprotein B 130.59±40.59mg/dl, homocysteine (median) 7.16mmol/dl, Protein C (median) 0.3mg/l. Using multiple regression analysis, only age was associated with IMT (P=0.049), a mean 0.005mm (95% CI: 0.000¿0.010) being the annual increase: up to 12 years the increase in IMT was 0.002mm/year on (95% CI: &amp;#8722;0.007-0,010) and then from that age it was 0.013mm/year (95% CI: &amp;#8722;0.023-0.049). Conclusions: The measurement of the carotid IMT could become an objective parameter in the evaluation of the FH in childhood. In our study, it is only associated with age, the increase being most marked from 12 years onwards (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Legarda Tamara, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dalmau Serra, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muro Velilla, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vitoria Miñana, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sangüesa Nebot, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: en la hipercolesterolemia familiar (HF), la concentración elevada de colesterol de las lipoproteínas de baja densidad (cLDL) desde el nacimiento produce depósito lipídico en la pared arterial, que puede medirse mediante el grosor del complejo íntima-media (GIM) arterial. Sujetos y métodos: se determinaron el GIM así como las concentraciones de colesterol y sus fracciones, los triglicéridos, la apolipoproteína A-I (apo A-I), la apolipoproteína B (apo B) y los factores de riesgo endotelial (homocisteína y proteína C ultrasensible) en 89 sujetos (44 varones) de 2 a 19 años (9,54±3,91 años). El GIM se midió en ambas carótidas a 1cm del bulbo por método de alta resolución (12MHz). Se comparó el GIM medio con la edad, el sexo y los parámetros analíticos mediante análisis de regresión múltiple. Resultados: los valores medios fueron GIM de 0,334±0,088mm; colesterol total de 273,62±91,93mg/dl; cLDL de 204,21±86,16mg/dl; LDL (lipoproteínas de baja densidad) y lipoproteínas de alta densidad (HDL) de 3,83±1,45mg/dl; apo A de 134,61±26,49mg/dl; apo B de 130,59 ± 40,59mg/dl; homocisteína (mediana) de 7,16mmol/dl, y proteína C reactiva mediana de 0,3mg/l. Según el análisis de regresión múltiple, sólo la edad se asocia al GIM (p=0,049), y su incremento anual es de 0,005mm (intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%: 0,000¿0,010); hasta los 12 años el incremento del GIM es de 0,002mm anuales (IC del 95%: &amp;#8722;0,007-0,010) y desde esa edad el incremento es de 0,013mm anuales (IC del 95%: &amp;#8722;0,023-0,049). Conclusiones: la medida del GIM carotídeo podría incorporarse como parámetro objetivo de valoración de la HF en la infancia. En este estudio sólo se relaciona con la edad; el aumento más marcado es a partir de los 12 años (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);70(4): 349-353, abr. 2009. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59960</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación del grosor del complejo íntima-media de la carótida en la hipercolesterolemia familiar durante la infancia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8251^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30469^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2834^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30469^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50504^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2834^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30468^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30468^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7118^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
