<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118530</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The mechanisms leading to the frequent occurrence of referred muscle pain (RP) are largely unknown. It is currently postulated that a chain reaction is activated implicating triggering of an ever-increasing number of afferent neurons and facilitation of the synaptic connection at the level of the spinal cord, causing more distally a distributed RP via convergent efferent pathways. The human interpretation of this phenomenon can be misleading when the tested person positions, after a few seconds, his RP distally from the site of pressure to the distally located RP area. As a result of what we have found in our experimentally induced RP probes, we hypothesize that deep pressure on a myofibrosis will, in the first place, within a few seconds, increase the nociceptive excitability of the afferent sensitive nerves from the RP area to the local spot of pressure on the muscle, which in return will, in the second place, excite the whole dependent RP area. The mechanism for referred muscle pain proposed in this article is linked to the &#145;&#145;prelocal hyper-excitability theory&#146;&#146; or &#145;&#145;barrier-dam theory&#146;&#146;. The afferent sensitive peripheral nerves might be entrapped in local muscle hardenings (barrier-dam) with the consequence of the hyper-excitation of pre-local nerves between the distally referred pain area and the local muscular zone of tenderness. The primary pathogenesis of referred muscle pain is likely to be a peripheral sensitization with additionally a central modulation and not vice versa. Clinical and fundamental studies with experimentally induced RP are nevertheless needed to examine the hypothesis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Farasyn, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuesta-Vargas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los mecanismos que llevan a una alta incidencia del dolor muscular referido (DMR) son en gran medida desconocidos. En la actualidad, se postula que se produce la activacion de una reaccion en cadena que implica el desencadenamiento de la excitacion de neuronas aferentes y la facilitacion de las conexiones sinapticas al nivel de la medula espinal, lo cual produce el DMR distribuido mas distalmente a traves de las vias convergentes eferentes. Como resultado de los hallazgos de nuestros estudios del DMR inducido experimentalmente, se puede plantear la hipotesis de que la presion profunda sobre la zona de miofibrosis incrementara primariamente la excitabilidad nociceptiva de los nervios aferentes sensitivos desde el area de DMR hasta el sitio de la presion local en el musculo en pocos segundos, lo cual a su vez excitara secundariamente el area total dependiente de DMR. El mecanismo propuesto en este articulo para el dolor muscular referido esta ligado a la teoria de la &#147;hiperexcitabilidad pre-local&#148; o la &#147;teoria de barrera-presa&#148;. Los nervios aferentes sensitivos perifericos pueden ser atrapados en los endurecimientos musculares locales (barrera-represa), con la consecuencia de la hiperexcitacion de los nervios pre-locales entre el area distal de dolor referido y la zona local muscular de sensibilidad dolorosa a la presion. La patogenesis primaria del dolor muscular referido puede ser probablemente la sensibilizacion periferica con la modulacion central adicional y no viceversa. Sin embargo, para verificar esta hipotesis, son necesarios estudios fundamentales clinicos con el DMR inducido experimentalmente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;20(6): 301-307, nov.-dic. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118530</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El dolor muscular referido es primariamente de origen periférico: la teoría de &#147;barrera-presa&#148;</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4484^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9324^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9327^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9334^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52114^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23938^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31887^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9401^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9401^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9324^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9401^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
