<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141317</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence and burden of visual impairment in Catalonia, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this work is to determine the prevalence of visual impairment in Catalonia and analyze inequalities in vision. Cross sectional study in the population having &amp;#8805;15 years of age (7,881 men and 8,045 women) based on data from the Encuesta de Salud de Cataluña 2006. Logistic regression models were used to calculate the adjusted odds ratio by age, civil state, level of studies, income and working situation with a confidence interval (CI) of 95%. A 4.7% (CI 95% 4.4-5.0) of the population of Catalonia, a 5.3% of female (CI 95% 4.8-5.8), and 4.1% of men (CI 95% 3.7-4.5) state that they have poor vision. The most unfavourable situations of self-reported poor vision by the Catalan population correspond to the elderly and women with lower levels of both studies and income (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tresserras-Gaju, Ricard</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Subirats, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brugulat-Guiteras, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rius, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guisasola, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este artículo es determinar la prevalencia de defectos visuales en Cataluña y analizar las desigualdades en visión. Estudio transversal en población &amp;#8805; 15 años de edad (7.881 hombres y 8.045 mujeres) a partir de los datos de la Encuesta de Salud de Cataluña de 2006. Se usaron modelos de regresión logística para calcular las odds ratio ajustadas por edad, estado civil, nivel de estudios, nivel de ingresos y situación laboral con un intervalo de confianza (IC) del 95%. El 4,7% (IC del 95%, 4,4-5,0) de la población de Cataluña, el 5,3% (IC del 95%, 4,8-5,8) de las mujeres y el 4,1% (IC del 95%, 3,7-4,5) de los hombres, declara tener mala visión. Las situaciones más desfavorables de mala visión autodeclarada por la población catalana corresponden a los ancianos y las mujeres con menores niveles tanto de estudios como de ingresos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);137(supl.2): 22-26, dic. 2011. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141317</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia y carga de defectos visuales en Cataluña</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15187^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54263</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52890</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
