<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61327</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-7606</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A contribution to the state of knowledge of nowadays Forensic Anthropology in Portugal</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A state of knowledge of nowadays ForensicAnthropology in Portugal is done by means of itscontextualization within the National Institute of ForensicMedicine and its relation with other forensic sciences.Teaching, research on Forensic Anthropology and thepublications that had been done during the last decade arecommented.The type, frequency and profile of forensicanthropology cases in Portugal are discussed. Two casesare briefly presented in order to illustrate the proceduresand methodologies adopted in our country(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cunha, Eugénia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se intenta dar a conocer el panorama actual de laAntropología Forense en Portugal a través de su encuadramientoen el Instituto Nacional de Medicina Legal yde su relación con otras disciplinas forenses. La docencia,el estado actual de las investigaciones sobre AntropologíaForense y las publicaciones que han sido efectuadas en laúltima década son abordados. Se analiza el tipo, frecuenciay perfil de los casos de antropología y se concluye conejemplos de dos casos que ilustran los procedimientos ymetodologías adoptadas en Portugal(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. med. forense;14(53/54): 201-211, jul.-oct. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61327</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Contribución para el conocimiento del desarrollo actual de la Antropología Forense en Portugal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32245^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d896^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1867^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d896^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d896^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13244</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1867^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11613^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32245^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32245^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
