<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122522</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Primary cancellous bone formation around micro-chambered beads</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: The question has been raised whether benign bone defects in patients can be treated with bone forming osteoconductive ceramics achieving primarily a cancellous bone scaffold, which is under load from the beginning Material and methods: Ten reconstructions were performed in 9 patients (6 women and 3 male), with a mean age of 49 (25-65) years, suffering a high variety of epi- and metaphyseal defects, four tibial fractures, two calcaneal fractures, one pathological phalangeal fracture, one chondroma of the distal femur and two open-wedge osteotomies were filled with micro-chambered ceramic beads of 4 and 6 mm in diameter. The mean follow up was 22 (7- 8) months. X-rays and CT-scans formed the basis for the evaluation of the reconstruction of the cancellous bone scaffolds. Results: All cancellous structures were rebuilt, if completely filled with bone-forming elements. If the filling was incomplete, no physiological cancellous bone scaffold resulted. The _-TCP micro-chambered beads were completely reabsorbed or sandwich-like incorporated at the time of evaluation. The HA micro-chambered beads revealed a contrast enhancement and were integrated in the osseous construction of the bone scaffold. Conclusion: Primary cancellous bone formation can be achieved with osteoconductive ceramic micro-chambered beads and can be combined with any osteosynthesis for stable fixation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Draenert, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Draenert, K</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Draenert, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Erler, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pohlemann, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);58(3): 131-137, mayo-jun. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122522</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Formación de hueso esponjoso con esferas microcompartimentales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32333^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1867^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1867^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2553^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9051</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50518^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1873^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
