<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141935</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0620</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of burnout on the health of prison workers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: This study investigates differences in health (Somatic Symptoms, Anxiety / Insomnia, Social Dysfunction and Severe Depression) relating to professional burnout (emotional exhaustion, depersonalization and personal fulfillment) suffered by prison staff, taking into account the workplace where they perform their activities (therapeutic vs. non therapeutic modules). Methods: The participants consisted of 222 workers of both sexes, with ages ranging from 18 to 60 years, working in different prisons in Spain (Educational and Therapeutic Modules, N = 1001; Non Educational and Therapeutic Modules = 121). The tools used were the General Health Questionnaire (GHQ-28) of Goldberg and Hillier (1979) and the burnout Inventory of Maslach and Jackson (1981). A mean comparison was performed using Student&#146;s t test along with a linear regression analysis, differentiating between Educational and Therapeutic Modules and Non Educational and Therapeutic Modules. Results: Significant differences were found between both clusters and predictive values of burnout factors for the different health levels in both prison models were identified. Possible explanations for the findings and the implications for intervention are discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bringas-Molleda, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Fresno, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Díaz, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Muñiz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Cordero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Investigar las diferencias respecto a la salud (Síntomas Somáticos, Ansiedad/Insomnio, Disfunción Social y Depresión Grave) con relación al síndrome de queme profesional &#151;Burnout&#151; (Cansancio Emocional, Despersonalización y Realización Personal) que sufren los funcionarios de prisiones, teniendo en cuenta el lugar de trabajo en que desarrollan su actividad laboral (módulo terapéutico vs No Terapéutico). Metodología: Los participantes han sido 222 trabajadores, de ambos sexos y con un rango de edad entre 18 y 60 años, provenientes de diferentes establecimientos penitenciarios del estado español (Módulos UTE, N= 1001; Módulos No UTE=121). Los instrumentos utilizados han sido el Cuestionario de Salud General (GHQ-28), de Goldberg y Hillier (1979) y el Inventario de Burnout, de Maslach y Jackson (1981). Se realizó un contraste de medias T de Student y un análisis de regresión lineal, diferenciando UTE vs No UTE Resultados: Se ofrecen diferencias significativas entre ambos agrupamientos y se identifican valores predictivos de los factores de burnout sobre los diferentes niveles de salud en ambos modelos penitenciarios. Se discuten las posibles explicaciones para los hallazgos y las implicaciones para la intervención (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. sanid. penit;17(3): 67-73, nov.-dic. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141935</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia del síndrome de burnout en la salud de los trabajadores penitenciarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11765^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11765^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
