<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-68093</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Infant colic is a common problem. Although several treatments have been tested over the years, none have proved to be definitive. A number of novel therapeutic strategies have been proposed in recent years, and anticolic or comfort formulas have appeared in the market. The present report is a systematic review of the dietary treatment of infant colic to provide an update of the available information and to establish the utility of different forms of dietary treatment. Methods: We conducted a systematic review based on electronic databases that entailed searching exclusively for studies classified as randomized, controlled trials involving dietary treatment of infant colic. We analyzed the modifications in the composition of the anticolic formulas, as compared to a standard formula, according to the data provided by the manufacturers of the product. Results: Of the twenty-three clinical trials selected, six modalities of dietary treatment were studied: reduction of lactose, low-allergen diet, fiber-enriched formula, sweetened solutions, probiotics and phytotherapeutic agents. Methodological problems, such as small sample size, high dropout rate and selection bias, were found in a substantial number of the trials analyzed.The elimination of cow&#146;s milk from the diet of bottle-fed infants, administration of phytotherapeutic agents and a low allergen diet in the mother of the breast-fed infant have been found to demonstrate a certain degree of efficacy. Additional studies are needed to verify the utility of other modalities of dietary treatment(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Polo Martín, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero Balanzá, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez de Laviada, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El cólico del lactante es un problema prevalente en el que se han ensayado a lo largo de la historia diversos tratamientos, ninguno de ellos definitivo. En los últimos años se han realizado nuevas propuestas terapéuticas, y han aparecido en el mercado las llamadas fórmulas anticólico o confort (FAC). En el presente trabajo se realiza una revisión estructurada sobre el tratamiento nutricional del cólico del lactante, con el objetivo de integrar la información actual sobre este aspecto y establecer las pruebas existentes sobre la utilidad de distintas modalidades de tratamiento nutricional. Metodología: Revisión sistemática mediante búsqueda bibliográfica electrónica de los ensayos clínicos con diseño aleatorizado y controlado acerca del tratamiento nutricional del cólico del lactante. Análisis de las modificaciones en la composición de las FAC en relación con la fórmula adaptada convencional según los datos proporcionados por los fabricantes del producto. Resultados: Los 23 ensayos clínicos incluidos estudiaron 6modalidades de tratamiento nutricional: disminución de lactosa en la fórmula artificial, dieta hipoalergénica, adición de fibra, administración de soluciones azucaradas, probióticos y preparados fitoterápicos. Una proporción significativa de los trabajos analizados presenta problemas metodológicos, como escaso número de pacientes, alta tasa de pérdidas y sesgos de selección, que dificultan la extrapolación de sus resultados a la práctica clínica. De las distintas intervenciones nutricionales, la exclusión de proteínas de leche de vaca en lactantes con fórmula artificial, la administración de preparados fitoterápicos y la dieta hipoalergénica extensa en la madre del lactante han demostrado tener algún grado de eficacia. Se necesitan estudios adicionales para verificar la eficacia de otras modalidades de tratamiento nutricional(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;66(4): 165-170, abr. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-68093</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27962^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27962^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24212^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38403^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16573^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33510^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33510^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24449^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
