<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056572</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Total enteral nutrition vs. total parenteral nutrition in patients with severe acute pancreatitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to compare the efficacy of early total enteral nutrition    (TEN) vs. total parenteral nutrition (TPN) in patients with severe    acute pancreatitis (SAP).    Methods: a total of 22 consecutive patients with SAP were    randomized to receive TPN (group I) or TEN (group II). SAP was    defined applying APACHE II score, C-reactive protein (CRP) measurements    and/or Balthazar CT scan score. Acute inflammatory    response (CRP, TNF-alpha, IL-6), visceral proteins (pre-albumin, albumin),    complications (systemic inflammatory response syndrome,    multiorgan failure, infections), surgical interventions, length of    hospital stay and mortality were evaluated.    Results: no significant differences were found between the    two groups in the APACHE II score, in CRP, TNF-alpha and IL-6    concentrations or in pre-albumin and albumin levels over the first    10 days. Seven patients in group I and 4 in group II suffered severe    complications. Three patients in group I required surgical intervention.    Length of hospital stay was alike in the two groups. Two    patients from group I died in the course of the hospitalization.    Conclusions: SAP patients with TEN feeding showed a tendency    towards a better outcome than patients receiving TPN</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jáuregui, C. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayala, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aracil, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Busquets, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galter, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gich, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Farré, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cardona, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fort, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: comparar la eficacia de la instauración precoz de    nutrición enteral total (NET) frente a nutrición parenteral total    (NPT) en pacientes con pancreatitis aguda grave (PAG).    Métodos: estudio prospectivo aleatorio. Se incluyeron consecutivamente    22 pacientes con PAG aplicando los criterios APACHE    II, valores de PCR y graduación de Balthazar en la TC. El    grupo I (n = 11) recibió NPT y el grupo II (n = 12) NET. Se valoró    la respuesta inflamatoria (PCR, TNF-alfa, IL-6), las proteínas viscerales    (pre-albúmina, albúmina), la tasa de complicaciones (síndrome    de respuesta inflamatoria sistémica, fallo multiorgánico, infecciones),    las intervenciones quirúrgicas, la estancia hospitalaria y la    mortalidad.    Resultados: no hubo diferencias significativas en los primeros    10 días entre los dos grupos en la evolución de los criterios APACHE    II, en las concentraciones de PCR, TNF-alfa e IL-6 ni tampoco    en los valores de pre-albúmina y albúmina. Siete pacientes del    grupo I presentaron complicaciones graves frente a 4 del grupo II.    Requirieron intervención quirúrgica 3 pacientes del grupo I. La estancia    hospitalaria fue similar en los dos grupos. Dos pacientes del    grupo I fallecieron.    Conclusiones: se ha observado una tendencia a una mejor    evolución de los pacientes con PAG que utilizaron NET frente a    los que utilizaron NPT</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;99(5): 264-269, mayo 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056572</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nutrición enteral total vs. nutrición parenteral total en pacientes con pancreatitis aguda grave</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10382^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30329^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22124^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30324^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29591^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22288^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29472^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
