<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040713</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">1984-2004, twenty years of rights and responsibilities</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We are not to talk about George Orwell and his novel 1984 neither about his character Winston Smith trying to rebel against the "System" to be finally annulated in his soul and his body. We talk here, about a period of twenty years, between the first "Humanization plan" developed by the National Health Service Institute (INSALUD), and the evolution, attempts, stoppages, reinventions and final creation of the present "User Attention Services" (SAU) and of course for the situation of the actual health service user. In most of the institutional projects and strategic plans for the development of modern health services, we always find the same basic line, defined as follows: "Our basic aim is defined by the coverage of all health needs of the population in the frame of a National Public Service, who guarantees the scientific and technical quality of the Service, the citizen satisfaction with it, and an optimal and efficient resources utilization". Finally our "health companies" must adjust to a basic principle of all services companies: to define the real needs of the customers, to have the ability to design the goods and services who match their expectations. And if it is possible to exceed them, for the sake of one reason: they are the reason of our "company"</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cárceles-Guardia, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">No vamos a hablar de George Orwell y, claro está, tampoco de su novela ni de su personaje Winston Smith, que intenta rebelarse para ser finalmente anulado en cuerpo y alma. Hablamos de los veinte años que separan el primer plan de humanización del extinto Instituto Nacional de la Salud (INSALUD) y la evolución, los intentos, parones, reinvención y situación de los servicios de atención al usuario de la sanidad y por ende de los usuarios de la sanidad. En la mayoría de los proyectos institucionales y planes estratégicos encontraremos, en estos o parecidos términos, como su línea básica la definición siguiente: "Nuestros objetivos son cubrir las necesidades de asistencia sanitaria a la población, en un marco de servicio público, asegurando la calidad cientificotécnica, la satisfacción del ciudadano y el aprovechamiento óptimo de los recursos". Además, nuestras empresas sanitarias (que son de servicios), si se ajustan al principio básico de toda "empresa de servicios", tienen el deber de determinar qué quieren sus usuarios. Todo ello para poder diseñar productos y servicios adecuados a sus expectativas y a ser posible que las superen. Por una simple razón: son la razón de nuestra empresa</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;20(6): 295-301, sep. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040713</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Derechos y deberes del paciente, 1984-2004</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24426^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36355^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32094^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
