<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056068</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Current situation of long-term treatment of depression</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Depression is the most common mental illness and the primary cause of disability. Currently, major depression is considered a chronic disorder, with very high lifetime recurrence rates. This article reviews the published literature on long-term treatment of depression, with special emphasis on unresolved issues of long-term treatment such as prevention of relapses and recurrences and optimal duration of maintenance treatment. Current recommendations on the treatment of major depression include three phases: the acute phase (4-8 weeks), where the objective is to achieve remission; the continuation phase, to maintain remission; and the maintenance phase, to prevent possible recurrences. Most of the studies reviewed support antidepressive therapy during continuation and/or maintenance phases, in patients who have responded to acute and/or continuation treatment with antidepressants. Current scientific evidence suggests that the effect of treatment persists for at least two years of maintenance treatment with antidepressants</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vallejo Ruiloba, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La depresión es la más común de las enfermedades mentales y la principal causa de incapacidad. Actualmente se considera que la depresión mayor es un trastorno crónico, con tasas muy elevadas de recurrencia a lo largo de la vida. En el presente artículo se ha realizado una revisión de la literatura publicada sobre el tratamiento a largo plazo de la depresión. Se ha hecho especial hincapié en las cuestiones no resueltas en el tratamiento a largo plazo, la prevención de recaídas y recurrencias y la duración óptima del tratamiento de mantenimiento. Las recomendaciones actuales sobre el tratamiento de la depresión mayor incluyen tres fases: la fase aguda (4-8 semanas), cuyo objetivo es lograr la remisión; la fase de continuación, cuyo objetivo es preservar la remisión, y la fase de mantenimiento, para prevenir las posibles recurrencias. La mayoría de los estudios revisados apoyan el tratamiento con antidepresivos durante las fases de continuación y/o mantenimiento en pacientes que han respondido al tratamiento agudo y/o de continuación con antidepresivos. La evidencia científica actual sugiere que el efecto del tratamiento persiste al menos durante los 2 años de tratamiento de mantenimiento con antidepresivos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;35(5): 285-299, sept.-oct. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056068</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Situación actual del tratamiento a largo plazo de la depresión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30381^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3885^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
