<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165471</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mediterranean diet adherence by patients with primary open angle glaucoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To study the adherence to the Mediterranean diet in patients affected by primary open angle glaucoma (POAG). Materials and methods: An observational study was conducted to assess the adherence to the Mediterranean diet in patients affected by POAG, and who attended the Ophthalmology Department of the Canary Islands University Hospital. The study included completing a 14-item questionnaire validated by the PREDIMED Study, in person or by telephone. Results: A total of 100 questionnaires were completed successfully by 50 males and 50 females. The mean age was 69.58 years for the males and 67.42 years for women. The men had more comorbidities than women (tobacco 14 vs. 3%), arterial hypertension, and diabetes (30 vs. 28%, and 16 vs. 6%, respectively). Adherence to the Mediterranean diet in males, was low in 9 patients (18%), moderate in 37 (74%), and high in 4 (8%) cases. In women adherence was low in 14 patients (28%), moderate in 34 (68%), and high in 2 (6%) cases. The overall adhesion to the Mediterranean diet is low in 23%, moderate in 71% and high in 6% of the cases. Conclusion: Patients who are affected by POAG have moderate adherence to the Mediterranean diet (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Luis, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arteaga-Hernández, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abreu-Reyes, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Mendez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abreu-González, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudiar la adherencia a la dieta mediterránea (dM) en pacientes diagnosticados de glaucoma primario de ángulo abierto (GPAA). Material y métodos: Se realizó un estudio observacional para valorar la adherencia a la dM en los pacientes diagnosticados de GPAA que acuden a la consulta del Servicio de Oftalmología del Complejo Hospitalario Universitario de Canarias. Consistió en la realización de una encuesta -personal o telefónica-, compuesta de 14 ítems validados por el estudio PREDIMED. Resultados: Se encuestó a 100 pacientes, 50 hombres y 50 mujeres. El grupo de los hombres tenía una edad media de 69,58 años y el de las mujeres, de 67,42 años. Los hombres presentaban mayores comorbilidades que las mujeres (tabaco 28 vs. 6%), hipertensión arterial (60 vs. 56%), diabetes (32 vs. 12%). La adherencia a la dM en hombres fue baja en 9 pacientes (18%), moderada en 37 pacientes (74%) y alta en 4 pacientes (8%). En las mujeres la adherencia a la dM fue baja en 14 pacientes (28%), media en 34 pacientes (68%) y alta en 2 pacientes (6%). El total de adherencia a la dM de los pacientes es baja en el 23%, moderada en el 71% y alta en el 6%. Conclusiones: Los pacientes diagnosticados de GPAA en nuestra área de atención sanitaria presentan en su mayoría una adherencia moderada a la dM. El papel del facultativo es importante y debe mejorar, para proporcionar la información adecuada sobre la dM y sus beneficios respecto al GPAA (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;92(8): 353-358, ago. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165471</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adherencia a la dieta mediterránea en pacientes afectos de glaucoma primario de ángulo abierto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d55468</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37653^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28204^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28054^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28053^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
