<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164248</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Global analysis of the readability of the informed consent forms used in public hospitals of Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose. To analyse the readability of informed consent forms (ICF) used in Public Hospitals throughout Spain, with the aim of checking their function of providing comprehensive information to people who are making any health decision no matter where they are in Spain. Material and methods. A descriptive study was performed on a total of 11,339 ICF received from all over Spanish territory, of which 1617 ICF were collected from 4 web pages of Health Portal and the rest (9722) were received through email and/or telephone contact from March 2012 to February 2013. The readability level was studied using the Inflesz tool. A total of 372 ICF were selected and analysed using simple random sampling. The Inflesz scale and the Flesch-Szigriszt index were used to analyse the readability. Results. The readability results showed that 62.4% of the ICF were rated as a &#147;little difficult&#148;, the 23.4% as &#147;normal&#148;, and the 13.4% were rated as &#147;very difficult&#148;. The highest readability means using the Flesch index were scored in Andalusia with a mean of 56.99 (95% CI; 55.42-58.57) and Valencia with a mean of 51.93 (95% CI; 48.4-55.52). The lowest readability means were in Galicia with a mean of 40.77 (95% CI; 9.83-71.71) and Melilla, mean=41.82 (95% CI; 35.5-48.14). Conclusions. The readability level of Spanish informed consent forms must be improved because their scores using readability tools could not be classified in normal scales. Furthermore, there was very wide variability among Spanish ICF, which showed a lack of equity in information access among Spanish citizens (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramirez-Durán, MV</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mariscal-Crespo, MI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coronado-Vázquez, MV</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Analizar la legibilidad de los documentos de consentimiento informado (DCI) empleados en la red de hospitales públicos de España para verificar su intrínseca función de informar de forma comprensible a las personas en situación de decisión sanitaria. Material y métodos. Estudio descriptivo transversal. Se recibieron un total de 11.339 consentimientos informados (DCI) en castellano. De ellos, 1.617 DCI fueron recibidos a través de contacto telefónico y/o email desde marzo del 2012 hasta febrero del 2013. La legibilidad se analizó mediante el instrumento Inflesz. Mediante muestreo aleatorio simple fueron seleccionados y evaluados 372 DCI. Se obtuvieron los índices de legibilidad: escala Inflesz e índice de Flesch-Szigriszt. Resultados. El 62,4% de los DCI se situaban en la escala «algo difícil», el 23,4% en «normal» y el 13,4% en «muy difícil». La media de legibilidad Flesch más alta residía en Andalucía (=56,9) y Valencia (=51,9). Las CC. AA. con menor media de legibilidad Flesch eran: Galicia (=40,7) y Melilla (=41,8). Conclusiones. El nivel de legibilidad de los consentimientos informados de España debería mejorarse ya que no poseían puntuaciones clasificables como normales en los índices de legibilidad empleados. Asimismo, existía una gran variabilidad en la legibilidad de los DCI en el territorio español. Este hecho mostró una inequidad en el acceso a la información de los ciudadanos, ya que dependiendo de su lugar de residencia, obtuvieron DCI con mayor o menor nivel de legibilidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;32(4): 200-208, jul.-ago. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164248</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis global de la legibilidad de los documentos de consentimiento informado utilizados en los hospitales públicos de España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6935^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6935^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6935^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28410</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
