<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162936</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cerebral magnetic resonance changes associated with fibromyalgia syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Fibromyalgia syndrome is a chronic disease, of unknown origin, whose diagnostic criteria were established in 1990 by the American College of Rheumatology. New criteria were proposed in 2010 that have not yet been validated. It is characterized by a generalized chronic musculoskeletal pain, accompanied by hyperalgesia and allodynia, as well as other motor, vegetative, cognitive and affective symptoms and signs. We have reviewed a set of studies with cerebral magnetic resonance (morphometry, connectivity and spectroscopy) that refer to changes in areas involved in pain processing. Modifications in gray and white matter volume, as well as in levels of N-acetylaspartate, choline or glutamate, among other metabolites, have been observed in the hippocampus, insula, prefrontal and cingular cortex. Neuroradiological findings are nonspecific and similar to those found in other examples of chronic pain. An increase in the sample size and a standardized methodology would facilitate comparison, allowing the drawing of general conclusions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guillen, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murga, Iñigo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lafuente, José-Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de fibromialgia es un trastorno crónico, de origen desconocido, cuyos criterios diagnósticos estableció en 1990 el Colegio Americano de Reumatología; en 2010 propuso unos criterios nuevos que aún no están validados. Se caracteriza por dolor musculoesquelético generalizado, crónico, acompañado de fenómenos de hiperalgesia y alodinia, así como otros síntomas y signos, motores, vegetativos, cognitivos y afectivos. Revisamos un conjunto de estudios con resonancia magnética cerebral (morfometría, conectividad y espectroscopia) que refieren alteraciones en áreas de procesamiento del dolor. Se observan cambios en el volumen de la sustancia gris y blanca, así como de los niveles de N-acetilaspartato, colina o glutamato, entre otros metabolitos, en hipocampo, ínsula, corteza prefrontal y cingular, principalmente. Los hallazgos neurorradiológicos son inespecíficos y superponibles a los de otros cuadros de dolor crónico, pero un aumento del tamaño muestral y una metodología estandarizada facilitaría la comparación entre series, permitiendo extraer conclusiones generalizables (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);148(11): 511-516, jun. 2017. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162936</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambios en la resonancia magnética cerebral asociados al síndrome de fibromialgia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52519^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54669^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10107</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
