<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167131</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Laparoscopic Choledochoduodenostomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Today's options for biliary bypass procedures, for difficult choledocholithiasis, range from open surgery to laparo-endoscopic hybrid procedures. The aim of this study was to analyze the outcomes of patients with difficult choledocholithiasis treated with laparoscopic choledochoduodenostomy. Methods: We performed a prospective observational study from March 2011 to June 2016. We included patients with difficult common bile duct stones (recurrent or unresolved by ERCP) in which a biliary bypass procedure was required. We performed a laparoscopic bile duct exploration with choledochoduodenostomy and intraoperative cholangioscopy. Results: A total of 19 patients were included. We found female predominance (78.9%), advanced mean age (72.4 ± 12 years) and multiple comorbidities. Most patients with previous episodes of choledocholitiasis or cholangitis, mode 1 (min-max: 1-7). Mean common bile duct diameter 24.9 ± 7mm. Mean operative time 218.5 ± 74min, estimated blood loss 150 (30-600) mL, resume of oral intake 3.2±1 days, postoperative length of stay 4.9 ± 2 days. We found a median of 18 (12-32) months of follow-up. All patients with normalization of liver enzymes during follow-up. One patient presented with sump syndrome and one patient died due to nosocomial pneumonia. Conclusions: Laparoscopic choledochoduodenostomy with intraoperative cholangioscopy seems to be safe and effective treatment for patients with difficult common bile duct stones no resolved by endoscopic procedures. This procedure is a good option for patients with advanced age and multiple comorbidities. We offer all the advantages of minimally invasive surgery to these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rojano-Rodríguez, Martin E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanjuan-Martínez, Carlos A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Portillo, Mucio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuendis-Velázquez, Adolfo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosales-Castañeda, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trejo-Ávila, Mario E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cárdenas-Lailson, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero-Loera, Sujey</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las opciones actuales para realizar procedimientos permanentes de derivación biliodigestiva, secundarios a coledocolitiasis compleja, van desde la cirugía abierta hasta el empleo de procedimientos híbridos laparoendoscópicos. El objetivo del estudio fue realizar un análisis de los resultados obtenidos en pacientes con coledocolitiasis compleja tratados con colédoco-duodeno anastomosis laparoscópica. Métodos: Se realizó un estudio observacional longitudinal en el período comprendido de marzo de 2011 a junio de 2016. Se incluyeron pacientes con coledocolitiasis compleja no resuelta por CPRE o resueltas por CPRE pero con dilatación masiva de vía biliar y evidencia de colestasis persistente, los cuales fueron seleccionados para procedimiento quirúrgico con colédoco-duodeno anastomosis. Resultados: Se incluyeron un total de 19 pacientes. La mayoría mujeres (78,9%), con edad media avanzada (72,4 ± 12 años) y con múltiples comorbilidades. Todos con al menos un episodio (mín-máx: 1-7) de coledocolitiasis o colangitis previos. El diámetro del colédoco fue de 24,9 ± 7mm. El tiempo quirúrgico fue de 218,5 ± 74 min, sangrado de 150 (30-600) mL, inicio de dieta en 3,2 ± 1 días y estancia hospitalaria postoperatoria de 4,9 ± 2 días. Se encontró una mediana de 18 (12-32) meses de seguimiento. Posterior al procedimiento se observó normalización de las pruebas de funcionamiento hepático. Un paciente presentó síndrome del sumidero y un paciente falleció por neumonía nosocomial. Conclusiones: La colédoco-duodeno anastomosis laparoscópica asistida con coledocoscopia representa una técnica segura y eficaz para el tratamiento de pacientes con coledocolitiasis compleja con indicación de derivación biliodigestiva, ofreciendo los beneficios de la cirugía de mínima invasión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);95(7): 397-402, ago.-sept. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167131</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Colédoco-duodeno anastomosis laparoscópica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2813^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38038^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22831^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
