<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050052</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adult progeria (Werner syndrome). Follow-up of 2 cases from primary care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Werner syndrome is a rare autosomal, recessive inherited disease. It is characterized by early aging of the patient that affects multiple organs and systems, having a characteristic appearance. Up to now, about 1300 cases have been documented, most in Japan. In this paper, we report the 10 year follow-up in Primary Care and in successive visits to Specialized Care of 2 brothers affected by this rare syndrome, which was first described in 1904 by the German ophthalmologist Carl Wilhem Otto Werner. We also report the most recent theories that try to explain its etiology</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Acevedo Gragera, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Rojas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salas Campo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de Werner es una rara patología hereditaria, autosómica recesiva, caracterizada por un envejecimiento precoz del paciente, que afecta a múltiples órganos y sistemas, y le confiere un aspecto característico. Hasta ahora están documentados unos 1.300 casos, la mayoría en Japón. Presentamos con este trabajo el seguimiento durante 10 años desde Atención Primaria, así como las sucesivas interconsultas a Atención Especializada, de 2 hermanos afectados por este raro síndrome, descrito por vez primera en 1904 por el oftalmólogo alemán Carl Wilhem Otto Werner, así como las teorías más recientes que tratan de explicar su etiología</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);32(8): 410-414, oct. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050052</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Progeria del adulto (síndrome de Werner). Seguimiento de 2 casos desde Atención Primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15300^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15300^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
