<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79878</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Translation, transcultural adaptation to spanish, to valencian language of the Foot Health Status Questionnaire</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The Foot Health Status Questionnaire (FHSQ) is a foot-specific health-related quality-of-life instrument that evaluates foot pain, foot function capacity, footwear and general foot health. This questionnaire was developed and validated for the English culture and has been used in different foot conditions. Our goal is to present the Spanish version of FHSQ after conducting a cross-cultural adaptation.Materials and methods. We used the translation-back-translation method recommended for cross-cultural adaptation of questionnaires. Several bilingual translators, one with a degree in Spanish Philology and the authors of the work participated. First, the questionnaire was adapted to Spanish and then the procedure was repeated to obtain the Valencian version of the FHSQ. Results. In general, there were no problems in the translation of the questions on the questionnaire, except for that related with the pain domain. Adapting the term &#147;feet ache&#148; as &#147;dolor continuo en los pies&#148; was achieved after the second meeting and thanks to the advice of the author of the original questionnaire. The other items required minimal adjustments. The pilot tests showed good understanding of both the questions and the questionnaire scale descriptors. Conclusions. The method used in the cross-cultural adaptation of the FHSQ questionnaire allows us to confirm the conceptual equivalence of the original version with the Spanish versions obtained in this work. Although the evaluation of its clinimetric characteristics is still pending, the Spanish adaptations presented can be used for clinical research (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sirera-Vercher, m. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáez-Zamora, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz-Amaro, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El Foot Health Status Questionnaire (FHSQ) es un cuestionario de calidad de vida relacionada con la salud específico para el pie, que valora dolor, capacidad funcional, calzado y salud general del pie. Es un instrumento desarrollado y validado para la cultura anglosajona que se ha utilizado en diversas enfermedades del pie. Nuestro objetivo es presentar la versión española del FHSQ tras haber realizado su adaptación transcultural. Material y método. Se utilizó el método de traducción-retrotraducción recomendado para la adaptación transcultural de los cuestionarios. Participaron varios traductores bilingües, una licenciada en Filología Hispánica y los autores del trabajo. En primer lugar se realizó la adaptación al castellano y, posteriormente, se repitió todo el procedimiento para obtener la versión en valenciano del FHSQ. Resultados. La mayoría de las preguntas del cuestionario no plantearon dificultades, salvo las relacionadas con el dominio «dolor». La adaptación del término «feet ache» como «dolor continuo en los pies» se logró después de la segunda reunión y gracias a los consejos del autor del cuestionario original. Para el resto de los ítems se requirieron mínimas adaptaciones. Las pruebas piloto evidenciaron una buena comprensión, tanto de las preguntas como de los descriptores de las escalas del cuestionario. Conclusiones. El método utilizado en la adaptación transcultural del FHSQ permite afirmar la equivalencia conceptual de la versión original con las versiones españolas obtenidas en este trabajo. Aunque queda pendiente la valoración de sus características clinimétricas, las adaptaciones que se presentan pueden ser utilizadas para la investigación clínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);54(4): 211-219, jul.-ago. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79878</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Traducción y adaptación transcultural al castellano y al valenciano del Foot Health Status Questionnaire</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6381^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5670^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5665^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
