<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045252</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interobserver concordance in functional assessment by Barthel index</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. The aim of this study is to analyze interobserver «reproductiveness» between clinical nurses in gerontology and residents in family medicine in their first contact with the Barthel Index (BI). Material and methods. One hundred patients were assessed. BI at two weeks before admission was scored by a patient or carer interview. Eighteen patients were excluded because interviews were not completed. Results. Mean BI of 82 patient included, assessed by nurses was 87.3 and by residents 88.2. In 40 patients some differences in the mean values of BI were observed. When analyzing the overall BI score the agreement was high (r = 0.793), but interobserver agreement was low (kappa &lt; 0.4) in some fields such as eating, dressing and transfers and medium in others (kappa from 0.40 to 0.75). Conclusions. Low reproductiviness interobserver in some patients of the BI when clinical nurses in gerontology and residents in family medicine are compared suggest that they need specific training in functional capacity evaluation in order to improve the BI use</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Formiga, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabot, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mascaro, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pujol, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Porras, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos. El objetivo del estudio es evaluar la reproductividad interobsevador entre enfermeras clínicas expertas en geriatría y médicos residentes en su primer contacto con el índice de Barthel (IB). Material y métodos. Se evaluaron 100 pacientes. El IB, dos semanas previas al ingreso, se recogió mediante entrevista al enfermo o al cuidador principal. Se excluyeron 18 pacientes en que fue imposible la revaloración. Resultados. En los 82 pacientes incluidos la media del IB valorada por la enfermera fue de 87,3 (19) y la del médico residente de 88,2 (21). En 40 pacientes existía alguna diferencia en el valor medio del IB. El acuerdo al examinar el total de la escala era bueno (r = 0,793); no obstante, el acuerdo interobservador era bajo (kappa &lt; 0,4) en los apartados de comer, arreglo y trasferencias. Conclusiones. La baja reproductividad interobsevador en algunos apartados del IB entre enfermeras clínicas expertas en geriatría y médicos residentes en su período de formación en geriatría sugiere la necesidad que tienen éstos de un período de aprendizaje en evaluación de la capacidad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;206(5): 230-232, may. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045252</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Concordancia interobservador en la valoración funcional mediante el índice de Barthel</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24807</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5991^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24693^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28598^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
