<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128692</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Resting State in Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder. A review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD) is a chronic disease that may have a great impact on functionality. The neuroimaging study on OCD has been advancing along with the advance in the technique. Functional neuroimages suggest the participation of the prefrontal cortex and basal ganglia, forming a subcortical cortex system. Study of the resting state is a new radiological technique that makes it possible to see connectivity and activity of the neuronal zones during rest. It has been used in many psychiatric conditions, among them OCD. Objective: To review the studies on resting state in OCD. Method: A systematic search was made in PubMed, Scielo and Liliacs, and 11 works for found for review. Results: OCD would be caused by variations in different brain circuits. The constant perception of error and checking need could be due to an internal hyperconnection in the cingulate cortex. Difficulty to control compulsions could becaused by alterations on the prefrontal cortex level. No alterations per se of the OCD and absences in controls have been found. The differences would be more qualitative than quantitative, the OCD being a deregulation of normal processes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Danke, Ingrid</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toro, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garcia, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León, Tomás</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El trastorno obsesivo compulsivo (TOC)es una enfermedad crónica que puede causar gran impacto en la funcionalidad. El estudio de las neuroimágenes en TOC ha ido avanzando de la mano con el avance de la técnica. Las neuroimágenes funcionales sugieren la participación de la corteza prefrontal y los ganglios basales, formando un sistema córtico subcortical. El estudio del estado de reposo es una nueva técnica radiológica que permite ver la conectividad y actividad de zonas neuronales durante el reposo. Se ha usado en múltiples patologías psiquiátricas, entre ellas TOC. Objetivo: Revisar los estudios de estado de reposo en TOC. Método: Se realizó una búsqueda sistemática en Pub-Med, Scielo y Liliacs, encontrándose 11 trabajos para la revisión. Resultados: TOC sería causado por variaciones en distintos circuitos cerebrales. La percepción constante de error y necesidad de chequeo podría deberse a una hiperconexión interna en la corteza cingulada. La dificultad para el control de las compulsiones podría ser causada por alteraciones a nivel de la corteza prefrontal. No se han encontrado alteraciones propias del TOC y ausentes en controles, las diferencias serían más cualitativas que cuantitativas, siendo el TOC una desregulación de procesos normales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;42(5): 250-258, sept.-oct. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128692</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estado de Reposo (Resting State) en Trastorno Obsesivo Compulsivo. Una revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54669^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12566^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9956^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9956^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9956^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54669^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3224^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3224^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3224^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9956^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
