<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115398</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adolescent psychiatry today</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper analyses the characteristics of current adolescent psychiatry. International classifications (DSM.IV, ICD-10) have a limited utility in adolescence, and in clinical practice we work with the four large classical groups of pathology; adjustment disorder, neurotic disorders, psychotic disorders and personality disorders. Genetic and neurobiological research has not made real progress. However, general progress in the neurosciences has proven compatible with concepts derived from clinical psychodynamics. These concepts configure the field of relational mental health, offering a pathogenic comprehension. The most adequate treatments and approaches, according to the author, are finally exposed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Manzano, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Analizamos un conjunto de aspectos de la psiquiatría de la adolescencia de hoy. Las clasificaciones internacionales (DSM, IV, CIM) se han demostrado poco útiles en la adolescencia. En la práctica trabajamos con los clásicos cuatro grandes grupos de patología: trastornos reactivos, neuróticos; psicóticos y de la organización de la personalidad. La investigación genética y neurobiológica no ha hecho un progreso real. Sin embargo, los progresos generales en neurociencias han demostrado se compatibles con concepciones derivadas de la clínica psicodinámica. Estos conceptos constituyen el campo de la salud mental relacional, ofreciendo una comprensión patogénica. Se describen los tratamientos y las medidas preventivas más adecuadas, según el autor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(19): 29-33, abr. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115398</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La psiquiatría del adolescente hoy</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
