<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101606</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Notes, hybrid notes, notes-assisted kidney surgery: what has been achieved so far?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">With improved technologies and the development of new techniques, has emerged the concept of &#147;scarless surgery&#148; in an attempt to treat certain diseases obviating the need for incisions to access the peritoneal cavity, resulting in direct benefit to patients and assuming an improvement in quality of life and offering an advantage over conventional laparoscopy. Laparoendoscopic single-site surgery (LESS) and natural orifice transluminal endoscopic surgery (NOTES) are evolutions of laparoscopy, and they are complementary techniques that should be included in this new concept. NOTES is an emerging surgical modality that uses endoscopic instruments through hollow viscera to enter the peritoneal cavity and allow surgical procedures without incisions. The NOTES procedure may provide additional benefits when compared with current minimally invasive procedures. Potential advantages include no skin incisions, improved cosmetic result, reduced postoperative pain, diminished risk of postoperative hernias, and earlier recovery. NOTES surgery has still some inconvenient regarding instrumentals, viewing orientation, control of complications. Attempts to overcome the current limitations of the technique have given rise to the concept of hybrid NOTES, which is performed with the assistance of transabdominal ports for the use of conventional laparoscopy equipment. NOTES is a very promising technique although further investigation is necessary until implementing NOTES surgery in the common clinical practice(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Clavijo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sotelo, Rene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcaraz, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribal, María J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Con la mejora de las tecnologías y el desarrollo de nuevas técnicas ha emergido el concepto de cirugía sin cicatriz en un intento de tratar ciertas enfermedades obviando la necesidad de hacer incisiones para acceder a la cavidad peritoneal, resultando en un beneficio directo para los pacientes y asumiendo una mejoría de la cavidad de vida y ofreciendo una ventaja sobre la laparoscopia convencional. La cirugía laparoendoscópica por puerto único (LESS) y la cirugía endoscópica transluminal por orificios naturales (NOTES) son evoluciones de la laparoscopia y son técnicas complementarias que deberían incluirse en este nuevo concepto. NOTES es una modalidad quirúrgica emergente que utiliza instrumentos endoscópicos a través de vísceras huecas para entrar en la cavidad peritoneal y permitir intervenciones quirúrgicas sin incisiones. La operación NOTES puede ofrecer beneficios adicionales cuando se compara con los procedimientos mínimamente invasivos actuales. Las ventajas potenciales incluyen ausencia de incisiones cutáneas, mejores resultados cosméticos, reducción del dolor postoperatorio, disminución del riesgo de hernias postoperatorias y recuperación más temprana. La cirugía NOTES tiene todavía algunos inconvenientes respecto a instrumental, orientación visual y control de complicaciones. Los intentos para superar las limitaciones actuales de la técnica han dado salida al concepto de NOTES híbrido, que se realiza con la asistencia de puertos abdominales para la utilización de equipo laparoscópico convencional. NOTES es una técnica muy prometedora aunque es necesaria investigación adicional hasta implementar la cirugía NOTES en la práctica clínica habitual(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;65(3): 399-406, abr. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101606</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">NOTES, NOTES híbrido, cirugía renal asistida por NOTES: ¿Qué se ha conseguido hasta ahora?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54198^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2947^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54198^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2947^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54198^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6706^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54198^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54198^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
