<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132779</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0952</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Exxenterol, an extract with hypolipidemic activity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Exxenterol is an herbal extract highly concentrated in high molecular weight proanthocyanidins, which has demonstrated its hypocholesterolemic activity in both, preclinical and clinical studies. In preclinical studies, total cholesterol was reduced significantly compared to other fibers. Clinical studies showed that  hypercholesterolemic  subjects  treated  with ExxenterolTM  during  4  weeks  reduced  their  total cholesterol serum levels more than 20%, and their triglycerides  more  than  12%.  ExxenterolTM  resulted  effective  in  both,  subjects  treated  with  other hypolipidemic treatments and subjects without any treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Poza, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintela, José Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuente, Esther de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Exxenterol es un extracto vegetal altamente concentrado en proantocianidinas poliméricas de alto peso  molecular,  cuya  capacidad  hipocolesterolemiante ha sido demostrada en estudios preclínicos y  clínicos.  En  los  estudios  preclínicos  realizados con ratas Exxenterol® mostró una eficacia en la reducción del colesterol significativamente superior a la de otras fibras. Los estudios clínicos realizados revelan que el tratamiento con Exxenterol®  en sujetos con hipercolesterolemia produce una reducción del colesterol total superior al 20% en 4 semanas, y mayor del 12% en el caso de los triglicéridos. Exxenterol fue eficaz tanto en sujetos tratados con hipolipemiantes como en los no tratados, y no se reportaron  efectos  adversos  relacionados  con  el tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. fitoter;8(2): 125-133, jul.-dic. 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132779</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Exxenterol®, un extracto con actividad hipolipemiante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d931^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36845</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14679^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38094^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d963^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23138^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54550^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
