<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110163</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Wikipedia and wikinutrition; key tools for the global promotion of nutrition</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Wikipedia is an encyclopedia collaboratively edited by volunteers from around the world built on the Web since 2003. Today is the sixth most visited site on the Internet, making it the biggest hit of participatory democracy in the field of information dissemination. The English edition, with more than 3 million items, has become an indispensable part of the Internet and the largest and most popular reference work. In this context, it could be argued that Wikipedia is a valuable tool for the general knowledge of the nutritional sciences terminology. At the same time, it does not only facilitate access to knowledge but also can generate it. It also permits to socialize these spaces for collaboration and development, contributing therefore to disclose science to the society. Consequently, in this article we present and discuss the main features of Wikipedia, emphasizing above all its role in food science and nutrition (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gil, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luengo, LM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Wanden-Berghe, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Culebras Fernández, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, MD</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Veiga, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz-Valero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Wikipedia es una enciclopedia editada en colaboración, por voluntarios de todo el mundo, que se ha ido construyendo en la Red desde el año 2003. Actualmente es el sexto sitio más visitado en Internet, lo que la convierte en el mayor éxito de la democracia participativa en el campo de la divulgación de la información. Su edición inglesa, con más de 3 millones de artículos, se ha convertido en una parte indispensable de Internet y la mayor y más popular obra de consulta. En este contexto, se podría afirmar que la Wikipedia se presenta como una valiosa herramienta para el conocimiento general de la terminología sobre las ciencias de la nutrición. A la par, no solo facilita el acceso al conocimiento, sino que es patente su validez para generarlo, socializando este tipo de espacios de colaboración y desarrollo del mismo, contribuyendo, en consecuencia, a la divulgación científica a la sociedad. En consecuencia, en este artículo queremos exponer y discutir las principales características de la Wikipedia. Pero, sobre todo, incidir en su papel en las ciencias de la alimentación y de la nutrición (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;27(5): 1375-1379, sept.-oct. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110163</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Wikipedia y Wikinutrición; herramientas clave para la promoción global de la nutrición</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52458^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52939^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50124</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36354</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
