<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125469</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9626</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The hepatocyte growth factor reduces vascular inflammatory mediators and hypertension in spontaneously hypertensive rats</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: This study was designed to examine the effects of hepatocyte growth factor (HGF)gene delivery on vascular inflammation and hypertension in spontaneously hypertensiverats (SHR). We speculated that HGF deficiency could play a key role in the pathogenesis of hypertension in SHR, and that increasing HGF levels will produce prolonged decreases in blood pressure due to reduced vascular inflammation. Materials and methods: Fifteen-week old male SHRs received weekly hydrodynamic injec tions of a naked plasmid containing human HGF (pCMV-HGF) (1mg/kg) or empty vector(pcDNA3.1) for 6 weeks. Two groups of Wistar-Kyoto (WKY) rats were used as controls (n= 6)and treated in the same manner. The activation of NF-B was assessed by Western blot and mRNA expression of pro-inflammatory cytokines by real-time PCR and Western blot. Results: Blood pressure, NF-B activation and expression of IL-6, MCP-1 and RANTES were significantly higher in SHR than in the control WKY. The HGF gene therapy normalized NF-B activity, pro-inflammatory cytokines expression, and decreased the hypertension in SHR. Conclusion: These observations suggest that decreased aorta HGF concentration may have a role in the vascular inflammation observed in SHR, and demonstrate that increasing HGFis a potential therapeutic target in the treatment of hypertension (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez, Mariela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Talavera, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Alberto J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chávez-Velásquez, Maribel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero-Vásquez, Freddy</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arcaya, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Este estudio fue diseñado para examinar el efecto del HGF sobre la inflamación vascular e hipertensión en ratas SHR. Nosotros especulamos que la disminución vascular del HGF puede desempeñar un papel fundamental en la patogénesis de la hipertensión arterial en SHR, y que el incremento de los niveles de HGF puede producir una disminución en la presión arterial a través de la reducción de la inflamación vascular. Materiales y métodos Se utilizaron SHR de 14 semanas de edad, a las cuales se les administró el gen del HGF humano (1 mg/kg) por vía hidrodinámica (SHR-pCMV-HGF, n = 6) o el vector vacío (SHR-pcDNA3.1, n = 6) por 6 semanas. Los controles fueron WKY (n = 6). La presión arterial sistólica fue medida semanalmente. La activación del factor NF-kB fue evaluada en la fracción nuclear mediante Western blot, la expresión de mediadores proinflamatorios mediante RT-qPCR y Western blot. Resultados La presión arterial, la activación del NF-&amp;#954;B y la expresión de IL-6, MCP-1 y RANTES fueron significativamente más elevadas en SHR que en WKY. La terapia génica con el HGF normalizó la actividad vascular del NF-&amp;#954;B, suprimió la expresión de los mediadores inflamatorios y redujo la HTA. Conclusión Este estudio sugiere que la disminución en la concentración de HGF en la aorta ejerce un papel importante en la activación de mediadores proinflamatorios observados en SHR y sugiere que el HGF puede representar un potencial agente terapéutico en el tratamiento de la HTA (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Inmunología (1987);33(3): 87-95, jul.-sept. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125469</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El factor de crecimiento del hepatocito disminuye la expresión vascular de mediadores inflamatorios y la hipertensión en ratas espontáneamente hipertensas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30701^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3421^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33519</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12352^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32175^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29472^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
