<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048763</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Brain lesions in patient diagnosed of meningitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Streptococcus pneumoniae is responsible for most community acquired bacterial meningitis in adults. During the course of meningitis, the development of a new neurological focality can be a sign of an associated complication such as cerebritis.    Clinical case. We report a case of pneumococcal meningitis in a 40 year old woman who reported blurred vision one week after hospital admission. Ophthalmologic exploration was normal. Brain MR images showed areas of cerebritis.    Conclusion. Cerebritis is a rare complication of penumococcal meningitis. We discuss the differential diagnosis and the utility of the different imaging techniques</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Deltoro, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente Mas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benítez Bermejo, R. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballester Belda, J. E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Streptococcus pneumoniae es responsable de la mayoría de las meningitis adquiridas en la comunidad en los adultos. Durante el curso de una meningitis el desarrollo de una nueva focalidad neurológica puede ser el signo de una complicación asociada como la cerebritis.    Caso clínico. Presentamos el caso de una meningitis neumocócica en una mujer de 40 años que refiró visión borrosa a la semana del ingreso hospitalario. La exploración oftalmológica fue normal. Las imágenes de la resonancia magnética cerebral mostraron áreas de cerebritis.    Conclusión. La cerebritis es una rara complicación de la meningitis neumocócica. Se plantea el diagnóstico diferencial y la utilidad que proporcionan las diferentes técnicas de imagen</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;21(1): 34-36, ene.-feb. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048763</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lesiones cerebrales en paciente con meningitis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8756^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14065^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14065^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15187^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8756^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
