<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99046</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mesenteric ischemia in hemodialysis patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Mesenteric ischaemia is an abdominal pathology with a high mortality rate. Among the population under dialysis treatment it presents some different traits such as non-occlusive mesenteric attacks in most of the cases. Its diagnosis is difficult and it is usually the result of an interdisciplinary collaboration. It is necessary to know better the symptoms of this illness among dialytic patients in order to improve its prognosis. Patients and methods: Eleven haemodialytic patients in our hospital (0.87% per patient-year) have diagnosed with mesenteric ischaemia confirmed by a laparothomy. We will list the main risk factors of this pathology, its symptoms, its evolution, some radiological and laboratory data more pointed out, the surgical findings anf its treatment. Results: Ten patients (91%) had suffer from cardiovascular pathologies, five of them (45%) had suffer an ischaemia cardiopathy. Seven patients (64%) had a spell of arterial hypotension during their haemodialysis session, which preceded mesenteric ischaemia. The reason for consulting a physician was abdominal pain, specially on the right hemiabdomen (64%). The analytical date most frequently observed was leucocytosis (54%). The usual radiologycal tests such as abdominal plain radiography and ecography didn´t give any detailed formation. Ten out of eleven patients (91%) had necrosis on the intestinal wall. The ileum was the most affected intestinal section. Five of the patients presented only a limited damage of the ileum (45%). Two patients (18%) presented an extensive damage in the whole small intestine and part of the right colon. Intestinal resection was the most chosen way of treatment, which was practiced on eight patients (73%). Only three of them (27%) survived the mesenteric ischaemia and were sent to their homes. The key factor of their survival was that they were operated on in less than 8 hours from their arrival at emergency room. Conclusions: Mesenteric ischaemia must be expected among patients under haemodialysis who suffer from abdominal pain, especially if they have had some arterial hypotensive spells during their previous dialytic session. It´s a matter of urgent surgery where not only its diagnosis but also its early surgical treatment can lessen its high morbi-mortality risk (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sardá, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Expósito, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sans, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Picazo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuxart, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La isquemia mesentérica es una patología abdominal con una elevada mortalidad. En la población en diálisis presenta unas características diferentes como la existencia en la mayoría de casos de infarto mesentérico no trombótico. Su diagnóstico resulta difícil y suele ser interdisciplinar. Es necesario conocer mejor las características de esta enfermedad en los pacientes en diálisis para intentar mejorar su pronóstico. Pacientes y métodos: Once pacientes en hemodiálisis de nuestro hospital (0,87% por paciente-año) han sido diagnosticados de isquemia mesentérica confirmada por laparotomía. Describimos los principales factores de riesgo para padecer esta patología, la evolución, la clínica, los datos radiológicos y de laboratorio más destacados, los hallazgos quirúrgicos y su tratamiento. Resultados: Diez pacientes(91%) tenían antecedentes de patología cardiovascular, cinco de ellos (45%) cardiopatía isquémica. Un episodio de hipotensión arterial durante la sesión de hemodiálisis que precedió a la isquemia mesentérica, tuvo lugar en siete enfermos(64%). El dolor abdominal fue el motivo de consulta en diez casos (91%), localizándose de manera más frecuente (64%)en hemiabdomen derecho. La leucocitosis fue el dato analítico más frecuentemente observado (54%). Las pruebas radiológicas convencionales como la radiografía simple de abdomen y la ecografía abdominal no aportaron información específica. Diez de los once pacientes (91%) presentaban necrosis de la pared intestinal. El íleon fue el tramo intestinal más afectado, de manera limitada en 5 casos (45%) y de forma masiva al existir afectación de todo el intestino delgado y gran parte del colon derecho, en dos enfermos (18%). La resección intestinal fue el tratamiento de elección, practicándose en ocho enfermos (73%). Sólo tres pacientes (27%) sobrevivieron a la isquemia mesentérica, pudiendo ser alta hospitalaria. En ellos la intervención quirúrgica fue temprana en menos de 8 horas desde su llegada a urgencias. Conclusiones: La isquemia mesentérica debe sospecharse en los pacientes en hemodiálisis que presenten dolor abdominal más si han presentado algún episodio de hipotensión arterial en la sesión previa de diálisis. Se trata de una urgencia quirúrgica, en la que tanto el diagnóstico como el tratamiento quirúrgico precoz pueden disminuir su elevada morbi-mortalidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;28(2): 198-202, mar.-abr. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99046</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Isquemia mesentérica en pacientes en hemodiálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7678^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7991^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3140^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28919^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7202^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8820^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
