<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85881</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">SERV clinical paractice guidelines: management of retinal vein occlusion</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: A guidelines for the management of retinal vein occlusion is presented. This is necessary because at this moment several therapeutic alternatives have been developed although their role is not yet sufficiently defined.MethodsReview of the literature for evidence published up to date. Relevant literature was identified and the level of evidence graded. Evidence was then assessed for consistency, applicability and clinical impact. The information was contrasted with those guides published in other countries.ResultsTaking into account the different options of treatment that are currently used, several modes of action are suggested. The role of the various complementary examinations are discussed and it is recommended that criteria for the treatment are based on clinical, angiographic, and tomographic findings.ConclusionsAlthough there is no overall consensus, these guidelines promote a good standard of clinical practise and provide an update of the management of retinal vein occlusion(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cabrera, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Ulla, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gili, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saravia, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cervera, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Basauri, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Layana, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abraldes, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nadal, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Propósito: Se presenta una guía de manejo de las oclusiones venosas retinianas. Esto se hace necesario en un momento en el que han aparecido varias alternativas terapéuticas cuyo papel aún no está completamente definido.MétodosSe revisa la literatura publicada hasta el momento identificando los artículos más relevantes, clasificándolos en base al nivel de evidencia.ResultadosTeniendo en cuenta las distintas opciones de tratamiento que existen en la actualidad, se sugieren varias líneas de actuación. Se discute el papel de las exploraciones complementarias y se recomiendan pautas de tratamiento en base a los hallazgos clínicos, angiográficos y tomográficos.Conclusionesaunque no existe un consenso total, esta guía promueve un estándar de buena práctica clínica y proporciona una actualización del manejo de las oclusiones venosas retinianas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;85(9): 294-309, sept. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85881</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Guías de práctica clínica de la SERV: manejo de las oclusiones venosas de la retina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12578^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8204^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8204^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8204^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19336^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28131^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12578^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28131^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28131^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19336^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12578^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19336^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
