<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92627</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patients who suffer from a personality disorder at work</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the working place the relationships between workers are shown, each individual&#146;s subjectivities are expressed, and the decisions made are influenced by personal styles, leadership styles, etc. Everything atwork is &#147;personal.&#148; Individuals with personality disorders are high consumers of medical care due to symptoms with no clear diagnosis, the disorder on numerous occasions converge with another types of psychiatric alterations and it is involved in social complications. For general, psychiatric and labour medicine, most of the times,these are people difficult to manage. Following a line of work in which we analyzed the interaction between mental health and work, the objective of this document is to present the different personality disorders reviewing their characteristics, identification and diagnostic criteria, analyzing their possible expression in the working place, and pointing outsome of the main lines for their assumption and management, both from a labour and clinic standpoint(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mingote Adán, José Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gálvez Herrer, Macarena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Jiménez, Bernardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el lugar de trabajo se hacen patentes las relaciones interpersonales entre los trabajadores, se expresan las subjetividades de cada individuo, se toman decisiones influenciadas por estilos personales, estilos de liderazgo, etc. Todo en el trabajo es &#147;personal&#148;. Los individuos con trastornos de personalidad son altos consumidores de asistencia médica por sintomatología sin diagnóstico claro, el trastorno converge en numerosas ocasiones con otros tipos de alteraciones psiquiátricas y media en complicaciones sociales. Tanto para la medicina general, psiquiátrica, como laboral, se trata en muchas ocasiones de personas de difícil manejo. Siguiendo una línea de trabajo en la que analizamos la interacción entre salud mental y trabajo, el objetivo del presente artículo es realizar una exposición de los diferentes trastornos de la personalidad revisando suscaracterísticas, identificación y criterios diagnósticos, analizando su posible expresión en el lugar de trabajo y señalando alguna de las principales líneas de afrontamiento y manejo, tanto laboral como clínico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;56(220): 226-247, jul.-sept. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92627</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El paciente que padece un trastorno de personalidad en el trabajo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16629</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
