<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111582</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Association between obesity and focal nodular hyperplasia telangiectasia. 24 cases re-evaluation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Focal nodular hyperplasia is not a true neoplasm. It is a regenerative response of hepatocytes to a vascularabnormality.24 cases were re-evaluated and diagnosed at pathologic examination confirmed as focal nodular hyperplasia. Three of the 24 cases were reclassified as inflammatory telangiectatic adenomas with imnumorreactividad against amyloid A. The presence of vascular and sinusoidal dilatation, congestion, peliotic areas with signs of inflammation associated with focal or diffuse immunoreactivity compared to Amyloid are histological signs that indicate the presence of inflammatory (..)  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Perez Rojas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernandez Giron, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vera Sempere, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brisa Estelles, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Artes Martinez, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guarin Corredor, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Huart Peris, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hiperplasia nodular focal no es una verdadera neoplasia. Es una respuesta regenerativa de los hepatocitosa una anomalía vascular. Se reevaluaron 24 casos diagnosticados y confirmados en el estudio anatomopatológico como hiperplasianodular focal. Tres de los 24 casos fueron reclasificados como adenomas inflamatorios telangiectásico, vinculado con antecedentes de síndromes metabolicos y con (..)  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;33(1): 73-78, ene.-abr. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111582</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asociación obesidad e hiperplasia nodular focal (HNF) telangiectásica. Reevaluación de 24 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34199^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5337^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14062^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
