<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107276</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Surgical approach to sialorrhea: A casuistic review and evaluation of grade of satisfaction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Drooling or sialorrhea is the involuntary, passive spillage of saliva from the mouth due to inability to handle oral secretions. The medical, psychosocial and economic impact of drooling is underestimated. Treatment should always involve a multidisciplinary team and can include a medical or surgical approach. Various surgical techniques are used to manage drooling; re-routing of the salivary ducts is one of the preferred methods in more significant situations. Objectives. To analyze retrospectively the group of children submitted to surgical correction of drooling in São Teotónio&#146;s Hospital and evaluate the clinical and caregiver satisfaction outcomes. Material and Methods. We analyse the clinical process of children submitted to surgical correction of drooling. Satisfaction scores (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Resende, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salgado, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliveira, R. S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La sialorrea corresponde a la emisión involuntaria y pasiva de la secreción salivar por la boca, por la incapacidad de contención. El impacto médico, económico y psicosocial de esta condición está subestimado. El enfoque terapéutico deberá, como regla, implicar a un equipo multidisciplinar. Se podrá recurrir a una modalidad terapéutica médica o quirúrgica, siendo en esta última la transposición bilateral de los canales salivares la técnica de elección para las situaciones de mayor gravedad. Objetivos. En este trabajo los autores consideran una revisión casuística de los niños con diagnóstico de sialorrea sometida a la mencionada cirugía en el Hospital de São Teotónio-Viseu y la evaluación (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;23(4): 211-214, oct. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107276</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfoque quirúrgico en la sialorrea:  Revisión casuística y evaluación del grado de satisfacción</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13178^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2587^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2527^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
