<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122206</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychosocial nursing care patient with major burns</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We must consider the patient as a human being from a holistic point of view; that is, not only from a physical point of view, but also from a mental emotional and spiritual perspective (not to be confused with religion). A patient with major burns is seen as a critical patient by the physician, and for him the most important issue is the survival of the patient. It is when the patient is admitted in the Burns Unit when the long and not easy road to recovery begins, in the understanding this is a new way to integrate, feel and ultimately learn to live again. The role of nursing during this journey will be vital. The prompt and better recovery of the patient will largely depend on the link established between nurse and patient, as well as his/her integration in the new life that awaits him. The following topics are developed in this article: &#149; Emotional evolution during his stage in the Burns Unit. &#149; Psychoemotional nursing care (fear, pain, image change, long hospital stay, resources). &#149; Management of the self-protection measures of the nursing staff to maintain its own emotional stability (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peña Lorenzo, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Callejas Herrero, Aurea</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuadrado Rodríguez, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez Sanz, M. Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Debemos considerar al paciente desde el punto de vista holístico, esto es, no sólo desde una perspectiva física, sino también mental, emocional y espiritual (que no ha de confundirse con la religiosidad). Un paciente gran quemado en el lugar del accidente es visto por el profesional que lo atiende como un paciente crítico, y para él lo primordial es su supervivencia. Es al ingresar en la Unidad de Grandes Quemados cuando comienza su largo y no fácil camino hasta su recuperación, entendiendo esta como el inicio en la mayoría de los casos de una nueva manera de integrarse, sentir, percibir y, en definitiva, de aprender de nuevo a vivir. El papel de la enfermería durante esta andadura resultará vital. Del vínculo que se establezca entre la enfermera o el enfermero y el paciente dependerá en gran medida su pronta y mejor recuperación y, por lo tanto, su integración y reinserción en la nueva vida que le espera. En este artículo se desarrollan los siguientes apartados: &#149; Evolución psicoemocional durante su estancia en la unidad (duelo). &#149; Cuidados psicoemocionales de la enfermería (miedos, dolor, cambio de imagen, larga estancia, recursos). &#149; Manejo de las medidas de autoprotección del personal de enfermería para mantener la propia estabilidad psicoemocional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;37(2): 131-36, feb. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122206</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuidados psicosociales de enfermería en el paciente gran quemado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32725^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32725^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32725^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6849^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33140^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6849^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2088^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2088^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
