<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044083</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of diabetes mellitus on the management and prognosis of non-ST-elevation acute coronary syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The presence of diabetes mellitus worsens prognosis in acute coronary syndromes. The aim of our study was to analyze retrospectively the influence of diabetes mellitus on the management and prognosis of patients with non-ST-segment elevation acute coronary syndrome. We compared the baseline clinical characteristics of 273 patients (93 diabetic and 180 non-diabetic) admitted consecutively to our department with the diagnosis of non-ST-segment elevation acute coronary syndrome. In both groups, we assessed the medical treatment given during hospitalization and the use of coronary angiography, percutaneous coronary intervention, and coronary artery bypass grafting. Finally, we determined the incidence of heart failure during hospitalization and mortality at 28 days and 6 months in both groups. Multifactorial analysis revealed that diabetes was an independent risk factor for mortality during the study period. Data from our registry indicate that these findings were not associated with more extensive use of interventions in diabetic patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferrer Hita, Julio J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bethencourt Muñoz, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Rodríguez, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abreu González, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marrero Rodríguez, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García González, Martín J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La diabetes mellitus condiciona un peor pronóstico del síndrome coronario agudo. Presentamos un estudio retrospectivo cuyo objetivo fue analizar la influencia de la presencia de diabetes en el pronóstico y el tratamiento de pacientes con síndrome coronario agudo sin elevación del segmento ST. Se compararon las características clínicas de 273 pacientes (93 pacientes diabéticos frente a 180 no diabéticos) ingresados en nuestro centro con el diagnóstico de síndrome coronario agudo sin elevación del segmento ST. Durante la hospitalización analizamos en ambos grupos el tratamiento médico y la realización de coronariografía, intervencionismo y cirugía coronaria. Finalmente, analizamos la incidencia acumulada de insuficiencia cardiaca intrahospitalaria y la mortalidad a los 28 días y 6 meses en ambos grupos. El análisis multifactorial demostró que la diabetes fue un predictor independiente de mortalidad durante el período de seguimiento. Estos hallazgos no se acompañaron en nuestro registro de un tratamiento más intervencionista en el grupo de pacientes diabéticos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;59(4): 383-386, abr. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044083</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de la diabetes mellitus en el tratamiento y el pronóstico del síndrome coronario agudo sin elevación del segmento ST</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9396^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
