<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125539</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cognitive impairment in patients with coronary disease: Relationship with clinical variables</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: Coronary disease has been associated with cognitive disorders. We studied the presence of dysexecutive mild cognitive impairment in patients scheduled for coronary surgery. Patients and methods: The executive function of 35 patients was evaluated (Trail Making Test). They were classi&amp;#64257;ed into 2 groups: normal performance or cognitive impairment, and we assessed the relationship with others variables (Mann-Whitney, chi-square and multiple regression analysis). Results: The dysexecutive cognitive impairment group (n = 7; 20%) showed greater degree of angina (odds ratio [OR] 1.4, 95% con&amp;#64257;dence interval [95% CI] 1.1-2.6; P = .04), 3-vessels coronary artery disease (OR 1.3, 95% CI 1.08-3.6; P = .04) and body mass index (OR 1.56, 95% CI 1.16-3.65; P = .03) and lower diastolic blood pressure (OR 1.56, 95% CI 1.2-2.98; P = .02), hemoglobin (OR 2.03, 95% CI 1.18-4.05; P = .02) and hematocrit (OR 2.45, 95% CI 1.67-3.99; P &lt; .001); these variables proved to be signi&amp;#64257;cant in the test performance considered as a dependent variable (R2 = 0.62). Conclusions: We found a signi&amp;#64257;cant prevalence of dysexecutive mild cognitive impairment, which was  associated with cardiovascular risk factors. We recommend assessment and monitoring of cognitive performance for probable neurological complications after cardiac surgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Belmonte, Luis M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lara, J. Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Román-Terán, Carlos M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez de Loma, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barbancho, Miguel A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olalla-Mercadé, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos y objetivo: La enfermedad coronaria puede actuar como factor de riesgo cognitivo. Se ha estudiado en pacientes programados para cirugía coronaria la presencia de deterioro cognitivo leve disejecutivo. Pacientes y método: Se ha evaluado en 35 pacientes la función ejecutiva (Trail Making Test). Se clasificaron en grupos con rendimiento normal o con deterioro, estudiándose su relación con otras variables (Mann-Whitney, ji al cuadrado y análisis de regresión múltiple). Resultados: El grupo con deterioro disejecutivo (n = 7; 20%) presentó mayor grado de angina (odds ratio [OR] 1,4, intervalo de confianza del 95% [IC 95%] 1,1-2,6; p = 0,04), enfermedad de 3 vasos (OR 1,3, IC 95% 1,08-3,6; p = 0,04) e índice de masa corporal (OR 1,56, IC 95% 1,16-3,65; p = 0,03), y menor presión arterial diastólica (OR 1,56, IC 95% 1,2-2,98; p = 0,02), hemoglobina (OR 2,03, IC 95% 1,18-4,05; p = 0,02) y hematocrito (OR 2,45, IC 95% 1,67-3,99; p &lt; 0,001); estas variables resultaron significativas del rendimiento en el test como variable dependiente (R2 = 0,62). Conclusiones: Se muestra una importante prevalencia de deterioro cognitivo leve disejecutivo asociado a factores de riesgo cardiovascular. Se recomienda realizar una valoración cognitiva prequirúrgica y un seguimiento posterior por las posibles complicaciones neurológicas posquirúrgicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);143(3): 109-112, ago. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125539</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Deterioro cognitivo en pacientes con enfermedad coronaria: relación con variables clínicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54753^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
