<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036259</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spontaneous pneumomediastinum as a complication of diabetic ketoacidosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Spontaneous pneumomediastinum is a rare condition defined as the presence of gas in the mediastinum not occurring after chest trauma or medical procedures. We present a case of spontaneous pneumomediastinum in a 21-year-old woman who had had type 1 diabetes mellitus since the age of 13 years and who was admitted to hospital with diabetic ketoacidosis. She had interrupted her dosage of insulin in the previous 48 hours. On admission, she was found to have a spontaneous pneumomediastinum, which resolved following correction of the metabolic disturbance. We describe the case and review the pathophysiological mechanisms and prognosis of this infrequent complication of diabetic ketoacidosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pinés, P. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Araujo, J. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luque, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejera, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roa, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, A. I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El neumomediastino espontáneo es una rara condición definida por la presencia de gas en el interior del mediastino, sin la presencia de un traumatismo torácico o intervencionismo médico previo. Se presenta en este artículo un caso de neumomediastino espontáneo en una paciente de 21 años con diagnóstico previo de diabetes mellitus tipo 1 desde los 13 años, que ingresa por cetoacidosis diabética. La paciente había suspendido su tratamiento con insulina en las últimas 48 h. En el momento del ingreso se detecta un neumomediastino espontáneo que se resuelve de manera paralela a la resolución del trastorno metabólico. Se describe el caso clínico, los mecanismos fisiopatológicos y el pronóstico de esta complicación infrecuente de la cetoacidosis diabética (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;52(2): 54-56, feb. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036259</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neumomediastino espontáneo como complicación de la cetoacidosis diabética</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30156^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8646^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8646^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
