<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80621</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-2074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Coeliac disease profi le in Down syndrome patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objective. Individuals with Down syndrome (DS) are a major risk groupfor coeliac disease (CD). The aim of this study is to fi nd differences in the CD profi le inthis group in order to take a different medical approach.Patients and methods. This observational, descriptive and comparative study included 81patients aged under 15 years monitored between January 1999 and December 2008.Patients were divided into two groups, a fi rst group including 28 children with CD and DS,and a second age- and sex-matched group of 53 children with CD and no DS. Retrospectivedata from medical records were analyzed.Results. There were no statistically signifi cant differences in age at diagnosis, clinicalpresentation, symptoms at diagnosis, body measurements, serological markers andhistological data. Members of the DS group were signifi cantly likelier to have no familyhistory of CD or an association with autoimmune thyroiditis. Breastfeeding was initiatedless frequently in the DS group, and the introduction of gluten was signifi cantly delayed.The genetic study showed a signifi cantly high frequency of the DQ8 heterodimer inpatients with SD.Conclusions. The clinical profi le of CD in children with DS appears to be similar to thatfor children without this condition. The risk heterodimer distribution in DS individuals inthis series differs from published data. Some nutritional features in this population couldentail new risk factors that might trigger the onset of CD (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Espín Jaime, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Martínez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pizarro Martín, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Meneses López, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Fernández-Palacios, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez de Terreros Sánchez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El colectivo de personas con síndrome de Down (SD) es uno de los más importantesdentro de los grupos de riesgo de enfermedad celíaca (EC). Nuestro objetivo esencontrar diferencias en el perfi l de la EC en este colectivo que permitan un manejomédico diferente.Pacientes y método. Estudio observacional, descriptivo y comparativo que incluyó a 81pacientes menores de 15 años controlados entre enero de 1999 y diciembre de 2008. Seestablecieron dos grupos; el primero incluyó a 28 niños con EC y SD y el segundo incluyóa 53 niños con EC y sin SD, ajustados por edad y sexo. Se analizaron retrospectivamentelos datos procedentes de las historias clínicas.Resultados. No se encontraron diferencias estadísticamente signifi cativas en cuanto a laedad de diagnóstico, la presentación clínica, la sintomatología al diagnóstico, la somatometría,los marcadores serológicos o los datos histológicos. Se observaron diferenciasestadísticamente signifi cativas en el grupo SD en relación con la ausencia de antecedentesfamiliares de EC y en la asociación con tiroiditis autoinmune. Este grupo inició menosfrecuentemente la lactancia materna y la introducción del gluten fue signifi cativamentemás tardía. El estudio genético mostró una importante frecuencia de heterodímeros DQ8en el grupo de pacientes con SD.Conclusiones. El perfi l clínico de la EC en el niño con SD parece similar al del niño sin estacondición. La distribución de los heterodímeros de riesgo en los individuos con SD denuestra serie difi ere de los datos publicados. Existen peculiaridades nutricionales en estecolectivo que podrían determinar la presencia de nuevos factores de riesgo que precipitenla aparición de una EC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SD, Rev. med. int. Síndr. Down (Ed. castell.);14(1): 3-9, mar. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80621</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfi l de la enfermedad celíaca en los pacientes con síndrome de Down</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29396^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22443^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9584^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2481^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36038^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2481^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36038^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
