<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159132</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Off-label and unlicensed drug use: Results from a pilot study in a pediatric intensive care unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To analyze the prevalence of use of off-label and unlicensed drugs in a pediatric intensive care unit of a University Hospital. Method: An observational, descriptive, prospective six week pilot study in a Pediatric Intensive Care Unit. Hospitalized patients aged between 0 and 18 years were included. Each prescribed drug was evaluated taking into account indication and condition of use, according to the information available on the Summary of Product Characteristics established by the European Medicines Agency. A sequential algorithm was defined allowing drug classification in unlicensed, off-label or approved. Results: Forty-two patients were included. A total of 696 prescriptions, involving 102 different drugs, were analyzed. All patients had at least one off-label prescription, and a median of 8.9 off-label prescriptions was obtained. Of the total prescriptions, 8.6% were unlicensed and 53.9% corresponded to off-label use. The main reason for off-label use was by indication, followed by age and dose. A lineal tendency between off-label drug use and patient age was observed, where off-label use increased as patient age decreased. The drugs most commonly used offlabel were: atropine, etomidate, dipyrone and ranitidine, and unlicensed drugs: spironolactone, sildenafil, acetazolamide and hydrochlorothiazide. Conclusion: Pediatric Intensive Care Units are characterized by a high ratio of off-label and unlicensed prescriptions. The scarce number of studies performed in this specific and complex sub-population added inconveniency to the current lack of data on safety and efficacy for drugs in paediatrics. Performing studies with these characteristics allows us to document practice on paediatric drug utilisation are required (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fuentes-Ríos,  Javier Ezequiel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-López, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manrique-Rodríguez, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Llamazares, y Cecilia M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar el perfil de utilización de medicamentos en situaciones no autorizadas en una unidad de cuidados intensivos pediátricos de un hospital universitario. Métodos: Se realizó un estudio observacional descriptivo prospectivo durante 6 semanas en una unidad de cuidados intensivos pediátricos. Se incluyeron pacientes ingresados con edades entre 0-18 años. Se evaluó cada uno de los medicamentos prescritos, indicación o condición de uso, según la información reflejada en las fichas técnicas autorizadas por la Agencia Europea de Medicamentos. Se definió un algoritmo secuencial para clasificar de manera estandarizada los medicamentos según la condición de prescripción en unlicensed, off-label o aprobado. Resultados: Se incluyeron 42 pacientes, analizándose un total de 696 prescripciones, que implicaron 102 fármacos diferentes. Todos los pacientes tuvieron al menos un tratamiento off-label. El 8,6% del total de tratamientos analizados se utilizaron en condiciones unlicensed y el 53,9% en off-label. El principal motivo de uso off-label fue por indicación, seguido de la edad y dosis. Existe una relación lineal entre frecuencia de uso de medicamentos en condiciones off-label y la edad del paciente, aumentando esta frecuencia según disminuye la edad del paciente. Los medicamentos más utilizados en condiciones off-label fueron: atropina, etomidato, metamizol y ranitidina, y en condiciones unlicensed fueron: espironolactona, sildenafilo, acetazolamida e hidroclorotiazida. Conclusión: La unidad de cuidados intensivos pediátricos se caracteriza por una alto ratio de medicamentos prescritos en condiciones no autorizadas. La realización de estudios de estas características permite documentar la práctica clínica respecto al uso de medicamentos en condiciones distintas a las autorizadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);86(1): 28-36, ene. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159132</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilización de medicamentos en condiciones off-label y unlicensed: resultados de un estudio piloto realizado en una unidad de cuidados intensivos pediátricos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d55468</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27771</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24747^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53391^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24747^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53391^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24747^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24747^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
