<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048879</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship between renal function and bone mineral density in postmenopausal women that undergo bone mass evaluation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">As osteoporosis and renal insufficiency are two prevalent pathologies in the agingpopulation we decided to evaluate retrospectively the renal function (estimatedby formula) in postmenopausal women who came to our Institute for bone massdetermination to establish the relationship between them. Thus, we studied 300postmenopausal women with a mean age of 66.9 ± 6.8 years who had a bonedensitometry performed; we chose total femur bone mineral density (TFBMD) fordefining osteopenia and osteoporosis as this measurement included substantialamounts of both trabecular and cortical bone; osteopenia/osteoporosis was diagnosedusing T score criteria recommended by the WHO. We also measured BMDat the femoral neck. Renal function was estimated by the Cockcroft-Gault formulausing serum creatinine determination. We found osteoporosis in 61 patients(20.3%). Of them, el 81.9% have renal insufficiency (estimated creatinine clearance-ECrC &amp;#8804; 60 ml/min), compared to 54% of 239 women who had normalBMD/osteopenia (p &lt; 0.001). Six of 61 (9.8%) women with osteoporosis had severerenal insufficiency (ECrC &amp;#8804; 36 ml/min) versus 4/239 (1.6%) women withnormal BMD/osteopenia (p = 0.001). Women with osteoporosis were older, andhad a significantly lower weight and ECrC compared to patients without osteoporosis(ECrC 52 ± 11 ml/min vs 59 ± 12 ml/min; p &lt; 0.0001). We found a significantpositive correlation between TFBMD and ECrC (r = 0.389) as well as withweight (r = 0.422) and a negative correlation between age and ECrCE (r = -0.51)and with TFBMD (r = -0.22). In the multiple regression analysis only weight continuedto correlate significantly with TFBMD (Beta = 0.344). When FNBMD wasconsidered as the dependent variable, we found a significantly negative correlationwith age (r = -0.30) and significantly positive correlations with height (r =0.16), weight (r = 0.33) and ECcr (r = 0.39). In the multiple regression analysisonly age (Beta = -0.20) and weight (Beta = 0.20) continued having an independentcorrelation FNBMD. We conclude that our data confirm that there exists asubstantial prevalence of renal insufficiency, even severe, among patients with densitometricosteoporosis that should be kept in mind when one is considering theprescription of medications as bisphosphonates that have renal clearance, so asnot to jeopardize the efficacy and the security of these drugs</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zanchetta, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lombas, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Negri, A. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Ya que la osteoporosis y la insuficiencia renal son dos patologías prevalentes en lapoblación que envejece quisimos evaluar en forma retrospectiva la función renal (estimadapor fórmula) en mujeres postmenopáusicas que concurrían a nuestro Institutopara evaluación de su masa ósea y establecer que tipo de relación existía entre lasmismas. Así estudiamos 300 mujeres postmenopáusicas con una edad promedio de66,9 ± 6,8 años a las que se les efectuó una densitometría ósea de cadera total(DMOCT) y cuello femoral (DMOCF); se diagnosticó osteoporosis sobre la base delos criterios de T score de la OMS. La función renal se estimó por fórmula de Cockcroft-Gault sobre la base de la medición de la creatinina sérica. Encontramos osteoporosisen cadera total en 61 pacientes (20,3%). De ellas, el 81,9% presentó insuficienciarenal (clearance de creatinina estimado &#151;CcrE &amp;#8804; 60 mil/min), contra el 54%de 239 mujeres que presentaron DMO normal u osteopenia (p &lt; 0,001). Seis de 61(9,8%) mujeres con osteoporosis presentaron insuficiencia renal severa (CcrE &amp;#8804; 36ml/min) contra 4/239 (1,6%) mujeres con DMOCT normal u osteopenia (p = 0,001).Las mujeres con osteoporosis fueron más añosas, y tuvieron un peso y un CcrE significativamentemenor que el de las pacientes sin osteoporosis (CcrE 52 ± 11 ml/minvs 59 ± 12 ml/min; p &lt; 0,0001). Encontramos una correlación positiva significativaentre DMOCT y CcrE (r = 0,389) así como con el peso (r = 0,422) y una correlaciónnegativa entre la edad y CcrE (r = -0,51) y con la DMOCT (r = -0,22). En lacorrelación múltiple solo el peso continuó correlacionando en forma significativa conla DMOCT (Beta = 0,344). Cuando se consideró la DMOCF como la variable dependiente,encontramos una correlación negativa significativa con la edad (r = -0,30)y correlaciones significativas positivas con la talla (r = 0,16), con el peso (r = 0,33)y con el CcrE (r = 0,39). En el análisis de correlación múltiple solo la edad (Beta =-0,20) y el peso (Beta = 0,20) continuaron presentando una correlación significativaindependiente con la DMOCF. En conclusión, nuestros datos confirman que existe unasustancial prevalencia de insuficienica renal, incluso severa, entre las pacientes quepresentan osteoporosis densitométrica que debería ser tenida en consideración al decidirla prescripción de medicaciones que como los bisfosfonatos se eliminan por víareal, para no comprender la eficacia o la seguridad de estas drogas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;26(2): 206-211, feb. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048879</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre función renal y densidad mineral ósea en mujeres posmenopáusicas que realizan evaluación de masa ósea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7840^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24543</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31161^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
