<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78222</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perinatal stroke associated with protein-C deficiency</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Stroke is an important cause of mortality and chronic neurological morbidity in children. Perinatal stroke has been defined as a cerebrovascular event occurring between 28 weeks of fetal life and the 28th postnatal day. The most common manifestation of stroke is neonatal seizures but this entity may also be asymptomatic until months after birth when asymmetry of reach and grasp, failure to reach developmental milestones, or postnatal seizures can develop. Improvements in neuroimaging and its availability have increased the diagnosis and awareness of perinatal stroke in newborns and infants with neurological symptoms. Obstetricians are responsible for monitoring pregnancies at high thromboembolic risk, but rarely consider the effect this has on the fetus or newborn. We present the case of a newborn with perinatal stroke associated with protein-C deficiency (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gippini Requeijo, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Virseda de Antonio, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villó Sirerol, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Sánchez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cristóbal García, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los accidentes cerebrovasculares (ACV) son una causa frecuente de mortalidad y morbilidad neurológica crónica en niños. El ACV perinatal se define como aquel que ocurre entre la semana 28 de gestación y los 28 días de vida. Se suele manifestar en forma de convulsiones en las primeras semanas de vida, aunque puede permanecer asintomático hasta meses después del parto, cuando aparecen alteraciones en la lateralidad de la función motora fina, fallo al alcanzar los hitos del desarrollo o convulsiones. Gracias a la mejora de los métodos diagnósticos de imagen, esta patología se ha incluido como diagnóstico diferencial en los recién nacidos con sintomatología neurológica. Los obstetras se encargan del seguimiento de los embarazos de alto riesgo trombótico, pero rara vez tienen en cuenta el efecto de este riesgo en el feto o en el recién nacido. Se presenta un caso de ACV perinatal asociado a déficit de proteína C (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);53(3): 106-111, mar. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78222</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trombosis de la arteria cerebral media en un neonato afectado de déficit de proteína C</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33773^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33773^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33773^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2581^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2581^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34258^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14312^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33773^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14312^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
