<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59419</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endovascular treatment in complex lesions in distal branches: an initial experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Patients with critical ischaemia and diffuse involvement of the distal branches, associated withthe absence of a suitable vein and/or important comorbidities, make up a group with scant possibilities of surgicalrevascularisation. We report our initial experience in the endovascular treatment of this kind of patients. Patients andmethods. Between February 2006 and October 2007, 23 patients with critical ischaemia and complex lesions in distalbranches were treated by means of percutaneous transluminal angioplasty (PTA): 18 males and 5 females, with a meanage of 73 years, 67% of whom were diabetics. The mean length of the segment of artery treated was 7 cm (range: 4-19 cm),mostly obstructions. In four cases more than one distal branch was recanalised (total: 29) and in 15 more proximallesions were also treated. The procedures were carried out in theatre, under local anaesthesia, by vascular surgeons.The Kaplan-Meier method was applied to analyse limb salvage rates. Results. Initial technical success rate was 86.9%. Thelimb salvage rate at 6 and 12 months was 83.33 and 72.92%, respectively. Complications: one distal embolisation. Threedeaths occurred, although they were not related to the procedure. Conclusions. In our initial experience, in patients withscarce possibilities of surgical revascularisation, PTA in complex lesions in the distal branches presents a good rate oflimb salvage, with scant morbidity(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramos-Gallo, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallina-Vázquez, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Salgado, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente-Santiago, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero-Lorenzo, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Fernández, L. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los pacientes con isquemia crítica y afectación difusa de troncos distales, asociado a la ausenciade una vena adecuada y/o comorbilidades importantes, constituyen un grupo con escasas posibilidades de revascularizaciónquirúrgica. Presentamos nuestra experiencia inicial en el tratamiento endovascular de este tipo de pacientes.Pacientes y métodos. Desde febrero de 2006 hasta octubre de 2007, 23 pacientes con isquemia crítica y lesiones complejasde troncos distales fueron tratados mediante angioplastia transluminal percutánea (ATP):18 hombres y 5 mujeres,con una edad media de 73 años, un 67% de los cuales eran diabéticos. Longitud media del segmento arterial tratado,7 cm (rango: 4-19 cm), la mayoría obstrucciones. En cuatro casos se recanalizó más de un tronco distal (total: 29) y en15 se trataron también lesiones más proximales. Los procedimientos se realizaron en quirófano, bajo anestesia local, porcirujanos vasculares. Se aplicó el método de Kaplan-Meier para el análisis de salvamento de la extremidad. Resultados.Éxito técnico inicial del 86,9%. La tasa de salvamento de la extremidad a 6 y 12 meses fue del 83,33 y el 72,92%, respectivamente.Complicaciones: una embolización distal. Hubo tres fallecimientos no relacionados con el procedimiento.Conclusiones. En nuestra experiencia inicial, la ATP en lesiones complejas de troncos distales, de pacientes con escasasposibilidades de revascularización quirúrgica, presenta una buena tasa de salvamento de la extremidad, con escasa morbilidad(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;61(1): 21-27, ene.-feb. 2009. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59419</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento endovascular en lesiones complejas de troncos distales: experiencia inicial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30956</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7678^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14364^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
