<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73141</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bacterial infections in critically ill patients: review of studies published between 2006 and 2008A</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">2008A systematic revision of medical publications between 2006 and 2008 regarding bacterial infectionsthat affect the critical patients was performed.Four subjects were selected: Community-acquired pneumonia, ventilator-associated pneumonia, catheter-related bloodstream infectionand new antimicrobial treatments. When dealing with community-acquired pneumonia and due to the absence of completely reliable standards,it is necessary to follow the locally adapted guidelines of clinical practice, to identify patients related to the health-care system and admit patientsto the ICU in accordance with the criteria. Regarding the etiological diagnosis of ventilator-associated pneumonia, any microbiological informationavailable must be used. Due to the risk of multidrug bacteria, combined empiric therapy should be initiated immediately and then monotherapyadjusted to the antibiogram should be established. Already established measures for mechanical ventilation associated pneumonia and catheter-related bacteriemias, which have been effective, should be implemented.The empirical treatment of catheter-related bacteremia must be directed towards the most probable pathogens according to the puncture site. The most recently sold antibiotics are basicallydirected towards multidrug gram positive resistant bacteria. However, for the treatment of gram negative resistant bacilli, the use of the new antimicrobials must be combined with a new evaluationof the antibiotics that have been used for years and the possibility of choosing different administrationforms(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Olaechea, Pedro M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se ha realizado una revisión de las publicacionesmédicas entre los años 2006 y 2008 sobre infeccionesbacterianas que afectan a los pacientes críticos. Se han seleccionado cuatro temas: neumoníaadquirida en la comunidad, neumonía asociadaa ventilación mecánica, bacteriemia asociadaa catéter y nuevos tratamientos antimicrobia-nos. En neumonía comunitaria se debe seguir las guías de práctica clínica adaptadas localmente, identificar a los pacientes con relacionados con los sistemas sociosanitarios e ingresar a los pacientesen UCI según criterios clínicos, por la ausenciade normativas completamente fiables. Es necesario aprovechar cualquier información microbiológicapara el diagnóstico de neumonía asociada a ventilación mecánica. Ante el riesgo de patógenos multirresistentes, hay que iniciar tratamiento combinado y luego pasar a monoterapiaajustada al antibiograma. Se debe implantar medidas de prevención de neumonía asociada a ventilación mecánica y bacteriemias relacionadas con catéter ya establecidas y que hayan resultado eficaces. El tratamiento empírico de la bacteriemia relacionadacon catéter debe ir dirigido contra los patógenos más probables según el lugar de punción.Los nuevos antibióticos recientemente comercializadosestán dirigidos básicamente hacia bacterias grampositivas resistentes, mientras que para el tratamiento de los bacilos gramnegativos resistentes es necesario combinar el uso de los nuevos antimicrobianos con una nueva valoración de los antibióticos utilizados desde hace años y la posibilidad de elegir distintas formas de administración(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);33(4): 196-206, mayo 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73141</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infecciones bacterianas en el paciente crítico: revisión de los estudios publicados entre 2006 y 2008</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31549^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52093^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31549^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12078^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1447^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1447^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32073^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31549^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d903^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52093^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52093^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200905</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
