<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149761</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidemiology of maxillofacial fractures due to traffic accidents in Medellin (Colombia)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To characterize maxillofacial fractures due to traffic accidents in patients attending the Hospital Universitario San Vicente Fundación (Medellin-Colombia) from 1998 to 2010. Methods: A descriptive study (n =1609) was carried out with information from the medical records of patients meeting the inclusion criteria established by the general objective of the study. The variables consisted of sex, age, year, type and number of fractures, and type of vehicle. A descriptive analysis of the variables was performed and the frequency of fractures due to traffic accidents was calculated according to year and sex. Crude and adjusted odds ratios (aOR) were estimated to establish associations among age, type of vehicle, and the presence of two or more fractures with stratification by sex. Results: The frequency of maxillofacial fractures due to traffic accidents increased in 2007 (men: n=198, women: n=35) and decreased from 2008 to 2010 in both sexes. Fractures were more frequent in persons aged &lt;35 years (80%) and in men (82%). The highest frequency of fractures was observed in motorists. Male users of motorcycles (aOR=1.41; confidence interval 95% [95%CI]: 1.02- 1.94) and bicycles (aOR=1.61; 95%CI: 1.01- 2.56) were more likely to report two or more fractures compared with pedestrians, after adjustment for other variables. Conclusions: Most maxillofacial fractures occurred in men and in motorists. Future studies should analyze other determinants affecting the epidemiology of maxillofacial fractures. Strategies should be designed to improve the use of protective elements and drivers&#146; knowledge and practices (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Levi Duque-Serna, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agudelo-Suárez, Andrés A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Restrepo-Molina, Lucas</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Herrera, Eliana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Caracterizar las fracturas maxilofaciales por accidente de tráfico en pacientes del Hospital Universitario San Vicente Fundación (Medellín-Colombia, 1998-2010). Métodos: Estudio descriptivo (n=1609) con la información de las historias clínicas de los pacientes que cumplieron los criterios de inclusión según el objetivo general. Variables: sexo, edad, año, número de fracturas, tipo de fractura, tipo de vehículo. Análisis descriptivo de las variables y de la frecuencia de las fracturas por accidente de tráfico según año de estudio y sexo. Se calcularon odds ratios crudas y ajustadas (ORa) mediante regresión logística con el fin de establecer asociaciones entre la edad y el tipo de vehículo con la presencia de dos o más fracturas estratificando por sexo. Resultados: Se observa un aumento en la frecuencia de fracturas maxilofaciales por accidente de tráfico en el año 2007 (hombres, n=198; mujeres, n=35), y un descenso en el periodo 2008-2010 para ambos sexos. Las fracturas ocurrieron con más frecuencia en menores de 35 años (80%) y en hombres (82%). La mayor frecuencia de fracturas ocurre en motoristas. Los hombres usuarios de motocicleta (ORa=1,41; intervalo de confianza del 95% [IC95%]: 1,02-1,94) y bicicleta (ORa=1,61; IC95%: 1,01-2,56) tuvieron una mayor probabilidad de presentar dos o más fracturas, en comparación con los peatones, tras ajustar por otras variables. Conclusiones: La mayoría de las fracturas ocurrieron en hombres y en motocicleta. Es necesario explorar otros determinantes que afectan su epidemiología y promover estrategias que permitan mejorar el uso de elementos de protección, así como los conocimientos y las prácticas de los conductores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;29(supl.1): 30-35, sept. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149761</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Epidemiología de las fracturas maxilofaciales por accidente de tráfico en Medellín (Colombia)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19251^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22947^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24517</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8613^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1342^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3137^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
