<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109577</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Curares and timbós, poisons used in the Amazon</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The natives that dwell along the banks of the Orinoco and Amazon rivers have used different poisons from plants for centuries. The study reviews the historical and ethnographic aspects of the use of curares and timbós in the Amazonian region. Development. Curare is prepared by boiling the roots, bark and stalks of different plants belonging to the Loganiaceae (Strychnos) and Menispermaceae families (Chondrodendron, Curarea and Abuta). The curares of the eastern Amazon are extracted from different species of Strychnos that contain quaternary alkaloids, which act by blocking the neuromuscular junction. They are used to hunt wild animals and death comes about due to paralysis of the skeletal muscles. The first  muscles to be paralysed are those of the eyes, nose and neck, and then those in the limbs; the diaphragm is the muscle that takes the longest to become paralysed. The earliest chronicles reporting their use were written by Fernández de  Oviedo, Cristoval de Acuña, Antonio de Ulloa and José Gumilla. La Condamine, Humbolt, Waterton and Schomburgk, among others, carried out a number of different ethnobotanical studies on curare. The ichthyotoxic poisons from plants, which are known as timbós or barbascos, are characterised by their high level of solubility, their fast diffusion and their high rate of activity. At least 70 plant species are used to poison the fish in the tributaries of the Amazon with the aim of  make fishing easier. Sapindaceae, Papilionaceae, Euphorbiaceae and Theophrastaceae contain ichthyotoxic substances,  such as rotenone or saponins. Conclusions. Ethnohistorical and ethnographic accounts show that the Amazonian cultures have a deep understanding of  the toxic properties of curares and timbós (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carod Artal, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los indígenas que habitaban los ríos Orinoco y Amazonas emplearon durante siglos diversos venenos de  origen vegetal. Se revisan los aspectos históricos y etnográficos del uso de curares y timbós en la región amazónica. Desarrollo. El curare se prepara hirviendo las raíces, corteza y tallos de diversas plantas de las familias Loganiaceae (Strychnos) y Menispermaceae (Chondrodendron, Curarea y Abuta). Los curares de la Amazonía oriental proceden de diferentes especies de Strychnos que contienen alcaloides cuaternarios, que actúan como bloqueadores de la unión neuromuscular. Se emplean para cazar animales salvajes y la muerte se produce por parálisis de los músculos esqueléticos. Los primeros músculos que se paralizan son los oculares, cuello y nuca, y después los miembros; el diafragma es el músculo que más tarda en paralizarse. Las primeras crónicas que relataron su uso proceden de Fernández de Oviedo, Cristoval de Acuña, Antonio de Ulloa y José Gumilla. La Condamine, Humboldt, Waterton y Schomburgk, entre otros, llevaron a cabo diversos estudios etnobotánicos sobre el curare. Los venenos ictiotóxicos de origen vegetal, llamados timbós o barbascos, se caracterizan por una gran solubilidad, rápida difusión y elevada actividad. Al menos 70 especies vegetales se emplean para intoxicar los peces en los afluentes del Amazonas y facilitar su pesca. Sapindáceas, papilionáceas, euforbiáceas y teofrastáceas contienen sustancias ictiotóxicas, como rotenona o saponinas. Conclusión. Los relatos etnohistóricos y etnográficos muestran un gran conocimiento de las propiedades tóxicas de los curares y timbós por parte de las culturas amazónicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;55(11): 689-698, dic. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109577</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Curares y timbós, venenos del Amazonas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3493^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37132^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9687^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23138^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11472^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
