<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036242</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Smoking and attitudes to smoking among primary care nurses in Bilbao (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To investigate smoking habits, and knowledge and attitudes related to smoking among nursing professionals in primary care in the area of Bilbao (Basque National Health Service). Method. A descriptive study was performed from December 2003 to February 2004 using a self completed questionnaire in 23 primary health care centres. Of 218 questionnaires sent, 156 (72%) valid responses were obtained. Results. Eighty-nine percent of respondents were female with a mean age of 42 years. Twenty-two percent were regular smokers, 8% smoked occasionally, 33% were former smokers and 37% were non-smokers. Seventy-seven percent of smokers wanted to quit, while 69% had attempted to quit. Forty-eight percent believed they would not smoke in the next 2 years. Ninety-five percent were in favor of making health centers a &#147;No Smoking Area&#148; and 82% were in favor of a smoking ban in all indoor public spaces (among smokers only 60%; p &lt; 0.001). Sixty-four percent asked their patients about smoking and 71% advised them to give up. Twelve percent considered they had sufficient knowledge to carry out smoking cessation programs and 94% showed interest in receiving training. Ninety-nine percent believed that health professionals should not smoke in front of patients and 88% cited &#147;setting a good example&#148; as a reason for quitting. Conclusions. The present study found a low prevalence of smokers and a high rate of former smokers in comparison with other studies performed among health professionals and the general population, but the rates remain higher than in other developed countries. Nurses showed great willingness to give advice to patients and strong interest in training and serving as role models. We believe that greater efforts should be made by management to put smoking cessation programs into practice</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez Pérez, Félix</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Hernández, Maria J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Explorar hábitos, conocimientos y actitudes con respecto al tabaquismo en enfermería de atención primaria de la zona de Bilbao (Osakidetza). Método. Estudio descriptivo mediante cuestionario autocumplimentado realizado entre diciembre de 2003 y febrero de 2004 en 23 centros de salud: 156 (72%) respuestas válidas sobre 218 cuestionarios remitidos. Resultados. El 89% son mujeres, con una media de edad de 42 años. El 22% son fumadores habituales; el 8%, ocasionales; el 33%, ex fumadores, y el 37%, no fumadores. Al 77% le gustaría dejarlo, y el 69% lo ha intentado. El 48% cree que no fumará en 2 años. El 95% es partidario de considerar los centros de salud como &#147;áreas sin humo&#148;, y el 82%, de hacerlo con los lugares públicos cerrados (entre los fumadores, sólo el 60%; p &lt; 0,001). El 64% pregunta a sus pacientes por su hábito, y el 71% aconseja siempre el abandono del tabaco. El 12% cree tener conocimientos suficientes para llevar programas de deshabituación, y el 94% está interesado en formarse. El 99% cree que los profesionales no deberían fumar delante del paciente, y el 88% cita &#147;dar buen ejemplo&#148; como motivo para abandonar el tabaco. Conclusiones. Baja prevalencia de fumadores y alta tasa de ex fumadores en comparación con otros estudios en sanitarios y población general, pero aún lejos de los valores de otros países desarrollados. Gran disposición para aconsejar a los pacientes. Gran interés en formarse y en asumir el papel ejemplar de la enfermería. Creemos que hace falta una mayor implicación de la Administración para aplicar consensos antitabaquismo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);15(3): 156-162, mayo 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036242</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hábito y actitud respecto al tabaco en enfermería de atención primaria de Bilbao</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29815^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
