<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125001</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4008</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparison of CKD-EPI and MDRD-IDMS equations and referrals to specialized care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The new KDIGO 2012 Guidelines recommend CKD-EPI equation as a more accurate estimation of glomerular filtration rate (GFR). A retrospective analysis was performed in order to evaluate the correlation between CKD-EPI and MDRD-IDMS and to calculate the difference in referrals to Specialized Care using both equations. Participants and methods: A concordance study was performed comparing CKD-EPI equation to MDRD-IDMS. The sample consisted of 16,720 requests of patients seen in Primary Care in the referral area of the University Hospital Joan XXIII in Tarragona within a one year period. To calculate the difference in referrals between both equations 8,478 patients were selected from the initial sample. Only laboratory parameters were taken into account (GFR and urine albumin). The analysis used the recommendations from the current chronic kidney disease (CKD) consensus document. The results were also calculated applying the referral criteria from 2008. Results: The study showed a good correlation between both equations (kappa = 0.94, P &lt; .001). The new consensus document involved an increase of 9 referrals (12.7%) using CKD-EPI in comparison to MDRD-IDMS, of which 7 (9.9%) were due to the group of patients older than 80 years. With the application of the old consensus document, using CKD-EPI would have had an increase of 28 referrals (7.4%) compared to using MDRD-IDMS. Conclusions: The CKD-EPI equation leads to a re-classification of CKD affecting clinical practice, the patient and the economy. An increase in the referrals of older patient was observed. In some cases, this reveals the need for applying more accurate equations to estimate GFR for this age group (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guiñón-Muñoz, Leonor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrat-Orúsa, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Veab, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Fornésa, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina-Borrása, Angel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las Guías KDIGO 2012 recomiendan la ecuación CKD-EPI como una estimación más exacta del filtrado glomerular (FG). Realizamos un análisis retrospectivo para evaluar la concordancia entre CKD-EPI y MDRD-IDMS y para calcular el diferencial de derivaciones a Nefrología. Participantes y métodos: Para el estudio de concordancia se analizó una muestra de 16.720 solicitudes de pacientes visitados en Atención Primaria en el área de influencia del Hospital Universitario Joan XXIII de Tarragona durante un año. Para el cálculo del diferencial de derivaciones se seleccionaron 8.478 pacientes. Solo se tuvieron en cuenta parámetros de laboratorio (FG y albuminuria). Se siguieron las recomendaciones del documento de consenso sobre  enfermedad renal crónica (ERC) del 2012 y se compararon con los resultados obtenidos al aplicar el documento de consenso del 2008. Resultados: Las ecuaciones mostraron una buena concordancia a nivel global (kappa = 0,94; p &lt; 0,001). Con la aplicación del nuevo documento de consenso, CKD-EPI supuso un incremento de 9 derivaciones (12,7%) respecto a MDRD-IDMS, siendo 7 (9,9%) atribuibles al grupo de pacientes de edad superior a 80 años. Con la aplicación del antiguo documento de consenso, CKD-EPI hubiese supuesto un aumento de 28 derivaciones (7,4%) respecto a MDRD-IDMS. Conclusiones: La ecuación CKD-EPI conduce a una reclasificación de la ERC que afecta a la práctica clínica, al paciente y a la economía. En los pacientes de mayor edad se observa un aumento de las derivaciones, indicando la necesidad de aplicar en algunos casos ecuaciones de estimación del FG más exactas en este grupo de edad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. lab. clín;7(2): 60-67, abr.-jun. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125001</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de la ecuación CKD-EPI respecto a MDRD-IDMS en la derivación de pacientes a Nefrología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7852^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7849^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
