<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60346</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Centenary of the fontilles sanitorium</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In recognition of the centenary of the Fontilles Sanitorium, we present some details of its history. The article discusses the foundation of the sanitorium by some of the numerous lepers with no health coverage in the region of Valencia, and Alicante in particular. After a difficult period between 1909 and 1932, the sanitorium was seized by the Republican government. After the civil war, it was returned to the board of trustees, who entrusted administrative tasks to the Compañía de Jesús while health care was overseen by the National Health Board. This coexistence was uneasy, and the board of trustees took over again in 1943. We comment on the transition from a sanitorium and colony into a hospital providing health care, research and training, and treatment with sulfones and subsequently other effective drugs. Also discussed are its role in the elimination of leprosy from Spain, admission to the International Federation of Antilepros y Associations in 1969, and its projects in endemic countries, with the ultimate goal of achieving a world free of leprosy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Terencio de las Aguas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Con motivo del Centenario de Fontilles, se exponen las circunstancias históricas de su fundación por los numerosos enfermos sin asistencia en la región valenciana, sobre todo en Alicante. La primera difícil etapa de 1909 hasta 1932 (año en que se produce la incautación por el gobierno de la República), la Guerra Civil y la devolución en 1941 a su propietario, el Patronato, encargando la administración a la Compañía de Jesús y el aspecto sanitario a la Dirección General de Sanidad, coexistencia que no funcionó y en 1943 vuelve a hacerse cargo el Patronato. Se comenta la evolución de la Colonia-Sanatorio hacia un hospital con función asistencial, investigadora y de formación, la aplicación de las sulfonas y posteriormente otros fármacos eficaces para la curación, el importante papel en la eliminación de la lepra en España, el ingreso en la Federación Internacional de Asociaciones de Lucha Contra la Lepra (ILEP) en 1969, los proyectos en países endémicos y la meta final de conseguir un mundo sin lepra (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;100(5): 362-373, jun.-jul. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60346</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Centenario del sanatorio de Fontilles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38889</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6825</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8096^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6917^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d859</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200907</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
