<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046716</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Optic nerve glioma in a case of neurofibromatosis-1 in a child</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Clinical case: The case of a three-year-old patient with neurofibromatosis type I is presented. Ophthalmologic evaluation revealed, by means of magnetic resonance imaging, the presence of a silent glioma in the optic nerve of the left eye. Discussion: Neurofibromatosis-1 can present in multiple ways to the ophthalmologist, with a glioma of the optic nerve being one of the most frequent central nervous system presentations in this illness. Generally the glioma affects the optic chiasm and its course is indolent, with conservative management and close monitoring usually being advised until progression is defined</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mengual-Verdú, E. N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coloma-González, I. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguirre-Balsalobre, F. E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Se presenta el caso de una paciente de tres años de edad con neurofibromatosis tipo 1. La exploración oftalmológica reveló, mediante resonancia nuclear magnética, la presencia de un glioma de curso silente en el nervio óptico del ojo izquierdo.Discusión: La neurofibromatosis-1 produce múltiples manifestaciones en el campo oftalmológico, siendo los gliomas de la vía óptica los tumores del sistema nervioso central más frecuentes en la enfermedad. Por lo general suelen afectar al quiasma y su curso suele ser indolente, aceptándose un tratamiento conservador con seguimiento estrecho hasta que se detecte progresión</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;81(1): 33-36, ene. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046716</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Glioma de nervio óptico en un caso de neurofibromatosis-1 infantil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33347^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34177^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30295^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
