<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125123</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of using an information leaflet in reducing perioperative anxiety and pain in patients undergoing urological surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The preoperative anxiety state is mainly caused by the fear of the circumstances surrounding the intervention. Anxiety causes increased postoperative pain, and a prolonged length of stay in hospital, which directly affect the cost of care. Objective: To evaluate the effects of providing an anaesthesia information leaflet on postoperative anxiety and pain in patients undergoing urological surgery in the Miguel Servet Hospital. Material and methods: A prospective quasi-experimental study of 100 cases, 51 of whom made up the intervention group who received the information leaflet, with the remaining 49 cases being in the control group. The Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale and the visual analogue scale for pain were assessed in both groups, before and after surgery. Results: Of the 100 patients, 72% were male and 28% female, with an average age (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miguel Romeo, M. Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sagardoy Muniesa, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El estado de ansiedad prequirúrgico se debe al miedo a las circunstancias que rodean la intervención. La ansiedad provoca incremento en el dolor postoperatorio, prolongación en los días de estancia hospitalaria que repercuten directamente en los costes de la atención. Objetivo Evaluar los efectos de un tríptico informativo en anestesia sobre la ansiedad y el dolor posquirúrgicos en pacientes sometidos a cirugía urológica en el Hospital Miguel Servet. Material y métodos Estudio prospectivo cuasi experimental de 100 personas; 51 formaron parte del grupo de intervención a los que se les entregó tríptico informativo y otras 49 formaron el grupo control. En ambos grupos se evaluó la ansiedad mediante la Escala Hospitalaria de (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);24(4): 233-240, jul.-ago. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125123</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos del uso de un tríptico informativo en la reducción de la ansiedad y el dolor perioperatorios en pacientes intervenidos de patología urológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13901^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14970^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54247^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13908^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52939^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
