<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85778</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Baltasar Llopis Mínguez (1934-1990). A pioneer in research on bladder cancer and introduction of computing in Urology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To recall the figure of a great Valencian urologist, to emphasize his great personality and humanity, and to draw particular attention to his significant contribution to the study of prognostic factors in urology and estimation of individual oncological risk, as well as to introduction of computing in urology. Method: His work, the testimony of colleagues who treated him, and data obtained from his close relatives, as well as our own personal knowledge, are reviewed. Result. Baltasar Llopis was born in Valencia, and obtained his degree and doctorate in Medicine at the Valencia University. He specialized in urology with Dr. Tramoyeres Cases, for whom he acted as assistant surgeon and with whom he shared work at La Fe Hospital, where he carried out his complete urological activity, since its inception. Dr. Llopis opted for oncological research, with a special focus on urothelial tumors. He pioneered diagnosis of these tumors using tumor markers and the study of prognostic factors to assess the individual risk of relapse and to implement a specific chemotherapeutic treatment, which he introduced in clinical practice at La Fe Hospital. He thus demonstrated the two essential components of his personality, his investigative and human sides. Conclusion:  A multi-faceted person with great skills and intelligence, Dr. Llopis eagerly devoted himself to research aimed at understanding the biological behavior of cancer, particularly urothelial tumors. In the early 80s he pioneered worldwide the development of specific markers, estimations of individual oncological risk, and prognostic factors useful for planning treatment. He was 20 years ahead of the era of predictive nomograms and their clinical introduction. In addition to being a forerunner of computing applications in Urology, he designed a database for registration of superficial bladder tumors, which allowed him to perform statistical and multivariate analyses using multiple regression models to predict the risk of relapse (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López González, P. Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Albacete, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Cerdá, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vera Donoso, C. D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: rememorar la figura de un gran urólogo valenciano, destacar su gran personalidad y humanidad, además de resaltar su importante aportación urológica en el estudio de los factores pronósticos y del cálculo del riesgo oncológico individual, así como introductor de la informática en Urología. Método: repasamos sus trabajos, el testimonio de los compañeros que lo trataron y datos obtenidos de sus familiares directos, además de nuestro conocimiento personal. Resultado: valenciano de nacimiento, licenciado y doctor en Medicina por su Universidad, formado en la especialidad con el Dr. Tramoyeres Cases, de quien fue su ayudante quirúrgico y a quien acompañó en el Hospital de La Fe desde su creación, donde desarrolló toda su actividad urológica. Se decantó por la investigación oncológica, especialmente por el tumor urotelial, en el que fue pionero en el diagnóstico mediante marcadores tumorales, y en el estudio de los factores pronósticos para evaluar el riesgo individual de recidiva y para llevar a cabo un tratamiento quimioterápico específico, los cuales introdujo en la práctica clínica en el Hospital La Fe. Con ello puso de manifiesto las dos vertientes esenciales de su personalidad: la investigadora y la humana. Conclusión: persona polifacética, dotado de grandes aptitudes y una elevada inteligencia, se dedicó con ahínco a la investigación del cáncer para entender su comportamiento biológico, especialmente el del urotelio; pionero mundialmente a principios de los ochenta en el desarrollo de marcadores específicos, de estimaciones de riesgo oncológico individual y de los factores pronósticos para llevar a cabo su tratamiento. Se adelantó en 20 años a la era de los nomogramas predictivos y a su introducción clínica, además de ser un precursor de la aplicación informática en Urología, diseñó una base de datos para el registro del tumor vesical superficial, que le permitió realizar análisis estadísticos y multivariantes con modelos de regresión múltiple para vaticinar el riesgo de recidiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;34(2): 158-164, feb. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85778</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Baltasar Llopis Mínguez (1934-1990). Pionero en la investigación del cáncer vesical y en la introducción de la informática en Urología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29575^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19243^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1704</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
