<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137076</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of neuromuscular blockers in the critical pacient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The use of neuromuscular blockers (NMB) is a frequent practice in Intensive Care Units. However most of the experience with the use of these agents come from the operating room used to deal with patients with different characteristics from those admitted in the ICU. Recent advances on neuromonitoring and the commercialization of newer agents make necessary the update in the management of NMB in the ICU. The NMB agent should be chosen attending to its pharmacokinetics and the physiopathology of the critically ill patient. Those NMB with organ-independent metabolism as well as those with rapid onset of action are the preferred ones for the use in the critically ill patient substituting older depolarizing agents and those whose metabolism is dependent on the liver and/or kidney, organs frequently impaired in the critically ill patients. Neuromuscular blocking in the critically ill patient should be done according to protocols and monitor its effects in order to avoid complications related to its prolonged use (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Anglés, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martrínez-Melgar, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torrado, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sandiumenge, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La utilización de bloqueantes neuromusculares (BNM) es una práctica habitual en las Unidades de Cuidados Intensivos. Sin embargo, la experiencia en el uso de estos agentes en el contexto del paciente crítico es limitada, ya que los conocimientos que poseemos derivan del ámbito anestésico, acostumbrado a tratar con pacientes cuya fisiopatología dista mucho de la del paciente ingresado en las Unidades de Cuidados Intensivos. La salida al mercado de nuevos agentes y los avances en la neuromonitorización obligan a un cambio en la pauta de utilización, monitorización y retirada de los BNM. El fármaco utilizado se debe elegir en función de las características fisiopatológicas del paciente y la farmacocinética del BNM. Los agentes de metabolismo órgano-independiente y aquéllos de inicio de acción rápida se perfilan como los más adecuados en el paciente crítico, sustituyendo a los agentes despolarizantes o a aquéllos metabolizados por el hígado y/o el riñón, a menudo con función alterada en estos pacientes. El bloqueo neuromuscular en el paciente crítico debería hacerse de forma protocolizada y con la adecuada monitorización para evitar la aparición de complicaciones asociadas a su uso prolongado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);32(supl.1): 69-76, feb. 2008. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137076</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilización de bloqueantes neuromusculares en el paciente crítico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9658^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9658^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52865^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9658^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9658</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52865^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52865^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52865^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9327^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9327^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9327^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9327^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200802</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
