<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121875</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acute visual loss in pregnancy caused by craniopharyngioma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report: A 38-year-old female, at 20-weeks gestation, experienced a sudden visual loss and visual-field abnormalities. The neuroimaging tests showed a craniopharyngioma. Surgical removal was performed with a successful outcome as regards the pregnancy and visual function. Discussion: It is known that pituitary adenomas may grow during pregnancy; however this is unusual in craniopharyngiomas. They usually present with visual problems due to their suprasellar topography. Surgery is the treatment of choice, the outcome essentially depending on its complete resection (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso Alonso, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grillo-Mallo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrero Collado, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Quiñones, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Benito, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diéz-Feijóo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Gestante de 38 años, acude a urgencias por déficit visual agudo y afectación campimétrica. Las pruebas de neuroimagen ponen de manifiesto una tumoración compatible con craneofaringioma. Se realiza la resección quirúrgica mejorando la función visual y continuando su embarazo normalmente. Discusión: Es conocido que los adenomas hipofisarios pueden crecer en el embarazo, sin embargo este hecho es inusual en los craneofaringiomas. Estos suelen manifestarse con clínica visual dada su topografía supraselar. El tratamiento de elección es quirúrgico, dependiendo el pronóstico fundamentalmente de su resección completa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;89(4): 152-156, abr. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121875</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pérdida visual aguda en el embarazo causada por craneofaringioma</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15187^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54195^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3413^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11693^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10077^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
