<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128115</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-2885</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Percutaneous ultrasound-guided renal cryotherapy: an option in the treatment of renal cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cryotherapy is a option for the treatment of renal cancer. The indication generally correspond to stages T1a preferably located on the posterior aspect and lower half of the kidney. The procedure can be guided using ultrasonography as a controlled manner to avoid irradiation and saving costs. There are usually no intraoperative complications. Monitoring is done with TC a month and then every 6 months. Criterion of good result is total lack to catch contrast. Recurrence is rare and represents one of the negative aspects of this technique. To avoid this is necessary to choose good cases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Faba, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gaya, J M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esquena, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palou, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villavicencio, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gausa, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre, P. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La crioterapia es una opción terapéutica para el tratamiento del cáncer renal (CR). La indicación suele corresponder a estadios T1a situados preferentemente en cara posterior y de borde externo medio e inferior del riñón. La ecografía permite realizar el procedimiento de forma controlada, además de ahorrar irradiación y costes. No suele haber complicaciones intraoperatorias. El seguimiento se realiza con TC al mes y después cada 6 meses. Se considera criterio de buen resultado, la ausencia total de incorporación de contraste. La recurrencia es poco frecuente y representa uno de los aspectos negativos de esta técnica y para evitarla hay que elegir bien los casos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Fund. Puigvert;33(3): 89-83, jul.-sept. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128115</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Crioterapia renal percutánea ecoguiada: una opción en el tratamiento de cáncer renal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31536^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7855^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
