<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-64075</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe number and type of hemoglobinopathies diagnosed in our area of reference during one year as well as the origin of these patients, to have a first contact with this pathology not characterized in our province until now. Material and method: All hemoglobinopathies diagnosed in one year were reviewed, either for suspected patients, after analyzing chromatogram to quantify hemoglobin (Hb) A1c or hemogram suspicious of &amp;#946;-thalassemia. The screening method was high pressure liquid chromatography (HPLC), to identify and quantify HbA2, HbS and HbC. The other variants were diagnosed at reference laboratory. Results: 198 hemoglobinopathies were diagnosed, 105 after measure HbA1c. The more frequent diagnoses were &amp;#946;-thalassemia trait and heterozygote HbS. 61.1% of patients are from Canary Islands, mainly fromTenerife. Conclusions: The high number of carriers found from Canary Islands, should be the start to design prospective studies on population groups, in order to know the hemoglobinopathies prevalence and to perform control and prevention official programs in the province of Santa Cruz de Tenerife</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Heras Flórez, S. de las</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Hernández, L. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir número y tipo de hemoglobinopatías diagnosticadas en nuestro área de referencia durante un año así como el origen de estos pacientes, para tener un primer contacto con esta patología hasta ahora no caracterizada en nuestra provincia. Material y método: Se revisaron las hemoglobinopatías diagnosticadas durante un año, bien por sospecha clínica, al realizar el cromatograma para la cuantificación de hemoglobina (Hb) A1c o por sospecha de &amp;#946;-talasemia en el hemograma. El método de despitaje ha sido la cromatografía líquida de alta resolución (HPLC), que identifica y cuantifica HbA2, HbS y HbC. El resto de variantes fueron diagnosticadas en el laboratorio de referencia. Resultados: Se diagnosticaron 198 hemoglobinopatías, 105 a partirde la realización de HbA1c. Los diagnósticos más frecuentes fueron &amp;#946;-talasemia minor y HbS en estado heterocigoto. El 61,1% de los pacientes son autóctonos de Canarias, mayoritariamente de Tenerife. Conclusiones: El alto número de pacientes autóctonos de Canarias portadores de hemoglobinopatías encontrado, nos indica que éste debe ser el punto de partida en el diseño de estudios prospectivos sobre grupos poblacionales concretos para conocer la prevalencia, y plantear el desarrollo de programas de control y prevención en la provincia de Santa Cruz de Tenerife</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;25(2): 61-66, feb. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-64075</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d2894^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6940^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6603^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6603^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200802</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
