<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61917</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1972</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hospital VIHrtual (HIV Virtual Hospital): analysis of a telemedicine system for the integral care of patients with HIV/Aids at home through the Internet</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The care given to chronic patients, as in the case of complex illnesses (diabetes, COPD, HIV/Aids), requires priority being given to the quality of life of these patients. It is therefore essential to adapt to the new resources, in order to take advantage of the improvements they bring. This article presents one of these innovations which leads to the improvement and care at home, the so-called Hospital VIHrtual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zamora, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La atención a pacientes crónicos, como el caso de las enfermedades complejas (diabetes, EPOC, VIH/sida), demanda priorizar la calidad de vida de los mismos. Para ello, se antoja ineludible la adaptación a los nuevos recursos, con el fin de aprovechar las mejoras que éstos suponen. Este artículo nos presenta una de esas innovaciones que apuestan por la mejora y la atención a domicilio, el llamado Hospital Virtual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Todo hosp;(241): 682-693, nov. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61917</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hospital VIHrtual: análisis de un sistema de telemedicine para la atención integral a pacientes con VIH/sida en su domicilio a través de Internet</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19371</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29416</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30481^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30481^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33921^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6856^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33921^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6459^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33921^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6856^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30481^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6896^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3222^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3222^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
