<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85854</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Metabolic control in diabetic immigrants</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the degree of metabolic control and the presence oftype 2 diabetes complications in diabetic immigrants. Methods: Cross-sectionalcase-control observational study, matched by age and sex. Cases: Hindustanidiabetic immigrants (n= 116) and non-hindustani (n= 113). Controls:native diabetic patients with type 2 diabetes (n= 229). The relation male/femalewas 6.7, 0.8 y 2, respectively. Metabolic control and presence of chroniccomplications were assessed. Results: Compared to native diabetics, immigrantdiabetics had a lower average age (51.9 vs. 60.7 years), with longerdiabetes duration (5.5 vs. 4.4 years). Hindustani immigrants presented statisticallysignificant higher HbA1c figures (8 vs. 7.4%). In general, diabetic immigrantspresented a better lipid profile (LDL 120.4 vs. 146 and HDL 46.3 vs.42.5 mg/dL) and better blood pressure figures (135/79 vs. 141/82 mmHg)than native diabetics (p &lt;0.001). As well, immigrants had lower BMI (27.5 vs.29.3). Considering age-adjusted complications, immigrant diabetics had fewerneuropathy than native (OR= 0.22; IC: 0.11-0.54) and considering non-hindustanidiabetics, fewer coronary heart disease (OR= 0.36; IC: 0.14-0.88).Conclusions: Immigrant diabetics have a different metabolic risk profile comparedto native diabetics, with poor glycaemic control, especially among hindustaniimmigrants(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Artal Traveria, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Sierra, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morató Griera, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canadell Rusiñol, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franch Nadal, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Patitucci Gómez, M. F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Valorar el grado de control metabólico y la presencia de complicaciones dela diabetes mellitus tipo 2 (DM2) en diabéticos inmigrantes. Material y métodos:Estudio transversal y observacional de casos y controles, apareados por grupos deedad y sexo. Casos: pacientes con DM2 inmigrantes indostanos (n= 116) y no indostanos(n= 113). Controles: pacientes autóctonos con DM2 (n= 229). La relaciónhombre/mujer fue de 6,7, 0,8 y 2, respectivamente. Se valora el control metabólico yla presencia de complicaciones crónicas. Resultados: Los diabéticos inmigrantestienen una media de edad menor (51,9 frente a 60,7 años en pacientes diabéticosnativos), pero un mayor tiempo de evolución de la DM (5,5 frente a 4,4 años). Lospacientes indostanos presentaron signifi cativamente mayores niveles de hemoglobinaglucosilada (del 8 frente al 7,4%). Los pacientes diabéticos inmigrantes presentan unmejor perfi l lipídico (colesterol-LDL de 120,4 frente a 146 mg/dL, y colesterol-HDLde 46,3 frente a 42,5 mg/dL) y tensional (135/79 frente a 141/82 mmHg) que losdiabéticos autóctonos (p &lt;0,001). También tienen menor índice de masa corporal(27,5 frente a 29,3). Los pacientes diabéticos inmigrantes tienen menor frecuencia deneuropatía que los autóctonos (odds ratio [OR] ajustado por edad = 0,22; intervalo deconfi anza [IC] del 95%: 0,11-0,54) y, en el caso de los no indostanos, menos cardiopatíaisquémica (OR= 0,36; IC del 95%: 0,14-0,88). Conclusiones: Los pacientesdiabéticos inmigrantes tienen un perfi l de riesgo metabólico distinto de los autóctonos,entre los que destaca un mal control glucémico, especialmente en los indostanos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;26(2): 107-111, mar.-abr. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85854</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El control metabólico en pacientes diabéticos inmigrantes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22190</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
