<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153397</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The archaic: reflections on the beginning of psychic life and its impact upon the organization of personal life</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper examines Freud&#146;s allusions to early psychic processes and his use of the term «archaic» as a synonym for phylogenetic. The author examines the appearance of the neologism «the archaic» and presents the aetiology and manifestations of the archaic in psychoanalytic clinical practice. The notion of representation is reconsidered, suggesting the advancement of an experiential representation: an effective way to represent oneself with the other in a scene of bodily relational encounter, whether integrated or failed. The author suggests that the communication between persons requires the intentional reciprocity of feelings together with complementary messages, be they verbal or gestural. Returning to Freud&#146;s «little [ad hoc] instincts», the author proposes reinstating their psychic value as foundational to the mind, the erogenous body and the psychic desire to live. Observations by early Childhood researchers are provided to lay the foundations for the author&#146;s proposals. Clinical illustrations of the author&#146;s patient DJ. and those of other authors are presented. The author proposes that we conceptualize the «death drive» as the dynamic and symptomatic consequences of having lost all hope of communicating with others as a recognized self. The Work concludes With reflections on technique to work through the archaic processes during analysis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rizzuto, Ana María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo revisa las alusiones de Freud a procesos psíquicos tempranos y su uso del término «arcaico» como sinónimo de &amp;#64257;logenético. Examina la aparición del neologismo «lo arcaico» como nombre y presenta la etiología y manifestaciones de lo arcaico en la clínica psicoanalítica. Reconsidera la noción de representación proponiendo que debemos ón proponiendo que debemos postular una representación vivencial: una form afectiva de representarse a sí mismo con el otro en un escenario de encuentro relacional corporal ya sea integrado o fallido. Sugiere que la comunicación entre personas requiere la correspondencia intencional de sentimientos juntamente con mensajes complementarios, ya sean verbales o gestuales. Retomando las «pequeñas pulsiones» de Freud, propone restaurarles su valor psíquico como fundantes de la mente, del cuerpo erógeno y del deseo psíquico de vivir. Ofrece observaciones de investigadores de la primera infancia para fundamentar sus propuestas. Presenta ilustraciones clínicas de otros autores y la de su paciente D. J. Propone que conceptualicemos la «pulsión de muerte» como las consecuencias dinámicas y sintomáticas de haber perdido toda esperanza de comunicarse con otros como un sí mismo reconocido. Concluye con reflexiones técnicas para elaborar los procesos arcaicos durante el psicoanálisis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(76): 267-296, 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153397</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lo arcaico: reflexiones sobre los comienzos de la vida psíquica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37709</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4389</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12012^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12012^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12012^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12012^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12012^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55715^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8738^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
