<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81537</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Radial head comminuted fractures: a comparative study between resection and internal fixation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The treatment of radial head fractures continues to be controversial. The open reduction and internal fixation (ORIF) method is expanding due to improvements in the techniques and the implants. However, it can be very demanding technically and is not free of complications. On the other hand, resection shows satisfactory results in the long term in stable elbows, although it is also associated with complications. We compared resection and ORIF in comminuted fractures of the radial head. Material and Method. A total of 23 patients with type III Mason fractures were included, of which 11 were subjected to resection of the radial head (Group A), and 12 to internal fixation of their fracture (Group B). The mean age was 54 and 45 years, respectively. The fractures were clinically and radiologically evaluated, with a mean follow-up of 80 months in Group A and 76 months in Group B. Results. The flexion-extension movement range was 121°&#150;(&amp;#8722;11°) in Group A and 131°&#150;0° in Group B. The functional results obtained according the Broberg and Morrey scale were: 82 points in Group A and 90.9 points in Group B. Discussion. Patients with comminuted fractures of the radial head subjected to open reduction and internal fixation have a satisfactory movement range, with greater strength, and therefore, better function. We recommend open reduction and internal fixation in the treatment of these fractures, particularly in young patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lajara Marco, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano Requena, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Gómez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ricón Recarey, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El tratamiento de las fracturas de cabeza radial continúa siendo controvertido. La reducción abierta y fijación interna (RAFI) está en expansión debido a la mejora de las técnicas y los implantes. Sin embargo, puede ser técnicamente muy demandante y no está exenta de complicaciones. Por otra parte, la resección muestra resultados satisfactorios a largo plazo en codos estables, aunque también asocia complicaciones. Comparamos la resección y la RAFI en fracturas conminutas de la cabeza de radio. Material y método. Se incluyeron 23 pacientes con fracturas Mason tipo iii, 11 sometidos a resección de la cabeza del radio (Grupo A), y 12 a fijación interna de su fractura (Grupo B). La media de edad fue 54 y 45 años, respectivamente. Las fracturas fueron evaluadas clínica y radiológicamente; con un seguimiento medio de 80 meses en el Grupo A y 76 en el B. Resultados. El rango de movilidad fue de 121°&#150;(&amp;#8722;11°) de flexo-extensión en el grupo A y de 131°&#150;0° en el grupo B. Según la escala de Broberg y Morrey los resultados funcionales obtenidos son: 82 puntos en el Grupo A y 90,9 puntos en el Grupo B. Discusión. Los pacientes con fracturas conminutas de la cabeza del radio sometidos a reducción abierta y fijación interna tienen un rango de movilidad articular satisfactorio, con mayor fuerza y por tanto, mejor función. Recomendamos la reducción abierta y fijación interna en el tratamiento de estas fracturas, sobre todo en pacientes jóvenes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);54(5): 280-288, sept.-oct. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81537</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fracturas conminutas de la cabeza radial: estudio comparativo entre resección y fijación interna</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32243^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32243^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12319^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32243^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12319^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32243^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
