<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140366</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of a multidisciplinary program on morbid obese patients and patients with comorbility who are likely to be candidates for bariatric surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Morbid obesity is a disease that must be treated comprehensively (i.e. multi/interdisciplinary). Bariatric surgery is an effective and secure procedure for treating this health condition; however, the higher the weight is, the greater the risk of morbimortality might be. Objective: The aim of this study is to determine the effects of a multidisciplinary treatment program on metabolic and anthropometric parameters and the physical condition of bariatric surgery candidates. Materials and Methods: 1 man and 9 women of ~42.5 years old, with morbid obesity ( n = 3) or obesity and comorbilities (diabetes mellitus type II, hypertension, dyslipidemia and insulin resistance) (n = 7), all of them candidates for bariatric surgery, were submitted to physical exercise, psychological support and nutritional education, 3 times a week during 3 months. 72 hours before and after the last intervention session: body mass; fat mass index; BMI; waist circumference; physical condition; glycemia; HDL, LDL and total cholesterol; and triglycerides, were assessed (with a &amp;#8805;12-hour fast). Results: After intervention, body mass (p=0.004), BMI (p=0.002), fat mass index (p=0.047) and physical condition (p=0.000) showed significant changes. Despite their tendency to decrease, remaining variables did not show significant changes. Conclusions: A comprehensive reasonable-frequent, short intervention (i.e. 3 sessions per week, during 3 months) may lead to significant weight and body fat loss, apart from enhancing considerably the physical condition of candidates for bariatric surgery. Longer time and/ or higher frequency in interventions might be necessary in order to modify significantly plasmatic variables (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Thuillier Lepeley, Nicole</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Osorio Poblete, Aldo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos Jara, Christian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Campillo, Rodrigo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alarcón Hormazábal, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Floody, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jerez Mayorga, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caamaño Navarrete, Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saldivia Mansilla, Claudia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La obesidad mórbida es una enfermedad que debe ser tratada de forma integral (i.e., multi/ interdisciplinar). Para esta condición la cirugía bariátrica es efectiva y segura en el tratamiento, sin embargo, a mayor peso preoperatorio podría aumentar la morbimortalidad. Objetivo: El objetivo del estudio es determinar los efectos de un programa de tratamiento interdisciplinar sobre parámetros metabólicos, antropométricos y la condición física en candidatos a cirugía bariátrica. Material y métodos: Un hombre y nueve mujeres con un promedio de 42,5 años de edad con obesidad mórbida (n = 3) u obesidad y comorbilidades (diabetes mellitus tipo II, hipertensión arterial, dislipidemia, resistencia a la insulina) (n=7) candidatos a cirugía bariátrica, fueron sometidos a ejercicio físico, apoyo psicológico y educación nutricional, tres veces por semana durante tres meses. Antes y 72 horas después de la última sesión de intervención se evaluó (en ayuno &amp;#8805;12 horas): masa corporal, porcentaje de masa grasa, IMC, perímetro de cintura, condición física, glicemia, colesterol total, colesterol HDL, colesterol LDL y triglicéridos. Resultados: Posterior a la intervención la masa corporal (p=0,004), el IMC (p=0,002), el porcentaje de masa grasa (p=0,047) y la condición física (p=0,000) presentaron cambios significativos. Las demás variables dependientes no presentaron cambios significativos, aunque tendieron a disminuir. Conclusiones: Una intervención integral de frecuencia moderada y corta duración (i.e., tres sesiones/semana durante tres meses) permitiría reducir significativamente el peso y la grasa corporal, además de mejorar considerablemente la condición física en candidatos a cirugía bariátrica. Una mayor duración y/o frecuencia de intervención podría ser necesaria para modificar significativamente variables plasmáticas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(5): 2011-2016, mayo 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140366</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de un programa de tratamiento multidisciplinar en obesos mórbidos y obesos con comorbilidades candidatos a cirugía bariátrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3162^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38836^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4071^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
