<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114505</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-7347</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Determining exertion capacity of adult  cystic fibrosis patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Cystic fibrosis (CF) is a hereditary disease linked to the deterioration of lung function, malnutrition and progressive exercise intolerance. The objective of this study was to examine the exertion capacity of CF patients and the relationship with lung function, nutritional status and physical activity. Method: Included in the study were fifty (50) patients who had been diagnosed with CF, age 24.4 (±5.9 years with FEV160.4 (28%). Measurements included body mass index (BMI), limb lean mass (LLM), lung function, assessment of exercise capacity (VO2 max) and 6-minute walk test. Physical activity was measured using a portable accelerometer. A multiple lineal regression model was calculated for VO2 max. Results: Patients had a reduced BMI (20.6 (±2.7) kg/m2) and LLM (17.2 (±2.6) g/cm2). The mean distance walked for the 6-minute walk was 633.3 (±74.5) m and the VO2 max reached was 70.9% (±17.7) The mean of the average steps measured was 8,173.8 (3,776.2). The VO2 max related significantly with the age (&#150;0.3 (&#150;0.561 / &#150;0.061), FEV1 (0.117; 0.059-0.175), average of daily steps (0.001 [0-0.001]), 6-minute walk (0.022[0-0.045]) and BMI (&#150;0.658[&#150;1.2 / &#150;0.067]). Conclusions: In our group of patients with CF, there were limits when exercising, with exercise being influenced by respiratory function, physical activity and nutritional status (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dapena Fernández, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valencia Azcona, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Campos, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez Martí- nez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cejudo Ramos, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintana-Gallego, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejero García, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La fibrosis quística (FQ) es una enfermedad hereditaria que se relaciona con un deterioro de la función pulmonar, malnutrición e intolerancia progresiva al ejercicio. La finalidad de nuestro estudio fue examinar la capacidad de esfuerzo de pacientes adultos diagnosticados de FQ y su relación con la función pulmonar, el estado nutricional y la actividad física. Método: Incluimos a 50 pacientes adultos diagnosticados de FQ, edad 24,4 (5,9) años con FEV1 60,4 (28)%. Las medidas incluyeron el índice de masa corporal (IMC), masa magra de extremidades (MMe), función pulmonar, evaluación de la capacidad de ejercicio (VO2max) y test de los 6 minutos (6MM). La actividad física fue medida mediante un acelerómetro portátil. Se calculó un modelo de regresión lineal múltiple para VO2max.Resultados: Los pacientes tenían un reducido IMC (20,6 (2,7) kg/m2) y MMe (17,2 (2,6) g/cm2). La distancia media andada en el 6MM fue 633,3 (74,5) m y el VO2max alcanzado fue 70,9 (17,7)%. La media de los pasos medios medidos fue 8.173,8 (3.776,2). La VO2max se relacionaba de forma significativa con la edad (&#150;0,3 (&#150;0,561 / &#150;0,061), FEV1 (0,117; 0,059-0,175), media de pasos diarios (0,001 [0-0,001]), 6MM (0,022[0-0,045]) e IMC (&#150;0,658[&#150;1,2 / &#150;0,067]). Conclusiones: En nuestro grupo de pacientes con FQ, había limitación en la realización de ejercicio, estando ésta influenciada por la función respiratoria, la actividad física y el estado nutriciona (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol. torac;25(2): 125-131, abr.-jun. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114505</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Determinantes de la capacidad de esfuerzo en pacientes adultos diagnosticados de fibrosis quística</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3568^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5180^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5178^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12542^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
