<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108889</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Obesity: etiologic and pathophysiological analysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the ef&amp;#64257;cacy of intermittent, high-dose treatment with intravenous glucocorticoids (IV GCs) in moderate to severe Graves&#146; ophthalmopathy (GO).Materials and methods: Patients with GO treated with IV GCs from August 2007 to August 2011at the Endocrinology Department of Reina Sofía Hospital were enrolled into the study. IV pulseprednisol one (7.5 mg/kg/day) was administered twice weekly every two weeks for 6 weeks, and at half the dose for 6 additional weeks. Results: Eighteen patients (mean age, 43+/-11 years) with moderate to severe GO were analyzed (83.3% females). Four were active smokers, &amp;#64257;ve former smokers, and the rest had never smoked. Hyperthyroidism due to Graves&#146; disease was found in 66.7% of patients, 41.6% of whom had received radioiodine therapy. Response to treatment was satisfactory in 72.2%, partial in11.1%, and poor in 16.7%. Mild side effects were reported by 5 patients. Before treatment,83.3% had diplopia, 33.3% eyelid retraction, 72.2% eye pain, and 44.4% exophthalmos. After treatment, only 33.3% had diplopia (P = .004), 5.6% eyelid retraction (P = .063), 16.7% eye pain(P = .002), and 11.1% exophthalmos (P = .031). Response to treatment was not related to the underlying disease (P = .866), prior radioiodine treatment (P = .447), or smoking status (P = .368).Conclusions: Intravenous glucocorticoid therapy decreased activity in patients with moderate to severe active GO, with major improvement occurring in diplopia, eye pain, and exophthalmos. Side effects were mild and uncommon. Treatment response was independent from the underlying disease, prior radioiodine treatment, or smoking status (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alhambra Expósito, María Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Moreno, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prior Sánchez, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benito López, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Jiménez, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gálvez Moreno, María Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la efectividad del protocolo de tratamiento intermitente con glucocorticoides a altas dosis por vía intravenosa (i.v.) en la oftalmopatía de Graves (OG) moderada-grave del Hospital Reina Sofía. Material y métodos Se incluyeron los pacientes con OG tratados con glucocorticoides i.v. en nuestro servicio desde agosto de 2007 a agosto de 2011. Se administró prednisolona i.v. en dosis de 7,5mg/kg/d 2d alternos durante 6 semanas alternas y mitad de la dosis durante 6 semanas más. Resultados Analizamos 18 pacientes (83,3% mujeres) con una edad media de 43±11 años. Cuatro eran fumadores, 5 habían dejado el hábito y el resto nunca habían fumado. El 66,7% presentaban hipertiroidismo por enfermedad de Graves, de los cuales el 41,6% habían recibido radioyodo. La respuesta al tratamiento fue buena en el 72,2%, parcial en 11,1% y mala en 16,7%. En 5 aparecieron efectos secundarios leves. Antes del tratamiento el 83,3% presentaron diplopía, el 33,3% retracción palpebral, el 72,2% dolor ocular y el 44,4% exoftalmos. Después del tratamiento solo el 33,3% continuaron con diplopía (p=0,004), el 5,6% con retracción palpebral (p=0,063), el 16,7% con dolor ocular (p=0,002) y el 11,1% con exoftalmos (p=0,031). El 22,2% precisaron radioterapia. La respuesta al tratamiento no se asoció a la enfermedad de base (p=0,866) al haber recibido radioyodo previo como tratamiento del hipertiroidismo (p=0,447) o al ser fumador (p=0,368).Conclusiones El tratamiento con glucocorticoides i.v. en la oftalmopatía tiroidea reduce significativamente la diplopía, el dolor ocular y el exoftalmos. Los efectos secundarios son leves y poco frecuentes. La respuesta al tratamiento es independiente de la enfermedad de base, de haber recibido radioyodo y de ser fumador (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;60(1): 10-14, ene. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108889</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la efectividad del tratamiento con glucocorticoides intravenosos en la oftalmopatía de Graves</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53972^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50490^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28010^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7450^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6082^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4229^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201301</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
