<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119125</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Indications for magnetic resonance imaging for low back pain in adults</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Low back pain is a common disorder that generates many medical consultations. Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) is commonly used in the clinical management of some of these patients. However, the cost of inappropriate MRI use is high, so there is a need to develop guidelines to help physicians make correct decisions and optimize available resources. Objective: To determine the main clinical indications for MRI scanning in adults with low backpain. Material and methods: The RAND/UCLA appropriateness method was used: After a systematic review (May 2012), a list of the clinical indications for MRI scanning in patients with low back pain was prepared. A multidisciplinary expert panel scored each indication from 1, «totally inappropriate» to 9,«totally appropriate». A first on-line round, an in-person panel meeting, where results of the first round were discussed, and a final second on-line round were arranged. A clinical indication was considered appropriate if the median score was 6.5 or higher, and there was agreement between experts (IPRAS index was used). Results: An MRI test is considered appropriate if cancer, spinal infection or a fracture, even with a negative X-ray test is suspected.; if there is inflammatory back pain; severe/progressive neurological deficit; severe and progressive low back pain; subacute or chronic low back pain with radicular involvement unresponsive to conservative therapy. Conclusions: Clinical indications for a MRI scanning are based on the suspicion of a secondary serious pathology. This methodology helps to set clinical indications for MRI, and may be of great value for both clinicians and health managers (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zubia Arratibel, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrera Zubizarreta, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñiz Saitua, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Millán Ortuondo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sola Sarabia, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La lumbalgia genera numerosas consultas. La resonancia magnética (RM) es una opción diagnóstica en el manejo de alguno de estos pacientes. Sin embargo, su uso inadecuado supone una pérdida de recursos que obliga a disponer de guías que ayuden a los clínicos en la toma de decisiones y permita una mejor gestión de los recursos. Objetivo: Establecer las principales indicaciones clínicas de RM en los casos de dolor lumbar en adultos. Material y métodos: Se empleó el método de uso apropiado RAND/UCLA: tras una revisión sistemática en mayo de 2012 se elaboró un listado con posibles indicaciones de RM ante lumbalgia que un panel de expertos multidisciplinar puntuó desde 1, «totalmente inapropiado», a 9 «totalmente apropiado». Se realizó una primera ronda de puntuación online, se presentaron y discutieron los resultados en una reunión presencial y se realizó una ronda final online. La RM se consideró apropiada en cada indicación si la puntuación mediana era de 6,5 o mayor y había acuerdo (empleando el índice IPRAS). Resultados: La RM se consideró apropiada ante sospecha afectación tumoral, sospecha de infección espinal, sospecha de fractura a pesar de radiografía negativa, lumbalgia con dolor de ritmo inflamatorio, déficit neurológico progresivo/grave, dolor muy severo y que progresa de intensidad y lumbalgia subaguda o crónica con irradiación radicular con fracaso en el tratamiento. Conclusiones: La indicación de RM parece basarse en la sospecha de enfermedad grave secundaria. La metodología empleada permite establecer indicaciones de RM que pueden ser de utilidad tanto al clínico como al gestor sanitario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;29(1): 51-57, ene.-feb. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119125</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Indicaciones de la resonancia magnética en la lumbalgia de adultos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33125^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
