<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85898</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Publications in respiratory nursing and physiotherapy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Respiratory Nursing and Physiotherapy Section of the Spanish Society of Pneumology and ThoracicSurgery, established as a working group more than 19 years ago, has been characterized by a high degree ofinvolvement and collaboration with all the research studies requiring nursing and physiotherapy techniques.However, publication of articles by this collective is scarce compared with that of the rest of the Society andthe characteristics, attitudes and limitations of this section pose an obstacle to increasing the number of itspublications. This article aims to explain some of the possible reasons that could have given rise to thissituation. The new tendencies and the attitude of this collective and the rest of the Society are encouragingand suggest that the work of the Respiratory Nursing and Physiotherapy Section will be better reflected in thefuture(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Macián Gisbert, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Gómez, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermería y la fisioterapia respiratoria, pertenecientes a SEPAR desde su nacimiento como grupo de trabajohace ya más de 19 años, se han caracterizado por el grado de implicación y de colaboración en todos los trabajosde investigación en los que los cuidados o las técnicas eran imprescindibles. La producción propia deartículos es ciertamente escasa por parte de nuestro colectivo comparada con el resto de la SEPAR. Nuestrascaracterísticas y peculiaridades, las actitudes y limitaciones históricas impiden poder tener una mayor presenciaen nuestra revista. En este artículo trataremos de explicar algunas de las posibles razones y motivosque creemos son los causantes de estas circunstancias.Las nuevas tendencias y la actitud de nuestro colectivo y del resto de la sociedad nos hace tener esperanzas ypensar que esta precariedad en el reflejo de nuestro trabajo se irá modificando en el proceso de cambio(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;47(supl.1): 16-18, ene. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85898</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Publicaciones de enfermería y fisioterapia respiratoria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32786</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11247^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11247^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11247^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201101</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
