<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154872</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reliability and validity of a questionnaire to evaluate the perceived quality of the families seen in Early Intervention Centers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To validate a tool to measure the perception of the quality of service provided in Early Intervention Centers. Material and method: A cross-sectional and multicenter study was performed for the validation of a self-completed questionnaire. Participants were the family members of children who were receiving treatment at 14 Early Intervention Centers in the province of Malaga. A total of 670 persons (75.8% women and 24.2% men) filled out the questionnaire. They had been selected by sampling for convenience with ages ranging from 20 to 80 years. Content validity was verified by experts. Internal consistency was evaluated using Cronbach's alpha coefficient. The exploratory factor analysis of the main components with eigenvalues above 1, and Varimax rotation was performed for construct validity. Different goodness of fit indexes were used for the confirmatory factor analysis. Results: The 48 items were grouped into 6 dimensions. Internal consistency was satisfactory. Exploratory factor analysis identified 14 factors that accounted for approximately 50% of the variance. The confirmatory factor analysis provided appropriate values for the adjustment indexes considered, with results within established limits. Conclusions: The Quality Inventory of Early Intervention Centers is a tool whose psychometric results are sufficient to be considered as a pragmatic, useful and reliable tool for the measurement of the quality perceived by users of the Early Interventions Centers (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romero-Galisteo, RP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Mendo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gálvez-Ruiz, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales-Sánchez, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Validar un instrumento para medir la percepción de la calidad del servicio prestado en los Centros de Atención Infantil Temprana. Material y método: Estudio transversal y multicéntrico para la validación de un cuestionario autocumplimentado. Los participantes fueron los familiares de niños-as que reciben tratamiento de Atención Temprana en 14 Centros de Atención Temprana de la provincia de Málaga, autocumplimentando el cuestionario 670 personas (75,8% mujeres y 24,2% hombres) seleccionadas mediante muestreo por conveniencia con edades entre los 20 y 80 años. Se comprobó la validez de contenido mediante grupo de expertos. La consistencia interna fue evaluada mediante el coeficiente alfa de Cronbach. Para la validez de constructo, el análisis factorial exploratorio se realizó con un método de componentes principales, autovalores mayores a uno y rotación varimax, mientras que en el análisis factorial confirmatorio se emplearon diferentes índices de bondad de ajuste. Resultados: Los 48 ítems se agruparon en 6 dimensiones. La consistencia interna fue satisfactoria. El análisis factorial exploratorio identificó una estructura de 14 factores, explicando cada dimensión en torno al 50% de la varianza. El análisis factorial confirmatorio proporcionó adecuados valores para los índices de ajuste considerados, con resultados dentro de los límites establecidos. Conclusiones: El inventario de calidad en los Centros de Atención Infantil Temprana es un instrumento que reúne adecuadas propiedades psicométricas como para ser considerado una herramienta pragmática, útil y fiable para medir la calidad percibida por los usuarios atendidos en este tipo de centros (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);37(5): 205-211, sept.-oct. 2015. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154872</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fiabilidad y validez de un cuestionario para evaluar la percepción de calidad de las familias atendidas en los Centros de Atención Temprana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54849^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
