<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73354</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hypoglycemia unawareness syndrome. Risk factors and treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hypoglycemia unawareness is a major limiting factor in the managementof type 1 and advanced type 2 diabetes. This common problem,which occurs in about 25% of patients treated with insulin, ischaracterized by loss of autonomic warning symptoms before developmentof neuroglycopenia. Hypoglycemia unawareness is also associatedwith ~7-fold increase in the risk to suffer severe hypoglycemia.Several risk factors for hypoglycemia unawareness have beenidentified, including long duration of diabetes, tight glycemic control(low HbA1c values), and repeated episodes of hypoglycemia. Reductionof counterregulatory hormone responses to hypoglycemia areprimarily responsible for hypoglycemia unawareness. Strict avoidingof hypoglycemia restores almost completely awareness of hypoglycemia.Therefore, several therapeutic strategies have been designedto prevent hypoglycemia. Among them, evening NPH insulin splitting,continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion, preferential use of insulinanalogues and, more recently, continuous glucose monitoring havebeen proved to be effective in most cases(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ampudia-Blasco, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La falta de reconocimiento de la hipoglucemia es un importante factorlimitante del tratamiento en la diabetes mellitus tipo 1 y tipo 2avanzada. Este problema, que ocurre hasta en un 25% de los pacientestratados con insulina, se caracteriza por una pérdida de lossíntomas autónomos de alarma antes de la aparición de la neuroglucopenia.La hipoglucemia inadvertida se asocia a un incremento deaproximadamente 7 veces el riesgo de sufrir hipoglucemias graves.Se han identifi cado diversos factores de riesgo para la hipoglucemiainadvertida, incluida la diabetes de larga duración, el control metabólicoestricto (valores bajos de HbA1c) y los episodios repetidos de hipoglucemia.La disminución de la respuesta contrarreguladora frentea la hipoglucemia es la causa principal de la hipoglucemia inadvertida.Evitar estrictamente las hipoglucemias restablece casi completamentesu percepción. En consecuencia, se han desarrollado diferentesestrategias terapéuticas para prevenir las hipoglucemias. Entreellas, el desdoblamiento de la insulina NPH nocturna, la infusión subcutáneacontinua de insulina, el uso preferente de los análogos deinsulina y, más recientemente, la monitorización continua de glucosa,han demostrado ser efectivas en la mayoría de casos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;25(4): 280-286, jul.-ago. 2009. graf, ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73354</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de falta de reconocimiento de la hipoglucemia. Factores de riesgo y tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22523^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7181^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
