<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151673</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnostic concordance of DSM-IV and DSM-% posttrauamtic stress disorder (PTSD) in a clinical simple</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: the present study aims to analyze diagnostic concordance between the DSM-IV and the DSM-5 for posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD) diagnostic criteria and their different groups of symptoms. Furthermore, analyses are conducted to establish the features of participants with no concordant diagnoses. Method: The study assessed 166 people over 18 who had experienced at least one traumatic event. PTSD diagnosis was established using the Global Scale for Posttraumatic Stress (EGEP), a self-report measure to assess PTSD. Results: The presence of cognitive avoidance was a determinant in the PTSD DSM-5 diagnosis (86% positive predictive value). The analysis of the non-concordant individuals revealed that individuals who were diagnosed according to the DSM-IV criteria but not the DSM-5 criteria were primarily indirect victims. Conversely, individuals who were diagnosed with the DSM-5 criteria and not with the DSM-IV criteria presented cognitive avoidance and alterations in cognition not included in the DSM-IV criteria. Conclusions: A within-subjects concordance analysis showed high agreement for PTSD diagnosis between the two classifications. Differences between the diagnoses are due to the new definition of C (avoidance) and D (negative alterations in cognitions and mood) in the DSM-5 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez, M Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: el presente estudio tiene como objetivo analizar la concordancia diagnóstica entre la clasificación DSM-IV y DSM-5 para el Trastorno de Estrés Postraumático (TEPT), en relación al diagnóstico y a la presencia de los diferentes grupos de síntomas. Además, se analizan las características de los participantes que no obtienen concordancia diagnóstica entre las dos clasificaciones. Método: 166 participantes, mayores de 18 años, fueron evaluados utilizando la Escala Global de Estrés Postraumático (EGEP), instrumento autoaplicado para evaluar la presencia de sintomatología postraumática y diagnóstico de TEPT. Resultados: el análisis de la no concordancia entre los diagnósticos reveló que los participantes diagnosticados de TEPT, según DSM-IV pero no diagnosticados según DSM-5, eran principalmente víctimas indirectas, mientras que los participantes diagnosticados de TEPT según DSM-5 pero no según DSM-IV presentaban síntomas de evitación cognitiva y alteraciones en cognición y ánimo, ambos síntomas no recogidos en la clasificación DSM-IV. Conclusiones: existe una alta concordancia entre las clasificaciones para el diagnóstico de TEPT. Las diferencias en el diagnóstico son debidas fundamentalmente a la nueva conceptualización de criterio C (evitación) y del criterio D (alteraciones negativas cognitivas y del estado del ánimo) en el DSM-5 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);28(2): 161-166, mayo 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151673</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Concordancia diagnóstica entre DSM-IV y DSM-5 para el Trastorno de Estrés Postraumático (TEPT) en una muestra clínic</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28627^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54263^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26426^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
