<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140404</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Magnesium in tap and bottled mineral water in Spain and its contribution to nutritional recommendations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: An appropriate magnesium intake has proved to have beneficial effects on bone health, reduce insulin resistance and prevent atherosclerosis. Objective: To determine the concentration of magnesium in drinking water and bottled mineral water in Spain and assess its daily contribution to dietary recommendations. Methods: We used ion chromatography to analyse the magnesium concentrations of public drinking waters in a representative sample of 108 Spanish municipalities (supplying 21,290,707 potential individuals) and 109 natural mineral waters sold in Spain (97 Spanish and 12 imported). Results: The water generally contained between 15 and 45 mg/L of magnesium, but in seven municipalities it contained over 45 mg/L. The average magnesium concentration of 97 brands of Spanish natural mineral water was 16.27 mg/L (range: 0.11-141.2 mg/L). Of these, 33 contained between 15 and 45 mg/L of magnesium and four contained over 45 mg/L. Of the 12 imported brands, 4 contained over 45 mg/L. Assuming water consumption is as recommended by the European Food Safety Agency, water containing 15 to 45 mg/L of magnesium provides between 9 and 76.5% of the recommended intake of magnesium for children aged one to thirteen, up to 25.7% in adolescents, between 7.5 and 25.7% for adults, and up to 27% for lactating women. Water with 60 mg/L of magnesium provides between 30 and 102% of the recommended dietary allowance, depending on the age of the individual. Discussion: The consumption of public drinking water and natural mineral water in a third of Spanish cities can be regarded as an important supplementary source of magnesium (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferreira-Pêgo, Cíntia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salas-Salvadó, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maraver, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vitoria, Isidro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armijo, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Una adecuada ingesta de magnesio condiciona una buena salud ósea y previene y la resistencia a la insulina y la arteriosclerosis. Objetivo: Determinar el contenido en magnesio en aguas de bebida en España y valorar su contribución diaria a las ingestas recomendadas de este mineral. Métodos: En 2012 se analizaron por cromatografía ió- nica las concentraciones de magnesio de distintas aguas de consumo público en una muestra representativa de 108 poblaciones españolas que abastecen a 21.290.707 personas, así como de 109 aguas minerales naturales embotelladas comercializadas en España (97 españolas y 12 importadas). Resultados: La concentración media de magnesio en aguas de consumo público fue de 14,65±16,23 mg/L (rango: 0,07-70,08 mg/L). En 25 poblaciones el agua contenía 15-45 mg/L de magnesio y en 7 fue superior a 45 mg/L. La concentración media de magnesio de las 97 marcas españolas de aguas fue 16,27 mg/L (rango: 0,11-141,2 mg/L), 33 de ellas contenían 15-45 mg/L de magnesio, mientras que en 4 de ellas era mayor de 45 mg/L. De las 12 marcas importadas, 4 contenían más de 45 mg/L. Asumiendo la cantidad de ingesta de agua recomendada por la EFSA, si el agua contiene 15-45 mg/L de magnesio, ésta aportaría entre el 9 y el 76,5% de la ingesta de magnesio recomendada para los niños de 1-13 años, hasta el 25,7% en adolescentes, entre 7,5 y 25,7% en adultos, y hasta el 27% en lactantes. El agua conteniendo 60 mg/L de magnesio aportaría entre el 30 y el 102% de las recomendaciones según la edad. Discusión: El agua de consumo público de un tercio de ciudades españolas y de aguas minerales naturales puede ser considerada como una fuente complementaria importante de magnesio ingerido (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(5): 2297-2312, mayo 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140404</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Magnesio en el agua de consumo público y aguas minerales naturales en España y su contribución en cubrir las necesidades nutricionales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51769^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16183^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24961</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15284^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8448^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
