<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040388</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Emotional dysfunctions in terminal cancer patient's caregiver</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: the informal caregivers play an excellent role in the presentsociety, and this role is greater if they deal with terminal cancerpatients.Objective: to evaluate the emotional situation of informal caregiverswho take care of cancer patients.Material and method: we developed a cross-sectional study throughsurveys to the terminal cancer patients and to their main caregivers.Patients&#146; variables studies were: demographic data, main diagnosis, symptomsand performance status by the Karnofsky index. Caregivers&#146; variableswere: demographic data, degree of relationship, main pathologies, time oflooking after the patient and level of anxiety and depression establishedusing the Goldberg test.Results: forty-nine terminal cancer patients were studied: 35 men and14 women, with an average of 72,55 years and a moderate functionalimpairment measured using the Karnofsky index of 46,53. Lung cancerwas the most prevalent tumor, followed by breast and prostate cancer.Pain was the most frequent symptom. The caregivers were mainly women(75,51%), with an average of 56,67 years. The wife was the caregiver in the59,18% cases. A 59,18% of caregivers suffered from osteomuscular pathology.The average time of follow up was 10,75 months. The Goldberg testcorroborated the tendency that depression and anxiety were directly proportionalto the time taking care of the patients, as well as to the patient&#146;sdegree of disability.Conclusion: the measures of support of the interdisciplinary teamtowards the main caregiver can be very important to prevent and to dealwith the syndrome of caregiver</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molina Linde, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Sañudo, R. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Cotelo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gálvez Mateos, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Rodríguez, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: los cuidadores informales juegan un papel relevante enla sociedad actual, y más aún cuando se habla de enfermos oncológicosterminales.Objetivo: evaluar el estado emocional de los cuidadores informales depacientes terminales de cáncer.Material y método: se realizó un estudio de tipo transversal medianteentrevista, tanto a los pacientes terminales como a sus cuidadores principales.En el paciente se registraron las variables sociodemográficas, diagnóstico,síntomas principales y grado de funcionalidad con el Karnofsky.En los cuidadores se recogieron los datos sociodemográficos, parentesco,patologías principales, tiempo que lleva cuidando al paciente y se les aplicóel test de Goldberg, para detectar posibles signos relacionados conansiedad y depresión.Resultados: se estudiaron 49 pacientes oncológicos terminales: 35hombres y 14 mujeres, con una edad media de 72,55 años, y un deteriorofuncional moderado (media del Karnofsky de 46,53). El cáncer de pulmónaparece como diagnóstico mayoritario, seguido de mama y próstata, siendoel dolor el síntoma más prevalente. Los cuidadores fueron mayoritariamentemujeres (75,51%), con una edad media de 56,67 años, cónyuges(59,18%), con patología osteoarticular asociada (59,18%), y un tiempomedio de 10,75 meses los que lleva cuidando al enfermo. El test de Goldbergcorroboró una tendencia a la depresión y ansiedad, directamente proporcionala la duración del periodo de cuidados al paciente, así como aldeterioro funcional del enfermo.Conclusión: las medidas de apoyo y soporte del equipo sanitario haciael cuidador principal son fundamentales para prevenir y tratar el síndromede cuidador</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;12(2): 83-87, abr.-jun. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040388</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alteraciones emocionales en el cuidador del enfermo oncológico terminal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33200</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17140</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14105^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
