<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134401</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of underweight, overweight and obesity in university students from the region of Anhui (China)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Overweight and obesity are epidemic worldwide. Our previous study found that the prevalence of overweight and obesity in primary students is high. Objective: we sought to estimate whether the prevalence of overweight and obesity among university students is still high in China. Methods: A cross-sectional study was designed to collect the routine health screening data for university students in 2013. The height and weight of students were measured, and BMI was calculated with height and weight, we estimated the underweight and obesity prevalence of university students using by two references [Working Group on Obesity references in China (2004) and World Health Organization (WHO) criteria (2000)]. Results: Depending on the China references used, the overall prevalence of underweight, overweight (including obesity) and obesity in male university students were 14.2%, 14.7% and 4.2%, respectively; in female university students were 27.5%, 4.4% and 0.6%, respectively. Depending on the WHO references used, the overall prevalence of underweight, overweight (including obesity) and obesity in male university students were 14.2%, 11.5% and 2.5%, respectively, in female university students were 27.5%, 2.4% and 0.3%, respectively. An interesting observation made was that the underweight prevalence of university students has an increasing trend, especially in female. Conclusion: The study showed that the prevalence of underweight in university students, especially in female students has become a critical health issue. Related department of school and government should pay more attention to student&#146;s physical health (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jin, Yuelong</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nie, Zhognhua</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ren, Xiaohua</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lu, Wei</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>He, Lianping</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ding , Lingling</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guo, Daoxia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Wang, Linghong</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tian, Li</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lu, Mi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yao, Yingshui</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chen, Yan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: El sobrepeso y la obesidad son epidemia en todo el mundo.Nuestro estudio anterior halló que la prevalencia de sobrepeso y obesidad en estudiantes de primaria es alto. Objetivo: Hemos tratado de estimar si la prevalencia del sobrepeso y la obesidad entre los estudiantes universitarios es todavía alta en China. Métodos: Un estudio transversal fue diseñado para recoger los exámenes de salud de rutina datos para estudiantes universitarios en 2013.La altura y el peso de los estudiantes fueron medidos, y el IMC se calcula con la altura y el peso, así como para estimar la prevalencia de insuficiencia ponderal y obesidad de la Universidad los estudiantes utilizando dos referencias [Grupo de trabajo sobre la obesidad referencias en China (2004) y la Organización Mundial de la salud (OMS) criterios (2000)]. Resultados: Dependiendo de la China referencias utilizadas, la prevalencia global de bajo peso, sobrepeso (obesidad) y la obesidad en estudiantes universitarios masculinos fueron 14,2%, el 14,7% y 4,2%, respectivamente; en mujeres estudiantes universitarios fueron el 27,5%, 4,4% y 0,6%, respectivamente. Dependiendo de los que referencias utilizadas, la prevalencia global de bajo peso, sobrepeso (obesidad) y la obesidad en estudiantes universitarios masculinos fueron 14,2%, 11,5% y 2,5%, respectivamente, en mujeres estudiantes universitarios fueron el 27,5%, 2,4% y 0,3%, respectivamente. Una observación interesante es que la prevalencia de insuficiencia ponderal de los estudiantes universitarios tiene una tendencia al aumento, sobre todo en mujeres. Conclusión: El estudio demostró que la prevalencia de la insuficiencia ponderal en estudiantes universitarios, especialmente en mujeres estudiantes se ha convertido en un problema de salud crítico. Related Departamento de la escuela y el Gobierno deben prestar más atención a la salud física del alumno (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(3): 1089-1093, mar. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134401</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de bajo peso, el sobrepeso y la obesidad en estudiantes universitarios de la región de Anhui (China)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2727^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
