<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117088</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evolution of renal function in abdominal aortic aneurysm surgery with suprarenal cross-clamping</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyse the effects of suprarenal cross-clamping (SC) as opposed to the infrarenal position (IC) in the evolution of the renal function abdominal aorta aneurysm (AAA) surgery. Material and method: A retrospective cohort study of AAAs treated by elective open surgery between 1998 and 2011. The preoperative level of serum creatinine (mg/dL) was determined and compared to postoperative level at 24, 48, 72 and 96 hours, and on discharge. A deterioration in the renal function was defined as a creatinine &gt; 2 mg/dL in patients with a normal baseline creatinine level or an increase of double the baseline creatinine in patients with a previous chronic renal insufficiency (CRI). A deterioration of the glomerular filtrate (GF) was defined as a &gt; 25% decrease. Multivariable analysis was performed on the evolution of the renal function. Results: A total of 464 AAA&#146;s were analysed, 359 (77.4%) with IC, and 105 (22.6%) with SC. The prevalence of preoperative CRI was similar in both groups. The type of clamp was not associated with a deterioration in the renal function (SC = 8.6% vs. IC = 5.7%; p = 0.13) but was associated with a deterioration of the GF (SC = 27.6% vs. IC = 13.4%; p = 0.001). The time the clamp was in place, the blood loss, and the preoperative CRI were independent risk factors for the deterioration of the renal function. The type of clamp increased the risk of deterioration of the renal function beyond 30 minutes (p = .001), being independently associated with a deterioration in the GF (OR 2.04; 95% CI: 0.94-4.47). Conclusion: With SC less than 30 min, in patients with a creatinine level, a deterioration in the renal function is not foreseeable. With prior CRI, or if a prolonged SC is foreseen, a deterioration in the renal function can be expected, thereby making it necessary to evaluate methods for renal protection (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Revuelta Suero, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rial Horcajo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Hernando, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernando Rydings, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saíz Jerez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Sánchez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez López, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar los efectos del clampaje suprarrenal (CSR) frente al clampaje infrarrenal (CIR) en la evolución de la función renal en la cirugía del aneurisma de aorta abdominal (AAA). Material y método: Estudio de cohortes retrospectivo de los AAA tratados mediante cirugía abierta electiva entre 1998 y 2011. Se analizó la creatinina sérica (mg/dl) preoperatoria y a las 24, 48, 72, 96 h postoperatorias y al alta. Se definió deterioro de la función renal como una creatinina &gt; 2 mg/dl en los pacientes con una creatinina basal normal o un aumento del doble de la creatinina basal en los pacientes con IRC previa. Se definió deterioro del filtrado glomerular (FG) como una disminución &gt; 25%. Análisis multivariable de la evolución de la función renal. Resultados: Se analizaron 464 AAA, 359 (77,4%) con CIR y 105 (22,6%) con CSR. La prevalencia de IRC preoperatoria fue similar entre ambos grupos. El tipo de clampaje no se asoció a deterioro de la función renal (CSR = 8,6% vs. CIR = 4,7%; p = 0,13) y sí al deterioro del FG (CSR = 27,6% vs. CIR = 13,4%; p = 0,001). El tiempo de clampaje, la pérdida sanguínea y la IRC preoperatoria fueron factores de riesgo independientes para deterioro de la función renal. El tipo de clampaje aumentó el riesgo de deterioro de la función renal a partir de los 30 min (p = 0,001), asociándose a deterioro del FG (OR 2,04; IC 95% 0,94-4,47) de forma independiente. Conclusión: Con CSR inferiores a 30 min, en pacientes con creatinina normal, no es previsible un deterioro de la función renal. Con IRC previa o si se espera un CSR prolongado, es esperable un deterioro de la función renal, por lo que deberían valorarse métodos de protección renal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;65(6): 211-217, nov.-dic. 2013. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117088</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución de la función renal en la cirugía del aneurisma de aorta abdominal con clampaje suprarrenal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7775</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3269</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30829^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7852^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
