<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054623</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Rivastigmine solution prescribing habits in patients with Alzheimer-type dementia in Spin (RIVASOL study)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. One of the most notable advances in the treatment of Alzheimer&#146;s disease today is the appearance of        the drugs rivastigmine, donepezil, galanthamine and memantine. Aims. We attempt to throw light on the dosage regimens,        degree of effectiveness and safety profile of rivastigmine solution by means of a retrospective, descriptive, cross-sectional        study known as the RIVASOL study. Patients and methods. The study involved 1516 patients (1386 of whom were evaluable)        who had been diagnosed with Alzheimer-type dementia (ATD) according to the criteria in the Diagnostic and Statistical        Manual of Mental Disorders, 4th edition (DSM-IV); these patients, who were selected by 157 participating physicians        (neurologists, psychiatrists and geriatricians), gave their informed written consent and had been receiving treatment with        rivastigmine solution over the past six months. The main variable was the rivastigmine solution treatment regimen and the        secondary variables included socio-demographic data, health care data and the researcher&#146;s overall clinical impression from        the time treatment was begun, among others. Results. Most of the patients who were evaluated were attended by neurologists        (57.4%). The mean time elapsed since Alzheimer&#146;s disease was diagnosed was 2.14 ± 1.68 years. After approximately one        year&#146;s treatment with rivastigmine solution, the mean score on the Folstein minimental test (MMSE) fell by 0.48 points.        Conclusions. Rivastigmine solution represents a convenient means of administration for patients with moderate and        moderately advanced phases of ATD; their cognitive performance is significantly improved with a reduction in the side effects        due to a slower and more progressive adjustment of the initial dosage</dc:description>
<dc:creator>GonzálezGutiérrez, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gobartt, AL</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Uno de los avances más relevantes en el tratamiento de la enfermedad de Alzheimer en la actualidad        lo constituyen los fármacos rivastigmina, donepecilo, galantamina y memantina. Objetivo. Intentamos esclarecer las pautas de        dosificación, grado de eficacia y perfil de seguridad de la solución de rivastigmina mediante un estudio transversal, retrospectivo        y descriptivo: el estudio RIVASOL. Pacientes y métodos. Se incluyeron 1.516 pacientes (1.386 evaluables) diagnosticados        de demencia de tipo Alzheimer (DTA) mediante los criterios del Manual diagnóstico y estadístico de los trastornos mentales, IV        edición (DSM-IV), que otorgaron su consentimiento informado por escrito y que habían estado en tratamiento con solución de        rivastigmina en los últimos seis meses, seleccionados por 157 médicos participantes (neurólogos, psiquiatras y geriatras). La        variable principal era la pauta de tratamiento de la solución de rivastigmina y las variables secundarias fueron los datos        sociodemográficos, de ámbito asistencial y la impresión clínica global del investigador (escala ICG-I) desde el inicio del tratamiento,        entre otros. Resultados. Los pacientes evaluados fueron mayoritariamente atendidos por neurólogos (57,4%). La        antigüedad media del diagnóstico de la enfermedad de Alzheimer era de 2,14 ± 1,68 años. Tras aproximadamente un año de        tratamiento con solución de rivastigmina, la puntuación media del test minimental de Folstein (MMSE) disminuyó en 0,48 puntos.        Conclusiones. La solución de rivastigmina ofrece una forma de administración oportuna para pacientes con DTA en fases        moderada y moderadamente avanzadas, y aporta una significativa mejoría del rendimiento cognitivo con disminución de los        efectos secundarios debido a un ajuste de la dosis inicial más lento y progresivo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;44(12): 705-710, jun. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054623</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hábitos de prescripción de rivastigmina en solución en pacientes con demencia de tipo Alzheimer en España (estudio RIVASOL)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2850^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2850^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
