<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-63697</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION. Analyze the concordance and validation at ten years of two coronary risk equations that use the calibrated Framingham function for Spanish population (REGICOR and DORICA) in type 2 diabetic patients. PATIENTS AND METHODS. Descriptive, longitudinal, follow-up study of a cohort over 10 years. A total of 131 diabetic patients from an urban health care center, from 35 to 65 years of age, without a background of ischemic heart disease, in whom coronary risk could be calculated before 1-01-1995. RESULTS. The real percentage of coronary events was 99% (8.8% in males and 11.1% in women). Global coronary risk calculated in the Framingham-REGICOR equation was 8.9%, it being perfectly adjusted to coronary risk in males (8.8%) and underestimated in women (9.0%). On the contrary, the Framingham-DORICA equation overestimated the global risk of the cohort (17.3% versus 9.9% of events) in both males (19.7%) and women (14.8%), their risks being significantly different (p &lt; 0.05). Concordance between the two functions was acceptable (Kappa index = 0.5). Initial application of the Framingham-DORICA function with a threshold for high coronary risk &amp;#8805; 10% and then the Framingham-REGICOR to patients listed as not high coronary risk (&lt; 10%) made it possible to correctly classify the coronary risk of the diabetic patients. CONCLUSIONS. Concordance between the Framingham-REGICOR and DORICA is acceptable, the REGICOR being that which approached the real risk of the cohort most. The sequential application of both equations correctly classified the coronary risk of diabetic patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cruces Muro, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Gómez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto Hernández, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañón Barroso, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Ochoa, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Buitrago Ramírez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">INTRODUCCIÓN. Analizar la concordancia y validación a diez años de dos ecuaciones de riesgo coronario que utilizan la función de Framingham calibrada para población española (REGICOR y DORICA) en pacientes diabéticos tipo 2. PACIENTES Y MÉTODOS. Estudio descriptivo, longitudinal, de seguimiento de una cohorte durante 10 años. Un total de 131 pacientes diabéticos de un centro de salud urbano, de 35 a 64 años de edad, sin antecedentes de cardiopatía isquémica, a quienes se les pudo calcular el riesgo coronario antes del 1-01-1995. RESULTADOS. El porcentaje real de eventos coronarios fue del 9,9% (8,8% en varones y 11,1% en mujeres). El riesgo coronario global calculado en la ecuación de Framingham-REGICOR fue del 8,9%, ajustándose perfectamente al riesgo coronario en varones (8,8%) e infraestimándolo en mujeres (9,0%). En cambio, la ecuación de Framingham-DORICA sobreestimó el riesgo global de la cohorte (17,3% frente al 9,9% de eventos), tanto en varones (19,7%) como en mujeres (14,8%), siendo sus riesgos significativamente distintos (p &lt; 0,05). La concordancia entre las dos funciones fue aceptable (índice Kappa = 0,5). La aplicación inicial de la función de Framingham-DORICA, con un umbral para riesgo coronario alto &amp;#8805; 10%, y posteriormente la de Framingham-REGICOR a los pacientes catalogados como de riesgo coronario no alto (&lt; 10%), permitieron clasificar correctamente el riesgo coronario de los pacientes diabéticos. CONCLUSIONES. La concordancia entre las funciones de Framingham-REGICOR y DORICA es aceptable, siendo REGICOR la que más se aproximó al riesgo real de la cohorte. La aplicación secuencial de ambas ecuaciones clasifica correctamente el riesgo coronario de los pacientes diabéticos</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);33(2): 50-57, feb. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-63697</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9145</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
