<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058447</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Access to the internet among nurses and type of information sought</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To identify how nurses use the Internet through a survey performed in May 2005. Method. A descriptive cross-sectional study was performed. The information source was a survey sent electronically and through surface mail. The study population consisted of nursing professionals from distinct autonomous regions. Results. The overall response rate was 40% (444 of 1,100). A total of 38.6% (184) of the nursing professionals used the Internet continually, especially men and nursing staff with a high level of English. The 5 most frequent reasons for surfing the net were searching for nursing literature (63% [264]), consulting the web pages of nursing journals (58.6% [256]), seeking information on drugs (55% [230]), seeking protocol manuals (50% [204]), and consulting the web pages of colleges of nursing (48). Conclusions. The behavior of nursing professionals is similar to that found among the general population in the "BBVA Foundation study of the Internet in Spain". Most nursing professionals are women. Male nursing professionals more frequently search for subjects related to nursing theory. Nurses use the Internet to search for nursing literature and consult journals, protocol manuals, and colleges of nursing, as well as to be familiar with the information aimed at patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferrer-Casares, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Costa-Pastrana, M. Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puchades-Simó, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marco-Gisbert, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piquer-Bosca, Cecilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Izquierdo, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canela-Ferrer, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Muñoz, Neus</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer el uso que los profesionales de enfermería hacen de internet, empleando un procedimiento por encuesta durante el mes de mayo de 2005. Método. Estudio descriptivo transversal que utiliza encuesta por correo postal y electrónico como fuente de información. La población de estudio ha sido profesionales de enfermería de diferentes comunidades autónomas. Resultados. La tasa global de respuesta ha sido del 40% (444 de 1.100). Utiliza internet de forma continua el 38,6% (184), y hay diferencias a favor de los varones y de los profesionales que dominan el inglés. Los 5 motivos más frecuentes son: búsqueda de literatura de enfermería 63% (264); consultar páginas de revistas de enfermería 58,6% (256); información acerca de fármacos 55% (230); manuales de protocolos 50% (204), y consultar páginas de colegios profesionales 48. Conclusiones. Los profesionales de enfermería tienen un comportamiento similar al encontrado en población general en "el estudio de la Fundación BBVA sobre Internet en España". La enfermería es una profesión mayoritariamente desempeñada por mujeres. Los temas que constituyen el desarrollo teórico de nuestra disciplina se consultan con mayor frecuencia por los varones. Se accede a internet para buscar literatura de enfermería, consultar revistas, manuales de protocolos, consultar colegios profesionales y para conocer la información que circula en la red dirigida a los pacientes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);18(1): 18-25, ene. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058447</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acceso a internet de los profesionales de enfermería y tipo de consultas que realizan</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9912^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36354</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200801</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
