<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139668</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cystatin C as a mortality predictor in a hypertensive population in Extremadura, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: Cystatin C has proven to be a useful parameter to evaluate renal and cardiovascular risk. Nevertheless, there are scanty reports on the utility of this test in the Spanish population. We performed a survey in a group of patients followed up in Primary Care settings. Material and methods: Prospective follow up of Primary Care attended patients recruited in 2008 and the first half of 2009. The sample included 142 subjects (mean age 64.2 ± 14.6 years, 59.2% men). In all cases, cystatin C was determined and glomerular filtration rate (GFR) was estimated through the Hoek formula. Serum creatinine was also quantified as it was GFR estimated using CKD-EPI equation. The primary objective was a combination of death and major cardiovascular events incidence. Results: There were 29 events registered (4 of them were deaths) and 9 non cardiovascular deaths. The odds ratio for the primary objective was 5.74 for the last quartile of cystatin C distribution (&gt; 1 mg/l) (P = .002), while it was 6.44 for cystatin C derived GFR (P = .008) and 5.59 for CKD-EPI estimated GFR (P = .002, Mantel-Haenszel test). Conclusions: Cystatin C showed a good association with general mortality and the incidence of cardiovascular events in the Spanish population. Nevertheless, it was not better than the observed relationship with GFR, estimated from creatinine (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Roberto Robles, Nicolás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matias Orozco, Nicolás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mena, Candido</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garcia Gallego, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cidoncha, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivos: La cistatina C ha cobrado importancia en los últimos años como parámetro para medir el riesgo renal y cardiovascular. Sin embargo, existen escasos datos sobre su utilidad en la población española. Hemos realizado el seguimiento de un grupo de pacientes atendidos en Atención Primaria a los cuales se midió este parámetro. Material y métodos: Estudio prospectivo de pacientes atendidos en Atención Primaria de Extremadura en el año 2008 y pr imera mitad de 2009. En total se seleccionaron 142 enfermos, con una edad media de 64,2 ± 14,6 años, siendo el 59,2% varones. En todos los casos se determinó cistatina C y se calculó a partir de esta el filtrado glomerular (FG) por la fórmula de Hoek. También se analizó la creatinina sérica y se estimó el FG mediante la fórmula CKD-EPI. El objetivo primario fue un combinado de la incidencia de muerte y episodios cardiovasculares en la población estudiada. Resultados: En total se produjeron 29 sucesos en el grupo estudiado (20 episodios cardiovasculares, 4 de ellos mortales, y 9 muertes no cardiovasculares). La odds ratio del objetivo combinado fue 5,74 para el último cuartil de la cistatina C (pacientes con cistatina C &gt; 1 mg/l) (p = 0,002), 6,44 para el FG calculado de cistatina C (p = 0,008) y 5,59 para el FG estimado por CKD-EPI (p = 0,002, prueba de Mantel-Haenszel). Conclusiones: La cistatina C mostró una asociación significativa con la mortalidad general y la incidencia de episodios cardiovasculares dentro de la población española. Sin embargo, esta no fue mayor que la estimación de FG a partir de la creatinina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);145(5): 198-200, sept. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139668</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cistatina C como predictor de mortalidad en población hipertensa de Extremadura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3421^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6063^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53168^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53168</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
