<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160405</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-2597</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">How do we approach the retropharyngeal abscess with mediastinal extension?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Retropharyngeal abscess is an uncommon but may develop rare complications, but potentially serious, as the invasion of adjacent structures, sepsis, mediastinitis or mediastinal extension thereof, obstruction of the airway, thrombosis of the internal jugular vein aneurysm carotid artery, requiring surgical treatment in many cases. It is presented as an example of handling, the case of a 4-year extension mediastinal abscess initially treated conservatively, but finally treated by transoral drainage of the abscess and surgical approach to the extension to the mediastinum. As remarkable complication associated with this condition developed Grisel syndrome. There is considerable controversy regarding the treatment of this disease, antibiotic treatment of conservative surgical option. For all this seems so necessary to formalize its approach more formal and present our proposal multidisciplinary approach and surgical treatment in cases of poor outcome, airway obstruction or evidence of mature abscess (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santa-Cruz, Vega</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lanza Gómez, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Obeso González, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Arguiano, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Holanda Peña, MS</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El absceso retrofaríngeo es una entidad infrecuente pero que puede desarrollar complicaciones poco comunes, pero potencialmente graves, como la invasión de estructuras contiguas, sepsis, mediastinitis o extensión mediastínica del mismo, obstrucción de la vía aérea, trombosis de la vena yugular interna y aneurisma de la arteria carótida, requiriendo tratamiento quirúrgico en muchos casos. Se presenta, como ejemplo de manejo, el caso de una niña de 4 años con absceso con extensión mediastínica tratada inicialmente de forma conservadora, pero que finalmente precisó drenaje transoral del absceso y abordaje quirúrgico de la extensión a mediastino. Como complicación reseñable asociada a esta patología desarrolló síndrome de Grisel. Existe gran controversia con respecto al tratamiento de esta patología, del tratamiento conservador antibiótico a la opción quirúrgica. Por todo esto, parece necesario protocolizar de manera más reglada su abordaje y presentamos nuestra propuesta de abordaje multidisciplinar y tratamiento quirúrgico en casos de mala evolución, obstrucción de vía aérea o evidencia de absceso maduro (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Bol. pediatr;56(237): 198-200, mar. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160405</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Cómo abordamos el absceso retrofaríngeo con extensión mediastínica?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10213^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27990^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8648^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31078^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
