<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60439</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Negative pressure therapy in wounds with enteric fistulas</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective Negative pressure therapy (VAC, vacuum assisted closure) is a method used still in our country. It consists of a system of aspirating a wound by means of a piece of foam and a few adhesive films. It allows the treatment of complex wounds, included (although this is still controversial) those with intestinal fistulas. We present 3 cases of treatment with VAC in this situation and a review of the published literature. Patients and method We have treated 10 patients, since VAC therapy was introduced into our centre of which 3 of whom had a fistula in the bed of the surgical wound. We describe the clinical information of the patients and the therapy that followed in each of the cases. Results Significant local clinical improvement of the disease, with control of the symptoms, was achieved in all 3 cases. We were able to re-operate to close the fistula in one of the patients, with subsequent good progression of the wound. In the other two cases it gave them a better quality of life although both died due to the overall complexity of their situation. Conclusions VAC therapy, although controversial in the treatment of intestinal fistulas, can help to improve the local situation of the wounds, the comfort of the patients and their general situation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Sánchez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bondía Navarro, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrasco Campos, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Pérez, Belinda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-López, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Aguilar, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos La terapia con presión negativa (VAC, vacuum assisted closure) es una modalidad poco utilizada aún en nuestro país. Consiste en un sistema de aspiración sobre la herida por medio de una esponja y unos adhesivos plásticos. Permite el tratamiento de heridas complejas incluidas aquellas con fístulas intestinales, aunque este punto es controvertido. Presentamos 3 casos de tratamiento con VAC en esta situación y un resumen de los estudios publicados. Pacientes y método Desde la introducción de la terapia VAC en nuestro centro, hemos tratado a 10 pacientes, 3 de ellos presentaban una fístula en el lecho de la herida quirúrgica. Describimos los datos clínicos de los pacientes y el tratamiento que se siguió en cada uno de los casos. Resultados En los 3 casos se consiguió una significativa mejoría clínica local de la enfermedad, con control de los síntomas. En uno de los pacientes pudimos realizar una nueva cirugía para cierre de la fístula con buena evolución de la herida. En los otros 2 casos se consiguió una mejor calidad de vida, aunque ambos fallecieron por la complejidad de la situación general. Conclusiones El tratamiento con VAC, aunque controvertido en las fístulas intestinales, puede ayudar a mejorar la situación local de las heridas, el confort de los enfermos y su situación general (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);86(1): 29-32, jul. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60439</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso de terapia con presión negativa en heridas con fístulas entéricas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13886^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29432^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200907</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
