<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83082</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Observational, Open-Label, Prospective Multicenter Study of Sexual Function in Patients Starting Treatment with Aripiprazole</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Treatment with neuroleptics maybe associated with secondary sexual dysfunction. Studies of sexual dysfunction induced by antipsychotic are important to establish the effectiveness of these agents in patients taking chronic treatments. The main objective of this study was to evaluate prospectively whether a 3 month course of aripiprazole produces changes in the sexual function of patients with schizophrenia. Methods. The efficacy analysis was performed in the intention-to-treat population (41 patients) and the perprotocol population (36 patients). The safety analysis was based on the total sample (42 patients). Results. The incidence of sexual dysfunction after 3months of treatment with aripiprazole was zero both in patients who switched therapy due to lack of efficacy and in those taking aripiprazole as a first antipsychotic. Aripiprazole led to an improvement in the symptoms of psychosis (score on the BPRS) and lower scores on the-SALSEX questionnaire. The most remarkable improvement was in delayed eyaculation /orgasm. Conclusion. During the 3 months of treatment, we observed an overall improvement in sexual performance, with a quicker recovery in men than in women, although recovery was similar in both at the end of treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Riesgo, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barber, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montejo, Á. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luque, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El tratamiento con neurolépticos puede asociarse a disfunción sexual secundaria. Los estudios sobre la disfunción sexual secundaria a antipsicóticos son importantes para poder establecer la eficiencia de estos fármacos en los tratamientos crónicos. El objetivo principal de este estudio ha sido valorar de forma prospectiva si el aripiprazol produce modificaciones en la función sexual de los pacientes con esquizofrenia 3 meses después de su instauración. Métodos. El análisis de eficacia se efectuó en dos poblaciones, la población para intención de tratamiento (41pacientes) y la población por protocolo (36 pacientes). El análisis de seguridad se ha realizado en la muestra total (42 pacientes). Resultados. Incidencia nula de disfunción sexual a los 3 meses de tratamiento con aripiprazol, tanto en los pacientes que recibían aripiprazol como primer antipsicótico como en los que habían cambiado a aripiprazol debido a una falta de eficacia de otro antipsicótico. Además de producir una mejoría de los síntomas de psicosis (escala BPRS), el aripiprazol disminuyó la puntuación en la escala SALSEX, siendo el retraso en la eyaculación u orgasmo el que presentó una mejoría media más marcada. Conclusiones. Mejoría global del funcionamiento sexual durante los 3 meses de tratamiento con aripiprazol, que muestra una recuperación más rápida en los hombres que en las mujeres, aunque ambos consiguen una recuperación similar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;38(1): 13-21, ene.-feb. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83082</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio sobre la función sexual de pacientes que inician tratamiento con aripiprazol. Estudio naturalístico, abierto, prospectivo y multicéntrico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13115^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
