<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164755</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nasal dorsum augmentation with soft implant of loose connective tissue and diced cartilage</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and Objective. Many techniques have been described to increase nasal dorsum. Autologous grafts are the preferred material in nasal reconstruction because of its biocompatibility and the reduced risk of infection and exposure. Diced cartilage technique wrapped in temporal fascia has become popular because it avoids visualization of the grafts through the skin of nasal dorsum. Our study aims to demonstrate that the loose connective tissue from the retro auricular region is a useful wrapper too, to conform with diced cartilage a soft implant, increasing the nasal dorsum to provide a natural aesthetic result. Methods. We conduct a retrospective study from December 2012 to December 2015 with 15 patients undergoing surgery via external rhinoplasty for nasal dorsum augmentation with diced cartilage of septum and auricular concha, wrapped in loose connective tissue obtained from the retro auricular region. Results were evaluated subjectively with a questionary handed to the patient and observing the photos before and after surgery. Objectively, we measured the height of the dorsum before and after surgery. Results.All the 15 patients had very satisfactory results. The average value of increased nasion level 3 months after surgery was 0.38 cm, in rinion was 0.39 cm, and in supratip was 0,41cm. These measures are maintained after 6, 12 and 18 months postoperative. Conclusions. We highlight the benefits of the loose connective tissue extracted from the retro auricular region for covering irregularities of the dorsum naturally, eliminating completely the appearance of fibrosis and strong contraction of the skin. It makes the loose connective tissue of the retro auricular region highly recommendable in the correction of nasal deformities. We also recommend diced cartilage as a valuable alternative to correct sinking of nasal dorsum after rhinoplasty, postraumatic and hereditary (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salcedo Orellana, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vásquez García, Mariana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y Objetivo. Están descritas innumerables técnicas para el aumento del dorso nasal. Los injertos autólogos son el material preferido en la reconstrucción nasal debido a su biocompatibilidad y a su menor riesgo de infección y exposición. La técnica de cartílago troceado envuelto en fascia temporal se ha popularizado porque evita la visualización de los injertos a través de la piel del dorso nasal. Nuestro estudio tiene como objetivo demostrar que también el tejido conectivo laxo retroauricular es una envoltura útil para conformar con el cartílago troceado un implante blando que aumente el dorso nasal, proporcionando un resultado estético natural. Material y Método. Realizamos un estudio retrospectivo, entre diciembre de 2012 a diciembre de 2015 con 15 pacientes sometidos a aumento de dorso nasal con cartílago troceado de septum y concha auricular envuelto en tejido conectivo laxo retroauricular, utilizando la vía de rinoplastia externa. Evaluamos los resultados de forma subjetiva con un cuestionario entregado a los pacientes y observando las fotos pre y postoperatorias a corto, medio y largo plazo. Objetivamente medimos las alturas del dorso nasal pre y postoperatoriamente. Resultados. Todos los pacientes presentaron resultados muy satisfactorios. El valor promedio de aumento del dorso nasal a los 3 meses de postoperatorio en nasion fue de 0.38 cm, en rinion de 0.39 cm y en suprapunta de 0.41 cm, manteniéndose iguales valores a los 6, 12 y 18 meses. Conclusiones. Destacamos los beneficios de la envoltura con tejido conectivo laxo retroauricular para cubrir de forma natural las irregularidades del dorso nasal, eliminando el estigma de nariz operada (fibrosis y cicatrización anómala). Su viabilidad en la zona receptora (dorso nasal) lo hace muy recomendable para la corrección de deformidades de esta zona. Es por ello que recomendamos su uso como alternativa para corregir hundimientos de dorso nasal de origen postraumatico, postrinoseptoplastia y hereditarios (nariz hipoproyectada) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;43(2): 107-116, abr.-jun. 2017. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164755</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aumento de dorso nasal con implante blando de tejido conectivo laxo y cartílago troceado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12636^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3258^s22070</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2400^s22070</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
