<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150723</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perineal approach for rectourethral fistulae after radical laparoscopic prostatectomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe our experience with the perineal approach to treat rectourethral fistulae (RUF) after radical laparoscopic prostatectomy. Materials and methods: We performed a retrospective study from 2012 to 2015 presenting 5 cases of RUF after radical laparoscopic prostatectomy. All cases required major abdominal surgery between the radical laparoscopic prostatectomy and the RUF treatment due to various complications. In no case was radiation therapy indicated prior to or after the repair. A perineal approach was performed in the 5 cases as the first option. One case required a second operation with a combined approach (abdominal and perineal) due to persistent fistulae. Results: After a minimum of 12 months of follow-up, 5 cases had resolved the RUF. Two patients presented urinary incontinence, and one patient had an anastomotic stricture that required internal urethrotomy. The other patients had no long-term complications. Conclusion: The perineal approach provides a healthy surgical field in patients who undergo multiple operations, achieving high rates of resolution of the fistulae (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tubau Vidaña, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pieras Ayala, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burgués Gasion, JP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piza Reus, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ozonas Moragues, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guimerà García, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir nuestra experiencia con el abordaje perineal para el tratamiento de las fístulas rectouretrales (FRU) tras prostatectomía radical laparoscópica. Materiales y métodos: Realizamos un estudio retrospectivo desde el año 2012 al 2015 presentando 5 casos de FRU tras prostatectomía radical laparoscópica. Todos los casos requirieron cirugías abdominales mayores entre la prostatectomía radical laparoscópica y el tratamiento de la FRU a causa de complicaciones varias. En ningún caso se indicó radioterapia previa o posterior a la reparación. Se realizó abordaje perineal en los 5 casos como primera opción. Un caso requirió una segunda intervención con abordaje combinado (abdominal y perineal) por persistencia de la fístula. Resultados: Tras un mínimo de 12 meses de seguimiento en los 5 casos se ha resuelto la FRU. 2 pacientes presentaron incontinencia urinaria y uno estenosis de la anastomosis que requirió uretrotomía interna. El resto no ha mostrado complicaciones a largo plazo. Conclusión: El abordaje perineal permite un campo quirúrgico sano en pacientes multioperados, obteniendo altas tasas de resolución de la fístula (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;40(2): 119-123, mar. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150723</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abordaje perineal de fístulas rectouretrales tras prostatectomía radical laparoscópica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29573^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29573^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29573^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
