<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106260</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">From fear of obesity to the obsesion with thinness; attitudes and diet</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Investigate the relationship between body satisfaction, attitudes toward body and obesity, diet quality and emotional health in a group of university students. The initial hypothesis was that attitudes to thinness and fear of obesity induces weight control behaviours and lower diet quality. Methods: 55 women of 19-25 years. The relationship between body mass index (BMI), diet quality (DQ), restrictive behaviours, eating attitudes (EDI-2, CIMEC) and attitudes toward obesity (AFA) was analyzed. Measures of health (SF-12) and emotional state (PNA) were also collected. Results: 10.9% of the sample had a diet classified as "poor", 83.6% "needs improvement" and 5.5% followed a "good" diet. Most of participants were dissatisfied with their weight even when their BMI was located in the normal range. Weight-restrictive behaviors were associated with risk attitudes to eating disorders, but DQ did not discriminate among high and low BMI groups, nor was related to attitudes. The more was the anxiety (negative affect), the more were the body dissatisfaction and pressures on body image. Idealized social image of thinness was linked to the stigmatization of obesity, lower dietary diversity and more restrictive practices. Conclusion: The results of this pilot study contributes to clarify the relationship between psychological and behavioral indices related to diet in university women students (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Basabe, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arroyo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alves, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Explorar la relación entre la satisfacción corporal, las actitudes hacia el cuerpo y hacia la obesidad, la calidad de la dieta y la salud emocional en un grupo de estudiantes universitarias. La hipótesis de partida fue que las actitudes favorables a la delgadez y de miedo a la obesidad inducirían conductas de control de peso y una peor calidad de la dieta. Métodos: Participaron 55 mujeres de 19-25 años. Se analizó la relación entre índice de masa corporal (IMC), calidad de la dieta (CD), conductas restrictivas, actitudes alimentarias (EDI-2, CIMEC) y hacia la obesidad (AFA). Asimismo se recogieron medidas de salud (SF12) y estado emocional (PNA). Resultados: El 10,9% de las participantes presentó una dieta "pobre", el 83,6% "necesita mejorar" y el 5,5% una dieta "buena". La mayoría estaba insatisfecha con su peso corporal aún cuando su IMC se situaba en parámetros normales. Las conductas restrictivas de control de peso se asociaron a actitudes de riesgo para trastornos de la conducta alimentaria, pero la CD no discriminó grupos de alto y bajo IMC, ni se relacionó con las actitudes. La insatisfacción corporal y las presiones sobre la imagen corporal fueron más frecuentes cuanto mayor era la ansiedad (afecto negativo). La imagen social idealizada de la delgadez se relacionó con estigmatización de la obesidad, con menor diversidad de la dieta y con más conductas restrictivas. Conclusión: Los resultados de este estudio piloto contribuyen a esclarecer la asociación entre índices psicológicos y conductuales relacionados con la alimentación en mujeres jóvenes universitarias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;27(4): 1148-1155, jul.-ago. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106260</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Del miedo a la obesidad a la obsesión por la delgadez; actitudes y dieta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5342^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14231^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1853</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9955^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4071^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
