<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050068</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pain and analgesia use in trauma and acute coronary syndrome in the out-of-hospital setting</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze pain and analgesia administration in patients with trauma or acute coronary syndrome in the out-of-hospital setting. Material and methods: An observational study was performed from January 2000 to October 2005 of all patients with trauma or a diagnosis of acute coronary syndrome attended by 061 emergency medical teams in the Autonomous Community of Andalusia (Spain). Patients who were unconscious or who had a low level of consciousness were excluded. Qualitative assessment of pain level (on a scale of 0-10) and the analgesia used was based on nursing reports. Results: This study included 2261 patients: 1369 with trauma and 892 with acute coronary syndrome. Ninety-six percent of the patients received some type of analgesia and only 4% received no analgesia. On arrival at the scene, the 061 team found mean pain scores of 7 points in patients with trauma and 6 in those with acute coronary syndrome. After on-scene treatment and analgesia administration by the 061 team, mean scores were 3 points for trauma and 2 for acute coronary syndrome. Conclusions: In the out-of-hospital setting, currently believed myths should be dispelled; patient-perceived pain should be measured and effective analgesia administered. Analgesia can be considered a quality norm in the healthcare process</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín-Castro, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayuso Batista, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Rueda, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Jiménez, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García del Águila, José Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaca, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Análisis del dolor y la analgesia utilizada en el medio extrahospitalario en el trauma y el síndrome coronario agudo. Material y metodos: Se ha realizado un estudio observacional durante el período de enero de 2000 a octubre de 2005 en la Comunidad Autónoma de Andalucía con los pacientes atendidos por los equipos de emergencias sanitarias 061. Se incluyó en el estudio a todos los pacientes atendidos por los equipos de emergencias 061 que presentaban algún traumatismo o fueron diagnosticados de síndrome coronario agudo. Se excluyó del estudio a los pacientes que presentaban un nivel de conciencia bajo o se encontraban inconscientes. Para la evaluación cualitativa de la analgesia y el grado de dolor, se utilizó el informe de enfermería y y se valoró el dolor con una escala numérica de 0 a 10. Resultados: Se ha analizado a un total de 2.261 pacientes: 1.369 traumatológicos y 892 con síndrome coronario agudo, atendidos todos ellos por los equipos de emergencias 061 de la Comunidad Autónoma de Andalucía. Al 4% de lo pacientes no se les aplicó analgesia, frente al 96% a los que sí se aplicó algún tipo de analgesia. Al inicio de la asistencia se encontró una puntuación media de 7 para el traumatismo y 6 para el síndrome coronario agudo. Al final de la asistencia, la puntuación media tras recibir medicación analgésica era de 3 para el traumatismo y 2 para el síndrome coronario agudo. Conclusiones: En el medio extrahospitalario, actualmente se han de superar los mitos y se debe medir el dolor percibido por el paciente, así como usar la analgesia de forma eficaz. Se puede considerar la analgesia una norma de calidad en el proceso asistencial</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;21(6): 287-292, nov. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050068</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dolor y analgesia en los traumatismos y el síndrome coronario agudo en el medio extrahospitalario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19283</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d798^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28561</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
