<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61514</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adolescent grandchildren with grandparents with dementia: ¿Is the disease changing relationship&#146;s nature?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Dementia is a disease with high incidence that implies a variety of changes in the family, in their roles and routine in order to adapt them to the disease. Although there is a huge literature about the main caregiver and his/her stress, less is know of other family members that are also suffering the impact of this disease. Therefore, the aim of this study is to explore the relationship adolescent grandchildren have with their grandparents that suffer this disease and the extent of their involvement in his/her care and leisure activities, comparing with a control group. Sixtyfour grandchildren from 14 to 21 years participated in the study, divided into two groups of 32 participants (healthy group vs. group with a grandparent with dementia), which coincided on gender and age of the grandchild, gender of the grandparent and family line (maternal or paternal). Results indicate that even with a similar frequency of contact, grandchildren of the healthy group perceived greater closeness with their grandparents, had a higher frequency of leisure activities and helped more to their grandparents in instrumental activities. Results are discussed in the light of the studies regarding adolescent grandchildren &#150; grandparent relationship and changes that naturally this relationship suffers (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Celdrán, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villar, Feliciano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Triadó, Carme</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La demencia es una enfermedad de gran incidencia y que comporta una serie de cambios familiares, tanto en sus roles como en su rutina para poder adaptarse a ella. Aunque existe una amplia literatura sobre la cuidadora principal de esta enfermedad y el estrés que sufre, poco se conoce de cómo otros familiares viven esta enfermedad. El objetivo de este estudio es explorar la relación que los nietos tienen en sus actividades de ocio y en actividades de cuidado con sus abuelos enfermos de demencia, comparándolo con un grupo control. Sesenta y cuatro nietos de 14 a 21 años participaron en el estudio, divididos en dos grupos de 32 participantes (grupo sano vs. grupo con abuelo con demencia) que coincidían por parejas en género del abuelo y del nieto, edad del nieto y línea familiar. Los resultados indican que aún manteniendo una frecuencia de contacto similar, los nietos del grupo sano percibieron una mayor cercanía con sus abuelos, una frecuencia de actividades de ocio superior y les ayudaban más en actividades instrumentales. Los resultados son contemplados a la luz de las investigaciones sobre relaciones entre abuelos y nietos en la adolescencia y los cambios que de forma natural se producen (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;25(1): 172-179, ene.-jun. 2009. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61514</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nietos adolescentes con abuelos con demencia: ¿La enfermedad cambia la naturaleza de la relación?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50223</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
