<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86925</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5274</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clínica y Salud (1998-2008). An Analysis of Ten Years of Publications</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Clínica y Salud has not only become over the years a publication of reference in the context of Spanish psychology but also, in view of the data that we have collected and their analysis carried out in this article, a scientific journal with a healthy and promising future. This upward trend already seemed to be emerging a decade ago, when the first bibliometric study of the publication was made, dealing with the first seven years of its existence. Therefore, it seemed appropriate to check now if that early success was an illusion or  really the beginning of a period of consolidation. Indeed, it is to studying and verifying this that we dedicate this bibliometric analysis. In this way we also hope that it will prove useful in order to draw conclusions and allow Clínica y Salud, its editorial team and all involved with the journal to continue growing in the future (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Fernández, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Clínica y Salud no sólo se ha convertido con el paso de los años en una publicación  e referencia en el entorno de la psicología española sino que, a la vista de los datos que hemos podido recabar, y cuyo análisis se ofrece en este trabajo, es también una revista científica saludable y con un prometedor futuro. Ya parecía encontrarse en esta línea ascendente hace una década, momento en el que se realizó el primer estudio bibliométrico de la  publicación que recogía la andadura de los siete primeros años de su existencia. En consecuencia, parecía pertinente comprobar ahora si aquellos primeros éxitos fueron un espejismo o el principio de la consolidación. Es precisamente al estudio y verificación de este hecho que dedicamos el presente trabajo de análisis bibliométrico esperando, asimismo, que sea útil para extraer conclusiones que permitan a Clínica y Salud, a su equipo editorial y a  sus afines, continuar creciendo en el futuro (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. salud;21(2): 141-150, jul. 2010. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86925</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Clínica y salud (1998-2008): Análisis de Diez Años de Publicaciones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50088</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37728</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201007</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
