<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109592</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relation between myocardial infarction and cyrcadian rhythm in patients attended in a prehospital emergency service</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives. The aim of this study is to analyze the presence of circadian rhythm in the time of onset of symptoms of acute myocardial infarction treated by a prehospital emergency system and the influence of modifiable cardiovascular risk factors and non-modifiable as modulators of that circadian rhythm. Patients and methods. Retrospective analysis of 709 patients clinically diagnosed with acute myocardial infarction on-site in the prehospital setting. The variables were time to onset of symptoms, age, sex, previous ischemic heart disease, hypertension, diabetes mellitus, hyperlipidemia and smoking. We analyzed the rhythm with cosinor multiple sinusoid method, with 3 harmonics (24, 12 and 8h) for the adjustment. Results. The time of onset of pain showed circadian rhythm (P &lt;,001), peaking at 10.39 and a valley at 4.28, showing a sinusoidal curve fitting bimodal aspect with a predominant morning peak and another evening one of lower amplitude. All subgroups categorized by the study variables showed circadian rhythm, with a cosine curve similar to the global infarction. Smokers had a predominantly evening peak. Conclusions. Acute myocardial infarction shows a circadian rhythm. Smoking and diabetes mellitus can modify the standard incidence rate of occurrence of myocardial infarction(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Corral Torres, Ervigio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garmendia Leiza, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrés de Llano, Jesús María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casaseca de la Higuera, Juan Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barneto Valero, María Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ardura Fernández, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo. El objetivo de este estudio es analizar la presencia de ritmo circadiano en la hora de inicio del infarto agudo de miocardio atendido por un sistema de emergencias prehospitalario, y la influencia en dicho ritmo de algunos factores de riesgo cardiovascular modificables y no modificables como posibles moduladores de ese patrón circadiano. Pacientes y método. Análisis retrospectivo de 709 pacientes con diagnóstico clínico confirmado in situ de infarto agudo de miocardio. Se analizan las variables: hora de inicio de los síntomas, edad, sexo, cardiopatía isquémica previa, hipertensión arterial, diabetes mellitus, dislipidemia y tabaquismo. El análisis de ritmo se ha efectuado utilizando un test simple de igualdad de series basado en el análisis cosinor de múltiples sinusoides, eligiendo 3 armónicos (24,12 y 8h) para su ajuste. Resultados. La hora de inicio del infarto muestra ritmo circadiano (p&lt;0,001), con un pico máximo a las 10.39 y un valle a las 4.28, mostrando una curva sinusoidal ajustada de aspecto bimodal, con un pico matinal predominante y otro vespertino de menor amplitud. Todos los subgrupos categorizados por la presencia de las variables analizadas presentaron ritmo circadiano, con una curva sinusoidal similar a la de la población global. Los pacientes fumadores muestran un pico vespertino predominante. Conclusiones. El infarto de miocardio presenta ritmo circadiano. El tabaquismo y la diabetes modifican el patrón de ritmo circadiano habitual del infarto(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);139(12): 515-521, nov. 2012. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109592</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre infarto de miocardio y ritmo circadiano en pacientes atendidos por un servicio de emergencias prehospitalario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35313^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50246</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201211</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
