<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60563</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Conclusions and perspectives</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This monograph discusses most important aspectsMaraviroc, the development and application perspectivesof this drug, as well as main questions raised in its use.Maraviroc is the first CCR5 antagonist approved fortreating HIV infection. Its imidazopyridine structureinteracts with CCR5 and induces a co-receptor conformation that prevents glycoproteins binding to theviral envelope. It has powerful antiviral activity and actson a wide spectrum of viruses with affinity for thisreceptor. This situation means that a tropism test has tobe done before treatment to define whether the patient isa carrier of R5 variants. Maraviroc is indicated in HIVinfected patients who have received previousantiretroviral treatment. It has a low toxicity and,according to preliminary data, a high genetic barrier. Theresistance mechanism is associated with changes in theV3 region which allow the virus to recognise the CCR5co-receptor bound to the Maraviroc molecule. The maincause of treatment failure is the selection of pre-existingX4 strains not detected by the reference test. Maraviroccan be combined with any other antiretroviral on themarket or in clinically advanced development. Theindication of Maraviroc in the early phases of theinfection is not currently recommended and will dependwhether it is shown to be inferior when compared othertreatments or a benefit in other pathogenic aspects, suchas recovery of CD4 lymphocytes or a reduction in viralreservoirs(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alcamí, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se discuten los aspectos más destacados de maravirocexpuestos en esta monografía, las perspectivas dedesarrollo y aplicación de este fármaco, así como lasprincipales preguntas planteadas en su utilización.Maraviroc es el primer antagonista de CCR5 aprobadopara el tratamiento de la infección por el VIH. Suestructura imidazopiridina interactúa con CCR5 e induceuna conformacion del correceptor que impide la unión delas glucoproteínas de la envuelta viral. Tiene una potenteactividad antiviral y actúa sobre un amplio espectro devirus con afinidad por este receptor. Esta circunstanciaobliga a realizar un test de tropismo previo altratamiento para definir si el paciente es portador devariantes R5. Maraviroc está indicado en pacientesinfectados por el VIH que han recibido tratamientoantirretroviral previo. Presenta una baja toxicidad y,según los datos preliminares, una alta barrera genética.El mecanismo de resistencia se relaciona con cambios enla región V3 que permiten al virus reconocer elcorreceptor CCR5 unido a la molécula de maraviroc. Lacausa principal de fallo terapéutico es la selección decepas X4 preexistentes no detectadas por la prueba dereferencia. Maraviroc puede asociarse con cualquierantirretroviral comercializado o en desarrollo clínicoavanzado. Las indicaciones de maraviroc en fasestempranas de la infección no es recomendada en elmomento actual y dependerá de la demostración de noinferioridad respecto a otros tratamientos o de unbeneficio en otros aspectos patogénicos como larecuperación de linfocitos CD4 o la reducción de los reservorios virales(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;26(supl.11): 49-54, oct. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60563</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conclusiones y perspectivas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36265^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29416^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38332^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4400</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33499^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33498^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
