<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147542</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of the present work was to analyze the financing of the outpatient pharmaceutical cost that it is generated by the consumption of medicines in a population who correspond to the 10% of the inhabitants of the Buenos Aires City in Argentina. The selected variable was the cost for the finance company (Social medicine, Medical prepaid medicine) of the consumption of medicines during the period of this study. It was carried out a retrospective study about the information obtained of a sample of 78778 prescription dispensed by 271 community pharmacies during May 2003. Using an analysis of sensibility and taking care consideration of the marked structure, it was determined the discount level and which market area could be provide it order to generate a saving of 20% in the cost of the finance company (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Filinger, Ester</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Claudio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente trabajo es analizar la financiación del costo farmacéutico ambulatorio, generado por el consumo de medicamentos, de una población correspondiente al 10% de las personas residentes en la Ciudad de Buenos Aires, en Argentina. La variable seleccionada fue el costo para el financiador (obra social o empresa de medicina prepaga) de los medicamentos consumidos durante el período del estudio. Se realizó un estudio retrospectivo de la información proveniente de una muestra de 78.778 recetas, dispensadas por 271 farmacias, durante el mes de mayo de 2003. Mediante un análisis de sensibilidad y en base a consideraciones de la estructura del mercado se determinó el nivel de descuentos y qué sector del mercado podía aportarlos para generar un ahorro del 20% en el gasto del financiador (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;6(1): 39-44, ene.-mar. 2004. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147542</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Financiamiento del Costo Farmacéutico Ambulatorio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5518^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11741^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31495^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30175^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1121</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30152^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5517^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
