<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137206</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Inappropriateness rate for colonoscopy indications in an open access unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objective: The suitability of indications for colonoscopy is important to optimize the available resources. The aim of this study was to assess the appropriateness of colonoscopy indications in an open access endoscopy unit using the EPAGE II criteria. Methods: Colonoscopies performed between October 1 and November 30, 2011 were retrospectively included. The appropriateness of the colonoscopy was established according to the EPAGE II criteria. Demographics, medical applicants, indications and relevant findings from these examinations were recorded. Results: We included 440 colonoscopies (60.8 ± 016.3 years, 54% women). The indication was appropriate in 75.4% (CI, 71-79.3%), uncertain in 13.1% (CI, 10.2-16.6%) and inappropriate in 11.4% (CI, 8.7-14.8%). In the univariate analysis, the relevant findings in the colonoscopy were associated with age, sex, colonoscopy indications and EPAGE II. In the logistic regression analysis, factors independently associated with the presence of relevant findings were age (&amp;#8805; 50 years) (OR, 1.84), male sex (OR, 2.7) and two indications, inflammatory bowel disease and post-polypectomy surveillance (P &lt; .03). The diagnostic yield of EPAGE II criteria was 37.3% for appropriate colonoscopies and 28.3% for inappropriate colonoscopies (P = .09). Conclusions: The rate of unnecessary colonoscopy is high, especially in young patients (&lt; 50 years) and some colonoscopy indications. Age (&amp;#8805; 50 years) and male sex are independently associated with the presence of relevant findings in colonoscopy. The diagnostic yield of EPAGE II criteria does not differ between appropriate and inappropriate examinations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aceituno, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espinós, Jorge C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viver, Josep M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esteve, Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andújar, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galí, Alex</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Loras, Carme</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sainz, Empar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Bañares, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo: La adecuación de las indicaciones de la colonoscopia a las recomendaciones vigentes es importante para optimizar los recursos disponibles. El objetivo fue valorar el grado de adecuación de las indicaciones de colonoscopia en una unidad de endoscopia de acceso abierto utilizando los criterios EPAGE II. Métodos: Se incluyeron de forma retrospectiva las colonoscopias realizadas entre el 1 de octubre y el 30 de noviembre de 2011. La adecuación de la colonoscopia se estableció de acuerdo con los criterios EPAGE II. Se registraron datos demográficos, médicos solicitantes, indicaciones y hallazgos relevantes de estas exploraciones. Resultados: Se incluyeron 440 colonoscopias (54% mujeres; edad, 60,8 ± 16,3 años). La indicación fue apropiada en 75,4% (IC: 71-79,3%), incierta en 13,1% (IC: 10,2-16,6%) e inapropiada en 11,4% (IC: 8,7-14,8%). En el análisis univariante la presencia de hallazgos relevantes se asoció a la edad, el sexo, la indicación y EPAGE II. En el análisis de regresión logística la edad &amp;#8805; 50 años (OR: 1,84), el sexo masculino (OR: 2,7) y 2 indicaciones, control EII y vigilancia pospolipectomía (p &lt; 0,03), se asociaron de forma independiente con la presencia de hallazgos relevantes. El rendimiento diagnóstico de los criterios EPAGE II fue 37,3% para las exploraciones consideradas apropiadas y 28,3% para las inadecuadas (p = 0,09). Conclusiones: El grado de inadecuación de la colonoscopia es elevado, sobre todo en pacientes jóvenes (&lt; 50 años) y en algunas indicaciones. La edad (&amp;#8805; 50 años) y el sexo masculino se asocian de forma independiente con la presencia de hallazgos relevantes. El rendimiento diagnóstico de los criterios EPAGE II no fue diferente entre exploraciones adecuadas e inadecuadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;38(5): 313-319, mayo 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137206</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Grado de adecuación de las indicaciones de la colonoscopia en una unidad de acceso abierto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3142^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33125^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53221^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50215^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29341^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
