<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-27572</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of Taenia solium antibodies in humans and in pigs in an endemic area of Colombia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Cysticercosis (CC) caused by Taenia solium in humans and in pigs is endemic in many rural communities in developing countries. The use of Western blot assays (WB) to determine T. solium antibodies has become the best serological tool available to date for identifying positive individuals in field conditions. Aims. The aim of this study was to determine the prevalence of T. solium antibodies in humans and in pigs in two rural communities in Antioquia, Colombia. Patients, materials and methods. Serological identification of humans and pigs with T. solium antibodies was performed using WB assays in two communities in Ituango, Antioquia. During the study, demographic variables, housing and health conditions were taken into account. Contingency tables were drawn up using &amp;#967;2  to compare the proportion of seronegative individuals and seropositive individuals with headache, fainting or convulsions. Results. The prevalence of human and porcine CC obtained was 2.23 and 6.82% in Pascuita and 1.17 and 2.33% in Guacharaquero, both respectively. Of the 11 WB-positive patients evaluated by imaging techniques, two individuals were found to have single calcifications in the TAC scan and RMI showed another to have an unspecified lesion. The prevalence of infection in humans and in pigs in two rural communities in the north of the district of Antioquia, Colombia, shows that CC is endemic and that steps must be taken to control it (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La cisticercosis por Taenia solium en humanos y cerdos es endémica en muchas comunidades rurales de los países en desarrollo. El uso de la inmunoelectrotransferencia (EITB) -para la determinación de anticuerpos contra T.solium-se ha constituido en la mejor herramienta serológica disponible hasta el momento para la identificación de individuos positivos en condiciones de campo. Objetivo. Determinar la prevalencia de anticuerpos para T. solium en humanos y cerdos en dos comunidades rurales de Antioquia, Colombia. Pacientes, materiales y métodos. Mediante la aplicación de la prueba del EITB, se realizó la identificación serológica de humanos y cerdos con anticuerpos para T. solium en dos comunidades de Ituango, Antioquia. Se tuvieron en cuenta variables demográficas, características de las viviendas y condiciones sanitarias. Se hicieron tablas de contingencia usando la prueba de 2 para comparar la proporción de individuos seronegativos e individuos seropositivos con cefalea, desmayos o convulsiones. Resultados. Se obtuvo una prevalencia para cisticercosis humana y porcina, respectivamente, del 2,23 y 6,82 por ciento en Pascuita y de 1,17 y 2,33 por ciento en Guacharaquero. De 11 pacientes con EITB positivo evaluados mediante imágenes, se encontraron dos individuos con calcificaciones únicas en la tomografía computarizada y uno con una lesión inespecífica en la resonancia magnética. La prevalencia de la infección en humanos y en cerdos en dos comunidades rurales al norte del departamento de Antioquia, Colombia, demuestra que la cisticercosis es endémica y que se necesitan emprender acciones que permitan su control (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;36(8): 706-709, abr. 2003. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de anticuerpos para Taenia solium en humanos y cerdos en una zona endémica colombiana</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Palacio, LG</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agudelo Florez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-27572</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d916</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22669</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3137</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13933</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22410</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36565</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
