<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127987</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Possible relationship between alopecia areata and enterovirus infections</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: alopecia areata is an autoimmune disease of unknown etiology that is associated to other autoimmune diseases. Hand-foot-mouth disease is a common viral infection in children caused by several enterovirus serotypes, and it is sometimes associated to onychomadesis. This study intends to investigate an increase in cases of alopecia areata after an outbreak of hand-foot-mouth disease in our environment. Methods: identification of patients under 14 years old diagnosed with hand-foot-mouth disease and/or alopecia areata in a Primary Care Service Area between 1/1/2011 and 31/12/2012. Review of medical records, collecting date of birth and diagnosis, age at diagnosis and clinical characteristics. Results: forty-nine patients diagnosed with hand-foot-mouth disease and 7 diagnosed with alopecia areata were found. An outbreak of hand-foot-mouth disease was confirmed with 42 cases within a period of 8 weeks. A subsequent increase in cases of alopecia areata (4 cases within 4 weeks, compared with 3 cases over the 11 months before and none during the previous year) was observed. Conclusions: following an outbreak of hand-foot-mouth disease an increased number of cases of alopecia areata was observed. This fact, coupled with the association of alopecia areata with other autoimmune diseases, and the relationship found between enterovirus infections and autoimmune diseases such as type 1 diabetes mellitus poses a possible causal relationship between enterovirus infections and alopecia areata, and a possible component of autoimmunity in onychomadesis associated to hand-foot-mouth disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Yuste Ara, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodrigo Val, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Clemente Roldán, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conde Barreiro, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Pelegrín, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la alopecia areata es una enfermedad autoinmune de etiología desconocida que se asocia a otras enfermedades autoinmunes. La enfermedad mano-pie-boca es una infección viral frecuente en la edad pediátrica, causada por diferentes serotipos de enterovirus y que en ocasiones asocia onicomadesis. El presente estudio pretende comprobar un incremento de los casos de alopecia areata tras un brote de enfermedad mano-pie-boca en nuestro entorno. Material y métodos: identificación de los pacientes menores de 14 años diagnosticados de enfermedad mano-pie-boca y/o alopecia areata en un área de salud entre el 1 de enero de 2011 y el 31 de diciembre de 2012. Revisión de historias clínicas, recogiendo fecha de nacimiento y diagnóstico, edad al diagnóstico y características clínicas. Resultados: se encontraron 49 pacientes diagnosticados de enfermedad mano-pie-boca y siete diagnosticados de alopecia areata. Se confirmó un brote de enfermedad mano-pie-boca con 42 casos en un periodo de ocho semanas. Se observó un incremento posterior de los casos de alopecia areata (cuatro casos en las cuatro semanas siguientes, frente a tres casos a lo largo de los 11 meses previos y ninguno durante el año anterior). Conclusiones: tras un brote de enfermedad mano-pie-boca se observó un incremento del número de casos de alopecia areata. Este hecho, unido a la asociación de la alopecia areata con otras enfermedades autoinmunes y a la relación encontrada entre infecciones por enterovirus y procesos autoinmunes como la diabetes mellitus tipo 1, plantea una posible relación causal entre infecciones por enterovirus y alopecia areata, así como un posible componente de autoinmunidad en la onicomadesis asociada a la enfermedad mano-pie-boca (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;16(63): e97-e93, jul.-sept. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127987</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Posible relación entre alopecia areata e infecciones por enterovirus</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4849^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4849^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4849^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4849^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6381^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6381^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d509^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24529^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6381^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d509^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4849^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4849^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
