<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157572</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hirschsprung disease with debut in adult age as acute intestinal obstruction: case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hirschsprung's disease is characterized by absence of ganglion cells in submucosal and myenteric plexus of distal bowel. Most cases become manifest during the neonatal period, but in rare instances, this disease is initially diagnosed in adult age. It usually presents as severe constipation with colonic dilatation proximal to the aganglionic segment. The treatment is surgical, removing the aganglionic segment and restoring continuity of digestive tract. The disease rarely presents as an acute intestinal obstruction. We report a case not previously diagnosed, which presented as a massive colonic dilatation with a maximum diameter of 44 cm, with imminent risk of drilling that forced to perform an emergency surgery. We include a review of existing literature (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Pérez, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Ruiz, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pareja Ciuró, Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tallón Aguilar, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Moreno, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliva Mompeán, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padillo Ruiz, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad de Hirschsprung consiste en la ausencia de células ganglionares en los plexos submucosos y mientérico del intestino. Suele diagnosticarse en el periodo neonatal, siendo muy poco frecuente que se descubra en el adulto. Suele presentarse como estreñimiento severo con dilatación cólica proximal al segmento agangliónico. El tratamiento es quirúrgico, extirpando el segmento agangliónico y restableciendo la continuidad del tubo digestivo. En muy raras ocasiones, esta enfermedad se presenta como un cuadro de obstrucción intestinal aguda. Presentamos el caso de un paciente, no diagnosticado previamente, que debutó como un cuadro de dilatación cólica masiva, con un diámetro máximo de 44 cm, con riesgo de perforación inminente, lo que motivó la realización de una cirugía urgente. Incluimos una revisión de la literatura existente al respecto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;108(11): 742-746, nov. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157572</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad de Hirschsprung en el adulto que debuta como obstrucción intestinal aguda. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23438^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6786^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8699^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23438^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3113^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6786^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22831^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7991^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6786^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8699^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7578^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8141^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8699^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7578^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7578^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
