<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058345</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Coping and psychological adaptation in parents of children with cleft palate</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The unexpected birth of a son with a chronic malformation such as cleft and lip palate has an enormous impact on family dynamics and the psychological organization of the parents. This study tries to give account of some of these aspects in a sample of 36 parents of children with a diagnosis of cleft lip and palate. Coping strategies in these parents and their personality styles, allow us to describe stable ways of response on individuals that can be excellent indicators of the way in which parents confront this new reality, as well as of its effects on the medium and long terms</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Patró Hernández, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Limiñana Gras, Rosa M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corbalán Berná, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El inesperado nacimiento de un hijo con una malformación crónica como la fisura palatina tiene un enorme impacto en la dinámica familiar y en la organización psicológica de los padres. Este estudio pretende dar cuenta de algunos de estos aspectos en una muestra de 36 padres y madres de un niño con un diagnóstico de fisura labio velo palatina. Las estrategias de afrontamiento en estos padres y sus estilos de personalidad, permiten describir modos de respuesta estables de los sujetos, que pueden resultar excelentes indicadores del modo en que los padres afrontan esta nueva realidad, y de sus efectos a medio y largo plazo</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;23(2): 201-206, dic. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058345</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Afrontamiento y adaptación psicológica en padres de niños con fisura palatina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10742^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10479^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d231^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3879^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10476</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29352^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
