<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130114</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Principles of antisepsis, disinfection and sterilization</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article aims to provide a brief review of the main concepts on which the prevention and control of infection are based. Antisepsis comprises a set of techniques aimed at the total sterilization, or at most, disinfection, removing germs that contaminate an environment. Both procedures must be preceded by an environmental cleanup in the location in which they intend to be applied. The disinfection is carried out using biocides or germicides. Antimicrobial chemicals, that have mechanisms of action and resistances very similar to antibiotics, are generating concern due to the possibility of crossing genetic information that aggravates the problem of bacterial resistance. Most biocides can act as antiseptics, and applied to skin tissue, or disinfectants on inanimate materials. The spectrum of action of germicides depends on the product itself and external controllable factors: temperature, concentration, exposure time, etc. Sterilization techniques are primarily physical, by exposing the material to steam, or sterilizing gas, using autoclaves. Major advances are the use of low temperatures with shorter exposure times, in parallel with technological advances in instrumentation in order to avoid high temperatures and high use rotations due to workload (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Celorrio-Pascual, José-Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lapresta Moros, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solano Bernad, Víctor-Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Navarrete, María-Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo pretende realizar una breve revisión de los principales conceptos en los que se basan las medidas de prevención y control de la infección. La antisepsia comprende el conjunto de técnicas destinadas a la eliminación total (esterilización) o mayoritaria (desinfección) de los gérmenes que contaminan un medio. Ambos procedimientos deben ir precedidos de una limpieza del medio donde se vayan a aplicar. La desinfección se lleva a cabo por medio de biocidas o germicidas, sustancias químicas antimicrobianas cuyos mecanismos de acción y resistencia son muy similares a los de los antibióticos. Esta similitud está generando inquietud por la posibilidad de cruce de información genética que agrave el problema de las resistencias bacterianas. La mayoría de los biocidas pueden actuar como antisépticos, aplicados sobre piel y tejidos, o desinfectantes, sobre materiales inanimados. El espectro de acción de los germicidas depende de las características propias del producto y de factores externos controlables: temperatura, concentración, tiempo de exposición, etc. Las técnicas de esterilización son fundamentalmente de carácter físico, a través de autoclaves que exponen el material a vapor o gas esterilizante. Los mayores avances están en las exposiciones a bajas temperaturas con tiempos más cortos de exposición, en paralelo con los avances tecnológicos de instrumentación con materiales que no soportan temperaturas elevadas y con rotaciones de uso altas, por la presión asistencial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;32(10): 681-688, dic. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130114</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fundamentos de antisepsia, desinfección y esterilización</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27916^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27987^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27916^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27987^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27916^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27840^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27840^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d903^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d903^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
