<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158957</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nontraumatic posterior urethral stenosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Posterior urethral stenoses and contractures are complications after treatment of benign prostatic hyperplasia (BPH), localised prostate cancer (PCa), and orthotopic neobladder formation, compromising prognosis and functional outcomes. Objectives: To identify factors related to aetiology, prevention and treatment of non-traumatic posterior urethral stenosis and contractures. Acquisition of evidence: Review of the published evidence related to posterior urethral stenosis and contractures after PCa treatment, BPH therapies and orthotopic neobladder formation. PubMed database search with English and Spanish papers considered. Cohort studies, case series, prospective and retrospective studies and review papers were included. Synthesis of evidence: Posterior urethral stenoses and contractures are common, leading to significant morbidity. A worsening on voiding quality should rise some concerns. Careful surgical and/or radiotherapic techniques prevent their development. Endoscopic therapies are the initial approach, with complex urethroplasties often required. Subsequent urinary incontinence, the most important sequelae, may need artificial sphincters. Conclusions: Non-traumatic posterior urethral stenoses could be important complications, potentially compromising the outcomes of initial therapy. They could require complex surgeries leading to urinary incontinence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Portillo Martín, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velarde Ramos, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Illanes, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos-Juanatey, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La enfermedad estenótica de la uretra posterior es una complicación no menor de los tratamientos aplicados en la hipertrofia benigna de próstata, cáncer de próstata (CaP) y tras neovejigas ortotópicas, pudiendo comprometer el resultado funcional miccional. Objetivos: Identificar los factores etiológicos de la enfermedad estenótica de causa no traumática de la uretra posterior, su prevención y su tratamiento. Adquisición de la evidencia: Se han revisado los artículos indexados en PubMed en idiomas inglés y español de las secuelas estenóticas de la uretra posterior tras los tratamientos aplicados en el cáncer de próstata, en la cirugía de la hipertrofia benigna de próstata y de las neovejigas ortotópicas. Se han incluido estudios de cohortes, revisiones de artículos y estudios prospectivos y retrospectivos, con el mayor número de casos. Síntesis de la evidencia: La evidencia obtenida en la bibliografía es que la frecuencia de aparición de dichas estenosis no es despreciable, que su morbilidad puede ser importante y que debe sospecharse tras la pérdida de la calidad miccional. Su prevención empieza con una apropiada técnica quirúrgica y/o radioterápica. Aunque el tratamiento endoscópico es el preferido inicialmente, en ocasiones se requieren uretroplastias complejas abiertas, siendo la incontinencia urinaria la secuela más importante, pudiendo requerir implantes de esfínteres artificiales. Conclusiones: Las estenosis no traumáticas de la uretra posterior son complicaciones que pueden ser importantes, llegando a comprometer el éxito del tratamiento inicial de la enfermedad de base y requiriendo en ocasiones de cirugías complejas que pueden llevar a la incontinencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;41(1): 1-10, ene.-feb. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158957</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patología estenótica no traumática de la uretra posterior</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11913^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14924^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14923^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
