<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161726</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors associated with condom use among young men who have sex with men</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The increase of HIV infections in Brazil among Men who have Sex with Men (MSM), aged between 15 and 24 years, has the low condom use as one of the factors. This research aims to describe the factors that are associated or not to condom use among young MSM. Methodology: Descriptive study, of quantitative nature, using sample for convenience. The scenario was six LGBT nightclubs in the city of Rio de Janeiro - Brazil, selected through a gay nightclub guide. Participants are MSM in the age group between 18 and 24 years who reported having had sex with men. Data collection took place during October 2012. A total of 220 young people were interviewed with the aid of a data collection instrument. Data analysis was performed through the EpiInfo program. Results: Condom use is associated with disease prevention. The justifications for not using condom in oral sex, in the first and last sexual relation were discomfort, lack of experience/knowledge and confidence in the partner respectively. Conclusion: This study indicates that the interviewees are susceptible to HIV infection when they abandon or do not use the condom because of their lack of knowledge and/or experience. Guidance and clarification activities with informative material are relevant, considering the vulnerability of this group to STIs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pinheiro, Carina D&#146; Onofrio Prince</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Spindola, Thelma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Francisco, Marcio Tadeu Ribeiro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fonte, Vinícius Rodrigues Fernandes da</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barcelos, Nathália de Souza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Costa, Cristiane Maria Amorim</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El aumento de las infecciones por el VIH en Brasil entre los hombres que tienen sexo con hombres (HSH), en el grupo de edad de15-24 años de edad, tiene como uno de los factores la baja utilización del condón. Objetivo: Describir los factores que se asocian o no con el uso del condón entre los jóvenes HSH. Metodologíia: Estudio descriptivo, cuantitativo, con el uso de una muestra de conveniencia. El escenario fue seis discotecas dirigidas a un publico de lesbianas, gays, bisexuales, travestis y transexuales, en la ciudad de Rio de Janeiro - Brasil, seleccionados mediante un guía de discotecas gays. Los participantes fueran hombres que hacen sexo com hombres, con edades entre 18-24 años. La recolección de datos se realizó durante el mes de octubre de 2012. Hemos entrevistado a 220 jóvenes con la ayuda de un instrumento de recolección de datos. Se realizó el análisis utilizando el programa EpiInfo. Resultados: El uso del preservativo está asociado a la prevención de enfermedades. La falta del uso del condón en el sexo oral, en la primera y última relación sexual fue justificada por la incomodidad que causa, la falta de experiencia/conocimiento y confianza en el compañero, respectivamente. Conclusión: El estudio indica que los entrevistados son susceptibles a la infección por VIH cuando abandonan el uso de condones por su confianza en el compañero, la falta de conocimiento y/o experiencia. Orientación de las acciones y aclaraciones con materiales de información son relevantes, teniendo en cuenta la vulnerabilidad de este grupo a las infecciones de transmisión sexual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;16(46): 50-64, abr. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161726</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores asociados con el uso del preservativo entre hombres jóvenes que tienen sexo con hombres</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30772^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24960^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3294^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32189^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
