<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145445</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Differential diagnosis of cutaneous mycoses</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The clinical manifestations of superficial mycoses span a wide spectrum. In each anatomical site, the fungus adopts very similar behavior that is replicated in each new patient. This allows us to establish concrete guidelines for the differential diagnosis in each localization. The bases for clinical suspicion are the morphology of the lesions, clinical course and sometimes epidemiology. Complementary studies, including Wood&#146;s light examination, direct visualization of scrapings to detect fungi, mycological culture and, in the most complex cases, histological evaluation of the lesion, are useful in establishing the definitive diagnosis. From an eminently practical point of view, we review the various mycoses according to the area of integument affected and, after a brief clinical description, in which we stress the aspects around which we center diagnostic considerations, we enumerate the various nosological entities that can cause confusion. Special attention is paid to the mainly morphological features and characteristics of the clinical course that are useful when making a practical differential diagnosis. With the same aim, we evaluate the most commonly implicated dermatoses, leaving aside those which, due to their infrequency or exceptionality, fall outside the scope of this review (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Fraile, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Unamuno-Pérez, Pablo de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Dorado, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las manifestaciones clínicas de las micosis superficiales abarcan un amplio espectro. De esta forma, en cada ubicación anatómica el hongo adopta un comportamiento muy similar y repetible en cada nuevo paciente, lo que nos permite establecer pautas de diagnóstico diferencial concretas según la localización. La morfología de las lesiones, la evolución del cuadro y, en ocasiones, la epidemiología, sentarán las bases de la sospecha clínica. Los estudios complementarios, incluyendo básicamente la exploración con luz de Wood, la visión directa de escamas para detectar hongos, el cultivo micológico y, en los casos más complejos, la valoración histológica de la lesión, serán útiles para establecer el diagnóstico definitivo. Desde un punto de vista eminentemente práctico, se revisan las micosis según la zona del tegumento afectada y, tras una breve descripción clínica, en la que se resaltan los aspectos sobre los que se centran las consideraciones diagnósticas, se enumeran las diferentes entidades nosológicas con las que se puede confundir. Se presta especial atención fundamentalmente a los rasgos morfologicoevolutivos, útiles a la hora de plantear un diagnóstico diferencial práctico. Con este mismo ánimo, se valoran las dermatosis más habitualmente implicadas, y se obvian aquellas que por su infrecuencia o excepcionalidad dermatológica escapan del ámbito de esta revisión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);126(supl.1): 30-36, ene. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145445</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico diferencial de las micosis cutáneas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9364^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3901^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14396^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3901^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14391^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30899^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9364^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30899^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27152^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
