<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-68036</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hypertriglyceridemia is a lipid disorder frequently found in type 2 diabetes mellitus. Lipoprotein lipase plays a central role in plasma triglyceride catabolism. Many polymorphic sites in the lipoprotein lipase gene, such as HindIII and S447X, have been associated with dyslipidemia in different populations. Our objective was to study the possible effect of these polymorphisms on plasma lipid levels in type 2 diabetes mellitus. Lipid and glycemic profi les of 83 patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus were analysed. These patients were classifi ed according to their fasting triglyceride levels as normotriglyceridemics (n= 32), with triglyceride values &lt;150 mg/dl, or hypertriglyceridemics (n= 51), with triglyceride values ³150 mg/dl. The lipoprotein lipase HindIII and S447X genotypes were identifi ed by polymerase chain reaction and restriction fragment length polymorphism analysis. Our results show that H+/H+ genotype of HindIII polymorphism was more frequent in the hypertriglyceridemic group compared to the normotriglyceridemic group: 0.745 vs. 0.500, respectively (p= 0.023). In the total sample of patients, H+/H+ homocygotes (n= 54) showed higher triglyceride levels compared to H&#150; allele carriers (n=29): 220±127 mg/dl vs. 165±84 mg/dl, respectively (p= 0.01). Moreover, H+/S447 haplotype carriers (n= 54) showed higher triglyceride values: 220±127 mg/dl compared to those found in H&#150;/X447 (n= 9) and H&#150;/S447 (n= 20) patients: 154±95 mg/dl and 169±83 mg/dl; p= 0.026 and p= 0.036, respectively. As conclusion, this study suggests an association between genetic variations in the lipoprotein lipase locus and plasma triglyceride levels in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Soland, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arriaga, S. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almará, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bouvet, B. R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hipertrigliceridemia es una alteración lipídica frecuente en la diabetes mellitus tipo 2. La lipoproteinlipasa cumple una función esencial en el catabolismo de los triglicéridos plasmáticos. Los polimorfi smos HindIII y S447X en el gen de la lipoproteinlipasa se han asociado con dislipidemia en diferentes poblaciones. El objetivo era evaluar el posible efecto de estos polimorfi smos sobre el perfi l lipídico de la diabetes mellitus tipo 2. En cuanto a la metodología, se analizaron los lípidos plasmáticos y el control glucémico de 83 pacientes con diabetes mellitus tipo 2. Los sujetos se consideraron normotrigliceridémicos (n= 32) o hipertrigliceridémicos (n= 51) según si sus valores en ayunas de triglicéridos (mg/dL) eran &lt;150 o ³150, respectivamente. Los genotipos HindIII (alelos H+ y H&#150;) y S447X (alelos S y X) se identifi caron por reacción en cadena de la polimerasa y análisis de los polimorfi smos de longitud de los fragmentos de restricción. Como resultados, el genotipo H+/H+ fue más frecuente en el grupo hipertrigliceridémico que en el normotrigliceridémico: 0,745 frente a 0,500, respectivamente (p= 0,023). En la muestra total de pacientes, los homocigotos H+/H+ presentaron mayores niveles de triglicéridos que los portadores del alelo H&#150;: 220±127, frente a 165±84, respectivamente (p= 0,01). Los portadores del haplotipo H+/S447 (n= 54) mostraron unos valores de triglicéridos de 220±127, superiores a los de los sujetos H&#150;/X447 (n= 9), de 154±95, y a los de los H&#150;/S447 (n= 20), de 169±83 (p= 0,026 y p= 0,036, respectivamente). En conclusión, este estudio sugiere una asociación entre variaciones genéticas en el locus de la lipoproteinlipasa y niveles de triglicéridos en la diabetes mellitus tipo 2</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;24(3): 231-236, mayo-jun. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-68036</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2894^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1812^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8245^s22007</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23686^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1812^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11547^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14679^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2834^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2834^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8245^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23686^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
