<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60399</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Low birth weight is a risk factor for type 1 diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and aim: Over recent years, the increasing incidence of type 1 diabetes mellitus (T1DM) has been associated with different factors, particularly increased obesity in childhood. The aim of this study was to find out if there was any relationship between birth weight, body mass index (BMI) increase during the first two 3 years of life, and BMI at diabetes onset with age at diagnosis, in a cohort of children diagnosed with T1DM. Material and method: Data from 100 Caucasian children with T1DM of both sexes (57 boys, 43 girls) between 10 months and 16 years of age, mean age 84.45 months (SD; 52.4), were studied. We analysed the following variables: age at diagnosis, gestational age, weight and height at birth, at two years of age and at diabetes diagnosis, expressed as SD scores (SDS). Results: All children were between 38&#150;40 weeks of gestational age. Diabetic patients have lower birth weight (&amp;#8722;2.88 ((&amp;#8722;0.51)&#150;(&amp;#8722;0.066)) and lower BMI at birth compared with healthy children &amp;#8722;0.5 ((&amp;#8722;0.77)&#150;(&amp;#8722;0.23)). Diabetic children have a significant increase in BMI during the first two years of life (4.58 versus 2.17; P&lt;0.001). Children with the lowest BMI at birth (12.77 versus 13.06; P&lt;0.006) are the youngest at onset of the disease. BMI at diagnosis was not related to any of the variables studied. There were no gender differences either. Conclusions: The low BMI at birth and the later increase in the following years of life seem to be related to intrauterine environment as a risk factor for T1DM (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vázquez, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carpintero, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutierrez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Cuartero, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Vergaz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carvajal, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herranz, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo: En los últimos años el aumento de la incidencia de diabetes mellitus tipo 1 (DM1) se ha relacionado con un incremento de la obesidad en la población infantil, entre otros factores. El objetivo del presente trabajo ha sido determinar de forma retrospectiva en la población española, en pacientes diagnosticados de DM1 de la Comunidad Autónoma de Madrid, la posible relación entre el peso del recién nacido, el incremento del índice de la masa corporal (IMC) en los 2 primeros años de vida y el IMC al comienzo de la enfermedad con la edad de presentación de la diabetes. Material y método: Participaron 100 niños diagnosticados de DM1 de ambos sexos (57 niños y 43 niñas), de raza caucásica, con una edad media de 84,45 meses (desviación estándar [DE] de 52,4). Se recogieron las siguientes variables: edad al comienzo de la enfermedad, edad gestacional, peso y talla de recién nacido, a los 2 años de vida y al comienzo de la enfermedad. Resultados: Los niños diagnosticados de DM1 tienen menor peso al nacer &amp;#8722;0,288 (&amp;#8722;0,51 a &amp;#8722;0,066) y menor IMC (puntuación de DE) al nacer que la población sana &amp;#8722;0,5 (&amp;#8722;0,77 a &amp;#8722;0,23). Además de un incremento mayor del IMC hasta los 2 años (4,58% frente a 2,17%; p&lt;0,001). Los niños con menor IMC al nacer (12,77% frente a 13,06%; p&lt;0,006) comienzan antes con la enfermedad. No se ha encontrado correlación entre el IMC al comienzo y el resto de las variables estudiadas. Conclusiones: El menor IMC al nacer de los pacientes con diabetes mellitus estudiados y el incremento de peso que se produce en los 2 primeros años de vida en esta población podría implicar a algunos factores durante la vida fetal como factor de riesgo de DM1 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);70(6): 542-546, jun. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60399</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El bajo peso al nacer es un factor de riesgo de diabetes mellitus tipo 1</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
