<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-66940</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine the level of hypovitaminosis D in adult healthy women attended in primary care and their associated factors. Design. Cross-sectional, descriptive study. Setting. A neighbourhood of Barcelona, Spain, with a socially deprived population with a high percentage of immigrants, and urban factors which meant that they lived with hardly any sunlight. Participants. Women between 15-50 years seen between February and March 2005. Measurements and results. Primary: residence time (years), skin phototype, sun exposure, vitamin D deficiency pain type, calcium, vitamin D consumed, and measurement of serum 25-hydroxyvitamin D (25[OH]D) or calcidiol and parathyroid hormone (PTH) if (25[OH]D) was &lt;10 ng/mL; 94 women were included. Mean age: 33 years (SD, 7.8); 62.8% immigrants (mean years of residence, 11.5). Mean (25[OH]D), 14.0 ng/mL (95% CI, 12.5-15.5). Skin phototype V-VI was associated with low levels of (25[OH]D) (P=.001). None of the women stated that they consumed the recommended amount of vitamin D and only 46% the recommended amount of calcium. Sun exposure of &gt;4 hours/week: 37%. Sixteen percent had musculo-skeletal pain. No relationship was found between vitamin D levels and immigration. All the women had (25[OH]D) levels of &lt;40 mg/mL, 47.9% had insufficient (25[OH]D), 10-20 ng/mL, and 37.2% were deficient: £10 mg/mL. PTH was within the normal range. Conclusions. All the women had low levels of vitamin D, more than a third of these, deficient. No relationship with immigration was found. A relationship was established between skin phototype V-VI and (25[OH]D) deficiency. None of the cases consumed the recommended amounts of vitamin D (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romagosa Pérez-Portabella, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gudiña Escudero, Nieves </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilamala Muns, Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Solanellas, Matilde</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Feliu, Ricard</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pozo Díaz, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zabaleta del Olmo, Edurne</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar el nivel de hipovitaminosis D en mujeres adultas sanas atendidas en atención primaria y los factores relacionados. Diseño. Estudio descriptivo, transversal. Emplazamiento. Barrio de Barcelona con población sociodeprimida con alto porcentaje de inmigración y con factores urbanísticos que condicionan que exista poca luz solar. Participantes. Mujeres de 15-50 años atendidas entre los meses de febrero y marzo de 2005. Mediciones y resultados principales. Tiempo (en años) de residencia, fototipo cutáneo, exposición solar, dolor típico por hipovitaminosis D, consumo de calcio y vitamina D, y medición de 25-hidroxivitamina D (25[OH]D) o calcidiol séricos, así como de hormona paratiroidea (PTH) si la (25[OH]D) era inferior a 10 ng/ml. Se incluyeron 94 mujeres, con una edad media de 33 años (DE = 7,8 años). El 62,8% de ellas eran inmigrantes (mediana de años de residencia, 11,5). El promedio de (25[OH]D) fue de 14,0 ng/ml (intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 12,5-15,5). El fototipo cutáneo V-VI se asoció con niveles bajos de (25[OH]D) (p = 0,001). Ninguna mujer refirió realizar los consumos recomendados de vitamina D y sólo un 46% de los de calcio. El 37% tenía una exposición solar superior a 4 horas a la semana. El 16% presentó dolor musculosquelético. No se encontró relación alguna entre concentraciones de vitamina D e inmigración. Todas las mujeres mostraron valores de (25[OH]D) inferiores a 40 mg/ml, un 47,9% presentó insuficiencia de (25[OH]D) de 10-20 ng/ml, y un 37,2% presentó deficiencia £ 10 mg/ml. La PTH se encontraba dentro de la normalidad. Conclusiones. Todas las mujeres presentaron hipovitaminosis D y un tercio de ellas tuvo, además, deficiencia de vitamina D. No se ha encontrado relación alguna con la inmigración. Se ha constatado que existe una asociación entre fototipo cutáneo V-VI y deficiencia de (25[OH]D). En ningún caso las pacientes atendidas realizaron los consumos recomendados de vitamina D (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;40(8): 393-399, ago. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-66940</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15210^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4716</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200808</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
