<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106409</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Principles of evaluation and functional results in upper extremity replantation surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to evaluate functional and subjective outcome after upper limb replantation, with assessment or range of motions, grip strength, and additional functional tests. Forty-one patients, mean age 44.8 years old, with upper limb amputations were treated in our hospital with replantation between January 2005 and December 2009. Functional results were assessed by modified Mayo scoring system for thumb, fingers and hand amputations. Proximal amputations were evaluated according to the criteria of Chen. Subjective results were documented in all patients by Russell´s Questionnaire. Most of the injuries were caused by avulsion forces and 30 (74 %) were work related. The final survival rate was 85 % (35 patients); we include 2 patients who have had immediate foot transplantations. Using modified Mayo score system the outcome was good in thumb patients and fair in fingers and hand amputations. According to Chen´s criteria the result was excellent in 1 forearm amputation and fair in 2 patients. Nineteen patients had returned to work, their time-off work averaged was 10 months. Patient satisfaction was rated as better than expected and satisfactory in 27 patients. Outcomes of replantation must be better than revision amputation. Although functional outcomes were moderate, most of patients were able to use their hands to perform some work and daily living activities (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Contreras Pedraza, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrio, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matarranz Faya, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García del Pozo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camporro Fernández, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo es evaluar nuestros resultados funcionales y subjetivos en pacientes sometidos a reimplante de miembro superior. Medimos rango de movilidad articular, fuerza de la prensión y otros tests en 41 pacientes con edad media 44,8 años que sufrieron amputación de miembro superior y fueron sometidos a reimplante quirúrgico en nuestro hospital entre enero del 2005 y diciembre del 2009. Los resultados funcionales se midieron con la tabla de Mayo modificada para lesiones de pulgar, dedos largos y mano, distal a muñeca. Las amputaciones proximales a muñeca se evaluaron según los criterios de Chen. Los resultados subjetivos fueron documentados aplicando a todos los casos el cuestionario de Russell. La mayoría de las lesiones fueron provocadas por mecanismos de avulsión y 30 (74 %) fueron accidentes laborales. La tasa final de supervivencia fue del 85 % (35 pacientes) incluyendo 2 pacientes en los que se realizó trasplante de pie a mano para salvar la amputación. Aplicando la tabla de Mayo modificada, los resultados fueron buenos en pulgar y discretos en mano y dedos largos. En reimplantes proximales obtuvimos 1 resultado excelente y 2 discretos. Diecinueve pacientes retornaron al mundo laboral en una media de 10 meses. Veintisiete manifiestan satisfacción alta con los resultados obtenidos. Los resultados de cualquier reimplante deben superar los del cierre simple de una amputación. Aunque los resultados objetivos de la serie son moderados, muchos pacientes retornan al trabajo y la mayoría es capaz de realizar sus actividades cotidianas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;38(3): 247-256, jul.-sept. 2012. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106409</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Principios de evaluación y resultados funcionales en los reimplantes de miembro superior</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d688^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36501^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12513^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
