<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157554</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1837</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Medical expert consensus in AH on the clinical use of triple fixed-dose antihypertensive therapy in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The opinion of experts (different specialties) on the triple fixed-dose antihypertensive therapy in clinical practice may differ. Materials and methods: Online questionnaire with controversial aspects of the triple therapy answered by panel of experts in hypertension (HT) using two-round modified Delphi method. Results: The questionnaire was completed by 158 experts: Internal Medicine (49), Nephrology (26), Cardiology (83). Consensus was reached (agreement) on 27/45 items (60%); 7 items showed differences statistically significant. Consensus was reached regarding: Predictive factors in the need for combination therapy and its efficacy vs. increasing the dose of a pretreatment, and advantage of triple therapy (prescription/adherence/cost/pressure control) vs. free combination. Conclusions: This consensus provides an overview of the clinical use of triple therapy in moderate-severe and resistant/difficult to control HT (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mazón, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mediavilla, JD</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gorostidi, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galve, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Górriz, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La opinión de expertos (de distintas especialidades) sobre la triple terapia antihipertensiva a dosis fijas en la práctica clínica puede variar. Material y métodos: Encuesta online con aspectos controvertidos del tratamiento triple realizada por un panel de expertos en hipertensión arterial (HTA) empleando un método Delphi modificado en 2 rondas. Resultados: Participaron 158 expertos: Medicina Interna (49) Nefrología (26) y Cardiología (83). Se consensuaron (acuerdo) 27/45 ítems (60%); 7 ítems presentaron diferencias estadísticamente significativas. Se consensuó: los factores predictivos de la necesidad de tratamiento combinado y su eficacia frente al aumento de dosis de un tratamiento previo, y las ventajas de la triple terapia (prescripción/adherencia/costes/control) frente a la combinación libre. Conclusiones: El presente consenso ofrece una visión amplia del uso clínico de la triple terapia en HTA moderada-severa y resistente/de difícil control (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Hipertens. riesgo vasc;33(4): 133-144, oct.-dic. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157554</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consenso de médicos expertos en HTA sobre el uso clínico de la triple terapia antihipertensiva a dosis fija en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4419^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
