<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122055</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Retrospective study on the infectious sacroiliitis in children: clinical presentation, management and outcome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Infectious sacroiliitis is a form of arthritis that must be differentiated from the inflammatory condition. Represent a small fraction of joint infections in children and require a high index of suspicion for early diagnosis. Patients and methods: Review of childhood clinical cases diagnosed in our hospital during the last 20 years. Several variables were gathered from medical records, including clinical and microbiological: presentation, duration, physical examination, complementary tests, microorganisms involved, pharmacotherapy and surgical procedures. We completed a systematic search of articles in major bibliographic databases, prioritizing reviews and studies on pediatric population and extracting the most relevant outcomes. Results: Eleven patients met the inclusion criteria. The groups affected were children aged between 1-2 and 11-16 years. Over 80% of patients presented with a history of fever, gait abnormalities and low back pain, both spontaneous or provoked. One third of the cases had skin disease or soft tissue infection. Staphylococcus and Brucella were the main causal agents in our sample. The pelvic magnetic resonance imaging supported the diagnosis in all cases. Conclusions: The combination of history, examination and image testing guided the diagnosis. This disease should be suspected in young children when rejection of sitting or standing is observed. Antibiotic treatment improves prognosis and empirical therapy should cover S. aureus (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Tamarit, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Camuñas, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Zahonero, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Otero Reigada, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arcos Machancoses, J. V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las sacroilitis infecciosas son una forma de artritis que deben diferenciarse de las inflamatorias. Suponen una fracción pequeña de las infecciones articulares en niños y requieren un alto índice de sospecha para realizar un diagnóstico precoz. Pacientes y métodos: Se llevó a cabo una revisión de los casos infantiles diagnosticados en nuestro centro en los últimos 20 años. A través de las historias clínicas se recogieron diversas variables clínicas y microbiológicas: presentación clínica, duración, exploración, resultados de las pruebas complementarias, microorganismos involucrados, farmacoterapia y procedimientos quirúrgicos empleados. Se completó con una búsqueda sistemática de artículos en las principales bases de datos bibliográficas, priorizando los trabajos sobre población pediátrica y extrayendo los resultados más relevantes. Resultados: Once pacientes cumplieron los criterios de inclusión. Los grupos de edad afectados fueron los niños de 1-2 y 11-16 años. Más del 80% presentó clínica de fiebre, alteraciones de la marcha y dolor lumbar bajo, espontáneo o por provocación. Un tercio de los casos presentó patología cutánea o infección de partes blandas. Staphylococcus y Brucella fueron los principales microorganismos responsables. La resonancia magnética pélvica permitió realizar el diagnóstico en todos los casos. Conclusiones: La combinación de la anamnesis, la exploración y las pruebas de imagen permite orientar el diagnóstico. En los niños pequeños, tanto el rechazo a la sedestación como a la bipedestación debe hacer sospechar la presencia de esta entidad. El tratamiento antibiótico precoz mejora el pronóstico y la antibioterapia empírica debe cubrir S. aureus (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;72(4): 81-87, abr. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122055</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio retrospectivo sobre la sacroilitis infecciosa en niños: presentación clínica, manejo y evolución</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23949^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53948^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12822^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34319^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
