<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135021</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Changes observed in three quality indicators after the implementation of improvement strategies in the respiratory intensive care unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To compare the results of quality monitoring after the implementation of improvement strategies in the respiratory intensive care unit (RICU).Design A prospective, comparative, longitudinal and interventional study was carried out. Setting The RICU of Hospital General de México (Mexico).Patients All patients admitted to the RICU from March 2012 to March 2013.InterventionsAn evidence-based bundle of interventions was implemented in order to reduce the ratios of three quality indicators: non-planned extubation (NPE), reintubation, and ventilator-associated pneumonia (VAP).Variables of interest NPE, reintubation and VAP ratios. Results A total of 232 patients were admitted, with a mean age of 49.5±17.8years; 119 (50.5%) were woman. The mean Simplified Acute Physiology Score (SAPS-3) was 49.8±17, and the mean Sequential Organ Failure Assessment (SOFA) score was 5.3±4.1. The mortality rate in the RICU was 38.7%. The standardized mortality ratio was 1.50 (95%CI: 1.20-1.84). An improved ratio was observed for reintubation and NPE indicators compared to the ratios of the previous 2011 cohort: 1.6% vs. 7% (P=.02) and 8.1 vs. 17 episodes per 1000 days of mechanical ventilation (P=.04), respectively. A worsened VAP ratio was observed: 18.4 vs. 15.1 episodes per 1000 days of mechanical ventilation (P=.5).Conclusions Quality improvement is feasible with the identification of areas of opportunity and the implementation of strategies. Nevertheless, the implementation of a bundle of preventive measures in itself does not guarantee improvements (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Maldonado, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cicero Sabido, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cueto Robledo, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Comparar los resultados de la monitorización de calidad después de la implementación de estrategias de mejora en la unidad de cuidados intensivos respiratorios (UCIR).Diseño Estudio de intervención prospectivo, comparativo y longitudinal. Ámbito La UCIR del Hospital General de México. Pacientes Todos los pacientes ingresados a la UCIR de marzo de 2012 a marzo de 2013.IntervencionesSe implementó un paquete de intervenciones basadas en la evidencia para reducir las tasas de tres indicadores: extubación no programada (ENP), re-intubación y neumonía asociada a la ventilación mecánica (NAV).Variables de interés Tasas de ENP, re-intubación y NAV. Resultados Ingresaron 232 pacientes con edad promedio de 49,5±17,8años; 119 (50,5%) fueron mujeres. El promedio de Simplified Acute Physiology Score (SAPS-3) fue de 49,8±17 y la puntuación promedio de Sequential Organ Failure Assessment (SOFA) fue de 5,3±4,1. La mortalidad en la UCIR fue de 38,7%, y la tasa de mortalidad estandarizada, de 1,50 (IC95%: 1,20-1,84). Los indicadores ENP y re-intubación mostraron mejoría comparados con la cohorte de 2011: 1,6% vs. 7% en la tasa de re-intubación (p=0,02) y 8,1 vs. 17 episodios/1.000 días de ventilación mecánica para ENP (p=0,04). El indicador NAV empeoró: 18,4 vs. 15,1 episodios/1.000 días de ventilación mecánica (p=0,5).Conclusiones La mejora de la calidad con la identificación de áreas de oportunidad e implementación de estrategias en la UCIR es factible. Sin embargo, la sola implementación de paquetes de medidas preventivas no garantiza la mejora (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);39(3): 142-148, abr. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135021</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambios en tres indicadores de calidad después de la implementación de estrategias de mejora en la unidad de cuidados intensivos respiratorios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12545^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54376^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
