<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143300</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-1285</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Self-efficacy in oral health: Concept, assessment and treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Self-efficacy is a factor that allows predicting patients&#146; behaviours to gain a suitable health level. In oral health this is fundamental, because patients&#146; behaviours determine the adherence to indications provided by the dentist. The present article addresses the definition of self-efficacy in general, in oral health in particular, and a review of the most common instruments to measure this dimension inside the dental context. Finally, it presents a review of an intervention model of self-efficacy in oral health that has shown appropriate effectiveness (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herrera Ronda, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Correa Ramírez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojas Alcayaga, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ríos Erazo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bustos Reydet, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La autoeficacia es un factor que permite predecir las conductas que un paciente realizará para obtener un adecuado nivel de salud. En salud oral, esto resulta ser fundamental ya que los comportamientos que realiza el paciente determinan la adherencia a las indicaciones que el odontólogo le entrega. El presente artículo aborda la definición de la autoeficacia en general, y en salud oral en particular, además de revisar cuales son los instrumentos más utilizados para medir esta dimensión dentro del contexto odontológico. Finalmente, se revisa un modelo de intervención de la autoeficacia en salud oral que ha mostrado una adecuada efectividad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av Odontoestomatol;31(5): 305-311, sept.-oct. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143300</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Autoeficacia en salud oral: Concepto, evaluación y tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33883</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9252^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28452</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10546^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
