<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77141</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-6045</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Homecare physiotherapy in the iberian peninsula public health system</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectivesTo become acquainted with the principal homecare physiotherapy services that are offered within the Public Health System for dependent elderly patients in the Iberian Peninsula (Spain and Portugal).MethodsA thorough and up-dated review of the literature regarding previous studies, research stays in Hospitals, Primary Health Care Centers and Public Health institutions in both countries financed by the Public Health Administration; in-depth interviews with specific informants.ResultsThe situation of homecare physiotherapy in Spain from the year 1987 to the August 2008 is described. In Portugal, these services are established within the services regulated by Primary Health Care (Decree-Law no. 28/2008, of February 22).ConclusionsThere are few studies in the Iberian Peninsula that offer scientific evidence based information on the effectiveness of these physiotherapy services, user satisfaction and the effect they have in relation to other treatments. However, these studies are needed in order to evaluate the current health legislations, appropriate distribution of resources, to review the clinical programs, clinical action methodologies, etc (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Catalán Matamoros, D. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padilla Góngora, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sousa Coutinho, M. I. M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Correia Brito, A. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva Miranda, A. M da</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Liria, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivosConocer los principales servicios de fisioterapia domiciliaria que oferta el Sistema Sanitario Público para las personas mayores dependientes de la Península Ibérica (España y Portugal).Estrategia de búsquedaRevisión bibliográfica actualizada y exhaustiva sobre los estudios previos; estancia de investigación en Hospitales, Centros de Salud y organismos financiados por la Administración Pública en ambos países; entrevistas en profundidad a informantes estratégicos.Síntesis de los resultadosSe describe la situación de la fisioterapia domiciliaria en España, desde el año 1987 hasta agosto de 2008. Se detecta que en Portugal la fisioterapia domiciliaria está recogida en la cartera de servicios de atención primaria (Decreto-Ley no 28/2008, del 22 de febrero).ConclusionesExisten pocas investigaciones a nivel de la Península que ofrezcan datos objetivos basados en la evidencia científica sobre la efectividad de estos servicios de fisioterapia, la satisfacción del usuario y las repercusiones que producen con respecto a otros tratamientos; sin embargo, estos estudios son necesarios para la evaluación de las políticas sanitarias, la distribución adecuada de recursos, la revisión de los programas, la metodología de actuación, etc (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. iberoam. fisioter. kinesiol. (Ed. impr.);12(1): 46-57, jun. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77141</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los servicios de fisioterapia domiciliaria en el sistema sanitario público de la Península Ibérica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36319</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28459</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6858</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6856</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6856^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20208</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6856^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30585</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50256</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
