<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98579</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sleep pattern and perception of sleep quality among medical residents and the relation to anxiety and depression</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To determine the prevailing sleep pattern and perception of sleep quality among medical residents indifferent specialties at a regional hospital and to explore their relation with several variables, especially with anxiety, depression, and psychoactive substance use on the other. Methods: Cross-sectional observational survey of medical residents in Regional Hospital 25. The subjects gave their informed consent to participation. The instruments used were the Pittsburgh sleep quality index, a questionnaire on use of psychoactive substances, and the Goldberg anxiety and depression scale. Other variables explored were age, gender, year of residency training, specialty, sleep pattern, number of on-call days, outside work, and family or social obligations, and their relationship with the sleep pattern and quality. Results: In the specialties of emergency medicine, anesthesiology, surgery, pediatrics and internal medicine, a total of 91.80% of the residents participated. The mean (SD) age was 25.6 (2.6) years; 53.6% of the respondents were men. Sleep pattern and quality significantly worsened after residence sterting (p &lt; 0.001), when short sleep pattern was present in 75.0% of residents and poor or very poor quality in 32,2%. Routine coffee drinking was reported by 87.5%,and 51.8% drank alcoholic beverages regularly; 37.5% were smokers. Signs of anxiety were detected in 46.4% and depression in 37.5%. A significant  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Márquez-Ávila, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rocha-Luna, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Loría-Castellanos, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Determinar el patrón y la calidad de sueño predominante en médicos residentes de diferentes especialidades de un hospital regional, así como su relación con distintas variables especialmente con ansiedad, depresión y el consumo de sustancias. Métodos: Estudio observacional del tipo transversal en el que se aplicaron a médicos residentes los siguientes instrumentos: &#147;Índice de calidad del sueño de Pittsburgh&#148;, &#147;Cuestionario para evaluar el consumo de sustancias&#148; y &#147;Escala de ansiedad y depresión de Goldberg&#148;. También se recogió la edad, sexo, grado académico, especialidad, patrón de sueño, guardias realizadas, y trabajos y actividades familiares o sociales ajenas a la residencia. Se estudió si alguna variable se asociaba con un patrón corto de sueño o con una calidad mala-muy mala del mismo. Resultados: Participaron el 91,8% de los residentes de las especialidades de urgencias, anestesiología, cirugía, pediatría y medicina interna. La edad fue de 25,6 ± 2,6 años y el 53,6% eran varones. Tanto el patrón como la calidad del sueño se deterioraron significativamente tras iniciar la residencia (p &lt; 0,001), donde el patrón fue corto en el 75,0% de los casos y la calidad mala-muy mala en el 32,2%. El 87,5% consumían café, el 51,8% bebidas alcohólicas, el 37,5% cigarrillos, el 46,4% mostraron rasgos de ansiedad y el 37,5% de depresión. Se encontró asociación significativa de los patrones de sueño corto y especialidad de urgencias (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);22(1): 33-39, feb. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98579</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patrón y calidad subjetiva de sueño en médicos residentes y su relación con ansiedad y depresión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
