<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040972</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical guidelines in the therapy of type 2 diabetes: limitations of stepped treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Therapeutic guidelines on type 2 diabetes from the European Diabetes Policy Group de la lntemational Diabetes Federation (IDF; 1999), the Scottish Intercollegiate Guidelines Network (SIGN; 2001), the National Institute for Clinical Excellence (NICE; 2002), the American Association of Clinical Endocrinologists (AACE; 2002), the New Zealand Guidelines Group (NZGG; 2003) and the Canadian Diabetes Association (CDA; 2003) were reviewed. In Spain, these recommendations have been included on the "Guía de tratamiento de la diabetes tipo 2 en Atención Primaria". The American Diabetes Association (ADA) has not particularly published any recent positional statement on pharmacological treatment of type 2 diabetes and its last publication is from 1999. The best therapeutic option will be selected taken into account the degree of adiposity (lean or obese), insulin resistance, defect of insulin secretion, metabolic control and HbA1c and predominant basal hyperglycemia or postprandial hyperglycemia. The presence of chronic diabetic complications or other concomitant diseases (renal or hepatic failure, congestive heart disease) are also important</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Franch Nadal, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se han revisado las recomendaciones terapéuticas en la diabetes mellitus tipo 2 del European Diabetes Policy Group de la Intemational Diabetes Federation (IDF; 1999), del Scottish Intercollegiate Guidelines Network (SIGN; 2001), del National Institute for Clínical Excellence (NICE; 2002), de la American Association of Clinical Endocrinologists (AACE; 2002), del New Zealand Guidelines Group (NZGG; 2003) y de la Canadian Diabetes Association (CDA; 2003). En España; estas recomendaciones han sido recogidas en la "Guía de tratamiento de la diabetes tipo 2 en Atención Primaria". La American Diabetes Association (ADA) no ha emitido ningún posicionamiento reciente sobre el tratamiento farmacológico de la DM2 y su última publicación al respecto data de 1999. La opción terapéutica que se seleccione estará supeditada a diversos aspectos de la enfermedad como son el estado ponderal (obesidad o normopeso), grado de resistencia a la insulina, grado de déficit de secreción de insulina, grado de control metabólico y la cifra de HbA1c, predominio de la hiperglucemia en ayunas o bien en estadio postprandial, así como de la existencia de las distintas complicaciones crónicas u otros procesos concomitantes (insuficiencia renal, cardiaca o hepática)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;21(supl.2): 78-83, dic. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040972</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Guías clínicas de tratamiento de la diabetes tipo 2: limitaciones del tratamiento escalonado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37656^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22649^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22231^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37656^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8837^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29653</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22649^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8837^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22231^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
