<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052479</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparison of Raz bladder neck suspension and the Bologna procedure for the treatment of urinary stress incontinence</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to evaluate and compare perioperative morbidity and the long-term results of Raz colposuspension and the Bologna procedure in the treatment of urinary stress incontinence in women. Data from 199 women who underwent either the Bologna procedure (group 1; n = 99) or Raz colposuspension (group 2; n =100) for urinary stress incontinence were retrospectively analyzed. Preoperative clinical data, urodynamic parameters and postoperative complications were compared between the two groups. Logarithmic analysis was used to compare time to recurrence of stress incontinence between the two groups. Multivariate analysis using a Cox proportional hazards regression model was performed to identify possible outcome predictors. The success rate was significantly higher in group 1 than in group 2 (p = 0.00001). The median incontinence- free interval was 51 months in group 1 and was 21 months in group 2 (p = 0.00001). No differences were found between the two groups in the frequency of intraoperative complications (inadvertent cystotomy, hemorrhage) and postoperative complications (hemorrhagic, infectious and embolic complications). Multivariate analysis using the Cox regression model showed that the only variable correlated with the surgical cure rate was the type of surgical anti-incontinence procedure adopted: Bologna or Raz (p = 0.00001). The results of this study indicate that the Bologna procedure should be preferred over Raz colposuspension in the treatment of urinary stress incontinence when sufficient anterior vaginal tissue is available to create vaginal bands. When this is not the case, Raz colposuspension, as performed in the present study, should be abandoned in favor of other colposuspension methods (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tejerizo García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejerizo López, L. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lanchares, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Rodríguez, S. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Henríquez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marino y Caba, M. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Hernández, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcántara, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Nuestra situación es la de comparar las complicaciones y los resultados sobre la incontinencia de esfuerzo de 2 técnicas de suspensión cervicouretral: la técnica de Raz y la técnica de Bologna. Se ha evaluado retrospectivamente a 199 pacientes que se han beneficiado de un tratamiento de incontinencia urinaria de esfuerzo, bien mediante la técnica de Bologna (grupo 1, 99 pacientes), bien por la técnica de Raz (grupo 2, 100 pacientes). Los datos clínicos preoperatorios, los parámetros urodinámicos y las complicaciones postoperatorias se han comparado en cada uno de los 2 grupos. El margen entre el tratamiento de la incontinencia urinaria y la recidiva se ha comparado con los 2 grupos por un test logarítmico. Se fabricó un modelo multivariante con la ayuda de un modelo de Cox, a fin de exponer los parámetros explicativos del fracaso quirúrgico. La duración de la curación en el grupo 1 es significativamente más larga que en el grupo 2 (p = 0,00001). La mediana de duración del intervalo libre sin incontinencia (éxito) es de 51 meses en el grupo 1 y de 21 meses en el 2 (p = 0,00001). La frecuencia de las complicaciones operatorias (lesión vesical y hemorragia) y postoperatorias (hemorrágicas, infecciosas y embólicas) no difieren en los 2 grupos. El análisis multivariante según el modelo de Cox muestra que la única variable preoperatoria explicativa de las recidivas es la técnica de colposuspensión realizada: Raz y Bologna. Después de este estudio comparativo, la técnica de Bologna debe preferirse a la de Raz para tratar los pacientes con IUE por el hecho de la presencia de suficiente pared vaginal anterior para confeccionar las cinchas vaginales. Si tal no es el caso, la técnica de Raz, tal y como nosotros la habíamos practicado, se debe abandonar en beneficio de otros métodos de colposuspensión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);34(2): 46-58, mar. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052479</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incontinencia urinaria de esfuerzo en la mujer. Comparación de la técnica de Raz y de la técnica de Bologna</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14950^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11824</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14950^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10487^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13894^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14950^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13894^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13895^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13894^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10487^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13894^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14963^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14963^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
