<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112979</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Elaboration and validation of an informative document on adenoamigdalectomy for patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Access to up-to-date and understandable health information is a growing citizen demand, as well as an ethical duty and a legal regulation. Written information reinforces information transmitted orally during the consultation and improves recall capacity. Adenoamigdalectomy is an intervention that affects a high number of patients, the majority from the child population that has a high emotional sensitivity, and it is experienced by parents with considerable anxiety. An informative guide on adenoamigdalectomy was elaborated and validated. The aim of this article is to describe the process of elaborating the document, emphasizing its validation and results. Material and methods. The document was validated in three phases: A) Clinical content validated by professionals with a checklist and a consensus meeting; B) Analysis of grammatical legibility according to the Flesch index; C) Validation of lexical legibility with citizens by means of a validation guide and interviews. Results. The validation by professionals and citizens was highly positive. The professionals stressed the accuracy of the content and corrected some imprecisions. They made suggestions concerning format, writing style and length. The citizens stressed understandable language, resolution of doubts, respectful tone and their satisfaction with the initiative. They also differed on aspects such as their opinion of the document&#146;s length. Conclusions. The validation of informative documents by both professionals and patients is a process of great interest. Lack of agreement in their analyses makes it clear why it is important to include both sectors. The document was improved by their contributions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-Pérez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escudero-Carretero, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Gómez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz-Amores, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández de la Mota, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto-Rodríguez, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. El acceso a una información sanitaria actualizada y comprensible es una demanda ciudadana creciente, así como un deber ético y una norma legal. La información por escrito refuerza la información que se transmite verbalmente en la consulta y mejora la capacidad de recuerdo. La adenoamigdalectomía es una intervención que afecta a un número elevado de pacientes, mayoritariamente a una población muy sensible emocionalmente, la infantil, cuyos padres y madres lo viven con bastante ansiedad. Se elabora y valida una guía informativa sobre adeno-amigdalectomía. El objetivo de este trabajo es describir el proceso de elaboración del documento, destacando el procedimiento de validación del mismo y sus resultados. Material y métodos. Validación del documento en tres fases: A) de contenidos clínicos por profesionales con checklist y reunión de consenso. B) análisis de legibilidad gramatical según el índice de Flesch. C) validación de legibilidad léxica con ciudadanía a través de guía de valoración y entrevista. Resultados. La valoración de profesionales y ciudadanía fue muy positiva. Profesionales destacaron la exactitud de los contenidos y corrigieron algunas imprecisiones. Hicieron sugerencias respecto a formato, redacción y extensión. Ciudadanía destacó: lenguaje comprensible, resolución de dudas, tono respetuoso y satisfacción por esta iniciativa. Difieren también en aspectos como la consideración sobre la extensión. Conclusiones. La validación de documentos informativos tanto con profesionales como con pacientes es un proceso de mucho interés. Al no coincidir en sus análisis se pone de manifiesto la importancia de incluir a ambos sectores. El documento mejoró con las aportaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;36(1): 21-33, ene.-abr. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112979</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Elaboración y validación de un documento informativo sobre adeno-amigdalectomía para pacientes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14458^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d242^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24356^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d241^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
