<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59655</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The effects of ileal transposition, gastrojejunal bypass and vertical gastroplasty on the regulation of ingestion in an experimental obesity model associated with diabetes mellitus type 2</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: The continual advances in our knowledge of the pathogenesis and hormonal disorders of morbid obesity lead to new studies in experimental animals and the development of new technical options. The aim is to asses whether ileal transposition can be a good treatment of morbid obesity associated with diabetes mellitus due to the action of intestinal peptide Glp-1 (enteroglucagon) compared to gastric bypass and vertical gastroplasty (VGB). Material and methods: Trial enviroment: experimental animals ZDF rats (Zucker Diabetic Fatty rats). Subjects of the study: three groups of 10 animals each one divided as: a) ileal tranposition; b) gastro-jejunal bypass; c) vertical gastroplasty. Parameters to determine: weight loss, levels of glycaemia, enteroglucagon, insulin and ghrelin in blood, one week before the operation as a baseline control, and 15 days after the surgical procedure. Results: Gastrojejunal bypass produces the most significant weight loss. There is a significant decrease in intake in all groups. Hyperinsulinaemia and hyperglycaemia tend to decrease after surgery in all groups, but in ileal transposition there is better control of ketosis. After gastrojejunal bypass and ileal transposition, we observed an increase in GLP-1 levels but were only significant in ileal transposition. Conclusions: Ileal transposition produces a decrease in plasma glucose and better control of diabetes mellitus, which could benefit patients affected by morbid obesity and poor metabolic control. More studies are needed on other models of obesity. A model of exogenous and reversible obesity could be a good option to study the real benefits of the interventions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernàndez Gonzàlez, Mercè</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo Déjardin, Daniel del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Marín, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Blasco, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morandeira Rivas, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabench Pereferrer, Fàtima</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En el marco de la cirugía metabólica, este estudio pretende valorar la transposición ileal como tratamiento quirúrgico de la obesidad mórbida relacionada con la diabetes mellitus no insulinodependiente gracias a la acción del péptido GLP-1, en relación con el bypass gástrico y la gastroplastia vertical. También determinar las concentraciones de grelina y su contribución a la pérdida de peso para cada técnica. Material y métodos: Animales de experimentación del tipo Zucker Diabetic Fatty, ratas obesas y modelo de diabetes tipo 2. Tres grupos de 10 animales cada uno: a) transposición ileal; b) bypass gastroyeyunal, y c) gastroplastia vertical. Parámetros determinados: pérdida de peso, cambios en la ingesta, valores de glucemia, GLP-1, insulina y grelina en sangre de cada uno de los animales una semana antes de la intervención quirúrgica y a los 15 días de la cirugía. Resultados: La intervención que produce una mayor pérdida de peso es el bypass gastroyeyunal. Hay una disminución de la ingesta calórica significativa para los tres tipos de intervención. No se consigue corregir el estado de hiperglucemia intensa en los tres grupos, aunque en el grupo de la transposición se logra frenar el estado de cetosis. El aumento de GLP-1 es sólo significativo en la transposición ileal. Conclusiones: En la respuesta metabólica a la cirugía no sólo se modifica una única hormona, sino que se establece un estado de regulación y contrarregulación como traducción de una determinada acción quirúrgica. Los animales obesos, cuyo exceso de peso es de causa exógena, pueden ser un buen modelo para otros estudios en esta dirección (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);85(4): 222-228, abr. 2009. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59655</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de la transposición ileal, el bypass gastroyeyunal y la gastroplastia vertical en la regulación de la ingesta en un modelo experimental de obesidad relacionada con diabetes mellitus tipo 2</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37575^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24255^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24255^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7991^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7991^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24255^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
