<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051455</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Trends in the frequency of Down syndrome in the infants of young mothers in the autonomous communities of Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: There is a universally proven relationship between maternal age and the risk of having an infant with Down syndrome (DS); the risk is greater as maternal age increases. The overall risk is increased almost 10-fold in mothers aged more than 34 years (traditionally accounting for 9-14% of all mothers) than in those aged less than 35 years. For this reason, mothers aged 35 years or older have constituted the target population for prenatal diagnosis of DS and, consequently, the frequency of newborn infants with DS in this age group has clearly decreased over time. However, the development of new prenatal screening techniques has allowed groups with a higher risk to be detected among young mothers. The aim of this study was to analyze trends in the frequency of DS in the infants of mothers aged less than 35 years old in Spain over the last 28 years by autonomous communities in Spain.                 Material and methods: Data from the Spanish Collaborative Study of Congenital Malformations (Estudio Colaborativo Español de Malformaciones Congénitas [ECEMC]) corresponding to the period 1976-2003, and obtained from all the autonomous communities in Spain, were used. The ECEMC is a clinical-epidemiological research program on the causes of congenital defects, structured as a permanent registration system with a case-control design. The program is hospital-based. For the analysis of time trends, the lineal trend test (&amp;#967;² with 1 degree of freedom) was used. To detect deviations from linearity, a &amp;#967;² test with k-2 degrees of freedom was used.                 Results: The overall frequency of DS in mothers younger than 35 years significantly decreased over time (p = 0.03), mainly in the last few years. This decrease was statistically significant in the autonomous communities of Catalonia (p = 0.002) and Galicia (p = 0.01), but was nonsignificant in Andalusia, Balearic Island, Madrid and the Basque Country. In Navarre and La Rioja, the most recent tendency could not be evaluated because these regions temporarily interrupted their participation in the study. A statistically significant increase was found in the Principality of Asturias. No notable tendencies were found in the remaining regions. The percentage of mothers older than 34 years progressively increased, accounting for 20.54% of all mothers in 2003, while the number and percentage of infants with DS born to mothers older than 34 decreased and was lower those of infants with DS born to mothers younger than 35 years.                 Discussion: Although the time trend of the frequency of DS in the infants of mothers aged less than 35 years showed a significant overall decrease, differences were found in the distinct autonomous communities. This finding could be a result of the application of different programs for the prenatal detection of DS in lower-risk maternal age groups. Therefore, homogenizing these programs would seem advisable</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Frías, María Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Grondona, Fermín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Fernández, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mansilla, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Pinilla, Elvira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuevas, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermejo, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Hay una relación universalmente probada entre la edad materna y el riesgo para tener hijos con síndrome de Down (SD), que es mayor a medida que aquélla aumenta. El grupo de madres con más de 34 años (entre un 9 y un 14% del total) tiene globalmente 10 veces más riesgo que el grupo con menos de 35 años. Por ello, las madres con 35 años o más han sido la población diana para el diagnóstico prenatal del SD. Como consecuencia de ello, la frecuencia de recién nacidos con SD en este grupo de madres va disminuyendo con el tiempo. Sin embargo, el desarrollo de nuevas técnicas de cribado ha facilitado también la detección de grupos de riesgo para SD en las madres con menos de 35 años. El objetivo de este trabajo era estudiar la evolución de la frecuencia de SD en los recién nacidos de madres menores de 35 años en España, durante 28 años y por comunidades autónomas.                 Material y métodos: Se han utilizado los datos registrados por el Estudio Colaborativo Español de Malformaciones Congénitas (ECEMC) entre 1976 y 2003, procedentes de todas las comunidades autónomas. El ECEMC es un programa de investigación clínico-epidemiológica sobre las causas de los defectos congénitos, estructurado como un sistema permanente de registro con un diseño de tipo casos y controles y de base hospitalaria. Para el análisis de la tendencia temporal se ha utilizado el test de tendencia lineal (&amp;#967;² con un grado de libertad) y la &amp;#967;² con k-2 grados de libertad para detectar desviaciones de la linealidad.                 Resultados: La frecuencia global de SD en el grupo de madres menores de 35 años ha disminuido de forma estadísticamente significativa con el tiempo (p = 0,03), fundamentalmente los últimos años. Dicho descenso es estadísticamente significativo en Cataluña (p = 0,002) y Galicia (p = 0,01). Sin embargo, no se alcanza la significación estadística para los descensos observados en Andalucía, Islas Baleares, Madrid y País Vasco. En la Comunidad Foral de Navarra y en La Rioja no se ha podido evaluar la tendencia más reciente porque estas comunidades interrumpieron temporalmente su participación en el estudio. En el Principado de Asturias hemos detectado un incremento secular significativo, y en el resto de las comunidades no se aprecian tendencias destacables. Además, el porcentaje de madres con más de 34 años ha aumentado progresivamente hasta alcanzar el 20,54% del total de madres en 2003, mientras que el número y el porcentaje de niños con SD que nacieron de madres con más de 34 años ha ido disminuyendo hasta ser inferior al de niños con SD hijos de madres con menos de 35 años.                 Discusión: La evolución global con el transcurso del tiempo de la frecuencia de SD en hijos de madres con menos de 35 años muestra ya un descenso significativo, pero éste no es igual en todas las comunidades autónomas. Este hecho puede ser consecuencia de la aplicación de planes diversos, que se deberían homogeneizar, dirigidos a la detección prenatal del SD en el grupo de madres de menor riesgo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);50(2): 67-80, feb. 2007. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051455</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución secular y por comunidades autónomas de la frecuencia de síndrome de Down al nacimiento en hijos de madres jóvenes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28087</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
