<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105798</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Central neuropathic pain in Parkinson's disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Central pain is one type of pain that occurs in patients with Parkinson's disease (PD). Because of its low incidence and prevalence, it often goes unnoticed and affected patients do not therefore receive adequate analgesic therapy, which increases their suffering. It is a burning pain with spontaneous onset and periods of exacerbation; pain is poorly localised and usually more intense on the more affected side. Its pathophysiology on patients with PD is not clearly defined. Methods: We performed a search and systematic selection of all clinical studies published from January 1986 to September 2010 concerning central neuropathic pain in Parkinson's disease. Conclusions: Treatment with L-Dopa has not been demonstrated to have an analgesic effect on this type of pain. Future studies are required to improve our understanding of this condition, and to develop interventions for preventing and treating it (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández Beltrán, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Munévar, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, C. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Alvares, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El dolor central es uno de los tipos de dolor que se presentan en los pacientes con enfermedad de Parkinson (EP). Debido a que su incidencia y su prevalencia no son elevadas, con frecuencia pasa desapercibido y, por consiguiente, los pacientes afectados no reciben tratamiento analgésico adecuado, lo cual incrementa su padecimiento. Este dolor es de tipo quemante, de inicio espontáneo, con periodos de exacerbación, pobremente localizado y usualmente más intenso en el lado motor más afectado. Su fisiopatología aún no está claramente definida. Desarrollo: Se realizaron una búsqueda y una selección sistemática de los estudios clínicos realizados en pacientes con EP, entre enero de 1986 y septiembre de 2010, que evaluaron el dolor neuropático central primario.Conclusiones: No se ha demostrado que el tratamiento con L-Dopa tenga efectos analgésicos sobre este dolor. Se requieren estudios futuros que permitan un mejor conocimiento de esta patología, para desarrollar mecanismos de prevención y tratamiento de esta enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;27(8): 500-503, oct. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105798</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dolor neuropático central en enfermedad de Parkinson</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31887^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9630^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
