<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121337</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidemiological profile of late mortality in severe polytraumatisms</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective A study is made of the epidemiology, chronogram and causes of late mortality in traumatized patients. Design A prospective, observational cohort study of adult trauma patients was carried out. Settings Province of Guipúzcoa (Basque Country, Spain). Intensive care unit of a tertiary hospital. Patients Patients with severe trauma (Injury Severity Score &gt; 15), admitted to the ICU from January 1995 to December 2009, with late death (&gt; 7 days).Variables Epidemiological, laboratory test, hemodynamic and transfusional data were collected. Severity scores: Abbreviated Injury Scale (AIS) and ISS. Results Patients: 2003; ISS: 24.3±14.2. Total deaths: 405 (20%). Late mortality (&gt;7 days): 102 (25.2%) patients, 9 years older and with a lower (18 points) ISS score than the patients who died early (48hours). Most frequent injuries: AIS-Head-Cervical spine &amp;#8805; 4 (52%); AIS-Abdomen &amp;#8805; 4 (19.6%); AIS-Chest &amp;#8805; 4 (11.7%); AIS-Extremities &amp;#8805; 4 (4.9%). Causes of death: 1) brain death (14.7%); 2) multiorgan failure (67.6%), in two injury contexts: a) severe brain trauma in  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Proyecto Poliguitania</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Conocer la epidemiología, cronograma y causas de mortalidad tardía en los politraumatizados graves. Diseño Observacional prospectivo de cohortes integrado en un registro provincial de trauma. Ámbito Provincia de Guipúzcoa. Unidad de cuidados intensivos (UCI) hospital terciario. Pacientes Todos los traumatizados graves: Injury Severity Score (ISS)&gt;15, ingresados en UCI entre el 1 de enero de 1995 y el 31de diciembre de 2009, fallecidos tardíamente (&gt;7días).Variables Epidemiológicas, analíticas, hemodinámicas, transfusionales y escalas de gravedad Abbreviated Injury Scale (AIS) e ISS. Resultados Pacientes: 2.003. ISS: 24,3±14,2. Exitus: 405 (20%). Fallecidos&gt;7días: 102 (25,2%) con 9 años más y 18 puntos menos de ISS que los fallecidos a las 48h. Lesiones más graves: AIS-cabeza-columna cervical &amp;#8805; 4 (52%); AIS-abdomen &amp;#8805; 4 (19,65) AIS-tórax &amp;#8805; 4 (11,7%); AIS-extremidades &amp;#8805; 4 (4,9%). Causas de fallecimiento: 1) muerte (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);37(6): 383-390, ago.-sept. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121337</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfil epidemiológico de la mortalidad tardía de los politraumatismos graves</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22947^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9294^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1952</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28637</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
