<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043598</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Primary primitive fallopian tube carcinoma and polymiositis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report a case of a primitive fallopian tube carcinoma associated with polymyositis. A 53­year-old woman consulted for pelvic pain, metrorrhagia, and leukorrhea. Physical examination revealed a renitent and mobile mass in the pelvis. Ultrasonography showed a right lateral uterine mass with hydrosalpinx. Pathological examination of the right annexectomy specimen provided the definitive diagnosis. No residual tumor was found at total hysterectomy with bilateral annexectomy. The patient was lost to follow-up for 3 years without complementary treatment and then consulted again for functional disability first of the upper limbs and subsequently of the lower limbs with myalgia, swallowing disorders and left supraclavicular node enlargement resulting from pelvic relapse of the right fallopian tube adenocarcinoma and left supraclavicular metastasis with paraneoplastic polymyositis. The patient was given 6 courses of chemotherapy with radiotherapy (45 Gy) centered on the left clavicular region. The patient showed excellent response to treatment, and remains in complete remission 50 months after diagnosis. The association of fallopian tube carcinoma with polymyositis is exceptional, requiring rapid treatment effective against the cancer and paraneoplastic polymyositis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Enríquez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Belloso, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lanchares, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejerizo-López, L. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejerizo-García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Hernández, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marino, M. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villalba, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Rodríguez, S. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez del Val, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los autores aportan un caso de asociación de un carcinoma tubárico primitivo a una polimiositis. Se trata de una paciente de 53 años, que consultó por dolores pelvianos, metrorragias y leucorreas amarillentas, con una masa pelviana de difícil movilización y móvil a la exploración clínica, y una masa laterouterina derecha con hidrosálpinx en la ecografía pelviana. El diagnóstico definitivo lo aportó el examen ana tomoclínico de la pieza de anexectomía derecha. La histerectomía total sin conservación anexial no dejó residuo tumoral. La paciente perdió contacto con nosotros sin tratamiento complementario y reconsultó 3 años después por una impotencia funcional de los miembros superiores, seguida de los inferiores, mialgias, alteraciones de la deglución y aparición de una adenopatía supraclavicular izquierda. Los exámenes clínicos, paraclínicos y anatomopatológicos mostraron que se trataba de un adenocarcinoma tubárico derecho con recaída ganglionar pelviana y metastásica supraclavicular izquierda, con polimiositis paraneoplásica. La paciente se ha beneficiado de 6 sesiones de quimioterapia, después de radioterapia en el hueco subclavicular izquierdo, a la dosis de 45 Gy. La respuesta al tratamiento ha sido excelente, y la paciente está en remisión completa después de un margen de 50 meses tras el diagnóstico. La asociación de cáncer de la trompa con una polimiositis es excepcional, y es necesaria una terapia antineoplásica rápida para tratar el cáncer y la polimiositis paraneoplásica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);33(2): 73-77, mar.-abr. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043598</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Carcinoma tubárico primitivo y polimiositis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10445^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d239^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10445^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d239^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5286^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5286^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5286^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30612^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30612^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30612^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d239^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10445^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
