<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158075</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-0618</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Notarial documents of apothecary apprentice in Madrid during the period from the 16th-17th centuries</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Apothecaries in Castile, from the Low Middle Ages, in which it took place in Europe the legal separation of the Medicine and the Pharmacy, in the absence of Schools in which formed did, practically until the first years of the nineteenth century in which the Royal Colleges of Pharmacy are created in order to formed apothecaries that in the apothecaries´s drugstores and they were examined by the Royal Court of Protomedicato. The years of practice enforceable in Court, during the period from the sixteen century to seventeen century, to be examined before the Court concerned and obtain administrative license to open own apothecary or work as officer of a companion were, according to the provisions, usually four. Although this fact is widely believed it is not less true that if had been studied primary sources, not had been published, nor the qualifications to teacher and learner. The discovery and analysis of several notarial documents of apprentice apothecary, of the centuries that we are studding, preserved in the Historical Archive of Protocols of Madrid, that if they knew had not been studied or published previously, allow us to meet the contractual framework of learning the craft and art of the apothecary, unless during that period (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lozano Estevan, María Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Basante Pol, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los boticarios en Castilla, desde el bajo medioevo en que se produce en Europa la separación legal de la Medicina y la Farmacia, al no existir centros docentes en los que formarse, lo hicieron, prácticamente hasta los primeros años del siglo XIX en que se crean los Reales Colegios de Farmacia, en la botica de un boticario examinado por el Real Tribunal del Protomedicato. Los años de práctica exigibles en la Corte, durante los siglos XVI-XVII, para poder examinarse ante el referido Tribunal y obtener de la licencia administrativa para abrir botica propia o trabajar como oficial en la de un compañero eran, según lo dispuesto, generalmente cuatro. Aunque este dato es creencia generalizada no es menos cierto que si habían sido estudiadas fuentes primarias, no habían sido publicadas, ni tampoco las condiciones exigibles a docente y discente. El hallazgo y análisis de varias escrituras notariales de aprendiz de boticario, de los siglos antedichos, conservadas en el Archivo Histórico de Protocolos de Madrid, que si se conocían no habían sido estudiadas ni publicadas con anterioridad, nos permiten conocer el marco contractual del aprendizaje del oficio y arte de boticario, al menos durante ese periodo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Real Acad Farm;82(3): 324-337, 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158075</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las escrituras de aprendiz de boticario en la villa de Madrid durante los siglos XVI-XVII</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4582^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38881</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12961^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38879</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36448</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10794^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
