<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143535</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neuropsychiatric aspects of progressive supranuclear palsy: Case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Progressive supranuclear palsy (PSP) is a neurodegenerative disease of unknown etiology, first described in 1964 by Steele, Richardson and Olszewsy. It presents with prominent postural instability as an onset symptom, followed by vertical supranuclear gaze palsy and Parkinsonian symptomatology, such as bradykinesia and rigidity. It also includes cognitive impairment and neuropsychiatric disorders. This paper describes the case of a patient, who after being evaluated by several specialists was referred due to a depressive syndrome to our mental health service, and was finally diagnosed with PSP. Despite the importance of neuropsychiatric aspects in the clinical manifestation of PSP, these have been less described in the literature than the neurological symptoms. Basal ganglia have an important role in the regulation of emotions, mood, motivation, and cognition, as well as in motor control. Early diagnosis of PSP is difficult, and as initial complaints are often vague, unspecific and misleading, it is common for these patients to be misdiagnosed as depression. Increased awareness of the disease to enable an early diagnosis to be made can prevent unnecessary treatment with medications and lead to appropriate interventions. The differential psychopathological and cognitive aspects of the PSP in relation to other neurodegenerative diseases will be reviewed, with special attention to apathy as symptom and its differentiation with depression (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cámara-Barrio, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Polo, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miranda-Sivelo, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La parálisis supranuclear progresiva (PSP) es una enfermedad neurodegenerativa de etiología desconocida descrita por primera vez en 1964 por Steele, Richardson y Olszewsy. Cursa con inestabilidad postural prominente como síntoma de comienzo, seguida posteriormente de parálisis supranuclear de la mirada vertical y sintomatología parkinsoniana como bradicinesia y rigidez. Incluye deterioro cognitivo y trastornos neuropsiquiátricos. En este trabajo se describe el caso de una paciente que tras ser vista por varios especialistas es derivada a Salud Mental por síndrome depresivo, siendo finalmente diagnosticada como PSP. A pesar de la importancia de los aspectos neuropsiquiátricos en el cuadro clínico de la PSP, estos han sido descritos de forma menos detallada en la literatura que los síntomas neurológicos. Cabe recordar que los ganglios basales desarrollan un papel muy importante en la regulación de las emociones, el ánimo, la motivación y la cognición, además del conocido respecto al control motor. El diagnóstico temprano de la PSP es difícil, las quejas iniciales suelen ser vagas, inespecíficas e inducen a error, es muy frecuente que estos pacientes sean diagnosticados erróneamente como depresivos. Un mayor conocimiento de la enfermedad que permita realizar un diagnóstico temprano puede prevenir tratamientos con medicaciones inútiles y llevar a cabo las intervenciones necesarias. Revisaremos los aspectos diferenciales psicopatológicos y cognoscitivos de la PSP en relación con otras enfermedades neurodegenerativas, prestando especial atención a la apatía como síntoma y su diferenciación con lo depresivo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);19(supl.1): 62-64, dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143535</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aspectos neuropsiquiátricos de la parálisis supranuclear progresiva: análisis de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54306^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36015^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19356^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30524^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
