<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119532</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-7823</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">One of the important goals of work and organizational psychology is to promote well-being and performance of employees. Nevertheless, the yoke of the current economic crisis tyrannize this aim, threating merciless the sustainability of the well-being and performance achieved in previous decades. The decrease in one of those factors may hamper the other, resulting in a vicious circle. In this context one of the biggest challenges to face by organizational psychologists is to reverse this trend in a virtuous cycle, where promoting high levels of well-being, suppose a performance improvement and vice-versa, in a &#147;sustainable productivity and well-being synergy&#148;. However, previous efforts have shown inconclusive results. We argue that the lack of rigorousness and neglectfulness of the most contemporaneous conceptualizations of well-being and job performance, as common praxis, is part of the reason for those disappointing results. The aim of the present paper is to provide a review of the contributions and efforts to the new reformulation of the concept of well-being and productivity. It also aims to integrate the most contemporaneous well-being and job performance´s concepts, revisiting the &#147;happy productive-worker&#148; thesis, using as framework the Fredrickson´s broaden-build theory of positive emotions, where the suitability and sustainability of the alternative models of &#147;unhappy-productive worker&#148; and happy-unproductive worker&#148; will be discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peiró, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayala, Yarid</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tordera, Núria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorente, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Uno de los principales objetivos de la psicología del trabajo y de las organizaciones es promover tanto el bienestar como el rendimiento de los empleados. Sin embargo, el yugo de la crisis económica actual tiraniza este objetivo, amenazando sin piedad la sostenibilidad del bienestar y del rendimiento alcanzado en décadas anteriores. El decremento en uno de esos factores puede afectar el otro, dando lugar a un círculo vicioso. En este contexto, uno de los mayores retos para los psicólogos organizacionales es convertir esta tendencia en un círculo virtuoso, en el que promover altos niveles de bienestar en el trabajo suponga una mejora del rendimiento y viceversa, lo que en este trabajo denominamos &#147;sinergia del bienestar-productivo sostenible&#148;. Sin embargo, estudios anteriores no han obtenido resultados concluyentes al respecto. La falta de rigor y de consideración de las conceptualizaciones más contemporáneas del bienestar y el rendimiento laboral, como praxis común, son parte de la causa de esos resultados. El objetivo del presente trabajo es proporcionar una revisión de los estudios previos, que permita sustentar una nueva reformulación del concepto de bienestar y de productividad. También se plantea integrar los conceptos más contemporáneos, revisando la &#147;tesis del trabajador feliz y productivo&#148; y utilizando como marco de referencia la teoría de emociones positivas de la &#147;ampliación y construcción&#148; de Fredrickson. Finalmente, se discute la adecuación y la sostenibilidad de modelos alternativos sobre el &#147;trabajador infeliz y productivo&#148; y el &#147;trabajador feliz e improductivo&#148; (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pap. psicol;35(1): 5-14, ene. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119532</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bienestar sostenible en el trabajo: Revisión y reformulación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12476</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6391</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31493</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201401</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
