<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156139</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Metastatic Crohn&#146;s disease in pediatrics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: Metastatic Crohn&#146;s disease (MCD) is an extraintestinal manifestation of Crohn&#146;s disease, with biopsy as fundamental diagnostic tool. There are few references to MCD in children, with a 0.5-1% estimated incidence in adults. There is no consensus about its therapeutic approach. We describe our diagnostic and therapeutic experience in MCD. Results: Four cases of MCD are described in our Pediatric Gastroenterology Unit in a tertiary care hospital. The age at diagnosis was between 7 and 13 years. Lesions appeared before the diagnosis of Crohn&#146;s disease in three of them, and during the course of the disease in another one, with genital location in three patients and bilateral pretibial region in the other. All four cases demonstrated non-caseificant granulomas on biopsy. Only two patients used exclusive enteral nutrition therapy with complete resolution, while other two cases received a combination of therapies (corticosteroids, azathioprine, tacrolimus, infliximab and adalimumab) because of recurrence. Only one case required surgery after poor clinical control. Conclusion: The MCD is infrequent but must always be included in the differential diagnosis of cutaneous lesions in Crohn&#146;s disease, considering it could be the debut of the disease. We will rely on biopsy anyway for definitive diagnosis. In this series the genital region is verified as the most commonly affected in children. The therapeutic approach does not differ from the management of intestinal involvement (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Girón Fernández-Crehuet, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sierra Salinas, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Nieto, Juliana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lendinez Ramírez, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luque Pérez, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navas López, Víctor M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego Gutiérrez, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blasco Alonso, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la enfermedad de Crohn metastásica (ECM) constituye una manifestación extraintestinal de la enfermedad de Crohn, siendo fundamental la biopsia para su diagnóstico. Existen referencias escasas a ECM en la edad pediátrica, y en adultos se estima una incidencia del 0,5-1%. No hay consenso sobre su abordaje terapéutico. Nuestro objetivo es describir nuestra experiencia diagnóstica y terapéutica en ECM. Caso clínico: se describen 4 casos de ECM en seguimiento en una Unidad de Gastroenterología Infantil en un hospital pediátrico de tercer nivel. Edades al diagnóstico entre 7 y 13 años. Las lesiones aparecieron antes del diagnóstico de enfermedad de Crohn (EC) en tres de ellos y durante la evolución de la enfermedad en otro. Localización genital en tres pacientes y en región pretibial bilateral en el otro. Todos demostraron granulomas no caseificantes en la biopsia. Dos pacientes precisaron únicamente nutrición enteral exclusiva, observándose resolución completa, mientras que otros dos recibieron terapias combinadas (corticoides, azatioprina, tacrolimus, infliximab y adalimumab) por recurrencia. Solo un caso requirió cirugía por mal control clínico. Discusión: la ECM es una entidad rara aunque siempre debemos incluirla en el diagnóstico diferencial de las lesiones cutáneas en enfermedad de Crohn, teniendo en cuenta que puede ser el debut de la enfermedad. Nos basaremos en la biopsia en cualquier caso para el diagnóstico definitivo. En esta serie se verifica la región genital como la más habitual en niños. El abordaje terapéutico no difiere del manejo de la afectación intestinal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;108(9): 598-603, sept. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156139</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad de Crohn metastásica en pediatría</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1716^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5968^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5967^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
