<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112674</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Functions of the municipal pharmacists in the province of Valencia (Spain) in 1954</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To present the organization and the functions performed by municipal pharmacists in the province of Valencia in 1954 in the context of important health deficiencies and simultaneously to show the potential of their work in improving rural health. Methods: This is a retrospective study carried out from the Memories of the College of Pharmacists of Valencia, 1954. For basic descriptive study has been used the statistical program SPSS. Results: The province of Valencia in 1954 had 116 pharmaceutical areas and 128 municipal pharmacists, of which 9.4% are women. The most significant health deficiencies are: sewage (78.4%),paved street (70.7%) and distribution of drinking water (60.3%). A total of 4,995 inspections of various types of establishments, 55 disinfections, 19,939 clinical and chemical analysis, 1,848 bromatological analysis and 6,312 analysis of the beneficence. Conclusions: The extensive work undertaken by municipal pharmacists evidence the significant potential in improving Spanish public health. Unfortunately over the years the municipal pharmacists had a marginal role in rural health (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Parrilla Valero, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Dar a conocer la organización y las funciones realizadas por los Farmacéuticos Titulares de la provincia de Valencia en el año 1954 en un contexto de importantes deficiencias sanitarias y mostrar al mismo tiempo las potencialidades de su labor en la mejora de la sanidad rural. Métodos: Se trata de un estudio descriptivo retrospectivo realizado a partir de las Memorias del Colegio Oficial de Farmacéuticos de Valencia de 1954. Para el estudio descriptivo básico se ha utilizado el paquete estadístico SPSS. Resultados: La provincia de Valencia en 1954 contaba con 116 partidos farmacéuticos y 128 farmacéuticos titulares, de los cuales el 9,4% son mujeres. Las deficiencias sanitarias más destacadas son la falta de alcantarillado (78,4%), de pavimentación de las calles (70,7%) y de distribución suficiente de agua potable (60,3%). Se realizaron un total de 4.995 inspecciones a diversos tipos de establecimientos, 550 desinfecciones, 19.939 análisis clínicos y químicos, 1.848 análisis bromatológicos y 6.312 análisis de la beneficencia. Conclusiones: La intensa labor realizada por los farmacéuticos titulares evidencia el importante potencial en la mejora de la salud pública española. Desgraciadamente con el paso de los años los farmacéuticos titulares tuvieron un papel marginal en la sanidad rural (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;54(1): 24-32, ene.-mar. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112674</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las funciones desempeñadas por los farmacéuticos titulares en la provincia de Valencia en 1954</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10786^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32616^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11016^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
