<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111147</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ground roasted peanuts leads to a lower post-prandial glycemic response than raw peanuts</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Few studies have evaluated the effect of nuts processing on the glycemic response and satiety. Objective: To evaluate the effect of peanut processing on glycemic response, and energy and nutrients intake. Method: Thirteen healthy subjects (4 men and 9women), with a mean age of 28.5 ± 10 years, BMI 22.7 ±2.5 kg/m², and body fat 23.7 ± 5.7% participated in this randomized crossover clinical trial. After 10-12 h of fasting, one of the following types of test meals were consumed: raw peanuts with skin (RPS), roasted peanuts without skin, ground-roasted peanuts without skin(GRPWS) or control meal. The test meals had the same nutrient composition, and were consumed with 200 ml of water in 15 minutes. Glycemic response was evaluated 2 hours after each meal. Energy and nutrients intake were assessed through diet records reflecting the habitual food intake and food consumption 24 hours after the ingestion of test meal. Result: The area under the glycemic response curve after GRPWS was lower (p = 0.02) the one obtained for RPS. There was no treatment effect on energy intake, macronutrients and fiber consumption after the test meal. Conclusion: The consumption of ground-roasted peanuts may favor the control and prevention of diabetes due to its reduction on postprandial glucose response. However, more prospective studies are needed to confirm this hypothesis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rocha, ALC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva, MVL da</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martino, HSD</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bordalo, LA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Faria, VC de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Costa, NMB</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reis, CEG</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Freitas, DMO</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alfenas, RC</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Escasos estudios han evaluado el efecto del procesado industrial de los frutos secos sobre la respuesta glicérica y la saciedad. Objetivos: Evaluar el efecto del procesamiento de maní sobre la respuesta glicémica y la ingesta de energía y nutrientes. Métodos: Trece sujetos sanos (4 hombres y 9 mujeres),con una edad media de 28,5 ± 10 años, IMC 22,7 ± 2,5kg/m², y un porcentaje de grasa corporal de 23,7 ± 5,7% participaron en este ensayo clínico aleatorizado y cruzado. Tras 10-12 h de ayuno uno de los siguientes tipos de comidas test fueron consumidas: maní crudo con la piel(RPS), maní tostado sin piel, maní tostado y molido sin piel (GRPWS) o comida control. Las comidas test presentaban la misma composición nutricional, y fueron consumidas con 200 ml de agua en 15 minutos. Se evaluó la respuesta glucémica 2 horas después de cada una de las comidas. La ingesta de energía y nutrientes contenida en la toma alimentaria y las 24 horas posteriores a la comida test fueron determinadas mediante registros dietéticos. Resultados: El área bajo la curva de respuesta glicémica después de GRPWS fue menor (p = 0,02) que la de RPS. No hubo efecto de los tratamientos sobre la ingesta de energía, macronutrientes y fibra posterior a la comida test. Conclusión: El consumo de maní tostado y molido sin piel, al reducir la respuesta glucémica postprandial podría ser beneficioso para el control y prevención de la diabetes. Sin embargo son necesarios estudios de intervención a largo plazo que lo confirmen (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;26(4): 745-751, jul.-ago. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111147</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Maní tostado y molido conduce a una menor respuesta glicémica postprandial comparado con maní crudo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37656^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1812^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4499^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10560</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
