<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89185</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characteristics of the protection against occupational hazards during pregnancy and breast-feeding in Madrid (2000-2008)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: 1. Quantifying the number of women applying for protection against occupational hazards during pregnancy or breast-feeding in Madrid from 2000 to 2008. 2. Describing the female workers by profession and alleged occupational hazards. 3. Analyzing the gestational average age.  Method: A descriptive retrospective study of a female workers population seeking the INSS protection for occupational hazards during pregnancy or breast-feeding in Madrid from 2000 to 2008. Variables: gestational age, profession, alleged occupational hazards and resolution. Descriptive statistical analysis. Results and conclusions: There has been a total amount of 6.441 occupational hazard applications during  pregnancy and breast-feeding in the course of the 9 year period of the study. The most frequent risks are the ergonomic ones and the inadequate working conditions. Average gestational age shows statistical differencesby profession (p &lt; 0.01) and it has been significantly rised throughout the study period (p &lt; 0.05) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Ortiz de Salazar, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: 1. Cuantificar el número de mujeres que solicitan la prestación por riesgo durante el embarazo y/o la lactancia en Madrid desde el año 2000 al 2008. 2. Describir a las trabajadoras según su profesión y los riesgos alegados. 3. Analizar la evolución de la edad gestacional media.  Método: Estudio descriptivo retrospectivo de una población de mujeres trabajadoras que solicitaron la prestación por riesgo durante el embarazo y la lactancia al INSS de 2000 a 2008 en Madrid. Variables: edad  gestacional, profesión, riesgos laborales alegados y resolución. Análisis estadístico descriptivo. Resultados y conclusiones: Se han registrado un total de 6.441 solicitudes de prestación durante el embarazo y/o la lactancia, durante los 9 años del estudio. Los riesgos más frecuentes son los físicos y las condiciones de trabajo inadecuadas. La edad media  gestacional al solicitar la prestación presenta diferencias significativas según la profesión (p &lt; 0,01) y ha aumentado significativamente a lo largo del periodo de estudio (p &lt; 0,05) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;18(1): 30-38, abr. 2009. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89185</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características de la prestación por riesgo durante el embarazo y/o la lactancia en Madrid de 2000 a 2008</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7952^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
