<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91600</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Understanding the disease: presentation of a clinical case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Some patients have very different responses to the disease than those expected under the current paradigm of Western medicine. Anthropology and medical sociology offer a plausible explanation for these differences. Intrinsic characteristics of individual beliefs about the disease and its relationship with social group membership often mediate this response. Among others, rural areas offer the possibility to check the influence of the various concepts that individuals may have of the disease and the role of the patient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valiño López, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Grávalos, G. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casado Górriz, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Algunos pacientes presentan respuestas a la enfermedad muy diferentes a las esperadas según el vigente paradigma de la medicina occidental. La antropología y la sociología médicas ofrecen una explicación plausible de estas diferencias. Características intrínsecas del individuo, creencias sobre la enfermedad y la relación con el grupo social de pertenencia mediatizan con frecuencia dicha respuesta. Entre otros, el medio rural ofrece la posibilidad de comprobar la influencia de las diferentes alternativas que sobre la concepción de la enfermedad y el papel de enfermo pueden tener los individuos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);37(9): 511-513, nov. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91600</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La concepción de la enfermedad: a propósito de un caso clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28564^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3487</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13305</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13306</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28564^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28457^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201111</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
