<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110769</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Physicians with access to point-of-care tests significantly reduce the antibiotic prescription for common cold</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. This study was aimed at evaluating the effect of two levels of intervention on the antibiotic prescribing in patients with common cold. Methods. Before and after audit-based study carried out in primary healthcare centres in Spain. General practitioners registered all the episodes of common cold during 15 working days in January and February in 2008 (preintervention). Two types of intervention were considered: full intervention, consisting in individual feedback based on results from the first registry, courses in rational antibiotic prescribing, guidelines, patient information leaflets, workshops on rapid tests &#150;rapid antigen detection and C-reactive protein tests&#150; and provision of these tests in the surgeries; and partial intervention, consisting of all the above intervention except for the workshop and they did not have access to rapid tests. The same registry was repeated in 2009 (postintervention). In addition, new physicians filled out only the registry in 2009 (control group). Results. 210 physicians underwent the full intervention, 71 the partial intervention and 59 were assigned to the control group. The 340 doctors prescribed antibiotics in 274 episodes of a total of 12,373 cases registered (2.2%).The greatest percentage of antibiotic prescription was found in the control group (4.6%). The partial intervention increased the antibiotic prescription percentage from 1.1% to 2.7% while only doctors who underwent the complete intervention lead to a significant reduction of antibiotics prescribed, from 2.9% before to 0.7% after the intervention (p&lt;0.001). Conclusion. Only physicians with access to rapid tests significantly reduced antibiotic prescription in patients with common cold(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grupo de Trabajo Happy Audit España</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Evaluar el efecto de dos niveles de intervención en la prescripción antibiótica en el resfriado común. Métodos. Estudio de garantía de calidad antes-después realizado en centros de salud de España. Los médicos participantes registraron durante 15 días laborables en enero y febrero de 2008 (preintervención) todos los contactos con resfriado. Se consideraron dos niveles de intervención: uno completo, que consistió en un feedback individual con presentación de los resultados del primer registro, cursos sobre prescripción racional de antibiótcios, guías, folletos de información para pacientes, talleres sobre pruebas rápidas &#150;test de detección antigénica y proteína C reactiva&#150; y provisión de estas pruebas en la consulta; y otro, parcial, realizando lo mismo menos el taller y no se dieron pruebas rápidas. En una segunda fase se repitió el mismo registro en 2009 (postintervención). Además, se incluyeron nuevos médicos que rellenaron sólo el registro en 2009 (grupo control). Resultados. Un total de 210 médicos fueron asignados al grupo de intervención completa, 71 a intervención parcial y 59 médicos fueron asignados al grupo control. Los 340 médicos participantes prescribieron antibióticos en 274 resfriados de un total de 12.373 casos registrados (2,2%). El mayor porcentaje de prescripción antibiótica se observó entre los médicos asignados al grupo control (4,6%). La intervención parcial aumentó el porcentaje de prescripción antibiótica del 1,1% al 2,7% mientras que los médicos que realizaron la intervención completa sí la disminuyeron, pasando de un 2,9% antes de la intervención a un 0,7% después (p&lt;0,001). Conclusión. Sólo los médicos con disponibilidad de pruebas rápidas redujeron significativamente la prescripción antibiótica en pacientes con resfriado común(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;26(1): 12-20, mar.2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110769</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los médicos que disponen de pruebas rápidas disminuyen significativamente la prescripción de antibióticos en el resfriado común</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3170^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8655^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3170^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8655^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5349^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3170^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8655^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
