<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78382</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anti-TNF drugs: new results on efficacy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Anti-TNF drugs have represented a great advancement in the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis since their introduction in the late 1990s. The development of these products has been very similar for etanercept, infliximab and adalimumab, the 3 approved TNF blockers for the treatment of RA. The first studies centered their attention on patients with active disease and refractory to several disease modifying treatments, finding very significant differences when compared to placebo or methotrexate in the ACR improvement scores. Trials in patients who had not been previously treated with methotrexate show less differences between anti-TNF and methotrexate, but becomes more significant when the two drugs are used combined. In this manuscript we analyze the results of the registry of anti-TNF studies with regard to other improvement indexes such as quality of life, reduction in cardiovascular risk, maintained efficacy through time and progression of joint erosions. We also contemplate the possibility of using lower doses than those authorized for rheumatoid arthritis and analyze factors related to a poor prognosis in patients refractory to methotrexate, which is currently the indication for the use of anti-TNF in RA accordiong to the SER consensus (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marenco de la Fuente, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solís Díaz, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los antagonistas del TNF (tumor necrosis factor &#145;factor de necrosis tumoral&#146;) han significado un gran avance en el tratamiento de la artritis reumatoide (AR) desde su introducción a finales de la década de 1990. El desarrollo de producto ha sido similar para los 3 anti-TNF licenciados en la actualidad para el tratamiento de la AR: etanercept, infliximab y adalimumab. Los primeros estudios se centraron en los pacientes con enfermedad activa y refractaria a varios tratamientos modificadores de la enfermedad, por lo que se han obtenido diferencias muy significativas frente a placebo o metotrexato (MTX) en los índices de mejoría del American College of Rheumatology (ACR). Los ensayos en los pacientes no tratados con MTX muestran una diferencia menos notable entre los anti-TNF y el MTX, que se hace más significativa para la combinación de MTX con anti-TNF. En este manuscrito se analizan los resultados de los estudios de registro de los anti-TNF así como otros índices de mejoría, como calidad de vida, reducción del riesgo cardiovascular, efectividad mantenida en el tiempo y progresión de lesiones articulares. También se plantea la posibilidad de tratar con dosis menores a las autorizadas para AR y se analiza la afección de mal pronóstico de los pacientes refractarios a MTX, que actualmente es la indicación para el uso de anti-TNF en AR según el consenso de la Sociedad Española de Reumatología (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);5(extr.1): 71-76, abr. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78382</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Antagonistas del TNF. Nuevos datos de eficacia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38737^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28169^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32355^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1178^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
