<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046081</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">In vitro three-dimensional reconstruction of human bladder mucosa</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: The purpose of this study is to apply the in vitro keratinocyte culture techniques and the tissue    engineering principles to human urothelium, to reconstruct an in vitro three-dimensional human bladder    mucosa, suitable for grafting.    Material and Methods: Biopsy specimens of human bladder mucosa were obtained from patients undergoing    suprapubic prostatectomy, in vitro cultured and finally, an immunohistochemical study was made.    Results: A three-dimensional in vitro tissue was obtained, composed of a bio-artificial submucosa (fibrin gel    and fibroblast) where the uroepithelial cells were seeding. We used a biodegradable polyglycolic acid mesh    to facilitate the tissue manipulation and implantation.    An immature epithelium was obtained with a weak immunostaining to cytokeratins. The immunohistochemical    study could not demonstrate the development of basement membrane.    Conclusions: In vitro keratinocyte culture techniques could be applied to other epithelial tissues like the    urothelium. We obtained a three-dimensional in vitro tissue suitable for grafting in a relatively short time,    which needs the matrix interactions in order to mature</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Diego Rodríguez, E. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meana Infiesta, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villanueva Peña, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Llames, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roca Edreira, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín García, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Ortega, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Aplicar las técnicas de cultivo in vitro de queratinocitos así como los principios de la ingeniería    tisular al epitelio urinario humano, con el fin de reconstruir tridimensionalmente una mucosa vesical    humana in vitro, apta para trasplantar.    Material y Métodos: Se obtuvieron muestras de mucosa vesical de pacientes programados para cirugía    abierta de próstata, previo consentimiento de los mismos, las cuales fueron cultivadas in vitro, para proceder    posteriormente al estudio histomorfológico de los tejidos obtenidos.    Resultados: Se obtuvo un tejido tridimensional compuesto por una submucosa bioartificial a base de un    gel de fibrina y fibroblastos, sobre la que descansan las células uroepiteliales, pudiendo utilizar una malla    de ácido poliglicólico, que facilite la manipulación de la mucosa y el posterior injerto de la misma. El tejido    obtenido tenía el aspecto de un epitelio inmaduro con muy escasa reacción a citoqueratinas, sin poderse    demostrar inmunohistoquímicamente el desarrollo de una membrana basal.    Conclusiones: Las técnicas de cultivo in vitro de queratinocitos son aplicables a otros epitelios, entre    ellos el urotelio humano. En un periodo de tiempo relativamente corto se puede obtener un tejido in vitro    tridimensional apto para trasplantar, precisando posiblemente de las interacciones con el lecho receptor    para poder madurar</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;30(2): 195-205, feb. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046081</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reconstrucción tridimensional in vitro de mucosa vesical humana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24758^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9284^s22071</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1768^s22071</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32875^s22071</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36305^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
