<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056377</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Goya and his lower urinary tract symptoms in Bordeaux, 1825</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The famous painter Francisco de Goya y Lucientes (1746-1828) suffered during his life one or several diseases, the nature of which has not been determined with certainty. The partially documented morbid episodes that happened during the years 1792-1793 in Seville and Cadiz, 1819 in Madrid, and 1825 in Bordeaux could be related. In the latter one, the urological signs and symptoms the distinguished patient presented have been demonstrated. The objective of this paper is to propose the hypothesis of neurosyphilis&#146; dorsal tabes responsible for the voiding disorders he presented in Bordeaux in the spring of 1825, having as a resource Goya&#146;s &#147;diplomatario&#148;, with the letters and documents that have been collected and made known to date, with the purpose of using an inductive-deductive method for their study and interpretation, setting an interrelation between these valuable sources with both the medical knowledge of the period and the current, particularly in urological features, and reviewing the available bibliography on that topic, with the natural reserve about giving a retrospective diagnosis which cannot be completely true due to its inherent characteristics. In the same way, and as a complement, we include a brief review of some circumstances and characters that surrounded the artist in France to help to incardinate and better understand the personality of Goya, already old and sick at that time</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómiz León, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El célebre pintor don Francisco de Goya y Lucientes (1746-1828) padeció a lo largo de su vida una o varias enfermedades cuya naturaleza no ha sido determinada con seguridad. Los episodios mórbidos, parcialmente documentados, correspondientes a los años 1792-1793, acontecidos en Sevilla y Cádiz; 1819, en Madrid, y 1825, en Burdeos, pudieran estar relacionados entre sí. En éste último, los signos y síntomas urológicos que el ilustre enfermó presentó sí han quedado acreditados. El objetivo del presente trabajo es proponer, recurriendo al material que no es otro que el &#147;Diplomatario de Goya&#148;, con las cartas y documentos que hasta la fecha han sido coleccionados y dados a conocer, pretendiendo observar un método inductivo-deductivo en su estudio e interpretación e interrelacionando estas valiosas fuentes tanto con los conocimientos médicos de la época como los contemporáneos, particularmente en lo que a sus aspectos urológicos se refiere, y revisando la bibliografía disponible al respecto, con las naturales reservas de un pronunciamiento diagnóstico retrospectivo que por tanto, por sus inherentes características, no puede ser de total certidumbre, la hipótesis de la tabes dorsal neurosifilítica como responsable de los trastornos miccionales que se le presentaron en Burdeos en la primavera de 1825. Igualmente, y de manera complementaria, se incluye un breve repaso de algunas de las circunstancias y personajes que rodearon al artista en Francia para ayudar a incardinar y comprender mejor la personalidad de Goya, ya por entonces anciano y enfermo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;60(8): 917-930, oct. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056377</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Goya y su sintomatología miccional de Burdeos, 1825</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13195^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9683^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9683^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1775^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14972^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1775^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1775^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34354^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34354^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38882</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23183^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23183^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14954^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14954^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
