<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72437</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Subcutaneous nodules as a sign of malignant lymphoproliferative syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Skin involvement in children with malignant processes usually appears at the same time or after the diagnosis of the primary tumour. We present the case of a girl with cutaneous involvement prior to the diagnosis of a malignant lymphoproliferative process. A previously healthy 5-month old girl who presented with an inflammatory subcutaneous lesion on the right foot. During hospital admission due to bronchiolitis at 7 months with associated pancytopenia while the myelogram showed myeloid and megakaryocytic hypoplasia, the abdominal and foot ultrasound were normal. After completing corticoid therapy for her respiratory process and transfusional support, the foot lesion had disappeared at discharge. Two months later she had a local recurrence with associated scattered subcutaneous nodules. The skin biopsy confirmed malignant infiltration; the myelogram showed 6% blast infiltration, and both abdominal ultrasound and CT scan demonstrated lymph node involvement. Immunophenotype confirmed the diagnosis of Precursor B Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma. Although complete remission was achieved at the end of the induction chemotherapy according EuroLB-02 protocol for stage IV, the patient presented a refractory leukaemia relapse thirteen months after diagnosis. Commentary: Malignancy should be suspected in the presence of a skin lesion with torpid evolution and biopsy should be considered. Differential diagnosis of malignant skin lesions in children, especially in infants, must include mainly secondary involvement of leukaemia, lymphoma, metastases of neuroblastoma or rhabdomyosarcoma and less frequently other primary processes. In our patient with an isolated cutaneous presentation, the progression of her malignant lymphoproliferative process could be modified by the corticotherapy given before the definitive diagnosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Galán del Río, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Teijeiro Álvarez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navajas Gutiérrez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Astigarraga Aguirre, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montiano Jorge, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintero Calcaño, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En su mayoría, las lesiones cutáneas de los procesos malignos aparecen de forma concomitante o posterior al diagnóstico del tumor primario. Se presenta el caso de una niña con tumefacción en la cara externa del pie derecho desde los 5 meses de vida, durante un ingreso hospitalario a los 7 meses por bronquiolitis con pancitopenia, el mielograma mostró hipoplasia mieloide y megacariocítica, con ecografía abdominal y del pie normales. Tras la administración de corticoterapia por su cuadro respiratorio y soporte transfusional, al alta se objetivó desaparición de la lesión del pie. Dos meses más tarde presentó reaparición de la tumefacción junto con nódulos subcutáneos diseminados. Confirmada la infiltración maligna en la biopsia cutánea, la estadificación demostró infiltración blástica del 6% en mielograma y afectación ganglionar abdominal en ecografía y tomografía computarizada. El inmunofenotipo F confirmó el diagnóstico de linfoma linfoblástico pre-B muy inmaduro. Se administró quimioterapia según protocolo EURO-LB-02 para estadio IV. En remisión completa al finalizar la fase de inducción; la paciente presentó recaída leucémica refractaria a los 13 meses del diagnóstico. Comentario: Ante una lesión cutánea de evolución tórpida se debe realizar una toma de biopsia para descartar malignidad. El diagnóstico diferencial de las lesiones cutáneas malignas en los niños (especialmente en lactantes) incluye fundamentalmente infiltración secundaria a leucemia o linfoma, metástasis de neuroblastoma o rabdomiosarcoma y, con menor frecuencia, otros procesos primarios. En esta paciente con presentación cutánea aislada, el curso de su proceso linfoproliferativo maligno pudo modificarse mediante la corticoterapia recibida previa al diagnóstico definitivo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);71(2): 148-152, ago. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72437</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nódulos subcutáneos como forma de presentación de síndrome linfoproliferativo maligno</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53101^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52571^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8403^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
