<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-15496</identifier>
<setSpec>1136-4890</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Heterogeneous distribution of cytochrome oxidase activity in the human substantia nigra pars compacta</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The activity of the enzyme cytochrome oxidase has been analyzed in the human substantia nigra at light microscope level. The distribution of this activity is relatively uniform in the substantia nigra, except in the caudomedial region of the pars compacta, where a reduction was observed. This nigral zone matched a region characterized by its relatively high content of acetylcholinesterase activity. Our results are analyzed with reference to data in the literature, showing the existence of a neuroanatomical and functional subdivision within the pars compacta. Our findings add new proof of the known neurochemical heterogeneity of the nigral complex (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sociedad Anatómica Española</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La actividad de la enzima citocromo oxidasa ha sido analizada en la sustancia negra humana a nivel de microscopía óptica. La distribución de dicha actividad es relativamente uniforme en la sustancia negra, con excepción de la región caudomedial de la partes compacta, donde se aprecia una reducción. Esta zona nigral correspondía a una región caracterizada por el contenido relativamente alto en actividad acetilcolinesterásico. Nuestros resultados se analizan con referencia a los datos publicados en la literatura, mostrando la existencia de una subdivisión neuroanatómica y funcional dentro de la partes compacta. Los hallazgos aportan nuevas evidencias sobre la conocida heterogeneidad neuroquímica del complejo nigral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Eur. j. anat;4(1): 15-18, mayo 2000. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Distribución heterogénea de la actividad de citocromo oxidasa en la pars compacta de la sustancia negra humana</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Castellanos, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Catalina Herrera, CJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Castellanos, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carmona, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-15496</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31728^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31728^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22685^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
