<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91298</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Integrating simulation training into the nursing curriculum</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Simulation is gaining momentum in nurse education across the UnitedKingdom. This article gives a brief history of simulation, discussescompetence and why simulation is best placed to teach nursesin today&#146;s health service.An innovative approach to implementing simulation into the nursingcurriculum is introduced: the Programme for Nursing CurriculumIntegration (PNCI) has been designed to assist in the integrationof human patient simulation throughout the pre-registrationnursing curriculum.The original PNCI that was developed in North America in 2005 wasreviewed and updated in 2008 with ten additional SCEs. In 2009, thePNCI for Canada was launched and in 2010 the PNCI for the UnitedKingdom will be reviewed and amended in line with changes in nursingpractice.The PNCI along with the METI family of simulators allows facultiesof health and social care to easily and effectively develop an evidence-based simulation curriculum to prepare nurses for caring in thetwenty-first century and beyond (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Doyle, Thomas J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Wilford, Amanda</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La simulación está adquiriendo una importancia sustancial en la enseñanzade Enfermería en todo el Reino Unido. Este artículo muestraun breve resumen de la historia de la simulación, discute la competenciay por qué la simulación es la mejor vía para enseñar a las enfermerasen el sistema sanitario actual. Se incluye además un sistema innovadorde implementación de la simulación en el currículo de Enfermería:el Programa para la Integración de la Simulación en la Enseñanzade Enfermería (PNCI). Ha sido diseñado para ayudar a la integraciónde la simulación del paciente en el currículo de Enfermería. El PNCI originalfue desarrollado en Norteamérica en 2005 y revisado y actualizadoen 2008 con diez &#147;Experiencias Clínicas Simuladas&#148; (SCEs) adicionales.En 2009 fue lanzado el PNCI de Canadá y en 2010 el PNCIdel Reino Unido será revisado y modificado con posibles cambios parala práctica de la Enfermería. El PNCI junto con la familia de simuladoresMETI (Medical Education Technologies Incorporated) permite a lasEscuelas de Enfermería, de una forma sencilla y efectiva, desarrollar uncurrículum de simulación basada en la evidencia para preparar a los profesionalesenfermeros en el cuidado en el siglo XXI y en adelante (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;12(8): 14-18, oct. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91298</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La simulación en la enseñanzade la Enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32065^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3499^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
