<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140932</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Optimization strategies in management of CMV infection in transplant patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Currently, two therapeutic strategies are applied for preventing the development of CMV end-organ disease in transplant recipients: universal prophylaxis and preemptive antiviral therapy. Both are potentially optimable. As for the former strategy,  precisely identifying patients at greatest risk of viremia would allow for a targeted prophylaxis. In this sense several genotypic, immunological and biological markers have been described that could be ancillary to that purpose. As for the latter strategy, combined monitoring of plasma CMV DNA load and peripheral levels of CMV-specific CD8 + and CD4 + IFN-&amp;#947; producing T cells would permit a more rationale use of antivirals, thus avoiding overtreatment and derived toxicity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Navarro, David</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la actualidad se emplean dos estrategias terapéuticas para prevenir el desarrollo de enfermedad orgánica por el CMV en el paciente trasplantado, la profilaxis universal y el tratamiento anticipado. Ambas son potencialmente optimizables. La primera, identificando con precisión a los pacientes con máximo riesgo de viremia con objeto de tratarlos selectivamente (profilaxis dirigida). En este sentido disponemos de marcadores genotípicos, biológicos en inmunológicos que podrían permitirlo. La segunda, a través de la monitorización conjunta de la carga viral del CMV en plasma y del nivel de LT CD8+ y CD4+ productores de IFN-g específicos frente al CMV (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;28(supl.1): 52-53, sept. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140932</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Optimación de estrategias en el manejo de la infección por el CMV en el trasplante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30037^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14572^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30037^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14572^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30037^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30037^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52055^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29653</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52055^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52055^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
