<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79819</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Opioids in spinal pain. Risk/benefit ratio and an appropriate strategy for their use</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the last few years there has been a notable increase in the use of opioids in our country, overcoming our traditional position at the end of the queue of opioid prescribers in Europe. This growth has also been reflected in the treatment of highly prevalent pain syndromes, such as spinal pain. However, the efficacy of opioids administered chronically for spinal pain is not clear, due to the risks that have to be assumed being obvious: addiction, aberrant behaviour, probable increase in time off sick and the many secondary effects, such as hyperalgesia or persistent constipation with treatment. Taking into account the narrow risk/benefit ratio for this treatment, we assume that these drugs have been prescribed only by physicians who can closely follow up the patients, patients in whom other options are exhausted, including different analgesic techniques and those who will have been amply informed on their correct use and possible side effects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Robaina, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caramés, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Clavo, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos años se ha observado un incremento notable en el uso de los opioides en España, por lo que queda ampliamente superada nuestra tradicional posición en el furgón de cola de los prescriptores de opioides en Europa. Este crecimiento se ha reflejado también en el tratamiento de uno de los síndromes dolorosos de mayor prevalencia: el dolor raquídeo. Sin embargo, la eficacia de los opioides administrados de forma crónica para el tratamiento del dolor raquídeo no está clara, aunque cada vez sí son más patentes los riesgos que hemos de asumir: adicción, conductas aberrantes, probable incremento en el tiempo de incapacidad laboral y múltiples efectos secundarios, como la hiperalgesia o el estreñimiento rebelde al tratamiento. Teniendo en cuenta una relación riesgo/beneficio estrecha para este tratamiento, planteamos que estos fármacos sólo los han de prescribir facultativos que puedan realizar un seguimiento atento de los pacientes, pacientes en los que se han agotado otras opciones terapéuticas, incluidas diferentes técnicas antiálgicas y a los cuales habremos informado ampliamente de su correcta utilización y posibles efectos secundarios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;17(3): 169-176, abr. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79819</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Opioides en el dolor raquídeo. Relación riesgo/beneficio y estrategia apropiada para su utilización</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d715^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22559^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
