<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139919</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sanitary waste in the hospital setting: attitude of health professionals toward advanced management of sanitary waste</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The aim of this study was to assess the attitude of nurse assistants, nurses, physicians, and lab technicians about advanced management of medical waste. Methods. Cross-sectional study of Attitude and explanatory variable degree of concordance between Attitude, Knowledge, and Risk Perception. The sample size was 176 health professionals from three hospitals in the Barcelona area. A questionnaire of 44 items with responses measured on a Likert scale type questions and free and spontaneous association and incomplete sentences was used. Results. Mean Attitude of health professionals surveyed was 4.40, with a standard deviation of 0.4 on a scale of 1-5, where 1 is considered a very negative and five a very positive Attitude. According to the values obtained with the Professional Category, the nurse assistants had an average value of 4.45 in Attitude, followed by nurses (4.36), physicians (4.27), and lab technicians (4.47). In the Pearson correlation, coefficients between Attitude, Risk Perception, Global Assessment, and level of Knowledge, values of r = 0.172 and p = 0.023 were obtained, r = -0.156 and p = 0.039 and r = 0.013 and p = 0.865 respectively. The mean values of the variables Knowledge, Risk Perception, Attitude, and Overall Rating were significantly different (ANOVA) in Knowledge level, according to Professional Category and Welfare Service, but not in other categories. Conclusions. The results of the current study suggest that health professionals generally have a very positive Attitude towards the management of medical waste. A significant relationship between Attitude and Risk Perception and Overall Rating was observed. In terms of the analysis of Variance, there was a significant difference in the level of Knowledge according to the Professional Category and the Assistance Service (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torres-Egea, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Girbau-García, M Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torrens-Garcia, M Llum</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Estalella, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sancho-Agredano, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galimany-Masclans, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fabrellas, Núria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Conocer la actitud que tienen los técnicos auxiliares de cuidados de enfermería, las enfermeras, los médicos y los técnicos de laboratorio frente a la gestión avanzada de los residuos sanitarios (RS). Metodología. Estudio descriptivo transversal de la variable Actitud y explicativo del grado de concordancia entre Actitud, Conocimiento y Percepción de Riesgo. El tamaño de la muestra fue de 176 profesionales sanitarios de tres hospitales de la provincia de Barcelona. Se utilizó un cuestionario de 44 ítems con respuestas medidas en una escala tipo Likert y preguntas de asociación libre y espontánea y de frases incompletas. Resultados. La Actitud media de los profesionales sanitarios estudiados es de 4.40, con una desviación típica de 0.4, en una escala de 1 a 5 donde 1 se considera una Actitud muy negativa y 5 muy positiva. De acuerdo con los valores obtenidos con la Categoría Profesional, tenemos que los técnicos auxiliares de cuidados de enfermería dan un valor medio de Actitud de 4.45, las enfermeras de 4.36, los médicos de 4.27 y los técnicos de laboratorio de 4.47. En los coeficientes de correlación de Pearson entre la Actitud, la Percepción de Riesgo, la Valoración Global y el Nivel de Conocimiento, se obtuvieron unos valores de r = 0.172 y p = 0.023, r = -0.156 y p = 0.039, y r = 0.013 y p = 0.865, respectivamente. Tras analizar los valores promedio de las variables Conocimiento, Percepción de Riesgo, Actitud y Valoración Global, se obtuvieron diferencias significativas a través del ANOVA, en nivel de Conocimiento en función de la Categoría Profesional y Servicio Asistencial, no así en el resto de categorías. Conclusiones. El análisis de los resultados sugiere que los profesionales de la salud tienen, en general, una Actitud muy positiva frente a la gestión de los RS. Se observa una relación muy significativa entre la Actitud, la Percepción de Riesgo y la Valoración Global. En cuanto al análisis de la Varianza, se obtuvo una diferencia significativa en el nivel de Conocimiento según la Categoría Profesional y el Servicio Asistencial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;38(6): 434-440, jun. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139919</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Residuos sanitarios en el ámbito hospitalario (y 3). Actitud de los profesionales de la salud frente a la gestión avanzada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24419</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31314</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31974^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23897</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29004</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
