<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163182</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hemodynamic and renal implications of sodium-glucose cotransporter-2 inhibitors in type 2 diabetes mellitus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In DM2, there is increased expression of the proximal glucose transporter SGLT2. The increased glucose reabsorption from the urine to the proximal tubule and subsequently to the bloodstream, has three direct effects on the prognosis of patients with DM2: a) it increases the daily glucose load by raising the renal threshold for glucose, thus augmenting requirements for oral antidiabetics and insulin. This progressive increase occurs throughout the course of the disease and in parallel with the increase in renal mass (renal hypertrophy); b) because of the greater glucose reabsorption, glycosuria is lower than the level corresponding to glycaemia, decreasing the stimulus on the tubuloglomerular feedback system of the distal nephron. As a result, the glomerular vasodilation caused by hyperglycaemia is not arrested, maintaining glomerular hyperfiltration, and c) the excess glucose transported to the proximal tubular cells modifies their redox status, increasing local production of glycosylating products and activating local production of proinflammatory and profibrotic proliferative mediators. These mediators are responsible for the direct free radical damage to proximal tubular cells, for increased SGLT2 expression, increased production of collagen IV and extracellular matrix, and activation of monocyte/macrophages able to cause endothelial injury. The use of SGLT2 inhibitors not only reduces the reabsorption of glucose from the glomerular filtrate back into the circulationthus improving metabolic control in diabetesbut also restores tubuloglomerular feedback by increasing glycosuria and distal urinary flow. However, the most notable effect is due to inhibition of glucose entry to the proximal tubular cells. Glycosuria is toxic to the kidney: it harms glucosetransporting cells, that is, the proximal cells, which contain SGLT2. In animal models, SGLT2 inhibition reduces local production of oxygen-free radicals, the formation of mesangial matrix and collagen IV, glomerular infiltration by inflammatory cells and monocyte/macrophage-dependent arteriosclerosis. In humans, SGLT2 have a demonstrated ability to reduce renal injury and cardiovascular risk in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tejedor Jorge, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Durante la diabetes mellitus tipo 2 se produce un aumento en la expresión del transportador proximal de glucosa SGLT2. Este aumento indebido de la recuperación de glucosa filtrada desde la orina hacia el túbulo proximal y, posteriormente, hacia el torrente sanguíneo tiene 3 repercusiones directas sobre el pronóstico del paciente con diabetes mellitus tipo 2: a) aumento de la carga diaria de glucosa al elevar el umbral de reabsorción. Como consecuencia aumentan los requerimientos de antidiabéticos orales y de insulina. Este aumento es progresivo a lo largo de la enfermedad y va a la par con el aumento de masa renal (hipertrofia renal); b) la mayor reabsorción de glucosa hace que la glucosuria sea menor de la correspondiente al valor de glucemia, disminuyendo el estímulo sobre el «feed-back» tubuloglomerular de la nefrona distal. Como resultado, no se contrarresta la vasodilatación glomerular causada por la hiperglucemia, perpetuándose la hiperfiltración glomerular, y c) el exceso de glucosa transportado a la célula del túbulo proximal modifica el estado redox de esta, aumentando la producción local de productos con capacidad glucosilativa y activando la producción local de mediadores proliferativos proinflamatorios y profibróticos. Estos mediadores son responsables del daño directo por radicales libres a la célula tubular proximal, del aumento de expresión de SGLT2, del aumento de producción de colágeno IV y de matriz extracelular, y de la activación de monocitosmacrófagos con capacidad lesiva endotelial. La utilización de inhibidores del transporte proximal de glucosa SGLT2 no solo reduce la reinyección de la glucosa ya filtrada desde la orina hacia la sangre, mejorando el control metabólico de la diabetes, sino que además restaura el «feed-back» tubuloglomerular al aumentar la glucosuria y el flujo urinario distal. Pero el efecto más notable se debe a la inhibición de la entrada de glucosa en la célula tubular proximal. La glucosuria es tóxica para el riñón: lo es para las células capaces de transportar glucosa, es decir, las células proximales dotadas de SGLT2. En modelos animales, al inhibir SGLT2 se reduce la producción local de radicales de oxígeno, disminuye la formación de matriz mesangial y de colágeno IV, hay menor infiltración glomerular por células inflamatorias y se reduce la arteriosclerosis dependiente de monocito-macrófago. En clínica humana, los iSGLT2 han mostrado su capacidad para reducir el daño renal y el riesgo cardiovascular de los pacientes con diabetes mellitus tipo 2 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);147(supl.esp.1): 35-43, nov. 2016. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163182</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implicaciones hemodinámicas y renales de los inhibidores del cotransportador sodio-glucosa tipo 2 en el contexto de la diabetes mellitus tipo 2</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55729^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7853^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7124^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6590^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50911^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6171^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
