<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116977</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mild cognitive Impairment: Risk of Dementia according to Subtypes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Mild cognitive impairment (MCI) has 3 clinical subtypes: amnestic (aMCI), multiple domains (mdMCI) and non-amnestic single domain (na-SD-MCI) whose evolutive possibility to dementia has not been profoundly studied. Objective: This paper aims to determine the conversion to dementia of the different subtypes of MCI and determine risk factors associated to conversion to dementia. Methods: A total of 127 patients diagnosed with MCI (age=70.21; SD=13.17) were evaluated with a neuropsychological and neuropsychiatric battery. They were classified into 3 groups: amnestic MCI (n=20), multiple domain MCI (n=98), non-amnestic MCI (n=9). Seventeen normal subjects (age=74.59; SD=10.63) were included. Results: Of those included, 27.1% developed Alzheimer&#146;s type dementia [average time for conversion to Alzheimer&#146;s dementia (AD) 11.12 months (SD=0.183)]. None of the controls developed dementia. Thirty-five percent (n=7) of amnestic MCI converted to AD: 20% (n=4) at 6 months and15% (n=3) at 12 months); 11.1% (n=1) of the non-amnestic single domain MCI converted to AD at 6 months. It was found that 31.6% (n=31) of multiple domain MCI rotated to AD: 15.3% (n=15) at 6 months and 16.3% (n=16) at 12months. Age (p&lt;0.05, &amp;#946;=1.03) increased the likelihood of rotation to AD. Multi-domain MCI subtype was the most frequent. However, the conversion to dementia in amnestic subtype was the highest, age and retirement being the variables that increased the likelihood of conversion to Dementia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Leis, Adriana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dillon, Carol</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Taragano, Fernando E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano, Cecilia M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Allegri, Ricardo Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El deterioro cognitivo leve (DCL) presenta 3 subtipos clínicos: amnésico (DCLa), múltiples dominios (DCLmd) y dominio único no amnésico (DCLduna), cuya evolutividad a demencia no ha sido extensamente estudiada. El objetivo de este trabajo es evaluar la conversión a demencia de los diferentes subtipos de DCL y determinar los factores de riesgo asociados a la misma. Métodos: Se reclutaron 127 pacientes con Deterioro Cognitivo Leve (edad 70,21; DS 13,17) fueron evaluados conuna batería neuropsicológica y neuropsiquiátrica y clasificados en 3 grupos: DCLa (n=20), DCLmd (n=98) y DCLduna (n=9). Diecisiete controles normales (edad 74,59; DE 10,63) fueron incluidos. Resultados: El 27,1% de los pacientes con DCL desarrolló demencia tipo Alzheimer (promedio 11,12 meses, DE=0,183).Ninguno de los controles convirtió a demencia. El 35% (n=7) del grupo con DCLa convirtió a Demencia: un 20% (n=4) a6 meses y un 15% (n=3) a 12 meses; 11,1% (n=1) del grupo con DCLduna convirtió a demencia en 6 meses. El 31,6%(n=31) de DCLmd rotó a demencia: el 15,3% (n=15) en 6meses y un 16,3% (n=16) al año. La edad (p&lt;0,05, &amp;#946;=1,03) aumentó la probabilidad de conversión a demencia. El grupo de DCLmd fue el más frecuente, sin embargo fue mayor la conversión a demencia en el DCLa, siendo la edad y la jubilación las variables que aumentaron la probabilidad de conversión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;41(6): 330-339, nov.-dic. 2013. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116977</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Deterioro cognitivo leve: riesgo de demencia según subtipos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
