<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042852</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-7823</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Image of Psychology as a sanitary profession in Psychology and Medicine university professors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study is to know the Psychology and Medicine professors´ opinion about Psychology as a sanitary profession. Atotal of 593 Psychology and Medicine University professors participated in the study. A questionnaire about Psychology as asanitary profession was designed and it was provided to the professors by an e-mail. The data were analyzed according toprofessors´ discipline, academic area and professional profile. The results indicated that there is a favourable opinion of thePsychology and Medicine professors about Clinical Psychology as a sanitary profession. The data obtained are useful as anapproximation about the Psychology and Medicine professors´ opinion about Psychology as a sanitary profession</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bretón-López, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Buela-Casal, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sierra, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agudelo, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Teva, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermúdez, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Roales-Nieto, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente estudio es conocer la imagen que tienen los profesores de Psicología y Medicina de la Psicología comodisciplina sanitaria. Participaron un total de 593 profesores universitarios de Psicología y Medicina. Se les aplicó un cuestionariode opinión sobre la Psicología como profesión sanitaria elaborado por los investigadores que les fue facilitado a travésde correo electrónico. Los datos se analizaron en función de la disciplina, área académica y categoría docente de los profesores.Los resultados indicaron que existe una opinión favorable de los profesores de Psicología y Medicina acerca de la PsicologíaClínica como disciplina sanitaria. Los datos obtenidos son útiles como aproximación sobre la opinión de los profesores dePsicología y Medicina acerca de la Psicología como profesión sanitaria</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pap. psicol;26(91): 4-15, ago. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042852</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Imagen de la Psicología como profesión sanitaria en profesores de Psicología y Medicina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12028^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12958^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12023^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5280^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14893^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1543^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
