<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119412</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">When babies suffer. Reflections on the psychic pain from the observation and clinic</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper addresses the importance for the development of the baby of the detection  and early treatment of psychopathological deviations of an autistic and  psychosomatic nature that can develop in the baby as a consequence of perinatal  traumatic situations. These traumatic situations, that can&#146;t be elaborated or integrated  into the mother&#146;s psyche, disturb the normal development of the mother-baby  interaction, creating in the child a traumatic emotional effect as they are transmitted  psychically without being transformed; a transmission which is unconscious and  unintentional. The modality of generational transmission and its effects are analyzed  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez de Plá, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo se plantea una reflexión sobre la importancia del dolor en los orígenes del  psiquismo y la existencia de situaciones traumáticas muy precoces capaces de  perturbar la frágil organización psíquica de los bebés por ruptura de la barrera  antiestímulo. Aunque también incluye aspectos teóricos, a través de viñetas clínicas y  sus comentarios el texto busca, sobre todo, mostrar diversas facetas de una realidad  que suele ignorarse, que está a nuestro alrededor en diferentes espacios y condiciones  económicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(22): 27-41, nov. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119412</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuando los bebés sufren. Reflexiones sobre el dolor psíquico desde la observación y la clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2696^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32270^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23274</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201311</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
