<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161317</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Safety culture among healthcare professionals</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to understand the perception by professionals in the Corporació Sanitària Parc Taulí (CSPT) (Sabadell, Barcelona), regarding patient safety culture. Method: a descriptive, transversal, observational study, including different types of healthcare professionals: managers, physicians, graduates (Nursing, Physiotherapy, etc., nursing assistants, and medium-level technicians with &gt;3-month seniority in the CSPT. The 61-item questionnaire published by the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ) in 2004, and validated by the Ministry of Health, was used in order to measure safety culture. Said questionnaire was available for participants through the hospital website, with an note of invitation to take part. The SPSS 15.0 statistical program was used for data analysis, and the ANOVA test was used to analyze the statistical significance of differences by type of professionals and hospital unit. The period of the study was from September, 2014 to April, 2015. Results: in total, 331 questionnaires were collected (overall response rate: 14%). &#145;Team work&#146; was one of the best valued dimensions, with 65% positive answers; on the other hand, two of the four questions assessing the &#145;Staffing&#146; dimension were negatively valued by &gt;70%. Conclusions: taking into account the low participation and the results obtained, we can reach the conclusion that there is a low safety culture in the CSPT, and that this would be a major area for improvement (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rus García, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caro Miquela, Aurora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Magide, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Partera Luque, M Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valls García, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Iruela, David</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: conocer la percepción de los profesionales de la Corporació Sanitària Parc Taulí (CSPT) (Sabadell, Barcelona), en relación a la cultura de seguridad del paciente. Método: estudio observacional descriptivo de corte transversal en el que participaron profesionales sanitarios de las siguientes categorías: gerentes/directores, médicos, diplomados (Enfermería, Fisioterapia, etc.), auxiliares de Enfermería y técnicos de grado medio con más de tres meses de antigüedad en la CSPT. Para medir la cultura de la seguridad se utilizó el cuestionario de 61 ítems publicado por la Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ) en 2004 y validado por el Ministerio de Sanidad. El cuestionario se puso a disposición de los participantes a través de la web del hospital junto con una nota que invitaba a la participación. Para el aná- lisis de datos se utilizó el programa estadístico SPSS 15.0 y para analizar la significación estadística de las diferencias por tipo de profesional y servicios el test ANOVA. El periodo de estudio fue de septiembre del 2014 a abril de 2015. Resultados: se recogieron un total de 331 cuestionarios (tasa global de respuesta 14%). La dimensión &#145;Trabajo en equipo&#146; fue una de las mejores valoradas con un 65% de respuestas positivas, mientras que dos de las cuatro preguntas que evaluaban la dimensión &#145;Dotación de personal&#146; fue valorada negativamente en más de un 70%. Conclusiones: teniendo en cuenta la baja participación junto a los resultados obtenidos se puede concluir que en la CSPT existe una baja cultura de seguridad y que sería una importante área de mejora  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;20(1): 6-15, feb. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161317</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cultura de seguridad en los profesionales sanitarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23790</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33118^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31061^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33550</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
