<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139916</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">From the silence and the obedience, to the innovation and the visibility</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Nursing process has been influenced and modified throughout history by different factors, as familiar, social and cultural aspects. Basically, the vocation has made nursing a tremendously servile and dedicated profession, which is drowing out its initiative and its innovation. Protectionist influences towards the profession, are the main barrier to the innovation, effective leadership and to different ways of thinking. Furthermore, the professional silence and the obedience to other disciplines, have slowed professional progress and the visibility of patient care. Nowadays, more than before, there is clearly perceived in the nursing staff a sense of helplessness and legally defenceless. At the same time, a lack of professional ideology and a sense of underused and undervalued profession. This undermines the development of innovation and effective leadership. Besides, it must be taken into account that the inviolability of personal approach and the invisibility of our profession are related to the professional silence. This fact has a direct effect on nurse&#146;s leadership team (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pocino Campayo, Angélica</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A lo largo de la historia al pensamiento enfermero lo han influido y modificado factores familiares, sociales y culturales. La vocación ha hecho de la enfermería una profesión fundamentalmente servil y entregada, lo que coarta en cierto modo su propia iniciativa y, con ello, la innovación. Las influencias proteccionistas hacia la profesión son la principal barrera a la innovación, al liderazgo y a formas diferentes de pensar. El silencio profesional y la obediencia a otras disciplinas han frenado el desarrollo profesional y la visibilidad de los cuidados enfermeros. En la profesión de enfermería se percibe una sensación de impotencia y desamparo legal, una ausencia de ideología profesional y un sentido de profesión infrautilizada e infravalorada que desincentiva la innovación y el liderazgo. La intangibilidad del trato personal y la invisibilidad de la profesión se relacionan con el silencio profesional que afecta directamente al liderazgo de la enfermería (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;38(6): 414-418, jun. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139916</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Del silencio y la obediencia a la innovación y la visibilidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8035</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37622^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36312</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
