<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157591</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-031X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Testicular pain due to thoracolumbar junction syndrome: a case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Thoracolumbar junction syndrome (TLJS) occurs as a result of a minor intervertebral dysfunction at the thoracolumbar junction, and causes pain in the low back, hip, groin, testicles and lower abdomen. Likewise the case hereunder, TLJS can often be confused with other pathologies that may cause these symptoms and leading to misdiagnosis and false treatment. Case report. A sixty-one year old man complained of pulsatile right testicle pain and low back pain after the instrumentation at L2&#150;L5 level for spondylolisthesis. For his insistent complains, his right testicle was removed surgically and medical treatment was given for low back pain but his complains did not relieved. Physical examination revealed severe limitation of the lumbar spine, and pain in all directions. Posteroanterior pressure at the T12&#150;L1 and L4&#150;5 intervertebral spaces, at the T12 spinous processes and transverse pressure against the lateral aspect of the T12 spinous process were painful. Pinch and roll test and pressure over the right trochanteric and pubic region were painful. According to these findings, we diagnosed the patient as a TLJS but we could not apply diagnostic T12 periapophyseal joint block because the patient did not accept this intervention, manipulation could not be applied because of the instrumentation at the thoracolumbar spine. The spinal mobilization therapy to the thoracolumbar segment was applied gently and gabapentin was started at a low dose of 300mg/day, and increased gradually to 2400mg/day. Exercise program and daily living activities were organized. His symptoms improved after 3 months of treatment. It was observed that the general well-being has continued after two years of follow up. Conclusion. Thoracolumbar junction syndrome is a pathology that should be considered in the differential diagnosis of testicular pain (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palamar, Deniz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ozkan, Feyza Unlu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Akgun, Kenan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aktas, Ilknur</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El síndrome de unión toracolumbar (TLJS de sus siglas en inglés) se produce como consecuencia de una disfunción intervertebral menor en la unión toracolumbar, y causa dolor en la zona baja de la espalda, la cadera, la ingle, los testículos y el abdomen inferior. Como en el caso que se presenta, el TLJS puede confundirse a menudo con otras patologías que pueden causar estos síntomas, conduciendo a un diagnóstico erróneo y tratamiento equivocado. Caso. Un hombre de 61 años refería dolor pulsátil en el testículo derecho y dolor en la zona baja de la espalda después de la instrumentación para espondilolistesis a nivel de L2-L5. Por su insistente queja, fue sometido a orquiectomía derecha y se indicó tratamiento médico para el dolor de la zona baja de la espalda, a pesar de lo cual las molestias persistieron. Un examen físico bien hecho reveló una importante limitación de la columna lumbar y el dolor en todas las direcciones. La presión posteroanterior en los espacios intervertebrales T12-L1 y L4-L5, apófisis espinosas T12 y la presión transversal contra la cara lateral de la apófisis espinosa T12 eran dolorosas. El signo del pellizco o enrollamiento y la presión sobre la región del trocánter derecho y región púbica eran dolorosos. De acuerdo con estos hallazgos, se diagnosticó al paciente como un TLJS, pero no pudo aplicarse el diagnóstico por bloqueo periapofisario T12 porque el paciente no aceptó esta intervención; la manipulación no pudo aplicarse debido a la instrumentación de la columna dorsolumbar. La terapia de movilización espinal para el segmento toracolumbar se aplicó cuidadosamente y se instauró tratamiento con gabapentina a una dosis baja de 300mg/día, la cual fue incrementándose gradualmente hasta 2.400mg/día. Se organizó un programa de ejercicios y actividades de la vida diaria. Sus síntomas mejoraron después de 3 meses de tratamiento. Se observó que el bienestar general ha continuado después de 2 años de seguimiento. Conclusión. El TLJS es una patología que debe ser considerada en el diagnóstico diferencial del dolor testicular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. int. androl. (Ed. impr.);14(4): 148-152, oct.-dic. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157591</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dolor testicular debido al síndrome de unión toracolumbar: reporte de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54686^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14112^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27938^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14116^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14116^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23533^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21066^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21066^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23533^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
