<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82767</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of use of hormone replacement therapy in women participating in a breast cancer screening program</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: the purpose of the study was to determine the prevalence and type of hormone replacement therapy (HRT) in participants in a breast cancer screening program (BCSP) in Barcelona. Patients and Method: Prevalence of use of HRT was obtained through a survey. Information about type of HRT, gynecological history and socioeconomic and educational level was collected. Prevalence was calculated with its corresponding 95% confidence interval. Results: From May 2001 to June 2005 there were 21835 participants in the BCSP with a mean age of 57,6 years. Most of the participants were postmenopausal (86,7%). Confirmed prevalence of use of HRT was 5,2%(CI95% 5,3&#150;6,0) with a greater use among women aged 55 to 59 years. The most frequent types of HRT were tibolone (39,5%) followed by combined estrogens plus progestin (30,4%). Higher education was associated with a higher use of HRT. Neither the use or the type of HRT influenced the results of the screening program. Conclusions: Prevalence of use of HRT was 5,2% in this study. The most frequently used agents were tibolone and combined estrogens plus progestin (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Puig, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solá, Judit</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintana, María Jesus</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Pino, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonfill, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Determinar la prevalencia y el tipo de tratamiento hormonal sustitutivo (THS) en participantes de un programa de cribado de cáncer de mama de Barcelona. Pacientes y método: La prevalencia de consumo de THS se obtuvo a través de una encuesta. Se recogió información sobre tipo de THS, antecedentes ginecológicos, situación laboral y nivel de estudios. La prevalencia se calculó con sus intervalos de confianza (IC) del 95%. Resultados: Entre mayo de 2001 y junio de 2005 participaron en el programa de cribado de cáncer de mama 21.835 mujeres con una edad media de 57,6 años (el 86,7% posmenopáusicas). La prevalencia confirmada de consumo de THS fue del 5,2% (IC del 95%: 5,3&#150;6,0), y se administró con mayor frecuencia a mujeres entre 55 y 59 años. Los tipos más frecuentes fueron la tibolona (39,5%) y la combinación de estrógenos y progestágenos (30,4%). El nivel educativo alto se relacionó con mayor consumo de THS. No hubo diferencias estadísticamente significativas en el resultado del cribado según consumo o tipo de THS. Conclusiones: La prevalencia de uso del THS fue del 5,2%. Los tipos de THS más frecuentes fueron la tibolona y la combinación de estrógenos y progestágenos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);134(10): 439-442, abr. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82767</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de tratamiento hormonal sustitutivo en mujeres que participan en un programa de cribado de cáncer de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32835^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
