<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055711</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Benign myoclonic epilepsy- a curious case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Benign myoclonic epilepsy in infants is a rare condition that belongs to the group of epilepsies and generalised epileptic syndromes. Doubts have recently arisen as to whether it is really benign, with some reports of cases of compromised psychomotor development when therapy is started late. The differential diagnosis can be associated with    epileptic and non-epileptic diseases, and it is important to preclude it from the former due to their severity. Lombroso and Fejerman&#146;s benign myocloni are the non-epileptic diseases that create most problems as far as the differential diagnosis is concerned. Congenital defects of the cranial vault are quite rare and are sometimes associated with other malformations. Exceptionally they appear in isolation, and familial cases have been reported. Case report. Here we describe the case of a female infant, who had been subject to a follow-up in the Children&#146;s Neurology department from the age of 7 months and who had been diagnosed as suffering from unspecific bone erosion of the cranial vault and benign myoclonic epilepsy in infants.    Psychomotor development has taken place within the range of parameters that can be considered to be normal and the patient is currently 25 months old. Conclusions. From the clinical point of view, in this case we can rule out the most severe epileptic situations. This is a clinical case that is atypical, not only because of the coexistence of two rare diagnoses, but also due to the clinical features and electroencephalographic manifestations. Both situations are very uncommon and there is no apparent relationship between them</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Velázquez-Fragua, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salgueiro, A. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Bermejo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La epilepsia mioclónica benigna del lactante es una entidad poco frecuente que forma parte del grupo de las epilepsias y los síndromes epilépticos generalizados. Últimamente, han aparecido dudas sobre si su carácter es realmente benigno, con algunas descripciones de casos de afectación del desarrollo psicomotor cuando la terapia se inicia tarde. El diagnóstico diferencial se puede asociar con enfermedades epilépticas y no epilépticas, y es importante descartarla de las primeras por la gravedad que acarrean. Las mioclonías benignas de Lombroso y Fejerman son las enfermedades no epilépticas que más problemas de diagnóstico diferencial comportan. Los defectos congénitos de la bóveda craneal son bastante raros    y, a veces, están asociados a otras malformaciones. Cuando se presentan de manera aislada, son excepcionales, registrándose casos familiares. Caso clínico. Lactante de sexo femenino, con seguimiento en la consulta de Neurología Infantil desde los 7 meses de edad, con los diagnósticos de erosión ósea inespecífica de la bóveda craneal y epilepsia mioclónica benigna del lactante. El desarrollo psicomotor se ha producido dentro de los parámetros considerados normales, y actualmente la paciente tiene 25 meses de edad. Conclusiones. Desde el punto de vista clínico, podemos descartar las situaciones epilépticas más graves en este caso. Se trata de un caso clínico atípico, no sólo por la coexistencia de dos diagnósticos raros, sino por la clínica y las manifestaciones electroencefalográficas. Ambas situaciones son muy poco frecuentes y no existe una relación aparente entre ellas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;45(3): 152-154, ago. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055711</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Epilepsia mioclónica benigna del lactante: un caso curioso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30333^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1873^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30333^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
