<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162078</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nursing intervention and specialized nursing ambulatory surgery clinic improvement of total quality management (perceived and scientific and technical quality) in patients undergoing ambulatory laparoscopic cholecystectomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the added value of nursing intervention in ambulatory laparoscopic  cholecystectomy in acceptance and security rates by patients and the associated increase in quality perception in terms of scientific and technical quality and perceived quality. Patients and methods: Patients belonged to private insurance companies undergoing elective ALC at the Institutor de Cirugía y Aparato Digestivo (ICAD) in Quiron Hospital at Valencia City. Quality assessment was performed trough the ICAD 15 questionnaire which is based on SUCMA14 modified for ALC patients. For comparison analysis we used a control group previously evaluated with the original ICAD questionnaire and the pilot study group of the ICAD questionnaire. Main measurements and outcomes: end point analysis included global satisfaction with ALC and the percentage of patients with security feeling at discharge and adequate consideration of postoperative hospital stay (measurement of ambulatory acceptance). Statistical analysis was performed with the SPSS (11 vs) using the Chi square test for percentages comparison. Statistical significances was accepted with a p value less than 0.05. Results: The rate of patients feeling satisfied or very satisfied in the Project investigation group reached  98.5 % which was similar to that in control group and the pilot study group, 94% without reaching statistical significance. In contrast the percentage of patients considering appropriate the ambulatory process was 81.1 % in the investigative protocol group in comparison with 69,6% in the control group, p &lt; 0.05. Similarly the percentage of patients considering as adequate the postoperative stay at the hospital reached 75% of patients in the investigative protocol group in comparison with 55.4 % in the control group. Moreover the nursing intervention decreased emergency medical consultations and anticipated office appointments reaching statistical significance. Conclusions: Increasing Nursing intervention all along through the clinical process of ALC increases acceptance, security and global satisfaction by patients, decreasing unplanned medical requirements due to care discontinuity associated to ambulatory procedures. A nursing intervention as a holistic ambulatory surgery nurse should be developed in all ambulatory units (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Espinosa, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marmaneu Vicent, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Planells Roig, MV</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cervera Delgado, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar el valor de la transformación de la actividad enfermera en el proceso de colecistectomía ambulatoria en el incremento de la aceptación y la seguridad del proceso por los pacientes, así como el aumento de la calidad asistencial en sus dos áreas: la científico-técnica y la percibida. Material y métodos: Pacientes de compañías aseguradoras privadas sometidos a CLA en el ámbito del Instituto de Cirugía y Aparato Digestivo (ICAD) en el Hospital Quirón de Valencia. La evaluación de calidad se realizó mediante la aplicación del cuestionario ICAD15, basado en el SUCMA 14 y modificado para el proceso de CLA, aplicado de forma prospectiva. El grupo control lo constituyeron dos grupos de pacientes: 404 casos evaluados previamente a la instauración del ICAD15 y 75 casos correspondientes al ensayo piloto del cuestionario de satisfacción. Principales medidas de resultados: se evaluaron como puntos finales de resultado la satisfacción global con el procedimiento y la proporción de pacientes con seguridad y consideración de estancia hospitalaria adecuada (medidas de aceptación del proceso ambulatorio). El análisis estadístico se realizó mediante el SPPS vs. 11 y se utilizó la comparación de porcentajes de la Chi cuadrado, aceptándose como significativo una p &lt; 0.05. Resultados: El porcentaje de pacientes muy satisfechos o satisfechos alcanzado en el grupo del protocolo de investigación  fue del 98,5%, similar al expresado por el grupo control, y el del grupo piloto que fue del 94%, no mostrando diferencias significativas. Por el contrario, el porcentaje de pacientes que consideraron adecuado el proceso ambulatorio fue del 81,1 % en el grupo del protocolo de investigación en comparación con un 69.6 % del grupo control (p &lt; 0.05). De igual modo, también alcanzó significación el porcentaje de pacientes que consideraron adecuado el tiempo de estancia en el hospital (75,0%) del grupo de protocolo de investigación en comparación con el grupo control (55,4%).Además la intervención enfermera del grupo del protocolo de investigación disminuyó significativamente los requerimientos de consulta médica urgente y de consulta anticipada. Conclusiones: La modificación de la intervención enfermera en el proceso de CLA mejora la aceptación del procedimiento aumentando la seguridad percibida del mismo por los pacientes, alcanza un alto nivel de satisfacción y disminuye los requerimientos asistenciales no planificados derivados de la discontinuidad asistencial generada por el proceso ambulatorio. La intervención enfermera de CMA global, como se ha desarrollado en este protocolo de investigación, debería implementarse en las unidades de CMA (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;21(3): 93-137, jul.-dic. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162078</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La intervención enfermera y la consulta de enfermería en la mejora de la calidad asistencial (calidad percibida y calidad científico-técnica) en pacientes sometidos a colecistectomía laparoscópica ambulatoria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30788^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10541^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
