<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-67751</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-7279</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Depression is a common disorder found in patients consulting at a primary care level. The quality of the attention and management implemented at this level affects the course and prognosis of the disease. Objectives. To evaluate patient satisfaction with the consult as a marker of the quality of attention before and after general practitioners received an educational intervention about depression at a primary care level in Bogotá.Method. Multicentric study. The educational intervention was applied to health professionals working in outpatient primary care centers in Bogotá. 1.650 patients filled the questionnaires before the intervention and 1.832 patients after it. The descriptive analysis variables and the comparison of the results in both phases were controlled for different participant characteristics. Results. The level of satisfaction with the different aspects of the consult was high on the baseline in patients diagnosed with depression as in those without the diagnosis. Nevertheless, after professionals received training on depression, the physician&#146;s concern for the impact of problems in the life of depressed patients increased (p &lt; 0,0001). Conclusion.&amp;#8194;Depressed patients seem to behave similarly to non depressed patients with regards to their satisfaction with the different aspects of the medical encounter. However, after receiving an educational intervention about depression, physicians changed their attitude towards depressed patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Riveros Vargas, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Restrepo, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Okuda Benavides, Mayumi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Laverde, Jacky Fabian</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La depresión es una patología frecuente en los pacientes que consultan en el nivel primario de atención. La calidad de la atención y el manejo que se implementa a este nivel afecta el curso y pronóstico de la enfermedad. Objetivos. Evaluar la satisfacción del paciente con la consulta como marcador de la calidad de la atención antes y después de que los médicos recibieran una intervención educativa sobre depresión en centros de atención primaria en Bogotá. Métodos. Estudio multicéntrico. Se aplicó la intervención a profesionales que trabajaban en centros ambulatorios en Bogotá. 1.650 pacientes autodiligenciaron los cuestionarios antes de la intervención y 1.832 lo hicieron posteriormente. Se realizó el análisis descriptivo de las variables y comparación de los resultados en ambas fases, y se controlaron los resultados por las diferentes características de los participantes. Resultados. El nivel de satisfacción con los diferentes aspectos de la consulta era elevado en la línea de base tanto en los pacientes diagnosticados con depresión como en los pacientes sin diagnóstico. Sin embargo, luego de que los profesionales recibieron el entrenamiento en depresión, aumentó la preocupación de los médicos por el impacto de los problemas en la vida de los pacientes deprimidos (p &lt; 0,0001). Conclusiones.&amp;#8194;En cuanto a la satisfacción con los diferentes aspectos de la consulta, los pacientes deprimidos parecen comportarse de manera similar a los pacientes sin depresión. No obstante, luego de recibir una intervención educativa los médicos presentaron un cambio en la actitud al abordar a los pacientes deprimidos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Inf. psiquiátr;(190): 473-485, oct.-dic. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-67751</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10221^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
