<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-15651</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Curative factors in group psychotherapy: its evaluation and analysis in a sample of recovered alcoholics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Taking the idea of the positive results of alcoholic group therapy found in the literature as our starting point, we undertook an evaluation of the results of group psychotherapy in a sample of alcoholic patients (n=34), treated as outpatients, with an abstinence time of three months to three and a half years, utilising the Yalom Curative Factors Questionnaire (60 items). We found the Group Curative Factors to be: 1) Altruism, 1) Understanding of oneself, 3) Revalidation of the family, according to Yalom&#146;s Theory, among those with the highest score. These results were compared with those reported previously in the literature on the subject of Yalom&#146;s group therapy, and also with a control group of psychiatric patients (n=19), establishing the corresponding differences. Useful inferences are also established for group psychotherapy for alcoholic patients and their needs during therapy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Socidrogalcohol</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se parte de la idea de los efectos positivos de la terapia de grupo de alcohólicos en la literatura y se plantea la evaluación de los resultados de la psicoterapia de grupo en una muestra de pacientes alcohólicos (n=34), tratados ambulatoriamente con un tiempo de abstinencia entre los tres meses y los tres años y medio, con el método de Cuestionario de Factores Curativos de Yalom (60 ítems), encontrándose los Factores Curativos de grupo 1) Altruismo, 2) Comprensión de sí mismo, 3) Revalidación de la Familia, según la teoría de Yalom, entre los de más alto puntaje, comparándose estos resultados con los reportados anteriormente en la literatura del tema del grupo de Yalom, y también con un grupo control de pacientes psiquiátricos (n=19), estableciéndose las correspondientes diferencias. Se establecen también inferencias útiles para la psicoterapia de grupo de pacientes alcohólicos y las necesidades de este en la terapia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);14(3): 381-391, jul. 2002. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores curativos en psicoterapia de grupo: su evaluación y análisis en una muestra de alcohólicos rehabilitados</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Colli alonso, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zaldívar Pérez, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-15651</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d23905</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d533</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12051</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200207</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
