<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133700</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reconstruction of large defects in trunk using the keystone perforator flap</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Keystone Perforator Island Flap (KPIF) is a local fasciocutaneous islanded flap, first published in 2003 by Behan, that does not require identification of the underlying perforator vessels. It permits the closure in a single surgical procedure of both, the defect and the donor site, usually with no need of skin grafting. Our goal is to demonstrate the usefulness of the KPIF for the coverage of large defects of the trunk. Over 120 cases have been reconstructed at our Service using the KPIF from April 2011 to May 2013. We present a series of 5 patients who underwent reconstruction of large defects of the trunk (maximum diameter ranging from 10 to 25 cm) All the surgeries were performed successfully and both, the excision defect and the donor site, were directly closed. All the patients experienced an uneventful intra and postoperative period, and all were satisfied with the eventual aesthetic appearance, without significant deformities or functional impairments. We conclude that KPIF is an optimal flap for the coverage of large defects in the trunk. It allows performing a soft tissue defect reconstruction, while the donor site is closed by direct apposition, with minimal morbidity, good cosmesis, short operative time and at a relatively low economic cost (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz-Gil, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilera-Sáez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barret-Nerín, J. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palao-Domènech, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sancho-García, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El colgajo en piedra clave (Keystone Perforator Island Flap KPIF), es un colgajo local fasciocutáneo en isla que no requiere identificación de perforantes, descrito por Behan en 2003, que permite el cierre en un único acto quirúrgico tanto del defecto como de la zona dadora sin precisar, generalmente, autoinjerto cutáneo. Nuestro objetivo es el mostrar la utilidad de este colgajo para la cobertura de defectos amplios en tronco. De los más de 120 casos realizados en nuestro Servicio con esta técnica sin tener en cuenta la localización del problema entre abril de 2011 y abril de 2013, presentamos 5 casos que, tras resección quirúrgica por diferentes etiologías, fueron los que presentaron defectos de cobertura de mayor tamaño en tronco (entre 10 y 25 cm de diámetro máximo) que fueron solventados satisfactoriamente mediante el KPIF. En todos obtuvimos un cierre directo tanto de la zona del defecto como de la zona dadora, sin complicaciones durante el acto quirúrgico ni en el postoperatorio, con resultados estéticos óptimos, sin deformidades significativas ni alteraciones funcionales. Creemos que el KPIF es un colgajo óptimo para la cobertura de defectos amplios en el tronco ya que permite cubrir el defecto y hacer un cierre primario de la zona dadora generando poca morbilidad, con un buen resultado estético, con un corto tiempo quirúrgico y con un bajo coste (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;40(4): 403-411, oct.-dic. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133700</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reconstrucción de defectos amplios en tronco mediante colgajo de perforante en piedra clave</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14292^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36507^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14294^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54867^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14286^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
