<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113876</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intraparotid first branchial arch cyst: Complex diagnostic and therapeutic process</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">First branchial arch cysts are uncommon. Therefore, together with its variable clinical and age presentation they are often misdiagnosed at first. The treatment is surgical, requiring a correct procedure to avoid future recurrences. In this paper we describe a typical case of first branchial arch cyst in which as described in other reports, we first made several misdiagnoses and therefore an inadequate treatment and lastly, with the correct diagnosis, we performed a meticulous complete excision under facial nerve monitoring (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Berenguer, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gilabert Rodríguez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín Molina, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomás Palacios, E. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Meli, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguado del Hoyo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Buitrago Weiland, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los quistes branquiales del primer arco son infrecuentes. Por este motivo, unido a su clínica y edad de aparición variables, a menudo se realizan diagnósticos primarios erróneos. El tratamiento es quirúrgico, requiriéndose un correcto procedimiento para evitar futuras recidivas. En este trabajo describimos un caso típico de quiste de primer arco branquial intraparotídeo en el que, al igual que en otros casos publicados, se realizaron al principio varios diagnósticos erróneos y por tanto un tratamiento inadecuado. Finalmente, con el diagnóstico correcto se llevó a cabo una meticulosa extirpación completa bajo monitorización del nervio facial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;26(1): 44-47, ene. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113876</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Quiste de primer arco branquial intraparotídeo: complejo proceso diagnóstico y terapéutico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1961^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1960^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22602^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201301</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
