<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132655</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Case-control study of risk factors for infectious mastitis in Spanish breastfeeding women (part I)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Title: Case-control study of risk factors for infectious mastitis in Spanish breastfeeding women (part I) Introduction: The purpose of this study was to identify potential predisposing factors associated with human infectious mastitis.  Methods: We conducted a case-control study amongbreastfeeding women, with 368 cases (women with mastitis) and 148 controls. Data were collected by a questionnaire designed to obtain retrospective information about several factors  related to medical history of mother and infant, different aspects of pregnancy, delivery and postpartum, and breastfeeding practices that could be involved in mastitis. Bivariate analyses and multivariate logistic regression model were used to examine the relationship between mastitis and these factors. Results: The variables significantly- and independently-associated with mastitis were cracked nipples (p &lt;0.0001), oral antibiotics during breastfeeding (p &lt;0.0001), breast pumps (p &lt;0.0001), topical antifungal medication during breastfeeding (p= 0.0009), mastitis in previous lactations (p= 0.0014), breast milk coming in later than 24 h postpartum (p= 0.0016), history of mastitis in the family (p= 0.0028), mother-infant separation longer than 24 h (p= 0.0027), cream on nipples (p= 0.0228) and throat infection (p= 0.0224). Conclusions: Valuable factors related to an increased risk of infectious mastitis have been identified. This knowledge will allow practitioners to provide appropriate management advice about modifiable risk factors, such as the use of pumps or inappropriate medication. They also could identify before delivery those women at an increased risk of developing mastitis, such as those having a familial history of mastitis, and thus develop strategies to prevent this condition (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mediano, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo de este estudio fue identificar los posibles factores de riesgo asociados a la mastitis infecciosa en mujeres lactantes. Métodos: Se diseñó un estudio de casos y controles, con 368 casos (mujeres lactantes con mastitis) y 148 controles (mujeres lactantes sin mastitis). La información se recogió de forma retrospectiva mediante encuestas, que recopilaron información sobre diversos aspectos del historial médico de la madre y del hijo, así como distintos factores relacionados con el embarazo, el parto, el posparto y la lactancia que pudieran estar implicados en el desarrollo de la mastitis. La asociación entre la mastitis y dichos factores se realizó mediante un análisis bivariante y un modelo de regresión logística multivariante. Resultados: Los resultados del análisis multivariante pusieron de manifiesto que los principales factores relacionados con un incremento estadísticamente significativo del riesgo de padecer mastitis fueron los siguientes: presencia de grietas en los pezones (p &lt;0,0001), uso de antibióticos orales (p &lt;0,0001), bombas de extracción (p &lt;0,0001) y antifúngicos tópicos (p= 0,0009) durante la lactancia, padecimiento de mastitis en lactancias previas (p= 0,0014), subida de la leche después de 24 horas posparto (p= 0,0016), antecedentes familiares de mastitis (p= 0,0028), separación madre-hijo tras el parto durante  más de 24 horas (p= 0,0027), aplicación de pomadas en los pezones (p= 0,0228) e infecciones de garganta (p= 0,0224).Conclusiones: En este trabajo se han identificado diversos  factores de riesgo relacionados con el desarrollo de la mastitisinfecciosa. Este conocimiento permitirá proporcionar un asesoramiento adecuado durante la lactancia sobre los factores de riesgo modificables, como el uso de bombas de extracción o de una medicación inadecuada. También se podría identificar  antes del parto a las mujeres con un riesgo elevado de desarrollar mastitis, como las que presentan antecedentes familia res de dicha enfermedad, y por tanto desarrollar estrategias para su prevención (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;73(1): 14-18, ene. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132655</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores de riesgo de la mastitis infecciosa en mujeres lactantes: estudio de casos y controles en población española (parte 1)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8584^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8584^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37660</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38861</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
