<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73610</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0316</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Suicide has existed from the beginning of the times, butat the moment it has increased worrisome the number ofpeople whom taking off chooses like solution to its lifeproblems. Due to the traumatic thing of the fact, as muchfor the relatives, if its act is consumed, like for the victim, ifits attempt is insolvent; they derive a great necessity fromwell-taken care of on the part of the nursing community, orin the first attention or the specialized attention.What he has taken to us to make this case it has been thefact that it is a very traumatic act for which lives it, and thatthe professional nurse must be prepared to act with effectivenessbefore these situations, mainly before the psychologicalnecessities, something in which frequently the nurseis not educated in covering.When investigating the existing bibliography there havebeen difficulties to find cases pertaining to the scope nurse,mainly in magazines published in paper. Bibliography ofthe suicide exists, but mainly it is of the psychologicalscope. If is something of the land nurse, it is dedicated tothe hospitable space, almost does not exist anything for thepsychiatric urgencies. It is obvious, that a protocol of performancefor the extrahospitary emergencies would have toexist, since thus would not exist the deficit in these patients(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Andújar, R. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García García, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero González, R. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El suicidio ha existido desde el principio de los tiempos,pero actualmente ha aumentado preocupantemente elnúmero de personas que lo elige como una solución a susproblemas.Si el intento es fallido, la propia víctima y sus familiaresprecisan de cuidados por parte de la comunidad enfermera,ya sea en la primera atención o en la atención especializada.Lo que nos ha llevado a analizar este caso es sensibilizaral personal enfermero para prepararse para afrontar estassituaciones críticas.Existe bibliografía del suicidio en el ámbito psicológico.Si se encuentra algo del terreno enfermero, está dedicado alespacio hospitalario, casi no existe nada para las urgenciaspsiquiátricas. Es obvio que debería existir un protocolo deactuación para las emergencias extra hospitalarias(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Puesta día urgenc. emerg. catastr;9(1): 37-44, ene.-mar. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73610</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuidados psicológicos en el intento de suicidio. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34814</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d555</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13792^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3437^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3437^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
