<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136707</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Implications of vitamin D deficiency in lithiasic patient and in general population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Context and objective: Vitamin D deficiency causes problems in mineral metabolism but also overall health. In first place a review of the topic was carried out. Then, in order to contextualize it in lithiasic patient, a study on Vitamin D deficiency and its possible relationship with impaired PTH levels is performed. Evidences acquisition: A review of topics such as metabolism, epidemiology and the relationship of vitamin D deficiency with several pathologies was performed. Besides a multivariate analysis and a correlation study between vitamin D and PTH levels was conducted in 100 lithiasic patients. Evidences synthesis: We present a review of Vitamin D metabolism, receptors and functions, as well as about its valuation methodology and the treatment of its deficiency. Lithiasic patients show a higher vitamin D deficiency than general population. Vitamin D deficiency has been significantly associated with increased PTH levels. In addition, there is enough literature showing a relationship between vitamin D deficiency not only with bone disease, but also with multiple diseases. Conclusion: vitamin D levels should be measured in all lithiasic patients, and those with vitamin D deficiency should be treated (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gavrilov, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Millán-Rodríguez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Martín, F. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villavicencio-Mavrich, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gracia-García, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Angerri-Feu, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Contexto y objetivo: El déficit de vitamina D ocasiona problemas en el metabolismo fosfocálcico, pero también de salud general. El objetivo es realizar una revisión del tema, y para contextualizarlo en el paciente litiásico realizar un estudio sobre el déficit de vitamina D y su posible relación con la alteración de los valores de PTH. Adquisición de evidencias: Revisión del metabolismo, la epidemiología y la relación del déficit de vitamina D con varias enfermedades. Análisis multivariable y estudio de correlación entre los niveles de vitamina D y PTH en 100 pacientes litiásicos. Síntesis de evidencias: Se presenta una revisión sobre el metabolismo, receptores, funciones y valoración de la vitamina D, así como del tratamiento de su déficit. Se ha encontrado un déficit de vitamina D superior en el paciente litiásico que en la población general y que se relaciona significativamente con un incremento de los valores de PTH. Además hay suficiente literatura que muestra una relación del déficit de vitamina D no solo con enfermedad ósea, sino con múltiples enfermedades. Conclusión: En todo paciente litiásico debe descartarse y tratarse un posible déficit de vitamina D (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;39(4): 245-252, mayo 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136707</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implicaciones del déficit de vitamina D en el paciente litiásico y en la población general</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10956^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2164^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52124^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15210^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10469^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
