<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106731</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of the budget impact for the Spanish National Health System of the fixed combination of amlodipine 5 or 10mg and atorvastatin 10mg</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To carry out a Budget Impact Analysis (BIA) of the inclusion of the administration, within the Spanish National Health System (SNS), of the fixed combination (FC) of amlodipine 5 or 10mg and atorvastatin 10mg for approved indications. Materials and Methods A BIA was carried out from the SNS perspective for a 3 year period (2009&#150;2011). A tree type decision model was designed (tree of patients), based on epidemiological data and scientific literature, to estimate the hypertensive population that could be treated with a FC. The total per annum BIA was calculated by attributing the retail price- VAT of the FC to the number of patients to be treated, and deducting the cost of the treatment for hypertension that was replaced and the updated average cost per patient of cardiovascular events (CVEs) prevented by the use of the FC by the SNS during the period of study. Results The patient population susceptible to treatment with the FC was 51,104 patients (1st year), with a growth rate of between 1&#150;2% over the following years, which means an annual cost (&#128;) of 15.9M (2009), 19.9M (2010) and 24.1M (2011), with a total of 60.0M. The BIA was compensated showing negative impact values for the SNS when the cost of replaced antihypertensive treatment and prevented CVEs was deducted, with savings of &#128;69.9M over 3 years. Conclusion The BIA of a FC of atorvastatin and amlodipine shows that the use of this medication for approved indications could generate net savings for the SNS of &#128;9.9M for the period 2009&#150;2011 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>De Salas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferro, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández De Bobadilla, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rejas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Realizar un análisis de impacto presupuestario (AIP) de la introducción en la prestación sanitaria del sistema nacional de salud (SNS) de la combinación fija (CF) de amlodipino 5 o 10mg y atorvastatina 10mg en la indicación aprobada. Material y métodos El AIP se ha realizado desde la perspectiva del SNS para un periodo de 3 años (2009&#150;2011). Se ha diseñado un modelo de decisión tipo árbol (árbol de pacientes) construido a partir de datos epidemiológicos y la literatura científica para estimar la población hipertensa susceptible de tratamiento con la CF. El AIP, por año y en total, se ha calculado imputando el coste a PVP-IVA de la CF al número de pacientes a tratar, del que se sustrae el coste del tratamiento antihipertensivo que se sustituye y el coste por paciente promedio actualizado de los eventos cardiovasculares prevenidos para el SNS por el uso de la CF en el periodo de referencia. Resultados La población susceptible de tratamiento con la CF es de 51.104 pacientes (1.er año), con una tasa de crecimiento entre 1&#150;2% en los sucesivos años, lo que supone un coste (&#128;) anual de 15,9M (2009), 19,9M (2010) y 24,1M (2011), totalizando 60,0M. El AIP se ve compensado mostrando valores de impacto negativo para el SNS cuando se descuentan los costes del tratamiento antihipertensivo sustituido y eventos cardiovasculares prevenidos, mostrando un ahorro de 69,9M &#128; en 3 años. Conclusión El AIP de la CF de atorvastatina y amlodipino muestra que su uso en la indicación aprobada podría generar ahorros netos para el SNS en el periodo 2009&#150;2011 de 9,9M (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;34(4): 170-180, Jul. -Ago. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106731</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis del impacto presupuestario para el Sistema Nacional de Salud de la combinación fija de amlodipino 5 o 10mg y atorvastatina 10mg</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12195^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9508^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12195^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30857^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6694^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22877</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30152</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9152</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30857^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
