<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058927</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pneumonia in the elderly population over 70 year with limited functional condition: case-control study of institutionalized patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Community acquired pneumonia (CAP) of the elderly is an increasingly important growing health problem due to its prevalence and mortality. Among the factors that are usually related with poor evolution are advanced age, poor functional status and coming from a socio-health care institution such as residential homes for the elderly. In this study, we have chosen a population over 70 years of age with limited functional capacity (Barthel Index &lt; 50) in order to know if coming from a residential home for the elderly is an isolated factor that is associated to worse prognosis of CAP.         Patients and methods. We selected 87 patients over 70 years from a prospective and multicenter study of the hospitalized CAPs during one year. We analyzed the evolution and course of the CAP based on place or origin and then conducted a case-control study of the elderly over 70 years with the Barthel under 50, including 21 elderly from residences and 21 from the own home.         Results. In elderly patients over 70 years with CAP, those coming from the residence have a confusional picture more often and come to emergency with lower values of systolic and diastolic blood pressure, lower arterial oxygen saturation, greater involvement on the x-ray, Fine Index is worse and die more often. When we limit the population to those over 70 years with Barthel under 50, we do not find differences in institutionalized patients versus the others.         Conclusion. In the elderly over 70 years with CAP, patients from assisted living residences have greater mortality. However, when functional capacity is bad (Barthel &lt; 50), place or origin (community or elderly residence) loses importance and becomes a variable that has no more influence than others in the clinical evolution and course of the CAP</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Fabrellas, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanquer, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Moragón, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguar, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serra Sanchis, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. La neumonía adquirida en la comunidad (NAC) de los ancianos supone un problema sanitario de importancia creciente por su prevalencia y mortalidad. Entre los factores que habitualmente se relacionan con una mala evolución destacan la edad avanzada, el mal estado funcional y la procedencia de una institución sociosanitaria como las residencias de ancianos. En este estudio hemos seleccionado una población mayor de 70 años con una capacidad funcional limitada (índice de Barthel &lt; 50) con el objetivo de conocer si el proceder de una residencia de ancianos es un factor aislado que se asocia a un peor pronóstico de la NAC.         Pacientes y método. Seleccionamos 87 pacientes mayores de 70 años de un estudio longitudinal prospectivo y multicéntrico de las NAC hospitalizadas durante un año. Analizamos la evolución y el curso de la NAC en función de su lugar de procedencia y realizamos después un estudio caso-control de los ancianos mayores de 70 años con índice de Barthel inferior a 50, incluyendo 21 ancianos procedentes de residencia y 21 procedentes de su domicilio particular.         Resultados. En la NAC de los pacientes mayores de 70 años, los que proceden de residencia presentan con más frecuencia cuadro confusional y llegan a Urgencias con menores cifras de presión arterial sistólica y diastólica, menor saturación arterial de oxígeno, mayor afectación radiológica y peor índice de Fine, a lo que se suma que fallecen con más frecuencia. Cuando limitamos la población a mayores de 70 años con índice de Barthel menor de 50, no encontramos diferencias en los pacientes institucionalizados frente al resto.         Conclusión. En los ancianos mayores de 70 años con NAC, aquéllos que proceden de residencias asistidas tienen mayor mortalidad, sin embargo cuando la capacidad funcional es mala (Barthel &lt; 50) el lugar de procedencia (comunidad o residencia de ancianos) pierde importancia y se convierte en una variable que no influye más que otras en la evolución y el curso clínico de la NAC</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;207(11): 548-554, dic.2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058927</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neumonía en la población mayor de 70 años y con estado funcional limitado: estudio caso-control de pacientes institucionalizados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6863</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31549^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24693</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
