<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97135</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Emergency department management of ambulance services</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine whether hospital emergency service management of ambulance services reduces wait time and complaints about delayed transport. Methods: A prospective study comparing 2 periods of time, one in which ambulance service was not managed by the hospital emergency department (October and November 2007) and another in which the department did manage the ambulance service (December 2007 and January 2008). The number of transfers, transport time, and complaints received in the 2 periods were analyzed. Ambulance trips taking patients to other hospitals were excluded from the analysis. Results: During the first period, patients from 544 emergency calls were brought in; in the second period, the service responded to 720 calls for emergency transport. In the first study period, the mean wait time was 2 hours and 4 minutes(maximum wait time, 8 hours). In the second period, the mean wait time was 1 hour and 1 minute (maximum, 4hours). Five complaints about emergency transport (9 written, 64 verbal) were lodged in the first period. The second period saw no written complaints and 19 verbal complaints. Twice the number of double transports (2 patients in the same ambulance) took place in the second period with in the first period. Conclusion: Emergency department management of ambulance services brought considerable improvement in the variables studied (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodellar, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Martín, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ollé, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guil, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedrol, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer si la gestión del transporte sanitario en ambulancia desde el servicio de urgencias hospitalario disminuye el tiempo de espera y las reclamaciones por la demora del mismo. Método: Análisis prospectivo y comparativo de dos periodos de tiempo, uno sin gestión del transporte sanitario (SGTS) en los meses de octubre y noviembre de 2007, y otro con gestión (CGTS) desde el servicio de urgencias en los meses de diciembre de2007 y enero de 2008. Se recogieron el número de transportes realizados, el tiempo de demora y las quejas recibidas en los dos periodos. Se excluyeron los transportes urgentes de pacientes en ambulancia a otros centros hospitalarios. Resultados: Durante el periodo SGTS se realizaron 544 evacuaciones y en el periodo CGTS 720. La demora media en el periodo SGTS fue de 2 horas y 4 minutos (espera máxima: 8 horas) y en el CGTS fue de 1 hora y 1 minuto (espera máxima: 4 horas). Durante el periodo SGTS se realizaron 5 quejas por escrito y 64 quejas orales en relación al transporte sanitario, mientras que en el CGTS no hubo quejas por escrito y se registraron 19 quejas orales. En este último periodo hubo el doble de transportes múltiples(2 pacientes en la misma ambulancia) que en el periodo SGTS. Conclusión: La gestión del transporte sanitario desde el servicio de urgencias en el periodo de estudio supuso una franca mejoría en las variables estudiadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);21(3): 183-185, ene.-dic. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97135</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gestión del transporte sanitario desde un servicio de urgencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54376^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28837^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28835^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200900</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
