<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102616</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Incidence, Prevalence and Mortality of Kidney Cancer in Spain: Estimates and Projections for the 1998-2022 Period</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To estimate kidney cancer incidence and prevalence in Spain, based on mortality and survival data from the period 1998-2007, and to provide projections of incidence, prevalence and mortality until the year 2022. Material and methods: All-cause and kidney-cancer mortality rates were obtained from the National Statistics Institute and survival data were obtained from the EUROCARE study. Estimations were carried out using the MIAMOD program. The Joinpoint program was used to quantify the expected annual change in the projections. Results: An increase in the incidence rate is expected in men from, this going from 11.92 (Adjusted Rate - AR=8.66) per 100,000 inhabitants/year to 15.7 (AR=9.55). Prevalence would increase from 72.84 (AR=51.62) to 94.47 (AR=59.57), and mortality would increase from 5.77 (AR=7.29) to 7.29 (AR=4.56). The incidence rate in women would increase from 5.56 (AR=3.86) to 26.77 (AR=16.4). Prevalence would increase from 24.6 (AR=17.28) to 133.69 (81.37), and for mortality, the expected increase would be from 2.46 (AR=1.54) to 11.65 (AR=6.56) cases per 100.000 inhabitants/year. Conclusion: The projections indicate that kidney cancer in Spain follows an increasing trend in incidence, mortality and prevalence. This needs to be considered in order to plan more effective prevention and treatment measures (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Souza, D. L. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernal, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Estimar la incidencia y la prevalencia del cáncer de riñón en España basándose en datos de mortalidad y supervivencia del período de 1998 a 2007 y proporcionar proyecciones de incidencia, prevalencia y mortalidad hasta el año 2022. Material y métodos: La mortalidad por todas las causas y por el cáncer de riñón se obtuvo del Instituto Nacional de Estadística y los datos de supervivencia del estudio EUROCARE. Las estimaciones han sido realizadas utilizando el programa MIAMOD. El programa Joinpoint ha sido utilizado para cuantificar el cambio anual que se espera en las proyecciones. Resultados: En hombres se espera un aumento de la tasa de incidencia de 11,92 (tasa ajustada [TA]=8,66) casos por 100.000 habitantes/año a 15,7 (TA=9,55). La prevalencia aumentaría de 72,84 (TA=51,62) a 94,47 (TA=59,57) y la mortalidad de 5,77 (TA=7,29) a 7,29 (TA=4,56). En mujeres la tasa de incidencia cambiaría de 5,56 (TA=3,86) a 26,77 (TA=16,4). La prevalencia de un 24,6 (TA=17,28) a 133,69 (TA=81,37) y para la mortalidad el aumento esperado sería de 2,46 (TA=1,54) a 11,65 (TA=6,56) casos por 100.000 habitantes/año. Conclusiones: Las proyecciones indican que el cáncer renal en España sigue una tendencia de aumento en la incidencia, mortalidad y prevalencia, que necesitan ser consideradas para planificar medidas de prevención y tratamiento más efectivas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;36(9): 521-526, oct. 2012. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102616</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incidencia, prevalencia y mortalidad del cáncer renal en España: estimaciones y proyecciones para el período 1998-2022</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7855^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28632</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2335^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
