<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123208</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacy of treatment with endo-luminal laser of the great saphenous and secondary insufficent troncal veins: long term ultrasound and statistical follow-up</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Endoluminal laser treatment is a valid alternative for elimination of dynamically insufficient great saphenous veins. Treatment is carried out under local anesthesia and/or with external cold air cooling; the procedure is not traumatic and has very little complications. We present a study on 120 limbs treated for insufficiency of the great saphenous vein with endoluminal laser on a total of 110 patients. Patients suffering from secondary varicose leg veins as a consequence of the great saphenous insufficiency were treated with polidocanol microfoam immediately after the endoluminal laser treatment. Patient control and follow-up was carried out over a mean period of 5 years. Recurrence observed was 11% over this period of time, which was analyzed to determine its origin and prompt action was taken for prevention of this recurrence. The endoluminal laser technique for the treatment of the great saphenous vein insufficiency is highly successful over medium and long term period, with results that are clearly better than those of classical stripping or similar techniques such as radiofrequency (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Osma, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trelles, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcolea, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La aplicación del láser endoluminal es una alternativa válida para la eliminación de la vena safena interna dinámicamente insuficiente. El tratamiento se realiza bajo anestesia local y/o por enfriamiento con aire frío externo, y supone un bajo trauma quirúrgico con pocas complicaciones. Presentamos el tratamiento de 120 extremidades afectadas por insuficiencia de la safena interna, realizado con técnica de láser endoluminal en un total de 110 pacientes. Los pacientes que presentaban varices tronculares secundarias a la insuficiencia de la safena interna fueron tratados con microespuma de polidocanol inmediatamente después de realizar el tratamiento endoluminal. El seguimiento de los pacientes y de los resultados alcanzados se realizó durante un período promedio de 5 años. Analizamos las recidivas observadas, 11% en ese período, para saber su causa y poder actuar de forma rápida en su prevención. La técnica de tratamiento de la insuficiencia de la safena interna mediante láser endoluminal es altamente eficaz a medio y largo plazo, con resultados claramente superiores a la fleboextracción clásica o a técnicas afines como la radiofrecuencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;40(1): 117-123, ene.-mar. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123208</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia del tratamiento de la vena safena interna y tronculares colaterales mediante láser endoluminal: seguimiento ecográfico y estadístico a largo plazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30853^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15051^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52861^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15095^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51716</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12878^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
