<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159137</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Changes in the international recommendations on neonatal stabilisation and resuscitation (2015)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The International Liaison Committee on Resuscitation (ILCOR) recommendations provide a universal guide of measures to support the transition and resuscitation of newborn after their birth. This guide is expected to be adapted by local groups or committees on resuscitation, according to their own circumstances. The objective of this review is to analyse the main changes, to discuss several of the controversies that have appeared since 2010, and contrasting with other national and international organisations, such as European Resuscitation Council (ERC), American Heart Association (AHA), or the Australian-New Zealand Committee on Resuscitation (ANZCOR). Thus, the Neonatal Resuscitation Group of the Spanish Society of Neonatology (GRN-SENeo) aims to give clear answers to many of the questions when different options are available, generating the forthcoming recommendations of our country to support the transition and/or resuscitation of a newborn after birth, safely and effectively (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Robles, Celia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iriondo Sanz, Martín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salguero García,  Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Thió Lluch, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguayo Maldonado, Josefa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zeballos Sarrato, Gonzalo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las recomendaciones internacionales del International Liaison Committee on Resuscitation (ILCOR), mediante una revisión exhaustiva de la evidencia disponible en el desarrollo de las medidas de soporte a la transición y de reanimación del recién nacido tras su nacimiento, aportan una guía universal a partir de la cual cada grupo o comité local puede adaptarla a su realidad e idiosincrasia, y elaborar sus propias guías o recomendaciones. El objetivo de esta revisión es analizar los principales cambios, abordar las controversias generadas desde 2010, contrastarlas con las de otras organizaciones nacionales e internacionales como son la European Resuscitation Council (ERC), American Heart Association (AHA) o la Australian-New Zealand Committee on Resuscitation (ANZCOR). De esta forma, el Grupo de Reanimación Neonatal de la Sociedad Española de Neonatología (GRN-SENeo) consensúa respuestas claras sobre muchas de las preguntas que ofrecen diferentes opciones de actuación, y genera las próximas recomendaciones de nuestro país para el soporte a la transición o la reanimación del recién nacido tras su nacimiento, con seguridad y eficacia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);86(1): 51.e1-51.e9, ene. 2017. tab, graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159137</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación de las recomendaciones internacionales en estabilización y reanimación neonatal 2015</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53820</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7216^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51692^s22082</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7216^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14869^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d668^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d668^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6493^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6091^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14869^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12569^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56037</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
