<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148463</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacy of the Boussignac continuous positive airway pressure device in patients with acute respiratory failure attended by an emergency medical service: a randomized clinical trial</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To assess the efficacy of the Boussignac continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) device for treating patients with acute respiratory failure transported by an emergency medical service. Methods. Retrospective, descriptive study of a series of patients treated with the Boussignac CPAP system by emergency medical service responders in Asturias between February 1, 2006, and March 19, 2012. We recorded demographic data, diagnosis, techniques and drugs used, technique failure and reasons, vital constants, (heart rate [HR], respiratory frequency [RF], systolic and diastolic blood pressures, and arterial oxygen saturation by pulse oximetry [SpO2]) at 5 times during the event (on contact without oxygen therapy in place, with conventional oxygen therapy, 5 and 15 minutes after starting CPAP, and on hospital transfer), and the duration of prehospital care. Results. A total of 203 patients with a mean (SD) age of 74.5 (10.6) years were enrolled; 133 (65.5%) were men. One hundred five (81.3%) had acute heart failure. The device failed in 28 patients (13.8%), 13 (6.4%) of whom required intubation. One (0.5%) died while still in prehospital care. All vital constants improved with CPAP. SpO2 values increased at all 5 recording times (P001); HR and RF improved significantly at 5 and 15 minutes of CPAP and on transfer (P&lt;001). Systolic and diastolic pressures were significantly lower than baseline after 15 minutes of CPAP and on transfer. Duration of care was significantly longer in patients who did not tolerate CPAP and in patients who were intubated (P&lt;.001). Conclusions. Most patients tolerated treatment with the Boussignac CPAP device and improved clinically. Few required intubation and mortality was very low (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Fernández, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrero Puente, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Argüelles Luis, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campa García, Ana María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mosteiro Díaz, María Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Regueiro, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Evaluar la efectividad del dispositivo de generación de presión positiva continua en la vía aérea de Boussignac® (CPAPB) en los pacientes atendidos con insuficiencia respiratoria aguda (IRA) por un servicio de emergencias médicas. Método. Estudio observacional descriptivo retrospectivo de una serie de pacientes en los que se aplicó CPAPB atendidos por las unidades móviles de emergencias de SAMU-Asturias entre el 1 de febrero de 2006 y el 19 de marzo de 2012. Se recogieron datos demográficos, diagnóstico, técnicas y fármacos aplicados, el fracaso de la técnica y sus causas, las constantes clínicas frecuencia cardiaca (FC), frecuencia respiratoria (FR), presión arterial sistólica (PAS) y diastólica (PAD) y saturación parcial de oxígeno (SpO2)] en los cinco momentos temporales (primer contacto con el paciente sin oxigenoterapia, con oxigenoterapia convencional, a los 5 y 15 minutos de aplicación de CPAPB y en la trasferencia hospitalaria) y la duración de la asistencia. Resultados. Se incluyeron 203 pacientes con una edad media de 74,5 (DE 10,6) años, 133 fueron hombres (65,5%). Ciento sesenta y cinco (81,3%) pacientes presentaron insuficiencia cardiaca aguda. Veintiocho (13,8%) pacientes presentaron fracaso del dispositivo, de los cuales 13 (6,4%) precisaron intubación orotraqueal (IOT) y 1 (0,5%) falleció durante la asistencia extrahospitalaria. Respecto a la evolución de constantes clínicas, se observó una mejoría significativa en todas ellas. Los valores de SpO2 aumentaron en los 5 momentos registrados (p &lt; 0,001), mientras los valores de FR y FC al inicio de asistencia tuvieron cambios significativos tras 5 y 15 minutos con CPAPB y a la transferencia (p &lt; 0,001). La PAS y PAD iniciales disminuyeron respecto a los 15 minutos con CPAPB y transferencia hospitalaria (p &lt; 0,001). La duración de la asistencia fue significativamente mayor en los pacientes que no toleraron CPAPB y los intubados (p &lt; 0,001). Conclusiones. La mayoría de los pacientes a los que se aplicó CPAPB toleró el tratamiento y presentó mejoría clínica, baja necesidad de IOT y mortalidad muy baja (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);28(1): 26-30, feb. 2016. tab, graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148463</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad del dispositivo de generación de presión positiva continua en la vía aérea (CPAP) de Boussignac® en los pacientes con insuficiencia respiratoria aguda atendidos por un servicio de emergencias médicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12552^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4711^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38345^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54205^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
