<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151098</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factor structure and psychometric properties of the Spanish version of the &#147;Dysfunctional Attitude Scale-Revised&#148;</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Dysfunctional Attitude Scale (DAS) is a 40-item measure of dysfunctional schemas, a key construct of the cognitive model of depression. Most research has relied on the total score because of the mixed results of previous exploratory factor analyses conducted on the DAS. Accordingly, a revised, 17-item version of the DAS (hereafter, the DAS-R) has been recently proposed using confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) and containing two factors: Perfectionism/Performance evaluation and Dependency. This study analyzes the factor structure and psychometric properties of the Spanish version of the DAS-R with a total of 629 participants. The DAS-R showed good internal consistency, temporal stability, and discriminant and convergent validity. CFA supported the two-factor solution found in the original scale; however, a  hierarchical factor model with two first-order factors and a general factor showed the best fit of the data. The DAS-R provides general and specific measures of dysfunctional schemas that are theoretically meaningful (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Odriozola Gonzalez, Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Eisenbeck, Nikolett</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lopez Lopez, Juan C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Budziszewska, Lidia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suarez Falcon, Juan C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barbero Rubio, Adrian</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La &#147;Escala de actitudes disfuncionales&#148; (DAS) es una medida de 40 items de los esquemas disfuncionales, un constructo clave del modelo cognitivo de la depresion. La mayor parte de la investigacion ha utilizado la puntuacion total debido a los resultados mixtos de los analisis factoriales exploratorios realizados sobre el DAS. De acuerdo a esto, una version reducida del DAS con 17 items (DAS-R) ha sido propuesta recientemente usando analisis factorial confirmatorio (AFC) y consistente en dos factores: Perfeccionismo/Evaluacion del rendimiento y Dependencia. Este estudio analiza la estructura factorial y las propiedades psicometricas de la version espanola de la DAS-R con un total de 629 participantes. La DAS-R mostro una buena consistencia interna, estabilidad temporal y validez discriminante y convergente. El AFC apoyo el modelo bifactorial encontrado en la escala original; sin embargo, un modelo factorial jerarquico con dos factores de primer orden y un factor general mostro el mejor ajuste a los datos. La DAS-R provee medidas generales y especificas de los esquemas disfuncionales que son teoricamente significativas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;23(2): 287-303, 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151098</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estructura factorial y propiedades psicométricas de la versión en español de la &#147;Escala de actitudes disfuncionales-revisada&#148;</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12055^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12055^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56077^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56077^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54263^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12055^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
