<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139769</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-7546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Grade I inversion ankle sprain causing paresia of the common peroneal nerve. Case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Inversion ankle sprains are common in population and the most usual injurie in the sports. Eventually ankle sprains can cause a common peroneal nerve neuropathy via traction mechanism over the superficial peroneal nerve. Case of a 37 year old man who suffered a minor ankle sprain during sport activity followed by common peroneal nerve paresia. This neuropathy was confirmed through ultrasonography and electrodiagnostic evaluation. Paresia solved with conservative treatment and electrostimulation. In spite of the uncommon presentation of common peroneal nerve injury after an inversion ankle sprain, it is important to know the association between both pathologies. Physician may evaluate the function of this nerve in all patients with minor severe ankle sprain in the first and later medical examination (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sobrá-Hidalgo, GÁ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Úbeda-Pérez de Heredia, Í</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los esguinces de tobillo, con mecanismo de inversión, son incidencias comunes en la población y constituyen las lesiones más frecuentes en el deporte. Eventualmente pueden ocasionar una neuropatía del nervio peroneo común, debido a un mecanismo de tracción indirecta, a través del nervio peroneo superficial. Se presenta el caso clínico de un varón de 37 años que, tras sufrir un esguince de tobillo de primer grado durante la práctica deportiva, presentó una paresia intensa del nervio peroneo común que se constató mediante estudio ecográfico y electroneuromiográfico. El cuadro se resolvió con tratamiento conservador y electroestimulación. Pese a su rareza, ha de conocerse la asociación entre el esguince de tobillo y la lesión del nervio peroneo común y debe evaluarse la función de dicho nervio en todos los pacientes con esguince de tobillo en sus diferentes grados, tanto en su exploración inicial como en el seguimiento posterior (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. andal. med. deporte;8(2): 86-91, jun. 2015. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139769</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Esguince de tobillo de primer grado como causa de paresia del nervio peroneo común. Caso clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30263^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10733^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10480^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1273^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13565^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
