<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116365</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fever, asthenia, myalgia and murmur due to cardiac myxoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cardiac tumours are rare, especially in children, and most of them are benign. Myxomas are unusual in children, being more common among adults. They are usually located in the left atrium, with 25% appearing in the right. The clinical signs and symptoms depend mainly on where the tumour is located. A feature of these tumours is that they can be accompanied by constitutional symptoms and laboratory abnormalities. Echocardiography is the study of choice, and a prompt resection is required to prevent serious complications. We present a case of a 10 year-old girl diagnosed with right atrial myxoma who presented with a fever, myalgia, asthenia and laboratory abnormalities. Diagnosis was made by echocardiography, and the early surgical resection of the tumour ran smoothly and showed a good postoperative recovery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jou Muñoz, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Felipe Villalobos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prada Martínez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caffarena Calvar, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giménez Roca, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cambra Lasaosa, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los tumores cardíacos son infrecuentes, sobre todo en la edad pediátrica, y en su mayoría son benignos. Los mixomas son excepcionales en pediatría, aunque son los más frecuentes en el adulto. La mayoría se encuentra en la aurícula izquierda, presentándose en un 25% en la derecha. Su cuadro clínico depende principalmente de la ubicación del tumor. Una característica de estos tumores es que se pueden acompañar de clínica sistémica y de alteraciones analíticas. La ecocardiografía es el estudio de elección y debe realizarse su resección temprana para evitar complicaciones graves. Se presenta el caso de una niña de 10 años diagnosticada de un mixoma auricular derecho a partir de una clínica de fiebre, mialgias, astenia y alteraciones analíticas. Se llega al diagnóstico mediante ecocardiografía; se realiza la exéresis de la tumoración sin incidencias y presenta buena evolución posquirúrgica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);79(4): 257-260, oct. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116365</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fiebre, astenia, mialgia y soplo por mixoma cardíaco</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54520^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6492^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6478^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5444^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9425^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1255^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
