<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130772</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparative analysis of dentin apical extrusion through different root canal techniques</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The purpose of this study was to conpare the solid material extruded through the apical foramen using manual techniques Step Back, Oregon and rotary systems: K3 Endo, ProTaper and FKG RaCe. Material and methods. Sixty-five single-root teeth were used with 15 for each of the groups. The extruded material of different techniques was collected in filter paper (Whatman®) submitted to oven drying and weighing in high precision digital scale. Through ANOVA test was observed the difference between the different studied groups and the Tukey parametric test was applied to the comparative analysis of the groups together. Results. The analysis of the results showed extrusion material through the foramen in all techniques. Step Back promoted the most significant being extruded  material in relation to the others that were statistically equivalent.Conclusions. No significant difference was observed between the technique of Oregon and rotary systems; among these being that K3 Endo system provided the lowest rate of extrusion (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martini Guimarães, Bruno</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernandes Eloy Da Costa, Clarice</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernardineli, Norberti</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bombarda De Andrade, Flaviana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hungaro Duarte, Marco Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burgos Ponce, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El propósito de este estudio fue comparar el material sólido extruido por el foramen apical usando las técnicas manuales Step Back,  regon y las rotatorias, Sistema K3 Endo, Sistemas Protaper y sistema F.K.G. RaCe. Material y métodos. Sesenta y cinco dientes unirradiculares fueron utilizados siendo 15 para cada uno de los grupos. El material extruído en las diferentes técnicas fue recogido en papel de filtro (Whatman®) sometidos a secado en estufa y pesado en balanza digital de alta precisión. A través del test ANOVA se observó la diferencia existente entre los diferentes grupos estudiados y el test paramétrico de Tukey fue aplicado para el análisis comparativo de los grupos entre sí. Resultados. El análisis de los resultados mostró extrusión de material por el foramen en todas las técnicas testadas.siendo que Step Back promovió la mayor cantidad de material extruido siendo significante en relación a las demás que fueron equivalentes estadísticamente. Conclusiones. No fue observada diferencia significativa entre la técnica de Oregon y las rotatorias siendo que entre estas el sistema K3 Endo proporcionó el menor índice de extrusión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);31(4): 179-184, oct.-dic. 2013. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130772</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis comparativo de la extrusión apical de dentina producida por diferentes técnicas de instrumentación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51231^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32617^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32884^s22071</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29816</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3776</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
