<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-34640</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Idiopathic recurrent facial palsy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report a 34 year old female patient with six episodes of idiopathic right facial palsy, all of wich had total recovery. Idiopathic recurrent facial palsy is a rare entity, with a few cases in the literature. Recurrent facial palsy is usually in the setting of a family history and have both autosomal dominant and recessive inheritance or in the setting of hypertension and diabetes. A review of the literature does not report a previous case with six episodes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sanidad y Ediciones (SANED, S.L.)</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos el caso de una paciente de 34 años que presenta en seis ocasiones parálisis facial periférica idiopática derecha, con recuperación total en todos los casos. La parálisis facial recidivante idiopática es una rara entidad, poco descrita en la literatura. Las parálisis recidivantes suelen estar asociadas a casos familiares relacionados con herencia autosómica tanto dominante como recesiva o a casos relacionados con hipertensión y diabetes. El hecho de que se produzca en seis ocasiones, sin asociación familiar es excepcional en la literatura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;55(7): 343-345, ago. 2004. tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Parálisis facial recidivante idiopática</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Scola Pliego, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Scola Yurrita, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Calvo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-34640</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5258^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5258^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
