<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163226</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidemiological differences between patients with chronic fatigue syndrome and fibromyalgia assessed on the medical unit of disability evaluation unit of Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe the epidemiological differences between patients with Chronic Fatigue Syndrome (CFS) and Fibromyalgia (FM). Method: A descriptive study was conducted on the patients in the Medical Unit of the National Institute of Social Security in Madrid from 2005 to 2014 with the diagnosis of CFS. A study was made on the following variables: age, sex, marital status, professional occupation and level of education. Later these results were compared with data from a previous study in patients with Fibromyalgia in the same area and the same age. Result: The total number of patients studied was 448. Regarding people with FM our area observed a median younger (48 against 53), a greater number of men (18% against 8%), a lower number of patients with primary education (10% against 33%) and a greater number of scientific - intellectual (16% against 4%) and administrative (37% against 19%) professionals. Conclusion: The CFS and FM share diagnostic criteria, an unknown etiopathogenesis, some epidemiological characteristics and absence of objective evidences. Perhaps the most distinguishing variables in both pathologies are the patient´s level of education and occupation. From a likely psychosomatic origin, this neurasthenic/somatoform syndrome, presents symptoms that are similar to the diagnostic criteria for FM in patients with lower educational background or more physical profession, while in patients with higher educational level or more intellectual work the symptoms are more in line with the criteria of CFS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Regal Ramos, Raúl Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir las diferencias epidemiológicas entre los pacientes con Síndrome de Fatiga (SFC) y Fibromialgia (FM). Metodo: Se realizó un estudio descriptivo en el que se incluyeron los pacientes valorados en la Unidad Médica de la Dirección Provincial del Instituto Nacional de la Seguridad Social de Madrid entre los años 2005 a 2014 en cuyo informe de valoración figurase el diagnóstico SFC. Se estudian las variables edad, sexo, estado civil, ocupación profesional y nivel de capacitación. Posteriormente estos resultados se compararon con los datos de un estudio previo realizado en pacientes con FM del mismo entorno y la misma franja de edad. Resultado: El total de pacientes estudiados fue de 448. Respecto a la población con FM de nuestro entorno observamos una mediana de edad menor (48 contra  53), un mayor número de hombres (18% contra 8%), un menor número de pacientes con estudios primarios (10% contra 33%) y un mayor número de profesionales científico-intelectuales (16% contra 4%) y de tipo administrativo (37% contra 19%). Conclusiones: SFC y FM comparten criterios diagnósticos, etiopatogenia no aclarada, algunas características epidemiológicas y una clínica no objetivable. Quizás las variables más diferenciadoras en ambas patologías sean el nivel de estudios y la ocupación del paciente. Partiendo de un probable origen psicosomático, este cuadro sindrómico neurasténico/somatomorfo, se manifiesta como una FM cuando el paciente tiene una menor formación académica o un trabajo más físico, y como un SFC cuando el paciente tiene una mayor formación académica o trabajos de mayor requerimiento intelectual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;62(245): 360-367, oct.-dic. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163226</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias epidemiológicas entre los pacientes con síndrome de fatiga crónica y fibromialgia evaluados en la Unidad Médica de Valoración de Incapacidades de Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24650^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
