<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142489</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Role of parenteral nutrition in oncologic patients with intestinal occlusion and peritoneal carcinomatosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and aims: the precise role of parenteral nutrition in the management of oncologic patients with intestinal occlusion is not well defined yet. We aimed to identify the effects of parenteral nutrition in these patients regarding prognosis. Material and methods: 55 patients with intestinal occlusion and peritoneal carcinomatosis were included. Parenteral nutrition aimed at 20-35 kcal/Kg/day, and 1.0 g/kg/day of amino-acids. Weight, body mass index, type of tumor, type of chemotherapy, and ECOG among others were recorded and analyzed. Results: 69.1% of the patients had gastrointestinal tumors, 18.2% gynecologic and 12.7% others. Age was 60 ± 13y, baseline ECOG 1.5 ± 0.5 and body mass index 21.6 ± 4.3. Malnutrition was present in 85%. Survival from the start of parenteral nutrition was not significant when considering baseline ECOG (log rank = 0.593, p = 0.743), previous lines of chemotherapy (log rank = 2.117, p = 0.548), baseline BMI (log rank = 2.686, p = 0.261), or type of tumor (log rank = 2.066, p = 0.356). Survival in patients who received home parenteral nutrition after hospital discharge was higher than those who stayed in-hospital (log rank = 7.090, p = 0.008). Survival in patients who started chemotherapy during or after parenteral nutrition was higher than those who did not so (log rank = 17.316, p &lt; 0.001). A total of 3.6% of patients presented catheter related infection without affecting survival (log rank = 0.061, p = 0.804). Conclusions: Parenteral nutrition in patients with advanced cancer and intestinal occlusion is safe, and in those who respond to chemotherapy, further administration of home parenteral nutrition together with chemotherapy may enhance prolonged survival (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Riveiro, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerra, Eva María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortés-Salgado, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrato, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nattero, Lía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega-Piñero, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrero, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valbuena, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Botella-Carretero, José Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grande, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateo-Lobo, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carabaña, Fátima</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: el papel preciso de la nutrición parenteral en el manejo de los pacientes oncológicos con obstrucción intestinal no está bien definido todavía. El objetivo del presente trabajo es evaluar los efectos de la nutrición parenteral en este tipo de pacientes en cuanto al pronóstico. Material y métodos: fueron incluidos 55 pacientes con obstrucción intestinal y carcinomatosis peritoneal. La nutrición parenteral proporcionó 20-35 kcal/Kg/día y 1.0 g/kg/día de aminoácidos. El peso, el IMC, el tipo de tumor, el tipo de quimioterapia recibida y el ECOG, entre otras variables, fueron recogidas y analizadas. Resultados: un 69,1% de los pacientes presentaban tumors gastrointestinales, un 18,2% ginecológicos y otros tumores el 12,7% restante. La edad media fue de 60 ± 13 años, con un ECOG basal de 1,5 ± 0,5 y un IMC de 21,6 ± 4,3. La presencia de malnutrición fue de un 85%. La supervivencia desde el inicio de la nutrición parenteral no fue significativamente distinta entre los pacientes al considerar su ECOG basal (log rank = 0,593, p = 0,743), las líneas previas de quimioterapia recibida (log rank = 2,117, p = 0,548), el IMC basal (log rank = 2,686, p = 0,261), o el tipo de tumor (log rank = 2,066, p = 0,356). La supervivencia en los pacientes en que fue posible el alta hospitalaria con nutrición parenteral fue superior (log rank = 7,090, p = 0,008). La supervivencia en los pacientes en que se inició la quimioterapia durante o tras iniciar la nutrición parenteral fue también superior (log rank = 17,316, p &lt; 0,001). Un total de 3,6% de los pacientes presentaron infección relacionada con el catéter sin afectar la supervivencia (log rank = 0,061, p = 0,804). Conclusión: la nutrición parenteral en los pacientes oncológicos con obstrucción intestinal y carcinomatosis peritoneal es segura y, en aquellos que responden a quimioterapia, el uso de la nutrición parenteral domiciliaria, junto con en tratamiento antitumoral activo, aumentan la supervivencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(3): 1222-1227, sept. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142489</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papel de la nutrición parenteral en pacientes oncológicos con oclusión intestinal y carcinomatosis peritoneal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7578^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55073^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d974^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53052^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30401^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10724^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54124^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
