<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130269</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence and determinants of obesity in children and young people in Catalonia, Spain, 2006-2012</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: To estimate the prevalence of obesity and overweight in children aged 2 to 14 years in Catalonia, its trends between 2006 and 2010-2012, and to evaluate social determinants and lifestyle associated with obesity. Material and methods: A cross-sectional study, using the data from 4,389 surveys from Catalonia Health Surveys of the years 2006 and 2010-2012, was conducted. Obesity and overweight were determined by World Health Organization criteria. Socioeconomic position, parent's education, usual diet and activity, and hours of sleep were assessed. Results: The prevalence of obesity and overweight were: 15.4 and 20.2% in 2010-2012. The prevalence of obesity was higher in boys (15.5%) compared to girls (12.8%) (P &lt; .05), and higher in children ranging from 2 to 9 years old (17.5%) than children aged 10 to 14 years (7.7%) (P &lt; .05). In 2006, the prevalence of obesity and overweight were similar to the prevalence in 2010-2012. Obesity was more frequent in children with parents with a low socioeconomic position and/or a primary or elementary parent's education. Conclusions: During the last 5 years (2006-2012), child obesity and overweight have remained stable in Catalonia, yet they are relatively high in Europe. Public health programmes against obesity must consider conducting an intersectional action taking social determinants and family life styles into account (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Puig, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina-Bustos, Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcañiz, Manuela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillén, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tresserras-Gaju, Ricard</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mompart-Penina, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brugulat-Guiteras, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Posso, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Estimar la prevalencia de obesidad y sobrepeso en la población catalana de 2 a 14 años, conocer su evolución durante los períodos 2006 y 2010-2012 y evaluar los determinantes sociales y estilos de vida relacionados con la obesidad. Material y métodos: Estudio transversal a partir de 4.389 encuestas correspondientes a las ediciones 2006 y 2010-2012 de la Encuesta de Salud de Cataluña. El sobrepeso y la obesidad se determinaron aplicando los criterios de la Organización Mundial de la Salud. Los condicionantes evaluados fueron la clase social, el nivel de estudios de los padres/madres, los hábitos alimentarios, las actividades de ocio y el sueño. Resultados: Durante el período 2010-2012, las prevalencias de obesidad y sobrepeso fueron, respectivamente, 15,4 y 20,2%. La obesidad fue superior en niños (15,5%) que en niñas (12,8%) (p &lt; 0,05), y superior en el grupo de 2 a 9 años (17,5%) que en el de 10 a 14 años (7,7%) (p &lt; 0,05). Durante el período 2006, las prevalencias de obesidad y sobrepeso fueron similares a las observadas durante 2010-2012. La clase social baja y el bajo nivel de estudios de los progenitores se relacionaron significativamente con una mayor prevalencia de obesidad. Conclusiones: La obesidad y el sobrepeso en la población infantojuvenil catalana se han mantenido estables durante 2006-2012, siendo de las más altas de Europa. Para afrontar este importante problema de salud pública, es necesario un enfoque integral e interdisciplinario que considere tanto los determinantes sociales como los estilos de vida del entorno infantil (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);143(11): 475-483, dic. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130269</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia y condicionantes de la obesidad en la población infantojuvenil de Cataluña, 2006-2012</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
