<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89830</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Derived control by compound and single stimuli in a matching-to-sample task in children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A matching-to-sample procedure was used to investigate whether 9-year-old children would demonstrate the emergence of a derived compound-sample conditional discrimination following training in four interrelated single-sample conditional discriminations and vice versa, as adults did in previous studies. In Experiment 1, three out of three children demonstrated the emergence of a compound-sample conditional discrimination following training in four single-sample conditional discriminations. In Experiment 2, two out of three children acquired a compound-sample conditional discrimination and they demonstrated the emergence of four single-sample conditional discriminations; one of them did so only after being exposed to a remediation training and testing procedure. Training variables that facilitated discrimination emergence in both directions are discussed. In general, results showed that the sophisticated learning skills that are supposedly possessed by adults are not required to demonstrate the two types of derived control under study (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-González, Luis Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Álvarez, Benigno</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se empleó un procedimiento de igualación a la muestra para investigar si niños de 9 años mostrarían la emergencia de una discriminación condicional de muestra compuesta a partir del entrenamiento de cuatro discriminaciones condicionales de muestra simple interrelacionadas, y viceversa, tal como hicieron participantes adultos en investigaciones previas. En el Experimento 1, tres de tres niños mostraron la emergencia de una discriminación condicional de muestra compuesta tras ser entrenados en cuatro discriminaciones condicionales de muestra simple. En el Experimento 2, dos de tres niños adquirieron una discriminación condicional de muestra compuesta y a continuación ambos mostraron la emergencia de cuatro discriminaciones condicionales de muestra simple; uno de ellos solo lo hizo tras haber sido expuesto a un procedimiento de entrenamiento y prueba específicamente diseñado para ello. Las características del entrenamiento que facilitaron la emergencia de discriminaciones en ambas direcciones son discutidas. En general, los resultados demostraron que las sofisticadas habilidades de aprendizaje que supuestamente poseen los adultos no son necesarias para mostrar el tipo de control de estímulos derivado que se estudió (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);23(3): 415-423, jul.-sept. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89830</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Control derivado ejercido por estímulos compuestos y simples en una tarea de igualación a la muestra en niños</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2698^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7349^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3240^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
