<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60306</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Surgical treatment for renal cancer metastases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Complete removal of metastatic lesions can contribute to improve clinical prognosis of renal cáncer. Nowadays, it is accepted that surgical extirpation of solitary metastases for patients with renal cancer is the only potential for long-term survival. Provided that the metastases could be technical and functionally resected. This review addresses the current evidence about resecable renal cancer metastases at lung, liver, bone, kidney and other organs. The criteria to consider a patient as candidate for resection of metastases are: control of primary tumor, surgical extirpation feasibility and lack of systemic disease. In patients with synchronous metastases, the surgical extirpation should be performed at the same time than nephrectomy. The clinical prognosis is worse when metastases are asynchronous. After the introduction of novel anti-angiogenic agents, surgery is also justified in patients with good responses. Although, this approach remains in the field of investigation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Cruz, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Cerdá, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La extirpación completa de lesiones metastásicas pueden contribuir a mejorar el pronóstico clínico del cáncer renal. Hoy en día, se acepta que la extirpación quirúrgica de las metástasis solitarias para los pacientes con cáncer renal es la única posibilidad de supervivencia a largo plazo. Siempre que las metástasis puedan ser técnica y funcionalmente resecadas. Esta revisión se refiere a la evidencia actual sobre metástasis resecables del cáncer renal a nivel de pulmón, hígado, hueso, riñón y otros órganos. Los criterios para considerar a un paciente como candidato a la resección de metástasis son: control de tumor primario, extirpación quirúrgica de viabilidad y la falta de enfermedad sistémica. En pacientes con metástasis sincrónicas, la extirpación quirúrgica debe realizarse al mismo tiempo que la nefrectomía. El pronóstico clínico es peor cuando las metástasis son asíncronas. Tras la introducción de las nuevos agentes anti-angiogénicos, también se justifica la cirugía en pacientes con buena respuesta. Si bien, este enfoque sigue estando en el ámbito de la investigación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;33(5): 593-602, mayo 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60306</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento quirúrgico de las metástasis del cáncer renal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7855^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d313^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2335^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9585^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8287^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1958^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200905</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
