<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136601</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnosis of urethritis in men. A 3 years review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetives. The aim of this study is to know the prevalence and tendency of microorganisms producing urethritis, in men, in the City Centre of Madrid. Methods. Cross-sectional study. The urethral samples of 1.248 men were analyzed, for 3 years. The samples were studied for: GRAM stain, when secretion exists; culture in habitual plates; detection of C. trachomatis, U. urealyticum and M. hominis, when there was suspicious, study of T. vaginalis and when suspicious injuries exist, study of virus Herpes simplex. Results. The percentage of positive samples was 22.60%. The isolated microorganisms were: U. urealyticum 7.61%, N. gonorrhoeae 6.33%, C. trachomatis 4.81%, M. hominis 0.24%, H. parainfluenzae 1.76%, H. influenzae 1.12%, Candida spp 0.48%, S. pyogenes 0.16% and Herpes virus simplex (2) 0.08%. Two or more microorganisms were isolated in 1.68%. The percentage of pos- itive samples in 2003 was 17.41% and N. gonorrhoeae the most frequent microorganism (6.22%). In 2004 was 25.57% and the most frequent U. urealyticum (10.18%). In 2005 the 24.50% of the samples were positive and U. urealyticum the most frequent (7.92%). The 79.41% of N. gonorrhoeae were susceptible to all antibiotics tested. It is not found resistance to ceftriaxone, claritromicine and amoxicilline/clavulanic acid. The 11.76% were betalactamase-producing. The 26.47% of Haemophilus spp. were betalactamase-producing and all strains were susceptible to cefotaxime. Conclusions. The isolated microorganisms most frequently were: U. urealyticum, N. gonorrhoeae and C. trachomatis. There is an increase of 7% of prevalence be- tween the years 2003 and 2005. Ceftriaxone, claritromicine and amoxicilline/clavulanic acid were susceptible to all the strains studied and cefotaxime to all Haemophilus spp (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orellana, M. Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Chacón, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, M Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer la prevalencia y tendencia de los microorganismos causantes de uretritis, en varones, de la zona centro de Madrid y la sensibilidad de las cepas de N. gonorrhoeae y Haemophilus spp. aisladas en el estudio. Métodos. Estudio observacional, descriptivo transversal. Se analiza el exudado uretral de 1.248 hombres, durante 3 años. Se realiza tinción de GRAM cuando existe secreción, siembra en medios habituales, detección de C. trachomatis, U. urealyticum y M. hominis. Cuando existe sospecha búsqueda de T. vaginalis y cuando existen lesiones sospechosas, estudio de Herpes simplex. Resultados. El porcentaje de muestras positivas fue del 22,60%. Los microorganismos aislados fueron: U. urealyticum 7,61%, N. gonorrhoeae 6,33%, C. trachomatis 4,81%, M. hominis 0,24%, H. parainfluenzae 1,76%, H. influenzae 1,12%, Candida spp. 0,48%, S. pyogenes 0,16% y virus Herpes simplex tipo 2 0,08%. Se aislaron &amp;#8805; 2 microorganismos en el 1,68%. El porcentaje de muestras positivas en el 2003 fue del 17,41% y N. gonorrhoeae el microorganismo más frecuente (6,22%). En 2004 fue del 25,57% y U. urealyticum el más frecuente (10,18%). En 2005 el 24,50% de las muestras fueron positivas y U. urealyticum el más frecuente (7,92%). El 79,41% de N. gonorrhoeae fueron sensibles a todos los antibióticos testados. No se encontró resistencias a ceftriaxona, claritromicina ni amoxicilina/ácido clavulánico. El 11,76% fueron productores de betalactamasa. El 26,47% de las cepas de Haemophilus spp. fueron productoras de betalactamasa, siendo todas las cepas sensibles a cefotaxima. Conclusiones. Los microorganismos aislados más frecuentemente en uretritis fueron: U. urealyticum, N. gonorrhoeae y C. trachomatis. Existe un incremento del 7% de prevalencia entre el año 2003 y 2005. Ceftriaxona, amoxicilina/ácido clavulánico y claritromicina fueron sensibles a todas las cepas de N. gonorrhoeae analizadas y cefotaxima a todas las cepas de Haemophilus spp. (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;22(2): 83-87, jun. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136601</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico microbiológico de uretritis en varones. Revisión de 3 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6720^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14925^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23966^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14925^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23966^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29757^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24198^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14904^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2209^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29757^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14925^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29756^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24198^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29757^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24198^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23966^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2209^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6720^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9537^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9537^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2738^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29756^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2738^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36323</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
