<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59781</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Living with dialysis: biopsychosocial factors associated with coping strategies and quality of life</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to analyze the psychosocial factors (trait-anxiety,perceived stress, comorbidity and social support) associatedwith coping strategies and quality of life in dialysis patients.Material and method: 93 patients aged &lt;70 years were studied,61 of them stable in HDH and 32 in CAPD. The CharlsonIndex, STAI-R, Perceived Stress Scale (PSS), MOS SocialSupport, coping strategies, health-related quality of life(CVRS-SF36) questionnaires were applied. Statistical analyseswere age- and sex-adjusted.Results: mean age was 53,67 years. Trait-anxiety was positivelyand significantly associated with avoidance and emotion-focused coping strategies. Perceived stress was positivelyassociated with escape/avoidance and social isolation,whilst perceived control presented a negative correlationwith these responses. Social support was positively associatedwith seeking support, positive restructuring and distraction,and negatively associated with social isolation. Thehigher the Charlson Index score, the lesser the delegation.The mental component of CVRS was positively correlatedwith perceived control and negatively with perceived stress,and was associated with greater social support.Conclusions: people with dialysis, especially those presentinganxiety, develop escape and avoidance responses. Whenthere is perceived control, these behaviours are diminished.Social support is a source of help to cope with the diseaseand can facilitate cognitive and emotional assimilation andgood psychosocial adaptation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz de Alegría Fernández de Retana, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moraza, María Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Basabe Barañano, Nekane</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Manjón, Maite</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urquiza, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Madinabeitia, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: analizar en las personas con diálisis los factores psicosociales(ansiedad-rasgo, estrés percibido, control percibido,comorbilidad y soporte social) asociados a las estrategiasde afrontamiento y de calidad de vida.Material y método: se estudiaron 93 pacientes, 61establesde HDH y 32 de DPCA, con edad &lt;70 años. Se aplicaron loscuestionarios de Índice de Charlson, STAI-R, Perceived StressScale (PSS)R, Soporte Social MOS, estrategias de afrontamiento,calidad de vida relacionada con la salud (CVRS-SF36).Los análisis estadísticos se ajustaron por edad y sexo.Resultados: la media de edad fue 53,67 años. La ansiedadrasgose asoció de forma positiva y significativa a las estrategiasde afrontamiento evitantes y centradas en las emociones.El estrés percibido se asoció positivamente conhuida/evitación y aislamiento social, mientras que la percepciónde control lo hizo negativamente. El soporte socialse asocia positivamente a la búsqueda de apoyo, la reestructuraciónpositiva y la distracción, y negativamente al aislamientosocial. La delegación es menor a mayor puntuaciónen el índice de Charlson. El componente mental de laCVRS correlacionó positivamente con la percepción de controly negativamente con la percepción de estrés y se asocióa un mayor soporte social.Conclusiones: las personas con diálisis desarrollan respuestasde huida y evitación, especialmente las personas ansiosas.Cuando se siente control estas conductas disminuyen. El soportesocial es una fuente de asistencia para afrontar la enfermedadque permitiría la asimilación cognitiva y emocionaly una buena adaptación psicosocial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;12(4): 65-71, mayo 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59781</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vivir en diálisis: factores biopsicosociales asociadosa las estrategias de afrontamiento y calidad de vida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200905</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
