<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111674</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hearing loss in drivers: a clinical case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">High noises in job centres expose many workers to suffer irreversible damages in health. Health surveillance allow to register in labour clinical sotry many information about worker and so driving habits and changes in psychophysics conditions, with obligation probable in driving flait. Because of that occupational physician has a fundamental role in prevention of injuries as consequence of traffic accident, promoting interventions to guarantee and adequate health and road protection, all these according to existing in Spain related to noise and driving (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Arcilla Conejo, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Chumbes, Gian C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Escribano, Marina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palomino Bladeón, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morrán Barboza, Sully V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La existencia de niveles de ruido elevados en los centros de trabajo expone a muchos trabajadores a padecer daños irreversibles para su salud. La vigilancia de la salud permite registrar en la historia clínica laboral mucha información acerca del trabajador y entre ellas los hábitos de conducción y los cambios en las condiciones psicofísicas, con probable compromiso en la aptitud para conducir. Es por estas razones que el médico del trabajo tiene un papel primordial en la prevención de lesiones derivadas de tráfico, promoviendo intervenciones que garanticen una adecuada protección de la salud y seguridad vial, todo ello en base a la normatividad existente en España relacionada al ruido y a la conducción (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;22(1): 34-39, mar. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111674</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hipoacusia en conductores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6470^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4862</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1340</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
