<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110739</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of particulate matter with diameter of less than 2.5 microns [PM2.5] on daily hospital admissions in 0-10-year-olds in Madrid. Spain [2003-2005]</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The last report of World Health Organization's Air Quality Guidelines establishes a value of 10µg/m3 as the annual mean particulate PM2.5 concentration. However, in large cities such as Madrid, this value is doubled and consequently an association between PM2.5 values and effects on morbidity and mortality is to be expected. Objective: To analyze and quantify the influence of PM2.5 concentrations on daily hospital admissions in 0-10-year-olds in Madrid. Material and methods: We analyzed the daily number of emergency hospital admissions for all causes (ICD-10: A00-R99) except traumatisms to the Gregorio Marañón General University Hospital in Madrid from 2003 to 2005. The age groups analyzed were 0-10 years and 0-1 year. A longitudinal ecological analysis of time series was performed using Poisson Regression Models. Seasonalities, trends, days of the week, and autocorrelation between morbidity series were controlled. Influenza epidemics, air pollutants, and noise and pollen concentrations were used as control variables. Results: The only primary pollutant found to be statistically significant in the models was PM2.5 concentration. The relative risk associated with an increase of 10µg/m3 in PM2.5 concentration was 1.03 (95%CI 1.00-1.05) for children less than 10 years old and 1.03 (95%CI 1.00-1.06) for infants less than 1 year old. The attributable risk was 2.7 and 2.8%, respectively. Conclusions: PM2.5 concentrations are an excellent indicator of the health impact of primary pollutants in Madrid. The results obtained demonstrate the need to implement measures to reduce PM2.5 concentrations in the atmosphere in large cities (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Linares, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La Organización Mundial de la Salud establece como valor límite anual para la concentración de partículas PM2,5 en el aire el valor de 10µg/m3. No obstante, en algunas grandes ciudades, como Madrid, este valor prácticamente se duplica, con el consiguiente impacto sobre la morbimortalidad. Objetivo: Analizar y cuantificar el impacto que las PM2,5 tienen sobre los ingresos hospitalarios diarios en la ciudad de Madrid en niños menores de 10 años. Material y métodos: Se analizan los ingresos diarios en el servicio de urgencias del Hospital Gregorio Marañón de Madrid, por todas las causas menos accidentes (CIE-10: A00-R99) en el período 2003-2005, tanto para menores de 10 años como de un año. La metodología de análisis es la regresión de Poisson. Se controla por contaminación atmosférica química, acústica y polínica, así como por autocorrelación, tendencias, estacionalidades, días de la semana y epidemias de gripe. Resultados: Las PM2,5 son el único contaminante primario que aparece relacionado con los ingresos hospitalarios en la modelización. El riesgo relativo asociado a un incremento de 10µg/m3 fue de 1,03 (intervalo de confianza [IC95%]: 1,00-1,05) para el grupo de menores de 10 años y de 1,03 (IC95%]: 1,00-1,06) para menores de un año. Los riesgos atribuibles fueron del 2,7 y el 2,8%, respectivamente. Conclusión: Las PM2,5 son un excelente indicador de los efectos en salud de contaminantes primarios. Se pone de manifiesto la necesidad de implementar medidas para la reducción de PM2,5 en la atmósfera de las grandes ciudades (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;23(3): 192-197, mayo-jun. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110739</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de las partículas de diámetro inferior a 2, 5 micras (PM2,5) sobre los ingresos hospitalarios en niños menores de 10 años en Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52409^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25419^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28419</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d400^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12560^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2711^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
