<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051920</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The diagnostic value of colour Doppler ultrasonography in the clinical monitoring of endovascular abdominal aortic aneurysm repair</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Clinical monitoring of the endovascular treatment of aneurysmal disease of the abdominal        aorta is based on evaluating the progression of the size of the aneurysm, the patency of the stent and the detection of        leaks. Aim. To compare colour Doppler ultrasonography (DU) with computerised axial tomography (CAT) for evaluating        the size of the aneurysm and the detection of leaks in the endovascular treatment of abdominal aortic aneurysms. Patients        and methods. A prospective study between January and December 2005; colour DU and CAT scans were conducted in        14 patients submitted to endovascular treatment at 1, 6 and 12 months. Sizes of the aneurysms were compared by means        of the t test for dependent samples and correlation studies. Sensitivity, specificity, predictive positive value and        predictive negative value and the kappa coefficient of agreement were calculated for leak detection. Results. The mean        period of clinical monitoring was 9.4 months and 49 examinations were compared. The mean diameter of the aneurysm        at three months&#146; clinical monitoring was 51.2 cm with colour DU and 52.5 cm with CAT scanning (p = non-significant).        The correlation coefficient was 0.97 (p &lt; 0.001). Patency was maintained in all the devices. In the detection of leaks, the        results of the colour DU study for sensitivity, specificity, predictive positive value and predictive negative value were 75,        61, 20 and 95%, respectively (kappa = 0.61). Conclusions. The colour DU study correlates very well with CAT in the        measurement of the size of aneurysms. In contrast, it has a very low predictive positive value for the detection of leaks</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blanco Alonso, M. Isabel del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero Puerta, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brizuela Sanz, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Fajardo, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mengíbar Fuentes, Lucas</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Norberto García, Enrique M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrera Díaz, Santiago A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez Maraña, María A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cenizo Revuelta, Noelia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Alonso, Vicente M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Río Solá, M. Lourdes del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El control clínico del tratamiento endovascular de la enfermedad aneurismática de la aorta        abdominal se basa en la valoración de la evolución del tamaño del aneurisma, la permeabilidad de la endoprótesis y la        detección de fugas. Objetivo. Comparar la ecografía Doppler (ED) color con la tomografía axial computarizada (TAC)        en la evaluación del tamaño del aneurisma y la detección de fugas en el tratamiento endovascular de aneurismas de aorta        abdominal. Pacientes y métodos. Estudio prospectivo entre enero y diciembre de 2005. En 14 pacientes sometidos a        tratamiento endovascular se realizó ED color y TAC a 1, 6 y 12 meses. Se compararon los tamaños del aneurisma        mediante la prueba t para muestras dependientes y estudio de correlación. Sensibilidad, especificidad, valor predictivo        positivo y valor predictivo negativo y el coeficiente de concordancia kappa se calcularon para la detección de fugas.        Resultados. El control clínico medio fue de 9,4 meses y se compararon 49 exploraciones. El diámetro medio del aneurisma        a los tres meses de control clínico fue de 51,2 cm con ED color y de 52,5 cm con TAC (p = no significativo). El coeficiente        de correlación ascendió a 0,97 (p &lt; 0,001). Todos los dispositivos se mantuvieron permeables. En detección de        fugas, el estudio ED color obtuvo una sensibilidad, especificidad, valor predictivo positivo y valor predictivo negativo de        75, 61, 20 y 95%, respectivamente (kappa = 0,61). Conclusiones. El estudio ED color obtiene una excelente correlación        con la TAC en la medida del tamaño de los aneurismas. En cambio, posee un valor predictivo positivo muy bajo para la        detección de fugas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;59(1): 29-37, ene.-feb. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051920</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valor diagnóstico de la ecografía Doppler color en el control clínico de la reparación endovascular de los aneurismas de aorta abdominal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30829^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32268</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30829^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30829^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
