<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151848</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-8927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Causes of absenteeism to Physical Education clases in Secondary Schools</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: This research tries to evaluate the incidence of disabling injuries during Physical Education (PE) classes in Secondary school students living in the Autonomous Region of Madrid. Methods: A total of 925 students (38 classes) attending grades 1 to 3 in Secondary Schools participated in the study. During one month, all events related to attendance or absence were analysed. Results: There was an 0.86% (8 students) injury incidence in PE classes compared to a 3.35% (31 students) injury incidence outside the PE classes. Conclusion: The results show a low injury incidence during PE classes at school. School non- attendance due to common diseases and injuries occurred during PE classes was in a relationship 4:1 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ávarez Barrio, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoa Blas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez de Haro, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valbuena Láiz, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cid Yagüe, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Castañón, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: El presente estudio valora la incidencia de las lesiones invalidantes en las clases de Educación Física en los alumnos de Educación Secundaria de la Comunidad de Madrid. Métodos: Se registran la no participación y sus causas en 38 grupos (926 alumnos) de 1º y 3º de ESO de la Comunidad de Madrid durante un mes del curso escolar. Resultados: Aparecen 8 (0,86%) alumnos lesionados en Educación Física y 31 (3,35%) alumnos lesionados fuera de las clases de Educación Física. Conclusiones: Los resultados demuestran la escasa incidencia de lesiones invalidantes producidas durante las clases de Educación Física, frente al número total de participaciones en clase. Las faltas de asistencia e inactividad debidas a enfermedades comunes y a lesiones producidas en actividades fuera de la clase de Educación Física superan a las producidas en las clases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Selección (Madr.);16(2): 84-90, 2007. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151848</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Causas de absentismo en educación física en ESO</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35173</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23556^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23556^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32027^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
