<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153258</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Low back pain in 12-years old adolescent as clinical manifestation of hematocolpos secondary to imperforate hymen</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present a case of hematocolpos due to an imperforate himen, diagnosed in a 12 years old patient who was referred to the Emergency Service because of a two weeks duration mechanic lumbago which did not improve despite the treatment with NSAIDs and muscle relaxants. The patient had severe low back pain that interfered with the night rest, with no previous history of trauma, and in the last 24 hours, also presented dif&amp;#64257;culty in urination. The study of the medical records and a physical exploration were enough to diagnose a pathology that, although rare, has a simple surgical treatment and whose diagnosis can prevent many complementary exams and unneccssary drug treatments (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Maduta, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villalobos Salguero, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Odriozola Grijalba, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perales Martínez, JI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lalaguna Mallada, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vara Callau, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Congost Marín, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos un caso de hematocolpos debido a himen imperforado, diagnosticado en paciente de 12 años que es remitida al Servicio de Urgencias por lumbalgia mecánica de 2 semanas de duración sin mejoría a pesar de tratamiento con antiin&amp;#64258;amatorios no esteroideos y relajantes musculares. La paciente presentaba dolor lumbar intenso que interfería en el descanso nocturno, sin antecedente traumático previo, y asociaba las últimas 24 horas di&amp;#64257;cultad para realizar micción. Una anamnesis y exploración física detallada son su&amp;#64257;cientes para diagnosticar una patología que, aunque poco frecuente, tiene un tratamiento quirúrgico sencillo y cuyo diagnóstico puede evitar multitud de exámenes complementarios y tratamientos farmacológicos innecesarios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;72(1): 60-62, ene.-feb. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153258</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lumbalgia en adolescente de 12 años como manifestación clínica de hematocolpos por himen imperforado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7103^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7674^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6549^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6549^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6549^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7103^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
