<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96148</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The current TNM staging system of renal cell carcinoma: are further improvements needed?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective of the study is to review the current 7th edition of the TNM classification of renal tumors and to perform a critical analysis of the recent evidence in order to identify the limitations of this new staging system. A search of the english literature was performed through the Medline and Pubmed database using the following keywords: renal cell carcinoma, staging system and TNM. Overall, 2600 references were initially scrutinized. Forty papers were selected based on their pertinence with the topic of the review, level of evidence provided and overall contribution to the field. Few changes have been made in the current version of the TNM staging system of renal tumors. pT2 tumors have been divided in 2 subgroups based on tumor size with a cut-off at 10 cm; the invasion of the renal vein was classified as pT3a; finally, the invasion of the ispsilateral adrenal gland was classified as pT4. However, other changes were suggested by the analysis of the recent literature and have not been introduced elecinthis new version. Further improvements of the TNM classification for renal tumors are needed especially with regard to locally advanced tumors and node-positive disease, in order to improve the accuracy of this important prognostic tool in renal oncology(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Terrone, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Volpe, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Billia, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del estudio es revisar la 7ª edición de la clasificación TNM actual de los tumores renales y hacer un análisis crítico de la evidencia reciente para identificar las limitaciones de este nuevo sistema de estadificación. Se realizó una búsqueda bibliográfica de la literatura inglesa en las bases de datos Medline y Pubmed utilizando las siguientes palabras clave: carcinoma de células renales, sistema de estadificación y TNM. En total, se examinaron 2600 referencias inicialmente. Se seleccionaron 40 artículos basados en su relación con el tema de la revisión, nivel de evidencia ofrecido y contribución global al campo. Se han hecho pocos cambios en la versión actual del sistema de estadificación TNM para tumores renales. Los tumores pT2 se han dividido en 2 subgrupos basándose en el tamaño del tumor con un valor de corte de 10 cm; la invasión de la vena renal se clasifica como pT3a; finalmente, la invasión de la glándula suprarrenal ipsilateral se clasifica como pT4. Sin embargo, otros cambios sugeridos tras el análisis de la literatura reciente no han sido introducidos en esta nueva versión. Para mejorar la precisión de esta importante herramienta pronóstica en oncología renal son necesarias mejoras adicionales de la clasificación TNM de los tumores renales, especialmente con respecto a los tumores localmente avanzados y la enfermedad con ganglios linfáticos positivos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;64(10): 929-937, dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96148</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estadificación TNM actual del carcinoma de células renales: ¿son necesarias más mejoras?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7855^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2335^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
