<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042243</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Emotional auditory paradigm in neuroimaging: a base for the study of psychosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Since the arrival of neuroimaging numerous studies have tried to analyze the differences between emotional and non-emotional response. The majority of these studies use visual approach (faces) and begin with data in normal subjects. The present study introduces a new paradigm for the study of emotional response based on auditory approach and designed specifically for the study of psychoses.    Method. The most frequent words heard by psychotic patients with auditory hallucinations were analyzed. They were classified according to five categories which were compared with 13 other words with the same structure but with a neutral emotional valency. This paradigm was applied to see the cerebral activation with functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) in 10 right handed healthy males.        Results. In the preliminary analysis a clear differentiation is observed depending on the type of stimulus applied (emotional or non-emotional), both in the intensity of activation (right and left temporal cortex) as in the activation of specific areas (right precentral and supramarginal gyrus) only with the emotional stimulus.        Conclusions. The present paradigm allows the observation of a differentiation in the cerebral activation to emotional auditory stimulus and could be of utility in the study of psychotic patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanjuán, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gadea, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Robles, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lull, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí-Bonmatí, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar, E. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moratal-Pérez, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Desde la llegada de la neuroimagen numerosos estudios han tratado de analizar las diferencias en la respuesta emocional frente a la no emocional. La mayoría de estos estudios utilizan la modalidad visual (caras) y parten de los datos en sujetos normales. En el presente estudio se presenta un nuevo paradigma para el estudio de la respuesta emocional basado en la modalidad auditiva y diseñado específicamente para el estudio de la psicosis.    Método. Se analizaron las palabras más frecuentes que oían los pacientes psicóticos con alucinaciones auditivas, se clasificaron según cinco categorías y a partir de las mismas se diseñó un tren de 13 palabras emocionales, comparándose con 13 palabras con la misma complejidad sintáctica y con una valencia emocional neutral. Se aplicó este paradigma para ver la activación cerebral mediante resonancia magnética funcional (RMf) en 10 varones sanos y diestros.        Resultados. En los análisis preliminares se observa una clara diferenciación según el estímulo sea emocional o no emocional, tanto en la intensidad de la activación (corteza temporal derecha e izquierda) como en la activación de áreas específicas (precentral y supramarginal derecha).        Conclusiones. El paradigma presentado permite observar una diferenciación en la activación cerebral de la respuesta a estímulos auditivos emocionales y podría ser de utilidad en pacientes psicóticos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;33(6): 383-389, nov.-dic. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042243</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Paradigma auditivo emocional en neuroimagen: una base para el estudio de la psicosis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14065^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6365^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6365^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6365^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14065^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
