<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78370</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adipocytokines: emerging mediators of the immune response and inflammation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Scientific interest in the biology of white adipose tissue (WAT) has increased since the discovery of leptin in 1994. The description of the effects of leptin, the product of the ob gene, has started to clarify the role of adipose tissue in the physiopathology of obesity related diseases and has helped in the identification of a great number of other molecules (named adipocytokines), some of them with a proinflammatory nature. In rheumatic diseases, adipocytokines derived from the WAT are among the most important factors related to obesity and promote inflammatory and/or autoimmune conditions. In this review we will present the most recent advances in adipocytokine research, with special attention to the role of leptin, adiponectin, resistin and visfatin and inflammatory, autoimmune and rheumatic diseases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez, Rodolfo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conde, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gualillo, Oreste</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lago, Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El interés científico en la biología del tejido adiposo blanco (TAB) se ha incrementado desde el descubrimiento de la leptina en 1994. La descripción de los efectos de la leptina (el producto del gen ob) ha empezado a aclarar el papel del tejido adiposo en la fisiopatología de las enfermedades relacionadas con la obesidad y ha ayudado a la identificación de otras muchas moléculas (denominadas adipocinas), algunas de ellas de naturaleza proinflamatoria. En las enfermedades reumáticas, las adipocinas derivadas del TAB están entre los factores más importantes relacionados con la obesidad que promueven las enfermedades inflamatorias o autoinmunes. En esta revisión se recopilarán los avances más recientes en la investigación sobre las adipocinas, y se prestará particular atención al papel de la leptina, la adiponectina, la resistina y la visfatina en enfermedades inflamatorias, autoinmunes y reumáticas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);5(extr.1): 6-12, abr. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78370</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las adipocinas: mediadores emergentes de la respuesta inmune y de la inflamación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52657^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50571^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52725^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34404^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32175^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52011^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50570^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7293^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
