<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160341</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9168</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Paraoxonase 1 (Q192R) gene polymorphism, coronary heart disease and the risk of a new acute coronary event</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Paraoxonase 1 (PON1) plays a major role in the oxidation of low density lipoprotein and in the prevention of coronary atherogenesis. In this context, coding region polymorphisms of PON1 gene, responsible for the enzyme activity, has become of interest as a marker for atherogenesis. Methods: A study and follow-up was conducted on 529 patients with an acute coronary event in order to assess the association between the PON1 Q192R (rs662;A/G) polymorphism, the type of acute coronary syndrome, cardiovascular risk factors (arterial hypertension, diabetes mellitus, dyslipidaemia, and smoking), the extent and severity of coronary atherosclerosis, and the medium-term clinical follow-up. Results: The QQ genotype was found in 245 (46.3%) patients, with 218 (41.2%) patients showing the QR genotype, and 66 (14.5%) patients had the RR genotype. No significant differences were found between the QQ and QR/RR genotypes as regards the clinical characteristics, the analytical data, and the angiographic variables. Similarly, Kaplan&#150;Meier survival analysis showed no significant differences in presenting with a new acute coronary event (p=0.598), cardiac mortality (p=0.701), stent thrombosis (p=0.508), or stent re-stenosis (p=0.598) between QQ and QR/RR genotypes during the follow-up period (3.3±2.2 years). Conclusions: In patients with an acute coronary syndrome, the PON1 Q192R genotypes did not influence the risk of suffering a new acute coronary event during the medium-term follow-up (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Medina Gil, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garay Sánchez, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-González, Fayna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tugores, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Quintana, Efrén</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La paraoxonasa 1 (PON1) juega un papel importante en la oxidación de las lipoproteínas de baja densidad y en la prevención de la aterosclerosis coronaria. En este contexto, el gen de la PON1, responsable de la actividad de la enzima, se ha convertido en un marcador de interés del proceso aterogénico. Métodos: Se estudiaron y siguieron a 529 pacientes con síndrome coronario agudo para evaluar la asociación entre el polimorfismo Q192R (rs662; A/G) del PON1 y el tipo de evento coronario, los factores de riesgo cardiovascular (hipertensión arterial, diabetes mellitus, dislipidemia y tabaquismo), la extensión y gravedad de la aterosclerosis coronaria y la incidencia de eventos cardiovasculares a medio plazo. Resultados: Un total de 245 pacientes (46,3%) presentaron el genotipo QQ, 218 (41,2%) el genotipo QR y 66 (14,5%) el genotipo RR. No se encontraron diferencias significativas entre el genotipo QQ y los genotipos QR/RR en relación con las variables clínicas, analíticas y angiográficas estudiadas. Por su parte, el análisis de Kaplan-Meier de supervivencia no mostró diferencias significativas en relación con la reincidencia de nuevos eventos coronarios (p=0,598), la mortalidad cardíaca (p=0,701), la trombosis del stent (p=0,508) o la reestenosis del stent (p=0,598) entre los genotipos QQ vs. QR/RR durante el tiempo de seguimiento (3,3±2,2 años). Conclusiones: El genotipo PON1 Q192R no influyó en el riesgo de sufrir un reevento coronario agudo a medio plazo entre los pacientes que presentaron un síndrome coronario agudo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. arterioscler. (Ed. impr.);29(1): 1-6, ene.-feb. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160341</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Polimorfismo del gen de la paroxonasa 1 (Q192R), enfermedad coronaria y riesgo de un nuevo evento coronario agudo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d38151^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11547</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8249^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19139^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
