<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95240</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pregnancy in a patient aged more than fifty years. Complete hydatidiform mole</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Gestational trophoblastic disease is more frequent in extreme ages of life and should be included in the differential diagnosis of menstrual disorders in the perimenopause. Although definitive diagnosis is pathological, transvaginal sonography and determination of human chorionic gonadotropin levels are useful. We present a case of complete hydatidiform mole, which was resolved with aspiration curettage (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carriles-Sastre,   R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-García,  C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Domínguez,  A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luengo-Tabernero,  Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zornoza-García,  V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad trofoblástica gestacional es más frecuente en las edades extremas de la vida. No ha de olvidarse como diagnóstico diferencial de las irregularidades menstruales en la perimenopausia. Aunque su confirmación es anatomopatológica, son de utilidad la ecografía transvaginal y la cuantificación de gonadotropina coriónica humana. En el caso que presentamos de mola hidatiforme completa, la enfermedad queda resuelta con un legrado aspirativo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);37(6): 258-260, nov.-dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95240</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gestación en paciente mayor de cincuenta años. Mola hidatiforme completa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11992^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24209^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29441</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
