<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120713</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ureteral triplication</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Ureteral triplication is considered a rare anomaly and its association with ectopic ureterocele, is unusual. Clinical case. We report a male with a history of recurrent urinary tract infections, who showed left vesicoureteral re&amp;#64258;ux associated with apparent ureteral duplication in multiple test performed, and only during the vesicostomy was discovered a third ureter ending in a ectopic ureterocele corresponding with the upper pole ectopic kidney. Conclusions. Being a very unusual and complex pathology, and despite all the tests made, it is very dif&amp;#64257;cult to make an accurate presurgical diagnosis, therefore the diagnosis sometimes is only performed during the surgical treatment, which must be individualized according to the unctional stage of each renal portion and the termination of each ureter (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blesa Sánchez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Hurtado, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cavaco Fernandes, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanjuán Rodríguez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La triplicidad ureteral se considera una anomalía muy poco frecuente y su asociación a ureterocele ectópico, no es habitual. Caso clínico. Presentamos a un varón con historia de infecciones urnarias de repetición, a quien en las múltiples pruebas realizas se observa un re&amp;#64258;ujo vesicoureteral izquierdo asociado a una aparente duplicidad ureteral, y sólo durante la vesicostomía se descubrió un tercer uréter que terminaba en un ureterocele ectópico correspondiente al riñón del pielon superior. Conclusiones. Al ser una patología tan poco frecuente y compleja y a pesar de todas las pruebas realizadas, es muy difícil efectuar un diagnóstico exacto previo a la intervención, por lo que el diagnóstico, a veces, sólo se realiza durante el tratamiento quirúrgico, el cual debe ser individualizado, según el grado de función de cada porción renal y la terminación de cada uréter (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;27(1): 49-51, ene.-mar. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120713</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Triplicidad ureteral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15123^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14917^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14964^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14912^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
