<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154324</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Giant primary liver abscess. Current treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Giant primary liver abscess is a rare entity. The diagnosis is often delayed because usually not suspected. Fever and abdominal pain are the most common clinical manifestations. Leukocytosis, high CRP and anemia are the most common laboratory abnormalities. Abdominal CT is the imaging test of choice for diagnosis. Percutaneous drainage and specific antibiotic treatment is sufficient and safe in most patients. Surgical drainage is indicated in cases of failure of conservative treatment. We present the case in a 72-year-old male patient, who required surgical treatment after failure of percutaneous drainage. We discuss aspects related to the etiology, cynical picture, diagnosis and current therapeutic approach (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carvajal Balaguera, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín García-Almenta, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cerquella Hernández, CM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camuñas Segovia, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El absceso hepático primario gigante, es una entidad poco frecuente. El diagnóstico suele retrasarse por que habitualmente no se sospecha. La fiebre y dolor abdominal son las manifestaciones clínicas más frecuentes. Leucocitosis con desviación izquierda, anemia y PCR alta son las alteraciones analíticas más frecuentes. El TAC de abdomen constituye la prueba de imagen de elección para el diagnóstico. El drenaje percutáneo y el tratamiento antibiótico específico, es suficiente y seguro en la mayoría de los pacientes. El drenaje quirúrgico está indicado ante el fracaso del tratamiento conservador. Presentamos el caso en un paciente varón de 72 años de edad, que precisó tratamiento quirúrgico tras el fallo del drenaje percutáneo. Discutimos los aspectos relacionados con la etiología, cuadro clínico, diagnóstico y abordaje terapéutico actual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;19(2): 73-77, 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154324</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Absceso hepático primario gigante. Tratamiento actual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27990^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8273^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
