<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133202</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neoplasm in kidney graft. Analysis of the cause of the tumour and treatment options</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Kidney transplant is the treatment of choice for chronic kidney disease. Cardiovascular disease, infections, and postransplant de novo neoplasms are the main causes of death in transplant patients. The most frequent kind of post kidney transplant neoplasms are lymphoproliferative processes and cutaneous neoplasms. Another type of neoplasm, that of kidney tumours, also represents approximately 3% of all neoplasms in transplant patients. A review of the kidney transplants from our unit performed between July 1985 and October 2012 which presented a mass in the kidney graft was carried out, confirming the diagnosis by taking a biopsy of the mass. In all the cases, the underlying pathology, kidney function and immunosuppressive treatment were analysed. This article aims to give importance to monitoring and management of the appearance of possible tumour masses in kidney transplants (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tapia-García, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lauzurica-Valdemoros, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Areal-Calama, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Satué, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibarz-Servio, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valverde-Vilamala, Ivanna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereira-Barrios, Juan C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañas-Solé, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El trasplante renal es el tratamiento de elección de la enfermedad renal crónica. La enfermedad cardiovascular, las infecciones, así como las neoplasiasde novo postrasplante renal son las principales causas de mortalidad de los pacientes trasplantados. Las neoplasias más frecuentes en el postrasplante renal son los procesos linfoproliferativos y las neoplasias cutáneas. Otro tipo de neoplasias, como son los tumores renales, también representan aproximadamente el 3 % de todas las neoplasias de los trasplantados. Se ha realizado una revisión de los trasplantados renales de nuestra unidad entre julio de 1985 y octubre de 2012 que han presentado una masa a nivel del injerto renal, confirmando el diagnóstico por biopsia de la masa. Se ha analizado en todos los casos la patología de base, la función renal y el tratamiento inmunosupresor. Este artículo quiere dar importancia a la monitorización de la aparición de posibles masas tumorales en el injerto renal y su manejo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;35(1): 87-91, ene.-feb. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133202</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neoplasia en el injerto renal. Análisis del origen tumoral y opciones terapéuticas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53221^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29431</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7855^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7344^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
