<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88570</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of abdominal aortic aneurysms in 65 year-old men (PAV65 Study)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To analyse the prevalence of abdominal aortic aneurysms (AAA), risk factors andpossible changes in serological parameters in 65-year-old men, born in 1943, registered in theInner Region of Bizkaia, and to compare this prevalence with that obtained in other previousepidemiological studies performed in 65 to 74-year-old men.Design. Cross-sectional epidemiological study.Material and methods. In October-December 2007 the 1,413 men born in 1943 were invited toparticipate in this study. A physical examination, body mass index (BMI), abdominal ultrasoundand general and specifi c blood tests were performed.Results. Nineteen (1.3 %) of the 1,413 registered men were deceased, 41 openly refused toparticipate in the study and we could not fi nd the current address of 250 men (17.7 %), so thefi nal number of available candidates was 1,103, of whom 781 (70.8 %) fi nally attended theirappointments. We diagnosed 37 AAA (4.7 %). Men with brothers diagnosed with an AAA, smokers,hypertensive and/or suffering from peripheral arterial disease had a greater probability ofdeveloping an AAA, in contrast with diabetic patients, who showed lower risk. The AAA patientshad higher levels of metalloproteinase-9 (MMP-9) and C-reactive protein (CRP) than the controls(mean ± standard deviation): 5.9 ± 3.9 ng/dl and 4.1 ± 3.4 mg/l versus 4.2 ± 3.4 ng/dl and2.6 ± 2.5 mg/l; p = 0.0042 and 0.002, respectively.Conclusion. The prevalence of AAA in 65-year-old men in our area is similar to that described in65 to 74-year-old men in other previous international studies. Peripheral MMP-9 and CRP levelsare increased in AAA patients compared to controls(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alvarez-Elizegui, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuente, N. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarobe, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viviens, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estallo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barba, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega de Céniga, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer la prevalencia de los aneurismas de aorta abdominal infrarrenal (AAA), factoresde riesgo y posibles alteraciones analíticas en los varones de 65 años, nacidos en 1943,censados en la Comarca Interior de Bizkaia, y compararla con la obtenida en estudiosepidemiológicos realizados en varones con edades entre 65-74 años.Diseño. Transversal.Material y métodos. Entre octubre y diciembre de 2007 invitamos a participar en este estudio alos 1.413 varones nacidos en 1943. Se realizó exploración física, índice de masa corporal (IMC) yeco-doppler de aorta abdominal. Analítica general y específi ca.Resultados. De los 1.413 hombres censados, 19 habían fallecido (1,3 %), 41 no quisieron participaren el estudio, en 250 casos (17,7 %) se desconocía la dirección actual, por lo que el númeroreal fue de 1.103, participando 781 (70,8 %). Se diagnosticaron 37 AAA (4,7 %). Los varones conhermanos portadores de AAA, los fumadores, hipertensos y/o con una arteriopatía periféricatienen una probabilidad mayor de tener un AAA, mientras que los diabéticos están protegidoscontra esta patología. Los portadores de AAA presentaron niveles más elevados de metaloproteinasas(MMP-9) y proteína C reactiva (PCR) que los individuos normales: 5,9 ± 3,9 ng/dl y4,1 ± 3,4 mg/l frente a 4,2 ± 3,4 ng/dl y 2,6 ± 2,5 mg/l, con una p de 0,0042 y 0,002, respectivamente.Conclusión. La prevalencia de los AAA en varones de 65 años es similar a la encontrada en losvarones entre 65 y 74 años. Los niveles de MMP-9 y PCR son signifi cativamente mayores en pacientescon AAA en relación al grupo control(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;63(1): 18-25, ene.-feb. 2011. graf, ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88570</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de aneurismas de aorta abdominal en varones de 65 años de la Comarca Interior de Bizkaia (Estudio PAV65)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34441^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30829^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28162^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
