<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-168102</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevention of suicidal behaviour in teenagers, identification of risk factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to identify the most frequent risk factors for suicidal behaviour among teenagers, due to the high incidence presented by this population group.  Method: a narrative review was conducted, based on the bibliographic review of literature in Medline, Pudmed, Scielo, Google Scholar and Dialnet. The DeCS descriptors used for the search were: Suicidio, Suicide, Adolescentes, Teenagers, Factores de riesgo, Risk factors. The languages used for this search were English and Spanish. Time limits were used, searching for documents within the past 12 years, and both in the national and international setting. The inclusion criteria were: studies relating to suicidal behaviour in adolescents from 10 to 19 years of age, with quantitative methodology, and published during the past 12 years.  Results: of the 43 articles initially identified, there was a selection of 7 that met the inclusion criteria. The most significant risk factors were identified with the relationship of the adolescent with his/her family, low performance at school, and the relationships established by the adolescent both with their most immediate setting (personal relationships) as with themselves (depression, sadness, hopelessness, etc.).  Conclusions: it is considered very necessary to identify those risk factors related with suicidal behaviour in teenagers, in order to prevent suicides within this age range, given that the bibliography consulted indicates there is a high prevalence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Victorio Molina, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomás Cánovas, Lidia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: identificar los factores de riesgo de las conductas suicidas más habituales en los adolescentes, debido a la alta incidencia que presenta este grupo poblacional. Método: se realizó una revisión narrativa a partir de la búsqueda bibliográfica de la literatura en Medline, Pudmed, Scielo, Google Scholar y Dialnet. Los descriptores DeCS utilizados para la búsqueda fueron 'suicidio', 'suicide', 'adolescentes', 'teenagers', 'factores de riesgo', 'risk factors', incluyendo el operador booleano and para unir las distintas palabras clave. Los idiomas que se manejaron para la misma fueron inglés y castellano. Se utilizaron limitadores de tiempo buscando la documentación dentro de los últimos 12 años y tanto del ámbito nacional como internacional. Los criterios de inclusión fueron estudios relacionados con conductas suicidas en adolescentes de edades entre los 10 y los 19 años, con metodología cuantitativa y publicados en los últimos 12 años. Resultados: de los 43 artículos identificados inicialmente se seleccionaron siete que cumplían los criterios de inclusión. Los factores de riesgo más significativos se identifican con la relación del adolescente con la familia, el bajo rendimiento escolar y las relaciones que establece el adolescente tanto con su entorno más inmediato (relaciones interpersonales) como consigo mismo (depresión, tristeza, desesperanza, etc.). Conclusiones: se aprecia como muy necesaria la identificación de factores de riesgo con relación a las conductas suicidas en adolescentes, a fin de prevenir los suicidios dentro de esta franja de edad, dado que la bibliográfica consultada indica que existe una alta prevalencia a este respecto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;20(8): 55-60, oct. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-168102</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevención de conductas suicidas en adolescentes, identificación de factores de riesgo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22845</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54296</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13792^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37586</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
