<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90415</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Paradigm Real Time 722® results in patient series with diabetes mellitus type 1</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives. Paradigm Real Time 722® (PRT-722) is a dual electronic device, which allows both continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion and real-time continuous glucose monitoring (RT-CGM). There is no information available from controlled trials on their benefits during normal clinical practice. Our objective was to determine blood glucose and quality of life improvement at three and twelve months in PRT-722 treated type 1 diabetes mellitus (T1DM) patients. Patients and methods. One-year follow-up was conducted on 24 patients who started PRT-722. Insulin treatment, diabetes quality of life (DQOL), severe hypoglycaemic events, capillary glucose, HbA1C and continuous glucose information, were all recorded. Results. T1DM medium duration, 15.5±9.5 years. Severe hypoglycaemic events during 1 year before PRT-722, 1.54±4. DQOL pre-PRT 722 score, 92.79±18.42. CGM system frequency use: 3-months, 20±10.7%; 12-months, 20.2±13.1%. We detected a significant reduction in HbA1C levels at 3 and 12 months (0.6±0.2% and 0.49±0.19%, respectively), as well as in severe hypoglycaemic events during follow-up, 1.08±0.53 (p &lt; .05). We also observed a significant improvement in DQOL score at 3 months (83.8±21.6, p &lt; .05) and 12 months (79.41±13.81, p &lt; .05). Conclusions. RT-CGM use close to 20 per cent with PRT-722 dual system was associated with a reduction of HbA1C levels, less severe hypoglycaemias and improvement of DQOL in T1DM patients at 3 and 12 months(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Silva, Julia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguirre, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Manzanares, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Fernández, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez García, Inés R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benito-López, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Paradigm Real Time 722® (PRT-722) permite la infusión subcutánea continua de insulina (ISCI) y la monitorización continua de glucosa intersticial en tiempo real (MCG-TR). Aparte de ensayos clínicos, no hay información sobre sus beneficios en la clínica habitual. Objetivos. Analizar los cambios en el control glucémico y en la calidad de vida relacionada con la diabetes (CVRD) en pacientes con diabetes mellitus tipo 1 (DM1) tratados con sistema PRT-722 a 3 y 12 meses. Material y métodos. Seguimiento durante 12 meses de 24 pacientes que iniciaron tratamiento con el sistema PRT-722. Variables: tratamiento insulínico, CVRD (cuestionario EsQOL), hipoglucemias graves (encuesta retrospectiva), MCG y hemoglobina glucosilada (HbA1C). Resultados. Duración media de DM1, 15,5 ± 9,5 años. Las hipoglucemias graves durante el año anterior fue de 1,54 ± 4. La puntuación EsQOL basal, 92,79 ± 18,42. La frecuencia de uso de MCG-TR fue 3 meses, 20 ± 10,7%; 12 meses, 20,2 ± 13,1%. Detectamos un descenso de HbA1C de 0,6 ± 0,2% y 0,49 ± 0,19% a los 3 y los 12 meses, respectivamente, y menos hipoglucemias graves (1,08 ± 0,53; p &lt; 0,05) durante el seguimiento. Además observamos una mejoría en la puntuación EsQOL a 3 (83,8 ± 21,6; p &lt; 0,05) y 12 meses (79,41 ± 13,81; p &lt; 0,05). Conclusiones. La utilización de PRT-722, con una frecuencia de uso de MCG-TR del 20%, se asoció con un descenso de HbA1C, menos hipoglucemias graves y una mejoría de la CVRD(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;27(2): 42-46, mar.-abr. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90415</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados del sistema Paradigm Real Time 722® en una serie de pacientes con diabetes mellitus tipo I</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22523^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7181^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7124^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22190^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
