<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119956</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Opinion of the community pharmacists of the province of Valencia about consultation and resolution of pharmacotherapeutics consultations of drug information</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims: To characterize and to describe the pharmacotherapeutic consultations drug of information (PCDI) in order to increase awareness of this activity in the community pharmacy. Methods: Observational, descriptive, cross-sectional study by means of an administered anonymous questionnaire to volunteer pharmacists of community pharmacies in the province of Valencia. Results: 222 community pharmacists (18.4%) responded to the questionnaire. The 3.5% of users who visit the pharmacy, do it just for the PCDI. The estimated daily frequency is between 4-9 consultations. Most PCDI are attended and resolved by the pharmacist in the same place of the pharmacy, without setting a specific time and without collectability. The average duration is 4 minutes and the most frequent reason for consultation is instructions for use of drugs. 74.5% of the pharmacists believes that they solve correctly the majority of consultations, but they only registers the 6.4% of them. Practically they all agree in the importance of the value that has this activity for the sanitary system and for the health of the patient, as well as that this activity is provided in the community pharmacy as a differentiated service. Practically they all agree that resolving the consultations get ready, detect and/or solve drug related problems and negative results associated with the medication. Conclusions: The study confirms the common realization of this activity in the Valencian community pharmacy and provides qualitative and quantitative relevant unpublished data to your knowledge, allowing to compare them with those obtained in field observational studies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salar Ibáñez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Royo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baixauli Fernández, V. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Caracterizar y describir la consulta farmacoterapéutica de información de medicamentos (CFTIM) con el fi n de aumentar el conocimiento sobre esta actividad en la farmacia comunitaria. Métodos: Estudio observacional, descriptivo, transversal mediante un cuestionario ad hoc anónimo autocumplimentado por los farmacéuticos voluntarios de las farmacias comunitarias de la provincia de Valencia. Resultados: Un total de 222 farmacéuticos comunitarios (18,4%) respondieron al cuestionario. El 3,5% de los usuarios que acuden a la farmacia lo hace sólo para realizar las CFTIM, cuya frecuencia diaria se estima entre 4 y 9. La mayoría de las CFTIM se atienden y resuelven por el farmacéutico, en el mismo lugar de la farmacia, sin establecer un horario determinado y sin cobrarlas. Su duración media es de 4 minutos, y el motivo de consulta más frecuente son las instrucciones de uso de los medicamentos. El 74,5% de los farmacéuticos cree que resuelve correctamente la mayoría de CFTIM, aunque sólo el 6,4% las registra. Casi todos están de acuerdo en la importancia del valor que tiene esta actividad para el sistema sanitario y la salud del paciente, así como en que se debe prestar como un servicio diferenciado en la farmacia comunitaria. Prácticamente todos están de acuerdo que resolviéndolas se previenen, detectan y/o resuelven problemas relacionados con los medicamentos y resultados negativos asociados a la medicación. Conclusiones: El estudio confirma la realización habitual de esta actividad en la farmacia comunitaria valenciana y aporta datos inéditos, cualitativos y cuantitativos, relevantes para su conocimiento, que permite contrastarlos con los obtenidos en estudios observacionales de campo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;16(1): 2-10, ene.-feb. 2014. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119956</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Opinión de los farmacéuticos comunitarios de la provincia de Valencia sobre la atención y resolución de consultas farmacoterapéuticas de información de medicamentos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11016^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4408^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50249</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52955^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
