<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046862</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cystic ectasia of the rete testis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: The cystic ectasia of the rete testis is a benign entity with a typical ultrasoundappearance as a collection of small hypoechoic structures in the confluence of the mediastinum testis. The clinical importance of these entity remains on doing an adequate differential diagnosis with testicular neoplasias with a cystic component.METHODS: We retrospectively reviewed the database of the Ultrasound Unit in the Department of Urology looking for patients with a diagnosis of cystic ectasia of the rete testis over a six-year period.RESULTS: Three cases of cystic ectasia of the rete testis were diagnosed over the six-year period, in all theindication for ultrasound was testicular pain. Mean patient age was 62 years. No patient developed testicular tumor on follow-up.CONCLUSIONS: The knowledge of the ultrasoundcharacteristics found in the cystic ectasia of the rete testis helps to make a proper diagnosis of this benign entity without the need of indication of testicular biopsy</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández González, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luján Galán, Marcos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espinales Castro, Gino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual Mateo, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez García, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berenguer Sánchez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: La ectasia quística de la rete testis es una entidad benigna y típicamente en la ecografíaaparece como una colección de pequeñas estructurasanecoicas en la confluencia del mediastinum testis. La importancia clínica de esta entidad radica en hacer un adecuado diagnóstico diferencial con la neoplasiatesticular con componente quísticoMÉTODO: De forma retrospectiva, se revisa en la base de datos de la Unidad de Ecografía del Servicio de Urología el número de pacientes diagnosticados de ectasiaquística de la rete testis durante un periodo de 6 años.RESULTADOS: Durante los 6 años revisados se han diagnosticado 3 casos de ectasia quística de la rete testis y la ecografía fue realizada por dolor testicular. La edad media de los pacientes fue de 62 años. Ningún paciente ha desarrollado durante el tiempo de seguimientoun tumor testicularCONCLUSIONES: El conocimiento de las característicasecográficas encontradas en la ectasia quística de la rete testis permite hacer un adecuado diagnóstico de esta entidad benigna sin necesidad de recurrir a la biopsia testicular</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;59(1): 49-54, ene.-feb. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046862</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ectasia quística de la rete testis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12570^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14112^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14112^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12570^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4151</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
