<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160712</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality in the anesthesia department of San Cecilio Hospital from the professionals&#146; perspective</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To evaluate the quality of the services provided by the anaesthesia department of the San Cecilio Clinical University Hospital, from the health professionals&#146; point of view. Material and methods. Location: Andalusia. Participants: 134 health professionals in contact with the hospital anaesthesia department. Tool: self-administered questionnaire, measuring: accessibility, personal treatment, comfort, scientific and technical quality (scale 1 to 5), overall satisfaction (scale 0 to 10), and suggestions for improvement. A descriptive statistical and correlation analysis were performed, including mean differences (by sex, frequency of contact with the anaesthesia department, and unit), as well as a regression model. Results. The quality of personal treatment received a mean of 4.2 points (SD 0.651), the scientific and technical quality 4.00 points (SD 0.532), accessibility 3.3 (SD 0.795), professional comfort 3.30 (SD 0.988), and patient comfort 2.62 points (SD 1.051). Overall satisfaction obtained a mean of 7.1 points (0 to 10 scale). Women and professionals working in units with less than 10 people had a better general evaluation of the anaesthesia department. The worse perspective was that of staff with daily contact with the anaesthesia department. Among the suggestions for improvement there were: Reducing waiting lists, creating special rooms to give information to families, improving working conditions, training and work satisfaction for staff, and achieving better communication and collaboration between health professionals. Conclusions. The internal evaluation shows the need for training strategies and organisational interventions in the anaesthesia department, in order to achieve a better quality and satisfaction for both professionals and patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>March-Cerdá, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Danet-Danet, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palacios-Córdoba, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Evaluar la calidad de los servicios prestados por el Bloque Quirúrgico (BQ) del Hospital Clínico Universitario San Cecilio (HUSC), desde el punto de vista del personal sanitario del hospital. Material y métodos. Emplazamiento: Andalucía. Participantes: 134 profesionales con contacto con el BQ del HUSC. Instrumento: cuestionario de elaboración propia, con las siguientes dimensiones: accesibilidad, trato personal, confortabilidad, calidad científico-técnica (escala 1-5 puntos), satisfacción global (escala 0-10) y propuestas de mejora. El análisis incluyó estudio descriptivo, correlación, diferencia de medias (según sexo, frecuencia de la relación y unidad de gestión clínica [UGC]) y modelo de regresión lineal. Resultados. La calidad del trato tuvo una media de 4,2 puntos (DT 0,5), la calidad científico-técnica de 4,0 (DT 0,5), la accesibilidad de 3,3 (DT 0,7), el confort del personal sanitario de 3,3 puntos (DT 0,9) y de los pacientes de 2,6 (DT 1,0). La satisfacción total con las prestaciones del BQ fue de 7,1 (escala 0-10). La evaluación del BQ es mejor entre las mujeres y las UGC con menos de 10 profesionales. Peor valoración se recibe por parte de las UGC con contacto diario con el BQ. Entre las propuestas de mejora se recogieron: reducir listas de espera, crear espacios de información a familiares, mejorar las condiciones laborales, la formación y la satisfacción del personal del BQ, la comunicación y colaboración interprofesional. Conclusiones. La evaluación realizada por profesionales sanitarios de otras UGC muestra la necesidad de formación del personal del BQ, así como de intervenciones en la organización e infraestructuras, con el objetivo de mejorar la calidad asistencial y la satisfacción general de profesionales y ciudadanía (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;32(2): 73-81, mar.-abr. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160712</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La calidad en el Bloque Quirúrgico del Hospital Clínico San Cecilio. La perspectiva del cliente interno</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10055^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6940^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13885^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6940^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29530^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6431^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10055^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6904^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13885^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
