<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94800</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Chizophrenia as a neurological condition caused by a failure in the lateralisation of the brain: macro adn microcopic observations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Summary. Introduction. Schizophrenia is a neurodevelopmentally defined condition. Some of its salient symptomatology refers to language abnormalities that resemble an aphasic disorder. Recent studies suggest that brain structures that define language functions may be abnormally lateralized in schizophrenic patients. Aims. To review the medical literature for evidence  of abnormalities of brain asymmetries in schizophrenic patients, and to discuss a new concept regarding the hierarchical organization of the cortex by interlinked minicolumns. Development. When reviewing the literature the limitation of applied techniques have to be taken into consideration. As of present, neuroimaging methods provide more credible data than those derived from autopsy series. Both neuroimaging and postmortem studies are consistent with the presence of a possible minicolumnopathy in schizophrenia. Minicolumns define a bias in corticocortical connections that throughout encephalization provide the opportunity for homologous cortical areas to become independent of each other. This new paradigm, derived from concepts of cortical modularity, sheds insights into the putative mechanisms of cerebral dominance and how they may be at fault in schizophrenia. Conclusions. Although there are no pathognomonic findings in schizophrenia a considerable majority of  studies make reference to the possible presence of abnormal cerebral dominance. If proven, the cadre of articles would suggest reevaluating our views in order to consider schizophrenia as a neurological disorder (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casanova, M. F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen. Introducción. La esquizofrenia es una condición definida durante el desarrollo del cerebro. En esta enfermedad, parte de la sintomatología se asemeja a un trastorno afásico. Estudios recientes sugieren que las estructuras del cerebro que definen las funciones del lenguaje están lateralizadas de manera anormal en pacientes esquizofrénicos. Objetivos. Revisar la bibliografía médica buscando evidencia sobre posibles anormalidades en las asimetrías del cerebro en pacientes esquizofrénicos y discutir un nuevo concepto con respecto a la organización jerárquica de la corteza. Desarrollo. Al revisar la bibliografía  hemos de tomar en consideración la limitación de cada técnica. Hasta el presente, los estudios de neuroimagen proporcionan datos más creíbles que aquellos que se derivan de series de autopsia. Sin embargo, ambos métodos, neuroimagen y estudios post mortem, presentan datos consistentes con la presencia de una minicolumnopatía en la esquizofrenia. Las minicolumnas definen conexiones corticocorticales que, a través del proceso evolutivo (encefalización), proporcionan la oportunidad de que áreas corticales homólogas adquieran su independencia. Esta nueva manera de pensar, derivada de conceptos sobre la modularidad cortical, ilumina posibles mecanismos que dan lugar a la dominancia cerebral y a cómo éstos pueden estar alterados en la esquizofrenia. Conclusiones. Aunque no hay hallazgos patognomónicos en la esquizofrenia, la mayoría de estudios sugieren la presencia de un fallo en la lateralización del cerebro. Si se comprueba esta conclusión, convendría reevaluar nuestras  opiniones y empezar a considerar la esquizofrenia como un trastorno neurológico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;49(3): 136-142, jul. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94800</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La esquizofrenia como condición neurológica debida a un fallo en la lateralización del cerebro: observaciones macro y microscópicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4351</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2527^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22878^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200907</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
