<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110062</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical Management of Solitary Pulmonary Micronodule: A Pilot Study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Solitary pulmonary micronodules (SPMN) characteristically have a diameter of 0.1&#150;0.5cm. Objective The aim of this prospective study is to evaluate the surgical approach to SPMN in order to establish the most appropriate treatment. Methods: Between January 2007 and June 2011, 146 SPMN patients (94 males and 52 females) were prospectively evaluated. Patients were divided into two groups based on history of malignancy (Group A, 59 patients) and generic risk factors for lung cancer (Group B, 87 patients). After gathering patient information, we proposed surgery or thin-section computed tomography (TSCT) follow-up to both Groups. Results: Preference for surgery versus TSCT follow-up was 90% versus 10% in Group A and 78% versus 22% in Group B, respectively. In Group A, we discovered 46 metastases from previous cancer (78%), 8 primary lung cancers (14%) and 5 benign lesions (8%). In Group B, we found 5 metastases (6%), 13 non-small-cell lung cancer (15%) and 69 benign lesions (79%). Statistical analysis revealed a high positive predictive value (PPV=0.9) between total surgical patients versus TSCT follow-up patients. Conclusions: The indication for surgery in solitary pulmonary micronodules is aimed at establishing early diagnosis and curing malignant disease. Our study indicates that in patients with previous cancer, surgery is essential. In patients with generic risk for lung cancer, surgical indications should be contemplated more carefully, even though the pulmonary malignancy rate of 21% in Group B seems to indicate the advisability of surgery(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Divisi, Duilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crisci, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: Los micronódulos pulmonares solitarios (MNPS) se caracterizan por un diámetro de 0,1-0,5cm. Objetivo El objetivo de este estudio prospectivo es evaluar el abordaje quirúrgico del MNPS con objeto de establecer el tratamiento más apropiado. Métodos: Entre enero del 2007 y junio del 2011, se evaluó prospectivamente a un total de 146 pacientes con MNPS, 94 varones y 52 mujeres. Se dividió a los pacientes en 2 grupos en función de los antecedentes de enfermedad maligna (grupo A, 59 pacientes) y los factores de riesgo genéricos para el cáncer de pulmón (grupo B, 87 pacientes). Tras obtener información sobre los pacientes, propusimos la cirugía o un seguimiento mediante tomografía computarizada de cortes finos (TCCF) a ambos grupos. Resultados: La preferencia por la cirugía frente al seguimiento con TCCF fue del 90% frente al 10% en el grupo A y del 78% frente al 22% en el grupo B, respectivamente. En el grupo A detectamos 46 metástasis de un cáncer previo (78%), 8 cánceres primarios de pulmón (14%) y 5 lesiones benignas (8%). En el grupo B encontramos 5 metástasis (6%), 13 cánceres de pulmón no microcíticos (15%) y 69 lesiones benignas (79%). El análisis estadístico puso de relieve un valor predictivo positivo elevado (VPP = 0,9) para el total de pacientes quirúrgicos frente a los pacientes con seguimiento mediante TCCF. Conclusiones: La indicación para la cirugía en el micronódulo pulmonar solitario tiene como finalidad establecer un diagnóstico precoz y la curación de la enfermedad maligna. Nuestro estudio indica que, en los pacientes con un cáncer previo, la cirugía es imprescindible. En los pacientes con un riesgo genérico de cáncer de pulmón, las indicaciones quirúrgicas deben ser más cuidadosas, aun cuando un 21% de enfermedades malignas en el grupo B parece indicar en cualquier caso la conveniencia de la cirugía(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;49(3): 94-98, mar. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110062</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento clínico del micronódulo pulmonar solitario: un estudio piloto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23039^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3105^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33478</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34525^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
