<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050332</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Review on treatment methods of torpid ulcers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The two important techniques to cure ulcers and wounds are dry cures and humid cures. Regardless of the type used, the objective continues to be the same: favor proliferation of granular tissue, avoid infection and favor debridement. Exposure of the wounds to air leads to slower cure after occlusion. In long course wounds, in leg ulcers, 18 of 39 (46%) cured completely, granulation tissue being developed in response to occlusion in all of them. By dressings, a human setting is favored and the best temperature conditions for tissue regeneration. A dressing according to the Goldman protocol (1992) should fulfill the following requirements: absorb the exudate, cause a humid microenvironment, be sterile and easy to manage, not cause allergic reactions or traumas and cause a favorable temperature for scarring, reducing pain. In the following, we present a synopsis of the existing protocols reviewed from the Agency for Health Care Policy and Research (1992), and those conducted by Anderson RM, in the European Congress on advances on the treatment of wounds, others from authors such as Elorriaga Ameyuga, with his manual from the National Health Institute, Bregstrom, Díaz Gonzalez (1995), protocols for venous lesions in lower limbs of Palfreyman. We also present extracts of the protocols of Nelson for arterial ulcers in lower limbs and those of Bradley for scars, Argüello and the American Family Physician, among others</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Chaparro Recio, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Novo García, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguirre Fernández, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez de los Heros, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Duvergé Montero, W</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las dos grandes técnicas de curación de úlceras y heridas son las curas secas y la cura húmeda. Independientemente del tipo de práctica utilizada el objetivo sigue siendo el mismo: favorecer la proliferación del tejido granular, evitar la infección, y favorecer el desbridamiento. La exposición al aire de las heridas cura más lentamente que tras oclusión. En heridas de larga evolución, en úlceras de piernas, 18 de 39 (46%) curaban completamente desarrollando tejido de granulación en respuesta a la oclusión en todas ellas. Mediante apósitos se propicia un ambiente húmedo y condiciones de temperatura más óptimas para la regeneración tisular. Un apósito, según protocolo Goldman (1992), debe cumplir los siguientes requisitos: absorber el exudado, provocar un microambiente húmedo, ser estéril y de fácil manejo, no causar reacciones alérgicas ni traumas y provocar una temperatura favorable para la cicatrización reduciendo el dolor. A continuación vamos exponer un compendio de los protocolos existentes revisados desde el Agency for Health Care Policy and Research (1992), también los realizados por Anderson RM en el congreso europeo en avances sobre el manejo de heridas; otros de autores como Elorriaga Ameyugo, con su manual del Instituto Nacional de la Salud, Bregstrom, Díaz González (1995) y protocolos para lesiones venosas en extremidades inferiores de Palfreyman. Asimismo, revisamos extractos de los protocolos de Nelson para úlceras arteriales en extremidades inferiores y los de Bradley para escaras, los de Argüello y el American Family Physician, entre otros</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);32(9): 437-443, nov. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050332</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión sobre métodos en el manejo de úlceras tórpidas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14854^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
