<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-68746</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper presents the theoretical construct of «coping with stress specific self-efficacy» and an instrument for its assessment, the Escala de Autoeficacia para el Afrontamiento del Estrés (EAEAE; in English, Coping with Stress Self-Efficacy Scale), as well as the results obtained concerning its psychometric properties from an adult population. 812 individuals, aged 18 to 64 years old (M= 26.46, SD= 9.93, 62.6% females and 37.4% males), recruited from various contexts, participated in this study. Participants completed the EAEAE along with other measures of constructs theoretically related to this specific self-efficacy. The EAEAE shows appropriate reliability in its complete form as well as in its two subscales of Efficacy Expectations and Outcome Expectations, and adequate factorial construct validity (which reveals the bi-dimensionality of the instrument), and convergent validity with the remaining measures. The characteristics of brevity and ease of application of the scale, in addition to its adequate psychometric properties, indicate that the EAEAE is an appropriate tool to assess and investigate coping with stress self-efficacy in research as well as clinical settings (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Delgado, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Godoy Izquierdo, Débora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Vázquez, Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Jiménez, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Chicheri García, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Godoy García, Juan F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta en este trabajo el constructo de «autoeficacia específica para el afrontamiento del estrés» así como un instrumento para su evaluación, la Escala de Autoeficacia para el Afrontamiento del Estrés (EAEAE), y los resultados sobre sus propiedades psicométricas. Participaron en este estudio 812 adultos de 18 a 64 años (M= 26.46; dt= 9.93; 62.6% mujeres y 37.4% hombres) procedentes de diferentes contextos. Los participantes contestaron la EAEAE junto con otras medidas de constructos teóricamente relacionados con esta autoeficacia específica. Tanto la escala completa como sus dos subescalas de Expectativas de Eficacia y Expectativas de Resultado muestran una adecuada fiabilidad, así como una apropiada validez de constructo factorial, que señala la bidimensionalidad del instrumento, y validez convergente con el resto de medidas. Las características de brevedad y facilidad de administración de la escala y la constatación de sus adecuadas propiedades psicométricas indican que la EAEAE es un instrumento apropiado para la evaluación e investigación sobre la autoeficacia específica para el afrontamiento del estrés en contextos de investigación y clínicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);20(1): 155-165, ene.-mar. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-68746</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33883</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
