<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118660</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Problem solving as a strategy in teaching offensive tactics at the under 8 level in 8-a-side-soccer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study focuses on teaching offensive tactics in soccer. Attacking tactics are a key strategic aspect of play in this sport and, given the number of factors that need to be coordinated, they are highly complex moves. The aim here was to study the way in which attacks were constructed during 8-a-side training sessions at the under 8 level where the coach used a series of drills based on the problem-solving approach to teaching. The results revealed improvements in two techniques that were worked on as part of offensive strategies, namely 1) keeping the ball, and 2) moving the ball and players towards the opponent&#146;s goal and, more specifically, the transition from an advanced midfield position to the attacking zone. The first of these techniques was shown to have been learnt prior to the second. Teaching attacking tactics needs to be complemented with a third technique (shooting at goal), and an analysis must be made of the extent to which all these skills are transferred to more complex match situations. (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herrero-Nivela, M. Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escolano-Pérez, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echeverría-Expósito, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo se centra en la enseñanza de la táctica ofensiva en fútbol. La acción de ataque u ofensiva del fútbol constituye una estrategia de juego fundamental y de gran complejidad en este deporte, por todos los elementos que son necesarios coordinar. Se pretende conocer qué desarrollo se produce en dicha acción ofensiva en un equipo de fútbol 8 de categoría pre-benjamín durante la implementación en los entrenamientos de una serie de ejercicios utilizando el entrenador un estilo de enseñanza de resolución de problemas. Los resultados indican mejoras en los dos elementos trabajados que forman parte de dicha táctica: 1) conservar el balón y 2) progresar el balón y los jugadores hacia portería, avanzando desde la zona media adelantada a la zona adelantada del campo contrario, si bien el aprendizaje del primer elemento se manifiesta en sesiones anteriores al del segundo elemento. Es necesario completar el entrenamiento de esta táctica con su tercer elemento (lanzar a portería) y conocer la transferencia de todo ello a situaciones más complejas como son los partidos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;23(1): 209-217, ene.-jun. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118660</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La resolución de problemas como estrategia de enseñanza para el aprendizaje de la táctica ofensiva en la categoría pre-benjamín de fútbol 8</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12025^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12025^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5180^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52426^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12025^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
