<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112491</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Schizophrenia and subjectivity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Recently, the group of symptoms known as &lt;subjective experiences&gt; of schizophrenia has raised a grouping interest. These phenomena have been shaped through concepts like depersonalization-derealization, mental automatism, disorders of the self and autism. The authors propose to review these syndromes, as well as their relationship with subjectivity understood as consciousness of the self (or self-awareness) and the shortcomings due to such a relationship. To finish, we will provide some hints into psychopathology understood as a technique of production of intelligibility which will hopefully help to provide a better grasp of the process describe above (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Pastor, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rejón Altable, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vírsela Antoranz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Existe actualmente cierto interés por las denominadas &lt;experiencias subjetivas&gt; en la esquizofrenia. A lo largo de la historia de esta patología estos fenómenos han tomado forma a través de conceptos como despersonalización-desrealización, automatismo mental, trastornos del yo y autismo. Los autores se proponen revisar dichos síndromes y su asentamiento en el paradigma de la subjetividad entendida como autoconciencia, así como los límites que dicho paradigma encierra. Se concluye tratando de encuadrar este proceso dentro del asunto más amplio de una psicopatología concebida como técnica de producción de inteligibilidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;32(4): 249-258, jul.-ago. 2004.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112491</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Esquizofrenia y subjetividad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3881^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3881^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1338^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1338^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3881^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3881^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
