<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161351</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Randomised clinical trial to evaluate the efficacy and safety of a new pediculicide made with saponified olive oil in the eradication of Pediculus humanus capitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The aim of the study was to evaluate the efficacy and safety of a new pediculicide in the eradication of Pediculus humanus capitis infestation. Material and methods. A randomised clinical trial was designed, in which children aged between 5 and 15 years diagnosed with pediculosis were selected. Treatment was administered on days 1 and 7 after selection, and they were evaluated in 4 visits (day 2, 7, 9, and 14). The product under evaluation with saponified olive oil was Inex Pediculicide Soap®, which was compared with Paranix®, with a similar mechanism of action. The primary efficacy endpoint was the eradication of the parasite by day 14 (louse-free rate), using an intention to treat analysis. Results. Six paediatricians from 5 Primary Health Care centres in the Community of Madrid (Spain) and one private clinic participated in the study. A total of 45 children were included, of which 75.6% were girls (n=34). The mean age was 7.1 years (95% CI 6.3-7.9). The large majority (80%) were middle class, and 82.2% had a history of previous pediculosis. The efficacy at 14 days was 76.2% (95% CI 52.8-91.8) in the group treated with Inex Pediculicide Soap® group, and 79.2% (95% CI 57.9-92.9) in Paranix® group (NNT=33.3). No adverse effects were observed with treatment. Conclusions. The 2 products were effective and safe in the eradication therapy Pediculus humanus capitis, with no statistical differences (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Soler, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruíz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castellares, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viver, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El objetivo del estudio fue evaluar la eficacia y seguridad de un nuevo pediculicida en la erradicación del Pediculus humanus capitis. Material y métodos. Se diseñó un ensayo clínico aleatorizado en el que se seleccionaron niños con edades entre los 5 y los 15 años, en los que se diagnosticó pediculosis. El tratamiento se administró en los días 1 y 7 tras su selección, y fueron evaluados en 4 visitas (días 2, 7, 9 y 14). El producto en evaluación con aceite de oliva saponificado fue Inex Pediculicide Soap®, que fue comparado con Paranix®, con un mecanismo de acción similar. La variable principal de eficacia fue la erradicación del parásito en el día 14, realizándose el análisis por intención de tratar. Resultados. Participaron 6 pediatras pertenecientes a 5 centros de salud de la Comunidad de Madrid (España) y una clínica privada. Se seleccionaron 45 niños, de los que el 75,6% eran niñas (n=34). La media de edad fue de 7,1 años (IC 95% 6,3-7,9), perteneciendo el 80% de los niños a la clase social media. El 82,2% tenían antecedentes de pediculosis previas. La eficacia a los 14 días fue del 76,2% (IC 95% 52,8-91,8) en el grupo tratado con Inex Pediculicide Soap®, y del 79,2% (IC 95% 57,9-92,9) en el grupo de Paranix® (NNT=33,3). No se registraron efectos adversos al tratamiento. Conclusiones. Los 2 productos en evaluación se mostraron eficaces y seguros en el tratamiento de erradicación del Pediculus humanus capitis, sin diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre ellos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);43(2): 91-99, mar. 2017. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161351</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ensayo clínico aleatorizado para evaluar la eficacia y seguridad en la erradicación del Pediculus humanus capitis de un nuevo pediculicida elaborado con aceite de oliva saponificado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10566^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29646</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10566^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54858^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27152^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55960^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53262^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
