<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119736</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Necrotizing pneumonitis is a rare entity in children. The most frequent causal gem is the. S Aureus on the contrary to adults in which it is anaerobic microorganisms. There is no unanimity on its treatment of choice, although most prefer penicillin, amoxicillin-clavulamic acid or clindamycin. We present the case of a 10 year old girl who is admitted from the Emergency Service due to precordial pain, weight loss and plain X-ray image consistent with multiple pulmonary  nodule (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrillo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La neurmonitis recrotizante es una entidad rara en niños. El germen causal más frecuente es el S. aureus a diferencia de en adultos, que son microorganismo anaerobios. No existe unanimidad ante su tratamiento de elección, aunque la mayoría se inclinan por penicilina, amoxicilina-clavulámico o clindamicina. Presentamos el caso de una niña de 10 años que ingresa procedente de urgencias por dolor precordial, pérdida de peso e imagen de radiología simple compatible con nódulo pulmonar múltiple (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;59(3): 292-294, mayo-jun. 2003. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119736</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neumonitis necrotizante: etiología poco frecuente del dolor torácico en niños</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13596^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12561^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13590^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53060^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
