<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102658</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">School climate, satisfaction with live, and school victimization. An analysis of the moderating effect of gender</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study has two aims: (1) to analyze the relationships of school climate and school adjustment with school victimization in adolescents through their relationships with non-conformist reputation and satisfaction with live, and (2) to explore the moderating effect of gender on these relationships. Participants were 1884 Spanish adolescents (52% boys and 48% girls), aged from 11 to 17 years. Structural equation modelling was carried out using the EQS program. Results shows that school climate and school adjustment are both directly and indirectly related to the school victimization, through its satisfaction with live. It has also found that gender has a moderating effect of gender on the path school climate and non-conformist reputation. Finally, results and its possible implications are discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Ruiz, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Povedano-Díaz, Amapola</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amador-Muñoz, Luís V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Ferrer, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente estudio tiene dos objetivos: (1) analizar las relaciones del clima escolar y el ajuste escolar con la victimización en adolescentes a través de sus relaciones con la reputación no-conformista y la satisfacción vital, y (2) explorar el efecto moderador del género en estas relaciones. Participaron en el estudio 1884 adolescentes españoles (52% chicos y 48% chicas) con un rango de edad comprendido entre los 11 y los 17 años (M=13.7, DT=1.4). Para analizar estas relaciones se llevó a cabo un modelo de ecuaciones estructurales con el programa EQS. Los resultados obtenidos muestran que el clima y el ajuste escolar se relacionan de modo directo e indirecto con la victimización escolar, a través de la satisfacción con la vida. También se ha encontrado el efecto moderador del género en la relación entre el clima escolar y la reputación no conformista. Finalmente, se discuten los resultados y sus posibles implicaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;28(3): 875-882, oct.-dic. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102658</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Clima escolar, satisfacción con la vida y victimización en la escuela. Un análisis del efecto moderador del género</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33199^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
