<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85931</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cervical subcutaneous emphysema and pneumomediastinum: a rare complication of adenoidectomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present a case of 5-year-old male patient that developed cervical facial subcutaneous emphysema and pneumomediastinum after having been operated of adenoidectomy. Three hours after the surgical procedure the patient showed neck and facial swelling with demonstrable crepitus occurred the symptoms included chest pain and odynophagia. The X-ray examination revealed subcutaneous emphysema and pneumomediastinum. He was treated with a broad-spectrum antibiotic and intravenous fluids therapy, and clinical and radiographic resolution at the end of the fifth day after surgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Maldonado Lozano, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos Martínez, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín García, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerrero Montenegro, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Martínez, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta el caso de un niño de 5 años de edad, intervenido de adenoidectomía, que desarrolló un enfisema subcutáneo cervicofacial y un neumomediastino después de ser sometido a la adenoidectomía. Tres horas después de la intervención quirúrgica el paciente presentó una hinchazón de la cara y el cuello, con presencia de crepitación, junto con dolor torácico y odinofagia. El examen radiológico puso de manifiesto la existencia de un enfisema subcutáneo y un neumomediastino. Se prescribió tratamiento con un antibiótico de amplio espectro y fluidoterapia intravenosa, y se produjo la resolución clínica y radiológica al quinto día poscirugía (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;69(1): 44-45, ene. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85931</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfisema subcutáneo cervical y neumomediastino: una rara complicación de la adenoidectomía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14458^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13740^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14458^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13740^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12309^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12309^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8646^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d241^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8646^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14458^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13740^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8646^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d241^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201101</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
