<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155217</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interventions to promote treatment adherence conducted by the nurses accredited according to the ACSA model</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: to describe the interventions conducted by hospitalization nurses accredited under the model of the Agency for Healthcare Quality in Andalusia (ACSA), with the objective of promoting and improving adherence to the therapeutic regimen; and to confirm if there were differences in these interventions according to the sociodemographical characteristics of the professional and the patient, as well as the level of accreditation achieved by the nurse.  Method: a descriptive transversal study on 2,196 clinical practice reports provided by the 1,098 nurses accredited from 2010 to 2016 in the Community of Andalusia. Variables: gender, age, and accreditation level of the nurses, interventions conducted, and patient age. Data collection was conducted through the ME_jora P computer application. Chi Square Test was used for bivariate analysis. Results: &#145;Education for Health&#146;, &#145;Education: the disease process&#146;, and &#145;Counselling&#146; were the interventions conducted by the majority of nurses in order to improve treatment adherence. The least conducted intervention was &#145;Promotion of willingness to learn&#146;. The older female nurses with accreditation at an Expert or Excellent level are those who conduct more interventions in order to promote treatment adherence. Conclusions: accredited nurses will adapt their interventions to the basic sociodemographic characteristics of patients. The experience acquired and knowledge demonstrated is a predictor for conducting more varied and complex interventions in order to improve treatment adherence. It would be necessary to conduct in depth studies about the differences in terms of patient conditions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herrera Usagre, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora Figueroa, Ana Rojas de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brea Rivero, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salguero Cabalgante, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: describir las intervenciones realizadas por enfermeras de hospitalización acreditadas bajo el modelo de la Agencia de Calidad Sanitaria de Andalucía (ACSA), encaminadas a potenciar y mejorar la adherencia al régimen terapéutico por parte de los pacientes; y comprobar si había diferencias en la realización de estas intervenciones según las características sociodemográficas del profesional y del paciente, así como el nivel de acreditación alcanzado por la enfermera. Método: estudio descriptivo transversal sobre 2.196 informes de práctica clínica aportados por las 1.098 enfermeras acreditadas desde 2010 hasta 2016 en la Comunidad de Andalucía. Variables: sexo, edad y nivel de acreditación de las enfermeras, intervenciones realizadas y edad de los pacientes. La recogida de datos se realizó a través de la aplicación informática ME_jora P. Para el análisis bivariante se utilizó el test Chi cuadrado. Resultados: &#145;Educación para la salud&#146;, &#145;Enseñanza: proceso de enfermedad&#146; y &#145;Asesoramiento&#146; fueron las intervenciones llevadas a cabo por la mayoría de las enfermeras para mejorar la adherencia terapéutica. La intervención menos realizada fue &#145;Potenciación de la disposición de aprendizaje&#146;. Las enfermeras mujeres de mayor edad y acreditadas en nivel experto o excelente son las que desarrollan más intervenciones para potenciar la adherencia terapéutica. Conclusiones: las enfermeras acreditadas adaptan sus intervenciones a las características sociodemográficas básicas de los pacientes. La acumulación de experiencia y conocimientos demostrados es un predictor de la realización de intervenciones más variadas y complejas para mejorar la adherencia terapéutica. Serían necesarios estudios que profundicen en las diferencias respecto a la patología del paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;19(6): 6-13, jul.-ago. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155217</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervenciones para potenciar la adherencia terapéutica realizadas por las enfermeras acreditadas según el modelo ACSA</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53262^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
