<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108624</identifier>
<setSpec>2174-5544</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quantitative Polymerase Chain Reaction and long term culture: the best method for cytogenetic study of chorionic villus sampling?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">First trimester cytogenetic prenatal diagnosis is performed on chorionic villus biopsies. Two methods are used to obtain metaphases: the short-term or semi-direct culture (STC) and long term culture (LTC). The main advantage of STC is that there is no risk of maternal contamination, and of LTC that no false-negative findings are described in the literature. It is considered that the combination of the two techniques (STC and LTC) is the most effective diagnostic strategy for this type of study. The technique of quantitative fluorescent PCR (QF-PCR) allows the evaluation of aneuploidy most frequently involved in prenatal diagnosis in 24-48 hours in chorionic villus samples. The aim of this study is to evaluate the combination of QF-PCR and LTC as a substitute for classical STC and LTC for prenatal diagnosis in chorionic villus samples. We present our experience in 900 chorionic villus samples(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cirigliano, Vincenzo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrero, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Plaja, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendoza, Judit</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barranco, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canellas, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palau, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Costa, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordoñez, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lloveras, Elisabet</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El diagnóstico prenatal citogenético durante el primer trimestre de gestación se realiza a partir de biopsias de vellosidad corial. Para la obtención de metafases se utilizan dos métodos: el cultivo corto o semidirecto (STC) y cultivo largo (LTC). La principal ventaja del STC es que no presenta contaminación materna y la del LTC es que no hay descritos en la literatura falsos negativos. Se considera que la combinación de las dos técnicas (STC y LTC) es la estrategia diagnóstica más eficaz para este tipo de estudios. La técnica de PCR cuantitativa fluorescente (QF-PCR) permite evaluar las aneuploidías más frecuentemente implicadas en el diagnóstico prenatal en 24-48 horas en muestras de vellosidad corial. El objetivo de este trabajo es evaluar la combinación de QF-PCR y LTC como sustituto de las clásicas STC y LTC para el diagnóstico prenatal en muestras de vellosidad corial. Para ello presentamos nuestra experiencia en 900 muestras de vellosidad corial(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Diagn. prenat. (Internet);22(3): 86-91, jul.-sept. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108624</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reacción en cadena de la polimerasa cuantitativa y cultivo largo: ¿el mejor método para el estudio citogenético de muestras de vellosidad corial?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34542^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23587^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34542^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23587^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3600^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3600^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3600^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23587^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34542^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23587^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
