<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127619</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1780</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The influence of social support on the emotional state and attitudes towards old age and ageing in a sample of elderly</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The stage of old age is marked by situations of dependency, isolation and loneliness. For this reason, this study attempts to analyse the role played by social networks in old people and their relationship with their emotional state and their attitudes towards their old age and aging. This study involved 117 people over the age of 50, without physical or psychological deterioration. The results were obtained through analysis of frequencies, gender differences and matrices of correlations. The sample presents a suitable social network, where the family nucleus is represented by the sons and daughters and the spouse who are the greatest social support for the old man. His emotional state is perceived as satisfactory and their attitudes towards his old age and aging are positive and favourable. The results indicate a positive relationship between social support, emotional state, and attitudes towards old age, which is reflected in an appropriate adjustment in the physical and psychological health (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castellano Fuentes, Carmen Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">No disponible</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int. j. psychol. psychol. ther. (Ed. impr.);14(3): 365-377, oct. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127619</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La influencia del apoyo social en el estado emocional y las actitudes hacia la vejez y el envejecimiento en una muestra de ancianos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23896</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
