<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59467</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hydroxyethyl starch to protect renal function in laparoscopic surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJETIVE: To evaluate the effect of prehydration withhydroxyethyl starch 130/0.4 (Voluven) compared tolactated Ringer solution in laparoscopic cholecystectomy.PATIENTS AND METHODS: We performed a randomizedsingle-blind clinical trial on patients classified as ASA 1and 2. The exclusion criteria were hypertension, kidneyfailure, treatment with diuretics or other antihypertensivedrugs, diabetes, and use of nonsteroidal anti-inflammatorydrugs. Balanced general anesthesia with remifentanil andsevoflurane was used. The total volume of administeredfluids (including prehydration) was 2 mL·kg-1·h-1 fastingplus 5 mL·kg-1·h-1 during surgery. Group 1 wasprehydrated 30 minutes before surgery with 500 mL oflactated Ringer solution in group 1; in group 2 the samequantity of Voluven was used. Ringer solution was used inboth groups to provide additional fluids. Blood pressurewas kept within 20% above or below baseline values.Standard anesthetic monitoring was performed.Intraoperative diuresis and creatinine clearance wererecorded. The groups were compared using the t test; a Pvalue of 05 or less was considered significant.RESULTS: Twenty-nine patients were enrolled in thestudy. Diuresis and creatinine clearance weresignificantly higher in the group that receivedprehydration with Voluven. The mean (SD) creatinineclearance rate was 176.44 (14.33) mL·min-1 in group 1and 61.90 (6.6) mL·min-1 in group 2 (P=.036). The meanvolume of urine excreted was 1.71 (0.06) mL·kg-1·h-1 ingroup 1 and 0.47 (0.02) mL·kg-1·h-1 in group 2 (P= .017).CONCLUSION: Prehydration with Voluven can be aneffective measure for protecting renal function againstthe adverse effects of pneumoperitoneum in laparoscopicsurgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García, J. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espí, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jover, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gregori, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almagro,  J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Valorar el efecto sobre la función renal dela prehidratación con hidroxietil almidón 130/0,4 (Voluven®) frente al Ringer Lactato en las colecistectomíaslaparoscópicas.PACIENTES Y MÉTODOS: Ensayo clínico aleatorizadosimple ciego en pacientes ASA I, II. Criterios de exclusión:hipertensión arterial, insuficiencia renal, tratamientocon diuréticos u otros antihipertensivos, diabéticos,uso de anti-inflamatorios no esteroideos. Anestesiageneral balanceada basada en remifentanilo-sevofluorano.Volumen total de fluidos administrados: (incluida laprehidratación): 2 mL Kg&#150;1 h&#150;1 ayuno + 5 mL Kg&#150;1 h&#150;1 deintervención. Prehidratación 30 minutos antes de laintervención con 500 mL de Ringer Lactado (RL) en elGrupo I y con la misma cantidad de Voluven® en el GrupoII. Resto de la fluidoterapia basada en Ringer Lactatoen ambos grupos. Mantenimiento de la presión arterialmedia ± 20% de los valores iniciales. Monitorizaciónanestésica habitual. Medida de diuresis intraoperatoriay aclaramiento de creatinina de diuresis intraoperatoria(ClCr). Comparación de grupos mediante t Student conun nivel de significación p &amp;#8804; 0,05.RESULTADOS: Se incluyeron 29 pacientes. Las diuresisy el aclaramiento de creatinina obtenidos fueron mayoresde forma estadísticamente significativa en el grupoen el que se realizó la prehidratación con Voluven®. ClCr(mL min&#150;1) GRUPO I: 176,44 ± 14,33, GRUPO II:61,90 ± 6,6 (p = 0,036); Diuresis (mL Kg&#150;1 h&#150;1) GRUPO I:1,71 ± 0,06, GRUPO II 0,47 ± 0,02 (p = 0,017).CONCLUSIONES: La prehidratación con Voluven® puedeser una medida eficaz en la protección de la función renalfrente a los efectos adversos del neumoperitoneo en lacirugía laparoscópica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;56(1): 27-30, ene. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59467</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso de hidroxietil almidón (Voluven®) como protecciónde la función renal en cirugía laparoscópica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7840^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5574^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7852^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29427^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200901</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
