<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042503</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diabetic foot</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">All patients who underwent a lower extremity amputation (LEAs) between January 1989 and December 2003 in Area 7, Madrid, were identified through operating theatre records. Vascular surgery department and Endocrinology service discharge records, and prescribing family doctors were used as secondary sources. According to Saint Vincent Declaration, a substantial decrease in LEAs and a later presentation were observed and related to a series of improvements in diabetic treatment. Despite these figures, a more substantial reduction in LEAs in diabetic people could be achieved with an earlier neuropathy screening, and intervention programes based on a continuing and well-structured education. The potential cost saving per 100.000 inhabitants and per year was estimated to be about 100.000 A</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Benedí, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calle-Pascual, A. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moñux, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durán, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García de la Torre, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Charro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Todos los pacientes a los que se les ha realizado una amputación de miembro inferior (AMI) entre enero de 1989 y diciembre de 2003 en el Área 7 de Madrid se identificaron a través de los partes de quirófano. Los informes de alta del servicio de cirugía vascular y del servicio de endocrinología, así como los médicos de familia (prescriptores), se utilizaron como fuente secundaria. De acuerdo con la Declaración de San Vincent, se observó una reducción en las AMI y un retraso en la edad de presentación, y se relacionó con una mejoría en la asistencia dispensada a las personas con diabetes. A pesar de esta mejoría, se podría alcanzar una reducción más importante en las AMI con un cribado de neuropatía más temprano, con programas de intervención basados en una educación bien estructurada de forma continuada, y facilitando el acceso al podólogo cubierto por la Seguridad Social en pacientes con pie en riesgo. El coste económico ahorrable se ha estimado en más de 100.000 A anuales por cada 100.000 habitantes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;53(1): 60-68, ene. 2006. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042503</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pie diabético</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31512^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d686^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31512^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31512^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d686^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d686^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
