<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90901</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Amyloidosis of the hip. Presentation of a case and a review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The term amyloidosis has been applied to a group of diseases which produce a deposit of extracellular material in organs and tissue. The joint symptoms appear due to the destruction process, with the development of erosions and significant joint effusions. The diagnosis and treatment of amyloidosis is based on histopathological and immunohistochemical study of the amyloid deposits. Clinical case. We present the case of a 58 year-old male, with a history of peritoneal dialysis 15 years ago and currently on haemodialysis treatment. He came to our clinic complaining of inguinal pain which began a year ago and was refractory to analgesic treatment. The radiology study showed a massive destruction of the coxofemoral joint. The study was extended by using magnetic resonance, which showed the presence of erosions with a sclerosing border in the iliac region and the presence of an abundant joint effusion; data suggestive of an erosive inflammatory arthritis associated with an infectious process or amyloid deposit. A joint biopsy using open surgery enabled the diagnosis of hip amyloidosis to be made using Congo red stain. After ruling out a septic process, it was decided to perform a hip replacement. Conclusion. Amyloidosis mainly in the bone and joint is an uncommon manifestation of this disease; the diagnostic suspicion is fundamental to be able to direct the histopathologist to its definitive diagnosis, since these stains are not used routinely (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rivera, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santacruz Arévalo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parrón Cambero, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El término amiloidosis se ha aplicado a un grupo de enfermedades que producen un depósito extracelular de material en órganos y tejidos. Cuando produce manifestaciones articulares genera una destrucción de las mismas con desarrollo de erosiones e importante derrame articular. El diagnóstico y el tratamiento de la amiloidosis se funda en el diagnóstico histopatológico e inmunohistoquímico de los depósitos de amiloide. Caso clínico. Presentamos un varón de 58 años, con antecedente de diálisis peritoneal hace 15 años y en tratamiento con hemodiálisis en la actualidad. Acude a nuestra consulta por dolor inguinal de un año de evolución y refractario a tratamiento analgésico. El estudio radiológico muestra una destrucción masiva de la articulación coxofemoral. Se amplió el estudio mediante resonancia magnética observando la presencia de erosiones con borde escleroso en la región ilíaca y la presencia de derrame articular abundante, datos sugestivos de artropatía inflamatoria erosiva en relación con proceso infeccioso o depósito de amiloide. Una biopsia articular mediante cirugía abierta permitió el diagnóstico de amiloidosis de cadera mediante el uso de tinción rojo Congo. Tras descartar proceso séptico se decidió la colocación de una artroplastia de cadera. Conclusión. La amiloidosis de predominio osteoarticular es una manifestación poco frecuente de esta enfermedad, el diagnóstico de sospecha es fundamental para poder orientar al anatomopatólogo a su diagnóstico definitivo, ya que el uso de estas tinciones no se realiza de rutina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);55(5): 385-388, sept.-oct. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90901</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Amiloidosis de cadera. Presentación de un caso y revisión de la bibliografía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d699^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d699^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7439^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7439^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6779^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1185^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d696^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d699^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
