<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142726</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The oral language is a ruled and complex system. It allows an exchange of information through a determined system of codification. It is not the only system, but with it, the thinking is constructed, invented and recreated, it regulates the interpersonal relationships, the behaviour of the individual itself and promotes the relationship between the child and his/her sociocultural atmosphere. The development of the oral language is the result of the interaction between the biological basis and the physical and social environment that surrounds the child. Our aim at writing this article is to approach the oral language from birth up to the age of 6 years, attending to the normalized evolution from its different dimensions (form, content and use) in order to detect as soon as possible the hypothetic problems and to put a stop to them with the educational and therapeutic suitable measures (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salmerón López, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Pedraza, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El lenguaje oral es un sistema reglado, muy complejo. Permite un intercambio de informaciones a través de un determinado sistema de codificación. No es el único, pero con él se estructura, inventa y recrea el pensamiento; regula las relaciones interpersonales, la propia conducta del sujeto y permeabiliza al niño en el medio sociocultural en el que está inmerso. Su desarrollo es el resultado de la interacción entre las bases biológicas y el entorno físico y social que rodea al niño. Nuestro objetivo al escribir este artículo es el abordaje del lenguaje oral desde su nacimiento hasta la edad de 6 años, atendiendo a la evolutiva normalizada desde sus diferentes dimensiones (forma, contenido y uso) con el fin de detectar lo más tempranamente posible las dificultades y atajarlas con las medidas educativas y terapéuticas adecuadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;8(32): 679-693, oct.-dic. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142726</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desarrollo de la comunicación y del lenguaje: indicadores de preocupación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7982</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3173</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7983</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1191</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7980</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7984</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2713</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13443</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6460</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13042</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
