<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134829</identifier>
<setSpec>2254-2884</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patient direct heparinization versus extracorporeal circuit heparinization in hemodialysis: a comparative study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Determine whether the mode of administration of heparin during hemodialysis treatment influences the coagulation status of the extracorporeal system. Methods: Quasi-experimental study in 27 patients on chronic hemodialysis. Two study periods were established. In the former the prescribed heparin was administered through the vascular access, during the second period through the arterial button of the extracorporeal system. Results: 27 patients were studied, being 37% female, and the mean age 68.63 ± 17.44. 63% of patients were treated with postdilutional online hemodiafiltration. There were no statistically significant differences in dose and dialysis parameters, vascular access, anticoagulant therapy or hemodialysis technique. Regarding the coagulation status, being grouped by varying score 5. In the first period, 5 points lower than average percentage was 94.09%, while in the second period was 97.1%, with significant differences (p = 0.035). Conclusions: In our study, the administration of sodium heparin in the extracorporeal circuit improves the coagulation end state of the system, which means less blood loss for the patient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pelayo Alonso, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibarguren Rodríguez, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Álvarez, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyero López, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuadrado Mantecón, María Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojo Tordable, Marina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar si la forma de administración de la heparina durante el tratamiento con hemodiálisis influye en el estado de coagulación del sistema extracorpóreo. Metodología: Estudio cuasiexperimental en 27 pacientes en Hemodiálisis crónica. Se establecen dos periodos de estudio. En el primero, la heparina prescrita se administra a través del acceso vascular y durante el segundo periodo, a través del botón arterial del sistema extracorpóreo. Resultados: Se estudiaron 27 pacientes, siendo el 37% mujeres, y la edad media 68,63±17,44. El 63% de los pacientes realizaba Hemodiafiltración on line postdilucional. No hubo diferencias estadísticamente significativas en cuanto a la dosis y parámetros de diálisis, el AV, el tratamiento anticoagulante ni la técnica de HD. En cuanto al estado de coagulación, si agrupamos por puntuación mayor o menor de 5, en el primer periodo, el porcentaje medio agrupado inferior a 5 puntos alcanza el 94,09% mientras que en el segundo periodo es de 97,1%, lo que sí resulta estadísticamente significativo (p=0,035). Conclusiones: Según nuestro estudio, administrar la Heparina sódica en el circuito extracorpóreo mejora el estado final de coagulación del sistema, lo que supone una menor pérdida sanguínea para el paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. nefrol;18(1): 48-55, ene.-mar. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134829</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Heparinización directa del paciente frente a heparinización del circuito extracorpóreo en hemodiálisis: estudio comparativo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23279^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23663^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31418^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
