<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-27553</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Autism and hyperlexia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Hyperlexia is described in children who present alterations or retardation in development and is frequently characterised by their teaching themselves to read at an early age. This ability to decode words does not correlate with their intellectual level and can course with different degrees of mental retardation. It is always accompanied by difficulty in establishing social relationships. Autism is a disorder that is prototypical of the autistic spectrum disorders (ASD), which are essentially characterised by qualitative alterations in social interaction, in communication and language development, and in the presence of a limited repertory of interests, accompanied by stereotyped or peculiar responses. Method. The presence of hyperlexia in autistic children is more frequent than in other development disorders. This phenomenon is linked with the increased skills involving visual memory, visual discrimination and motivation/interest towards visually represented material that is to be found in people with autism. However, not all autistic individuals present hyperlexia and not all children with hyperlexia present autism, although evidence shows that hyperlexia is a phenomenon that is observed with greater frequency in autism and in ASD. Conclusion. Hyperlexia, understood as meaning a &#145;little island of ability&#146; in children with autism and ASD, poses a number of question and represents an important challenge in neuropsychological research in this population (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los fenómenos de hiperlexia se describen en niños que presentan alteraciones o retraso en el desarrollo y se caracterizan por la habilidad para acceder a la lectura de forma precoz y autoaprendida. Esta habilidad para la decodificación de palabras no se correlaciona con el nivel intelectual y puede cursar con diferentes grados de retraso mental y, siempre, con dificultades de relación social. El autismo es el trastorno prototípico de los trastornos de espectro autista (TEA), que se caracteriza fundamentalmente por alteraciones cualitativas en la interacción social, en el desarrollo de la comunicación y el lenguaje y la presencia de un repertorio limitado de intereses, acompañado de respuestas estereotipadas o peculiares. Desarrollo. La presencia de hiperlexia en niños con autismo es más frecuente que en otras alteraciones del desarrollo. Este fenómeno se relaciona con las habilidades mejor conservadas de memoria visual, discriminación visual y motivación/interés hacia el material representado de forma visual que presentan las personas con autismo. Sin embargo, no todas las personas con autismo presentan hiperlexia, ni todos los niños con hiperlexia presentan autismo, a pesar de la evidencia de que el fenómeno de hiperlexia se observe con más frecuencia en el autismo y en los TEA. Conclusión. La hiperlexia, entendida como `islote de capacidad' en niños con autismo y TEA, plantea numerosos interrogantes y supone un importante reto en la investigación neuropsicológica en esta población (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;36(supl.1): 57-60, feb. 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Autismo e hiperlexia</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Martos Pérez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayuda Pascual, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-27553</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12366</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
