<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117046</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cutaneous Metastases of Internal Tumors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cutaneous metastases are relatively rare in clinical practice and their diagnosis requires a high index of suspicion because clinical findings can be subtle. These metastases reveal the presence of disseminated malignant disease and can lead to the diagnosis of unsuspected internal tumors or the spread or recurrence of an already diagnosed tumor. Early recognition of cutaneous metastases can facilitate prompt and accurate diagnosis resulting in early treatment; however, they are generally indicative of a poor prognosis. Some tumors have a predilection to metastasize to specific areas. Recognition of these patterns provides essential information that can guide the search for the underlying tumor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Avilés Izquierdo, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez Fernández, R. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Antón Martínez, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parra-Blanco, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las metástasis cutáneas son relativamente raras en la práctica clínica. Su diagnóstico requiere un alto índice de sospecha, pues los hallazgos clínicos pueden ser sutiles. Las metástasis cutáneas ponen de manifiesto la presencia de un tumor maligno diseminado y pueden permitir el diagnóstico de neoplasias internas no conocidas, o indicar la diseminación o recurrencia de otras ya diagnosticadas. Su reconocimiento temprano puede llevar a un diagnóstico preciso y rápido, con el consiguiente tratamiento oportuno, aunque en la mayoría de los casos son indicativas de un pronóstico infausto. Algunos tumores tienen predilección por metastatizar en áreas específicas. El reconocimiento de esos patrones es esencial para dirigir la búsqueda del tumor subyacente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;104(10): 841-853, dic. 2013. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117046</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Metástasis cutáneas de origen visceral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19257^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
