<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120756</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Triage in medical emergencies: differences between immigrant and native populations in a hospital in Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: to assess most common causes requiring hospital emergency care and their seriousness by means of a comparison and analysis of the differences between native population and immigrant population. Material and methods: a 12-month (July 2011-June 2012), cross sectional, descriptive study was carried out over several working shifts in an emergency department at the Móstoles Hospital, Madrid, Spain. Study endpoints: sex, age, country of origin, MTS (Manchester Triage System), reason for consultation, having a medical card, and previous Primary Care visit. Results: overall, 238 patients were assessed: 190 native patients and 48 immigrant patients. A majority of immigrant patients (54%)were from Latin America. Most common MTS was green (standard category) (51.7%). Statistically significant differences were found forage (younger age in immigrant patients) and reason for consultation(cardiac problems more common in native patients), but not for sex, MTS, or previous visit to a Primary Care doctor. Conclusions: MTS-based seriousness of conditions resulting in emergency department visits at Móstoles Hospital is similar in immigrant and native patients. Immigrant patients were younger, and cardiac problems were more common in native patients. More than 70% of patients in both groups did not attend to a previous visit to a Primary Care doctor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arcones Marín, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio Alonso, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pintor Holguín, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Murillo, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáiz Navarro, Elena María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hoyo Jiménez, José Félix</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: determinar las causas más frecuentes de requerimiento de asistencia urgente hospitalaria y su gravedad comparando y analizándolas diferencias entre la población autóctona y la población inmigrante. Material y método: estudio descriptivo transversal realizado en varios turnos de urgencia hospitalaria durante doce meses (julio 2011- julio2012) del Hospital de Móstoles (Madrid). Variables de estudio: sexo, edad, país de origen, MTS (Manchester Triage System), motivos de consulta, tener tarjeta sanitaria y haber acudido previamente a Atención Primaria. Resultados: se estudiaron 238 pacientes: 190 autóctonos y 48 inmigrantes. La mayoría de los inmigrantes (54%) procedían de Latinoamérica. El MTS más habitual fue el verde (urgencia estándar) (51,7%).Se encontraron diferencias estadísticamente significativas en cuanto a la edad (el grupo de inmigrantes era más joven), y en el motivo de consulta (los autóctonos acudieron por más problemas cardiológicos)pero no respecto al sexo, el MTS ni en asistencia previa al médico de Atención Primaria. Conclusiones: los pacientes inmigrantes que acuden al servicio de urgencia del Hospital de Móstoles tienen la misma gravedad (según MTS) que los autóctonos. La población inmigrante que acude a urgencias es más joven, y la autóctona lo hace en mayor proporción por sintomatología cardiológica. Más del 70% en ambas poblaciones no había acudido previamente al médico de Atención Primaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;17(1): 18-22, feb. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120756</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Triage de urgencias médicas: diferencias entre población inmigrante y autóctona en un hospital madrileño</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28838^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25631</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
