<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89339</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical significance of adenovirus isolation in feces of pediatric patients with viral acute respiratory infection</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: In the patients with acute respiratory infections caused by adenovirus, the deglution process of respiratory secretions allows the presence of these viruses in the intestinal tract (feces). Aim: to study the clinical significance of adenovirus isolation in the feces of 348 patients with respiratory tract infection caused by adenovirus. Method: The respiratory and fecal samples were inoculated in the Hep-2 cell line and the monlayers stained by a monoclonal antibody against adenovirus. Results. Adenovirus were isolated simultaneously in the respiratory and fecal samples, in 22 (35,4%) only in the respiratory samples and in 14 (22,5%) only in the feces. Overall adenovirus were isolated in 48 respiratory samples (77,4%) and 40 feces (64,5%). In 3 patients the feces agglutinated with the enteric adenoviruses (serotypes 40 y 41). Conclusions: the isolation of adenovirus in the feces of patients with acute respiratory tract infection could be an efficient method to support the isolation in the respiratory samples (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Reina, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferres, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Plasencia, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En los pacientes con infección respiratoria aguda por adenovirus, el progreso de deglución de las secreciones determina el paso de los virus al tracto intestinal (heces). Objetivo: Estudiar el significado clínico del aislamiento de adenovirus en las heces de 348 pacientes con infección respiratoria causada por adenovirus. Métodos: Las Muestras respiratorias y heces fueron sembradas en la línea celular Hep-2 y las monocapas reveladas con anticuerpos monoclonales frente a los adenovirus. Resultados : en 62 pacientes (17,8%) se aislaron adenovirus. En 26 (41,9%) se aislaron simultáneamente en la muestra respiratoria y fecal, en 22 (35,4%) sólo en la muestra respiratoria y en 14 (22,5%) sólo en la muestra fecal. Globalmente los adenovirus fueron aislados en 48 muestras respiratorias (77,4%) y 40 heces (64,5%). En 3 casos la muestra fecal aglutinó frente a los adenovirus entéricos (serotipos 40 y 41). Conclusiones: El aislamiento de adenovirus en las heces de pacientes con infección respiratoria aguda puede ser un método útil y eficaz como apoyo al aislamiento en las muestras respiratorias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;65(2): 98-100, mar.-abr. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89339</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Significado clínico del aislamiento de adenovirus en muestras fecales en pacientes pediátricos con infección respiratoria aguda viral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d265^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12561^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5346^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d267^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13568^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
