<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74889</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of the relationship between perceived emotional intelligence and metnal health of couples</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study analyzes the relationship between Perceived Emotional Intelligence (PEI) and Mental Helath in the couple´s member. 73 couples between 40 and 64 years old composed the sample. The instruments used to measure the variables of interest were the Trait Meta Mood Scale-24 (TMMS24; Fernández-Berrocal, Extermera &amp; Ramos, 2004) and the Scale of Mental Health-5 (MH-5; Alonso, Prieto &amp; Antó, 1995). The results sho the absence of direct relationship among PEI for one couple´s member and mental health of the other. However multiple reression analysis indicates that Mental Health of couple´s member is predicted in the first place by yout own PEI and by your couple´s Mental Health in second place. In conclusion we found and indirect relationship between IEP FOR the couplés member and the Mental Health of the other(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montañés, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Latorre, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Berrocal, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este estudio se analiza la relacióne xistente entrela Inteligencia Emocional Percibida porunmiembro de la pareja y la Salud Mental del oro miembro. 73 parejas de entre 40 y64 años componían la muestra. Los instrumetos utilizados para medir las variables de interés fueron el Trait Meta Mood Scale-24 (TMMS-24); Fernández-Berrocal, Extremera y Ramos, 2004) y el Mental Health-5 (MH-5; Alonso, Prieto y Ató 1995). Los resutlados muestran la inexstencia de relación directa entre la IEP por un miembro de la pareja y la salud mental del otro, sin embargo el análisis de regrisónmúltiple nos indica que la Salud Mental de cada miembro de la pareja se predice en primer lugar por su propia IEP y en segundo lugar por la Saud Mental de su pareja. Concluimos con la posible relación no directa pero si indirecta, entre la IEP por un miembro de la pareja y la Salud Mental del otro(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;12(2/3): 343-353, dic. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74889</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de las relaciones entre la inteligencia emocional percibida y la salud mental en la pareja</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10167^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7528^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52882^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
