<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056639</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hospital admissions for infectious diseases: 1999-2003 incidence in one health district in the Autonomous Community of Valencia, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BacKground:. Infectious diseases are still currently one        of the leading causes of death and illness. Their dynamic        nature justifies the epidemiological study thereof. This study is        aimed at analyzing the incidence of infectious diseases most        often conditioning hospital admissions.        Methods: A study was conducted of those individuals        admitted to hospital during the 1999-2003 period whose main        diagnosis at admission to hospital had been encoded according        to the International Disease Classification (ICD 9-CM) as an        infectious disease in the Minimum Basic Data Set. A total of        2,010 active infectious disease codes were selected and were        grouped into 25 groups as per the ICD 9-CM. The target        population was that of one district in the Autonomous        Community of Valencia.        Results: A total of 9.7% of the admissions during the        period under study (8,585 records) were due to an infectious        disease. Those affected averaged 38 years of age, median age        of 37, standard deviation 31 and the range of 1-102 years. The        admissions of males (54.5%) prevailed over females (48.5%).        The incidence rate of admissions due to infectious diseases        was 728 cases / 100,000 inhabitants / year. The highest rate of        admissions was among young children and the elderly. The        groups of diseases showing the largest number of admissions        were, in descending order, infectious digestive, respiratory and        genitourinary diseases.        Conclusion: The hospital admissions due to infections        diseases totaled one tenth of the admissions, and 7/ 1,000        inhabitants / year required hospitalization for an infectious        disorder. The highest incidence rates were found for intestinal        diseases, digestive, respiratory and genitourinary tract diseases        among the childhood-aged population, but also, although in        smaller percentages, among individuals over 65 years of age</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guerrero Espejo, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomás Dols, Sofía</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: La enfermedad infecciosa persiste en la        actualidad como una de las principales causas de mortalidad y        morbilidad. Su naturaleza dinámica justifica el estudio epidemiológico        de las mismas. El objetivo del trabajo fue analizar        la incidencia de enfermedades infecciosas que con mayor frecuencia        condicionan el ingreso hospitalario.        Métodos: Se realizó un estudio de las personas ingresadas        entre los años 1999-2003 cuyo diagnóstico principal al alta        hospitalaria se hubiera codificado, de acuerdo a la Clasificación        Internacional de Enfermedades (CIE 9-MC), como enfermedad        infecciosa en el Conjunto Mínimo Básico de Datos. Se        seleccionaron 2.010 códigos de enfermedades infecciosas en        actividad y se concentraron en 25 grupos adaptados al CIE 9-        MC. La población diana fue la correspondiente a un area de la        Comunidad Valenciana.        Resultados: El 9,7% de los ingresos durante el periodo        estudiado (8.585 registros) se debió a una enfermedad infecciosa.        La media de edad de las personas afectadas fue 38 años,        la mediana 37, la desviación típica 31 y el rango entre 0-102        años. Predominó el ingreso de varones (54,5%) sobre el de        mujeres (45,5%). La tasa de incidencia de ingresos por enfermedades        infecciosas fue de 728 casos/100.000 habitantes y        año. La mayor tasa de ingreso se produjo en niños y ancianos.        Los grupos de enfermedades con mayor número de ingresos        fueron, en orden decreciente, las enfermedades infecciosas        digestivas, respiratorias y genitourinarias.        Conclusión: Los ingresos hospitalarios por enfermedades        infecciosas alcanzaron la décima parte de los ingresos y 7 de        cada 1.000 habitantes al año requirió ser hospitalizado con        motivo de una patología infecciosa. Fue mayor la incidencia        de las enfermedades intestinales, de aparato digestivo, respiratorio        y genitourinario en la población infantil pero también,        aunque en menor proporción, en los mayores de 65 años</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;81(4): 411-420, jul.-ago.2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056639</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ingresos hospitalarios por enfermedades infecciosas: incidencia desde 1999 hata 2003 en un area sanitaria de la Comunidad Valenciana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28582^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28405^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31670</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
