<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78783</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-6585</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Descriptive photoelastical analysis of two different dental implants design submitted to vertical compression load</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of this study was to analyze the subsequent tensions distribution generated in the photoelastic models after application 7.5 N vertical loads, in two different dental implant designs. It were selected two different configuration implants, being one conic (Másters Conect Cônico®4.13×13 mm) and the other cylindrical (Titamax Ti Medula® 3.75×13 mm). For the analysis of the tensions distribution it were made two photoelastic resin models with dimensions of 40×10 mm of base and 30 mm of height. Each implant was positioned in the model and received vertical loads to7,5 N, being possible to visualize the isochromatic strips generated in it, through the polariscope. The Másters Conect Cônico® implants, that have long internal hexagon, polished cervical portion, top of spirals rounded, continuous passage of the spirals, distances between these of 0.5 tenth of millimeters, angled spirals and conical apex, presented the concentration of the tensions in the apical region. The cylindrical implants (Titamax Ti Medula®) with external hexagon, polished cervical portion, with top of the spirals in form of a &#147;v&#148;, continuous passage of spiral, with distance between the spirals of 0,5 tenth of millimeters, angled spirals and rounded apex, presented the distribution of the tensions on apical and cervical regions of the implants. Based on the results of this study it is possible to conclude that: the conical implants configuration concentrated the tensions in apicalregion, being the cylindrical configuration tensions concentrated on the apical and cervical region of the implants (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Albergaria Barbosa, JR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mazzonetto, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jaimes, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Duque de Miranda Chaves Netto, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olate, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio fue analizar la distribución de las tensiones generadas en los modelos fotoelásticos posterior a la aplicación de cargas verticales a 7,5 N, en dos diferentes diseños de implantes endoóseos. Fueron seleccionados 2 implantes con diferentes configuraciones: Implante(Máster Conect Cônico® 4,13×13 mm) e Implante (Titamax Ti Medula® 3,75×13 mm). Para el análisis de la distribución de tensiones fueron confeccionados 2 modelos en resinas fotoelástica con dimensiones de 40×10 mm de base y 30 mm de altura. Cada implante posicionado en los modelos recibieron carga vertical a 7,5 N, siendo posible visualizar las franjas isocromáticas generadas en los modelos, a través del polariscopio. El implante Máster Conect Cônico® con hexágono interno largo, porción cervical pulida, tope de las roscas redondeadas, pasos de las roscas continuas, distancia entre estas de 0,5 décimas de milímetros, espirales angulados y ápice cónico presento concentración de las tensiones en la región apical. El implante cilíndrico, Titamax Ti Medula®, con hexágono externo, porción cervical pulida, con tope de las roscas en forma de v, paso de roscacontinuo, con distancia entre las roscas de 0.5 décimas de milímetros, espirales angulados y ápicere dondeado presento distribución de las tensiones en la región apical medio y cervical del implante. Basado en los resultados de este estudio puede concluirse que: el implante de configuración cónica concentró las tensiones en región apical, siendo que el implante de configuración cilíndrica concentro las tensiones en la región apical medio y cervical del implante (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. periodoncia implantol. oral;21(3): 135-140, dic. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78783</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis fotoelástico descriptivo de dos diferentes diseños de implantes endoóseos sometidos a carga decompresión vertical</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13882</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29747</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3773</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9143</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
