<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047951</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Search for a pharmaceutical for marijuana dependency</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">No kind of pharmaceutical has been found that responds adequately to the demands for treatment being made by an increasing number of marijuana users. There have, however, been trials of compounds currently being used to alleviate the symptoms associated with abstinence from other drugs, but the results have not been positive in this case. Among compounds acting as agonists or antagonists of cannabinoid receptors, only the controlled use of &amp;#948;-9-tetrahydrocannabinol (THC) has produced interesting results in treating abstinence. But, there are limitations on the use of THC, as it does not reduce the craving. There is a new line of research relating to the function of the endocannabinoid system, based on the design of compounds that increase the half-life of anandamide in the brain of patients undergoing treatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramos Atance, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">No se ha encontrado todavia ningún tipo de fármaco que responda adecuadamente a las demandas de tratamiento realizadas por un número creciente de consumidores de marihuana. Por un lado, se han ensayado compuestos que están siendo utilizados para aliviar los síntomas asociados a la abstinencia al consumo de otras drogas de abuso, sin que los resultados hayan sido positivos en este caso. Entre los agonistas y antagonistas del receptor de cannabinoides, solo el uso controlado de &amp;#948;-9-tetrahidrocannabinol (THC), ha producido resultados interesantes para el tratamiento de la abstinencia. Pero presenta la limitación de que no disminuye el deseo de consumo. Una nueva línea de investigación esta relacionada con la funcionalidad del sistema endocannabinoide, y se basa en el diseño de fármacos que aumenten la vida media de la anandamida en el cerebro de las personas en tratamiento</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);18(1): 5-10, ene. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047951</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Búsqueda de un tratamiento farmacológico para la dependencia a la marihuana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29633</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2220^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2220^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30515^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29291^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4418^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4418^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12476</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4003^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
