<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61138</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-1375</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality of life and kidney transplants in over-65s</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Quality of life is defined as &#147;the personal perception of an individual of his or her life situation, within the cultural context and the context of the values in which he or she lives, and in relation to his orher goals, expectations, values and interests&#148;. The aim of this study is to determine the quality of life of patients over 65 years of age who have undergone kidney transplants. A qualitative, descriptive and retrospective study. The sample encompassed a total of 31 patients aged over 65 who received kidney transplants at our centre between July 2003 and July 2006. The instrument used to compile the information was in two parts: a survey of 11 items and questionnaire SF-36.The aspect that received the lowest rating from the patients surveyed (51.6 points) related to the capacity for intense physical efforts. However, activities of lower intensity received a higher score (88.7 points). Patients aged over 65 who have received a kidney transplant perceive an important improvement in their quality of life compared to the period prior to the transplant. This is reflected in an extension of the range of activities they can carry out (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torruella Barraquer, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conejos Alegre, Consuelo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mirada Ariet, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz Izquierdo, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuenmayor Díaz, Amaranta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Martín, M. Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vela Ballestero, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La calidad de vida se define como &#147;la percepción personal de un individuo de su situación de vida, dentro del contexto cultural y de valores en el que vive, y en relación con sus objetivos, expectativas, valores e intereses&#148;. El objetivo de este trabajo es conocer la calidad de vida de los pacientes trasplantados renales mayores de 65 años. Estudio cualitativo, descriptivo y retrospectivo. La muestra abarcó un total de 31 pacientes mayores de 65 años que fueron trasplantados en nuestro centro desde julio de 2003 hasta julio de 2006. El instrumento de recogida de información fue doble: una encuesta de 11 ítems y el cuestionario SF-36.El aspecto peor valorado por los encuestados (51,6 puntos) se refería a la capacidad de realizar un esfuerzo físico intenso. Sin embargo, actividades de menor intensidad recibieron una puntuación más elevada (88,7 puntos). Los pacientes mayores de 65 años que han recibido un trasplante renal, perciben una mejoría importante en su calidad de vida respecto al período anterior. Esto se refleja en una ampliación del abanico de actividades a realizer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Enferm. Nefrol;12(1): 26-30, ene.-mar. 2009. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61138</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida y trasplante renal en mayores de 65 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
