<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80530</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6982</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fibrous dysplasia of the bone. Contribution of Nuclear Medicine in the diagnosis of suspicion of sarcomatous degeneration</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Fibrous dysplasia (FD) is a relatively frequent benign disease of the bone in which there is a maturation disorder of the bone-forming mesenchyme where the lamellar bone marrow is replaced with abnormal fibrous tissue. Its diagnosis is often an accidental finding when X-ray studies or bone scans are performed for other reasons since it is usually asymptomatic. There may be complications such as deformities, pathological fractures and exceptionally malignant transformation. The differential diagnosis between malignancy and FD can be complicated and lead to late diagnosis when sarcomatous degeneration already exists. In this context, the positron tomography with 18F-fluorodeoxyglucose (FDG-PET) may be useful in the monitoring of this condition. We present two cases of patients diagnosed of FD with suspicion of malignization of their bone lesions who were referred to Nuclear Medicin(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santiago Chinchilla, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llamas Elvira, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Font, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tello Moreno, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego Peinado, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro-Pelayo Láinez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rebollo Aguirre, A. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La displasia fibrosa (DF) es una enfermedad benigna del hueso relativamente frecuente, en la que existe un trastorno de la maduración del mesénquima óseo con sustitución del tejido lamelar de la cavidad medular de los huesos por un tejido fibroso anómalo. Su diagnóstico a menudo es un hallazgo casual al realizar estudios radiológicos o gammagráficos óseos por otros motivos ya que normalmente es asintomática. En ocasiones puede presentar complicaciones como deformidades, fracturas patológicas y excepcionalmente transformación maligna. El diagnóstico diferencial entre DF y neoplasia maligna puede ser complicado y llevar a un diagnóstico tardío de cuando ya existe degeneración sarcomatosa. En este contexto, la tomografía de positrones con 18F-fluorodesoxiglucosa (PET-FDG) puede ser de utilidad en el seguimiento de esta patología. Presentamos 2 casos de pacientes diagnosticadas de DF con sospecha de malignización de sus lesiones y a las que se les solicitaron estudios complementarios de medicina nuclear(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Med Nucl;29(4): 172-176, jul.-ago. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80530</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Displasia fibrosa ósea. Aportación de la Medicina Nuclear al diagnóstico de sospecha de degeneración sarcomatosa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5493^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12888^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9871^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13515^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38793^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12888^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5493^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38793^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38793^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12888^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
