<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167083</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0952</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Therapeutic potential of Ginkgo biloba extract (EGb) in patients with schizophrenia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Schizophrenia is one of the most serious psychiatric disorders. It is a psychotic mental disorder characterized by alterations in thinking, mood and behavior. Almost all antipsychotic drugs have neurological or physical side effects, which often leads to noncompliance. From this perspective, it is justified the convenience and social relevance of searching products that offer an improvement in the symptomatology of the disease and reduce adverse effects and interactions in patients. The purified dry extract of Ginkgo biloba leaf is able to improve the symptoms of chronic schizophrenia when it is used as an adjuvant to antipsychotic therapy, alleviating the adverse effects caused by its prolonged use (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Rodríguez, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vanaclocha, Bernat</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La esquizofrenia representa uno de los trastornos psiquiátricos más graves. Se trata de un trastorno mental psicótico caracterizado por alteraciones del pensamiento, del estado de ánimo y del comportamiento. Casi todos los antipsicóticos tienen efectos secundarios neurológicos o físicos, lo que frecuentemente conlleva el incumplimiento del tratamiento. Desde esta perspectiva es fácil justificar la conveniencia y relevancia social de buscar productos que ofrezcan una mejoría en la sintomatología de la enfermedad y reduzcan los efectos adversos y las interacciones en los pacientes. El extracto seco purificado de la hoja de Ginkgo biloba es capaz de mejorar los síntomas de la esquizofrenia crónica como un coadyuvante a la terapia con antipsicóticos, paliando los efectos adversos provocados por el uso prolongado de éstos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. fitoter;17(1): 37-51, jun. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167083</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Potencial terapéutico del extracto de Ginkgo biloba (EGb) en pacientes con esquizofrenia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4421^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8682^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33751^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22965^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
