<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61397</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Conventional surgery following failure of endovascular treatment in chronic mesenteric ischarmia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Mesenteric angina is an infrequent symptom of atherosclerosis. The classical signs and symptomshave been reported as: post-prandial pain, weight loss and fear of intake. Standard treatment has consisted in openrevascularisation of the mesenteric vessels. Endovascular techniques have opened up new opportunities for treatment,although with lower patency outcomes. We report the case of a female patient with chronic mesenteric ischaemia andshort-term failure of endovascular treatment. Case report. A 77-year-old woman with multiple cardiovascular risk factorsand signs and symptoms of a classic abdominal angina. In 2006 she underwent an operation involving an angioplastyand stent in the superior mesenteric artery (SMA) to treat a sub-occlusive lesion at its origin. Clinical recurrenceoccurred 10 months after the treatment due to occlusion of the stent and a progression of the existing lesion at the originof the celiac trunk. A diagnostic-therapeutic arteriography scan was used to treat a lesion &gt; 70% of the celiac trunk withangioplasty and stent, although it was not possible to rechannel the previous stent in the SMA. The episodes of painreappeared eight months after the last intervention. The clinical recurrence caused by the endovascular treatment meantthat the decision was taken to perform a retrograde aortomesenteric bypass in the SMA. Conclusion. The aim ofrevascularisation is to relieve the symptoms, prevent intestinal infarction and improve the nutritional status. The patientthat we report here suffered from recurring abdominal pains following failure of the endovascular techniques. Conventionalsurgery has been clinically satisfactory and with 18 months&#146; patency(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Abdelkader Abu-Sneimeh, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Redondo-López, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio-Montaña, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuesta-Gimeno, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La angina mesentérica es un síntoma infrecuente de la ateroesclerosis. La clínica clásicamentedescrita es: dolor posprandial, pérdida de peso y miedo a la ingesta. El tratamiento estándar ha sido la revascularizaciónabierta de los vasos mesentéricos. Las técnicas endovasculares han abierto nuevas oportunidades de tratamiento, aunquecon resultados de permeabilidad menores. Presentamos el caso de una paciente con isquemia mesentérica crónica yfracaso a corto plazo del tratamiento endovascular. Caso clínico. Mujer de 77 años de edad, con múltiples factores deriesgo cardiovasculares y clínica de ángor abdominal clásico. En el año 2006 fue tratada mediante una angioplastia ystent de la arteria mesentérica superior (AMS) por lesión suboclusiva en su origen. Se produjo una recidiva clínica 10meses tras el tratamiento debido a una oclusión del stent y una progresión de la lesión ya existente en el origen del troncocelíaco. Mediante una arteriografía diagnóstico-terapéutica se trató una lesión &gt; 70% del tronco celíaco con angioplastiay stent sin poder recanalizar el stent previo de la AMS. Los episodios de dolor reaparecieron a los ocho meses dela última intervención. Debido a la recidiva clínica por fracaso del tratamiento endovascular se decidió realizar unbypass aortomesentérico retrógrado a la AMS. Conclusión. El objetivo de la revascularización es aliviar los síntomas,evitar el infarto intestinal y mejorar el estado nutricional. La paciente que se presenta sufrió síntomas recurrentes abdominalestras el fracaso de las técnicas endovasculares. La cirugía convencional ha resultado satisfactoria clínicamente ycon una permeabilidad de 18 meses(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;61(2): 99-103, mar.-abr. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61397</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cirugía convencional tras el fracaso del tratamiento endovascular en la isquemia mesentérica crónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23977^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8815^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d798^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30956^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7678^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23162^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
