<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-63771</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The questionnaire is one of the tools used most in social and socio-health care research. It has been used frequently in different researches with different designs and objectives. However, the questionnaire is a tool to collect information having a very definite and specific place in the framework of the phases that a research project should include. In this way, the questionnaire is a central tool during the phase that we generally call "field work" ­ that is, the time when the information is collected that will serve to compare the hypotheses formulated for our research. Even more, the questionnaire is only pertinent when the investigator has chosen and defined a research model based on the standardization of the information through mathematical-statistical language. Thus, to assure an effective hypothesis contrast (that is a contrast based on information faithful to the nature of the study purpose), it is necessary to design a "good questionnaire". This task depends on a large number of factors, all of them important when designing a questionnaire. The present chapter stresses two of these factors, formulating the basic subjects to be considered when the investigator needs to make a questionnaire. On the one hand, the chapter deals with the keys to formulate questions correctly and adequately, and the requirements that should be fulfilled by the coding of the answers for the data to be useful and reliable</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Moreno, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cuestionario constituye una de las herramientas más utilizadas en la investigación social y sociosanitaria. Su utilización ha sido frecuente en diversas investigaciones con distintos diseños y diferentes objetivos. Sin embargo, el cuestionario constituye una herramienta de recogida de información con un lugar bastante concreto y específico en el marco de las fases que un proyecto de investigación debe incluir. De esta manera, el cuestionario es una herramienta central durante la fase que solemos denominar "trabajo de campo", es decir, el momento en el cual se recoge la información que servirá para contrastar las hipótesis formuladas para nuestra investigación. Más aún, el cuestionario sólo es pertinente cuando el investigador ha seleccionado y definido un modelo de investigación basado en la estandarización de la información a través del lenguaje matemático-estadístico. Por tanto, para asegurar un contraste de hipótesis eficaz (es decir, un contraste basado en información fiel a la naturaleza del objeto de estudio), es preciso diseñar un "buen cuestionario". Esta tarea depende de un amplio número de factores, todos ellos importantes a la hora de diseñar un cuestionario. El presente capítulo enfatiza dos de dichos factores, formulando los temas básicos a considerar cuando el investigador se ve en la necesidad de construir un cuestionario. Por un lado, la forma en la cual se administra el cuestionario (es decir, la forma a través de la que el cuestionario nos relaciona con el entrevistado). Por otro lado, el capítulo se ocupa de las claves para formular preguntas de manera correcta y adecuada, así como de los requisitos que debe cumplir la codificación de las respuestas para que los datos sean útiles y fiables</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);33(8): 412-416, oct. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-63771</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28595</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28598^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
