<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044784</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Peripheral nerve blocks: an alternative technique in ambulatory surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION: Current investigations have demostrated that peripheral nerve block is associated with a superior outcome than general anestesia and it constitutes an useful and frequent technique in ambulatory surgery. The purpose of this manuscript is to show actual situation of peripheral nerve blocks in our Unit of Ambulatory Surgery and how it has modified our usual practice. MATERIAL AND METHODS: We made a prospective revision of peripheral nerve blocks used over the last two years. We analyzed a lot of variables onthe nerve block control sheet: patients´ data type of block, nerve stimulation technique and others. RESULTS: We registered 185 blocks in ambulatory surgery. All of them were for orthopaedic surgery and the majority in the lower limb. The local anesthetic most used was mepivacaine. Lateral popliteal block was the most frequent approach. Axillary block was the most frequent brachial plexus approach. All the patients were discharged six hours after the block. DISCUSSION: Today, peripheral nerve blocks are more popular than some years ago inour Unit for Ambulatory surgery. Selective peripheral nerve blocks, depending on the type and location of surgery, using a short acting local anesthetic allow an early discharge of patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortiz de la Tabla González, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reina Molina, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echevarría Moreno, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Gutiérrez, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino Grande, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Navas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Recientes investigaciones han puesto de manifiesto que los bloqueos nerviosos periféricos se asocian con mejores resultados que la anestesia general y que constituyen una práctica cada vez más frecuente en el ámbito de la cirugía ambulatoria. Nuestro objetivo es poner de manifiesto la situación actual de los bloqueos nerviosos periféricos en nuestra Unidad de Cirugía Mayor Ambulatoria y cómo ésta ha modificado la práctica habitual. MATERIAL Y MÉTODOS: Revisión retrospectiva de los bloqueos realizados en los dos últimos años, mediante el análisis de una hoja de bloqueos en la que se incluyen múltiples variables: datos del paciente, características del bloqueo, técnica de neuroestimulación y otras. RESULTADOS: Se realizaron 185 bloqueos en régimen de C.M.A., todos ellos en cirugía ortopédica y la mayoría en la extremidad inferior. El anestésico local empleado habitualmente fue mepivacaína. El bloqueo que se realizó con mayor frecuencia fue el bloqueo del nervio ciático en la fosa poplítea mediante abordaje latral. En la extremidad superior el abordaje del plexo braquial más frecuente fue a nivel axilar. Todos los pacientes fueron dados de alta a las 6 horas tras la realización de la técnica. DISCUSIÓN: En nuestra Unidad la práctica de bloqueos nerviosos periféricos en cirugía ambulatoria ortopédica está adquiriendo popularidad y en los últimos años se ha incrementado de manera muy importante. El empleo de bloqueos selectivos ajustados a las necesidades quirúrgicas con anestésico local de corta duración permiten una regresión temprana del bloqueo y el alta hospitalaria precoz (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;11(1): 20-23, mar. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044784</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bloqueos nerviosos periféricos: una alternativa en cirugía mauor ambulatoria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9600^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10221^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10221^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10162^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10162^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9600^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36501^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36500^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
