<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-17797</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factor structure of the Spanish WAIS-III</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Spanish version of the WAIS-III scale was published two year after the American one only. Taking into account the polemic about the factor structure of the previous versions (WAIS, and WAIS-R), it is critical to test what this new scale is assessing. Several structural models were analysed in the total sample (N = 1369), and in every normative age group through confirmatory factor analysis procedures. A model with four first-order factors (Verbal, Perceptual Organisation, Working Memory and Processing Speed) presents the best fit in all samples. When a second-order factor (identified with the g factor) is added to this model, the fit indexes also show acceptable values. Results support that g would be the main cognitive ability assessed by the WAIS-III. Implications for the scores computed after the scale (Total IQ, Verbal IQ, Performance IQ, and four cognitive indexes) are discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abad, Francisco José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Tan solo dos años después de la publicación en EE.UU. de la tercera versión de la escala Wechsler para adultos (WAIS-III), se adaptó dicha escala en España. Teniendo en cuenta la polémica sobre la estructura factorial de las versiones previas, es necesario comprobar qué factores esta evaluando la nueva escala. Con este objetivo diversos modelos estructurales fueron ajustados tanto en la muestra total (N=1369) como en cada grupo de edad. El modelo con cuatro factores de primer orden (Verbal, Organización perceptiva, Memoria de trabajo y Velocidad de procesamiento) obtuvo el mejor ajuste en todas las muestras. Por su parte, cuando se añadía un factor de segundo orden (identificado con g) al modelo anterior, los índices de ajuste presentaban valores considerados aceptables. En general, los resultados avalan la conclusión de que g es la principal aptitud cognitiva evaluada por la versión española del WAIS-III. Se discuten las implicaciones sobre las puntuaciones obtenidas a partir de la escala (CI total, CI verbal, CI manipulativo así como cuatro índices cognitivos) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);15(1): 155-160, feb. 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-17797</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estructura factorial de la versión española del WAIS-III</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15290</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
