<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-66787</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present a new mastopexy technique, simpler, which precludes the recidivism and reduces the risk of breast cancer. The study was based on 25 female patients between 25 to 50 years old with breast ptosis. With the patients standing up, was realized the traditional marks. If breasts were small, implants were positioned by submuscular way, and if bigger, the way was retroglandular. For recidivism prevention, it was positioned 2 internal straps; if the gland-implant was bigger and heavier an immobile strap from the breast to the clavicle periostium and to the 3rd rib, was realized; if it would result smaller or median size only were fixed to the third ribs with a dermal flap. Controls were realized between 1month to 3 years. Ptosis was corrected between 5 to 12cm without any recidivism, neither post-surgery pseudo-ptosis. With the support of an elastic brassier, physical exercise is recommended after15 days. The scarring was highly satisfactory. Complications were partial disruptions in 2 patients and ardors, tautness sensation and areolar enlargement in patients with more than 12cm ptosis and wide areola. Because of the execution simplicity and security, surgery was ambulatory. We propose this technique called 5th generation that precludes the periareolar, the inframamary, the vertical and the T scar; partial elimination of both upper breasts quadrants lessen the possibility of breast cancer in this upper area and ptosisrecidivism by the use of the internal straps (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Enríquez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torreblanca, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos una nueva técnica de mastopexia, más sencilla, y que evita recidivas además de disminuir el riesgo de carcinoma mamario. El estudio se realiza sobre 25 pacientes femeninas de 25a 50 años de edad, con ptosis mamaria. Con las pacientes de pie se realizó el marcaje tradicional; si las mamas son pequeñas se colocan implantes en el plano submuscular, y si son grandes, en el retroglandular. Para evitar recidivas se colocaron dos tirantesinternos con suturas irreabsorbibles. Si el complejo resultante glándula-implante es grande y pesado, se fija un tirante de la mama al periostio hemiclavicular y otro al periostio de la tercera costilla; si es pequeño o mediano, únicamente se fija a la costilla. Realizamos controles entre 1 mes y 3 años tras la intervención. Conseguimos corregir ptosis de entre 5 a 12cm., sin recidiva en ninguno de los controles, ni pseudo-ptosis postoperatoria. El ejercicio físico fue posible a los 15 días de la cirugía con el apoyo de un sujetador elástico. La cicatrización fue altamente satisfactoria. Las únicas complicaciones presentadas fueron dehiscencias parciales en 2 pacientes y sensación de ardor, tirantez y elongación dela areola en pacientes cuya ptosis excedía los 12cm y con areolas grandes. La facilidad de ejecución de la técnica y su seguridad, permiten que la cirugía sea ambulatoria. Proponemos esta técnica, que denominamos de quinta generación, que evita la cicatriz periareolar, la inframamaria, la vertical y la &#147;T&#148; invertida; además, elimina parte de ambos cuadrantes superiores de la mama, lo que disminuye notablemente la posibilidad de desarrollar ulteriores casos de carcinoma mamario y evita recidivas con el uso del tirante clavicular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;34(2): 89-100, abr.-jun. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-66787</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29995^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1965^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29995^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29995^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13895^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11916^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11916^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1965^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1965^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
