<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135386</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fibromyalgia patients&#146; perceptions of the impact of the disease in the workplace</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To explore the perceptions of patients with fibromyalgia (FM) on the problems they experience in the workplace, to discuss how they face and adapt to the limitations imposed by the symptoms of this disease. Design: An exploratory qualitative study conducted in 2009. Location. Associations of patients of FM from Valencia (Spain). Participants: Sixteen patients (13 women and 3 men) diagnosed with FM by a rheumatologist, of different ages and occupations, selected from key informants and the snowball technique. Method: Pragmatic sample. Semi-structured interviews until saturation of information when no new information emerged. Qualitative content analysis using the software Atlas.ti-5, to generate and assign codes, forming categories and identifying a latent theme. Results: We identified four categories: difficulties in meeting the work demands, need for social support in the workplace, strategies adopted to continue working, and resistance to leave the employment. A theme which crosscut these categories emerged: FM patients' motivation to continue in the labour market. Conclusions: Addressing the specific needs of patients it is essential in order to helping them to stay in the labour market, according to their capabilities. Awareness programs about the consequences of FM in the workplace are needed to achieve the collaboration of managers, entrepreneurs, occupational health professionals and primary care physicians and nurses (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Briones-Vozmediano, Erica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ronda-Pérez, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vives-Cases, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Explorar las percepciones de pacientes con fibromialgia (FM) sobre los problemas que experimentan en el ámbito laboral, para analizar cómo se enfrentan a ellos y se adaptan a las limitaciones derivadas de los síntomas de esta enfermedad. Diseño: Estudio cualitativo exploratorio realizado en 2009. Emplazamiento: Asociaciones de pacientes con FM de la Comunidad Valenciana (España). Participantes: Dieciséis personas (13 mujeres y 3 hombres) diagnosticadas de FM por un reumatólogo, de distintas edades y ocupaciones, seleccionadas a partir de informantes clave y por la técnica de bola de nieve. Método: Muestreo pragmático. Entrevistas semiestructuradas hasta alcanzar la saturación de la información cuando no emergían contenidos nuevos. Análisis de contenido cualitativo utilizando el software informático Atlas.ti-5 para generar y asignar códigos, formar categorías e identificar un tema latente. Resultados: Se identificaron 4 categorías: las dificultades para cumplir las exigencias laborales, la necesidad de apoyo social en el entorno laboral, las estrategias adoptadas para continuar trabajando y la resistencia a abandonar el mercado de trabajo. De forma transversal a estas categorías emergió un tema: la disposición de permanecer o reincorporarse al mercado laboral. Conclusiones: Se requiere atender las necesidades específicas de los pacientes con el fin de que logren permanecer en el mercado laboral, de acuerdo a sus capacidades. Para ello, emerge la necesidad de programas de sensibilización sobre las consecuencias de la FM en el entorno laboral para lograr la colaboración de los directivos, empresarios, profesionales de Atención Primaria y médicos del trabajo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;47(4): 205-212, abr. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135386</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Percepciones de pacientes con fibromialgia sobre el impacto de la enfermedad en el ámbito laboral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25783^s22082</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25783^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
