<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-62054</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Controversies in the Prostate Surgical Anatomy. A literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Radical prostatectomy technique has improved in the last years based on accumulated surgical experience and new anatomical findings. We think it is time to update anatomical concepts to standardized the criteria for mentioning structures related with radical prostatectomy. Material and Method: With the followings key words: &#147;cavernosal nerves, prostatectomy, anatomy, neurovascular bundle&#148; we search in Medline/PubMed database selecting papers fulfilling the search criteria. Conclusions: The prostate does not have a true capsule but rather an incomplete fibromuscular band as an intrinsic part of the gland. Periprostatic fascia seems to be a different structure from this fibromuscular band. Histologically Denonvilliers´s fascia is formed by two thin layers that cannot be separated during surgery. The longitudinal smooth muscle fibres located beneath the posterior bladder neck corresponds to the posterior longitudinal fascia of the detrusor muscle. Cavernosal nerves are located between the two layers of the endopelvic fascia, the inner layer could be named periprostatic fascia and the outer, levator ani fascia. Cavernosal nerves merged from the pelvic plexus running within a neurovascular bundle around the prostate that could be found as a singular bundle or spread all around the anterolateral surface of this gland. There are overlapping terms to designate the pelvic fascia, therefore it could be useful for Urologists to standardized them (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Maximiliano Bun, Maximiliano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramiro Cabello Benavente, Ramiro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carmen González Enguita, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Felipe Herranz Amo, Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juan I. Monzó Gardiner, Juan I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jesús Gómez Muñoz, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La técnica para la prostatectomía radical ha evolucionado dinámicamente durante los últimos años en base a una mayor experiencia quirúrgica acumulada y descubrimientos anatómicos. Nos parece oportuno revisar y actualizar algunos conceptos anatómicos básicos que nos permita conseguir una uniformidad de criterios y términos al referirnos a esta técnica quirúrgica. Material y Método: Hemos realizado una búsqueda bibliográfica en Medline/PubMed. Palabras clave: cavernosal nerves,prostatectomy, anatomy, neurovascular bundle. Realizamos una lectura detallada de los resúmenes de los artículos obtenidos, seleccionando aquellos que se ajustaban a los diferentes temas fijados para la revisión. Conclusiones: La glándula prostática no posee una cápsula verdadera sino que esta representada por una banda fibromuscular incompleta que es intrínseca a la glándula. La fascia periprostática parece ser una estructura distinta de esta banda fibromuscular. La Fascia de Denonvilliers en una fascia histológicamente compuesta por dos láminas pero quirúrgicamente indistinguibles. Las fibras ubicadas longitudinalmente por debajo del labio posterior del cuello vesical parecen corresponder a la fascia longitudinal posterior que pertenece al músculo detrusor. Los nervios cavernosos se sitúan entre dos hojas de la fascia endopélvica que podríamos denominar fascia periprostática (más interna) y fascia del elevador (más externa). Los nervios cavernosos son referencias del plexo pélvico y se ubican dentro de un fascículo neurovascular con distribución variable alrededor de la próstata según cada individuo (fascículo único o dispersos por la superficie antero lateral de la próstata). Consideramos conveniente que la comunidad de Urólogos unifique los términos para denominar las fascias pélvicas y evitar superposición de términos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;33(3): 228-234, mar. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-62054</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Controversias en la anatomía quirúrgica prostática. Revisión de la literarura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5309^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11910^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11910^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
