<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155654</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The problem of beginning of the personal being in the anthropology of V. E. Frankl</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this paper we review the V. E. Frankl&#146; conception of the &#145;person&#146;, which he understands as the superior part in man. This study consists of three parts: a) In the first we study 10 thesis that the father of logo therapy offers on the person, namely:1st) the person is an individual;2nd) whiteout possibility of sum; 3rd) is a new being; 4th) is spiritual; 5th) is existential; 6th) is the &#145;I&#146; or the &#145;ego&#146;; 7th) provides unity and wholeness; 8th) is dynamic; 9th) is able to transcend and to face herself; 10th) He is not understood by itself but from the point of view of transcendence. b) In the second part are studied 7 synonyms that the founder of the third Viennese school of psychology offers on the person: 1st) individual; 2nd) I; 3rd) personality; 4th) existence; 5th) spirit; 6th) heart; 7th) becoming. c) The third part we review the franklian hypothesis defending that the human person appears after the birth of human biological life. Although it is the third part that gives the title of this work, it can only be understood, and also reviewed, after having founded in the preceding two parties what specifically understand V.E. Frankl for person (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sellés Dauder, Juan Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este trabajo se revisa la concepción de V. E. Frankl sobre la &#145;persona&#146;, a la que él entiende como la dimensión superior del hombre. En concreto, este estudio consta de tres partes: a) En la primera se investigan las 10 tesis que el padre de la logoterapia ofrece sobre la persona, a saber: 1º) la persona es un individuo; 2ª) es insumable; 3ª) es un ser nuevo; 4ª) es espiritual; 5ª) es existencial; 6ª) es &#145;yoica&#146;; 7ª) brinda unidad y totalidad; 8ª) es dinámica; 9ª) es capaz de trascenderse y de enfrentarse a sí misma; 10ª) no se comprende a sí misma sino desde el punto de vista de la trascendencia. b) En la segunda parte se estudian los 7 sinónimos que el fundador de la tercera escuela vienesa de psicología ofrece sobre la persona: 1º) individuo; 2º) yo; 3º) personalidad; 4º) existencia; 5º) espíritu; 6º) corazón; 7º) devenir. c) En la tercera parte se revisa la hipótesis frankliana de que la persona aparece tras el nacimiento de la vida biológica humana. Aunque sea la tercera parte la que da título a este trabajo, ésta solo se puede entender y revisar tras haber fundado en las dos partes precedentes que entiende en concreto V.E. Frankl por persona (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad Bioet;27(90): 207-221, mayo-ago. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155654</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El problema del comienzo del ser personal en la antropología de V. E. Frankl</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37709</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10878</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d896</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36316</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7381</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36369</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7382</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33143</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
