<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75138</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-0599</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present article explains some important aspectsof the modern man. To achieve this goal I base myselfin the production character theory; this is an involuntarilypsychological orientation and unconscious thatserves to work and that determines the man&#146;s culture.The difference among other articles, this explains themodern man psychology, since it establishes cause relationsbetween its psychology and the merchandise propertieswith objective relation which has the characteristicsof the burguess production. The feeling of likeness,the individualism, the unconscious feeling of being athing, the alignment, the strangeness, the feeling thathas a value as a person as long as it is an interchangesubject. These characteristics of modern man&#146;s psychologyare explained through the production character, takingas reference the merchandise properties(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bernalmora, H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente artículo explica algunos aspectos importantesde la psicología del hombre moderno. Para lograreste objetivo me baso en la teoría del carácter de producción;esta es una orientación psicológica involuntariae inconsciente que sirve para trabajar y que determinala cultura del hombre. A diferencia de otros muchosartículos esta explica la psicología del hombre modernoya que establece relaciones causales entre su psicologíay las propiedades de la mercancía como relación objetivaque caracteriza la producción burguesa. El sentimientode igualdad, el individualismo, el sentimientoinconsciente de ser cosa, la alienación, la extrañeza, elsentimiento de que tiene valor como persona en tantosea sujeto de intercambio. Estas características de la psicologíadel hombre moderno se explican mediante elcarácter de producción tomando como referencia laspropiedades de la mercancía(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psiquiatr;25(2): 85-91, mar.-abr. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75138</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La mercancía y la psicología del hombre moderno</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8741</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36352</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3179</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51307</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
