<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141264</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Necrotising periodontal diseases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Necrotizing gingivitis (NG) or necrotising ulcerative gingivitis (NUG) is considered to be an acute opportunistic gingival infection caused by bacterial plaque. It appears more frequently in undernurished children and young adults as well as patients with immunodeficiency. In its pathogenesis, there are factors related to the oral microbiota with invasion processes on the one hand, and on the otrer hand, factors associated with the host, such as signs of capillary and immunological disorders as well as undernurishment. The disease is characterized by pain, bleeding and papillary necrosis with tendency to relapse. Diagnosis is made by a simple clinical examination. However, complementary tests ought to be performed in order to eliminate the possibility of illnesses systemic or immunodeficiency. Early and sustained treatment is strongly recommended. Lesions of the gums (craters in the interdental papillae) as an aftermath of the disease is a possibility, or if there is necrotizing periodontitis there will be loss of attachment tissue (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bermejo Fenoll, Ambrosio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Pérez, Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La gingivitis necrosante (GN) o gingivitis ulcerativa necrosante (GUN), se considera como una infección gingival oportunista aguda por placa bacteriana. Se produce más frecuentemente en jóvenes y niños desnutridos, así como en sujetos inmunodeprimidos. En su patogénesis están implicados por un lado factores dependientes de la microbiota con fenómeno de invasión y por otro factores relacionados con el huésped (alteración capilar e inmunológica y desnutrición). La clínica se caracteriza por dolor, sangrado, necrosis de las papilas y tendencia a la recidiva. El diagnóstico se realiza por la clínica, y los exámenes complementarios deben descartar la posible existencia de enfermedad sistémica subyacente o inmunodeficiencia. El tratamiento debe ser precoz y mantenido. Pueden permanecer lesiones residuales en la encía (cráteres en las papilas) o pérdidas de tejido de inserción en el caso de que se produzca una periodontitis necrosante (PN) o periodontitis ulcerativa necrosante (PUN) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);9(supl): 108-119, dic. 2004. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141264</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedades periodontales necrosantes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6031^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6031^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6031^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1447^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1447^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10709^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10709^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10709^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
