<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129373</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fetal bradycardia: A retrospective study in 9 Spanish centers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The aim of this study is to review the current management and outcomes of fetal bradycardia in 9 Spanish centers. Methods: Retrospective multicenter study: analysis of all fetuses with bradycardia diagnosed between January 2008 and September 2010. Underlying mechanisms of fetal bradyarrhythmias were studied with echocardiography. Results: A total of 37 cases were registered: 3 sinus bradycardia, 15 blocked atrial bigeminy, and 19 high grade atrioventricular blocks. Sinus bradycardia: 3 cases (100%) were associated with serious diseases. Blocked atrial bigeminy had an excellent outcome, except for one case with post-natal tachyarrhythmia. Of the atrioventricular blocks, 16% were related to congenital heart defects with isomerism, 63% related to the presence of maternal SSA/Ro antibodies, and 21% had unclear etiology. Overall mortality was 20% (37%, if terminations of pregnancy are taken into account). Risk factors for mortality were congenital heart disease, hydrops and/or ventricular dysfunction. Management strategies differed among centers. Steroids were administrated in 73% of immune-mediated atrioventricular blocks, including the only immune-mediated IInd grade block. More than half (58%) of atrioventricular blocks had a pacemaker implanted in a follow-up of 18 months. Conclusions: Sustained fetal bradycardia requires a comprehensive study in all cases, including those with sinus bradycardia. Blocked atrial bigeminy has a good prognosis, but  tachyarrhythmias may develop. Heart block has significant mortality and morbidity rates, and its management is still highly controversial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rueda Nuñez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Teodoro Marin, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Deiro Bronte, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zabala Arguelles, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galindo Izquierdo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Centeno Malfaz, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perin, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García de la Calzada, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Vázquez del Rey, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer Menduiña, Q</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Revisar el manejo actual y la evolución de la bradicardia fetal en 9 centros españoles. Método: Estudio multicéntrico retrospectivo: análisis de todos los fetos con bradicardia diagnosticados en 9 centros españoles entre enero de 2008 y septiembre de 2010. Los mecanismos electrofisiológicos responsables de la bradicardia fetal se estudiaron mediante ecocardiografía. Resultados: Se registraron 37 casos: 3 fetos con bradicardia sinusal, 15 con extrasistolia auricular no conducida y 19 con bloqueo auriculoventricular (AV) de alto grado. Bradicardia sinusal: el 100% asoció patologías severas. Extrasistolia auricular no conducida: excelente pronóstico, pero un caso desarrolló posnatalmente taquicardia supraventricular. Entre los bloqueos AV de alto grado, el 16% asociaban cardiopatía congénita con isomerismo, el 63% anticuerpos antiRo/SSA maternos y el 21% fueron de etiología desconocida. La mortalidad global de los bloqueos AV fue del 20% (37% si consideramos la interrupción voluntaria del embarazo). Factores de riesgo fueron: asociar una cardiopatía congénita, hídrops y/o disfunción ventricular. El tratamiento fue variable según el centro, se administraron corticoides en el 73% de los bloqueos de grado iii inmunomediados y en el único caso de bloqueo de grado ii inmunomediado. En un seguimiento medio de 18 meses, se implantaron marcapasos en el 58% de los bloqueo AV de alto grado. Conclusiones: La bradicardia fetal sostenida precisa siempre de un estudio exhaustivo, incluso en el caso de la bradicardia sinusal. La extrasistolia auricular no conducida tiene buen pronóstico pero puede asociar taquicardia. El bloqueo AV de alto grado fetal tiene todavía una morbimortalidad significativa y su tratamiento es controvertido (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);81(5): 275-282, nov. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129373</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bradicardia fetal: estudio multicéntrico retrospectivo en 9 hospitales españoles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1945^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52608^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38806^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5429^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5426^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201411</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
