<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131985</identifier>
<setSpec>1697-641X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Therapeutic methods of ranula. three case reports</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Sublingual ranula is a salivary retention pseudocyst located in the floor of the mouth with develops from mucous extravasation and accumulation that settles in the surrounding soft tissue, owing to any ruptured sublingual gland excretory ducts after trauma or obstruction. Intraoral examination shows an oval and fluctuating swelling which has soft consistency and bluish discolouration. It usually has an asympyomatic clinic but an increase of its size may affect patients swallowing and speech. Because of this, surgical treatment is recommended. Complementary diagnostic tools such as cervical magnetic resonances or computerized tomographs are required in order to confirm the clinical diagnosis. Marsupialization and intraoral removal of the ranula with the sublingual gland are the main therapeutic options. Patient&#146;s age or success and recurrence rates are decisive in order to choose the best therapeutic method. Three ranula case reports are presented in order to compare different therapeutic methods depending on patient&#146;s age. In addition, the results of the literature review are included (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Loughney González, Aitana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Domínguez, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Veiga López, Benazir</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Sánchez, Ruth</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villalva Hernández-Franch, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La ránula sublingual es un pseudoquiste de retención salivar localizado en el suelo de la boca que se produce tras un fenómeno de extravasación y acúmulo del contenido mucoide de la glándula sublingual en el tejido blando adyacente. Etiológicamente se relaciona con episodios traumáticos u obstructivos en alguno de los conductos excretores de la glándula. A la exploración física se observa una tumoración ovalada, fluctuante, de consistencia blanda y coloración azulada. Clínicamente suele ser asintomática pero su crecimiento progresivo puede llegar a comprometer la deglución y fonación del paciente, siendo este el principal motivo por el cual se indica el tratamiento quirúrgico. Se requiere de pruebas diagnósticas complementarias como la Resonancia Magnética cervicofacial, la Tomografía Computerizada o la Punción Aspiración con Aguja Fina para confirmar el diagnóstico clínico de presunción. Las principales opciones terapéuticas incluyen la marsupialización y la exéresis de la ránula junto con la glándula sublingual (sublingualectomía). Factores como la edad del paciente, el porcentaje de éxito y el índice de recidiva de la lesión tras un primer tratamiento, son determinantes a la hora de elegir la modalidad terapéutica de elección. Se presentan tres casos clínicos de ránula sublingual con el fin de comparar las diferentes opciones terapéuticas en función de la edad de presentación de la lesión. Se presenta además el análisis de los resultados de la revisión bibliográfica hecha al respecto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cient. dent. (Ed. impr.);11(3): 55-59, sept.-dic. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131985</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Modalidades terapéuticas de la ránula sublingual. A propósito de tres casos clínicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33572^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12336^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13749^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
