<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-69867</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Nausea and vomiting occurs in 50-90% of pregnancies, usually beginning by 5-6 weeks of gestation and  resolving by week 20. However, symptoms may persist through the third trimester in 15-20% and even until childbirth in 5%. The first phase of gastric herniation, as a complication of adjustable gastric lap band placement, is characterized by pyrosis due togastroesophageal reflux until complete feeding intolerance occurs. Improvement of this condition, mainly in the incipient phases, is achieved by complete band decompression. We present the case of a pregnant woman who underwent laparoscopic adjustable gastric banding who presented with nausea, vomiting and oral intolerance, a clinical picture compatible with hyperemesis gravidarum, related to gastric herniation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Causso, Claudia M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romeo, Iñaki</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Petrina, Estrella</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larrañaga, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zugasti, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El 50-90% de las embarazadas tiene náuseas y vómitos a partir de la quinta, sexta semana de la gestación que habitualmente desaparecen en la semana 20. Sin embargo, en un 15-20% los síntomas continúan durante el tercer trimestre y en un 5% hasta el parto. La herniación gástrica tras la colocación de una banda gástrica ajustable cursa con una primera fase de pirosis por reflujo hasta desarrollar una intolerancia alimentaria total que se soluciona, sobre todo, en fases incipientes, abriendo el paso del estoma. Presentamos el caso de una gestante portadora de una banda gástrica con cuadro de vómitos e intolerancia oral, compatible clínicamente con el diagnóstico de &#147;hiperemesis gravídica, en relación con herniación gástrica&#148; (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;54(10): 536-565, dic. 2007. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-69867</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23640^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7119^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7119^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
