<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163097</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hypernatremic dehydration. Optimized intravenous rehydration: generic and secure</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Acute neurological complications during intravenous rehydration (IVR) of patients with hypernatremic dehydration (DH) relate to the rate of resulted decline in effective plasmatic osmolality (EPO) dependent of natremia, whose oscillations are directly related to the tonicity and/or infusion rate (IR) of used fluids. These two aspects differentiate the two types of existing IVR guidelines: conventional (CIR) and rapid (RIR). A comprehensive review of published experience on RIR and two previous theoretical analysis of maximum rates achieved in CIR and comparative risk linked to the pace of natremic decline in CIR versus RIR from scenarios of hypernatremic-DH, identified both optimized type of solution (glucose hydro-electrolytic-isotonic-isoclhorinated [GHEITIC]) and IR to propose to study. Objective: To evaluate the efficacy and safety of IVR of hypernatremic dehydrated patients with a GHEITIC solution (glucose 4.7%, sodium 132.7 mmol/L, chlorine 109 mmol/L, acetate 42.8 mmol/L, potasium 19.4 mmol/L) at a generic IR of 10 mL/kg/h (GHEITIC-10-IVR). Methodology: A prospective, experimental study: on 8 hypernatremic cases of 62 dehydrated patients (3 months-9 years) by digestive losses, treated by GHEITIC-10-IVR, were analyzed their clinical and laboratory course; main variable: natremia. Results: Most intense basal hyperchloremias and acidosis significantly correspond with hypernatremic cases and were corrected satisfactorily; their basal DH degree had been underestimated in all and they presented during GHEITIC-10-IVR a slow decrease in natremia (0.84 mmol/L/h), even incomplete in some, but all ended the correction orally. There was no end hyponatremia or significant ionic disturbances. Conclusions: The GHEITIC-10-IVR of hypernatremic dehydrated cases proves to be effective, safe and easy to run (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aragó Domingo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calero Navarro, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Busselo, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las complicaciones neurológicas agudas durante la rehidratación intravenosa (RIV) de pacientes con deshidratación (DH) hipernatrémica se relacionan con el ritmo de descenso ocasionado en la osmolaridad efectiva plasmática (OEP) dependiente de la natremia, cuyas oscilaciones guardan una relación directa con la tonicidad y/o el ritmo de infusión (RI) de los fluidos empleados. Estos dos aspectos diferencian a las dos modalidades de RIV vigentes, la convencional (RIC) y la rápida (RIR).  Una revisión exhaustiva de la experiencia publicada sobre RIR y dos análisis previos teóricos de ritmos máximos alcanzados en la RIC, así como del riesgo comparativo vinculado al ritmo de descenso natrémico en la RIC frente a la RIR, desde casos hipotéticos de DH hipernatrémica, permitieron identificar un tipo de solución (glucohidroelectrolítica isotónica-isoclorada [GHEITIC]) y un RI optimizados para proponer en el estudio.  Objetivo: Evaluar la eficacia y la seguridad de la RIV de pacientes deshidratados hipernatrémicos con una solución GHEITIC (glucosa 4,7%, sodio 132,7 mmol/L, cloro109 mmol/L, acetato 42,8 mmol/L, potasio 19,4 mmol/L) en un RI genérico de 10 mL/kg/h (RIV-GHEITIC-10).  Metodología: Estudio prospectivo y experimental de 62 pacientes (de 3 meses a 9 años de edad) deshidratados debido a pérdidas digestivas, tratados con RIV-GHEITIC-10; en 8 casos hipernatrémicos se analizó el curso clínico y analítico, cuya variable principal fue la natremia. Resultados: Las hipercloremias y las acidosis basales más intensas se concentraron significativamente en los casos hipernatrémicos y se corrigieron satisfactoriamente; el grado de DH basal había sido subestimado en todos los casos y presentaron con la RIV-GHEITIC-10 un descenso horario lento de la natremia (0,84 mmol/L/h), incluso incompleto en algunos, y todos terminaron la corrección por vía oral. No hubo ninguna hiponatremia final ni disionias significativas.  Conclusiones: La RIV-GHEITIC-10 en casos de DH-hipernatrémica se demuestra eficaz, segura y fácil de ejecutar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;75(3/4): e28-e40, mar.-abr. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163097</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Deshidratación hipernatrémica. Rehidratación intravenosa optimizada: genérica y segura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19210^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5574^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24857^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7136^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7721^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1951^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3694^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
