<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045092</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness of health care interventions in the Primary Health Care service of chronic patients with hypercholesterolemia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE. Measure effectiveness on lipid control in the primary health service of chronic patients with hypercholesterolemia. METHODS. Observations, prospective study conducted in four urban health care sites on 285 dyslipidemic patients seen in the adult program. Follow-up was done according to the usual clinical practice for 18 months in six primary health care consultations. Lipid profile and lipid-lower drug treatment were recorded at onset and at 18 months. Lipid control was classified according to NCEP II and III recommendations. RESULTS. At the end of the study, a percentage reduction of the lipid parameters of total cholesterol (12.9%), LDL-cholesterol (16.5%) and triglycerides (7.6%) and an increase in the HDL-cholesterol levels (15.0%) were observed. By gender, reduction in the LDL-cholesterol values is greater in women (18.9%) and in patients in secondary prevention (22.6%). Grade of optimum control of the LDL-cholesterol levels is higher (40.7%) at the end of the study. Women have a greater optimum control percentage (45.3%) than men (33.6%). If the new NCEP III criteria are used, the control percentage decreased to 31.9%. CONCLUSIONS. A clear reduction of lipid plasma levels has been observed in patients, with more moderate results in patients in primary prevention and men</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Parada Brigido, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferre Larrosa, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Navarro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Cuadrado, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereñíguez Barranco, J. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Herráez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO. Medir la efectividad sobre el control lipídico en el servicio de pacientes crónicos con hipercolesterolemia de Atención Primaria. MÉTODOS. Estudio observacional, prospectivo, realizado en cuatro centros de salud urbanos, sobre 285 pacientes dislipémicos atendidos en el programa del adulto. El seguimiento se ha efectuado según la práctica clínica habitual durante 18 meses en seis consultas de Atención Primaria. Se registró el perfil lipídico y el tratamiento hipolipemiante al inicio y a los 18 meses. El control lipídico se clasificó según las recomendaciones del NCEP II y III. RESULTADOS. Al finalizar el estudio, se observa una reducción porcentual de los parámetros lipídicos del colesterol total (12,9%), colesterol LDL (16,5%) y triglicéridos (7,6%) y un aumento de los niveles de colesterol HDL (15,0%). Por sexos, la reducción de los valores de colesterol LDL es mayor en las mujeres (18,9%) y en los pacientes en prevención secundaria (22,6%). El grado de control óptimo de los niveles de colesterol LDL es más elevado (40,7%) al final del estudio. Las mujeres tienen un porcentaje de control óptimo mayor (45,3%) que los hombres (33,6%). Si se utilizaran los nuevos criterios del NCEP III el porcentaje de control descendería hasta el 31,9%. CONCLUSIONES. Se ha observado en los pacientes una reducción clara de los niveles plasmáticos de lípidos, con resultados más moderados en los pacientes en prevención primaria y varones</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);32(3): 111-116, mar. 2006. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045092</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad de las intervenciones asistenciales en el servicio de pacientes crónicos con hipercolesterolemia de Atencion Primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d963^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
