<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153169</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Association between nutritional status and flat foot prevalence in Chilean children from 6 to 10 years old</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Given the increment of overweight and obese children, it is relevant to study not only metabolic but also musculoskeletal consequences that may affect motor functionality such as flat foot in this population. Objetive: To identify the association between nutritional status and the prevalence of flat foot in Chilean children from 6 to10 years old. Methods: Z-score of body mass index and footprint using Hernandez-Corvo methodology were recorded and analyzed from 388 school children (52.3% girls). A two-sample proportion test was used to test differences between groups. Statistical significance was set at p &amp;#8804; 0.05. Results: The prevalence of overweight children was over 40%. This prevalence was higher in women (47.8%) than in men (42.7%). The prevalence of children with flat foot was 17% and higher for the right foot (18.3%) than for the left foot (15.7%). There was a significant higher prevalence of flat foot in obese children in relation to overweight and normal weight children. Conclusion: Nutritional status is associated with greater prevalence of flat foot in children. In infantile population of 6 to 10 years old, obesity is associated with a morphological alteration of feet (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Fuenzalida, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Contreras Molina, Ángela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguirre Polanco, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Quezada, Javiera</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Canales, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyes Ponce, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: dado el incremento del sobrepeso y obesidad infantil, es relevante estudiar no solo las consecuencias metabólicas, sino también aquellas de índole musculoesqueléticas que pueden afectar la funcionalidad motriz, como es el pie plano, en esta población. Objetivo: identificar la asociación entre el estado nutricional y la prevalencia de pie plano en niños y niñas chilenos de 6 a 10 años. Métodos: el z-score del índice de masa corporal (IMC) y el registro y análisis de las huellas plantares según la metodología de Hernández-Corvo fue llevado a cabo en 388 escolares (52,3% niñas). Un test de diferencia para dos proporciones fue utilizado para evaluar las diferencias entre los grupos. Se considera una significancia estadística con p &amp;#8804; 0,05. Resultados: la prevalencia del exceso de peso fue de más del 40%. Esta prevalencia fue más alta en las niñas (47,8%) que en los niños (42,7%). La prevalencia de pie plano en todos los niños fue del 17%, presentando valores más elevados el pie derecho (18,3%) que el izquierdo (15,7%). Hay un incremento significativo de la prevalencia de pie plano en los niños obesos en relación con los niños con sobrepeso y normopeso. Conclusión: el estado nutricional está asociado con incrementos en la prevalencia de pie plano en niños. En la población infantil de 6 a 10 años de edad, la obesidad está asociada con la alteración morfológica del pie (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;33(2): 249-254, mar.-abr. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153169</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asociación entre el estado nutricional y la prevalencia de pie plano en niños chilenos de 6 a 10 años de edad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23245^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55220^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
