<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113078</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sleep routines and adolescent adjustment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper presents the results of a study that describes the sleep routines in a sample of 2400 Andalusian adolescents aged between 12 and 17 years and its relation to three indicators of psychological adjustment such as substance use, and internalizing and externalizing problems, both assessed by the Youth Self Report (YSR; Achenbach, 1991). The results indicate that, particularly among older teens, there is a significant sleep deprivation during school days, and a delay in bedtime hours during weekends. These sleep routines were significantly related to psychological adjustment, since those boys and girls who reported sleeping fewer hours and going to bed later on weekends had a worse emotional and behavioral adjustment. The article suggests the importance of developing some measures to allow teens healthier sleep routines</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oliva Delgado, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antolín Suárez, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pertegal Vega, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reina Flores, Mª Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este trabajo se presentan los resultados de un estudio en el que se describen las rutinas de sueño de una muestra de 2400 adolescentes andaluces con edades comprendidas entre los 12 y los 17 años y su relación con tres indicadores de ajuste psicológico, como son el consumo de sustancias, los problemas interiorizados y los exteriorizados, ambos evaluados mediante el &#147;Autoinforme juvenil&#148; (Youth Self Report, YSR; Achenbach, 1991). Los resultados indican que, sobre todo entre los adolescentes de más edad, hay un importante déficit de sueño los días de colegio y un retraso en la hora de acostarse durante los fines de semana. Estas rutinas de sueño se mostraron significativamente relacionadas con el ajuste psicológico, ya que aquellos que declararon dormir menos horas y que se acostaban más tarde los fines de semana presentaron un peor ajuste emocional y conductual. Se sugiere la importancia de poner en marcha algunas medidas que permitan a los adolescentes unas rutinas de sueño más saludables (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;19(3): 541-555, sept.-dic. 2011. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113078</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rutinas de sueño y ajuste adolescente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8718^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2966</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13272</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
