<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100603</identifier>
<setSpec>2254-2884</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Standardising care of metabolic syndrome in peritoneal dialysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: We detected a high prevalence of cardiovascular risk factors in both incidental and prevalent cases in peritoneal dialysis. Aim: To draw up a standardised care plan for patients in peritoneal dialysis to deal with the problems arising from metabolic syndrome. Material and Method: The target population consisted of patients in peritoneal dialysis. A needs assessment was carried out using Marjory Gordon&#146;s approach, in which the NANDA, NIC and NOC classifications were used to establish the most frequent diagnoses, interventions and criteria for outcomes. Results: The most prevalent diagnoses were: lack of knowledge, ineffective management of the therapy regime, nutritional imbalance due to excess and deterioration in physical mobility. The interventions to be performed in the nursing consulting room and the criteria for expected outcomes were drawn up. The interventions were based on educating patients about altering their lifestyle, proper management of their diet, doing physical exercise appropriate to their age and in matters concerning their basic pathology and its treatment, such as administering and managing medication and peritoneal dialysis liquids. Conclusion: Through a care plan we standardised care of the health problems arising from metabolic syndrome in patients on a peritoneal dialysis programme (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rosales Sánchez, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Espejo, Jesús Lucas</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cirera Segura, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Montes, Myriam</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Detectamos una gran prevalencia de factores de riesgo cardiovascular en los pacientes incidentes y prevalentes en diálisis peritoneal. Objetivo. Elaborar un plan de cuidados estandarizado para pacientes en diálisis peritoneal que diera respuesta a los problemas derivados del síndrome metabólico. Material y Método. La población objeto fueron los pacientes en diálisis peritoneal. Se realizó una valoración de las necesidades según Marjory Gordon, y se utilizaron las taxonomías NANDA, NIC y NOC para establecer los diagnósticos, intervenciones y criterios de resultados más frecuentes. Resultados. Los diagnósticos más prevalentes fueron: Conocimientos deficientes, Manejo inefectivo del régimen terapéutico, Desequilibrio nutricional por exceso y Deterioro de la movilidad física. Se elaboraron las intervenciones a realizar en la consulta de Enfermería, así como los criterios de resultados esperados. Las intervenciones se basaron en la educación del paciente sobre la modificación del estilo de vida, manejo adecuado de alimentación, realización de ejercicio físico adecuado a su edad, y en los aspectos relativos a la patología de base y tratamiento, como administración y manejo de los fármacos y líquidos de diálisis peritoneal. Conclusión. Hemos estandarizado mediante un plan de cuidados, la atención a los problemas de salud derivados del síndrome metabólico, en los pacientes en programa de diálisis peritoneal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. nefrol;15(2): 129-137, abr.-jun. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100603</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estandarización de cuidados del síndrome metabólico en diálisis peritoneal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19270^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19270^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19270^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4074^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19270^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4074^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
