<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139153</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characteristics of anemia in cancer patients receiving palliative treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To study anaemia in cancer patients as well as the type of treatment used in a Palliative Care Unit (PCU). Patients and method: Descriptive, prospective observational study of patients admitted to the General University Hospital PCU of Ciudad Real during a one year follow up (June 2010-2011) who had an anaemic syndrome. The study protocol included epidemiological data, type of tumour, and the treatment received for anaemia. Control of symptoms was measured with the ESAS scale, and patient survival with the PaP Score scale. Results: The unit admitted 208 patients during the study period, of whom 65 (31.2%) were included. Of these, 37 (57%) were male and 28 (43%) were female. The mean age of the patients was 70.5 years. The reason for admission was anaemic syndrome in 7 (10.8%) of the cases. The most common type of tumour was gastrointestinal 25 (38.5%), followed by urological 15 (23.1%), and lung 14 (21.5%). The most common aetiology was receiving previous chemotherapy, followed by chronic disorders, folic acid and iron deficiency. In 19 (29.2%) cases the aetiology was multifactorial, and in 16 (24.6%) unknown. Forty-two treatments were administered to 22 (33.8%) patients: 15 with folic acid, 13 with iron, 12 transfusions of red blood cells, and 2 with vitamin B12. According to the PaP Score, 38.4% of patients were in group A, 44.6%, in group B, and 17% in group C. Conclusions: The anaemia in cancer patients receiving palliative treatment is of various aetiologies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abataneo, Gisela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galiana, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salcedo, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bencosme, Erika</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mañas, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lázaro, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudio de la anemia en una unidad de cuidados paliativos (UCP) hospitalaria y del tratamiento empleado para su mejoría. Pacientes y método: Estudio descriptivo, observacional y prospectivo de los pacientes ingresados en la UCP del Hospital General Universitario de Ciudad Real durante un año de seguimiento (junio de 2010 a junio de 2011) que presentaban síndrome anémico. El protocolo de estudio incluyó datos epidemiológicos, tipo de tumor y tratamiento recibido para la anemia. El control de los síntomas se midió con la escala ESAS y la supervivencia con la PaPScore. Resultados: Durante el tiempo de estudio ingresaron en la unidad 208 pacientes. Se incluyeron en el estudio 65 (31,2%). De ellos 37 (57%) eran varones y 28 (43%) mujeres. La edad media fue de 70,5 años. El motivo de ingreso fue el síndrome anémico en 7 (10,8%) casos. El tipo de tumor más frecuente fue el gastrointestinal (25 [38,5%]), seguido del urológico (15 [23,1%]) y el pulmonar (14 [21,5%]). La causa más frecuente fue haber recibido quimioterapia (QT) previa, seguida de trastornos crónicos, déficit de ácido fólico y ferropenia. En 19 (29,2%) casos la etiología fue multifactorial y en 16 (24,6%) desconocida. Se administraron 42 tratamientos a 22 (33,8%) pacientes: 15 de ácido fólico, 13 de hierro, 12 transfusiones de hematíes y 2 de vitamina B12. Según la PaPScore se encontraban en el grupo A el 38,4% de los pacientes, en el B el 44,6% y en el C el 17%. Conclusiones: La anemia en el paciente oncológico en tratamiento paliativo con frecuencia se debe a varias etiologías (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;22(3): 100-105, jul.-sept. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139153</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características de la anemia en los pacientes oncológicos en tratamiento paliativo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31478^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1829^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30048^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
