<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76013</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fibromuscular dysplasia. Asymptomatic dissection and occlusion of the basilar artery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Historically, basilar artery occlusive disease has been considered to convey a poor prognosis and a high mortality rate. In contrast, recently prospective studies have shown a better prognosis. The basilar artery is most commonly affected by atherosclerosis, but may also be affected by embolisms, dissections, aneurysms, and other conditions like fibromuscular dysplasia. Case report. The case of a 46 year-old male who was admitted after suffering a transient episode of ataxic gait and dysarthria is reported. Transcranial Doppler showed a stenotic flow in the basilar artery with distal embolic signals. Magnetic resonance (MR) angiography demonstrated an isolated fibromuscular dysplasia of the basilar artery that caused a &gt; 50% stenosis without parenchymal lesions. Oral anticoagulation treatment was initiated. The control MR angiography performed ten months later, and although the patient was asymptomatic, showed a dissection which evolved into a complete occlusion of the basilar artery. Its distal portion was filled via a reverse flow from both posterior communicating arteries.Anticoagulation treatment was discontinued. Discussion. Fibromuscular dysplasia of the basilar artery is a rare and usually asymptomatic disease. It may develop into a dissection, but the usual clinical presentation is stenosis-related ischemic stroke. Intracranial artery dissections may be further complicated by subarachnoid hemorrhage. Many authors have recommended anticoagulant therapy for fibromuscular dysplasia. Basilar artery occlusion, as this case shows, does not always convey a poor prognosis. This is determined, at least partially, by the presence of good collateral circulation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calleja, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benavente, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lahoz, C. H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Clásicamente, la oclusión de la arteriabasilar ha sido considerada una entidad de mal pronóstico ycon alta tasa de morbimortalidad. Estudios prospectivos másrecientes sugieren, sin embargo, un pronóstico más benigno.La arteria basilar se afecta sobre todo por la arteriosclerosis,pero también puede ser asiento de embolismos, disecciones,aneurismas y otras afecciones como la displasiafibromuscular.Caso clínico. Un hombre de 46 años fue ingresado por unepisodio transitorio de ataxia y disartria. El Doppler transcranealreveló un flujo estenótico en la arteria basilar conseñales microembólicas distales a la estenosis. La angiografíapor resonancia magnética (RM) demostró una displasiafibromuscular aislada en la arteria basilar que causaba unaestenosis mayor del 50 % sin lesiones parenquimatosas. Seinició tratamiento anticoagulante y 10 meses después, permaneciendoel paciente asintomático, una RM de controlmostraba una disección que evolucionó a oclusión completade la arteria basilar. Su porción distal se rellenaba por flujoinverso desde ambas arterias comunicantes posteriores. Laanticoagulación fue suspendida.Discusión. La displasia fibromuscular de la arteria basilares rara y habitualmente asintomática. Aunque puededesembocar en una disección, la presentación clínica másfrecuente es el ictus isquémico secundario a la estenosis. Lasdisecciones intracraneales se asocian con riesgo de hemorragiasubaracnoidea. Pese a ello, muchos autores recomiendanel tratamiento anticoagulante para la displasia fibromuscular.La oclusión de la arteria basilar, como muestraeste caso, no siempre conlleva un mal pronóstico. Éste estádeterminado, al menos en parte, por la presencia de una circulacióncolateral adecuada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;23(6): 388-391, jul.-ago.  2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76013</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Displasia fibromuscular, disección y oclusión asintomática de la arteria basilar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15119^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5488^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5488^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5488^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15119^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32158^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200808</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
