<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157272</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of overweight and obesity among adolescents in eight Arab countries: comparison between two international standards (ARABEAT-2)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The aim of this study was to highlight the prevalence of overweight and obesity among adolescents in eight Arab countries. Methods: A school-based cross-sectional study was conducted in eight Arab countries: Iraq, Jordan, Kuwait, Libya, Palestine, Saudi Arabia, Sudan and Tunisia. The total sample included was 6,447 adolescents aged 15-18 years (3,111 males, 3,336 females). The International Obesity Task Force (IOTF) and World Health Organization (WHO) reference standards were used to determine obesity levels. Results: The WHO standard provided lower prevalence of overweight but higher prevalence of obesity than the IOTF standard. According to the IOTF standard, overweight among males was highest in Kuwaiti adolescents (24.8%), followed by Saudi Arabian (23.2%). Among females, the highest prevalence was reported in Kuwaiti adolescents (22.1%), followed by Jordanian (20.0%). Regarding obesity, Kuwaiti adolescents showed the highest prevalence of obesity for both males (28.6%) and females (21.1%). Conclusion: Findings revealed no progress in reducing prevalence of obesity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tayyem, Reema</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elati, Jalila</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benhamad, Mofi da</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Musaiger, Abdulrahman O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Al-Haifi, Ahmad R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abahussain, Nada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Al-Mannai, Mariam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jalambo, Marwan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nabag, Fatima</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Al-Mufty, Berivan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: el objetivo de este estudio fue poner de relieve la prevalencia del sobrepeso y la obesidad en los adolescentes de ocho países árabes. Métodos: estudio transversal basado en escolares, que se llevó a cabo en ocho países árabes: Irak, Jordania, Kuwait, Libia, Palestina, Arabia Saudí, Sudán y Túnez. La muestra total estuvo compuesta por 6.447 adolescentes de 15-18 años (3.111 hombres, 3.336 mujeres). Se utilizaron para determinar los niveles de obesidad de la Fuerza Internacional de Obesidad (IOTF) y los patrones de referencia de la Organización Mundial de la Salud (OMS). Resultados: el estándar de la OMS presentó menor prevalencia de sobrepeso, pero mayor prevalencia de obesidad que el estándar de la IOTF. De acuerdo con la norma IOTF, el sobrepeso entre los varones fue más alto en los adolescentes kuwaitíes (24,8%), seguido de Arabia Saudí (23,2%). Entre las mujeres, se informó de la más alta prevalencia en adolescentes kuwaitíes (22,1%), seguido por las jordanas (20,0%). En cuanto a la obesidad, los adolescentes kuwaitíes presentaron la mayor prevalencia de obesidad tanto en hombres (28,6%) como en mujeres (21,1%). Conclusión: los resultados revelaron que no se ha conseguido ningún progreso en la reducción de la prevalencia de la obesidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;33(5): 1062-1065, sept.-oct. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157272</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La prevalencia de sobrepeso y obesidad en los adolescentes de ocho países árabes: comparación entre dos normas internacionales (ARABEAT-2)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1090^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12436</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
