<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91808</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Radiological findings in congenital anosmia: a case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Hypoplasia of the olfactory tracts and bulbs is a rare cause of anosmia in the paediatric population. In most cases it is usually due to an acquired cause and in only a few is it associated to chromosomal disorders (Kallman&#146;s syndrome,  among others). Case report. A 10-year-old boy with no chromosomal disorders and a family history of anosmia, who visited because of isolated anosmia; a magnetic resonance scan revealed bilateral hypoplasia of the olfactory tracts and bulbs. Conclusions. Magnetic resonance imaging allows the anatomy of the olfactory tract to be studied in detail and this makes it a valuable tool in the diagnosis of structural abnormalities in cases of olfactory disorders and also in the planning of treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carrascoso Arranz, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez de Vega, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Pérez, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Recio Rodríguez, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez De la Peña, Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La hipoplasia de bulbos y tractos olfatorios es una causa rara de anosmia en la población pediátrica. La mayoría de las veces es de causa adquirida, y se asocia en la menor parte de casos a alteraciones cromosómicas (síndrome de Kallman, entre otros). Caso clínico. Niño de 10 años sin alteraciones cromosómicas con antecedentes familiares de anosmia, que acudió por anosmia aislada y cuya resonancia magnética objetivó una hipoplasia bilateral de bulbos y tractos olfatorios. Conclusión. La resonancia magnética permite estudiar la anatomía de la vía olfatoria de manera que constituye una herramienta muy útil en el diagnóstico de anomalías estructurales en casos de trastornos de la olfacción y ayuda también a  la planificación del tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;53(2): 87-90, jul. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91808</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hallazgos radiológicos en la anosmia congénita: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d871^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10019^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10016^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d871^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201107</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
