<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-30900</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Transcranial magnetic stimulation. Applications in cognitive neuroscience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. In this review we trace some of the mayor developments in the use of transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) as a technique for the investigation of cognitive neuroscience. Technical aspects of the magnetic stimulation are also reviewed. Development. Among the many methods now available for studying activity of the human brain, magnetic stimulation is the only technique that allows us to interfere actively with human brain function. At the same time it provides a high degree of spatial and temporal resolution. Standard TMS applications (central motor conduction time, threshold and amplitude of motor evoked potentials) allow the evaluation of the motor conduction in the central nervous system and more complex TMS applications (paired-pulse stimulation, silent period) permit study the mechanisms of diseases causing changes in the excitability of cortical areas. These techniques also allow investigation into motor disorder, epilepsy, cognitive function and psychiatric disorders. Conclusions. Transcranial magnetic stimulation applications have an important place among the investigative tools to study cognitive functions and neurological and psychiatric disorders. Even so, despite the many published research and clinical studies, a systematic study about the possible diagnostic value and role in neurocognitive rehabilitation of TMS testing need to be realized to offer new possibilities of future applications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El objetivo de este trabajo es describir los nuevos usos de la estimulación magnética transcraneal (EMT) en la investigación neurocognitiva básica. Se revisan también distintos aspectos técnicos de la EMT. Desarrollo. A diferencia de los distintos instrumentos utilizados en neuroimagen para la investigación de la actividad cerebral, la EMT permite estudiar el funcionamiento cerebral produciendo una interferencia en su actividad normal. Además, proporciona una alta resolución temporal y espacial. Se han utilizado habitualmente sencillas aplicaciones de la EMT (velocidad de conducción, umbral y amplitud de potenciales evocados motores) para el estudio del sistema motor. Estos estudios, así como el desarrollo de nuevas aplicaciones más complejas de la EMT (estímulos magnéticos apareados, período de silencio) y EMT repetitiva, han permitido la investigación, bajo este paradigma, de trastornos motores y psiquiátricos y de la función cognitiva. Conclusiones. El conjunto de las distintas aplicaciones de la EMT la sitúa dentro de los instrumentos importantes para el estudio de la función cognitiva, los trastornos neurológicos y las alteraciones psiquiátricas. A pesar de la gran cantidad de investigaciones que en la actualidad optan por el uso de la EMT, se requiere un estudio sistemático sobre su valor en la clínica (diagnóstico, pronóstico y posible papel en la rehabilitación), ofreciendo un amplio abanico de posibilidades para futuras aplicaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;38(4): 374-380, feb. 2004.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estimulación magnética transcraneal. Aplicaciones en neurociencia cognitiva</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Calvo Merino, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Haggard, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-30900</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d19624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33145</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53282</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
