<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053396</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Temporomandibular juxtaarticular chondroma: case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Chondromas are benign tumours composed of mature hyaline cartilage.We present here the first case in the English language medical literature of juxtaarticular chondroma of the temporomandibularjoint in the parotid region. Within the rarity of cartilage disorders of the temporo-mandibular joint (TMJ), this particular condition is a diagnostic curiosity. The patient, a 54 year old woman, presented a right preauricular tumour of 3.5 cm. which had been developing for 4 years. It was not painful but there was a recent symptomology of TMJ dysfunction, with pain and clicks. The diagnostic possibilities of a parotid pleomorphic adenoma and of a cartilage tumour of the TMJ suggested a difficult preoperative differential diagnosis, which influenced our approach regarding therapy. The tumour was excised, preserving the parotid gland. This enabled us to confirm the histological diagnosis of chondroma, composed solely of chondroide tissue.We have described the clinical characteristics of our case, and carried out a review of the relevant literature, emphasising the differential diagnoses</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Mahía, Inés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferreras Granado, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo Franco, Fernanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Cedrún Cembranos, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los condromas son tumores benignos compuestos por cartílago hialino maduro.Presentamos el primer caso en la literatura anglosajona de condroma yuxtaarticular temporomandibular en la región parotídea. Dentro de la rareza de los trastornos cartilaginosos de la ATM, esta entidad constituye una auténtica curiosidaddiagnóstica. El paciente, mujer de 54 años de edad, presenta un tumor preauricular derecho de 3,5 cm, de 4 años de evolución, no doloroso pero con sintomatología reciente de disfunción de ATM, con dolor y chasquidos. Las posibilidades diagnósticas de un adenoma pleomorfo parotídeo y de un tumor cartilaginoso de la ATM plantean un diagnóstico diferencial preoperatorio difícil, que nos condicionaba la actitud terapéutica.Se realizó la extirpación del tumor conservando la glándula parótida, lo que nos permitió confirmar el diagnóstico histológico de condroma, compuesto exclusivamente por tejido condroide.Describimos las características clínicas de nuestro caso, y hacemos una revisión de la literatura al respecto, haciendo hincapié en los diagnósticos diferenciales</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);12(2): E171-E174, mar. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053396</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Condroma yuxtaarticular temporomandibular: informe de caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2862^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14082</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2862^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22602^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22602^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
