<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59822</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of socioeconomic factors on weight, length and head circumference measurements in newborns from 35 to 42 weeks gestational age</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: gestational age and anthropometric measurements, i.e. weight, length and head circumference at birth, have all been used as predictors of neonatal morbidity-mortality and adult morbidity. Differences in ethnic or socioeconomic background of newborn cohorts, as well as methodological differences between studies limit the validity and application of current anthropometric curves across different populations. Thus, we conducted a study to obtain local reference data in a Hospital that had a medium-high socio-economic class population, probably different to others recently published in our geographic area, and to compare them. Patients and method: Weight, length and head circumference at birth were retrospectively analysed in 31,397 live Caucasian neonates born at 23&#150;42 weeks in SCIAS-Hospital de Barcelona between 1992 and 2006. Only single gestations were selected and no other exclusion by materno-fetal or neonatal pathology criteria were applied. Percentile values, mean and standard deviation for each anthropometric measurement were calculated according to gestational age and gender. They were compared with the results from recent publications of our geographic area. Results: Males were found to have significantly higher weight, length and head circumference values than females from 36 weeks. There was a trend towards higher values in our population when compared with others in our geographic area. Conclusions: The influence of socioeconomic factors on fetal growth seems evident. Nevertheless, it is difficult to assume that the observed differences must be exclusively due to the population characteristics or the different methodologies in the selection of the sample. Thus, it is desirable to have anthropometric reference curves obtained from populations of surrounding areas, with epidemiological methodologies that might be more appropriate in identifying valid outcome predictors, and enable us to compare with others groups according to racial, socioeconomic and disease factors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vila Cerén, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Demestre Guasch, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sala Castellví, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Raspall Torrent, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elizari Saco, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Nadal, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pallás Ribes, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo: la clasificación del recién nacido según peso, longitud y perímetro occipitofrontal al nacer en relación con la edad gestacional se ha utilizado como indicador de morbimortalidad neonatal, así como factor pronóstico de enfermedades de la edad adulta. Las diferentes poblaciones analizadas y metodologías en la recogida de datos hacen que los resultados sean dispares entre publicaciones. El objetivo es establecer los valores antropométricos de referencia para nuestro hospital, que atiende a una población caracterizada por un nivel socioeconómico medio-alto, distinta, probablemente, de otras publicadas recientemente en nuestro entorno, y compararlas. Pacientes y método: análisis del peso, la longitud y el perímetro occipitofrontal al nacimiento de 31.397 recién nacidos vivos consecutivos en SCIAS-Hospital de Barcelona, de 1992 a 2006, con edades gestacionales entre 23 y 42 semanas. Se seleccionaron las gestaciones únicas y se separaron según sexo. Todos ellos de raza caucásica. No hubo exclusiones por enfermedad materna, fetal o neonatal. Se obtuvieron los valores en percentiles, media y desviación estandar, y se compararon según sexo. Se realizaron curvas según la edad gestacional a partir de las 35 semanas. Se compararon con los resultados de publicaciones recientes referidas a poblaciones de nuestro entorno geográfico. Resultados: se aprecian diferencias significativas en el peso, la longitud y el perímetro occipitofrontal al nacer según sexo a partir de las 36 semanas, con valores más altos en los varones. Se observa una tendencia a valores más altos en nuestra población al compararlos con otras de nuestro entorno geográfico. Conclusiones: la influencia del factor socioeconómico sobre el crecimiento fetal parece evidente. Sin embargo, es difícil asegurar que las diferencias observadas sean debidas, exclusivamente, a las características poblacionales o a las diferentes metodologías en la selección de la muestra. Es recomendable disponer de valores antropométricos poblacionales de referencia de la zona geográfica a la que pertenecemos, obtenidos a partir de metodologías epidemiológicas, para clasificar al recién nacido de forma adecuada y poder establecer comparaciones con sectores poblacionales diferenciados según factores raciales, socioeconómicos o por enfermedades (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);70(3): 241-252, mar. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59822</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de los factores socioeconómicos en el peso, la longitud y el perímetro occipitofrontal de los recién nacidos entre 35 y 42 semanas de gestación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1852</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28264</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29399</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
