<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161588</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The development of emotional intelligence in adolescence</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to analyse the development of the different dimensions of emotional intelligence in adolescents over one school year and in a cross-sectional study involving 484 adolescents of both sexes from the six school years between year 1 of Spanish secondary school (age 12-13) and year 2 of the Spanish Baccalaureate (age 17-18). Participants were administered the Spanish version of the Emotional Quotient Inventory: Young Version Short (Caraballo &amp; Villegas, 2001). Consistently with most previous research, the findings indicate that, except for the stress management dimension in the female sample group, none of the dimensions of emotional intelligence undergo substantial changes in relation to age (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Esnaola, Igor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarasa, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Revuelta, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ros, Iker</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este estudio se analizó el desarrollo de las diferentes dimensiones de la inteligencia emocional durante un curso escolar y transversalmente entre los seis cursos analizados en una muestra de 484 adolescentes de ambos sexos, entre 1º de ESO y 2º de Bachiller, a quienes se administró la versión en castellano del Emotional Quotient Inventory: Young Version Short (Caraballo y Villegas, 2001). Coincidiendo con el grueso de la investigación previa, los resultados indican que, salvo en lo que respecta a la dimensión manejo del estrés en la muestra femenina, el resto de dimensiones de la inteligencia emocional no experimenta cambios sustantivos en relación con la edad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;33(2): 327-333, mayo 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161588</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El desarrollo de la inteligencia emocional durante la adolescencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53742</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10746^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
