<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045773</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Calculation of the number of terminally ill patients through their use of opioid analgesics and tumor mortality</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To find the number of patients in terminal care in Madrid Health District 3. Design. Ecological, descriptive study. Setting. Eleven Health Districts. Madrid, Spain, 2002. Main measurements. Two models were used to calculate the number of patients in terminal care and were compared with data from the Primary Care Service Portfolio. Model A: consumption of morphine and fentanyl. The number of defined daily doses (DDD) of these active principles and the DDD per 1000 inhabitants and day (DID) were calculated. Prescription details: prescriptions charged to Social Security from registered doctors in Madrid (primary care and specialists). Model B: tumor mortality, i.e. the number of deaths due to tumors in the year 2000, published in 2004. Results. The number of terminal patients calculated by the 2 models in 7 of the 11 Health Districts and in the Community of Madrid is higher than in the Primary Care Service Portfolio. In the Community of Madrid, morphine and fentanyl are prescribed basically in primary care (96%). There was an important jump in fentanyl prescription from 2001 to 2002, due to the main fentanyl prescribed being transdermal. Conclusions. There are differences between the models in calculation of terminal patients. Moreover, the models offer heterogeneous results between health districts. Fentanyl consumption has become greater than morphine use in Madrid. The registers of terminal patients and/or their recruitment need to be improved</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Troncoso-Viejo, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larrubia-Muñoz, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escortell-Mayor, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Martínez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Romero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguel-Sánchez, C. de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer el número de pacientes en situación terminal del Área 3 de Madrid. Diseño. Estudio descriptivo, ecológico. Emplazamiento. Once áreas de salud. Comunidad de Madrid (CM). Año 2002. Mediciones principales. Se utilizan dos modelos para estimar a la población de pacientes en situación terminal y se comparan con los datos obtenidos en la cartera de servicios: ­ Modelo A. Consumo de opioides mayores (fentanilo y morfina). Se calcula el número de dosis diarias definidas (DDD) y la dosis diaria definida por 1.000 habitantes y día (DHD) para estos principios activos. Datos de prescripción: recetas facturadas por la Seguridad Social de médicos colegiados de la CM (atención primaria y especializada). ­ Modelo B. Mortalidad por tumores: número de defunciones por tumores del año 2000, publicado en 2004. Resultados. El número de pacientes en situación terminal estimado por los 2 modelos en 7 de las 11 áreas y en la CM es superior al obtenido en la cartera de servicios. La prescripción de opioides mayores se realiza fundamentalmente en atención primaria (96%) en la CM. Se produce un salto cuantitativo en la utilización de fentanilo entre 2001 y 2002, debido a la prescripción mayoritaria de fentanilo transdérmico. Conclusiones. Hay diferencias en la estimación de pacientes en situación terminal según los distintos modelos. Además, los modelos no presentan resultados coherentes entre las distintas áreas de salud. La utilización de fentanilo ha desplazado a la morfina en la CM. Es importante mejorar los registros y/o la captación de pacientes en situación terminal</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;37(2): 88-94, feb. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045773</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estimación de la población de enfermos en situación terminal a través de la utilización de analgésicos opioides y de la mortalidad por tumores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4422^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d715^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33200^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14105^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
