<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129101</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of a program evaluation of school meals in the Elda Health Department (Alicante)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: A program for the prevention of childhood  obesity is implemented in our department. The evaluation of school menus is one of the activities performed. In this  study we analyze the impact of this program after 4 years in operation. Methods: Longitudinal study with 4 years follow-up of the  menus served in the department. The nutritional composition of the menus offered in all educational centres with school  meals in the department from 2007 to 2010 has been  conducted using the software DIETSOURCE 1.2. The  statistical processing and analysis of the data were  conducted with Epi Info 6.04. Results: The school menus have improved since the  program was launched. They are now closer to WHO recommendations. Percent energy provided by fat, which was high at the initial evaluation, and carbohydrates, which was low, are now within the recommended ranges, as well as protein. Trend lines are more pronounced for fat and  carbohydrates with R2 values of 0,735 and 0,940  respectively and less pronounced in the case of protein  which shows a steep decline in the second year, and then remains stable. Conclusions: To assess the school menus and provide  feedback including general and individual recommendations is an effective strategy, although the follow-up study should  continue in order to confirm this (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Payá Molina, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez López, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cremades Bernabeu, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina Navarro, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Subiela Escribá, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miralles López, Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arroyo Fernández, Gerardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mira Diez, Zulima</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: En nuestro departamento se lleva a cabo un  programa de Prevención de la Obesidad Infantil entre cuyas actividades se encuentra la valoración de los menús escolares. En este estudio pretendemos analizar el impacto de este programa en los 4 años que lleva en funcionamiento. Métodos: Estudio longitudinal con 4 años de seguimiento  de los menús servidos en el departamento. Se ha valorado la composición nutricional de los menús ofertados en todos los centros educativos con comedor escolar del  departamento desde el año 2007 al 2010 con el programa DIETSOURCE 1.2. El tratamiento estadístico y el análisis de los datos se realizaron con el programa estadístico Epi Info 6.04. Resultados: Los menús escolares ha mejorado desde que  se ha puesto en marcha el programa acercándose a las recomendaciones de la OMS, pasando a estar dentro de los porcentajes recomendados tanto los lípidos como los  hidratos de carbono que estaban altos y bajos  respectivamente; y las proteínas a estar prácticamente dentro de cifras normales. Las líneas de tendencia son más acusadas en lípidos y carbohidratos con unas R2 de 0.735 y 0.940 respectivamente y menos acusada en el caso de las proteínas que hay un descenso brusco en el segundo año y luego se mantiene estable. Conclusiones: Se ha mostrado eficaz la estrategia de  valorar los menús escolares y remitir los resultados a los colegios, proporcionándoles una serie de recomendaciones individuales así como unas generales, aunque habrá que seguir con el estudio con el fin de confirmarlo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;18(1): 6-11, ene.-mar. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129101</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de un programa de valoración de menús escolares en el Departamento de Salud de Elda (Alicante)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8781^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2280^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23100^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
