<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125415</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Lisfranc fractures in children. Two clinical cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Lisfranc injuries are rarely seen in children and adolescents. Although clinically subtle, untreated cases can predispose to chronic pain and disability in the adult life. Material and methods: Two Lisfranc injuries of adolescents were treated operatively in Hospital de Basurto in 2012. Both patients were treated immediately in the emergency&#146;s theatre with closed reduction and internal fixation. Clinical and radiological follow-up was done, as well as a final questionnaire concerning the function and pain of the foot. Results: Anatomical reduction was achieved in both cases. None claimed harm, discomfort or physical limitation in the injured foot. Conclusions: Clinical and radiological evaluation is crucial in detecting Lisfranc injuries in children and adolescents. Prompt diagnosis and treatment provide clinical and radiological good results (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Espinazo Arce, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García de Cortázar Antolín, U</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña Arantzibia, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernaiz Alzamora, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Presentamos dos casos clínicos con lesiones de Lisfranc, raras en niños y adolescentes. Aunque clínicamente son sutiles, los casos no tratados pueden predisponer a dolor crónico y discapacidad en el adulto. Material y metodología: Se trataron quirúrgicamente dos lesiones de Lisfranc que se redujeron de forma inmediata en quirófano de urgencias mediante reducción cerrada y fijación interna. Se realizó seguimiento clínicoradiológico, así como un cuestionario final de función y dolor en el pie. Resultados: Se logró reducción anatómica en ambos casos. No se apreció en las revisiones dolor, malestar ni limitación funcional en el pie afectado. Conclusión: La valoración clínica y radiográfica es crucial para detectar lesiones de Lisfranc en niños y adolescentes. El diagnóstico y tratamiento tempranos posibilitan buenos resultados clínicos y radiográficos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);25(2): 92-96, abr.-jun. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125415</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fractura-luxación de Lisfranc pediátrica. A propósito de dos casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d906^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4928^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32246^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22943^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4265^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22943^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32246^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4265^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4928^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32246^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
