<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133875</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Study of the viability and adhesion of osteoblast cells to bone cements mixed with hydroxyapatite at different concentrations to use in vertebral augmentation techniques</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The purpose of this study is to compare the biocompatibility and the effect in osteoblasts of polymethyl methacrylate alone, and mixed with hydroxyapatite in different concentrations of 5, 10, 15 and 20%, without exceeding 20%, as it can alter mechanical properties of the composite. Material and methods: Experimental study comparing osteoblast response to Polymethyl methacrylate alone and with hydroxyapatite in different concentrations. Results: Composites at 15 and 20% obtained better osteoblast response, with higher osteoblastic activity markers, and lower apoptosis markers. Electron microscopy images show improved adhesion of osteoblasts (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jorge-Mora, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Couceiro-Otero, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pino-Mínguez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Santiago, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo de este estudio es comparar la biocompatibilidad y efecto sobre osteoblastos de polimetilmetacrilato solo y PMMA al que se ha añadido, hidroxiapatita en concentraciones del 5, 10, 15 y 20%, no superando nunca esta cifra del 20%, dado que si se supera esta cifra pueden verse alteradas las propiedades biomecánicas del PMMA. Material y métodos: Estudio experimental que consiste en el estudio de la adhesividad, diferenciación y muerte celular sobre discos de PMMA y composite PMMA/HA a diferentes concentraciones. Resultados: Los composites al 15 y especialmente al 20% presentaron mejor respuesta osteoblástica, mayores marcadores de actividad y menores marcadores de apoptosis. En las imágenes de microcopía electrónica se aprecia una mayor adhesión celular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);59(2): 122-128, mar.-abr. 2015. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133875</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de viabilidad y adhesividad celular de osteoblastos a cementos óseos utilizados en técnicas de refuerzo vertebral, mezclados con hidroxiapatita a distintas concentraciones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1868^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d275</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33389^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10184^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29128^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29076^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7040^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
