<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037019</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gene therapy: current situation and expectations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this review the current situation of gene therapy        is described in hematological diseases,        immunological conditions, and cancer. In all of        them, the principal objective of various approaches        with gene therapy is transduction of therapeutic        genes in most of target cells. In chronic or        immunological diseases, a stable expression of        therapeutic genes is also required; in tumor cells,        the efficiency or porcentage of transduced cells        make conditional on the treatment success.        Consequently, vectors are one of the basic        elements to optimize gene therapy approaches and        protocols in view of the facts that we know that        with liposomes less than 10% of cells are        transduced, that retrovirus only infect cells in        replication, and that adenovirus give rise to an        important inflammatory response and a transitory        transduction of the therapeutic gene. In addition        recent approaches in cancer gene therapy with        selective replication virus, suicidal genes, etc., are        discussed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barquinero Máñez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alemany Bonastre, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramón y Cajal Agueras, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En esta revisión se describe la situación actual        de la terapia génica en enfermedades        hematológicas, inmunológicas y en cáncer. En        todas ellas el objetivo principal de los diversos        abordajes de la terapia génica es el transducir        los genes terapéuticos en la mayor parte de las        células diana. A nivel de enfermedades crónicas        o inmunológicas se requiere, asimismo, una        expresión estable de los genes terapéuticos        y a nivel de las células tumorales la eficiencia        o porcentaje de células transducidas condiciona el        éxito de los tratamientos. Por consiguiente, los        vectores son uno de los elementos básicos para        optimizar los abordajes y protocolos de terapia        génica dado que sabemos que con el empleo de        liposomas menos del 10% de las células van a ser        transducidas, que con el empleo de retrovirus sólo        se van a infectar células en replicación y que con        los adenovirus va a haber una respuesta        inflamatoria importante y una transducción        transitoria del gen terapéutico. Asimismo se        discuten los últimos abordajes en terapia génica        del cáncer con virus de replicación selectiva, genes suicidas, etc</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;205(4): 178-188, abr. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037019</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Terapia génica: realidades actuales y expectativas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7291^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5955</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6552^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
