<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047894</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Extensive tinea corporis in immunocompetent patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Tinea corporis is caused by infection of glabrous skin from dermatophytes. They are generally fairly localized lesions in immunocompetent patients. A 40 year old male, of Romanian origin, consulted about itchy cutaneous lesions with the shape of large rings up to 30 cm in diameter, with a scaly erythematous border containing papules. It affected up to 60% of the total body surface. A KOH test and culture of the lesions were done, and were positive for trichophyton rubrum, the diagnosis of tinea corporis being established. Socio-health care conditions play a very important role in infections due to dermatophytes, the immigrant population being a risk group. In the case presented, we think that the socio-health care situation of the patient is that which must determine the distinctive clinical presentation of such a widespread tinea corporis</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz Díaz, R. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quesada Cortés, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos Muñoz, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arranz Sánchez, D. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Tinea corporis es producida por la infección por dermatofitos de la piel lampiña. Habitualmente son lesiones poco extensas en pacientes inmunocompetentes. Un varón de 40 años, de origen rumano, consultó por lesiones cutáneas pruriginosas anulares de hasta 30 cm, de borde papuloso eritemato escamoso, afectando hasta un 60% de la superficie corporal total. Se realizó una visión con hidróxido de potasio (KOH) y cultivo de las lesiones, que resultaron positivos para Trichophyton rubrum, estableciéndose el diagnóstico de tinea corporis. Las condiciones sociosanitarias desempeñan un papel de gran importancia en las infecciones por dermatofitos, siendo un grupo de riesgo la población inmigrante. En el caso presentado, pensamos que es la situación sociosanitaria del paciente la que ha debido determinar la presentación clínica peculiar de una tinea corporis de tan gran extensión</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);32(6): 304-306, jun. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047894</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tinea corporis extensa en paciente inmunocompetente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14649^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14394^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14394^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31378^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
