<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84771</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-8831</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Apnea as presenting sign of enterovirus meningitis in an infant</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The differential diagnosis of apnea in infants is broad, and includes infections, gastroesophageal reflux, seizures, airway anomalies, choking, congenital heart diseases, and metabolic diseases. Clinical Observation. A previously healthy one-month-old infant presented to the emergency department after an apneic episode at home; physical examination upon arrival was unremarkable. Twelve hours later, he presented a new apneic episode without bradycardia, requiring bag and mask ventilation, and followed by fever and clinical deterioration. A septic work-up was performed, including lumbar puncture and evaluation of cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) for enterovirus by polymerase chain reaction (PCR). The patient was started on empirical antibiotic therapy, and was transferred to the intensive care unit. The nasopharyngeal swab culture and CSF PCR were both positive for enterovirus. Antibiotics were discontinued, and the patient recovered uneventfully. Comments. Symptoms of meningitis in infants can be very nonspecific. The initial reason for consultation may be malaise, vomiting, poor feeding or pallor, with or without fever. Seldom has apnea been reported as initial symptom; however, infectious diseases should be considered in the differential diagnosis of this event. Enteroviruses are the most frequently identified etiologic agents in aseptic meningitis (80-90%), usually indistinguishable from bacterial meningitis. The enterovirus PCR has high sensitivity and specificity and is a very useful tool for diagnosis, helping reduce the hospitalization rates and antibiotic treatment(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Roger Garcia, Roger</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Margarit, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rius, Neus</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solé, Elisenda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pizà, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molera, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El diagnóstico diferencial de apnea en el lactante es amplio, e incluye infecciones, reflujo gastroesofágico, convulsiones, alteraciones de vía aérea, atragantamiento, cardiopatías y metabolopatías. Episodi d&#146;apnea en un lactant: clínica inicial de meningitis per enterovirus Neus Rius, Anna Pizà, Cristina Molera, Elisenda Solé, Roger Garcia, Jaume Margarit Servei de Pediatria. Hospital Universitari Mútua de Terrassa. Terrassa (Barcelona) Caso clínico. Lactante de un mes de vida, previamente sano, que consulta por episodio compatible con apnea en el domicilio y con exploración anodina a su llegada a urgencias. A las 12 horas realiza un nuevo episodio de apnea sin bradicardia que recupera con ventilación con bolsa y mascarilla. Pico febril posterior con afectación del estado general y mala coloración. Ante la sospecha de sepsis se realiza analítica, hemocultivo, sedimento de orina y punción lumbar, se envía muestra para estudio de reacción en cadena de la polimerasa (PCR) a enterovirus, y se inicia antibioticoterapia endovenosa. Se traslada a la Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos Pediátricos del hospital de referencia. La evolución es favorable. El cultivo nasofaríngeo y la PCR en líquido cefalorraquídeo son positivos para enterovirus, por lo que se retira la antibioterapia, y se da de alta. Comentarios. La clínica de meningitis en lactantes puede ser muy inespecífica a diferencia de la del niño. El motivo de consulta inicial puede ser decaimiento, vómitos, rechazo del alimento o palidez cutánea, asociados o no a fiebre. La apnea como síntoma inicial aislado de meningitis está poco descrito en la literatura, aunque debe formar parte del diagnóstico diferencial de enfermedades infecciosas. Los enterovirus son el agente etiológico identificado más frecuentemente en meningitis asépticas (80-90%), clínicamente indiferenciables de las meningitis bacterianas. La PCR para enterovirus, con elevada sensibilidad y especificidad, reduce las tasas de hospitalización y tratamiento antibiótico en estos casos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. catalan;70(4): 162-164, jul.-ago. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84771</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Episodio de apnea en un lactante: clínica inicial de meningitis por enterovirus</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8746^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1056^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4849^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8746^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1056^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13513^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13513^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4849^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
