<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88587</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Association between occupational exposure to chalk dust and respiratory tract disease in school teachers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The aim of this study was to evaluate the associations between exposure to chalk dust and respiratory tractsymptoms and diseases in a sample of school teachers.Methods: A cross-sectional study was carried out between January and May 2010, in a sample of 420 teachers of sevenschools from Barcelona, Girona, Navarra and Valencia who answered a self-administrated questionnaire, focused on determinantsof chalk dust occupational exposure, respiratory disorders and demographic variables. We evaluated the associationsbetween six variables related with determinants of chalk dust occupational exposure and seven respiratory tract symptomsand diseases. Odds ratio of prevalence (ORP) and confidence intervals 95% (IC 95%) were calculated using multivariatelogistic regressions to assess the associations, adjusting by the variables sex, age, smoking and body mass index (BMI).Results: Overall survey response rate was 96.7%. The percentage of teachers who used chalk for at least an hour a day was68% and 24% indicated shaking the eraser in class to eliminate the adhered dust. The most prevalent disorders were hoarseness,frequent upper respiratory tract symptoms (FURS) and chronic bronchitis. Shaking and/or frequent use of the eraser and/or using chalk in class was significantly associated with an increased prevalence of wheezing (ORPa=4.04;IC95%=1.73-9.42),frequent respiratory infections (FRI) (ORPa=5.64;IC95%=1.32-24.04), FURS (ORPa=2.42;IC95%=1.33-4.43), and hoarseness(ORPa=1.75;IC95%=1.01-3.04). The prevalence of wheezing, FRI, FURS and hoarseness decreased with age.Conclusions: Respiratory disorders are associated with exposure to chalk dust among teachers. The inverse relationshipwith age for wheezing, FRI, FURS and hoarseness suggests a selection effect, and justifies research to determine whetherteachers are leaving the profession because of respiratory health(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Delclós Clancheta, Jordi L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramada Rodilla, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zock, Jan-Paul</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Haar, Rudolf van der</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serra Pujadas, Consol</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar la asociación entre la exposición a polvo de tiza y trastornos respiratoriosen un colectivo de maestros.Métodos: Estudio transversal realizado entre enero y mayo de 2010 a una muestra de 420 maestros de siete colegios delas provincias de Barcelona, Girona, Navarra y Valencia que contestaron un cuestionario auto-cumplimentado sobre factoresdeterminantes de la exposición a polvo de tiza y trastornos respiratorios. Se evaluaron las asociaciones entre seis variablesindicadoras de exposición a polvo de tiza y siete variables relacionadas con efectos adversos sobre el aparato respiratorio.Se calcularon odds ratio de prevalencia (ORP) e intervalos de confianza del 95% (IC95%) mediante regresión logísticamultivariada, ajustando por las variables sexo, edad, hábito tabáquico e índice de masa corporal.Resultados: La tasa de respuesta fue del 96,7%. El 68% de los maestros usaban tiza durante al menos una hora al díay un 24% sacudía el borrador en clase. Los trastornos más prevalentes fueron afonía, sintomatología frecuente de vías altas(SFRS) y bronquitis crónica. Sacudir y/o usar frecuentemente el borrador y/o usar tiza en clase se asoció significativamentea una mayor prevalencia de sibilancias (ORPa=4,04; IC95%=1,73-9,42), infecciones respiratorias frecuentes (IRF)(ORPa=5,64; IC95%=1,32-24,04), SFRS (ORPa=2,42; IC95%=1,33-4,43) y afonía (ORPa=1,75; IC95%=1,01-3,04). Parasibilancias, IRF, SFRS y afonía la prevalencia disminuyó con la edad.Conclusiones: Los trastornos respiratorios se asocian a la exposición al polvo de tiza. La relación inversa con la edadpara sibilancias, IRF, SFRS y afonía sugiere un efecto de selección, debiéndose investigar si hay maestros que abandonan laprofesión por motivos de salud respiratoria(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. prev. riesgos labor. (Ed. impr.);14(2): 88-95, abr.-jun. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88587</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asociación entre la exposición laboral a polvo de tiza y patología respiratoria en maestros de escuelas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7784^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12542^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32400^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
