<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74626</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Frontal sinus fracture treatment and complications</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Frontal sinus fractures are caused by highvelocity impacts. Inappropriate treatment can lead to seriouscomplications, even many years after the trauma. Objectives. Toevaluate epidemiological data and associated complications. Tostandardize the treatment protocol. Materials and methods. theclinical records of 95 patients with frontal sinus fractures treatedbetween January 1990 and December 2004 at the Oral andMaxillofacial Surgery Department, &#147;12 de Octubre&#148; Hospital (Madrid,Spain), were reviewed. Results. The average age of patients withfrontal sinus fractures was 34 years. Most of them were male (78%)and the most frequent mode of injury was motor vehicle accident.The commonest frontal sinus fracture pattern was the outer tablefracture. The complications described were: cosmetic deformation,frontal sinusitis, frontal mucocele, orbital cellulitis, intolerance ofosteosynthesis material, meningitis and persistent CSF leak.Conclusions. Treatment of frontal sinus fractures must be tailoredfor each individual patient. Its aim should be to reduce associatedcomplications, which may need a long-term follow-up to be detected(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castrillo Tambay, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montalvo Moreno, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zubillaga Rodríguez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heredero Jung, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Aniceto, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las fracturas de seno frontal se producen comoresultado de impactos de alta energía. Un tratamiento inadecuado puedeconducir a complicaciones serias incluso muchos años después del traumatismo.Objetivos. Evaluar los datos epidemiológicos y revisar las complicacionesasociadas. Estandarizar el protocolo de tratamiento. Materialesy métodos. Se revisaron 95 pacientes diagnosticados de fracturas deseno frontal pertenecientes al servicio de Cirugía Oral y Maxilofacial delHospital Universitario 12 de Octubre de Madrid, entre enero de 1990 ydiciembre de 2004. Resultados. La edad media de los pacientes revisadoses de 34 años. La mayoría son hombres (78%) y la causa más frecuente deltraumatismo, los accidentes de tráfico. El patrón de fractura más comúnes el que afecta únicamente a la pared anterior del seno frontal. Las complicacionesdescritas son: deformidad estética frontal, sinusitis frontal, mucocelefrontal, celulitis fronto-orbitaria, intolerancia al material de osteosíntesis,complicaciones infecciosas del SNC y persistencia de fístula de líquidocefalorraquídeo. Conclusiones. El objetivo ha de estar encaminado aprevenir las complicaciones asociadas a los pacientes con fracturas de senofrontal. Hay que individualizar el protocolo de tratamiento en cada caso.Es recomendable un seguimiento a largo plazo para identificar precozmentelas posibles complicaciones(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;29(3): 145-153, mayo-jun. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74626</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento y complicaciones de las fracturas de seno frontal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5762^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13268^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
