<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165488</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacy of cognitive rehabilitation of attention, executive functions, and working memory in psychotic disorders: A systematic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cognitive impairment is a core aspect of schizophrenia. Studies have postulated that it is the basis of the disease as evidenced by its independent and persistent quality and its relation to prognosis. Research on cognitive deficits in psychotic disorders has led to the development of intervention strategies for the cognitive rehabilitation of these patients. Attention, working memory, and executive functions are among the most widely affected functions and are closely related to the functionality of these patients. This work aims to study the effectiveness of cognitive rehabilitation targeting attention, executive functions, and working memory in people diagnosed with a psychotic disorder (mostly schizophrenia). An exhaustive search in PubMed and PsycINFO was conducted up to January 2016. All research papers that were included studied a therapeutic technique to improve one or more of the aforementioned functions in patients over age 16 years diagnosed with psychotic disorder. Studies with methodological diversity were included, which were afterwards organized by levels of evidence. Thirty-four papers were studied, from which we can conclude that cognitive rehabilitation of the aforementioned cognitive functions brings about improvements in cognition. As a result of the influence of cognitive rehabilitation on other variables such as social functioning and symptoms of the disease, the results are promising (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ríos-Lago, Marcos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidal-Mariño, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lubrini, Genny</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Blanco, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los déficits cognitivos se consideran una parte primaria de la esquizofrenia y se postula que puedan estar en la base de la enfermedad dado su carácter independiente, persistente y determinante en el pronóstico. Paralelamente al desarrollo de los estudios de investigación sobre los déficits cognitivos en los trastornos psicóticos, se han ido desarrollando estrategias de intervención para la rehabilitación cognitiva de estos pacientes. La atención, la memoria operativa y las funciones ejecutivas están entre las funciones más afectadas, y se encuentran íntimamente relacionadas con la funcionalidad de estos pacientes. El objetivo de este trabajo fue estudiar la eficacia de la rehabilitación cognitiva de la atención, funciones ejecutivas y memoria operativa en personas diagnosticadas de trastorno psicótico (principalmente la esquizofrenia). Para ello se realizó una búsqueda electrónica exhaustiva en las bases de datos PubMed y PsycINFO hasta enero de 2016 y se seleccionaron los artículos que estudiaban una técnica terapéutica orientada a la mejoría de una o varias de las funciones mencionadas, en pacientes mayores de 16 años diagnosticados de trastorno psicótico. Se seleccionaron estudios con diversidad metodológica que posteriormente se organizaron según su nivel de evidencia. Finalmente se estudiaron 34 artículos de los que se puede extraer que la rehabilitación de las funciones mencionadas produce mejorías a nivel cognitivo. En cuanto a su influencia sobre otras variables como el funcionamiento social y la sintomatología, los resultados son promisorios (AU) </dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;45(4): 167-178, jul.-ago. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165488</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia de la rehabilitación cognitiva de la atención, funciones ejecutivas y memoria operativa en los trastornos psicóticos. Revisión sistemática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
