<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153796</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Placental site trophoblastic tumour: a case report and a review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Placental site trophoblastic tumour is rare, being one of the gestational trophoblastic neoplasms that comprises a group of tumours with potential for local invasion and metastases. We report a case of placental site trophoblastic tumour in a 33 year-old woman. Macroscopically the uterine wall showed a 3.5 × 2.5 cm haemorrhagic soft tumour that occupied almost the entire wall with a perforation point in the fundus. Histologically there was diffuse infiltration of large, polyhedral cells with large, irregular nuclei and occasionally bi- and multinucleated cells. They occurred either individually or in sheets dissecting muscle fibres. Immunohistochemistry revealed CK AE1/AE3, placental lactogen and inhibine but not hCG and p63 expression. Adverse prognostic factors are discussed and the relevant literature is reviewed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gimeno, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almajano, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Adiego, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bengochea, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateos, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tumor trofoblástico del lecho placentario es un tumor infrecuente ubicado dentro del grupo de la neoplasia trofoblástica gestacional, que comprende un grupo de tumores con capacidad de producir invasión local y metástasis. Presentamos un caso de tumor trofoblástico del lecho placentario en una mujer de 33 años. Macroscópicamente la pared uterina presentaba una tumoración de 3,5 × 2,5 cm de aspecto hemorrágico y blando que ocupaba todo su espesor, con un punto de perforación en el fondo. Histológicamente mostraba infiltración difusa de células grandes y poliédricas con núcleos grandes e irregulares con ocasionales células bi y multinucleadas. Se disponían de manera aislada o en masas, disecando fibras musculares. Inmunohistoquímicamente se demostró positividad para CK AE1/AE3, lactógeno placentario e inhibina, y negatividad para hCG y p63. Presentamos una revisión de la literatura y comentarios sobre una serie de factores pronósticos adversos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;49(3): 200-204, jul.-sept. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153796</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumor trofoblástico del lecho placentario. Presentación de un caso y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24738^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31923^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31923^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
