<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137301</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Addiction and endogenous cannabinoid system: the role of cannabinoid receptor CB1 in the mesotelencephalic dopaminergic neurones physiology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The endogenous cannabinoid transmission is a new cell signalling system constituted by the cannabinoid CB-1 and CB2 receptors, as well as by several lipid transmitters including anandamide and 2-arachidonoylglycerol.The cannabinoid receptors are the pharmacological targets of the psychoactive constituents of cannabis sativa preparations, commonly used as illegal recreational drugs. Several lines of research using animal models have established that cannabinoids are drugs that modify the activity of the brain reward system, specially the physiology of mesotelencephalic dopaminergic neurones, in a way that resemble the actions of ethanol or the opiates. The present work analyse the anatomical, biochemical and pharmacological evidences that support the role of the endogenous cannabinoid system as a modulator of dopamine transmission in the brain. Cannabinoid CB-1 receptor are present in both, dopamine receptor-containing neurones and mesencephalic and hypothalamic dopaminergic neurones. Moreover, the pharmacological stimulation of striatal dopamine D-2 receptors is the most potent activator of anandamide release known to date. The released anandamide will act as an endogenous break to the hyperactivity associated with a high dopaminergic output. These findings allow us to propose that drugs which interfere with the endogenous cannabinoid system might be useful as a therapy in that problems where the dopamine system intervene as addictions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodriguez de Fonseca, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El sistema cannabinoide endogeno es un nuevo sistema de comunicación intercelular compuesto por los receptores para cannabinoides CB-1 y CB-2 y varios transmisores lipidicos, que incluyen a la anandamida y el 2-araquidonilglicerol. Los receptores para cannabinoides CB1 y CB2 son la diana farmacológica de los cannabinoides naturales, los compuestos psicoactivos presentes en las preparaciones de Cannabis sativa, que se consumen como droga ilegal. La investigacion en modelos animales ha constatado que los cannabinoides inducen cambios en los sistemas cerebrales de recompensa, en especial sobre las neuronas dopaminérgicas mesotelencefálicas, equiparables a los que inducen otras drogas como los opiáceos y el etanol. El presente trabajo analiza las evidencias anatómicas, bioquímicas y farmacológicas que apoyan el papel del sistema cannabinoide endógeno en la modulación de la transmisión dopaminérgica. El receptor CB1 no sólo se localiza en las neuronas que expresan receptores para dopamina, sino que se expresa también en células dopaminéricas del mesencéfalo y el hipotálamo. La estimulación de los receptores para dopamina D2 es, además, el estímulo más potente capaz de liberar anandamida que se ha descrito hasta la fecha. La liberación de anandamida bloquearía la hiperactividad comportamental asociada a un exceso de señal dopaminergica. Estos hallazgos permiten esperar que fármacos capaces de interferir con el sistema cannabinoide endógeno puedan ser útiles en la terapéutica de procesos con participación dopaminérgica como la adicción a drogas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);12(supl.2): 83-95, 2000. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137301</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adicción y sistema cannabinoide endógeno: papel del receptor para cannabinoides CB1 en la fisiología de las neuronas dopaminérgicas mesotelencefálicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38269^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30236^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38329^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54418^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
