<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132364</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sternoclavicular septic arthritis: a series of 5 cases and review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Infectious arthritis is a medical emergency whose prognosis, in terms of general morbidity and the final functionality of the joint, depends on rapid diagnosis and treatment. The sternoclavicular joint is an area of low prevalence of this type of arthritis, although its frequency is often concentrated in immunosuppressed patients, users of parenteral drugs or after traumatic events. We present a series of 5 microbiologically documented cases of sternoclavicular septic arthritis, 3 of which occurred in immunocompetent patients, and a short review of this pathology (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carballo, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aranda García, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casa Resino, Cristina de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zea Mendoza, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carpena Zafrilla, MAría</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roldan Moll, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillén Astete, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Braña Cardeñosa, Adela</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La artritis infecciosa es una urgencia médica de cuyo rápido diagnóstico depende el pronóstico a corto y medio plazo del estado general del paciente y de la funcionalidad final de la articulación. La articulación esternoclavicular es una región de baja prevalencia de este tipo de artritis, aunque su frecuencia se suele concentrar en pacientes inmunosuprimidos, usuarios de drogas parenterales o tras procedimientos traumáticos. Presentamos una serie de 5 casos microbiológicamente documentados de artritis infecciosa esternoclavicular, 3 de los cuales se presentaron en pacientes inmunocompetentes, y una revisión de esta peculiar enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);11(1): 48-51, ene.-feb. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132364</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Artritis infecciosa esternoclavicular: serie de 5 casos y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23949^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3050^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23949^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23949^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23949^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13596^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13621^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13621^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13621^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13621^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d673^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23949^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
