<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041862</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Guide for the clinical management of osteoarthritis of the hip and the knee</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Guides of clinical practice can help to take evidencebasedand patient-focused decisions. However, these mustnot be understood as strict rules, but as recommendationsbased on clinical effectiveness studies. The physician is inthe best position to decide between the different therapeuticoptions available for each individual patient.These guides are based on the updated review of themedical literature, combined with the opinion of experts inthe relevant field.Different guides have been published recently for themanagement of osteoarthritis of the hip and the knee thathelp the physician to decide the best treatment for the patientswith such condition. Despite being based on thesame evidences, recommendations issued by different workgroups are in disagreement.This work has aimed to review the current clinical managementof osteoarthritis of the hip and the knee, as wellas to identify its optimum approach according to the evidence-based medicine</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Bustamante, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morgado, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moguer, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, A. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres, L. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las guías de práctica clínica son importantes a la horade tomar decisiones basadas en la evidencia y centradasen el paciente, no debiéndose interpretar como mandatosrígidos sino como recomendaciones basadas en estudiosde efectividad clínica, siendo el médico quien está en lamejor situación a la hora de decidir entre las distintasaproximaciones terapéuticas para cada uno de sus pacientes.Estas guías surgen de la revisión actualizada de la literaturamédica en combinación con la opinión de los expertosen la materia.Recientemente han sido publicadas varias guías para elmanejo de la artrosis de cadera y rodilla con el objeto deayudar al clínico en el tratamiento de pacientes con tal patología;a pesar de basarse en una misma evidencia, existenpuntos discrepantes en las recomendaciones hechaspor distintos grupos de trabajo.El objetivo de este trabajo es revisar el manejo clínicoactual de la artrosis de cadera y rodilla así como identificarel abordaje óptimo de la misma en función de la medicinabasada en la evidencia</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;12(5): 289-302, jun.-jul. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041862</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Guía de manejo clínico de la artrosis de cadera y rodilla</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33759^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d86^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27938^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30165^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23791^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
