<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145453</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The goal of treatment is to achieve sterilization of the tuberculous lesion in the shortest possible time in order to minimize the possibility of development of resistant organisms. A 6-month regimen consisting of isoniazid, rifampin and pyrazinamide for the first 2 months and isoniazid and rifampin for the remaining 4 months is recommended for treatment of drug-susceptible pulmonary disease. The overall success rate of this regimen has been greater than 98 %, and the incidence of clinically important adverse reactions has been less than 2 %. Careful monthly monitoring of the clinical response to therapy is important in order to assess drug adherence, efficacy and toxic effects of antitubercular drugs. Daily administration of drugs is desirable. However, after the initial 2-week period and when adherence to a regimen is likely to be unreliable, isoniazid and rifampin can be given two or three times a week by directly observed therapy (DOT). When drug resistance is possible, particularly if the child is an immigrant from a country with high prevalence of isoniazid-resistant tuberculosis or the adult source case has risk factors for drug-resistant tuberculosis, initial therapy should include a fourth drug, either ethambutol or streptomycin, until drug susceptibility results are available. For cases of multidrug-resistant tuberculosis, the treatment regimen should include at least 4 antitubercular drugs to which the organism is susceptible and duration of therapy usually is extended to at least 12 to 24 months. In these cases, daily DOT is critical to prevent emergence of further resistance (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Baquero-Artigao, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del tratamiento antituberculoso es conseguir la negatividad de los cultivos en el menor tiempo posible para prevenir la aparición de resistencias. El tratamiento de elección consiste en la asociación de isoniazida, rifampicina y pirazinamida durante 2 meses continuando con isoniazida y rifampicina durante cuatro meses más. Esta pauta consigue tasas de curación del 98% con frecuencias de recidivas tardías inferiores al 2 %. Se deben realizar controles clínicos mensuales para asegurar el correcto cumplimiento, detectar la aparición de efectos secundarios y comprobar la eficacia del tratamiento. Es preferible la administración diaria de los fármacos. Sin embargo, si el riesgo de incumplimiento terapéutico es alto, y siempre después de la segunda semana de tratamiento, se pueden administrar los fármacos dos o tres veces por semana mediante terapia directamente observada (TDO). En pacientes con riesgo de tuberculosis resistente, especialmente si se trata de inmigrantes procedentes de países con altas tasas de resistencia o si el caso índice es fármaco resistente o sospechoso de serlo, el tratamiento inicial debe incluir un cuarto fármaco, estreptomicina o etambutol, hasta que se conozca la sensibilidad de M. tuberculosis. En los casos con tuberculosis multirresistente, el tratamiento debe incluir al menos cuatro fármacos con sensibilidad comprobada frente a la cepa aislada, y la duración del tratamiento debe alargarse al menos 12-24 meses. Además se recomienda realizar TDO diario para asegurar la adherencia al tratamiento y prevenir la aparición de nuevas resistencias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);66(supl.2): 52-62, mayo 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145453</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de la tuberculosis pulmonar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7705^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12705^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30997^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23466^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5069^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14798^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d999^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12154^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
