<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101724</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hypokaliemia: diagnostic approach in Pediatrics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hypokalemia, defined as plasma concentration of potassium below 3.5 mEq/L, is a commonly found clinical condition. Acute and transient hypokalemia usually results from changes in the internal potassium distribution. Chronic hypokalemia is secondary to a negative external balance caused by increased losses of potassium by feces or urine. An algorithm for the diagnosis of hypokalemia of renal origin in pediatric population is presented here on the basis of values of blood pressure, circulating concentrations of aldosterone and renin and the status of acid-base equilibrium (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santos, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hipopotasemia, definida como una concentración plasmática de potasio, inferior a 3,4 mEq/L, es una situación frecuente en clínica. De forma aguda y transitoria, se produce habitualmente como resultado de cambios en al distribución del potasio interno. La hipopotasemia crónica suele ser secundaria a un balance externo negativo por aumento de las pérdidas de potasio por heces u orina. Se presenta un algoritmo que permite orientar el diagnóstico de la hipokalemia de origen renal en población infantil en  base a los valores de tensión arterial, los valores circulantes de renina y aldosterona y el estado del equilibrio ácido-base (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;67(6): 354-357, nov.-dic. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101724</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hipopotasemia: aproximación diagnostico en Pediatría</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1822^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29553^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d453^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7186^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12506^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d144^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d143^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
