<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114996</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anxiety. A review from Mishel's theory</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Anxiety is an emotional response resulting from the anticipation of a perceived danger or threat. Its function is to activate and facilitate the response of an individual, being possible to get to the situation where it interferes with the individual´s capacity to overcome difficulties when the anxiety levels are high and persistent. Uncertainty may generate anxiety as it can decrease the ability of an individual to adapt and cope with a situation. Given that our purpose is to contribute to the dissemination of nursing models and to provide elements for critical reflection, the aims of this theorization are focused on the conceptualization of the terms discussed and on the analysis of the evidence-based practice found in the literature approaching the knowledge obtained from the theoretical sources of nursing to the practice so that it can develop under ethical, theoretical and philosophical relationships in which care emphasize the person as a whole (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Renedo, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferré, Carme</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ricart, Maite</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torrents, Roser</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferreiro, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lleixà, Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La ansiedad es una reacción emocional ante la percepción de peligro o amenaza caracterizada por ser anticipatoria, activadora y facilitadora de la respuesta del individuo, pudiendo llegar a interferir en su capacidad para superar las dificultades, situación o entorno causantes si esta ansiedad es elevada y persistente. La incertidumbre genera ansiedad, ya que puede disminuir la capacidad de afrontamiento y adaptación del individuo. Teniendo como finalidad el interés en contribuir a la diseminación de los modelos de enfermería y aportar elementos para la reflexión crítica, los objetivos de la presente Teorización se centran en la conceptualización de los términos abordados y en el análisis de la práctica evidenciada en la literatura acercando el conocimiento de las fuentes teóricas a la práctica enfermera para que ésta pueda desarrollarse bajo unas relaciones éticas, teóricas y filosóficas donde los cuidados pongan énfasis en la totalidad de la persona (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;22(1/2): 60-64, ene.-jun. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114996</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ansiedad en los cuidados. Una mirada desde el modelo de Mishel</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5932^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37587</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5084</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32094^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
