<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89056</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Abdominal compartment syndrome in vascular surgery: management and bibliographic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION. The abdominal compartmental syndrome (SCA) is a complication that associates an important morbi-mortality in the vascular patient. The objective of our paper is to review the scientific bibliography in order to modernize rules of management of the SCA and the associated consequences. MATERIAL AND METHODS. We reviewed the scientific literature of the  last years that deal with diagnosis and therapeutic of the SCA. We used the data base of the National Library of Medicine (PubMed). The study was limited to articles published in 10 last years, in English and Spanish language that they have an abstract on-line. The key words introduced for the search was abdominal compartment symdrome, vascular surgery, ruptured aneurysm. RESULTS. With these parameters we found 84 works, 46 of them makes direct reference to our aim while the 38 remaining works were discarded by not adjusting to the purpose of the search. 16 of them were analyzed. CONCLUSIONS. The vascular patient presents high risk in order to develop the SCA for it would be monitorized the intraabdominal pressure in the unit of intensive cares after the surgery. The surgical decompression should reserve for those patient with refractory SCA  to the medical treatment, using a system of vacuum assisted closure (VAC) whenever it is possible (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salvador, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrera, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castambide, M. V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brizuela, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Revilla, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Fajardo, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mengíbar, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">INTRODUCCIÓN. El síndrome compartimental abdominal (SCA) continúa siendo actualmente una complicación que asocia una importante morbi-mortalidad en el paciente vascular. El objetivo de nuestro trabajo es revisar la bibliografía científica para actualizar pautas de manejo del SCA y las consecuencias asociadas. MATERIAL Y MÉTODOS. Se realizó una revisión de la literatura  científica de los últimos años que versa sobre el manejo diagnóstico y terapéutico del SCA además del abdomen abierto tras laparotomía descompresiva. Para ello se utilizó la base de datos de la Nacional Library of Medicine (PubMed). El estudio se limitó a trabajos publicados en los últimos 10 años en inglés y español que dispusieran de abstract on-line. Las palabras clave introducidas para la búsqueda fueron abdominal compartment symdrome, vascular surgery, ruptured aneurysm. RESULTADOS. Con dichos parámetros de búsqueda aparecen 84 trabajos de los cuales, 46 de ellos hacen referencia  directa o indirecta mientras que los 38 trabajos restantes fueron desechados por no ajustarse a la finalidad de la búsqueda. De los trabajos recogidos se analizaron detenidamente 16 de ellos, a los cuales se hace referencia en el artículo de acuerdo al orden de aparición. CONCLUSIONES. El paciente sometido a cirugía vascular abdominal presenta alto riesgo para desarrollar el SCA por ello se debería monitorizar la presión intraabdominal en el ingreso en la unidad de cuidados intensivos tras la cirugía. La descompresión quirúrgica debería reservarse para aquellos pacientes con SCA refractario al tratamiento médico intensificado, utilizando un sistema de cierre asistido por vacío (VAC) como primera elección siempre que fuera  posible (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;13(4): 179-182, oct.-dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89056</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome compartimental abodominal en cirugía vascular: manejo y revisión bibliográfica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3192^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36498^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30855^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7991^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33112^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
