<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057791</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A review of the characteristics of the Constant-Murley score</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To review the characteristics and properties of the Constant-Murley score, one of the most frequently used tests to measure shoulder function. Detailed knowledge about this score will enable clinicians and researchers to gain a better understanding of its value.         Search strategy. Searches were carried out in PubMed, Embase, Pedro, and Dare to select all articles that compare different tests or discuss the use of the Constant-Murley score.         Results. Since its conception, the test has suffered from methodological deficits: it is not completely standardized; it has not been validated; and its use is questionable in certain cases.         Conclusions. The lack of standardization makes it mandatory for researchers to provide detailed information about the methodology employed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barra-López, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Revisar las características y propiedades del test de Constant-Murley, uno de los más utilizados en la bibliografía para medir la función del hombro. Su conocimiento detallado permitirá, a los clínicos o investigadores que lo utilicen, una mejor comprensión de su valía.         Estrategia de búsqueda. Se han realizado búsquedas en PubMed, Embase, Pedro y Dare y se han seleccionado todos los artículos que comparaban varios tests o aportaban opiniones sobre el uso del test de Constant-Murley.         Resultados. El test adolece, desde su formulación original, de algún déficit metodológico, no está completamente estandarizado, no ha sido validado y su uso es cuestionado en determinados casos.         Conclusiones. La falta de estandarización obliga a que los investigadores que lo utilicen informen detalladamente de la metodología seguida en su caso</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);41(5): 228-235, sep.2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057791</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El test de Constant-Murley. Una revisión de sus características</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13167^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29097^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29834^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15294</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
