<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76298</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The adult age in the medical field is reached at 16 years, acquiring the capacity then, ingeneral, to make autonomous decisions. Between 12 and 16 years, however, minors can maketheir own decisions if they meet the conditions of sufficient maturity. While none of the mentionedsituations happens, the parents will replace the child in the decisions. It may happen,however, that parents are in disagreement between them towards the decision to be taken underthese conditions, due to the situation of lack of understanding between them in their personallives. It should be noted that in case of separation or divorce one parent has the custody, but both retain normally parental authority and therefore both have the right and obligationof caring for the child&#146;s health, their common child. It may happen; too, that the child wants tomake a decision that is detrimental to his own interest. The interest of the child is always preferredover any other conflicting interest and the doctor may have to ultimately assume the roleof ombudsman of the child, invoking, if necessary, judicial assistance. The doctor is in thedifficult position of deciding whether the child is capable of taking his/her own decisions, dueto his/her age or maturity, if is the decision of the parents the one to prevail, or if, finally, becomingthe guarantor of the minor&#146;s health, has to go to court. Anything but easy is the rolethe doctor has to assume in these cases(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Siso Martín, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La mayoría de edad en el terreno sanitario se alcanza a los 16 años. Se adquiere entoncesla capacidad, con carácter general, para tomar decisiones autónomas. Entre los 12 y los16 años, sin embargo, el menor puede tomar sus propias decisiones si reúne las condicionesde madurez suficientes. Mientras que no sucede una de las situaciones mencionadas, sonlos padres quienes sustituyen la voluntad del menor. Puede ocurrir, sin embargo, que lospadres estén en desacuerdo respecto de la decisión que tomar en estas condiciones por la situaciónde desencuentro personal que viven. Conviene tener en cuenta que, en caso de separacióno divorcio, uno de ellos tiene la custodia, pero ambos conservan, normalmente, lapatria potestad y, por ello, los dos tienen el derecho y la obligación de cuidar la salud delmenor, hijo común. Puede ocurrir también que el menor quiera tomar una decisión que eslesiva a sus intereses. El interés del menor es siempre preferente sobre cualquier otro enconflicto, y el médico puede tener que llegar a asumir el papel de defensor del menor, invocando,si es preciso, el auxilio judicial. El médico se encuentra en la difícil situación de decidirsi atiende la voluntad del menor por creerle capaz por edad o madurez; si debe seguir ladecisión de los padres y, en caso de desacuerdo entre ellos, a cuál ha de atender; o si, porúltimo, a ninguno hace caso y, convirtiéndose en garante de la salud del menor, ha de acudira la justicia. El papel que asume el médico en estos casos resulta cualquier cosa menosfácil(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;11(44): 685-693, oct.-dic. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76298</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El médico, el paciente menor y los padres de éste. Un triángulo que debe ser amoroso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5323</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29636</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2697^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2697^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2697^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2697^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29907</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
