<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100863</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study aims to determine the understanding of nurses working at a sentry hospital of adverse events, to identify the most frequent events and the actions taken by the institution for the safety of care, from the viewpoint of nurses. This is a descriptive, exploratory study conducted during 2009 in a teaching hospital in the Midwest with 50 nurses who answered to a questionnaire. The data were analyzed statistically, featuring the absolute and relative frequencies. Adverse events most frequently cited were hospital infection, medication error, trauma during the procedure, pressure ulcers, falls and burns. Most of them understand the concept of adverse events, though some have pointed out the difficulties. All of them recognized the risks and noted the adoption of measures for monitoring and evaluating the service to improve health care practice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tanferri de Brito Paranaguá, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Queiroz Bezerra, A. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Queiroz, E dos S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Weber, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente estudio tiene como objetivo determinar la comprensión de las enfermeras que trabajan en un hospital centinela de eventos adversos, identificar los eventos más frecuentes y las medidas adoptadas por la institución para la seguridad de la atención, desde el punto de vista de las enfermeras. Estudio descriptivo, exploratorio, realizado durante el año 2009 en un hospital universitario en el Medio Oeste con 50 enfermeras que respondieron a un cuestionario. Los datos se analizaron estadísticamente, con las frecuencias absolutas y relativas. Los eventos adversos más frecuentes fueron las infecciones hospitalarias, error de medicación, trauma durante procedimientos, úlceras por presión, caídas y quemaduras. La mayoría comprende el concepto de eventos adversos, aunque algunos han señalado las dificultades. Todos reconocieron los riesgos y señalaron la adopción de medidas de acompañamiento y evaluación del servicio para mejorar la práctica asistencial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;11(27): 186-197, jul. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100863</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reacciones adversas: indicadores de resultados según la percepción de las enfermeras de un hospital centinela</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6940^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6940^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16859</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2088^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10662</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201207</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
