<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150957</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Study of anesthesia in ambulatory surgery procedures used in área III y and IV of the community of Cantabria</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Anesthetic aspects of Ambulatory Surgery (AS) tend not precisely detailed in the official statistics of health activity. Usually in Spain and its different regions ambulatory surgical activity is known, but without providing data anesthetics. They administered anesthetic techniques for surgical procedures in the context of the various specialties CMA carried out in the area III and IV of SCS for the years 2013 and 2014 were collected. Anesthetic activity was first analyzed, and their relationship with ASA (scale of anesthetic risk) second. Globally, a clear predominance of Monitored Anesthesia Monitoring (VAM), which represents 65% of casuistry is observed. This is the anesthetic technique of choice in ophthalmology procedures (specialty with an important weight in the total of patients CMA), and comorbidities. The second most used technique was general anesthesia (GA) about 23% presenting similar percentages technique endotracheal intubation AG with respect to the LMA. The sum of regional blocks represented 10% of the total, resulting spinal anesthesia variety most commonly used with 6.8 and 7% respectively for the years 2013 and 2014. The choice of anesthetic technique will be based patient intervention and our own organizational capacity taking into account at all times the cost-effectiveness of drugs and equipment used in its development (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez,  J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cagigas, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nicolás, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ochoa, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez Aja, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bóver, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velasco,  R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cagigas Roecker, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcano, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bolado, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los aspectos anestésicos de la Cirugía Mayor Ambulatoria (CMA) no suelen detallarse con precisión en las estadísticas oficiales de actividad sanitaria. Generalmente en España y en sus distintas comunidades autónomas se conoce la actividad quirúrgica ambulatoria, pero sin proporcionar datos anestésicos. Se recogieron las técnicas anestésicas administradas para procedimientos quirúrgicos en régimen de CMA de las distintas especialidades llevadas a cabo en el área III y IV del SCS durante los años 2013 y 2014. Se analizaron la actividad anestésica en primer lugar, y su relación con el ASA (escala de riesgo anestésico) en segundo lugar. De manera global, se observa un claro predominio de la Vigilancia Anestésica Monitorizada (VAM), que representa un 65% de la casuística. Esta técnica anestésica es la de elección en los procedimientos de oftalmología (especialidad con un peso importante en el total de pacientes de CMA), y con comorbilidades asociadas. La segunda técnica más utilizada fue la Anestesia General (AG) alrededor del 23% presentando porcentajes similares la técnica de AG con intubación orotraqueal respecto a la mascarilla laríngea. La suma de las anestesias locorregionales supuso un 10% del total, resultando la anestesia intradural la variedad más utilizada con un 6,8 y 7% respectivamente durante los años 2013 y 2014. La elección de la técnica anestésica se hará en función del paciente, de la intervención y de nuestra propia capacidad organizativa teniendo en cuenta en todo momento el coste-beneficio de los fármacos y del equipo empleados en su desarrollo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;19(1): 13-19, 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150957</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de los procedimientos de anesthesia en CMA utilizados en Área III y IV de la comunidad de Cantabria en 2013-2014</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
