<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61365</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Severe tubulo-interstitial nephritis secondary to 5-ASA</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report a new case of chronic interstitial nephritis in a patient with ulcerative colitis diagnosed in 2002 who was originally treated with 5-ASA. Three years later deterioration of renal function was apparent with an increase in serum creatinine, which was normal before treatment. Withdrawal of 5-ASA led to partial improvement of renal function. In patients with a delayed diagnosis of kidney damage, recovery of renal function is incomplete and, in some cases, the patient even requires some form of renal replacement therapy. We stress the importance of monitoring renal function in patients diagnosed with inflammatory bowel disease treated with this drug(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bosque López, M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido Durán, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vanrell Garau, Margalida</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ginard Vicens, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Munar Vila, M. Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mariño Méndez, Zoe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gayà Cantallops, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos un nuevo caso de nefritis intersticial crónica de una paciente con colitis ulcerosa diagnosticada en 2002, que desde el principio fue tratada con 5-ASA. Tres años más tarde apareció un deterioro de la función renal con un incremento de los valores de creatinina sérica, los cuales eran normales antes del tratamiento. La función renal mejoró parcialmente tras la supresión del tratamiento. En los pacientes con un retraso en el diagnóstico del daño renal, la recuperación de la función renal no es completa, e incluso, en algunos casos, el paciente necesita alguna forma de terapia de reemplazo renal. Queremos recordar la importancia del registro de la función renal en pacientes diagnosticados de enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal en tratamiento con este fármaco(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;32(1): 29-31, ene. 2009. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61365</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nefropatía tubulointersticial grave secundaria a 5-ASA</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33400^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33400^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29505</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27938^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27938^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9588^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23971^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200901</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
