<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-26627</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Healthcare personnal training in a healthcare district to respond to an industrial disaster. Asturias, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: In order to provide a response to industrial accidents with a view to minimizing their consequences, the healthcare personnel working in areas at risk must be properly trained. This study is aimed at determining the degree of subjective perception that healthcare professional have with regard to how well-prepared they are to take action in response to an industrial accident resulting in a large number of injuries, as well as their knowledge of industrial hazards inherent to the area. Methods: A questionnaire was designed to measure five dimensions related to the response to industrial accidents (technical knowledge, knowledge of the Area, practical skills, attitudes and training). The sample was comprised of all of the Primary Care physicians and nursing staff in the District and from the Emergency Department at the related hospital. Results: The response rate was 61.2%. The results for the questions related to each dimension, on a maximum scale of 4, were: Technical skills (µ=1.3;&amp;#61540;=0.81); Knowledge of the District (µ=0.75;&amp;#61540;=0.96); Practical skills (µ=0.9; &amp;#61540;=0.8); Attitudes (µ=3.25; &amp;#61540;=0.73) and Training (µ=0.75; &amp;#61540;=0.88). Those working in hospital emergency departments and those hired under indefinite or temporary contracts scored higher than those employed under permanent contracts. Conclusions: Information and training is lacking among these healthcare professionals, contrasting with the interest shown in correcting these lacks. It is necessary for a basic training and information program to be set up in order to deal with industrial disasters in our Healthcare District (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ministerio de Sanidad y Consumo</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: Para responder a los accidentes industriales, de cara a minimizar sus consecuencias, es necesaria una correcta preparación del personal sanitario que trabaja en zonas de riesgo. El objetivo de este estudio es establecer el grado de percepción subjetiva que tienen los profesionales sanitarios sobre su preparación para actuar en un accidente industrial con múltiples víctimas, así como su conocimiento sobre los riesgos industriales propios de la zona. Métodos: Se diseñó un cuestionario para medir cinco dimensiones relacionadas con la respuesta ante accidentes industriales (conocimiento técnicos, conocimientos del Área, habilidades prácticas, actitudes y formación). La muestra estaba formada por todos los médicos y personal de enfermería de Atención Primaria del Área y del Servicio de Urgencias del hospital de referencia. Resultados: La tasa de respuesta fue del 61,2 por ciento. Los resultados en las cuestiones de cada dimensión, con un valor máximo de 4, fueron: Conocimientos técnicos (µ=1,3; =0,81); Conocimientos del Área (µ=0,75; d=0,96); Habilidades prácticas (µ=0,9; =0,8); Actitudes (µ=3,25; =0,73); y Formación (µ=0,75; =0,88). Obtienen mejores puntuaciones los trabajadores del servicio de urgencias hospitalario y aquellos con contratos indefinidos o temporales, por encima de los trabajadores con contrato fijo. Conclusiones: Existe un déficit de información y de formación entre los profesionales sanitarios que contrasta con el interés mostrado por subsanar estas carencias. Es necesario establecer un programa de información y formación básica para responder ante desastres industriales en nuestra Área de Salud (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;77(5): 639-655, sept. 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Preparación del personal sanitario en un área de saludde asturias altamente industrializada para responder ante un desastre industrial</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Castro Delgado, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuartas Álvarez, Tatiana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arcos González, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-26627</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4249</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2435</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7395</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
