<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154807</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Chronic pain after breast surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Breast surgery is one of the paradigms of chronic post-surgical pain. The high incidence of breast cancer and the remarkable improvements in survival rates achieved in recent years, have made of chronic pain after breast surgery a problem of increasing magnitude. Our knowledge of risk factors for the development of chronic pain in these patients has increased. Amongst them, the presence of pain before surgery, the age (higher incidence with decreased age), axillary dissection or radiotherapy, must be highlighted. The most frequently involved tissue injury is damage to the intercostobrachial nerve. In terms of strategies to reduce this complication, the scientific evidence is still low and suffers from methodological deficiencies. The use of regional techniques in the perioperative period, like paravertebral block, consistently appears to decrease the incidence of chronic pain after breast surgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nieto Mouronte, CM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La cirugía sobre la mama constituye uno de los paradigmas del dolor crónico postquirúrgico. La elevada incidencia del cáncer de mama y las notables mejoras en la supervivencia alcanzadas en los últimos años se traducen en que el dolor crónico tras cirugía de mama se haya convertido en un problema de creciente magnitud. Ha aumentado nuestro conocimiento de los factores de riesgo para el desarrollo de dolor crónico en estos pacientes. Entre los mismos destacan la presencia de dolor antes de la intervención, la edad (mayor incidencia cuanta menor edad), disección axilar, radioterapia, etc. La lesión tisular más frecuentemente implicada es el clan sobre el nervio intercostobraquial. En cuanto a las estrategias para intentar disminuir esta complicación, la evidencia científica es todavía escasa y adolece de problemas metodológicos. La utilización de técnicas regionales en el periodo perioperatorio, como el bloqueo paravertebral, parece disminuir de manera consistente la incidencia de dolor crónico tras cirugía de mama (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;19(1): 18-23, ene.-mar. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154807</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dolor cronico tras cirugía de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54522^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8580^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
