<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124640</identifier>
<setSpec>2173-4712</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The reduction of prejudice towards Gypsies in real life: Effects of visiting the exhibition</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Gypsy population is one of the groups that are most discriminated against in Spain. In this research, we studied the impact of the visit to the exhibition Vidas Gitanas (Gypsy Lives) on undergraduate students' prejudice towards Gypsies. This exhibition was organized with the aim of providing a realistic vision of this population and its culture and to alleviate the lack of knowledge about the reality of Gypsies. In this study 91 participants were exposed to one of two different conditions: visiting the exhibition or control group. Participants showed a better evaluation of Gypsies after visiting the exposition than before. Moreover, compared to the control group, participants who visited the exhibition showed a better evaluation and a greater inclusion of Gypsies within the superordinate social category "Spaniards". These results are discussed in the light of different strategies on prejudice reduction (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Willis, Guillermo B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urbiola, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moya, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Romero, Josefa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La población gitana es uno de los grupos más discriminados en España. En esta investigación se examina el impacto en estudiantes universitarios de la visita a la exposición Vidas Gitanas sobre el prejuicio hacia los gitanos. Esta exposición pretende ofrecer una visión realista de este pueblo y de su cultura para paliar la falta de conocimiento sobre la realidad del pueblo gitano. Los participantes (N = 91) fueron divididos en dos condiciones: visita a la exposición vs. grupo control. Los resultados mostraron que los participantes evaluaron mejor a los gitanos después de visitar la exposición que antes. Asimismo, en comparación con el grupo control, los participantes que visitaron la exposición mostraron una evaluación más positiva y una mayor inclusión de los gitanos en la categoría social supraordenada "españoles". Dichos resultados son discutidos a la luz de las diferentes estrategias de reducción del prejuicio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Interv. psicosoc. (Internet);23(1): 11-16, ene.-abr. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124640</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La reducción del prejuicio hacia la población gitana en la vida real: Efectos de la visita a la exposición "Vidas Gitanas (Lungo Drom)"</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11724</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13304</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55088</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23896</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55086</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13628</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23908</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12261</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
