<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163596</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Educational intervention to improve eating practices and psysical activity in elementary schools of Quintana Roo</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: It has been shown that education is an important social health determinant. An educational intervention aimed at changing eating habits and physical activity in school children can help to prevent childhood overweight and obesity. Objective: The effect of an educational intervention on eating practices and physical activity of school children in the state of Quintana Roo was evaluated. Methods: An educational intervention based on playful learning activities was performed in 131 schools in the state of Quintana Roo. To assess its effect on eating practices and physical activity, a longitudinal study was performed in 5 schools (intervention group), chosen at random, and one school as a control. Results: Four out of the five schools significantly reduced the percentage of energy adequacy for the school snack in relation to the control (p &lt; 0.001). In relation to the time practicing exercise during break time, a difference between the control school and three schools in the intervention group (p &lt; 0.05) was observed. Conclusions: The results of the educational intervention suggest an improvement in eating practices and physical activity in the schools implementing the intervention (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Fernández, Teresita del Niños Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vivas Rodríguez, Gabriela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macías Gómez, Andrea</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suinaga Martín del CampoColumba</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aedo Santos, María de los Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: Se ha demostrado que la educación es un determinante social fundamental de la salud, por lo que una intervención educativa encaminada al cambio de hábitos de alimentación y actividad física en los escolares puede contribuir a prevenir el sobrepeso y la obesidad infantil. Objetivo: Se evaluó el efecto de una intervención educativa sobre las prácticas de alimentación y actividad física de escolares del estado de Quintana Roo. Métodos: Se llevó a cabo una intervención educativa basada en resolver actividades lúdicas de aprendizaje, en 131 escuelas del estado de Quintana Roo. Para evaluar su efecto sobre las prácticas de alimentación y actividad física, se realizó un estudio longitudinal en 5 escuelas pertenecientes al programa, elegidas al azar, y una escuela control. Resultados: Cuatro de las cinco escuelas redujeron significativamente el porcentaje de adecuación de energía del refrigerio escolar respecto a la escuela control (p &lt; 0,001). En cuanto al tiempo que hacen ejercicio durante el recreo, al final se observó que existían diferencias entre la escuela control y tres de las escuelas del grupo de intervención (p &lt; 0,05). Conclusiones: Los resultados de la intervención educativa sugieren una mejora de las prácticas de alimentación y de actividad física en las escuelas donde se llevó a cabo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;21(4): 9-16, oct.-dic. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163596</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervención educativa para la mejora de prácticas de alimentación y actividad física en escuelas primarias del estado de Quintana Roo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32270^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5350^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12953^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32270^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2698^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50311</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
