<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76865</identifier>
<setSpec>0556-6177</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endometriosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Endometriosis is a common gynaecological disease of unknown aetiologywhich affects an estimated 10% to 15% of all premenopausal women.It is defi ned as the presence of endometrial tissue, consisting of bothglandular epithelium and stroma, outside the uterine cavity.Three different clinical entities of endometriosis can be distinguished:peritoneal endometriosis, ovarian endometriosis and deep invasiveendometriosis. There are several theories to explain their pathogenesis:metaplasia of the mesothelium, in situ development of Müllerianremnants in the rectovaginal area (deep-invasive lesions) or retrogradetransplantation of shed menstrual effl uent (peritoneal implants). Themost widely accepted hypothesis for the development of endometriosisis retrograde menstruation. However, some other factor renders certainwomen susceptible to the implantation and growth of this ectopicendometrium (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aubá, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olartecoechea, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Royo Manero, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Manero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La endometriosis es una de las enfermedades más enigmáticas queafecta a las mujeres en edad reproductiva. Esta enfermedad se defi ne porla presencia de tejido endometrial (epitelio glandular y estroma) fuerade la cavidad uterina, localizándose habitualmente sobre la superfi cieperitoneal y sobre el ovario. Desde un punto de vista epidemiologico,se describen varios factores de riesgo como la edad, las caracteristicasreproductivas, los habitos personales y los factores hereditarios comodirectamente relacionados con el desarrollo de la enfermedad.En la actualidad existen cuatro teorías para explicar la patogénesis dela endometriosis: metaplasia celómica, restos de células embrionarias,diseminación linfática y vascular y trasplante de tejido endometrial.Sin embargo, no podemos concluir que conozcamos el origen de laenfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Med Univ Navarra;53(2): 4-7, jun. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76865</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Endometriosis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4794^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4794^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
