<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038651</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Calcifying odontogenic cyst associated with complex odontoma: Case report and review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report a calcifying odontogenic cyst associated with odontoma(COCaO) and an included permanent canine in the superiormaxilla, in a 19 year-old-man.The calcifying odontogenic cyst (COC) was first described asa distinct entity by Gorlin et al in 1962.The lesion is a mixed odontogenic benign tumor, and althoughmost of the cases present cystic characteristics, a few are of thesolid type (15%), and its rare malignant transformation is welldocumented.The COC may occur in association with other odontogenictumors, the most common is the odontoma, occurring in about24% of the cases. For this association the term Odontocalcifyingodontogenic cyst has been suggested.Radiographically is a well defined mixed lesion and histologicallyconsists of a large cyst. In the central area of the cyst enameland dentin deposits can be found, irregularly distributed in areasand in other parts it takes on a well defined organoid aspect.A thorough review of literature takes place and the pathogenesisis discussed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gallana Alvarez, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Gómez, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayorga Jimenez, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Avellá Vecino, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salazar Fernandez, Clara</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta un caso de quiste odontogénico calcificante asociadocon odontoma (QOCaO) y con un canino permanente incluidoen maxilar superior, en un paciente varón de 19 años.El Quiste Odontogénico Calcificante (QOC) fue descrito porprimera vez cómo una entidad patológica por Gorlin y col. en1962.Se trata de un tumor benigno odontogénico mixto,y aunquela mayoria de estas lesiones presentan características quísticasen algunos casos se presenta como una masa sólida (15 %), ysu transformación maligna está bien documentada. El QOC sepresenta en ocasiones asociado a otros tumores odontogénicos,el más común es el odontoma al que aparece relacionado en el24% de los casos. Para esta asociación se ha sugerido el términode &#132;Quiste Odontogénico Odontocalcificante&#137;.Radiológicamente es una lesión mixta, bien definida y quehistológicamente consiste en un gran quiste en cuya parte centralexiste un área sólida con acúmulos de esmalte y dentinadistribuidos irregularmente en algunas zonas y en otros lugaresadopta un aspecto organoide bien definido.Se efectúa una revisión de la literatura y se discute su patogénesis</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);10(3): 243-247, mayo-jul. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038651</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Quiste odontogénico calcificante asociado con odontoma complejo: Presentación de un caso y revisión bibliográfica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31239^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24274^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d783</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24273^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
