<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057962</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Trends in obesity, diabetes mellitus, hypertension and hypercholesterolemia in Spain (1997-2003)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: To evaluate the trend in the prevalence in Spain of obesity, diabetes mellitus, hypertension and hypercholesterolemia. Material and method: The Spanish National Health Surveys (ENS) of 1997, 2001, 2003, which select representative samples of the Spanish general population were used. In total, 49,113 participants of both sexes were included. Self-reported data about weight and height were used to estimate the body mass index. The prevalence of diabetes, hypertension and hypercholesterolemia was estimated. Linear trend *2 tests and multivariate logistic regression models adjusted for age, sex and educational level, were estimated. Results: A significant increasing temporal trend for the prevalence of obesity, diabetes, hypertension and hypercholesterolemia was found for the studied period (1997-2003) according to the ENS. We found that the increased trend in obesity prevalence was restricted to younger participants with a significant interaction. Conclusions: The prevalence of obesity, diabetes mellitus, hypertension and hypercholesterolemia has increased in Spain between 1997 and 2003</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez, J. Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seguí-Gómez, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-González, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bes-Rastrollo, Maira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Basterra-Gortari, F. Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Forga, Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Evaluar la tendencia de la prevalencia en España de la obesidad, diabetes mellitus, hipertensión e hipercolesterolemia. Material y método: Se usaron las Encuestas Nacionales de Salud (ENS) de 1997, 2001 y 2003, todas ellas representativas de la población española. Sumando las bases de datos se valoró en total a 49.113 personas de ambos sexos. Para calcular el índice de masa corporal se usó la información referente al peso y la talla autorreferidos. Se estimó la prevalencia de diabetes, hipertensión e hipercolesterolemia. Se realizaron tests de la *2 de tendencia lineal y regresiones logísticas multivariantes para ajustar por edad, sexo y nivel educativo. Resultados: Se estimó una tendencia temporal significativa de incremento de la prevalencia de obesidad, diabetes, hipertensión arterial e hipercolesterolemia en el período estudiado (1997-2003). Se observó que el incremento de la prevalencia de obesidad sólo afecta a los participantes más jóvenes, con una interacción significativa. Conclusiones: La prevalencia de obesidad, diabetes mellitus, hipertensión e hipercolesterolemia ha aumentado en España entre los años 1997 y 2003</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);129(11): 405-408, sept. 2007. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057962</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tendencias de la obesidad, diabetes mellitus, hipertensión e hipercolesterolemia en España (1997-2003)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
