<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72304</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quantitative test to distinguish spinal fluid from saline solution in combined spinalepidural anesthesia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: To validate the use of a digital bloodglucose meter for detecting the presence of spinal fluidduring combined spinal-epidural anesthesia in terms ofspecificity, positive and negative predictive values, andlikelihood ratios.PATIENTS AND METHODS: Validation was studied in 30patients scheduled for surgery under combined spinalepiduralanesthesia. A positive finding, defined asdetection of spinal fluid return or aspiration by theepidural or spinal needle, was compared with results ofstandard reference tests (the pattern of sensory or motorblock after administration of the local anesthetic). Afterlocating the epidural space with saline solution, the testwas performed and 3 mL of local anesthetic wasadministered. If no sensory or motor blockade wasevident, the test was considered a true negative. Spinalpuncture was then performed, the test was repeated, and2 to 3 mL of local anesthetic was injected. The test wasconsidered a true positive if sensory or motor blockadewas evident. These findings entered into the validationanalyses.RESULTS: Sensitivity was 100%, specificity 94%,positive predictive value 93%, negative predictive value100%, the positive likelihood ratio 15.5, and negativelikelihood 0.CONCLUSION: Blood glucose meter readings provide avalid quantitative measure for distinguishing spinal fluidfrom saline solution during combined spinal-epiduralanesthesia. The method, which uses a readily availabledevice, is easy to use to rule out the presence of spinalfluid(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gallen Martín, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Morillo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Hernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solaz Roldán, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soliveres Ripoll, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balaguer Doménech, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVOS: Proponer la utilización de un glucómetrodigital como método cuantitativo sencillo para detectarlíquido cefalorraquídeo durante la técnica de anestesiacombinada epidural-intradural y determinar su validez,a través de la sensibilidad, especificidad, valores predictivosy cocientes de probabilidad.PACIENTES Y MÉTODOS: Se realizó el estudio de validezdel test en 30 pacientes programados para cirugía conanestesia combinada intradural-epidural. Se consideróun resultado positivo si había glucosa en el líquido querefluía o se aspiraba a través de la aguja epidural eintradural, y se contrastaba con un patrón de referencia(las características del bloqueo sensitivo o motor tras laadministración de anestésico local). Tras localizar elespacio epidural con solución salina, se realizaba el testy se administraban 3 mL de anestésico local. Si no habíabloqueo sensitivo o motor, el test se consideraba verdaderonegativo. Se realizaba la punción dural, se realizabael test y se administraban 2-3 mL de anestésico local.En este caso si había bloqueo sensitivo o motor el test seconsideraba verdadero positivo. Con todo ello se realizóel análisis de validez.RESULTADOS: La sensibilidad del test fue del 100%, suespecificidad del 94%, el valor predictivo positivo de93%, y el valor predictivo negativo de 100%, la razón deprobabilidad positiva de 15,5 y la negativa de 0.CONCLUSIÓN: El glucómetro utilizado es un métodocuantitativo válido para diferenciar líquido cefalorraquídeode solución salina durante la anestesia combinada,de uso sencillo y fácilmente disponible, con una granutilidad para confirmar o descartar la presencia delíquido cefalorraquídeo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;56(4): 206-211, abr. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72304</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Método cuantitativo para distinguir el líquido cefalorraquídeo de la solución salina en la anestesia combinada intradural-epidural</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13060^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d786^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d778^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4448^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4904^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2594^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23461</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7593^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6091^s22043</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d783^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6091^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24296^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23461^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
