<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95032</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sexuality, communication and emotions: A situational study in women affected by gynecologic cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: gynecological cancer and its treatment regimes profoundly affect several quality-of-life domains such as sexuality. Our study identifies main sexual symptoms and some factors related to sexual dysfunction. Method: We interviewed women affected by ovarian, endometrial, cervical or vulvar cancer treated in our centre. Women answered a questionnaire on sociodemographic data, the Hospital Anxiety Depression Scale to evaluate emotional adjustment and the Woman Sexual Functioning Questionnaire to detect sexual symptoms. Results: One third of all women (34%) had quieted sexual relations for cancer-related reasons. Sexually active women at the time of interview experienced the following symptoms: low lubrication (62,5%), low frequency of relations (57,8%) and poor sexual desire (57,8%); difficulties with excitation (62,5%), orgasm (39,1) and penetration (34,4%). Sexual functioning diminishes with depression (p=0,002) and anxiety. Longer time free of treatment tends to improve SF (p=0,045). No significant difference4s of SF were observed depending on cancer site, disease stage, age and menopause status. Conclusions: gynecologic cancer and its treatments profoundly affect sexuality. Most of women expressed their wish to be better informed. Further research should clarify the role of specific treatments (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palli, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lluch, Jun</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valero, Sergi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El cáncer ginecológico y sus tratamientos pueden alterar profundamente distintos aspectos de la calidad de vida de las mujeres afectadas, entre ellos, su vida sexual. Nuestro estudio detecta los principales síntomas sexuales e identifica algunos factores que influyen en la posible afectación sexual. Método: Participaron en el estudio mujeres afectadas de cáncer de ovario, endometrio, cérvix, vagina o vulva y tratadas en nuestro centro, respondiendo un cuestionario sobre datos sociodemográficos, la escala HADS para valorar el ajuste emocional y el cuestionario sobre datos socio demográficos, la escala HADS para valorar el ajuste emocional y el cuestionario Función sexual de la Mujer (FSM) para detectar sintomatología sexual. Resultados: un tercio (34%) de las mujeres abandonaron las relaciones sexuales por causas relacionadas con el cáncer. Las mujeres activas sexualmente en el momento de la entrevista sufrían los siguientes síntomas: lubricación escasa 862,5%), baja frecuencia de relaciones escasa (62,5%), baja frecuencia de relaciones (57,8%) y pobre deseo (57,8%); dificultades por la excitación (62,5%), el orgasmo (39,1) y la penetración (34,4%). El funcionamiento sexual disminuye con la depresión (p=0,0002) y la ansiedad. A mayor tiempo libre de tratamiento, mayor es la recuperación de la sexualidad (p=0,045). No se detectan diferencias significativas en el funcionamiento sexual en función de la localización del tumor, el estadio de la enfermedad y la presencia de menopausia antes del diagnóstico del cáncer. Conclusiones: el cáncer ginecológico y sus tratamientos alteran considerablemente la sexualidad de las mujeres afectadas. La mayoría de las mujeres expresaron su deseo de tener más información. La investigación futura debería aclara el papel de los tratamientos específicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);7(1): 153-173, jun. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95032</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sexualidad, comunicación y emociones: estudio situacional con mujeres afectadas de cáncer ginecológico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2623^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15029^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33534^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5969^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
