<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77912</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0316</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Spain is one of the European countries with the highestrates of traffic accidents, this accounting for the first causeof mortality among young people between 15 and 29 yearsof age. Traffic accidents reach impressive figures surpassingdeaths caused by epidemics. As Simonn "the car hasreplaced the microbe as an agent of morbidity and mortality."Medico-legal aspects of assistance in traffic accidentsare an important issue at present due to its important legalimplications and legal. The performance of the professionalsinvolved in the same condition to a large extent the successor failure of the medical-legal investigation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Durán, E. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Quintosa, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Fumadó, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amores Ruiz, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">España es uno de los países europeos con mayores tasasde accidentes de tráfico, los cuales suponen la primeracausa de mortalidad entre los jóvenes entre 15 y 29 años.Los accidentes de tráfico alcanzan cifras impresionantessuperando las víctimas mortales causadas por epidemias.Como dijo Simonn &#147;el automóvil ha venido a reemplazar almicrobio como agente de morbilidad y mortalidad&#148;. Losaspectosmédico-legales de la asistencia en los accidentes detráfico son un tema relevante en la actualidad debido a susimportantes implicaciones jurídicas y legales. La actuaciónde los profesionales que intervienen en los mismos condicionanen gran medida el éxito o fracaso en la investigaciónmédico-legal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Puesta día urgenc. emerg. catastr;8(1): 14-20, ene.-mar. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77912</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Accidentes de tráfico. Actuación de los serviciossanitarios y la investigaciónmédico-legal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5688</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
