<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-15535</identifier>
<setSpec>1136-4890</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Glycidic components expressed in the intestinal epithelium of teratomas are similar to those presented in both tumoral and inflammatory intestinal disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this work we used several different lectins to determine the glycidic components that appear in the prismatic intestinal epithelium of teratomas along the development. These tumoral masses show structures derived from the three blastodermic layers and usually present transdifferentiative processes. Many authors have reported glycoproteic changes in malignant processes of the colonic epithelium, attending to many environmental influences, but the development of this kind of tumour does not appear to be influenced by these factors. The present data show that many of the glycidic components expressed in the prismatic intestinal epithelium of teratomas are very similar to those observed in this mucosa in both tumoral and inflammatory disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sociedad Anatómica Española</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este trabajo usamos diferentes lectinas para determinar los componentes glicídicos que aparecen en el epitelio prismático intestinal de teratomas a lo largo del desarrollo. Estas masas tumorales muestran estructuras derivadas de las tres hojas blastodérmicas y normalmente presentan procesos de transdiferenciación. Muchos autores han referido cambios glicoproteicos en procesos malignos del epitelio del colon atendiendo a muchas influencias ambientales, pero el desarrollo de esta clase de tumores no parece estar influenciado por estos factores. Los datos presentes muestran que muchos de los componentes glicídicos expresados en el epitelio intestinal prismático de los teratomas son muy similares a los observados en esta mucosa en la enfermedad inflamatoria y tumoral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Eur. j. anat;4(3): 191-197, dic. 2000. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los componentes glicídicos expresados en el epitelio intestinal de los teratomas son similares a los presentes en la enfermedad intestinal inflamatoria y tumoral</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Fernández Trujillo, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Verástegui, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, M Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrando, Amor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prada, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-15535</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d24373</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14102</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22940^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7576^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8042</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
