<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140272</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-6585</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fixed implant-supported rehabilitation in edentulous patients. A 2-year study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The aim of this study was to report the clinical outcomes of treatment of edentulous patients with fixed prostheses supported with dental implants. Methods: 20 patients were treated with 248 Galimplant® external connection and sandblasted and acid-etched surface implants for fixed rehabilitation. Implants were loaded after a healing freeloading period of 2 months. The follow-up were at least 24 months. Results: 145 implants were inserted in maxilla and 103 implants in mandible. 27 fixed rehabilitations, 15 maxillary and 12 mandibular were realized. 100% of patients were restored with cemented fixed prostheses. Clinical results indicate a survival and success rate of implants of 98.4%. 4 implants were lost during the healing period. After a mean functioning period of 27.3 months, no late complications were reported. Conclusions: This study indicate that treatment with fixed protheses by dental implants in edentulous patients constitute a successful treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz Prada, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Castro, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galarza Estebaranz, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Fontal, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El objetivo del presente estudio era mostrar los resultados clínicos del tratamiento con una rehabilitación fija mediante implantes dentales en pacientes edéntulos totales. Métodos: Veinte pacientes fueron tratados con 248 implantes Galimplant® de conexión externa y con superficie arenada y grabada para la rehabilitación fija. Los implantes fueron cargados después de un periodo de cicatrización de 2 meses. El seguimiento clínico fue al menos de 24 meses. Resultados: 145 implantes fueron insertados en el maxilar superior y 103 implantes en la mandíbula. Se realizaron 27 rehabilitaciones fijas, 15 maxilares y 12 mandibulares. El 100% de las prótesis realizadas fueron cementadas. Los hallazgos clínicos indican una supervivencia y éxito de los implantes del 98,4%. Cuatro implantes se perdieron durante el periodo de cicatrización. Después de un periodo medio de carga funcional de 27,3 meses, no ha habido complicaciones tardías. Conclusiones: Este estudio indica que el tratamiento con una rehabilitación fija mediante implantes dentales en pacientes edéntulos constituye una terapéutica con éxito (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. periodoncia implantol. oral;27(3): 135-144, dic. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140272</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La rehabilitación fija sobre implantes en pacientes edéntulos totales. Un estudio a dos años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24600^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33384^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15343^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29433^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13897^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13897^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29433^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28145^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24600^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
