<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158584</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: To describe the profile of the overactive bladder (OAB) patient on treatment with flexible-dose antimuscarinic treatment in daily clinical practice. METHODS: This was an observational, retrospective and multicenter study, carried out at 88 public and private hospitals. Adult patients diagnosed with OAB who initiated flexible-dose antimuscarinic treatment. Type of  antimuscarinic, dose, concomitant treatments, treatment benefit and treatment adherence were recorded. RESULTS: This was a pluripathological (83.5%) and polymedicated (73.4%) population, comprised of 846 patients, mostly women (74.5%) with a mean (SD) age of 61.3 (12.1) years and more than one year of OAB evolution. Main initially prescribed antimuscarinics were fesoterodine (66.5%) and solifenacine (30.0%). Overall, 68.2% of the patients started treatment with the low dosage; at the follow-up visit 47.0% changed the dosage (84.2% increased the dosage, 15.8% decreased the dosage). Patients who changed the dosage showed a significantly greater morbidity, worse OAB symptoms, greater health resources use, and worse adherence to treatment compared with those that maintained the high dosage all the time. CONCLUSION: No differences were found regarding the demographic or clinical characteristics that allow us to identify which patients should receive the different options of available dose of antimuscarinic drugs, although greater benefits seem to be achieved with the use of the highest or the lowest dose from the outset than with the change of dose (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Mediero, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Ballester, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arumi, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sobrón-Bustamante, Marcos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lizarraga, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Describir en el entorno de la práctica clínica diaria, el perfil del paciente con vejiga hiperactiva (VH) tratado con dosis flexible de antimuscarícos. MÉTODOS: Estudio observacional, retrospectivo y multicéntrico llevado a cabo en 88 Hospitales públicos y privados. Se incluyeron pacientes adultos, diagnosticados de VH que iniciaron tratamiento con algún antimuscarínico a dosis flexible. Se recogió tipo de antimuscarínico, dosis, tratamientos concomitantes, beneficio aportado y cumplimiento terapéutico.  RESULTADOS: Población constituida por 846 pacientes mayores de 60 años, pluripatológica (83,5%) y polimedicada (73,4%), formada mayoritariamente por mujeres (74,5%) y con más de un año de evolución de la VH. Principales antimuscarínicos inicialmente prescritos: fesoterodina (66,9%) y solifenacina (31,0%). El 68,2% de los pacientes iniciaron el tratamiento con la dosis baja. En la visita de seguimiento, el 47,0% modificó dosis (84,2% aumentaron la dosis, 15,8% disminuyeron la dosis). Los grupos que tuvieron que modificar dosis presentaron significativamente mayor morbilidad, peor sintomatología, mayor empleo de recursos sanitarios y peor cumplimiento terapéutico que el grupo de pacientes tratados siempre a dosis alta. CONCLUSIÓN: En determinados pacientes, el empleo desde el inicio del tratamiento antimuscarínico de dosis- flexible a la dosis más alta, podría proporcionar mayor beneficio terapéutico, adherencia y menor empleo de recursos sanitarios que el escalado de dosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;69(10): 698-707, dic. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158584</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfil del paciente con vejiga hiperactiva tratado con dosis flexible de antimuscarínicos en la práctica clínica diaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50293</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51811^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51811^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32129^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32129^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52129^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52129^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3008^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52129^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3008^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
