<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120709</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ovarian torsion. Long-term follow-up of the black-bluish  ovary after laparoscopic detorsion</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Ovarian torsion presents low incidence in children and unspeci&amp;#64257;c clinical presentation, therefore the diagnostic delay is rather common. Traditionally, necrotic appearance has been synonymous of oophorectomy, however the current trend defends ovary preservation. We present our experience in conservative management of ovarian torsion. Methods. A retrospective review was made of patients between May 2010 and May 2013. Seven girls were operated by laparoscopy because of ultrasound and clinical suspicion of ovarian torsion. The diagnosis was con&amp;#64257;rmed in six patients, &amp;#64257;nding an enlarged, friable and black-bluish ovary. Detorsion and adnexal sparing were performed in all cases, despite the gross appearance. Results. The mean age was 8.5 years (3-12), the time interval between the onset of symptoms to surgery was 6.5 days (1-15) and postoperative stay was 2.6 days (2-3). In 4 cases the damaged ovary was right, and the average size was 5.8 cm. Tumor markers were normal. During the &amp;#64257; rst 6 months the follow-up ultrasound showed good results. However, the long-term outcome evidenced one involved ovary atrophied and two oophorectomies due to recurrent (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garrido Pérez, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vargas Cruz, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lasso Betancor, C. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murcia Pascual, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paredes Esteban, R. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Granero Cendón, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. La torsión ovárica es infrecuente en la edad pediátrica lo que, sumado a su clínica inespecí&amp;#64257;ca, hace que la mayoría de los diagnósticos sean tardíos. La apariencia necrótica del anejo ha sido durante décadas sinónimo de ooforectomía, sin embargo, la tendencia actual de&amp;#64257;ende su preservación. Presentamos nuestra experiencia en el tratamiento conservador de la torsión ovárica. Material y métodos. Revisión de los casos de torsión ovárica aguda tratados en nuestro servicio desde mayo del 2010 hasta mayo del 2013. Siete niñas fueron intervenidas vía laparoscópica por sospecha clínica y ecográ&amp;#64257;ca de torsión ovárica. En seis se con&amp;#64257;rmó el diagnóstico, encontrando un ovario aumentado de tamaño, friable y de coloración negro-azulada. A pesar del aspecto macroscópico se decidió detorsión y preservación del anejo.Resultados. La edad media fue 8,5 años (3-12), el tiempo transcurrido entre el inicio de la clínica y la cirugía fue de 6,5 días (1-15) y la estancia postoperatoria de 2,6 días (2-3). En 4 casos el ovario afecto fue derecho, siendo el tamaño medio de 5,8 cm. Los marcadores tumorales fueron negativos. El seguimiento se efectuó mediante ecografías seriadas y durante los primeros 6 meses existió una evolución favorable. Posteriormente, un ovario quedó atró&amp;#64257;co y en 2 casos se llevó a cabo ooforectomía, una tras dos recidivas de torsión y otra por masa anexial compatible con teratoma. Conclusiones. La detorsión laparoscópica con preservación del anejo permite que ovarios que parecen inviables macroscópicamente puedan recuperarse. No obstante, es necesario un seguimiento exhaustivo y a largo plazo para poder valorar los resultados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;27(1): 26-30, ene.-mar. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120709</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Torsión ovárica. Evolución del ovario necróticotras detorsión laparoscópica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10227^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54689^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52916</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9527^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
