<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99899</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">An experimental study of bone cement penetration in total knee arthroplasty depending on cementing technique used</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the distribution and penetration of the cement mantle in knee arthroplasty depending on technique used. Material and method: Parts were cemented in the second and fifth minute using two techniques: digital pressurization (fingerpacking) directly over the model (technique M) or over the implant (technique P). We analyze digitally the photographs of the cemented models determining length of the cement mantle, percentage penetration and mean penetration. Results: The best quality of cement mantle was obtained with the technique M applied in the second minute, which achieved a mean penetration of 4.44 mm and a percentage penetration of 79.36%; technique P in the fifth minute obtained poorer result (2.12 mm and 45.79%), these differences being significant (p = 0.029). The tangential planes (anterior and posterior) proved to be poorer cemented, with a mean penetration of 2 mm. The technique M obtained the longest cement mantle in these two planes (35 mm and 17.9 mm), while tehnique P covered &lt; 50% of the length of the plane (p = 0.01). Conclusions: Fingerpacking pressurization over the bone surface achieves a greater depth and percentage penetration of the cement mantle than cementing over the prosthetic implant. Tangential femoral cuts (anterior and posterior) are fixed unstably if it is cemented over the implant (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Mañanes, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero Martín, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villanueva Martínez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la distribución y penetración del manto de cemento óseo en la artroplastia de rodilla según la técnica de cementación empleada. Material y método: Se cementaron las piezas en el segundo y quinto minuto según dos técnicas: presurización digital directa sobre el modelo (técnica M) o sobre la prótesis (técnica P). Se analizaron digitalmente las fotografías de los modelos cementados, determinando la longitud del manto de cemento, el porcentaje y la media de penetración. Resultados: La mejor calidad del manto de cemento se obtuvo con la técnica M aplicada en el segundo minuto, que logró una penetración media de 4,44 mm y un porcentaje de penetración del 79,36%; la técnica P en el quinto minuto tuvo el peor resultado (2,12 mm y 45,79%), siendo estas diferencias significativas (p=0,029). Los planos de corte tangencial (anterior y posterior) resultaron ser los peor cementados, con una media de penetración de 2 mm. La técnica M consiguió la mayor longitud de cemento en estos dos planos (35 mm y 17,9 mm), mientras que la técnica P cubrió menos del 50% de la longitud del corte (p=0,01). Conclusión: La cementación con presurización digital sobre la superficie ósea consigue mayor profundidad y porcentaje de penetración que la cementación sobre la prótesis. Los cortes femorales tangenciales (anterior y posterior) se cementan de forma precaria si se aplica sobre el implante (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);23(1): 48-58, ene.-mar. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99899</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio experimental sobre el patrón de penetración del cemento óseo en la artroplastia de rodilla según la técnica de cementación empleada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1868^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1868^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28573</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
