<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040753</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-2597</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Passive smoking and childhood asthma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Environmental tobacco smoke represents a significant        risk for children health. The role of passive smoking habit        in exposed children suffering from asthma is to be studied.        Patients and methods: A retrospective matched casecontrol        study is conducted in 835 children, who are distributed        in groups according to their age and sex. Acontrol is        randomly chosen per each case, thus matching 482 children.        The following factors were analyzed: living with smokers,        living with an usual smoking mother, usual presence of smokers        at home during pregnancy, and maternal smoking habit during pregnancy. Data are arranged in 2x2 tables. &amp;#967;2 Mantel-        Haenszel test is conducted. Odds ratio, with a 95% confidence        interval, and ethiological risk fraction are calculated        for each one of the studied factors.        Results: Our study does not show significant association        between usual presence of smokers at home and higher        childhood asthma frequency. However, having an usual        smoking mother &#150;specially if she smokes during pregnancy&#150;        and her living with smokers during this period, do associate        significantly with this pathology.        Conclusions: Our study reveals the risk that implies the        exposure to tobacco smoke for the development of childhood        asthma, demonstrating a higher prevalence of asthma        in children of smoking mothers &#150;particularly if they smoked        during pregnancy&#150; and perhaps contributing to trigger        bronchial obstruction in those who were exposed to other        people smoking habit during that period</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romo Melgar, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Melgar del Arco, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salazar Alonso-Villalobos, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romo Cortina, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El humo ambiental del tabaco es un riesgo significativo        para la salud de los niños pequeños. Se pretende estudiar        el papel del tabaquismo pasivo en el padecimiento de asma        en niños expuestos al mismo.        Material y métodos: Se realiza un estudio retrospectivo        de casos y controles apareados en 835 niños, distribuidos por        grupos de edad y sexo. Se elige de forma aleatoria un control        por cada caso, realizándose el apareamiento de 482 niños. Se        analizan los siguientes factores: convivencia con fumadores,        cohabitación con una madre fumadora habitual, presencia de        fumadores en el domicilio durante la gestación y tabaquismo        materno durante la misma. Los datos se organizan en        tablas tetracóricas. Se realiza el test &amp;#967;2 de Mantel-Haenszel.        Se calcula la odds ratio, con intervalo de confianza del 95% y        la fracción etiológica del riesgo para cada una de ellas.        Resultados: El estudio no demuestra asociación significativa        entre presencia habitual de fumadores en el domicilio        y mayor frecuencia de asma infantil. En cambio, tener        una madre fumadora habitual &#150;especialmente si fuma        durante la gestación&#150; y la convivencia de aquélla con fumadores        en ese período, sí se asocia significativamente con tal        patología.        Conclusión: Nuestro estudio pone de manifiesto el riesgo        que supone la exposición al humo del tabaco para el desarrollo        del asma infantil, determinando una mayor prevalencia        de asma en los hijos de mujeres fumadoras &#150;sobre        todo si fumaron durante la gestación&#150; y quizás coadyuvando        para desencadenar obstrucción bronquial en los que se expusieron        al tabaquismo de otras personas en ese período</dc:description>
<dc:source>Bol. pediatr;45(193): 185-191, jul.-sept. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040753</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tabaquismo pasivo y asma infantil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30272^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
