<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147060</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Life satisfaction and self-efficacy in wheelchair basketball players</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The main aim of this study was to analyse the relationship between life satisfaction and mobility self-efficacy in wheelchair basketball players. The study was developed with an ex post facto design. 103 people with physical disabilities took part in this study. The measurements were reliable, with high internal consistency. Subjects showed high levels of satisfaction with life and self-efficacy of mobility in a wheelchair. There were no outstanding differences in these variables in relation to the level of sporting excellence. Satisfaction with life was more related to the perception of wheelchair mobility self-efficacy than to age or functional classification as a sportsperson (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Barquín, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega-Marcos, Ricardo de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejero-González, Carlos María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero-Maestre, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del estudio fue analizar la relación entre satisfacción con la vida, y autoeficacia de movilidad en personas con discapacidad física que practican baloncesto en silla de ruedas. El estudio siguió un diseño ex post facto. La muestra fue de 103 participantes. Las mediciones se mostraron fiables, con altos coeficientes de consistencia interna. Los deportistas declararon altos niveles de satisfacción con la vida y de autoeficacia de movilidad en silla de ruedas. No se encontraron diferencias significativas en dichas variables en función del nivel de excelencia competitiva. Se concluye que la satisfacción con la vida está más relacionada con la percepción de autoeficacia de movilidad en silla de ruedas que con la edad o la clasificación funcional de los deportistas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;25(1): 51-56, 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147060</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Satisfacción con la vida y autoeficacia en jugadores de baloncesto en silla de ruedas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6531</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55433^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55433^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33883</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30935^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15310^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
