<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144006</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Measuring precarious employment in times of crisis: the revised Employment Precariousness Scale (EPRES) in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: This study examines the psychometric properties of the revised Employment Precariousness Scale (EPRES-2010) in a context of economic crisis and growing unemployment. Methods: Data correspond to salaried workers with a contract (n=4,750) from the second Psychosocial Work Environment Survey (Spain, 2010). Analyses included acceptability, scale score distributions, Cronbach's alpha coefficient and exploratory factor analysis. Results: Response rates were 80% or above, scores were widely distributed with reductions in floor effects for temporariness among permanent workers and for vulnerability. Cronbach's alpha coefficients were 0.70 or above; exploratory factor analysis confirmed the theoretical allocation of 21 out of 22 items. Conclusion: The revised version of the EPRES demonstrated good metric properties and improved sensitivity to worker vulnerability and employment instability among permanent workers. Furthermore, it was sensitive to increased levels of precariousness in some dimensions despite decreases in others, demonstrating responsiveness to the context of the economic crisis affecting the Spanish labour market (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moncada, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vives, Alejandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llorens, Clara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benach, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Este estudio examina las propiedades psicométricas de la versión revisada de la Escala de Precariedad Laboral (EPRES-2010) en un contexto de crisis económica y creciente desempleo. Métodos: Muestra de personas ocupadas con contrato (n=4750) provenientes de la segunda Encuesta de Riesgos Psicosociales (España, 2010). Se evaluaron la aceptabilidad, la distribución de puntuaciones, la consistencia interna y el análisis factorial exploratorio. Resultados: La aceptabilidad estuvo en torno al 80%, con puntuaciones ampliamente distribuidas y una reducción del efecto suelo para «vulnerabilidad» y «temporalidad». La consistencia interna estuvo en torno a 0,70. El análisis factorial confirmó la pertenencia de 21 de 22 ítems a las escalas correspondientes. Conclusión: La versión revisada de la EPRES demostró adecuadas propiedades psicométricas y mayor sensibilidad para medir la vulnerabilidad, así como la inestabilidad laboral en personas con contrato permanente. Además, fue sensible a incrementos de la precariedad en algunas dimensiones, a pesar de su disminución en otras, demostrando sensibilidad a los profundos cambios ocurridos en el mercado laboral español (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;29(5): 379-382, sept.-oct. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144006</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Medición de la precariedad laboral en tiempos de crisis: versión revisada de la Escala de Precariedad Laboral en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16368</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53789</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16359^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9975^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
