<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167228</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interface terminology as an axis for safe care: on line questionnaire about knowledge and understanding of ATIC(R) nursing interventions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Nursing languages should contribute to obtain ccurate and reliable data to ease effective communication and ensure patients&#146; safety. Interface terminologies like ATIC(R), arise to complement reference terminologies and are intended to guide their use in clinical settings. Moreover, these terminologies provide information regarding healthcare concepts with sufficient clinical specificity, leading to a better understanding among healthcare team members. Objective. To evaluate nurses&#146; level of knowledge and understanding in clinical settings surveillance and control interventions of ATIC terminology(R). Materials and methods. A descriptive, observational, cross-sectional, multicenter study was performed administering a validated electronic questionnaire. Collected data was analyzed using descriptive and inferential statistics. Results. 85 % of nurses favorably assessed their knowledge level about surveillance and control interventions of ATIC terminology (R). Higher levels were achieved by 51.8 % and 32.8 % scored as adequate level. Significant differences were found in knowledge level and length of use of terminology, as well as workplace and attendance to clinical care sessions (CCS). The evaluation of understanding indicates that over 95 % of participants have high (75.8 %) or moderate (20.1 %) understanding levels. Furthermore, we found significant differences in relation to the level of understanding and length of time using ATIC(R) (more than 1 year) together with attendance to CCS. Conclusions. Nurses that use the ATIC Terminology© in electronic health records have a high knowledge and understanding level of surveillance and control interventions. Nurses understand the concepts clearly and accurately, what might be considered as an indirect measurement for reliability of the ATIC intervention axis in terms of usability, enhances at the same time safety in the provision process of care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Adamuz-Tomás, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado-Hito, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Samartino, Maribel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Jiménez, María Magdalena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juvé-Udina, María Eulalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matud Calvo, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tapia Pérez, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los lenguajes enfermeros deben contribuir a obtener datos precisos y fiables que faciliten una comunicación eficaz y garanticen unos cuidados seguros. Las terminologías de interfase, como ATIC(R), surgen para complementar las terminologías de referencia y orientan su desarrollo hacia su uso en la práctica clínica. Además, contribuyen a proporcionar información en relación con los conceptos que representan los cuidados con suficiente especificidad clínica que conlleva a un mejor entendimiento entre los miembros del equipo asistencial. Objetivo. Evaluar el nivel de conocimiento y comprensión de las enfermeras acerca de las intervenciones de vigilancia y control de la terminología ATIC(R). Material y métodos. Estudio descriptivo, observacional, transversal y multicéntrico, mediante un cuestionario electrónico validado. Los datos recogidos se analizaron utilizando estadística descriptiva e inferencial. Resultados. Un 85 % de las enfermeras evalúan favorablemente su nivel de conocimientos sobre las intervenciones de vigilancia y control de la terminología ATIC(R). El 51.8 % refiere un nivel de conocimiento superior y el 32.8 % adecuado. Se identificaron diferencias significativas respecto el nivel de conocimientos y el tiempo de uso de ATIC(R), el lugar de trabajo o la asistencia a sesiones clínicas de cuidados (SCS). La evaluación de la comprensión indica que más del 95 % de las participantes tienen una comprensión elevada (75.8 %) o moderada (20.1 %). Además, se identificaron diferencias significativas en relación con la utilización de ATIC(R) durante más de 1 año y la asistencia a SCC. Conclusiones. Las enfermeras que utilizan la terminología ATIC(R) en los registros electrónicos de salud tienen un elevado nivel de conocimiento y comprensión de las intervenciones de vigilancia y control. Las enfermeras entienden los conceptos de forma clara y precisa, lo que contribuye a establecer la fiabilidad del eje de intervención de esta terminología en términos de usabilidad y aumenta la seguridad del proceso de prestación de cuidados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;40(10): 698-709, oct. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167228</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Una terminología interfase como eje de unos cuidados seguros. Nivel de conocimiento y de comprensión de intervenciones enfermeras ATIC(R)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55139^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10221^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
