<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73338</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Blood pressure targets in various clinical situations in diabetic patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of this paper is to review the evidence that supports therecommendations of the Clinical Practice Guidelines on arterial hypertensionand diabetes mellitus with regard to blood pressure controltargets. Nearly all the Guidelines currently state, with certain nuances,that the targets are to achieve and maintain a systolic blood pressureof &lt;130 mmHg and a diastolic blood pressure of &lt;80 mmHg. Apartfrom certain exceptions &#150;diabetic nephropathy with proteinuria greaterthan 1 g/24 hours is the only one&#150; those targets do not vary accordingto the presence of other pathologies associated with diabetes. Thereview of the clinical trials makes it possible to conclude that bloodpressure lowering is, without a doubt, benefi cial. Nevertheless, even inthe conditions of the clinical trials, which are very far removed from thepractical reality of Primary Health Care, a substantial percentage ofpatients do not achieve the control targets recommended in the guidelines;this is especially true in the case of systolic blood pressure, despitethe use of combinations of two or more antihypertensive drugs(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Figuera von Wichmann, M. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo es revisar las evidencias que avalan las recomendacionesde las guías de práctica clínica sobre la hipertensiónarterial y la diabetes mellitus en relación con los objetivos de controlde la presión arterial (PA). En la actualidad, la práctica totalidad de lasguías coinciden, con algunos matices, en que los objetivos son alcanzary mantener unas cifras de presión arterial sistólica (PAS) &lt;130mmHg y de presión arterial diastólica &lt;80 mmHg. Con alguna excepción(la nefropatía diabética con proteinuria superior a 1 g/24 h es laúnica), estos objetivos no varían en función de la presencia de otraspatologías asociadas a la diabetes. La revisión de los ensayos clínicospermite concluir que la reducción de las cifras de PA es, sin duda, beneficiosa. Sin embargo, incluso en las condiciones de los ensayosclínicos, muy apartadas de la realidad práctica de la atención primaria,un porcentaje considerable de pacientes no alcanzan los objetivos decontrol propuestos en las guías, especialmente de PAS, a pesar de lautilización de combinaciones de dos o más fármacos antihipertensivos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;25(3): 187-191, mayo-jun. 2009. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73338</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Objetivos de presión arterial en diversas situaciones clínicas en pacientes con diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1822^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3951^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
