<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131989</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The quality of life of the users of a community center for elderly</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this investigation we have tried to verify if the assistance to the community centers of major persons is an effective way for the improvement of the major persons's quality of life, that is to say, if the users of the above mentioned centers have a better quality of life that those that do not come to them. For it, we have possessed an experimental group and a group control. Later we have gone on to them to both groups two tests: one that values the quality of life and other one the cognitive deterioration. Once spent the tests and obtained the punctuations we have concluded that the users of the community center have a major quality of life that the subjects that do not come to it (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bugallo Carrera, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gandoy Crego, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Cantorna, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En esta investigación hemos intentado comprobar si la asistencia a los centros sociales de personas mayores es un medio eficaz para la mejora de la calidad de vida de las personas mayores, es decir, si los usuarios de dichos centros tienen una mejor calidad de vida que aquellos que no acuden a ellos. Para ello, hemos contado con un grupo experimental y un grupo control. A continuación ambos grupos han pasado dos pruebas: una que valora la calidad de vida y otra, el deterioro cognitivo. Una vez pasadas las pruebas y obtenidas las puntuaciones, hemos concluido que los usuarios del centro social tienen una mayor calidad de vida que los sujetos que no acuden a él (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);25(3): 103-106, sept. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131989</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La calidad de vida de los sujetos usuarios de un centro social de personas mayores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13036^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24693^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
