<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140739</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Small bowel intussusception in the adult caused by ileal submucous lipoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present the case of a 68 year-old male patient with secondary intestinal intussuspection due to a submucous lipoma of the ileum. This is a rare entity in adults and is usually due to an organic lesion. The clinical manifestation is characterized by vomiting, abdominal pain and melenas. In our case the patient, following a colonoscopy and an abdominal CT-scan, was subjected to an extended resection of caecum and terminal ilium. At present, the precision of the etiological diagnosis of intussuspections has increased thanks to the development of image tests, like CT-scan. Early surgical treatment is recommended, without intraoperative deintussuspection given the high risk of presenting a malign or ischemic lesion in the adult (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hoz, ML de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernando, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arredondo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta el caso de un paciente de 68 años con invaginación intestinal secundaria a un lipoma submucoso de íleon. Se trata de una entidad rara en adultos y que suele ser debida a una lesión orgánica. La manifestación clínica se caracteriza por vómitos, dolor abdominal y melenas. Se presenta el caso de un paciente al que tras la realización de una colonoscopia y un TAC abdominal, se realizó una resección ampliada de ciego e íleon terminal. En la actualidad la precisión del diagnóstico etiológico de las invaginaciones ha aumentado gracias al desarrollo de las pruebas de imagen, como el TAC. Se recomienda un tratamiento quirúrgico precoz, sin desinvaginación intraoperatoria dado el elevado riesgo de presentar una lesión maligna o isquémica en el adulto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;38(2): 343-346, mayo-ago. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140739</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Invaginación de intestino delgado en el adulto causada por lipoma submucoso de íleon</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7604^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7261^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29341^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7604^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7261^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7265^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7578^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15241^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7604^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7261^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7265^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7261^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7578^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
