<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053244</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-0599</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of psychosis with olanzapine in a patient with agenesis of the corpus callosum: an incidental fiding</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The agenesis of the corpues callosum may be asymptomatic in some of the individuals with this brain malformation. Cases about association of the agenesis of the corpus callosum and mental disorders have been reported. We report a case of 31 years old man with the finding of agenesis of the corpus callosum on magnetic resonance and acute psychosis using theICD 10ª diagnostic criteria, successfully treated with olanzapine</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Prieto Barrera, W. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo Iglesias, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La agenesia del cuerpo calloso puede ser asintomática en algunos de los individuos con esta malformación cerebral. Se han descrito casos sobre la asociación de agenesia del cuerpo calloso y enfermedades mentales. Describimos el caso de un varón de 31 años con el hallazgo de agenesia del cuerpo calloso en la resonancia magnética y psicosis aguda según los criterios de la CIE 10, tratada con éxito con olanzapina</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psiquiatr;23(1): 31-33, ene.-feb. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053244</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de psicosis aguda con olanzapina en un paciente con agenesia del cuerpo calloso: un hallazgo incidental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3353^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9614^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
