<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80263</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of hamstring stretching on rectus abdominis muscle activation pattern during trunk flexion and extension</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveTo determine the effects of hamstring stretching (propioceptive neuromuscular propioception) on the muscle activation pattern of rectus abdominis (RA) during trunk flexion and extension.HypothesisRepeated hamstring stretching techniques could either delay or anticipate RA activation during trunk flexion or extension, respectively.MethodologyElectromyography activity of the rectus abdominis and grades of hip flexion during flexion-extension movements of the trunk before and after stretching hamstring muscles was recorded in 11 volunteer subjects. Study variables: RA onset, RA offset (expressed as a percentage of the maximum hip flexion value) and RA average EMG.ResultsThe paired T-test showed significant differences in RA onset and offset before and after stretching (p&lt;0.05).ConclusionAfter prolonged hamstring muscle stretching, the rectus abdominis takes a long time to become activated during trunk flexion and the contraction is shorter. The combined effect of increased laxity of hamstring and altered response of RA after stretching might alter the sensorimotor systems of lumbopelvic region motor control, increasing the risk of injuries(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hermida Marrades, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gonzalo Pallarés, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cervera Gasch, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lisón Párraga, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Zuriaga, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno González, A. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lliberós Torner, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoDeterminar los efectos del estiramiento de las estructuras isquiotibiales mediante técnicas de facilitación neuromuscular propioceptiva sobre el patrón de activación del recto del abdomen durante los movimientos de flexoextensión del tronco.HipótesisEl estiramiento repetido de las estructuras isquiotibiales podría retrasar la activación del recto del abdomen durante la flexión del tronco y adelantarla durante la extensión.MetodologíaSe registraron en 11 sujetos voluntarios la activación electromiográfica del recto del abdomen y los grados de flexión de la cadera durante movimientos de flexoextensión del tronco antes y después de realizar los estiramientos. Las variables de estudio fueron los porcentajes de flexión de la cadera al inicio y al final de la contracción del recto del abdomen y la actividad electromiográfica media del músculo.ResultadosEl t-test mostró que hay diferencias significativas en el inicio y el final de la contracción del recto del abdomen (onset y offset) antes y después del estiramiento (p&lt;0,05).ConclusiónTras un estiramiento prolongado de la musculatura isquiotibial, el recto del abdomen tarda más tiempo en activarse durante la flexión del tronco, y la contracción es de menor duración. El efecto combinado de la laxitud aumentada de las estructuras isquiotibiales y la alteración de la respuesta del recto del abdomen podría alterar los sistemas sensoriomotores de control del movimiento de la región lumbopélvica, aumentando el riesgo de lesiones(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);31(6): 235-240, Nov. - dic. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80263</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos del estiramiento isquiotibial sobre el patrón de activación muscular del recto del abdomen durante la flexoextensión del tronco</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52426^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31090^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4648</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30961^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
