<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057351</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Utility of cystatin-C in hospitalized patients. Comparing with different methods of assessing renal fuction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Serum creatinine is the most widely used parameter to assessing renal function,        even though limitations, some time is necessary meassure 24 h creatinine clearance        (CLcr), or estimate Cockroft-Gault (C-G) or MDRD formulas. Different methods        can offer different results, and cause confusion in clinicians. Using Cystatin-        C as new parameter of renal function could suppose an important improvement.        The objective of our study was to compare the different methods from renal evaluation        and establish the utility of cistatina-C in the hospital area. In the study        were included 70 patients (44 men) selected of random way, predominate patients        with kidney disease and diabetics, which was made CLcr and calculated CG        and MDRD formulas. The mean age of the patients was 66 ± 14years, mean        weight 73 ± 17Kg, creatinine 2,14 ± 1,77 mg/dL, cystatin-c 1,77 ± 1,18 mg/L,        CLcr 54,39 ± 36,2 mL/min. The correlation of 1/Crea with the Clcr, C-G and        MDRD formulas was respectively: 0,7735, 0.8269 and 0.9613, (p  0,05). In conclusion, most of the urine collections could        be avoided with the use of the formulas. Cystatin-c is far beyond the creatinine,        mainly to detect slight renal alteration (sensitivity 80,4% US 44,7% in men) becoming        a promising alternative, that could reduce considerably hidden renal insufficiency        (non detected by creatinine), although more studies are needed to confirm</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Baños, L. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pobes, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cepeda, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La prueba utilizada habitualmente para valorar la función renal es la creatinina        sérica, aunque por sus limitaciones, en muchas ocasiones es necesario recurrir        a la medida del aclaramiento de creatinina en orina de 24 horas (Clcr), la        fórmula de Cockroft-Gault (CG) o la fórmula de Levey (MDRD). Los distintos        métodos pueden dar distintos resultados, creando una situación de confusión a        los clínicos. La introducción de la Cistatina-C como nuevo marcador de función        renal, podría suponer una mejora considerable. El objetivo de nuestro estudio        fue comparar los distintos métodos de valoración renal y establecer la utilidad        de la cistatina-C en el ámbito hospitalario. Fueron incluidos en el estudio 70 pacientes        (44 hombres) seleccionados de manera aleatoria, predominando enfermos        renales y pacientes diabéticos, a los que se les realizó el CLcr y se calculó        CG y MDRD. La edad media de los pacientes fue 66 ± 14años, peso medio        73 ± 17Kg, creatinina 2,14 ± 1,77 mg/dL, cistatina-c 1,77 ± 1,18 mg/L, CLcr        54,39 ± 36,2 mL/min. La correlación entre 1/Crea con el Clcr, CG y MDRD fue        respectivamente: 0,7735, 0,8269 y 0,9613, (p  0,05). En conclusión, la mayoría de las recogidas de orina podrían evitarse        con la utilización de las fórmulas. La Cistatina es muy superior a la creatinina,        sobre todo para detectar leve alteración renal (sensibilidad 80,4% vs 44,7%        en hombres) convirtiéndose en una alternativa prometedora que reduciría a más        de la mitad la IRC oculta generada por la creatinina, aunque se necesitan más        estudios para confirmarlo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;27(2): 168-174, mar.-abr. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057351</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de la cistatina C en el ámbito hospitalario. Comparación con los distintos métodos de valoración renal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6063^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3421^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24594^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
