<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057125</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of a questionnaire on patient satisfaction with the dispensing service in community pharmacies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To analyze the validity and reliability of a patient satisfaction questionnaire about drug dispensing in Argentine community pharmacies.                 Design. Descriptive, cross-sectional study.                 Setting. Community pharmacies of Argentina that voluntarily agreed to take part in the study.                 Participants. All patients or their careers who attended the pharmacies during the period of the study (March and April, 2006) and knew how to read and write.                 Main measurements. Scores on the satisfaction scale of the questionnaire.                 Results. Twenty-seven pharmacies from 6 provinces of Argentina took part; 473 questionnaires were obtained with a 72.4% response rate. Factorial analysis revealed one single component that explained 54.8% of total variance. A 0.90 Cronbach's alpha coefficient was obtained and Pearson's correlation between each of the items and the total score on the scale showed that all items correlated with each other (P&lt;.01). Patients expressed additional comments in 124 questionnaires (26.2%). These concerned the quality of care received and other aspects, such as gratitude, cost of medicines, insufficient stock, and friendliness.                 Conclusions. The questionnaire, in showing evidence of content validity, validity as internal structure, validity related to other variables, and reliability, could assess patient satisfaction with the drug dispensing service in the community pharmacies of Argentina</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Faus Dáder, María J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Pérez, Sebastián R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armando Carle, Pedro D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí Pallarés, Merçè</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Uema, Sonia A. N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solá Uthurry, Nancy H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Analizar la validez y fiabilidad de un cuestionario de satisfacción de pacientes con el servicio de dispensación en las farmacias comunitarias argentinas.                 Diseño. Descriptivo, de corte transversal.                 Emplazamiento. Farmacias comunitarias de Argentina que voluntariamente aceptaron participar en el estudio.                 Participantes. Todos los pacientes o sus cuidadores que concurrieron a las farmacias durante el período de estudio (marzo y abril de 2006) y que supieran leer y escribir.                 Mediciones principales. Puntuaciones de la escala de satisfacción del cuestionario.                 Resultados. Participaron 27 farmacias, pertenecientes a 6 provincias de Argentina. Se consiguieron 473 cuestionarios, con un porcentaje de respuesta del 72,4%. El análisis factorial reveló un único componente que explicaba el 54,8% de la varianza total. Se obtuvo un coeficiente alfa de Cronbach de 0,90 y la correlación de Pearson entre cada uno de los ítems y la puntuación total de la escala mostró que todos los ítems están correlacionados entre sí (p &lt; 0,01). Los pacientes expresaron comentarios adicionales en 124 cuestionarios (26,2%) que se relacionaron con la calidad de la atención recibida y con otros aspectos, tales como agradecimiento, coste de los medicamentos, insuficiente stock y amabilidad.                 Conclusiones. El cuestionario mostró evidencias de la validez de contenido, validez como estructura interna, validez relacionada con otras variables y fiabilidad para valorar la satisfacción de los pacientes con el servicio de dispensación en las farmacias comunitarias argentinas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;39(11): 591-596, nov. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057125</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación de un cuestionario de satisfacción de pacientes con el servicio de dispensación en farmacias comunitarias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32795^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32795^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d284^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10786^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10786^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32795^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
