<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144670</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-7279</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper describes the authors&#146; understanding on intersubjective listening and its importance in order to enlighten the person&#146;s therapeutic process when he is in the context of a psychosocial rehabilitation.  Once the term intersubjectivity is clearly defined, the authors continue explaining the fundamental characteristics of an attitude of listening. This is followed by the beginning of the therapeutic alliance and the importance of promoting a collaborative attitude vs. a hierarchic attitude or relationship.  Then, the authors offer a reflection about the impact that this type of therapeutic intervention, based on the intersubjectivity, could have both for the mental health nertwork and for the professionals that put it in practice.  To finish, the benefits that this model of intervention offer the person user of the service, are mentioned (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso Valcárcel, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Felices de la Fuentes, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se describe lo que los autores entienden por escucha intersubjetiva, y la importancia que ésta tiene para dar sentido al proceso terapéutico del usuario dentro de un contexto de rehabilitación comunitaria.  A la definición del término intersubjetividad le seguirán las características que pensamos son importantes para poder hablar de una actitud de escucha. Se hará hincapié en el comienzo de la relación terapéutica, y la importancia de fomentar una actitud de colaboración versus una actitud o relación jerárquica.  A continuación se reflexionará sobre el impacto que este proceso de escucha basado en la intersubjetividad puede tener para la red de servicios, y para el profesional.  Por último, se mencionarán los beneficios que este modelo de intervención ofrece al usuario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Inf. psiquiátr;(218): 29-38, oct.-dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144670</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dar sentido al proceso de rehabilitación psicosocial: una escucha intesubjetiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33152^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12030^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33152^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9954</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33152^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33152^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12030^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
