<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-37317</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Primary headaches in children with hydrocephalus who have a ventriculoperitoneal bypass valve</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Headache, which is the clinical manifestation of intracranial hypertension, is also a clinical ailment in medical practice, as well as one of the main causes of visits in the paediatric age. Determining whether this symptom is secondary or not to a decompensation of the intracranial pressure in children with hydrocephalus is sometimes a challenging task. The aim of this study is to classify the headaches in a population of children with a ventriculoperitoneal bypass valve due to hydrocephalus. Patients and methods. We conducted a study of a series of cases with a longitudinal follow-up. 20 children with a ventriculoperitoneal bypass valve owing to hydrocephalus were followed up over a mean period of eight months because they suffered from recurring headaches. All of them answered a questionnaire in order to define the characteristics of their headache. Those who were suspected of suffering from intracranial hypertension were submitted to a cerebral tomography study. Results. In all, we studied 20 patients (eight males and 12 females) with a mean age of 8.6 ± 2.8 years. Hydrocephalus was secondary to abnormalities in the craniocervical transition and myelomeningocele in all cases. The aetiology of the headache was primary migraine-type headache (14 patients; 70%), and tension-type headache (two patients; 10%). Secondary headaches appeared in four patients (20%) due to acute sinusitis, refraction errors and systemic infection; only one patient had headache due to intracranial hypertension. Conclusions. Migraine predominates as the primary headache in children with bypass valves &#150;a phenomenon that can be explained by its high prevalence in the paediatric population (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La cefalea, manifestación clínica de la hipertensión intracraneal, es también una queja clínica en la práctica médica y una de las principales causas de consulta en la edad pediátrica. En ocasiones, determinar si este síntoma es secundario o no a una descompensación de la presión intracraneal en niños con hidrocefalia es un desafío. El objetivo de este trabajo es clasificar las cefaleas en una población pediátrica portadora de una válvula de derivación ventriculoperitoneal por hidrocefalia. Pacientes y métodos.  Estudio de una serie de casos con seguimiento longitudinal. Se trata de 20 niños portadores de una válvula de derivación ventriculoperitoneal por hidrocefalia seguidos durante un período medio de ocho meses por presentar cefaleas recurrentes. A todos ellos se les aplicó un cuestionario para definir las características de la cefalea. Aquellos con sospecha clínica de hipertensión intracraneal se sometieron a un estudio mediante tomografía cerebral. Resultados. Se estudiaron 20 pacientes, ocho niños y 12 niñas, con una edad media de 8,6 ñ 2,8 años. La hidrocefalia era secundaria a malformación de la transición craneocervical y mielomeningocele en todos ellos. La etiología de la cefalea fue: cefalea primaria de tipo migrañosa (14 pacientes, 70 por ciento) y cefalea de tipo tensional (dos pacientes, 10 por ciento). Las cefaleas secundarias aparecieron en cuatro pacientes (20 por ciento) debido a sinusopatía aguda, errores de refracción e infección sistémica; tan sólo un paciente presentó cefalea por hipertensión intracraneal. Conclusiones. La migraña predomina como cefalea primaria en niños portadores de válvulas de derivación, fenómeno que puede explicarse por su alta prevalencia en la población pediátrica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;39(12): 1101-1104, dic. 2004. tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cefaleas primarias en niños con hidrocefalia portadores de una válvula de derivación ventriculoperitoneal</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Carod Artal, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palma-da Cunha Matta, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-37317</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d6134</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8994</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9329</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8999</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32124</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31309</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12460</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
