<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94589</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Percutaneous endoscopic gastrostomy: a 7 years experience long-term tube feeding. Follow-up</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Percutaneous endoscopic gastrostomy (PEG) is the first choice method for long-term enteral feeding when the digestive tube is undamaged and the patients&#146; survival is longer than 2 months. There are increasing series and indications reported and although it is a safe technique we should take into account an appropriate patient selection. The aim of this work was to analyze the followup of the patients undergoing percutaneous endoscopic gastrostomy (PEG) at a hospital with high assistance level and one of the referents for organ transplantation in our community, with the peculiarities that this may have on our series. We analyze a cohort of 73 patients submitted to PEG during the years 2000-2007 at the Reina Sofía Hospital of Córdoba. Neurological and ENT neoplasms and upper GI tract neoplasms are among the most frequent causes, with similar results to those reported in other series. We highlight the number of young patients with cystic fibrosis (CF) in our series with nutritional support through PEG complementing oral and nocturnal feeding, which has lead to improved nutritional parameters before lung transplant. In consequence, we therefore analyze patients&#146; selection and their characteristics, the ethical and moral implications in some of these patients,such in neurological patients, their complications, mortality,and we mention as being of interest the transient and well tolerated indication in a subgroup of CF patients that deserves especial mention (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molina Puertas, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Alcántara, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benito López, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calañas Continente, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lavado Hernández, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Ortega, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Gastrostomía Endoscópica Percutánea (PEG) es el método de elección para la alimentación enteral a largo plazo, cuando el tubo digestivo está indemne, y la supervivencia de los pacientes es superior a 2 meses. Son cada vez más, las series comunicadas e indicaciones, a pesar de ser una técnica segura, debemos tener en cuenta una adecuada selección de los pacientes. El propósito de este trabajo es analizar el seguimiento de los pacientes sometidos a Gastrostomía Endoscópica Percutánea (PEG), en un Hospital de gran nivel asistencial y uno de los referentes de Trasplante de órganos en nuestra comunidad, con las peculiaridades que esto tiene en nuestra serie. Analizamos una cohorte de 73 pacientes sometidos a PEG, durante los años 2000 a 2007 en el Hospital Reina Sofía de Córdoba. Las Enfermedades Neurológicas y Neoplásicas de la esfera ORL y Digestiva alta son las causas más frecuentes, con resultados similares a los publicados en otras series. Destacamos, el número de paciente jóvenes con Fibrosis Quística (FQ), en nuestra serie, con soporte nutricional a través de PEG complementaria a la alimentación oral y nocturna, lo cual, ha supuesto una mejora de los parámetros nutricionales de cara al trasplante pulmonar. En consecuencia, analizamos las características de los pacientes, las implicaciones éticas y morales de algunos de ellos, como son los enfermos neurológicos, sus complicaciones y mortalidad. Destacamos con interés, la indicación transitoria y bien tolerada en un subgrupo de pacientes con FQ, que en nuestra serie merece especial mención (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;26(2): 399-401, mar.-abr. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94589</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gastrostomía Endoscópica Percutánea: 7 años de experiencia en nutrición enteral a largo plazo. Seguimiento clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3568^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30324^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28919^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23254^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
