<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-30361</identifier>
<setSpec>1136-4890</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Immunocytochemical distribution of the AMPA receptor subunits GluR2/3 and GluR4 in the cristae ampullares of the hatched chicken</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A preembedding immunoperoxidase method was used to study the distribution of the GluR2/3 and GluR4 AMPA subunits of the ionotropic glutamate receptors in the peripheral vestibular epithelium of the hatched chicken. At the light microscopic level, a strong immunoreactivity for both subunits was observed around type I hair cells in the cristae ampullares. At ultrastructural level, immunoreaction product was accumulated in calyx-type profiles of vestibular ganglion afferent fibres closely attached to type I hair cells. Occasionally, bouton-type endings supposedly on type II hair cells were immunostained for GluR4. These observations, together with the electrophysiological evidence, suggest that GluR2/3 and GluR4 subunits play a role in the transmission of vestibular sensory information during early development of the chicken (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sociedad Anatómica Española</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este trabajo hemos estudiado la distribución de las subunidades GluR2/3 y GluR4 del receptor ionotrópico AMPA de glutamato en el epitelio vestibular periférico del pollo posteclosión. Para ello, hemos empleado un método de inmunoperoxidasa preinclusión para microscopía de luz y electrónica. A nivel de las crestas ampulares, observamos una intensa inmunorreactividad frente a GluR2/3 y GluR4 alrededor de las células pilosas tipo I. A nivel ultraestructural, la inmunorreacción era evidente en las terminales caliciformes de las fibras aferentes del ganglio vestibular que abrazaban a las células pilosas tipo I. GluR4 también se expresaba en algunos botones terminales dispuestos sobre células pilosas tipo II.Estas observaciones, junto con evidencias electrofisiológicas, sugieren que las subunidades GluR2/3 y GluR4 participan en la transmisión de la información vestibular durante el desarrollo temprano del pollo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Eur. j. anat;7(2): 79-83, sept. 2003. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Distribución inmunocitoquímica de las subunidades GluR2/3 y GluR4 del receptor AMPA de glutamato en las crestas ampulares del pollo posteclosión</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Grandes, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Azkue, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flores, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Doñate-Oliver, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bilbao, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elezgarai, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puente, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hermida, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-30361</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d30561^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29203^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2691</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31141^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6351^s22071</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23315</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
