<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156613</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Early diagnosis of Bruton´s disease: the importance of an adequate medical and family history</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bruton&#146;s disease or X-linked agammaglobulinemia (XLA) is a primary immunodeficiency characterized by severe hypogammaglobulinemia. This causes increased susceptibility to bacterial recurrent infections at young age. It is very important, but difficult, to establish a diagnosis based on suspicion because of the common clinical symptoms of this rare disease. Once XLA is suspected, it is very important to refer the patient to a specialized hospital for specific analysis to confirm the disease. First, a blood analysis is done to see if antibody levels are low. In that case, a fluorocytometric analysis is needed to study the antibody classes. Genetic analysis shows mutation of BTK gene resulting in defective B cell differentiation and it must be done for diagnosis certainty. Treatment is based on intravenous immunoglobulin administration for life. We report a case in which a good clinical history was the key for an early diagnosis and treatment of a patient with Bruton´s disease before any potential complications appeared (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herranz Aguirre, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urriza Ripa, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez García, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villarreal Calvo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Arroyo, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durán Urdániz, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad de Bruton o agammaglobulinemia ligada al cromosoma X es una inmunodeficiencia primaria que cursa con la disminución drástica o la inexistencia de inmunoglobulinas en la sangre periférica. Esto va a originar una predisposición a desarrollar infecciones bacterianas recurrentes en el periodo de lactancia. Lo más importante y complejo a su vez es establecer el diagnóstico de sospecha, ya que se trata de una enfermedad infrecuente que cursa con manifestaciones muy comunes, como son las infecciones. Una vez sospechada la enfermedad, es importante derivar al paciente a un centro especializado para realizar los análisis pertinentes; en primer lugar, un análisis de sangre con recuento de inmunoglobulinas, y si están descendidas hay que solicitar la determinación de subpoblaciones linfocitarias mediante citometría de flujo. El diagnóstico de certeza se establece mediante análisis genéticos. El tratamiento consiste en la administración temprana de gammaglobulina intravenosa. Presentamos el caso de un paciente en el que una buena historia clínica permitió un diagnóstico precoz de enfermedad de Bruton, previo a la aparición de potenciales complicaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;18(71): e111-e114, jul.-sept. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156613</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad de Bruton de diagnóstico precoz: importancia de una adecuada historia clínica y los antecedentes familiares</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5567^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5567^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22183^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22206^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22206^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d366^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23164^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d366^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7334^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
