<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137291</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Therapeutic uses of cannabis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This chapter aims to present the current knowledge of the therapeutic properties of cannabinoids (marijuana and its synthetic derivatives). A growing body of evidence has been presented over the last years about the therapeutic properties of cannabinoids including analgesia, ocular hypotension, antiemesis in cancer chemotherapy, muscle-relaxing properties in multiple sclerosis, medullar traumatisms and movement disorders. Furthermore, recent reports indicates other potential therapeutic roles for cannabinoids as neuroprotectants (in animal models of neurodegenerative diseases and brain ischaemia), antiathsmatic or anticonvulsivants. More recently some naturally occurring compounds as well as several others CB agonists receptor have demonstrated antineoplastic effects both in vitro and in vivo. A large international debate is currently carry on scientific evidences versus legal restrictions about the possible use of these compounds. More clinical studies are needed to establish a rationale for dosage regimen, routes of administration, and a complete risk - benefit balance comparing cannabinoids and other therapeutic approaches (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Leza, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este capítulo se expone el estado actual del conocimiento sobre las propiedades terapéuticas del Cannabis (marihuana y derivados sintéticos). En los últimos años se han presentado un gran número de evidencias científicas sobre las propiedades terapéuticas de los cannabinoides, en especial analgesia, disminución de la presión intraocular, efecto antiemético en vómitos inducidos por quimioterapia antineoplásica, propiedades relajantes musculares en esclerosis múltiple, traumatismos medulares y alteraciones del movimiento. Además, algunas aportaciones recientes indican otros posibles usos de estas sustancias como neuroprotectores (en modelos animales de enfermedades neurodegenerativas e isquemia cerebral), antiasmáticos y anticonvulsivantes. Más recientemente, algunos compuestos naturales y agentes sintéticos agonistas de receptores CB han demostrado efectos antineoplásicos in vivo e in vitro. En la actualidad se está llevando a cabo un amplio debate internacional sobre las evidencias científicas versus las restricciones de tipo legal sobre el posible uso de estos compuestos. Se necesitan más estudios clínicos con el fin de establecer qué dosis, vías de administración son las más adecuadas en cada caso, así como el balance entre beneficio y riesgo comparando los cannabinoides con otras estrategias terapéuticas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);12(supl.2): 149-168, 2000.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137291</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad terapéutica del Cannabis y derivados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13323^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22937^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15241^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9322^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26226^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d939^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55339^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2218^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
