<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112461</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-6221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Linezolid induced toxic optic neuropathy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Linezolid is a new class of synthetic antimicrobial, belonging to the family of oxazolidinones approved by the Food and Drugs Administration for use in gram positive infections by staphylococcus spp and enterococcus spp, resistant tooxacillin and vancomycin. Among its mains uses are diseases such as nosocomial pneumonia, kin infection and soft tissue We describe the case of a patient with optic neuropathy associated with linezolid, most of these cases have been documented in patients who were in therapy at 28 days than recommended, physicians shouldbe alert to various adverse effects associated with linezolid such as optic neuropathy, but there is anincreased risk of leucopenia, thrombocytopenia and peripheral neuropathy associated with this medicine (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Cardona, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Roldán, C. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castaño Alate, C. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco Echeverri, C. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Foronda, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Linezolid es un antimicrobiano sintético que pertenece a un nuevo grupo, elde las oxazolidinonas, aprobado por la Foods and DrugsAdministration (FDA) para su uso en infecciones por microorganismos gram positivos, staphylococcusspp y enterococcusspp, resistentes a la oxacilina y a la vancomicina.Dentro de sus usos principales están enfermedades como neumonías nosocomiales, infecciones de piel y tejidos blandos.  Se describe el caso de una paciente con neuropatía óptica asociada al linezolid. La mayoría de estos casos han sido documentados en pacientes que recibieron una terapia superior a los 28 días recomendados.Los médicos debemos estar atentos a diferentes efectos adversos asociados con el linezolid como la neuropatía óptica, aunque es mayor el riesgo de leucopenia, trombocitopenia y neuropatía periférica, asociados a este medicamento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. oftalmol;3(1): 18-20, ene.-mar. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112461</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neuropatía óptica tóxica inducida por Linezolid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27728^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32073^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d903^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35322^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
