<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163150</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1780</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Texas Christian University Model for assessment and treatment of substance use disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Texas Christian University Model for Assessment and Treatment of Substance Use Disorders. This article aims to present a critical review of the literature regarding the Texas Christian University (TCU) Model in the field of assessment and treatment of substance use disorders (SUD). First, the background that prompted the development of the TCU Model is summarized. Subsequently, the central aspects of the model are detailed, including an assessment of empirical research that supports it. Then, the assessment tools developed within the model are described, with a focus on the psychometric properties of the instruments. Finally, the intervention strategies that constitute the TCU Treatment System are presented, emphasizing the evidence supporting the utilization of those interventions. The last three sections end up with a critical analysis in which the positive and negative aspects of the model, the assessment tools, and the associated interventions are presented (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vergés, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Portilla Huidobro, Rodrigo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laborda, Mario A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">No disponible</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int. j. psychol. psychol. ther. (Ed. impr.);17(2): 245-258, jun. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163150</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Modelo Texas Christian University para evaluación y tratamiento de trastornos por uso de sustancias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1083^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37627^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10746^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1541^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
