<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131355</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-7279</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The current article is about the experience of a patient, Almudena, who was being taken care by the «Equipo de ApoyoSocio-Comunitario (EASC) Retiro» from April 2008. Recently, in January2013, she achieved her legal capacity back after she was in a legal situation of economic partial guardianship for three years and a half. This situation was applied by a guardianship institution called «Agencia Madrileña de Tutela de Adultos (AMTA)».Both the fact and its psychosocial intervention in order to achieve it have boosted a process of reflection and inner self-criticism among the professionals involved in this case. First of all, that reflection was focused on the analysis of the position rather «passive» &#151;instead of a proactive one&#151; that we are keen to adopt before this kind of propositions at first glance. Secondly, it was also focused on the mistrust from which we start regarding the success of the process &#151;that was contrary to the factor of hope, a key factor in any therapeutic intervention&#151;.Thirdly, it was focused on the function and/or functions that we the professionals play in general and the (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Amores González, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Conde, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente artículo trata sobre la experiencia de una usuaria, Almudena, atendida por el Equipo de Apoyo Socio Comunitario(EASC) «Retiro» desde abril de 2008, quien recientemente, en el mes de enero de 2013, consiguió la Reintegración de su capacidad legal tras haber estado durante tres años y medio en situación de curatela económica, ejercida por una institución tutelar, la Agencia Madrileña de Tutela de Adultos (AMTA).Este hecho y la intervención psicosocial articulada para lograrlo, han promovido un proceso de reflexión y de autocrítica interna en los profesionales implicados y cercanos al caso. Esa reflexión se centró en primer lugar en un análisis de la posición más bien pasiva (en vez de proactiva) que tendemos a adoptaren un primer momento ante este tipo de propuestas, en segundo lugar sobre la desconfianza de la que partíamos con (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Inf. psiquiátr;(214): 473-481, sept.-dic. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131355</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El proceso de re-integración de la capacidad legal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2986^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55125^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29004</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
