<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103514</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical use of 30: 70 controlled-release methylphenidate in the treatment of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) is one of the most frequent reasons for visits in daily clinical practice, with a prevalence rate of 1-7% in Spain. The effectiveness of stimulants for the treatment of ADHD has been widely demonstrated and methylphenidate (MPD) is the most commonly used. There are currently several different immediate-release or extended-release formulations of MPD on the market.  Aims. To review the characteristics of the different formulations of MPD, with special attention paid to the studies on Equasym ®, an extended-release preparation soon to be made available in Spain. The article also includes recommendations for clinical practice and the choice of drugs. Development. Several studies have assessed the effectiveness of Equasym ® versus placebo or in comparison to other MPD formulations. The extended-release preparations have a therapeutic action that is similar to that of the immediaterelease versions, the difference between them being the plasma concentration profiles over time during the day, which are reflected in the pharmacodynamic effects. Equasym ® is more effective in the morning, whereas other formulations, such as Concerta ®, allow greater control of the symptoms in the afternoon. These differences are important when it comes to prescribing the treatment. Conclusions. One of the main advantages of having different formulations of MPD available is that it allows the professional to choose the drug that best suits the clinical features and needs of each patient. The individual response is the essential criterion in deciding on the most appropriate treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mardomingo Sanz, María. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El trastorno por déficit de atención/hiperactividad (TDAH) constituye uno de los motivos más frecuentes de consulta en la práctica clínica diaria, con una tasa de prevalencia del 1-7% en España. La eficacia de los estimulantes para el tratamiento del TDAH está ampliamente demostrada, y el metilfenidato (MTF) es el más comúnmente utilizado. En la actualidad se comercializan varias formulaciones de MTF de acción inmediata o prolongada. Objetivo. Revisar las características de las distintas formulaciones de MTF, con un enfoque especial en los estudios sobre Equasym ®, un preparado de acción prolongada próximamente disponible en España. También se incluyen recomendaciones para la práctica clínica y la elección de los fármacos. Desarrollo. Varios estudios han evaluado la eficacia de Equasym ® frente a placebo o en comparación con otras formulaciones de MTF. Los preparados de liberación prolongada tienen una acción terapéutica parecida a los de liberación inmediata,  y se diferencian entre sí por los perfiles temporales de concentración plasmática durante el día, que se reflejan en los efectos farmacodinámicos. La eficacia de Equasym ® es mayor por la mañana, mientras que otras formulaciones, como Concerta ®, permiten un mejor control de los síntomas por la tarde. Estas diferencias son importantes a la hora de prescribir el tratamiento. Conclusiones. Disponer de diferentes formulaciones de MTF es beneficioso, porque permite elegir en cada caso el fármaco que mejor se ajuste a las características clínicas y necesidades de cada paciente. La respuesta individual es el criterio fundamental para decidir el tratamiento más adecuado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;55(6): 359-369, sept. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103514</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso clínico de metilfenidato 30: 70 de liberación modificada en el tratamiento del trastorno por déficit de atención / hiperactividad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4364</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8961^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d711^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
