<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154411</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reduction in serum concentration of valproic acid secondary to the intake of ibuprofen as an example of valproic acid auto-induction metabolism</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. In 1998, an unexplained drug-drug interaction between valproic acid (VPA) and ibuprofen was reported. VPA has been considered a moderate inhibitor of several metabolic enzymes, but recently its inductive properties have been described, including the possibility of auto-induction. Ibuprofen can displace VPA from the plasmatic protein, increasing its serum free concentration, and subsequently its pharmacological actions, including auto-induction. The objective of this article is to describe a similar case and to contribute to the clarification of the underlying pharmacokinetic mechanisms. Methods. A 29-year-old Spanish Caucasian male with schizophrenia was followed with steady-state trough serum concentrations of VPA and clozapine for 5 years, including 3 ibuprofen trials. The main outcome variable was the concentration-to-dose (C/D) ratio, a measure of the ability to eliminate a drug. Independent sample Mann-Whitney U tests were performed to compare C/D ratios. Results. Five VPA C/D ratios, contaminated by VPA auto-induction occurring during or shortly after the two latter ibuprofen trials, were significantly lower (p&lt;0.001)  than the other 34 VPA C/D ratios of VPA not contaminated by auto-induction. During the highest ibuprofen dose in the third trial, the patient had two very low clozapine C/D ratios, which were significantly lower than the other 26 clozapine C/D ratios (p=0.021). Conclusions. Reduction in total VPA concentrations could be explained by ibuprofen displacing VPA from the plasma proteins, increasing the serum free VPA. This may induce the metabolism of VPA (and clozapine) and subsequently decrease their serum total concentrations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lama, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León, José de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuster, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marti-Bonany, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En 1998, se comunicó una inexplicada interacción farmacológica entre el ácido valproico (AVP) e ibuprofeno. El AVP se ha considerado un inhibidor moderado de varias enzimas metabólicas, pero recientemente se han descrito propiedades inductivas que incluyen la posibilidad de auto-inducción. Ibuprofeno puede desplazar el AVP de las proteínas plasmáticas, aumentando su concentración plasmática libre y consecuentemente sus acciones farmacológicas, incluyendo la auto-inducción. El objetivo de este artículo es describir un caso similar y contribuir a clarificar los mecanismos farmacocinéticos subyacentes. Metodología. En un varón caucásico español de 29 años con esquizofrenia se siguieron durante 5 años las concentraciones plasmáticas de AVP y clozapina, incluyendo 3 ensayos con ibuprofeno. La variable de resultado principal fue la concentración-dosis (C/D) ratio, una medida de la capacidad para eliminar un fármaco. La prueba de U-Mann-Whitney para muestras independientes se utilizó para comparar las C/D ratios. Resultados. Cinco C/D ratios de AVP, contaminadas por auto-inducción de AVP durante o poco después de los dos últimos ensayos con ibuprofeno, fueron significativamente inferiores (p&lt;0.001) que las restantes C/D ratios de AVP. Con la mayor de las dosis de ibuprofeno del tercer ensayo, el paciente tuvo dos C/D ratios de clozapina muy bajas que fueron significativamente inferiores a las restantes C/D ratios de clozapina (p=0,021). Conclusiones. La reducción de las concentraciones plasmáticas totales de AVP puede explicarse porque ibuprofeno desplaza el AVP de las proteínas plasmáticas, incrementando el AVP libre. Éste puede inducir el metabolismo del AVP (y de clozapina) y consecuentemente disminuir su concentración plasmática total (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;44(4): 136-144, jul.-ago. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154411</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reducción en la concentración sérica del ácido valproico secundaria a la toma de ibuprofeno como ejemplo de autoinducción metabólica del ácido valproico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27999^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3051^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3051^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29291^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29291^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29291^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52955^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29291^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4421^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52955^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52955^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28145^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4409^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28145^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
