<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145341</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Kisspeptins were first identified as a family of structurally-related peptides, encoded by the KiSS-1 gene, with ability to inhibit tumor metastasis through binding to the G protein-coupled receptor GPR54. However, in late 2003, two independent publications demonstrated the presence of inactivating mutations of GPR54 gene in patients suffering lack of puberty onset and hypogonadotropic hypogonadism; a phenotype which was also observed in mice with genetic inactivation of GPR54. These observations disclosed the essential roles of the ligand/receptor system KiSS-1/ GPR54 in the control of reproductive function in general, and in the regulation of puberty onset in particular. These contentions have been fully substantiated during the last three years, by a number of experimental studies in different species (from Mouse and rats to humans), which have defined the indispensable role of kisspeptins and their receptor in the regulation of different aspects of reproduction. In the present article, we will review the most salient facets of the KiSS-1/GPR54 system in the control of the gonadotropic axis, with special emphasis on the potential involvement of kisspeptins in the pubertal activation of the reproductive system and its modulation by key regulatory factors, such as energy balance and the metabolic status of the organism (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tena-Sempere, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las kisspeptinas fueron inicialmente identificadas como un grupo de péptidos estructuralmente relacionados, codificados por el gen KiSS-1, con capacidad de inhibir la metástasis de ciertos tumores mediante la activación del receptor acoplado a proteínas G, GPR54. No obstante, a finales de 2003, sendas publicaciones demostraron que mutaciones inactivantes del gen GPR54 se asocian a ausencia de pubertad e hipogonadismo hipogonadotropico, tanto en humanos como en roedores, lo que puso de manifiesto el papel clave del sistema ligando-receptor KiSS-1/GPR54 en el control del eje reproductor en general, y de los mecanismos de activación de la pubertad en particular. Estas observaciones iniciales se han visto sustanciadas en los últimos 3 años a través de numerosos estudios experimentales en diversas especies (desde roedores hasta humanos), que han permitido establecer el papel absolutamente crucial de las kisspeptinas y su receptor en la regulación de diversas facetas de la función reproductora. En este trabajo revisaremos los aspectos más sobresalientes del papel del sistema KiSS-1/GPR54 en el control del eje gonadotrópico, con especial atención a la descripción de la implicación de las kisspeptinas en la activación puberal del sistema reproductor y su modulación por factores relevantes, tales como el estado energético y metabólico del organismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);66(supl.1): 31-37, abr. 2007. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145341</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Kisspeptinas y pubertad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29311^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54575^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19321^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7184^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12519^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6209^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29534^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
