<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126578</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9572</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Insomia types and clinical evaluation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of revision is to describe the objectives and clinical instruments for a correct insomnia evaluation. The first and most important aspect of the evaluation is the clinical interview and sleep history. Full evaluation of the insomnia requires a multidimensional (psychiatric, physical, drugs...) approach because those aspects of the sleep disorder that are most distressing to the patient will vary among individuals. The clinician need and must have a clear understanding of insomnia types for a correct diagnosis and treatment. Insomnia types are described (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Siurana, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benetó Pascual, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objeto de la revisión es relatar los objetivos y los instrumentos clínicos para una correcta evaluación del insomnio. El primero y más importante aspecto de la evaluación es la entrevista clínica y la historia de sueño. La evaluación completa del insomnio requiere un abordaje multifactorial (psiquiátrico, físico, medicamentos, etc.), debido a que los aspectos de la alteración del sueño que son más perturbadores pueden variar de unos sujetos a otros. El médico necesita y debe tener un conocimiento claro de los tipos de insomnio para un correcto diagnóstico y tratamiento. Se describe los tipos de insomnio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Vigilia sueño;18(supl.1): 9-15, sept. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126578</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Historia clínica básica y tipos de insomnio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34371^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34371^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28219^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12039^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12039^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
