<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109511</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical Utility and Economic Impact of Conventional Transbronchial Needle Aspiration of Mediastinal Lymphadenopathies in Bronchogenic Carcinoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To analyze the clinical utility and economic impact of conventional transbronchial needle aspiration (TBNA) in patients with diagnosis of bronchogenic carcinoma (BC) and mediastinal lymphadenopathies in thoracic computed tomography (CT). To assess the predictive factors of valid aspirations. Patients and methods: Retrospective observational study between 2006 and 2011 of all TBNA performed in patients with final diagnosis of BC and accessible hilar or mediastinal lymphadenopathies on thoracic CT. Results: We performed TBNA on 267 lymphadenopathies of 192 patients. In 34.9% of patients, two or more lymph nodes were biopsied. Valid aspirations were obtained in 153 patients (79.7%) that were diagnostic in 124 (64.6%). Multivariate analysis showed that factors associated with valid or diagnostic results are the diameter of the lymph node and the number of lymph nodes explored. TBNA was the only endoscopic technique that provided the diagnosis of BC in 54 patients (28.1%). Staging mediastinoscopy was avoided in 67.6% of patients. The prevalence of mediastinal lymph node involvement was 74.4%, sensitivity of TBNA was 86.2% and negative predictive value was 63.6%. Including mediastinoscopy and other avoided diagnostic techniques, TBNA saved 451.57 &#128; per patient. Conclusions: TBNA is a clinically useful, cost-effective technique in patients with BC and mediastinal or hilar lymphadenopathies. It should therefore be performed on a regular basis during diagnostic bronchoscopy of these patients(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mediano San Andrés, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallardo Carrasco, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almonacid Sánchez, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Resano Barrio, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castelao Naval, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Hernández, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Francés, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo Alonso, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Analizar la utilidad clínica y el impacto económico de la punción transbronquial convencional (PTBC) en los pacientes con carcinoma broncogénico (CB) y adenopatías mediastínicas en la tomografía computarizada (TC) torácica. Analizar los factores predictores de punción válida. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio observacional retrospectivo entre 2006 y 2011 de todas las PTBC realizadas a pacientes con CB y adenopatías mediastínicas o hiliares accesibles a la técnica en la TC torácica. Resultados: Se realizó PTBC sobre 267 adenopatías de 192 pacientes. En el 34,9% de los pacientes se pinchó más de una adenopatía. Se obtuvo punción válida en 153 pacientes (79,7%) y diagnóstica en 124 (64,6%). El análisis multivariante mostró que los factores que se asocian a la obtención de punción válida y diagnóstica son el diámetro de la adenopatía y el número de adenopatías pinchadas. La PTBC fue la única técnica endoscópica que permitió el diagnóstico de CB en 54 pacientes (28,1%). La PTBC evitó el 67,6% de las mediastinoscopias de estadificación. La prevalencia de afectación tumoral mediastínica fue del 74,4%, la sensibilidad de la PTBC del 86,2% y el valor predictivo negativo del 63,6%. Entre mediastinoscopias y otras técnicas diagnósticas evitadas, la PTBC ha supuesto un ahorro de 451,57 &#128; por paciente estudiado. Conclusiones: La PTBC es una técnica clínicamente útil y económicamente rentable en los pacientes con CB y adenopatías patológicas mediastínicas o hiliares, por lo que debería ser realizada como una técnica endoscópica más, de forma habitual, en estos pacientes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;49(2): 41-46, feb. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109511</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad clínica e impacto económico de la punción transbronquial convencional de adenopatías mediastínicas en el carcinoma broncogénico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2326^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2326^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1732^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2326^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
