<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124488</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Occupational risks perception in professional nursing practitioners at health care center</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The aim of this study aim is to describe the perception of occupational risks by nursing professionals in health care center. Method: A descriptive cross-sectional study was conducted on a total population of 122 registered nurses (RNs) and 89 certi&amp;#64257;ed nurse aides (CNAs). A convenience sample of nursing professionals was recruited with 72 RNs (27 males and 45 females), and 45 CNAs (1 male and 44 females). They were asked about their perception of occupational risks during their everyday work practice. Sex and age variables were considered, as well as work-related accidents and occupational risk prevention training that had been registered in the last &amp;#64257;ve years. The sample mean age was 47.29 ± 7.98 years (RNs, 45.11; and CNAs, 50.77). Results: Main sources of risks as perceived by RNs were those accidents due to biological materials exposure (52.78%), carrying and moving weight (19.44%), and to occupational stress (19.44%); amongst CNAs, those accidents due to carrying and moving weight (44.44%), biological materials exposure (26.67%) and other infections (15.56%) were also mentioned. As regards the overall risks identi&amp;#64257;ed by these professionals, 23.08% of them had perceived no risk at all during their work; 35.04% only identi&amp;#64257;ed one risk, and 29.06% perceived two risks in their day to day activity, whereas 12.82% identi&amp;#64257;ed three or more occupational risks. Conclusions: As a general rule, the nursing professionals tend to underestimate the occupational risks they are exposed to, with biological, musculoskeletal, and occupational-related stress are perceived as the main sources of risk (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oliva-Reina, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santacruz-Hamer, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Porras-Povedano, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir y analizar los riesgos laborales percibidos por las profesionales de enfermería de un centro sanitario.MétodoEstudio descriptivo transversal sobre una población total de 122 diplomadas universitarias en enfermería (DUE) y 89 auxiliares de enfermería (AE). Se seleccionó una muestra por conveniencia entre profesionales que acudieron a vigilancia de la salud, de 72 DUE (27 hombres y 45 mujeres) y 45 AE (un hombre y 44 mujeres). Se preguntó a las profesionales por los riesgos laborales percibidos en su trabajo habitual, se recogieron las variables sexo y edad, así como los accidentes laborales y la formación en prevención de riesgos laborales en los últimos 5 años de registros internos. La edad media de la muestra fue de 47,29 ± 7,98 años (DUE: 45,11; AE: 50,77).ResultadosLos principales riesgos percibidos entre las DUE fueron los accidentes por exposición a material biológico (52,78%), cargas/movilizaciones (19,44%) y estrés laboral (19,44%); entre las AE fueron las cargas y movilizaciones (44,44%), los accidentes por exposición a material biológico (26,67%) y otras infecciones (15,56%). En cuanto al número total de riesgos percibidos por las profesionales se aprecia que el 23,08% de ellas no perciben ningún riesgo en su trabajo habitual, el 35,04% solo percibe un riesgo y el 29,06% percibe 2 riesgos laborales en su trabajo habitual, mientras que el 12,82% percibe 3 o más riesgos laborales.ConclusionesExiste una infraestimación de riesgos laborales a los que las profesionales de enfermería se encuentran expuestas en su trabajo habitual, centrándose la percepción en riesgos biológicos, musculoesqueléticos y estrés (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);24(3): 191-195, mayo.-jun. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124488</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Percepción de riesgos laborales en profesionales de Enfermería de un centro sanitario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29063^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35435</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9929^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
