<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117541</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-6221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intraoperative floppy iris syndrmome (IFIS)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Intraoperative Floppy Iris Syndrome constitutes now a days a very important and frequent pathology, with which we, as Ophthalmologist, have to be familiarized. Urologist, Cardiologist and other medical specialists tend to prescribe alpha antagonist to their patients, making it practically impossible for us to avoid or to have any Floppy Iris Syndrome case in our professional live. It is very important to be able to detect the possible intraoperative complications during the cataract surgery, in order to give and warrant our patients the best possible visual acuity result after surgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rivas Dangel, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos García, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>CunhaMartins, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miyagi Yonamine, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Síndrome de Iris Flácido constituye hoy en día una patología con la cual todo oftalmólogo debe de estar familiarizado. El uso de antagonistas de los receptores alfa adrenérgicos es cada vez más frecuente, haciendo que nos sea prácticamente imposible evitar toparnos con estos pacientes en nuestra vida profesional. Es muy importante detectar las posibles complicaciones intraoperatorias durante la cirugía de catarata en nuestros pacientes, a fin de poder garantizarles un adecuado resultado visual postoperatorio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. oftalmol;3(3): 167-168, jul.-sept. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117541</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de iris flácio intraoperatorio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7666^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2431^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19035^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d319^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7593</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
