<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051530</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0367</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Historiography of psychoanalysis in Spain (1975-1985)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this article, we present a historical bibliography of psychoanalysis in Spain during the period 1975-1985. Our aims is to put together a reliable bibliography and a study of its main features by examining the documents contained in it. To gather our repertoire, we went systematically through the psychoanalytical journals published in Spain during the period, as well as some foreign journals that include historical work on psychoanalysis in Spain. Next, we provide the relevant quantitative data and a conceptual analysis of certain aspects of the bibliography, for information on the salient characteristics of the authors´different approaches and methodologies</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Druet, Anne-Cecile</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se ofrece una bibliografía histórica del psicoanálisis en España en el período 1975-1985. El objetivo es lograr una bibliografía fiable y un estudio de las principales características de la misma, mediante el examen directo de los documentos incluidos en ella. Para la elaboración del repertorio se realizó un vaciado sistemático de las revistas de psicoanálisis publicadas en España durante ese período, así como de algunas revistas extranjeras que incluyen trabajos históricos sobre psicoanálisis en España. Se proporciona a continuación los datos cuantitativos pertinentes y se realiza un análisis conceptual de algunos aspectos de la bibliografía, con el objetivo de ofrecer información sobre las aportaciones y las características relevantes de las distintas metodologías y perspectivas de los autores</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. psiquiatr;69(3): 197-217, jul.-sept. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051530</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Historiografía del psicoanálisis en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38889</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
