<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117171</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Personality differences in coaches from the Costa and MacCrae model</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of the present work is to know the personality profile of coaches, the differences based on professional success, edge and years of experience as a coach. In order to do this, we applied the NEO Personality Inventory (NEO-FFI, Costa and McCrae, 2008) to 32 coaches (men) between the ages of 25 and 59 (M = 36.63, d.t. = 8.69). The results indicate that successful coaches obtained significantly higher scores on the trait Agreeableness (p &lt;.001) and a trend to statistical significance in the Responsibility factor (p &lt;.10), where coaches have lower scores than normal reference population. In addition, there are no statistically significant differences in the personality of the coaches according to professional success. Finally, coaches with fewer years of experience have higher scores on the Kindness trait (p&lt;.05) and lower scores in Neuroticism trait (p&lt;.05) than most experienced sports coaches. It is concluded that a prolonged and professional role as coach accentuates certain type of personality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Naveira, Alejo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Barquín, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente trabajo es conocer el perfil de personalidad de los entrenadores, las diferencias en función de su éxito profesional, edad y los años de experiencia como entrenador. Para ello, se aplicó el Inventario de Personalidad NEO (NEO-FFI; Costa y McCrae, 2008) a 32 entrenadores (hombres) con una edad comprendida entre los 25 y 59 años (M= 36.63; d.t.= 8.69). Los resultados indican que los entrenadores de éxito obtienen significativamente mayores puntuaciones en el rasgo Amabilidad (p&lt;.001) y una tendencia a la significación estadística en el factor Responsabilidad (p&lt;.10), donde los entrenadores obtienen menores puntuaciones que la población normal de referencia. Además, no existen diferencias estadísticamente significativas en la personalidad de los entrenadores en función del éxito profesional. Por último, los entrenadores de menos años de experiencia tienen mayores puntuaciones en el rasgo Amabilidad (p&lt;.05) y menores puntuaciones en el rasgo Neuroticismo (p&lt;.05) que los entrenadores de mayor experiencia deportiva. Se concluye que el ejercicio profesional y prolongado del rol del entrenador acentúa cierto tipo de personalidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;13(2): 53-62, jul.-dic. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117171</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias de personalidad en entrenadores desde el modelo de Costa y McCrae</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32065</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
