<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79545</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Elders sexual expression: An overdose of false myths</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Sex among elderly people is still a topic full of false beliefs and myths. Evidence suggests that old people are sexually active, and in some cases, even more active than general adult population. Therefore, it is stated that age itself is not an obstacle to enjoy and practice sex. This paper explores the social factors that make difficult to enhance sexual relations among old people and creates a debate about genitality and sexuality among elders (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Leyva-Moral, Juan Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Para muchas personas, la sexualidad durante la vejez continúa siendo un tema tabú repleto de falsas creencias y mitos. Las evidencias sugieren que los ancianos son sexualmente activos y, en algunos casos, más aún que la población general adulta. Por tanto puede afirmarse que la edad como tal no es un obstáculo para disfrutar una vida sexual plena y satisfactoria. En este artículo se analizan los factores sociales que dificultan la sexualidad del anciano y se debate sobre la genitalidad y sexualidad en la vejez (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;17(2): 124-127, abr.-jun. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79545</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La expresión sexual de los ancianos. Una sobredosis de falsos mitos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d20174^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
