<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042040</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Process of asaptation to Spanish of the Temperament Evaluation of Memphis, Pisa, Paris and San Diego Scale. Self applied version (TEMPS-A)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Investigation of the predisposing factors for affective disorders has shown that measures to assess affective temperament are necessary. The TEMPS-A is a self-evaluation measure to assess four affective temperaments (hyperthymic, depressive, cyclothymic and irritable) and anxious temperament.Method. The TEMPS-A questionnaire version that includes 110 questions has been adapted following the translation-backtranslation methodology, including two translations to Spanish and the classification of equivalence to English by an independent author.Results. The study results indicated that a satisfactory translation was obtained, as indicated by the validation of equivalence by the bilingual consultant. All the items showed a perfect (A) or satisfactory equivalence (B).Conclusions. The TEMPS-A, Spanish version, is an understandable questionnaire that is equivalent to the original version in English, that allows for the evaluation of affective temperaments</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Arán, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Akiskal, K</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saiz-Ruiz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Akiskal, H. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrantes-Vidal, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montes, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Moreno, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vieta, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La investigación de los factores predisponentes para los trastornos afectivos ha demostrado que son necesarias medidas para la evaluación del temperamento afectivo. La TEMPS-A es una medida de autoevaluación para evaluar cuatro temperamentos afectivos (hipertímico, depresivo, ciclotímico e irritable) y el temperamento ansioso.Método. La versión del cuestionario TEMPS-A que incluye 110 preguntas se ha adaptado siguiendo la metodología de traducción-retrotraducción, incluyendo dos traducciones al español y la clasificación de equivalencia al inglés por un autor independiente.Resultados. Los resultados del estudio indicaron que se obtuvo una traducción satisfactoria, tal y como indica la validación de equivalencia por parte del asesor bilingüe. Todos los ítems mostraron una equivalencia perfecta (A) o satisfactoria (B).Conclusiones. La TEMPS-A, versión española, es un cuestionario comprensible y equivalente a la versión original en inglés, que permite la evaluación de los temperamentos afectivos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;33(5): 325-330, sept.-oct. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042040</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Proceso de adaptación al español de la Escala de temperamento de Memphis, Pisa, París y San Diego. Versión autoaplicada (TEMPS-A)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7980</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14072</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
