<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141614</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mortality predictive factors in patients with urinary sepsis associated to upper urinary tract calculi</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: The aims of this study were to determine the clinical characteristics of patients with urinary sepsis associated to ureteral calculi admitted to the Intensive Care Unit (ICU), and to identify predictors of mortality in the first 24hours of admission. Design: A retrospective observational study covering a 16-year period (2006-2011) was carried out. Setting: The combined clinical/surgical ICU of a secondary-level University hospital. Patients: All patients admitted to the ICU due to obstructive urinary sepsis. Interventions: None. Main variables: We analyzed general clinical and laboratory test and urological data. The diagnostic technique, affected side, decompression technique, isolated microorganism and antibiotic therapy used were also considered. The assessment of risk factors was performed by multiple logistic regression analysis. Results: A total of 107 patients admitted to the ICU were included in the study, with a mortality rate of 19.6%. The diagnosis was mainly established by ultrasound, and the most commonly used decompression technique was retrograde JJ stenting. Microorganisms were isolated in 48.6% of the patients. In total, 20.6% of the patients had bacteremia. Multivariate analysis found age, acute renal failure and the use of vasoactive drugs administered continuously for the first 24hours of admission to be independently associated to mortality. Conclusions: Advanced age, acute renal failure and the need for vasoactive drugs were associated to an increased risk of mortality in patients with urinary sepsis associated to upper urinary tract calculi (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gormaz, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilanova, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domingo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gavilan, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trujillano, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serviá, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Badia, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo de este estudio fue conocer las características clínicas de los pacientes con sepsis urológica obstructiva por litiasis ureteral que ingresaron en la Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos e identificar los factores predictores de mortalidad en las primeras 24 horas del ingreso. Diseño: Estudio observacional retrospectivo durante un periodo de 16 años (1996-2011). Ámbito: Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos polivalente de 20 camas de un hospital universitario de 2.° nivel. Pacientes: Todos los pacientes que ingresaron en Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos por sepsis urológica obstructiva. Intervenciones: Ninguna. Variables de interés principales: Variables clínicas y analíticas generales y relacionadas con el proceso urológico. Método diagnóstico, técnica desobstructiva, germen aislado y tratamiento. Análisis de factores de riesgo mediante regresión logística múltiple. Resultados: Ciento siete pacientes ingresados con una mortalidad del 19,6%. El diagnóstico fue mayoritariamente por ecografía y la técnica descompresiva más utilizada fue la colocación de catéter ureteral doble J. Se aisló germen en el 48,6% de los pacientes. El 20,6% presentaron bacteriemia. En el análisis multivariante, la edad, el fallo renal agudo y el uso de drogas vasoactivas en las primeras 24 horas del ingreso se relacionaron de forma independiente con la mortalidad. Conclusiones: La edad avanzada, el fallo renal agudo y la necesidad de fármacos vasoactivos se relacionaron con un aumento de riesgo de mortalidad en los pacientes con urosepsis secundaria a litiasis ureteral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);39(5): 290-297, jun.-jul. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141614</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores predictores de mortalidad en la sepsis urinaria con obstrucción ureteral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14923^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52127^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1460^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12140^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
