<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81015</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The aim of this article is to explore the relevanceof the analysis in anthropological research on nutritioneducation analyzing aspects of food and socialization nutridietizaciónor set of rules, recommendations and nutritionalguidelines whose aim is changing the eating behavior inareas beyond the purely nutritional, whose ultimate aim isto achieve some uniformity food in two areas: family andsociocultural.Methods: The investigation used a qualitative methodology:6 discussion groups among children aged between 4 and14 years in a total sample of 36 children and in-depthinterviews with 15 parents and children 3 to 14 years.Results: In the context of the family is taking food meaninginsofar as they are consumed within the family and arebeing received with confidence. The cultural transmission ofcertain foods to taste part of the socialization food analysedespecially anthropology of food.The nutridietización reflected in the fact that 90% ofchildren, with the exception of some smaller (4-5 yearsold) know all the recommendations and standards to befollowed, even talk of a balanced diet and healthy in theseterms. We emphasize that the discussion group of 4-5years is a clear tendency to imitation of responses amongthe group members.Conclusion: Nutrition education should understand themechanism nutridietizador prevailing in the current foodsociety to understand those factors socio-cultural, economicand political influence that both the eating behavior and thatoften escape with some nutritional myopia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Navas López, Julia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: El objetivo del artículo es estudiar la pertinenciadel análisis antropológico en las investigaciones sobreeducación nutricional. Se analizan aspectos relacionados conla socialización alimentaria y la nutridietización o conjuntode normas, recomendaciones y guías nutricionales cuyoobjetivo es la modificación del comportamiento alimentarioen aspectos más allá de los puramente nutricionales, cuyafinalidad última es la de conseguir cierta homogeneidadalimentaria en dos ámbitos: el familiar y el sociocultural.Métodos: En la investigación se utiliza una metodología cualitativa:6 grupos de discusión entre niños de edades entre4 y 14 años en una muestra total de 36 niños y entrevistasen profundidad a 15 padres y a 3 niños de 14 años.Resultados: En el ámbito familiar los alimentos van tomandosignificado en la medida en que son consumidos en el senofamiliar y van siendo percibidos con confianza. La transmisióncultural del gusto a ciertos alimentos forma parte dela socialización alimentaria analizada especialmente por laAntropología de la alimentación.La nutridietización queda reflejada en el hecho de que el90% de los niños, con excepción de algunos más pequeños(4-5 años) conocen todas las recomendaciones y normasque deben de seguir, incluso hablan de dieta saludable yequilibrada en estos términos. Destacamos que en el grupode discusión de 4-5 años se muestra una clara tendencia a laimitación de las respuestas entre los miembros del grupo.Conclusiones: La educación nutricional debe entender elmecanismo nutridietizador que impera en la sociedad alimentariaactual para poder comprender aquellos factoressocioculturales, económicos y políticos que tanto influyenen el comportamiento alimentario y que suelen escapar antecierta miopía nutricional(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;14(1): 22-28, ene.-mar.2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81015</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La educación nutricional en el contexto familiar y sociocultural</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d20182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5350^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3487</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
