<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83381</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The epidemiology of cleft lip and palate over the period 1990&#150;2004 in Asturias</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Cleft lip and palate (oral clefts) are the most common congenital facial defects. Objective: To assess the prevalence of oral clefts and to describe the associated malformations in a geographically defined population. Method: Data from the Asturias Registry of Congenital Defects were used to investigate the epidemiology of congenital facial clefts over the period 1990&#150;2004 among the 103,452 births in the region. The results were also compared with data from EUROCAT and other Spanish registries. Results: Out of 145 oral clefts recorded, cleft lip was 26.9%, cleft lip and palate 28.3% and cleft palate 44.8%. Total prevalence of oral clefts was 14.4 per 10,000 births. Other associated defects were found in 18.6% of the total cases, with skeletal, cardiovascular and central nervous systems being the most common anomalies. Syndromes or sequences were found in 22% of clefts. A prenatal diagnosis was made in 12.4%. Conclusion: The prevalence of oral clefts in Asturias over this period fell within the range reported for other European registries. An exhaustive prenatal ultrasound and examination of the affected newborns to look for other malformations should be considered in infants with clefts, due to the high association with them (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mosquera Tenreiro, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García López, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Dehli, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riaño Galán, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Toral, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Fernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ariza Hevia, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las fisuras labiales y palatinas son los defectos congénitos faciales más frecuentes. Objetivo: Conocer la frecuencia de estos defectos en Asturias y realizar una descripción clinicoepidemiológica de sus anomalías asociadas. Metodología: Análisis de los datos del Registro de Defectos Congénitos de Asturias de los años 1990&#150;2004 sobre una población de 103.452 nacidos y comparación con el European Concerted Action on Congenital Anomalies and Twins y otros registros españoles. Resultados: De los 145 casos registrados, el 26,9% eran fisuras labiales, el 28,3% eran fisuras labiopalatinas y el 44,8% eran fisuras palatinas. La prevalencia total de las fisuras labiales o palatinas fue de 14,4 por 10.000 nacidos. Un 18,6% tenía otros defectos asociados, y fueron más frecuentes las anomalías esqueléticas, las cardiovasculares y las del sistema nervioso central. Un 22,1% de las fisuras labiales y palatinas pertenecía a un síndrome o secuencia reconocida. El diagnóstico prenatal fue del 12,4%, principalmente en los casos polimalformados y síndromes. Conclusiones: La prevalencia total de las fisuras labiales y palatinas en Asturias durante este período fue similar a la de otros registros europeos. Debido a la elevada asociación a otras anomalías, debe realizarse una búsqueda minuciosa de ellas, tanto en la ecografía prenatal como en la exploración del recién nacido (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);73(3): 132-137, sept. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83381</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Epidemiología de las fisuras labiales y palatinas durante los años 1990&#150;2004 en Asturias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29352^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28219^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29353^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28402^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
