<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132715</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">150years of the Spanish Red Cross humanitarian assistance as a human right</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Spain has been connected to the Red Cross since its founding, now 150 years ago. Its inspirer, Henry Dunant, gave this world the legacy of the idea of humanitarian assistance as a human right. In 1863, a Spanish delegation attended the First International Conference in Geneva, where the International Committee of the RedCross was created. Spain was the seventh nation to have ratified the First Geneva Convention in 1864, undertaking the obligation of impartially coming to the aid of all those wounded in war and to protect the civilians rendering help under the RedCross symbol. This analysis focuses on the development of this right, invoking International Humanitarian Law. Similarly, it sets out the evolution of the Law of The Hague and the Law of Geneva. Concluding that, in the evolution of both of these bodies of law, the nature of humanitarian assistance is explained as a human right (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Conesa, Juana María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">España ha estado vinculada a la Cruz Roja desde su fundación, hace ahora 150años. Su inspirador, Henry Dunant, legó al mundo la idea de la asistencia humanitaria como un derecho humano. En 1863 una delegación española acudió a la Primera Conferencia Internacional en Ginebra, donde se crea el Comité Internacional de la Cruz Roja. España fue la séptima nación que, en 1864, ratificó el I Convenio de Ginebra, obligándose a socorrer, con imparcialidad, a todos los heridos en la guerra, y a la protección de los civiles que les prestan ayuda bajo la enseña de la Cruz Roja. Este análisis se centra en el desarrollo de este derecho, invocando al Derecho Internacional Humanitario. Igualmente, establece la evolución del Derecho de la Haya ydel Derecho de Ginebra. Concluyendo que en la evolución de ambos ordenamientos, se explica la naturaleza de la asistencia humanitaria como un derecho humano (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;23(4): 260-263, sept.-dic. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132715</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">150 años de la Cruz Roja española la acción humanitaria como derecho humano</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12488^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12431^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6958</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35058</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
