<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154043</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Optimal method to obtain platelet-rich plasma at the Pain Management Clinic of the NMC 20 de noviembre ISSSTE</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the optimal method to collect platelet- rich plasma (PRP). Material and methods: We collected 15 ml of blood from 36 healthy adults to determine platelet count and to test which of the following three protocols were the best to collect PRP. We used 3 ml of blood for each method: protocol 1: (n = 21) the blood tube was tested at 1200 revolutions per minute (RPM) in 2 centrifuge cycles of 8 minutes each; protocol 2 (n = 8): 1200 RPM/1 cycle/8 minutes, and protocol 3: (n = 7): 1200 RPM/1 cycle/10 minutes. From the blood samples that we collected, we also analyzed 1 ml of plasma to determine platelet performance by using an automatic flow cytometer (BD FACSCanto II). Platelet performance was determined by the following formula: platelet PRP count (100)/platelet count from total blood. The statistical method used were measures of central tendency, Chi-square, t-test, analysis of variance and the Wilcoxon and Kruskal-Wallis tests. Results: The basal overall count of platelet was 261.2 miles/ mcl for the three methods (p = 0.906), 662.3 ± 243.3 (p = 0.001) for protocol 1; 377.9 ± 101.4 (p = 0.008) for protocol 2 and 30.9 ± 18.8 (p = 0.016) for protocol 3. Platelet performances were 255.2 ± 57.6 %; 149.3 ± 24.6 %; 13.3 ± 11.6 % respectively. Conclusion: Applying the first protocol we obtain PRP (1200 RPM/2 cycles of 8 minutes each). This study was done in healthy adults; however, future studies with a larger sample size are needed to confirm our findings of this method. In case of collecting platelets in studies with greater population being the adequate, its clinical utility should be validated by including patients with chronic and degenerative diseases and take care of associated diseases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández Santos, JR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valadez Báez, XL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Huerta, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canseco Aguilar, CP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tenopala Villegas, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;23(4): 175-180, jul.-ago. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154043</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Método óptimo para la obtención de plasma rico en plaquetas en el Servicio de Clínica del Dolor del CMN 20 de noviembre ISSSTE</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52020^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52020^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52020^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11406^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11406^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35170^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28636^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
