<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105615</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Learning to search on the Web of Science: A reply to the Aluja, Becoña, Botella, Colom, Echeburúa, Forns, Pérez and Vila (2011) study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aims of this paper are, on the one hand, to present the differences in the results that may be incurred when working with some automated database functions to obtain scientific production and, on the other hand, to reveal the mistakes made by Aluja et al. (2011) in their considerations and suggestions to the study of Olivas-Avila and Musi-Lechuga (2010a). In this paper, we show that the procedure used to replicate the study is incorrect and, therefore, the authors did not only confuse production with diffusion indicators, but also suggest many indicators that have no discriminative power with the sample studied,- and the most striking&#151;one hundred percent out of the ten cases analyzed were incorrectly analyzed and, therefore, the results do not correspond to the real record count in the Web of Science (WoS). In some cases, the errors involved items omitted from the WoS. The authors also propose rates like the percentage of articles in journals of Spanish spheres, or the percentage of items as first author. These indexes have no theoretical or empirical justification or previous studies that support them (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso Olivas-Ávila, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Musi-Lechuga, Bertha</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los objetivos del artículo son, por un lado, dar a conocer la diferencia de resultados en que se puede incurrir al trabajar con algunas funciones automatizadas de las bases de datos para la obtención de la producción científica en artículos de investigadores y, por otro lado, poner de manifiesto los múltiples errores que cometen Aluja et al. (2011) en las consideraciones y sugerencias al estudio de Olivas-Ávila y Musi-Lechuga (2010a). En el presente trabajo se demuestra que el procedimiento utilizado para replicar el estudio no es correcto y, por ello, los autores no solo confunden indicadores de producción con difusión, sino que proponen indicadores sin capacidad de discriminación en la muestra objeto de estudio y lo más llamativo es que el cien por cien de los diez casos que analizan lo hacen de manera incorrecta y por ello los resultados no corresponden con los registros reales en la Web of Science (WoS), los errores en algunos casos implican artículos omitidos de la WoS. Además, los autores proponen índices como porcentaje de artículos en revistas de ámbito hispano o porcentaje de artículos como primer autor, estos índices no tienen justificación teórica ni empírica ni estudios previos que los avalen (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);24(4): 594-602, oct.-dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105615</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aprendiendo a buscar en la Web of Science: réplica al estudio de Aluja, Becoña, Botella, Colom, Echeburúa, Forns, Pérez y Vila (2011)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19131^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54383</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33619^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33619^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19131^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
