<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042805</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Behaviour of vancomycin with the new techniques in haemodialysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">When using high convection dialysis techniques it arouses the necessity of consideringthe suitability of the regular protocols when administrating drugs, such as vancomycin. Objectives: To confirm if the usual guideline of vancomycin is efficient in patientsundergoing treatments with acetate free biofiltration (AFB) and haemodiafiltrationon-line (on-line). To propose an alternative guideline of administration.Material and methods: 13 patients treated with AFB or On-line. 10 of them usedfilters of polysulfone and 3 of them of AN69. First part: 6 patients were administered1 g iv during the last hour of dialysis. Second part: 7 patients were given a loadingdose of 30 mg/kg iv with a reinforcement of 500 mg post-dialysis. The blood levelsof the antibiotic were monitorized during the week following the administration.Outcomes: During the first phase it was noticed a decrease of 41% in the serumlevel of vancomycin during dialysis, conditioning subtherapeutic levels in the 83% ofthe patients until the end of the study. As for the second phase, therapeutic non-toxiclevels were maintained during the whole study. The existence of a post-dialysis reboundof the 21% was confirmed. A bigger clearance of vancomycin was obtainedwith the On-line technique rather than with AFB (176 vs 135 ml/min). We find astrong correlation between the decrease of the antibiotic and the volume ultrafiltratedwith the On-line technique.Conclusions: The usual guideline of vancomycin may not be enough with the newconvective dialysis techniques. A guideline based on a loading dose of 30 mg/kg anda reinforcement of 500 mg at the end of each dialysis could be adequate. The antibioticclearance with the On-line technique is probably made by convective transport</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mardaras, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tarragó, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Guisande, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bravo, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tato, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Donado, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Con el uso de técnicas de diálisis de alta convección surge la necesidad de plantearsela idoneidad de los protocolos habituales de administración de algunos fármacos,como la vancomicina.Objetivos: Confirmar si la pauta habitual de vancomicina es eficaz en pacientes atratamiento con biofiltración libre de acetato (AFB) y hemodiafiltración en línea(On-line). Proponer una pauta alternativa de administración.Materiales y métodos: Trece pacientes a tratamiento con AFB u On-line. Diez utilizabanfiltros de polisulfona y 3 de AN69. Primera parte: a 6 pacientes se les administró1 g iv de vancomicina en la última hora de diálisis. Segunda parte: a 7 pacientesse les administró una dosis de ataque de 30 mg/kg iv durante las dos últimas horas dediálisis, con un refuerzo de 500 mg post-diálisis. Se hizo un seguimiento de los nivelessanguíneos del antibiótico durante la semana siguiente a la administración.Resultados: En la primera fase se observó un descenso del 41% de los niveles séricosde vancomicina durante la diálisis, condicionando niveles subterapéuticos enel 83% de los pacientes hasta el final del estudio. Durante la segunda fase se consiguiómantener niveles terapéuticos y no tóxicos durante todo el estudio. Se confirmóla existencia de un rebote post-diálisis del 21%. Con la técnica de On-line se conseguíaun mayor aclaramiento de vancomicina que con AFB (176 vs 135 ml/min). Encontramosuna fuerte correlación entre el descenso del antibiótico y el volumen ultrafiltradocon la técnica de On-line.Conclusiones: La pauta habitual de vancomicina puede resultar insuficiente enpacientes a tratamiento con On-line y AFB. Podría ser adecuada una pauta basadaen una dosis de ataque de 30 mg/kg y un refuerzo de 500 mg al final de cada diálisis.Posiblemente el aclaramiento de este antibiótico con la técnica de On-line seproduzca por transporte convectivo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;25(5): 527-534, sept.-oct. 2005. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042805</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comportamiento de la vancomicina con las nuevas técnicas de diálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23504^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23504^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
