<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136530</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of infectious diseases in al-Andalus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The treatment used in Islamic Spain, al-Andalus, for a number of infectious diseases such as leprosy, tuberculosis, gonococcal disease, diarrhea, smallpox, measles, parasitic diseases, etc., is reviewed briefly. The different remedies of plant, animal and mineral extracts employed by renowned physicians of the time, such as Isaac, Arib ibn Said, Abulcasis, al-Gafiqi and Averroes among others, are analyzed briefly to provide an understanding of the approach to the treatment of infectious diseases nowadays known to be caused by microorganisms (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casal, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casal, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se pasa revista al tratamiento de una serie de enfermedades infecciosas que se presentaban en al-Andalus, como la lepra, la tuberculosis, la gonococia, diarreas, la viruela, el sarampión, parasitosis intestinales, etc. Para ello se analizan los muy diversos remedios, vegetales, animales o minerales, que usaron los afamados médicos de esa época, como Isaac, Arib ibn Said, Abulcasis, al-Gafiqi y Averroes entre otros. Con todo ello podemos hacernos una idea de lo que en aquellos años se pensaba acerca del tratamiento de las enfermedades que hoy sabemos causadas por microorganismos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;17(4): 350-356, dic. 2004. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136530</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El tratamiento de las enfermedades infecciosas en al-Andalus</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38876</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
