<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90349</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">High exposure to antibiotics in the population and differences by sex and age</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To determine antibiotic use and its distribution by age and gender, as well as the mostprescribed therapeutic group.Design: Observational descriptive with retrospective data.Settings and participants: Population from the Lleida (Spain) Health Region receiving antibioticprescriptions from 2002 to 2007.Measurements: Daily Dose Per Inhabitant (DID) was calculated, as well as the number of patientsunder treatment. The study variables were: age, gender, number of patients under antibiotictreatment and pharmacological group.Results: Mean prevalence of patients receiving antibiotics was 36.93% (33.51% in men and40.42% in women). The DID in Lleida during 2007 is 23.52. The majority (56%) had receivedantibiotics once a year. The antibiotic consumption prevalence has a &#145;&#145;V&#146;&#146; shape with highervalues among children and old people. There is an annual exposure to antibiotics in 58.8% ofthe 0 to 4 years-old age group. The most prescribed antibiotic is amoxicillin/clavulanic.Conclusions: We observe a high antibiotic prescription rate among children and older people,the high consumption in childhood being of note. There is also a higher use of antibiotics amongwomen and changing of prescription towards broad spectrum antibiotics(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ribes, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Godoy, Pere</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serna, M. Catalina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gascó, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Real, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galván, Leonardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar la prevalencia de consumo de antibióticos y su distribución por edad ysexo, así como el grupo terapéutico más prescrito.Diseño: Estudio observacional descriptivo con datos retrospectivos.Emplazamiento: Región Sanitaria de Lleida.Participantes: Personas que reciben prescripción de antibacterianos entre los años 2002 y 2007.Mediciones principales: Se calcula la dosis habitante día (DHD) y los pacientes expuestos atratamiento. Las variables de estudio son: edad, sexo, número de pacientes con tratamientoantibacteriano y grupo farmacológico.Resultados: La prevalencia de pacientes expuestos a tratamiento con antibacterianos en un añoes del 37% con un 33,5% en hombres y un 40,4% en mujeres. La DHD de Lleida durante el año 2007fue de 23,52. Un 56% han recibido antibiótico una sola vez durante el año. La prevalencia deconsumo tiene una forma de V en relación a la edad con cifras superiores en los grupos extremos(niños y ancianos). En el grupo de edad de 0 a 4 años un 58,8% de niños se encuentra expuestoa antibiótico al año. El principio activo más prescrito es la amoxicilina/ácido clavulánico.Conclusiones: Observamos una elevada prescripción de antibióticos con un mayor consumo enlas edades extremas de la vida, siendo llamativa la elevada prevalencia en la infancia, así comoun mayor consumo de antibióticos en mujeres de 5 a 74 años y en hombre mayores de 74 años.También se constata una desviación de las prescripciones hacia moléculas de amplio espectro(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;43(5): 236-244, mayo 2011. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90349</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alta exposición a antibióticos en la población y sus diferencias por género y edad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33384^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4422^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11742^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201105</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
