<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144764</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1837</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Selection of mono-, combination or triple therapy with olmesartan according to target decrease in blood pressure</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Achieving therapeutic targets is essential to reduce the cardiovascular risk of hypertension, ideally in as short a time as possible. The hypotensive effectiveness of the distinct drugs has been well characterized by the various studies supporting their use. Therefore, clinicians should base their selection of the drug to be used on the target blood pressure decrease required in each patient and prescribe a drug or drug combination with sufficient antihypertensive potency to achieve the desired reduction. Olmesartan is an angiotensin II receptor antagonist with marked hypotensive potency that is well tolerated and whose use in combination with dihydropyridines and/or hydrochlorothiazide has been well established. The present article reviews the evidence supporting the use of olmesartan as monotherapy or in combination treatment in the current context of the management of hypertension. Special attention is paid to determining the demonstrated blood pressure-lowering potency of this drug in situations in which the therapeutic targets can realistically be achieved; we compare this agent with other commonly used drugs and discuss the evidence on 24-hour blood pressure control, as well as the effectiveness of therapeutic combinations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Paz Bermejo, Marco Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Para minimizar el riesgo cardiovascular derivado de la hipertensión arterial (HTA) es de vital importancia alcanzar los objetivos terapéuticos, idealmente en el menor tiempo posible. La capacidad hipotensora de los diferentes fármacos está bien determinada por los diferentes estudios que avalan su uso. Por ello, el clínico debería elegir el tratamiento con criterio basándose en el descenso de presión arterial que requiera el paciente y utilizar un fármaco o combinación cuya potencia antihipertensiva permita prever que se logre el objetivo terapéutico. Olmesartán es un antagonista de los receptores de la angiotensina II (ARA II) de notable potencia hipotensora, bien tolerado y cuya combinación con dihidropiridinas y/o hidroclorotiazidas se halla bien establecida. En este artículo se revisan las evidencias que justifican el uso de olmesartán o sus combinaciones en el contexto actual del manejo de la HTA. Se presta especial atención en determinar la potencia hipotensora demostrada del fármaco para precisar los casos en los que es esperable alcanzar los objetivos terapéuticos, su comparación con otros fármacos de uso común, las evidencias en el control de la presión arterial durante las 24 h y la eficacia de las combinaciones terapéuticas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Hipertens. riesgo vasc;30(supl.1): 28-34, ene. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144764</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Selección de olmesartán en monoterapia, combinación o triple terapia en función del descenso necesario de la presión arterial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4419^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54126^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7005^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30857^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201301</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
