<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95919</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fundamentals in the clinical management of intoxication due to smoke inhalation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Intoxication due to smoke inhalation is the main cause of morbidity and mortality from fires. Smoke is a mixture of carbon particles suspended in hot air containing toxic gases. Carbon monoxide (CO) and cyanuric acid are the gases that are mainly responsible for tissue anoxia. The clinical signs of intoxication due to smoke inhalation vary. They may include eye irritation, sore throat, laryngeal stridor, dysphagia, soot in sputum, cough, breathlessness, laryngeal spasm,bronchospasm, coronary syndrome, coma, hypoxemia, lactic acidosis, cyanosis, and death. A finding of soot in the nostrils, mouth or sputum suggests severe intoxication. Lactate dehydrogenase levels over 10 mmol/L are indicative of cyanuric acid levels over 40 mmol/L. Pulse oximetry has represented an important advance for diagnosis, examination, and follow-up in this setting. The possible need for early intubation must be assessed and oxygen administration (at100%) is essential. The treatment of choice for cyanuric acid poisoning is hydroxocobalamin. This antidote must be administered promptly whenever a patient has inhaled smoke (soot in mouth, throat or sputum), shows neurologic signs(confusion, coma, agitation, convulsions), or has any of the following signs: bradypnea, respiratory arrest, cardiac arrest,shock, hypotension, lactate dehydrogenase over 8 mmol/L, or lactic acidosis. There after, management will be dictated by symptoms or complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Puiguriguer, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burillo Putze, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferre, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bajo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Climent, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dueñas-Laita, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Felices, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Frutos, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nogué, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corral, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La intoxicación por humo es la principal causa de morbimortalidad en los incendios. El humo es una mezcla de partículas carbonáceas suspendidas en aire caliente y gases tóxicos. De todos ellos, el monóxido carbono (CO) y fundamentalmente el ácido cianhídrico(CNH), son los que van a provocar la anoxia tisular. Las manifestaciones clínicas de la intoxicación por humo son variables. Algunas de las manifestaciones potenciales podrían ser: irritación ocular, dolor de garganta, estridor laríngeo, disfagia, esputo carbonáceo, tos, disnea, laringoespasmo, broncoespasmo, síndrome coronario, coma, hipoxemia,acidosis láctica, cianosis y muerte. En la evaluación de estos enfermos la presencia de hollín en nariz, boca o esputo sugiere intoxicación grave. Los valores delactato superiores a 10 mmol/L indican cifras de cianuro mayores de 40 micromol/L. Lapulsicooximetría ha supuesto un avance importante para el diagnóstico, valoración y seguimiento de estos pacientes. En el tratamiento será indispensable valorar la necesidad de una intubación temprana. La administración de oxígeno al 100% será esencial. Como antídoto para el cianuro, el de primera elección es la hidroxicobalamina. Su administración ha de ser precoz. Los criterios de administración son: paciente que ha inhalado humo (restos de hollín en boca, faringe o esputo) y que tenga alteraciones neurológicas (confusión, coma, agitación, convulsiones) y que además presenta una de las siguiente circunstancias: bradipnea, parada respiratoria, parada cardiorrespiratoria, shock, hipotensión, lactato   8 mmol/L o acidosis láctica. Logicamente, el resto del manejo será el convencional en función de síntomas o complicaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);22(5): 384-394, Oct. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95919</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bases para el manejo clínico de la intoxicación por humo de incendios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23831^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5525^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3506^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22594^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2288^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7033^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13287^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
