<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130670</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Emotional response to threatening stimuli in psychosis and anxiety disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Evolution has provided humans with an alarm system that may facilitate adaptation. Both psychosis and anxiety disorders involve danger detection difficulties. Our main goal is to compare threat responses of these diagnostic groups and with those of healthy subjects. We studied 24 subjects with an anxiety disorder diagnosis, 39 with psychosis, and 39 healthy control subjects. We compared threat and pleasantness perception using visual stimuli (human and nonhuman stimuli, either threatening or nonthreatening). Regarding threat perception, significant differences were found between psychosis and control groups. Subjects with anxiety disorder diagnosis evaluated any kind of stimuli more negatively. These results suggest differential emotional processing of diverse visual stimuli in these diagnostic groups (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Brotons, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorente, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar, Eduardo J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luengo, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanjuán, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escartí, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, José Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrero, Neus</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leal, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La evolución ha dotado al ser humano de un sistema de detección de peligros cuyo adecuado funcionamiento facilita la adaptación al medio. Tanto en la psicosis como en los trastornos de ansiedad existe una disfunción de estos mecanismos de alarma. El objetivo de este estudio es comparar la respuesta ante estímulos visuales amenazantes entre estos grupos diagnósticos y sujetos sanos. Se estudiaron 24 pacientes con trastorno de ansiedad, 39 con psicosis y 39 controles, comparando las respuestas en percepción de amenaza y agradabilidad ante distintos tipos de estímulos visuales, humanos y no humanos, ya fueran amenazantes o no. Los resultados reflejan una diferente percepción de amenaza entre psicóticos y sanos, así como una valoración de las imágenes como más desagradables por parte del grupo ansioso. Todo ello sugeriría una diferente evaluación emocional de los distintos estímulos entre ambos trastornos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);21(1): 51-56, ene.-mar. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130670</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Respuesta emocional ante estímulos amenazantes en psicosis y trastornos de ansiedad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53742</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13601</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34663</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
