<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122034</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Consensus document: Recommendations for the use of equations to estimate glomerular filtration rate in children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The appearance of the K/DOQI guidelines in 2002 on the definition, evaluation and staging of chronic kidney disease (CKD) have led to a major change in how to assess renal function in adults and children. These guidelines, recently updated, recommended that the study of renal function is based, not only on measuring the serum creatinine concentration, but this must be accompanied by the estimation of glomerular filtration rate (GFR) obtained by an equation. However, the implementation of this recommendation in the clinical laboratory reports in the paediatric population has been negligible. Numerous studies have appeared in recent years on the importance of screening and monitoring of patients with CKD, the emergence of new equations for estimating GFR, and advances in clinical laboratories regarding the methods for measuring plasma creatinine and cystatin C, determined by the collaboration between the departments of paediatrics and clinical laboratories to establish recommendations based on the best scientific evidence on the use of equations to estimate GFR in this population. The purpose of this document is to provide recommendations on the evaluation of renal function and the use of equations to estimate GFR in children from birth to 18 years of age. The recipients of these recommendations are paediatricians, nephrologists, clinical biochemistry, clinical analysts, and all health professionals involved in the study and evaluation of renal function in this group of patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escribano Subias, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montañés Bermúdez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diez de los Ríos Carrasco, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fraga Rodríguez, G. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Nieto, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gràcia Garcia, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Melgar, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La aparición de las guías K/DOQI en el año 2002 sobre definición, evaluación y clasificación en estadios de la enfermedad renal crónica (ERC) han supuesto un cambio importante en la forma de evaluar la función renal en adultos y en niños. Estas guías, recientemente actualizadas, recomiendan que el estudio de la función renal se realice a partir de la medida de la concentración sérica de creatinina y de la estimación del filtrado glomerular (FG) obtenido mediante una ecuación. Sin embargo, la implementación de esta recomendación en los informes del laboratorio clínico en población pediátrica ha sido casi nula. Los estudios aparecidos en los últimos años sobre la importancia de la detección y seguimiento de los pacientes con ERC, la aparición de nuevas ecuaciones de estimación del FG y los avances en los laboratorios clínicos respecto a los métodos de medida de creatinina y de cistatina C han determinado la colaboración entre los servicios de pediatría y de los laboratorios clínicos con objeto de establecer recomendaciones homogéneas y basadas en la mejor evidencia científica sobre la utilización de las ecuaciones de estimación del FG en este grupo de población. El objetivo de este documento es proporcionar recomendaciones sobre la evaluación de la función renal y la utilización de ecuaciones de estimación del FG en niños. Los destinatarios de estas recomendaciones son los pediatras, nefrólogos, bioquímicos clínicos, analistas clínicos y todos los profesionales de la salud relacionados con el estudio y la evaluación de la función renal de este grupo de pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);80(5): 326-326[e1-e13], mayo 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122034</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Documento de consenso: recomendaciones sobre la utilización de ecuaciones para la estimación del filtrado glomerular en niños</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7852^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3421^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6063^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53168^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
