<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164866</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pharmacokinetic monitoring of chronic treatment with digoxin from Primary Health Care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the pharmacokinetic monitoring of SDC performed from primary healthcare (PH) in patients with chronic treatment. Methods: Cross-sectional retrospective study of patients with chronic treatment with digoxin belonging to the department of a General University Hospital. Data were analized: age, sex, diagnosis, number of serum digoxin concentration determinations, date and origin of the request for monitoring, analytical result and pharmacokinetic assessment are collected. Results: 624 patients are undergoing chronic treatment with digoxin, 68% women, mean age 78.4 (39-98) years. 308 (49.4%) patients haven&#146;t analytical determination of SDC (Group 1), 183 (29.3%) patients have a SDC occasionally performed with a request from specialist care (Group 2) and 133 (21,3%) patients have CSD performed with a request from primary healthcare doctors, with an average of 2.42 monitoring per patient and year (Group 3). These are those patients who have pharmacokinetic monitoring of chronic treatment with digoxin. Of the group 2.25 (13.6%) patientes were hospital admission from emergency department for presenting digitalis intoxication with CSD&gt;2 ng/ml, and 39 (21.3%) patients for low dosing with CSD (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Matoses Chirivella, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Lucena, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murcia López, Ana Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Ruiz, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Iranzo, Emma M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Monsalve, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar el seguimiento farmacocinético de las CSD que se realiza desde Atención Primaria (AP) en pacientes con tratamiento crónico. Métodos: Estudio trasversal observacional retrospectivo de pacientes en tratamiento crónico con digoxina que pertenecen al departamento de un Hospital General Universitario. Se recogen datos de edad, sexo, diagnóstico, número de determinaciones séricas de digoxina realizadas, fecha y origen de la solicitud de monitorización, resultado analítico y valoración farmacocinética. (Infradosificación, normodosificación o supradosificación). Resultados: 624 pacientes están en tratamiento crónico con digoxina: 68% mujeres, edad media 78,4 (39-98) años. 308 (49,4%) pacientes no tienen realizada ninguna determinación analítica de CSD (Grupo 1), 183 (29,3%) pacientes tienen CSD realizadas de manera esporádica con solicitud tramitada desde Atención Especializada (Grupo 2) y 133 (21,3%) pacientes tienen CSD realizadas de manera periódica con solicitud cursada por médicos de AP, con un promedio de 2,42 monitorizaciones por paciente y año (Grupo 3). Estos son los que tienen un seguimiento farmacocinético del tratamiento crónico con digoxina. Del Grupo 2,25(13,6%) entran por el Servicio de Urgencias por presentar intoxicación digitálica con CSD&gt;2 ng/ml, y 39 (21,3%) pacientes por baja dosificación con CSD (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;41(4): 527-532, jul.-ago. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164866</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguimiento farmacocinético del tratamiento crónico con digoxina desde Atención Primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d902^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1150^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4116^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30150^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4116^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
