<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056375</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Urology before illustration. From the Urology of the Royal College of Cadiz to that of the "veneranda" gathering</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The study of the urological activity in the Andalusian occident is contained in the printed and handwritten &#147;Observations&#148; of the records of the Royal Society of Medicine of Seville and the Royal College of Surgery of Cadiz. They encompass the period from 1693 to the first third of the 18th century. By the first of October 1701, the &#147;Veneranda&#148; gathering consolidates and Philip V gives the &#147;royal warrant&#148;. The &#147;Royal Society of Medicine and Other Sciences of Seville&#148; starts its medical-surgical path. It should be reminded that all the Andalusian surgery and specially the one from Cadiz (through the Royal College of Surgeons) was present in the Royal Society. Ordoñez de la Barrera, Sánchez Bernal, Fray Ambrosio de Guibeville, Juan Lacombe, Pedro Virgili and many others were founders of this extraordinary event. Surgical training and, by extension, urological training had their root and basement in the anatomical amphitheaters (Seville 1731 and Cadiz 1728), which were considered ungodly by the Church. José Celestino Mutis (1750-53) and Pedro Fernandez Castilla (1741) excluded the university from this new movement. There was and intense relationship between Navy surgeons and the Royal Society, being members since its foundation: Guibeville (1719); Sánchez Bernal (1719); Gregorio Arias (1729); Gaspar de Pellicer (1729); Lacombe (1730); Fernández Castilla (1741); Calero (1789). The main protagonist was Luis Montero, real paradigm with projection to the next century, having a neat French influence altogether with Ramos, both of them being Beaumond&#146;s alumni (an anatomist of recognized prestige)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Solano Castro, Domingo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero de Soto, Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valencia Vergara, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ledó Cepero, M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero de Soto, Reyes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soto Villalba, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Tenorio, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Vázquez, Amalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Ossorio, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El estudio de la actividad urológica del occidente andaluz se encuentra contenido en las &#147;Observaciones&#148; impresas y manuscritas de las Memorias de la Regia Sociedad de Medicina Sevillana y en aquellas pertenecientes al Real Colegio de Cirugía de Cádiz. Comprende un período que abarca desde 1693 hasta el primer tercio del siglo XVIII. Se consolida la Veneranda Tertulia, Felipe V concede &#147;Cédula Real&#148;; es el 1º de Octubre de 1701. Inicia su andadura Médico &#150; Quirúrgica la &#147;Regia Sociedad de Medicina y demás Ciencias de Sevilla&#148;. Hay que recordar que toda la cirugía andaluza y especialmente la de Cádiz (a través del Real Colegio de Cirugía) estuvo presente en la Regia Sociedad. Ordoñez de la Barrera, Sánchez Bernal, Fray Ambrosio de Guibeville, Juan Lacombe, PedroVirgili y otros muchos fueron fundacionales de este extraordinario acontecimiento. La formación quirúrgica y, por ende, la urológica tenía su raíz y fundamento en los anfiteatros anatómicos, (Sevilla 1731) y (Cádiz 1728) definidos &#147;impíos&#148; por la Iglesia. José Celestino Mutis (1750 &#150; 53) y Pedro Fernández Castilla (1741) aíslan a la Universidad de este nuevo movimiento. Hubo una intensa relación entre Cirujanos de la Armada y la Regia Sociedad, siendo socios desde su fundación: Guibeville (1719); Sánchez Bernal (1719); Gregorio Arias (1729); Gaspar de Pellicer (1729); Lacombe (1730); Fernández Castilla (1741); Calero (1789). Siendo el principal protagonista Luis Montero, verdadero paradigma con proyección hacia la centuria siguiente, de influencia netamente francesa junto con Ramos, ambos alumnos de Beaumond, anatómico de reconocido prestigio</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;60(8): 902-908, oct. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056375</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La urología preilustrada. De la urología del Real Colegio de Cádiz a la de la Veneranda Tertulia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13883^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13901^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14972^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13885^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38876</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13901^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10055^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
