<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86182</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reversed diastolic flow in the uterine artery and thick heterogeneous placenta: predictors of adverse pregnancy outcome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Uterine artery Doppler allows an early study of trophoblastic invasion and constitutes a useful tool to assess the risk of pre-eclampsia and fetal growth restriction. Also, there are many studies that describe an association between the placental thickness and adverse pregnancy outcome. We present a case of a pregnant with a reversed diastolic flow in the uterine artery Doppler and a sonographically thick placenta that required an emergent cesarean section for abruptio placentae (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Cancela, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ricart Calleja, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vives Argilagós, Ángels</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Doppler de las arterias uterinas permite estudiar de forma precoz el fenómeno de la invasión trofoblástica y constituye una herramienta muy útil para el cribado de retraso de crecimiento intrauterino y preeclampsia precoz. Existen numerosos estudios que asocian un engrosamiento de la placenta detectado ecográficamente con resultados perinatales desfavorables. Se presenta un caso clínico con Doppler arterias uterinas patológicas asociado a placenta engrosada que requirió de finalización urgente por desprendimiento prematuro de placenta normoinserta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);54(3): 132-135, mar. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86182</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Flujo reverso diastólico en arterias uterinas y engrosamiento placentario: marcadores de resultado perinatal desfavorable</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4361</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11351^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32092^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1164^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d40^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d40^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11351^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32092^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23623^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
