<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91292</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Experiences and living experiences of women with fibromyalgia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Fibromyalgia is a syndrome characterized by generalised chronic pain in the locomotivesystem, among other symptoms. The aetiology of the disease is unknownand its prevalence in our setting is 2.4%. The quality of life of the people affectedby the disease is deteriorated and the treatment must include multiple strategies,both pharmacological and non-pharmacological. An understanding of theexperiences lived by fibromyalgia sufferers permit to design an ad hoc therapeuticplan. The paper depicts a bibliographic review to analyse the experiences, theliving experiences and what the disease means for women diagnosed with fibromyalgia.The review was carried out using national and international databasescovering the period between 1995 and 2006. The results from the review analysisyielded areas of relevance to understand the phenomenon: to be diagnosed withthe disease; pain, fatigue, and sep disorders; concentration problems, depression;a fear not to be understood, and relationship changes. This systematic review providesa further insight into the process of this disease and its consequences andcontributes towards the development of new care strategies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Marcos, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La fibromialgia es un síndrome que se caracteriza por dolor crónico generalizadolocalizado en el aparato locomotor, además de otros síntomas. Su etiología es desconociday su prevalencia en nuestro entorno se estima en un 2,4%. La calidadde vida de las personas afectadas está perturbada y en su tratamiento debenusarse estrategias múltiples farmacológicas y no farmacológicas. Conocer la experienciay comprender los síntomas permite adecuar el plan terapéutico. Se presentauna revisión bibliográfica para analizar las experiencias, vivencias y significadosde la enfermedad en mujeres diagnosticadas de fibromialgia. La revisión serealizó en bases de datos nacionales e internacionales cubriendo desde 1995hasta 2006. Los resultados de los análisis distinguieron temas considerados relevantespara la comprensión del fenómeno: recibir el diagnóstico; el dolor; fatigay problemas de sueño; problemas de concentración y depresión; no ser entendida,no se creída; cambios en las relaciones. Estas investigaciones facilitan la comprensiónde este proceso de enfermar y sus consecuencias y pueden favorecer eldesarrollo de estrategias de cuidados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;12(6): 26-30, jul. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91292</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencias y vivenciasde mujeres con fibromialgia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5325^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200907</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
