<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148379</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">COOP/WONCA: Reliability and validity of the test administered by telephone</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: The COOP/WONCA test was initially proposed as a self-report in which the answers were supported by drawings illustrating the state investigated. Subsequent studies have confirmed its usefulness as a mere verbal self-report face-to-face administered. No data have been found about its useful when administered by telephone interview. The aim of this study was to determine the psychometric properties of the COOP / WONCA test to measure Related Quality of Life (HRQoL) administered by telephone and compare them with those obtained in other forms of prior administration. Design: Cross-sectional study on a random. Setting: City of Madrid. Participants: Random sample of 802 adult subjects, representative of the adult population in Madrid, obtained by stratification from the population census. Main measurements: Questionnaire COOP/WONCA with 9 ítems included in a broader battery, administered by telephone interview. Results: The unrestricted factor analysis points to the unifactoriality of the scale, which measures a single latent construct (HRQOL), showing high internal consistency, not significantly different from those found by face-to-face administration, ruling out the existence of biases in the phone modality. Conclusions: The COOP/WONCA test appears as a reliable and valid measure of HRQOL and telephonic administration allows to assume no changes in the results, which can reduce costs in population studies, increasing efficiency without loss of quality in the information collected (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pedrero-Pérez, Eduardo J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Olalla, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: La prueba COOP/WONCA se propuso inicialmente como un autoinforme en el que las respuestas eran apoyadas por dibujos que ilustraban el estado indagado. Estudios posteriores han ratificado su utilidad como mero autoinforme verbal administrado presencialmente. Carecemos de datos sobre su utilidad administrada telefónicamente. El objetivo del presente trabajo es conocer las propiedades psicométricas de la prueba COOP/WONCA para estimar la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud (CVRS), administrada telefónicamente, y compararlas con las obtenidas en otras modalidades de administración previas. Diseño: Estudio epidemiológico transversal. Emplazamiento: Ciudad de Madrid. Participantes: Muestra aleatoria de 802 sujetos adultos, representativa de la población adulta de Madrid, obtenida por estratificación a partir del censo poblacional. Mediciones principales: Cuestionario COOP/WONCA de 9 ítems, incluido en una batería más amplia, administrada mediante entrevista telefónica. Resultados: El análisis factorial sin restricciones apunta a la unifactorialidad de la escala, que mide un solo constructo latente (CVRS), mostrando una gran consistencia interna, sin diferir significativamente de los hallados mediante administración presencial, descartándose la existencia de sesgos asociados a la modalidad telefónica. Conclusiones: La prueba COOP/WONCA aparece como una medida fiable y válida de la CVRS y su administración telefónica no supone alteraciones en los resultados, lo que puede reducir costes en estudios poblacionales, aumentando su eficiencia sin pérdida de calidad en la información recogida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;48(1): 25-32, ene. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148379</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">COOP/WONCA: fiabilidad y validez de la prueba administrada telefónicamente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28598^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54263</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33118^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
