<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-168008</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of hypertrophic pyloric stenosis:  size does matter</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To analyze the correlation between pyloric size and evolution of patients surgically treated for infantile hypertrophic pyloric stenosis (IHPS). Patients and methods. We realized a retrospective study of 109 patients undergoing IHPS in 5 years. We analyzed by &amp;#967; 2 test if a correlation between evolution time, age and postoperative vomiting and gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD), and pyloric muscle thickness (group A &gt; 4.5 mm and group B &amp;#8804; 4.5 mm) and pyloric channel length (group A &amp;#8805; 20 mm and group B &lt; 20 mm) exists. Results. There is a statistically significant correlation between longer evolution history (&gt;48 h) and pyloric length &amp;#8805; 20 mm and between  age (&gt;30 days) and muscle thickness &gt; 4.5 mm (p= 0.022 and p= 0.009, respectively). Also, 38.5% of 109 patients had postoperative emesis 2 days after surgery and 13.8% had GERD for a median time of 8.27 months (1-12 months), showing that there is a statistically significant correlation (p= 0.007) between pyloric channel length &amp;#8805; 20 mm and postoperative emesis. It was not observed correlation between pyloric thickness and length and GERD. Conclusions. It has been observed that there is correlation between pyloric length &amp;#8805; 20 mm and postoperative emesis. However, it has not been observed regarding the pyloric muscle thickness. A longer preoperative evolution and age &gt; 30 days are correlated to channel length  &amp;#8805; 20 mm and muscle thickness &gt; 4.5 mm, respectively (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez García, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Ruiz, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elías Pollina, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Atuán, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Siles Hinojosa, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bragagnini Rodríguez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Analizar la relación entre el tamaño del píloro y la evolución de los pacientes intervenidos de estenosis hipertrófica del píloro (EHP). Pacientes y métodos. Estudio retrospectivo de 109 pacientes intervenidos de EHP en 5 años. Se analiza mediante el test de ji al cuadrado si existe relación entre las horas de evolución, la edad y los vómitos y reflujo gastroesofágico (RGE) postoperatorios, con el grosor muscular pilórico (grupo A &gt; 4,5 mm y grupo B &amp;#8804; 4,5 mm) y la longitud del canal pilórico (grupo A &amp;#8805; 20 mm y grupo B &lt; 20 mm). Resultados. Existe una relación estadísticamente significativa entre el mayor tiempo de evolución (&gt;48 h) y la longitud del píloro &amp;#8805; 20 mm y entre la edad (&gt;30 días) y el grosor muscular &gt; 4,5 mm, con una p= 0,022 y p= 0,009, respectivamente. Asimismo, de los 109 pacientes, el 38,5% presentó algún vómito durante los 2 días posteriores a la intervención y el 13,8% presentó RGE durante un tiempo medio de 8,27 meses (1-12 meses), demostrándose que existe relación entre una longitud pilórica &amp;#8805; 20  mm y la presencia de vómitos postoperatorios, siendo estadísticamente significativo (p= 0,007). No encontramos una relación estadísticamente significativa entre el grosor y la longitud del píloro con el RGE. Conclusiones. Se ha observado que existe relación entre una longitud del canal pilórico &amp;#8805; 20 mm y los vómitos postoperatorios, sin embargo,  no se ha observado relación con el grosor muscular pilórico. Pese a ello, un mayor tiempo de evolución y una edad &gt; 30 días sí están relacionados con la longitud &amp;#8805; 20 mm y el grosor muscular &gt; 4,5 mm, respectivamente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;30(3): 142-145, jul. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-168008</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la estenosis hipertrófica del píloro:  el tamaño sí importa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24004^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15241^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12143^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24004^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38621^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201707</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
