<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79992</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Atrial septal defect with severe pulmonary hypertension in elderly patients: usefulness of transient balloon occlusion</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In patients with an atrial septal defect and severe pulmonary hypertension, it is important to determine whether the latter is reversible before percutaneous or surgical closure. In addition to determining pulmonary resistance, one simple technique is to transiently occlude the septal defect using a balloon catheter and to evaluate the hemodynamic response. We defined a positive response as a &amp;#8805;25% reduction in mean pulmonary artery pressure during occlusion relative to the basal level, without a fall in systemic pressure or an increase in ventricular end-diastolic pressure. The study included five patients aged over 60 years with an atrial septal defect and severe pulmonary hypertension who were referred for percutaneous closure. In one patient, the test gave a negative result and closure of the atrial septal defect was not performed. In the remaining four, closure was indicated. In three patients, closure was performed percutaneously, while the fourth underwent surgery. The drop in pulmonary pressure observed during the test was maintained over the long term at a mean follow-up time of 22 months (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Galeote, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliver, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Sendón, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Recalde, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Valero, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los pacientes con comunicación interauricular e hipertensión pulmonar severa, es importante valorar su reversibilidad antes del cierre percutáneo o quirúrgico. Además del cálculo de las resistencias pulmonares, una técnica sencilla es el cierre temporal con balón de la comunicación interauricular y valorar la respuesta hemodinámica. Definimos como respuesta positiva el descenso de la presión pulmonar media durante la oclusión &amp;#8805; 25% respecto a la basal, sin un descenso de la sistémica y sin elevación de las presiones telediastólicas ventriculares. Estudiamos a 5 pacientes mayores de 60 años con comunicación interauricular e hipertensión pulmonar severa remitidos para cierre percutáneo. En una paciente el test resultó negativo y no se cerró la comunicación interauricular. En los otros 4 pacientes se indicó el cierre, que fue percutáneo en 3 y quirúrgico en 1. El descenso de la presión pulmonar observado durante el test se mantuvo a largo plazo, con un seguimiento medio de 22 meses (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;63(7): 860-864, jul. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79992</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comunicación interauricular con hipertensión pulmonar severa en pacientes de edad avanzada: utilidad de la oclusión transitoria con balón</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35394^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7155^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35394^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35394^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7155^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23275^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7155^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23233^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7155^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6590^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201007</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
