<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115132</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Severe mitral regurgitation following resection of a giant atrial myxoma: case report and literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Evaluation of the competence of a mitral valve can often be impossible in the clinical setting of a giant atrial myxoma. A 50-year-old woman with severe mitral regurgitation in the post-bypass period following a myxoma resection was managed with a mitral valve replacement. The absence of mitral insufficiency in the preoperative examination should not be taken as a reliable predictor of normal valve function. So herein, we discuss the role of the intraoperative echocardiographic examination, the underlying mechanisms, and the proposed management of severe mitral regurgitation following the resection of an atrial myxoma(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Osorio Esquivel, J. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abello Sánchez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orozco Vinasco, D. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La evaluación de la competencia de la válvula mitral puede ser imposible en el escenario de un mixoma auricular gigante. Presentamos el caso de una paciente de 50 años, que sufrió insuficiencia mitral severa en el período posderivación cardiopulmonar, tras resección de un mixoma auricular izquierdo, que precisó recambio valvular. La ausencia de insuficiencia mitral en el examen ecocardiográfico preoperatorio no debe ser tomada como un predictor fiable de una función valvular adecuada. Discutimos el papel del ecocardiograma intraoperatorio, los mecanismos fisiopatológicos y el tratamiento propuesto de la insuficiencia mitral severa, después de la resección del mixoma(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;60(7): 403-406, ago.-sept. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115132</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Insuficiencia mitral severa posresección de mixoma auricular gigante: presentación de un caso y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31496^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23233^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31496^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23233^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9133^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9425^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9425^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9425^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9133^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23233^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9133^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31496^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
