<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162335</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Global clinical benefits of cognitivebehavioral therapy for insomnia and mindfulness-based therapy applied to fibromyalgia: systematic review and meta-analysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cognitive-behavioral therapy focused on insomnia (CBT-I) is useful to improve sleep and other manifestations of fibromyalgia (FM). It has also been suggested that mindfulness-based therapy (MBT) may help alleviate insomnia, but it is unknown whether its clinical benefits are higher than CBT-I on FM. This review analyzes the value of the MBT to address sleep, pain, depression and impairment in FM and its differential efficacy regarding CBT-I. The MEDLINE, PsyARTICLES, SCOPUS and Cochrane Library databases for the period 2000-2015 were examined, and randomized controlled trials that implemented CBT-I or MBT in patients with FM were selected, and 11 studies were identified. CBT-I achieved higher changes than MBT in sleep but lower changes in pain, and both therapies achieved significant  improvements in depression and impairment, although favorable magnitude to CBT-I. The possibility of extending the clinical benefits that enable CBT-I on the FM incorporating the principles of mindfulness is suggested (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez, M Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miró, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Ana I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La terapia cognitivo conductual centrada en el insomnio (TCC-I) resulta de utilidad para mejorar el sueño y otras manifestaciones de la fibromialgia (FM). Asimismo, se ha sugerido que la terapia basada en conciencia plena (TBCP) puede contribuir a atenuar el insomnio, pero se desconoce si comporta mayores beneficios clínicos que la TCC-I en la FM. Esta revisión analiza el valor de la TBCP para abordar el sueño, el dolor, la depresión y el deterioro en la FM y su eficacia diferencial respecto a la TCC-I. Se examinaron las bases de datos MEDLINE, PsyARTICLES, SCOPUS y Cochrane Library en el período 2000-2015 y se seleccionaron los ensayos controlados aleatorizados que hubieran aplicado TCC-I o TBCP en pacientes con FM, identificándose 11 estudios. La TCC-I logró cambios superiores a los de la TBCP en el sueño pero inferiores en el dolor, y ambas terapias consiguieron mejorías importantes en depresión y deterioro, aunque de magnitud favorable a la TCC-I. Se sugiere la posibilidad de extender los beneficios clínicos que posibilita la TCC-I en la FM incorporando los principios de conciencia plena (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;24(3): 459-480, 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162335</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Beneficios clínicos globales de la terapia cognitivo conductual para el insomnio y de la terapia basada en conciencia plena aplicadas a la fibromialgia: revisión sistemática y metaanálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30967</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55384^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
