<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94735</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Differential diagnosis of encephalitis due to anti-NMDA receptor antibodies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Anti-NMDA receptor (NMDAR) encephalitis usually develops as a multistage syndrome with a broad differential diagnosis.Patients: We report 2 patients with anti-NMDAR encephalitis and a clinical picture typical of this disorder but whose initial evaluation suggested other aetiologies.Discussion: The frequent development of this disorder in young individuals presenting with psychiatric manifestations often suggests other diagnostic possibilities, most commonly viral encephalitis, psychiatric disorders, and neuroleptic malignant syndrome. In addition, several less clearly defined syndromes or descriptively reported disorders in adult and paediatric patients were likely cases of anti-NMDAR encephalitis. Conclusions: Anti-NMDAR encephalitis should be considered in young individuals with subacute presentation of psychiatric symptoms, abnormal movements, and autonomic dysfunction. The clinical and immunological characterization of this disorder has lead to the identification of new antibodies that affect memory, learning, behaviour and psychosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dalmau, j</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosenfeld, M. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Valcárcel, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La encefalitis por anticuerpos contra el receptor de NMDA (NMDAR) suele desarrollarse como un síndrome característico de evolución multifásica y diagnóstico diferencial amplio. Pacientes: Presentamos a 2 pacientes diagnosticadas de encefalitis por anticuerpos NMDAR con un cuadro clínico típico, pero que inicialmente señaló otras etiologías. Discusión:La afectación frecuente de pacientes jóvenes con manifestaciones psiquiátricas prominentes indica frecuentemente otras consideraciones diagnósticas; las más frecuentes son las encefalitis virales, los procesos psiquiátricos y el síndrome neuroléptico maligno. Varios síndromes previamente definidos de manera parcial o descriptiva en adultos y pacientes pediátricos probablemente eran casos de encefalitis anti-NMDAR.Conclusiones: La encefalitis anti-NMDAR debe considerarse en pacientes jóvenes con manifestaciones psiquiátricas subagudas, movimientos anormales y alteraciones autonómicas. La caracterización clínica e inmunológica de esta enfermedad ha llevado a la identificación de nuevos anticuerpos que afectan a procesos de memoria, aprendizaje, conducta y psicosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;25(7): 409-413, sept. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94735</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico diferencial en la encefalitis por anticuerpos contra el receptor NMDA</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30889^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32264^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4736^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9650^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
