<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138651</identifier>
<setSpec>2014-9832</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The evaluation of clinical skills is an important part of the medical training. The present article describes the results of a pilot study that was carried out to analyze the feasibility of the implementation of the Mini-Clinical Evaluation Exercise (mini-CEX) in medical students. Subjects and methods. Mini-CEX was used in students from third, fourth and fifth year of Medical School of the University of Barcelona during their clerkship in Internal Medicine, Pneumology/Thoracic surgery, Nephrology/Urology in the academic year 2013-2014. Students completed at least one encounter and several tutors from different departments participated in the study. Results. Thirteen tutors and 27 students participated, with 64 encounters and a mean of 2.4 encounters by student. The mean time of the encounters was 8.4 min (range: 4-60 min) and of the feedback period of 8.4 min (range: 3-30 min). The mean score of students&#146; satisfaction (9.2; range: 6-10) was higher than of the tutors (8.8; range: 7-10). Conclusions. The study showed the feasibility of mini-CEX in medical students regarding the time needed to perform it and the satisfaction of tutors and students with the experience (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gomar-Sancho, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palés-Argullós, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grau-Junyent, Josep M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sentí, Mariano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baños, Josep E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La evaluación de la competencia clínica constituye un importante elemento de la formación médica. En el presente artículo se presentan los resultados de un estudio piloto para evaluar la factibilidad del empleo del Mini-Clinical Evaluation Exercise (mini-CEX) en estudiantes de grado de medicina. Sujetos y métodos. Se utilizó el mini-CEX en estudiantes de tercer, cuarto y quinto cursos de la Facultad de Medicina de la Universitat de Barcelona durante las prácticas clínicas de semiología y propedéutica, neumología/cirugía torácica y nefrología/urología en el curso académico 2013-2014. Los estudiantes completaron al menos una evaluación y participaron diversos profesores de los departamentos correspondientes. Resultados. Participaron 13 tutores y 27 estudiantes, con un total de 64 observaciones y una media de 2,4 observaciones por estudiante. El tiempo medio empleado en cada una de ellas fue de 14 min (rango: 4-60 min) y en el período de feedback, de 8,4 min (rango: 3-30 min). La satisfacción media de los estudiantes (9,2; rango: 6-10) fue superior a la de los tutores (8,8; rango: 7-10). Conclusiones. El estudio demostró la factibilidad del empleo del mini-CEX en estudiantes de medicina en cuanto al tiempo empleado para realizarlo y en la satisfacción de los participantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Fund. Educ. Méd. (Ed. impr.);18(2): 155-160, mar.-abr. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138651</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El mini-CEX como instrumento de evaluación de la competencia clínica. Estudio piloto en estudiantes de medicina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13724^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
