<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162105</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevention of postoperative nausea and vomiting with dimenhydrinate in outpatients with moderate risk (as scale Apfel) undergoing laparoscopic cholecystectomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Postoperative nausea and vomiting (PONV) is one of the main problems associated with surgical procedures. Currently these episodes still occur in 20-30 % of patients who undergo an surgery. In addition to the high degree of discomfort that this problem can be generated in patients, they may lead to other negative consequences such as dehydration and electrolyte disturbances by recurrent vomiting, evisceration or wound dehiscence due to mechanical effort, delay in reinstating the oral diet, delayed discharge in outpatient surgery units, etc. (1-3). All of these complications are also an increase in spending health (2,3). Objective and methods: The evidence shows that the most effective drugs are: droperidol, ondansetron and dexamethasone. Our study seeks to deepen the unders-tanding of antiemetic drugs less used as dimenhydrinate, in order to provide new alternatives with a good cost / effectiveness in the case of PONV. This has been compared the dimenhydrinate combination + dexamethasone versus dexamethasone + ondansetron for the prevention of PONV in outpatients undergoing laparoscopic cholecystectomy moderate risk according to the scale of Apfel. Results: In this study we have observed no significant differences in both groups in both efficacy and safety. Conclusion: We can conclude that dimenhydrinate is a good alternative for the prevention of PONV in moderate-risk patients who require dual therapy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López González, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Illodo Miramontes, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Picallo Vieito, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Álvarez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Higuera Arévalo, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amate Penal, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las náuseas y vómitos postoperatorios (NVPO) constituyen uno de los principales problemas asociados a las intervenciones quirúrgicas. En la actualidad, estos episodios se siguen produciendo en un 20-30 % de los pacientes que son sometidos a una intervención quirúrgica. Además del alto grado de disconfort que este problema puede generar en los pacientes, pueden acarrear otras consecuencias negativas como deshidratación y alteraciones hidroelectrolíticas por vómitos recurrentes, evisceración o dehiscencia de suturas debido a la mecánica del esfuerzo, retraso en la reinstauración de la dieta por vía oral, retraso del alta en las unidades de cirugía ambulatoria, etc. (1-3). Todas estas complicaciones suponen también un aumento del gasto sanitario (2,3). Material y métodos: La evidencia actual muestra que los fármacos más efectivos son droperidol, ondansetrón y dexametasona. Nuestro estudio trata de profundizar en el conocimiento de los fármacos antieméticos menos usados, como el dimenhidrinato, con el fin de proporcionar nuevas alternativas con una buena relación coste/efectividad para la prevención de las NVPO. Para ello se han comparado la combinación dimenhidrinato + dexametasona frente a ondasentrón + dexametasona para la prevención de las NVPO en pacientes de riesgo moderado según la escala de Apfel, intervenidos de colecistectomía laparoscópica en régimen ambulatorio. Resultados: En este estudio no se han observado diferencias significativas en ambos grupos, tanto en la eficacia como en la seguridad. Conclusión: Podemos concluir que el dimenhidrinato es una buena alternativa para la prevención de las NVPO en pacientes de riesgo moderado que precisan una doble terapia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;22(1): 15-20, ene.-mar. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162105</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevención de las náuseas y vómitos postoperatorios con dimenhidrinato en pacientes con riesgo moderado (según escala de Apfel) intervenidos de colecistectomía laparoscópica en régimen ambulatorio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2816^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4155^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30788^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33763^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
