<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97712</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vaginal and uterine metastases from colon cancer: an exceptional combination</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Both vaginal and uterine metastases from colon cancer are rare. The co-occurrence of both entities is exceptional. After the most common causes of genital bleeding have been excluded, a diagnosis of metastasis should be considered in women with abnormal vaginal bleeding and a history of cancer. Because of the rarity of these cases, there are no established treatment guidelines or survival data. The factor with the greatest influence on a worse prognosis seems to be the presence of uterine metastasis, which is almost always associated with widespread metastatic disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guinarte Paz, Genoveva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moral Santamarina, Eloy</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferreiro García, Esteban</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Bol, Liliana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las metástasis vaginales de cáncer de colon son raras. Lo mismo sucede con las metástasis uterinas. La coincidencia de ambas es excepcional. Después de ser descartadas las causas más frecuentes de sangrado genital, se ha de considerar el diagnóstico de metástasis ante un sangrado anormal en una mujer con antecedente de cáncer. Debido a la rareza de estos casos, no existen pautas de tratamiento establecidas ni datos de supervivencia. Lo que más parece ensombrecer el pronóstico es la presencia de una metástasis uterina que casi siempre está asociada a enfermedad metastásica generalizada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);55(2): 85-88, ene.-mar. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97712</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Metástasis vaginal y uterina de un cáncer de colon: una combinación excepcional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29341^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3142^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29341^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11693^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11693^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11693^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11693^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
