<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046755</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The «Institute for Scientific Information» journal selection criteria. Its application to Archivos de la Sociedad Española de Oftalmología</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Application of Institute for Scientific Information (ISI) Journal Selection Criteria (JSC) to Archives of the Spanish Society of Ophthalmology. Methodology: Information about the journal, as well as instructions for authors, were sampled through 24 issues (2003-2004). ISI criteria were converted into quantitative indicators and applied to the journal in question and by extension to other Spanish medical journals. Results: Compliance with international standards: Article titles (means of 7.3 keywords, 2 descriptors, 1.4 MeSH headings), author affiliation (included in 100% of cases, 21% error rate), bibliographic references (12% error rate in abbreviated journal titles), titles in English (8% translation error rate), abstracts (196 words average, 100% structured), keywords (4 words average, 1.2 coincidence with MeSH). External peer-review system is mentioned but no annual information is given on results. There was a 228-day delay on average between reception and acceptance and a 35-day delay between acceptance and publication. The journal covers 87% of ophthalmology research articles published in Spain. International scope: 57% of editorial board members publish in international journals of impact. National scope, but low presence (11%) of foreign authors. Citations to relevant international literature accredited by ISI journals are included. The journal appears in leading biomedical databases. Citations: 133 international citations between 1998 and 2005. Its impact factor potential (0.165) is superior to the last journals listed in the JCR under the heading of «Ophthalmology». Editorial board citations: 261 for the 2000-2004 period. Conclusions: Archives is an excellent means of communicating research results. It is the dominant dissemination channel for published and visible ophthalmology in Spain. Its international projection is good and the impact of its contents shows promising results</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Delgado López-Cózar, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Contreras, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Pérez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Aplicación de los criterios para la selecciónde revistas científicas del Institute for ScientificInformation (ISI) a Archivos de la SociedadEspañola de OftalmologíaMétodos: Muestra de 24 números (2003-2004), lainformación sobre la revista y sus instrucciones aautores. Se transforman los criterios del ISI en indicadorescuantitativos para su aplicación a la revistaestudiada y por extensión aplicable también a lasrevistas médicas españolasResultados: Cumplimiento estándares internacionales:Títulos artículos (media de 7,3 palabras claves,2 descriptores, 1,4 términos MeSH), filiaciónautores (se incluye en el 100% de los casos, tasa deerror del 21%), referencias bibliográficas (tasa deerror del 12% en títulos abreviados de revistas),títulos en inglés (tasa de error del 8% en traducción),abstract (media de 196 palabras, 100%estructurados), palabras claves (media de 4 palabras,1,2 coincidentes con MeSH). Se declara sistemade revisión externo por pares, pero no se dainformación anual sobre los resultados. Demora descontenentrerecepción-aceptación de artículos de 228 díasy entre aceptación-publicación de 35. Cobertura del87% de la oftalmología publicada en España. Internacionalidad:Equipo editorial publica el 57% desus trabajos en revistas internacionales de impacto.Cobertura nacional y escasa presencia de autoresextranjeros (11%). Cita la literatura internacionalrelevante y homologada con revistas ISI. Recogidaen las principales bases de datos biomédicas. Citación:133 citas internacionales entre 1998-2005. SuFI potencial (0,165) es superior al de las últimasrevistas de la categoría «Ophthalmology» del JCR.Citas equipo editorial: 261 para el período 2000-2004.Conclusiones: Archivos es un buen medio decomunicación de resultados de investigación. Es elcanal de difusión privilegiado de la oftalmologíapublicada y visible en España. Su proyección internacionales buena y la repercusión de los contenidosque publica muestra unos resultados optimistas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;81(5): 245-268, mayo 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046755</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de Archivos de la Sociedad Española de Oftalmología según criterios del «Institute for Scientific Information» para la selección de revistas científicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
