<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142747</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Alternative treatment for retinoblastoma: Intra-arterial chemotherapy with melphalan</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report: A 10-month old infant was referred for the study of a leukocoria of the left eye of one month onset. On examination, a retinoblastoma occupying the macular area was detected. Treatment with intra-arterial chemotherapy (melphalan 6 mg) was performed, with no further intervention required for disease control. Discussion: Melphalan is an effective chemotherapeutic agent. However, its use is limited by the systemic toxicity that may occur. Intra-arterial chemotherapy allows the selective release of melphalan into the ophthalmic artery, thus limiting its systemic toxicity. This combination of efficiency, safety and accuracy makes it an attractive therapeutic alternative for the management of retinoblastoma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martinez-Costa, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Harto-Castaño, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aviño, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Freytas, A de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barranco, H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Un lactante de 10 meses fue remitido para estudio de leucocoria izquierda de un mes de evolución. En la exploración se detectó un retinoblastoma que ocupaba el área macular. Fue tratado con quimioterapia intraarterial con 6 mg de melfalán, sin requirir posteriores intervenciones para el control de la enfermedad. Discusión: El melfalán es un agente quimioterápico muy efectivo, con uso limitado por la toxicidad sistémica que genera. La quimioterapia intraarterial permite la liberación selectiva en la arteria oftálmica, lo que limita la toxicidad sistémica. Esta combinación de eficacia, seguridad y precisión la hacen una alterativa terapéutica atractiva para el manejo del retinoblastoma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;90(10): 487-490, oct. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142747</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alternativa terapéutica para el retinoblastoma: quimioterapia intraarterial con melfalán</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8727^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12591^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12591^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12591^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12591^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12591^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12591^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4418^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4418^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
