<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113870</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Open surgery, laparoscopic Palomo varicocelectomy and embolization in children with varicocele</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. Our aim was to prove the outcomes in varicocele treatment during last 10 years in our institution regarding to the recurrence rate and reactive hydrocele in children and adolescents treated with open technique, laparoscopic approach or embolization. Patients and Methods. Medical charts of patients with varicocele younger than 17 years old were reviewed. Age, weight, surgery indications, treatment (open surgery, laparoscopic Palomo varicocelectomy or embolization), location, varicocele grade, hospital stays, recurrence, postoperative hydrocele, genitofemoral nerve damage, infection, bleeding, postoperative incisional hernia and re-do varicocelectomy were collected. Results. From 2000 to 2010, 98 boys with varicocele diagnosis were treated in our institution. Mean age of patients was 12 years. The varicocele location in all cases was on the left side. Grade III varicocele was found in 94 boys and grade II in 4 patients. Indications for surgery were high grade in 81, chronic pain in 16 and testicular hypotrophy in 1. Treatment approach was as follows: 12 patients underwent open surgery (Palomo or Ivanissevich technique), 32 underwent embolization and laparoscopic Palomo varicocelectomy was performed in 54. We found a global recurrence rate of 14.3% and an overall postoperative hydrocele of 24.5% Recurrence rate was higher in the embolization group than the open surgery and laparoscopic group. Three patients presented intraoperative bleeding in the laparoscopic group and there was one conversion to open surgery. Conclusions. Our retrospective review proves that laparoscopic Palomo varicocelectomy is a safe and efficient approach to treat varicocele in pediatric population, because of its low recurrence rate without any major adverse outcome. Due to our high secondary hydrocele formation, lymphatic sparing laparoscopic procedure should be taken into account in order to decrease this complication (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garrido Pérez, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vargas Cruz, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Ceballos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo Fernández, A. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lasso Betancor, C. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Beltrán, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escassi Gil, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. El objetivo del presente estudio es examinar los resultados en el tratamiento del varicocele en nuestro hospital durante los últimos 10 años, valorando la de tasa de recurrencia y de hidrocele reactivo en los niños y adolescentes tratados mediante cirugía abierta, embolización o varicocelectomía laparoscópica. Pacientes y métodos. Se revisaron las historias clínicas de los pacientes menores de 17 años intervenidos de varicocelectomía. Las variables recogidas fueron peso, edad, localización, grado de varicocele, indicación de cirugía, tratamiento, estancia hospitalaria, recurrencia, hidrocele postoperatorio, lesión de nervio genitofemoral, infección, sangrado, hernia incisional y necesidad de nueva varicocelectomía. Resultados. 98 pacientes con diagnóstico de varicocele fueron tratados en nuestra institución entre los años 2000 a 2010. La edad media fue de 12 años. Todos los casos fueron de localización izquierda. 94 pacientes tenían varicocele grado III y 4 varicocele grado II. Las indicaciones de cirugía fueron varicocele de alto grado (grado III) en 81 pacientes, dolor crónico en 16 e hipotrofia testicular en 1. Se realizó cirugía abierta en 12 pacientes, embolización en 32 casos y varicocelectomía laparoscópica en 54 pacientes. La tasa global de recurrencia fue de 14,3% y el porcentaje de hidrocele reactivo fue del 24,5% La tasa de recurrencia fue mayor en el grupo tratado con embolización, que en el de cirugía abierta y en el de laparoscopia. En el grupo de tratamiento laparoscópico, tres pacientes presentaron sangrado postquirúrgico y hubo una conversión a cirugía abierta. Conclusiones. Nuestra revisión retrospectiva indica que la varicocelectomía laparoscópica es un tratamiento seguro y eficaz en el manejo del varicocele en los (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;26(1): 9-12, ene. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113870</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cirugía abierta, Palomo laparoscópico y embolización en niños con varicocele</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4695^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32645^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15049^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201301</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
