<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84338</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Contribution of isokinetic dynamometry of the lumbar spine in an occupational mutual insurance company</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: To determine the discrepancy between the clinical manifestations and complementary test findings in lumbar spine disorders. Patients and methods: A total of 64 patients (50 males, 14 females) with a mean age of 45 years (range: 33-55) were subjected to dynamometric testing to determine concentric and eccentric strength of the extensor muscles of the lumbar spine. The patients presented lumbar disorders; 36 had suffered occupational accidents and 28 common contingencies. Most of the males worked in construction, while the women were involved in processing or assembly operations. Exertion sincerity was determined by REC (eccentric / concentric ratio) and DEC (difference between REC at high velocity and REC at low velocity). Results: The mean days from the start of sick leave to the moment of testing was 280 days in the case of occupational accidents and 157 days in the case of contingencies. Most of the tests (68%) registered parameters indicative of maximum exertion. These tests showed extensor deficiencies in the eccentric (50%) and concentric modalities (60%). Conclusions: Isokinetic dynamometry of the lumbar spine offers an estimation of spinal functionality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ridao, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chaler, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Müller, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer la discordancia entre la clínica y las pruebas complementarias en la patología del raquis lumbar. Pacientes y metodología: Estudiamos 64 pacientes (50 hombres, 14 mujeres), con una edad media de 45 años (rango: 33&#150;55), que fueron evaluados con un dinamómetro para conocer la fuerza concéntrica y excéntrica de los músculos extensores de la columna lumbar. Padecían de lumbalgia, 36 procedían de accidente laboral y 28 de contingencia común. La mayoría de los hombres realizaban trabajos en la construcción y las mujeres trabajos de manipulación o en cadenas de montaje. Se obtuvo la sinceridad del esfuerzo mediante REC (índice excéntrico / concéntrico) y DEC (diferencia entre REC a velocidad alta y REC a velocidad baja). Resultados: La media de días desde la baja hasta realizar la prueba fue de 280 días en accidentes laborales y 157 días en las contingencias. En el 68% de las pruebas se registraron parámetros indicativos de esfuerzo máximo. En ellos se registraron unos valores deficitarios de extensores en modalidad excéntrica (50%) y concéntrica (60%). Conclusiones: La dinamometría isocinética de columna lumbar permite hacer una estimación sobre la funcionalidad de la columna (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);20(4): 229-233, oct.-dic. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84338</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aportación de la dinamometría isocinética de columna lumbar en una mutua laboral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9971^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9972^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13515^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52443^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52443^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13507^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13505^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13505^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
