<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88327</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Asthma control. Possible obstacles along the way</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">With current therapeutic regimens, asthma should be well controlled in most patients. However, althoughasthma-related hospital admissions and mortality have decreased, the potential efficacy of treatments isnot translating into optimal asthma control and quality of life. This discrepancy may be due to severalfactors and is complex to analyze. Poor asthma control can be caused by diverse reasons such as thepatient&#146;s failure to understand how to take the medication, the presence of an untreated, underlyingcomborbid condition that aggravates the asthma, and the possibility that the patient has a severe form ofglucocorticosteroid-insensitive asthma.The present article reviews the situations in which poor asthma control occurs for human-related reasons.These situations can be due to patients themselves and be independent of the disease or can be due toinadequate intervention by health professionals in specific areas and circumstances linked to asthma. Asmall but important group of patients with asthma is also analyzed; in this group, the asthma per se issevere and is refractory to routine treatments(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Kersul, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torrego, Alfons</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balmes, Santi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Con las pautas terapéuticas actuales, la mayoría de pacientes con asma debería alcanzar un buen control dela enfermedad. Sin embargo, aunque si bien los ingresos y la mortalidad por asma han disminuido, los resultadosrelativos al nivel de control y calidad de vida están lejos de la situación óptima que sería esperablede acuerdo a la eficacia potencial de los tratamientos. Esta discrepancia puede deberse a diferentes factoresy es compleja de analizar. Un mal control del asma puede estar causado por motivos tan diversos como queel paciente no haya entendido como tomar la medicación, u otros como que padezca una comorbilidad notratada que empeore el asma o bien que sufra una forma de asma grave insensible a los glucocorticoides.En el artículo se repasan circunstancias en las que el mal control del asma sucede por razones atribuibles aaspectos humanos, los cuales pueden ser debidos al propio paciente e independientes a la propia enfermedad,o bien a un déficit en la actuación de los profesionales de la salud en aspectos específicos y circunstanciasvinculadas al asma. Además, también se analiza un pequeño pero importante grupo de pacientes conasma en los que la enfermedad en sí misma es grave y refractaria a los tratamientos habituales(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;46(supl.6): 8-13, oct. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88327</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Control del asma. Posibles &#147;piedras en el camino&#148;</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10546</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32858^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6082^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
