<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83494</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Update on the latest family of oral drugs marketed for the treatment of type 2 diabetes: DPP-4 inhibitors. Contributions with respect to other families of oral antidiabetic agents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The recent introduction of new drugs in the therapeutic arsenal for the management of hyperglycemia in type 2 diabetes has opened up new perspectives and raised hope for improved metabolic control in these patients. DPP-4 inhibitors are a family of drugs whose action is mediated by the incretin hormones, in particular GLP-1. This hormone is involved in the control of glucose homeostasis, as it stimulates insulin secretion in response to food intake and halts glucagon production. This effect, which is altered in patients with type 2 diabetes, can be improved by administering this group of drugs. The available evidence suggests that the efficacy, tolerability, safety, low drop-out rate and limited effects on weight, together with the low risk of hypoglycemic episodes, could place this group of drugs high on the treatment list in patients with type 2 diabetes. Incretin therapy provides an alternative to currently available glucose-lowering drugs for type 2 diabetes with good efficacy and a favorable profile on weight. In the studies performed to date, DPP-4 inhibitors seem safe. However, these agents must continue to be evaluated in long-term studies performed in clinical practice to ensure their effectiveness and safety profile, as well as to determine their precise role among all the currently available options in the treatment of type 2 diabetes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Guisasola, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La reciente introducción de nuevos fármacos en el arsenal terapéutico para el manejo de la hiperglucemia en la diabetes mellitus tipo 2 (DM2) abre nuevas perspectivas y esperanzas en la mejora del control metabólico de estos pacientes. Los inhibidores de la dipeptidilpeptidasa-4 (DPP-4) constituyen un grupo farmacológico cuya acción está mediada por las hormonas incretinas, en particular del péptido similar al glucagón tipo 1. Esta hormona está involucrada en el control de la homeostasis de la glucosa, al estimular la secreción de insulina en respuesta a la ingesta y frenar la producción de glucagón. Este efecto, alterado en los pacientes con DM2, puede mejorarse a través de la administración de este grupo de fármacos. La evidencia disponible sugiere que su eficacia, tolerabilidad y seguridad, su baja tasa de abandonos y sus escasos efectos sobre el peso, unido al bajo riesgo de hipoglucemias, podría posicionar a este grupo terapéutico en un escalón avanzado del tratamiento de los pacientes con DM2. La terapia con incretinas ofrece una opción alternativa a los actuales fármacos hipoglucemiantes disponibles para la DM2, con una buena eficacia y un perfil favorable sobre el peso. Aunque en los estudios realizados hasta la fecha los inhibidores de la DPP-4 parecen seguros, se deberán seguir evaluando en estudios a largo plazo en la práctica clínica para asegurar su efectividad y perfil de seguridad, así como para determinar su papel exacto entre todas las opciones disponibles en el momento actual para el tratamiento de la DM2(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;42(supl.1): 33-40, sept. 2010. graf, tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83494</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actualización sobre la última familia de fármacos orales comercializados para el tratamiento de la diabetes tipo 2: los inhibidores de la DPP-4. Aportaciones respecto a las otras familias de antidiabéticos orales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52846^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52843^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
