<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167626</identifier>
<setSpec>0367-2743</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: The aim of this study was to describe the patterns and trends of autochthonous leprosy in the Valencia Region (Spain). Methods: : We included all new leprosy cases originating from the Valencia Region between the years 1940 and 2015. Patients originating from other countries or other Spanish regions were excluded. New cases were analysed by age, sex, clinical type, occupation, and geographic distribution.Results: A total of 442 patients with presumably autochthonous leprosy were included. Incidence rates consistently declined over the study period. Mean age at onset gradually increased from 34·2 years during the period 1940-1949 to 59·5 years during 2000-2015. There were no cases with clinical onset after 2006 and no cases born after 1973. Patients were predominantly males (57·7%) and 85·4% had multibacillary leprosy. The proportion of multibacillary cases increased gradually after 1970. The majority of male patients (67·9%) worked in agriculture. Most of the cases, especially during the later periods, were concentrated in the coastal regions. Conclusions: Our findings are consistent with trends described in other regions with declining leprosy incidence rates and suggest that the transmission of M. leprae infection in this area may well have now stopped. Autochthonous leprosy in this region has had a male predominance and a high proportion of multibacillary cases. The geographic distribution and the high incidence in agricultural workers suggest that environmental factors  should be further explored (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fine, Paul EM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mol Cervera, Fátima</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Barroso, Diana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Echevarría, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez García, Inés</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos:  El  objetivo  del  estudio  es  describir  los  patrones  y  tendencias  de  la  lepra  autóctona  en  la  Comunidad  Valenciana (España). Métodos: Se incluyeron todos los casos nuevos d lepra de la Comunidad Valenciana entre los años 1940 y 2015. Se excluyeron pacientes de otros países u otras regiones españolas. Los nuevos casos se analizaron por edad, sexo, forma clínica, ocupación y distribución geográfica. Resultados:  Se   incluyeron   442   pacientes   presumiblemente   autóctonos.   La   incidencia   disminuye   de   forma   constante  a  lo  largo  del  período  de  estudio.  La  edad  media  al  comienzo  de  la  enfermedad  aumenta  desde  34·2  años  durante  el  período  1940-1949  hasta  59·5  años  durante  2000-2015.  No  se  detectaron  nuevos  casos  desde  2006 y ningún caso nacidos después de 1973. Los pacientes eran mayoritariamente hombres (57·7%) y el 85·4% con tipo multibacilar. La proporción de casos multibacilares aumentó gradualmente después de 1970. La mayoría de  los  pacientes  varones  (67·9%)  desarrollaban  labores  en  el  campo.  La  mayoría  de  los  casos,  sobre  todo  en  los  últimos períodos, se concentran en las regiones costeras. Conclusiones: Nuestros resultados concuerdan con otros estudios de otras regiones con características semejantes y  sugieren  que  la  transmisión  de  M.  leprae  en  esta  área  ha  sido  interrumpida.  La  lepra  autóctona  ha  sido  mayoritariamente  masculina  con  muchos  casos  multibacilares.  Hay  que  investigar  más  porque  su  distribución  geográfica y la elevada incidencia en trabajadores del campo sugieren posibles causas medioambientales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fontilles, Rev. leprol;31(2): 119-132, mayo-ago. 2017. ilus, tab, graf, mapas</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167626</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Declive en la Lepra Autóctona en la Comunidad Valenciana: Patrones y tendencias 1940-2015</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8096^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9359^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12797^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53481^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
