<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59543</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-0740</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The influence of excessive weight gain during pregnancy on the type of delivery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To find out whether excessive weight gain during pregnancyhas an influence on whether the delivery ends up being vaginal,spontaneous or instrumental, or a caesarean.People and method: A case-control study carried out in Barcelona&#146;sVall d&#146;Hebron Hospital in the year 2006. The study population consistedof nulliparous pregnant women at term, with a single foetus and cephalicpresentation. The cases were the women who had an instrumentalvaginal delivery or a caesarean and the controls those who had aspontaneous vaginal delivery. Weight gain was considered to be excessivewhen more than 15 kg were gained. The data was collected fromthe information recorded in the clinical history.Results: In total 317 women were studied, 164 cases and 153 controls.Of the sample, 27.1% (86) gained more than 15 kg during pregnancy.Of the women who gained between 7 kg and 15 kg, 49.5%(104) had a spontaneous vaginal delivery, while of those who gainedmore than 15 kg, 46.5% (40) had a spontaneous vaginal delivery. Ofthe total, 64% (203) of the women started the pregnancy with a normalweight. The odds ratio (OR) of the relationship between the weight gainand the type of delivery was OR= 0.908 (IC 95%: 0.55-1.49).Conclusions: Relative to the type of delivery, the percentages of spontaneousvaginal deliveries were similar between the pregnant women whogained between 7 kg and 15 kg and those who gained more than 15 kg.Therefore, weight does not seem to influence the type of delivery. Threequarters of the pregnant women did not gain more than 15 kg, which coincideswith the recommendations regarding weight gain during pregnancy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Curro-Fernández, M. Inés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conde-García, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Averiguar si un aumento excesivo de peso durante la gestacióninfluye en la finalización del parto por vía vaginal, eutócico o instrumentado,o por cesárea.Personas y método: Estudio de casos y controles realizado en elHospital ®Vall d&#146;Hebron» de Barcelona en 2006. La población estudiadafueron las gestantes nulíparas a término, con feto único y presentacióncefálica. Se consideraron casos las que tuvieron un parto instrumentadoo por cesárea, y controles las que presentaron un partoeutócico. Se consideró como aumento excesivo de peso un incrementosuperior a 15 kg. La recogida de datos se realizó extrayendo la informaciónque constaba en la historia clínica.Resultados: Se estudiaron 317 mujeres, 164 casos y 153 controles.Aumentaron más de 15 kg durante la gestación el 27,1% (86) de lamuestra. De las mujeres que mostraron una ganancia ponderal de 7 a15 kg tuvieron un parto eutócico el 49,5% (104), mientras que de lasque aumentaron más de 15 kg lo tuvieron el 46,5% (40). El 64% (203)de las mujeres inició la gestación en normopeso. La odds ratio (OR) entreel aumento de peso y el tipo de parto fue de 0,908 (intervalo deconfianza [IC] del 95%: 0,55-1,49).Conclusiones: En cuanto al tipo de parto, los porcentajes de partoeutócico entre las gestantes que aumentaron de 7 a 15 kg y las queaumentaron más de 15 kg fueron similares. Por tanto, el peso pareceno influir en el tipo de parto. Tres cuartas partes de las gestantes no superaronlos 15 kg de ganancia ponderal, lo que coincide con las recomendacionessobre el aumento de peso durante la gestación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Matronas prof;9(4): 22-27, oct. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59543</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia del aumento excesivo de pesodurante la gestación en el tipo de parto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22968</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23861^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7922^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2625^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
