<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057502</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-7823</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychological bases of drug-dependence treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There is substantial scientific support for the effectiveness of psychological techniques in the treatment of drug addiction, based on empirical    evidence demonstrating that drug use and abuse behaviours are operant behaviours, and that contingencies play a determinant    role in their explanation. Behaviour therapy offers empirically validated approaches that are considered essential strategies for    the effective treatment of drug addiction. Operant (contingency management), classical conditioning (exposure) and cognitive-behavioural    (skill training) techniques &#150;as well as their different combinations&#150; have emerged as critical components of such programmes.    Nevertheless, despite this relative effectiveness, relapse rates in the long term (more than one year of follow-up) remain high in all    types of addictive behaviours. Therefore, future research lines should aim to remedy some of the deficiencies with a view to improving    the long-term results of these programmes</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Hermida, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carballo, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Rodríguez, Olaya</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Secades-Villa, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Existe un amplio soporte científico que avala la eficacia de las técnicas psicológicas en el tratamiento de la drogadicción. Dicha eficacia    se fundamenta en la evidencia empírica que ha demostrado que las conductas de uso y abuso de drogas son conductas operantes    y que las contingencias juegan un papel determinante en la explicación de las mismas. La terapia de conducta cuenta con    tratamientos empíricamente validados que se consideran estrategias esenciales para el tratamiento efectivo de la drogadicción. Las    técnicas operantes (manejo de contingencias), de condicionamiento clásico (exposición), las técnicas cognitivo-conductuales (entrenamiento    en habilidades) y las distintas combinaciones entre ellas se muestran como los componentes críticos de estos programas. No    obstante, a pesar de esta relativa eficacia, las tasas de recaídas a largo plazo (más de un año de seguimiento) siguen siendo altas en    todos los tipos de conductas adictivas. Por tanto, las futuras líneas de investigación han de ir dirigidas a resolver algunas deficiencias    que mejoren los resultados a largo plazo de estos programas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pap. psicol;28(1): 29-40, ene. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057502</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fundamentos psicológicos del tratamiento de las drogodependencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12476</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30236^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30236^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
