<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128723</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of Continuous Positive Airway Pressure and Upper Airway Surgery on Exhaled Breath Condensate and Serum Biomarkers in Patients With Sleep Apnea</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Studies on inflammation biomarkers in serum and in exhaled breath condensate (EBC) in obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) have shown conflicting results. The objective of this study is to assess EBC and serum biomarkers in OSA patients at baseline and after continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) or upper airway surgery (UAS). Patients and methods: Nine OSA patients referred for UAS were matched for anthropometric characteristics and apnea&#150;hypopnea index with 20 patients receiving CPAP. pH, nitrite (NO2&amp;#8722;), nitrate, and interleukin 6 in EBC and NO2&amp;#8722;, nitrate, leukotriene B4, and interleukin 6 in serum were determined. EBC and serum samples were collected at baseline and 3 months after CPAP or UAS. Results: Patients&#146; mean body mass index was 30 (range 24.9&#150;40) kg/m2. EBC biomarker levels at baseline were within normal range and did not differ significantly after CPAP or UAS. No significant changes were observed in the serum concentration of the biomarkers determined after CPAP but the serum concentration of NO2&amp;#8722; increased significantly at 3 months after UAS (P=0.0078). Conclusion: In mildly obese OSA patients, EBC biomarkers of inflammation or oxidative stress were normal at baseline and remained unchanged 3 months after UAS or CPAP. Although UAS was not effective in terms of reducing OSA severity, it was associated with an increase in serum NO2&amp;#8722; (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Vidaurre, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferré, Àlex</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sampol, Gabriel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lloberes, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorente, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morell, Ferran</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz, María Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los estudios de los biomarcadores inflamatorios en suero y en el condensado de aire exhalado (CAE) en la apnea obstructiva del sueño (AOS) han producido resultados contradictorios. El objetivo de este estudio es evaluar los biomarcadores en CAE y en suero en pacientes con AOS en la situación basal y después de la aplicación de presión positiva continua de vías aéreas (CPAP) o de cirugía de las vías aéreas superiores (CVAS). Pacientes y métodos: Nueve pacientes con AOS que fueron remitidos para CVAS fueron emparejados según sus características antropométricas y el índice de apnea-hipopnea con 20 pacientes que fueron tratados con CPAP. Se efectuaron determinaciones de pH, nitrito (NO2&amp;#8722;), nitrato e interleucina 6 en CAE, y de NO2&amp;#8722;, nitrato, leucotrieno B4 e interleucina 6 en suero. Se obtuvieron muestras de CAE y de suero en la situación basal y 3 meses después de la CPAP o la CVAS. Resultados: El valor medio del índice de masa corporal de los pacientes fue de 30 (rango 24,9-40) kg/m2. Los niveles de marcadores en CAE en la situación basal estuvieron dentro del rango normal y no presentaron diferencias significativas tras la CPAP o la CVAS. No se observaron cambios significativos en las concentraciones séricas de los biomarcadores evaluados tras la CPAP, pero la concentración sérica de NO2&amp;#8722; aumentó significativamente a los 3 meses de la CVAS (p = 0,0078). Conclusión: En los pacientes con AOS y obesidad leve, los biomarcadores de la inflamación o el estrés oxidativo en el CAE presentaron unos niveles basales normales y se mantuvieron inalterados 3 meses después de la CVAS o la CPAP. La CVAS, aunque no resultó efectiva por lo que respecta a la reducción de la gravedad de la AOS, se asoció a un aumento de los niveles séricos de NO2&amp;#8722; (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;50(10): 422-428, oct. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128723</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de la presión positiva continua en las vías aéreas y de la cirugía de las vías aéreas superiores sobre los biomarcadores en condensado de aire exhalado y en suero en pacientes con apnea del sueño</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13273^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30611^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13273^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30611^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13273^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30611^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13273^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
