<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141217</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Medical-legal conduct with individuals in judicial or police custody</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The problems involved in caring for individuals in custody, as well as deaths that occur during custody, are relevant aspects of legal and forensic medicine in terms of the possible criminal, civil and administrative responsibility of health professionals and/or public or private institutions that might hold individuals in custody and deprived of freedom. The rule of law should ensure that these cases comply with state law and international agreements and treaties related to human rights and the special treatment of individuals deprived of freedom in hospitals or detention centers. Of particular mention is the medical-forensic activity regarding deaths associated with the use of control holds and/or restraint during the detention of individuals by members of the armed forces or law enforcement or in healthcare centers by safety and healthcare personnel. In these cases, both the immediate healthcare treatment subsequent to the events and the medical-forensic study should be particularly careful. These situations, which are often high profile, cause social alarm and involve judicial actions that can result in especially severe liabilities (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martin-Fumadó, Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medallo Muñiz, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nuno Vieira, Duarte</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La problemática asistencial de personas en custodia así como la muerte en custodia son aspectos relevantes para la medicina legal y forense, en relación con la posibilidad de responsabilidad penal, civil y administrativa de los profesionales sanitarios y/o instituciones públicas o privadas que puedan tener en custodia sujetos privados de libertad. Un estado de derecho debe garantizar que en estos casos se cumplan la legislación estatal y los tratados y compromisos internacionales relacionados con los derechos humanos, y el tratamiento especial de personas privadas de libertad en centros hospitalarios o de detención. Mención particular merece la actuación médico forense en las muertes en situaciones de reducción y/o contención en el momento de la detención de un sujeto por miembros de las fuerzas y cuerpos de seguridad, o en centros asistenciales por personal de seguridad o asistencial. En estos casos, tanto el tratamiento asistencial inmediato posterior a los hechos como el estudio médico forense deberán ser particularmente cuidadosos. Estas situaciones, habitualmente mediáticas, provocan alarma social y conllevan actuaciones judiciales que puede derivar en responsabilidades especialmente graves (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);142(supl.2): 12-15, mar. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141217</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actuación medicolegal en personas en custodia judicial o policial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5688^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8574</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5158</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21056^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6864^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21056^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14495^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11765^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12113</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16925^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33917^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11766^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
