<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73649</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence, personality features and microenvironment cannabis consumers adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES. To know the prevalence of the consumption of cannabis in adolescents, as well as its association with personality features, familial dysfunction and another variables. METHODS. Descriptive study, in a sample of 1568 adolescents of 12 to 18 years of high schools of Lanzarote health area, chosen through sampling by conglomerates. A questionnaire of 41 items, that included 19 items about way to think, feel or act, was used as measurement instrument. RESULTS. Forty-nine adolescents (3.1%; 95% CI: 2.2-4) consumed cannabis habitually and 166 (10.6%; 95% CI:9.1-12.1) did it sporadically. Consumption increased with the age and was more frequent in men. The sporadic or habitual consumption of cannabis associated mainly with habitual consumption of tobacco and/ or alcohol, to have consumed cocaine sometimes and to have intoxicated 5 or more times. The habitual consumers of cannabis had greater prevalence of depressive symptoms (28.6%) (OR = 3.1 respect to non-consumers; p &lt; 0.001), of familial dysfunction (27.1%) (OR = 10.5; p &lt; 0.001), and was more frequent in children of mothers habitual drinkers. The habitual consumption of cannabis associated to different personality indicators but the OR of association was superior in those related with antisocial conduct. CONCLUSIONS. The consumption of cannabis in adolescents is a problem of high magnitude, being more frequent in older men, the consumers of tobacco and/or alcohol, who have ever consumed cocaine, and in those with greater number of drunkenness (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Toledo Perdomo, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendoza Luzardo, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Báez Álvarez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrera Mateos, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Zerpa, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVOS. Conocer la prevalencia del consumo de cannabis en adolescentes, así como su asociación con rasgos de la personalidad, disfunción familiar y otras variables. SUJETOS Y MÉTODOS. Estudio descriptivo, en una muestra de 1.568 adolescentes de 12 a 18 años de los Institutos de Educación Secundaria del área de salud de Lanzarote, elegidos mediante muestreo por conglomerados. Como instrumento de medida se empleó un cuestionario autoadministrado de 41 ítems, que incluía 19 sobre la forma de pensar, sentir o actuar. RESULTADOS. Cuarenta y nueve adolescentes (3,1%; IC 95%: 2,2-4) consumían habitualmente cannabis y 166 (10,6%; IC95%: 9,1-12,1) lo hacían esporádicamente. El consumo aumentaba con la edad y era más frecuente en los varones. El consumo esporádico o habitual de cannabis se asoció sobre todo con el consumo habitual de tabaco y/o alcohol, haber consumido cocaína alguna vez y haberse emborrachado 5 o más veces. Los consumidores habituales de cannabis tenían mayor prevalencia de síntomas depresivos (28,6%) (OR = 3,1 respecto a los no consumidores; p &lt; 0,001), de disfunción familiar (27,1%) (OR = 10,5; p &lt; 0,001) y era más frecuente en hijos de madres bebedoras habituales. El consumo habitual de cannabis se asoció a diferentes indicadores de personalidad, pero la OR de asociación fue superior en aquéllos relacionados con la conducta antisocial. CONCLUSIONES. El consumo de cannabis en los adolescentes es un problema de elevada magnitud, siendo más frecuente en los varones de mayor edad consumidores de tabaco y/o alcohol que alguna vez consumieron cocaína, así como en aquéllos con mayor número de borracheras (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);34(8): 392-399, oct. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73649</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia, rasgos de personalidad y microambiente en adolescentes consumidores de cannabis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d991^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
