<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056780</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Retroperitoneal sarcomas. Report of five new cases and review of the current situation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Soft-tissue sarcomas represent a heterogeneous group of rare tumors arising from the mesenchymal cells of the connective tissue. Approximately 15% of these tumors arise in the retroperitoneum. These neoplasms are locally aggressive and the only curative treatment is surgical resection "en-bloc". The main cause of mortality is locoregional recurrence. Five-year survival is 3-58%, depending on the histologic subtype and grade.   Patients and method. Over a 5-year period (2001 to 2006), we performed surgery in five patients with retroperitoneal sarcomas. The mean age was 59 years (range, 46-76) with a male-to-female ratio of 3:2. The most frequent signs were abdominal pain and the appearance of a mass. In 2 patients, an incidental diagnosis was made during the surgical intervention.                 Results. Surgical resection was performed in 5 patients but was incomplete in two patients. We removed 2 liposarcomas, 1 leiomyosarcoma, 1 chondrosarcoma and 1 fusocellular sarcoma arising in the kidney. Locoregional recurrence occurred in four patients, requiring between 1 and 2 new relaparotomies (using the retroperitoneal approach in 2 patients). There was one death. Conclusions. Retroperitoneal sarcomas are a heterogeneous group of tumors, in which the only common factor is the anatomical location. New randomized, prospective, multicenter trials are required to apply different therapeutic options according to the subtype of retroperitoneal sarcoma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vega-Ruiz, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro-Piñero, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo-Durán, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega Olías, María Coral de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín-Gómez, Luis M. </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Ureña, Miguel A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Godoy, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los sarcomas constituyen un grupo muy heterogéneo de tumores infrecuentes que se originan a partir de las células mesenquimales localizadas en el tejido conectivo. De éstos, el 15% es de localización retroperitoneal. Son tumores localmente agresivos cuyo único tratamiento curativo es la resección quirúrgica en bloque con márgenes libres. La principal causa de muerte es la recidiva locorregional. La supervivencia a los 5 años es de un 3-58%, y la evolución varía según el subtipo histológico y el grado de diferenciación del sarcoma.  Pacientes y método. Desde 2001 hasta 2006, hemos operado 5 sarcomas retroperitoneales. La media de edad fue de 59 (46-76) años, con una proporción varones:mujeres de 3:2. El dolor y la masa abdominal fueron los signos iniciales más frecuentes. En 2 casos el diagnóstico se realizó incidentalmente en el acto quirúrgico.   Resultados. Los 5 casos fueron resecados, si bien fue incompleta en 2. Resecamos 2 liposarcomas, 1 leiomiosarcoma, 1 condrosarcoma y 1 sarcoma fusocelular de origen renal; 4 pacientes refirieron recidiva local y precisaron entre 1 y 2 nuevas resecciones con intención curativa (en esa ocasión realizamos un abordaje retroperitoneal en 2 casos). Registramos una muerte.    Conclusiones. Los sarcomas retroperitoneales constituyen un grupo muy heterogéneo de tumores que tienen como único dato común la localización. Creemos que deberían llevarse a cabo estudios prospectivos aleatorizados y multicéntricos para aplicar criterios terapéuticos distintos según el subtipo de sarcoma retroperitoneal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);82(3): 172-176, sept. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056780</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sarcomas retroperitoneales. Aportación de cinco nuevos casos y revisión de la situación actual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12603^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12888^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3162^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12603^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12888^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30193</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
