<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85581</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Complex craneofacial reconstruction: titanium mesh, autologous bone preserved in ethylene oxide and tridimensional polimetilmetacrilate implants (HTR-PMI)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The evolution of craniofacial surgery began with Jean Paul Tessier, who in 1967 supported the use of fresh autologous bone to cover bone defects in the craniofacial area. Recently different types of reconstructions using autologous bone preserved in ethylene oxide and advanced custom-made polimetacrilate implants that have allowed more complex and esthetically rewarding procedures to patients have suffered extensive bone loss in the craniofacial area. We report our initial experience using these techniques with a retrospective analysis of 21 patients operated from January 2007 to March 2009 by a multidisciplinary team in the Hospital Militar, Centro Panamericano de Ojos and Hospital de Diagnóstico of El Salvador, who required complex craniofacial reconstruction using one or more techniques to cover the defects. The reconstructed areas have been cranium, orbital roof and floor as well as cigomatic region, anterior cranium fossa and superior maxillary sinuous. No infections or retrieval of material for reconstruction or fistulas were reported and only one post-traumatic ulcer that resolved in a conservative way. The esthetic results in the patient soperated have been considered acceptable, to excellent. As a conclusions, multidisciplinary team, combination of surgical techniques and the acquisition of advanced prosthesis material for craniofacial reconstructions has resulted in a significant advance from the functional and aesthetic point of view in areas that involve this anatomically complex area (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lovo Iglesias, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flores-Lima, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La evolución de la Cirugía Craneofacial se inició con Jean Paul Tessier, quien en 1967 preconizó el uso de injertos autólogos de hueso fresco en gran cantidad para cubrir extensas brechas óseas en la corrección de disóstosis craneofacial. Recientemente, diferentes tipos de reconstrucción utilizando hueso autólogo preservado en óxido de etileno y materiales como el polimetilmetacrilatoporoso confeccionado a medida, han permitido también la corrección de grandes defectos óseos craneofaciales. Presentamos nuestra experiencia inicial en el uso de estas técnicas a través de un análisis retrospectivo sobre 21 pacientes operados por un equipo multidisciplinario entre Enero del 2007 y Marzo del 2009 en el Hospital Militar, Centro Panamericano de Ojos y Hospital de Diagnóstico de El Salvador, en los que se utilizaron formas alternativas pera reconstrucción de calota craneana, piso de órbita, fosa craneal anterior, área órbito-cigomática y maxilar superior. No registramos casos de infección o retirada de material de osteosíntesis aloplástico o de los injertos autólogos, ni hubo fístulas. Si se presentó una úlcera postraumática en una zona de unión de tejido desvitalizado, que se resolvió con tratamiento conservador. Los resultados estéticos obtenidos fueron de aceptables a buenos. Como conclusión, el equipo multidisciplinario, la combinación de técnicas quirúrgicas y el uso de material protésico para la reconstrucción craneofacial compleja ha dado como resultado avances significativos desde el punto de vista funcional y estético ante lesiones que involucran esta compleja área anatómica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;36(1): 31-38, ene.-mar. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85581</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reconstrucción craneofacial compleja: malla de titanio, hueso autólogo preservado en óxido de etileno y reconstrucciones tridimensionales en polimetilmetacrilato (HTR-PMI)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32333^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14414</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33389^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5120^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6410^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1696^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
