<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157977</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patient safety recommendations for out of operating room procedure sedation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. There is an increasing and more complex demand for sedation for procedures out of the operating room. For different reasons, nowadays the administration of sedation varies considerably. We believe that a patient safety approach rather an approach out of corporate or economic interests is desirable. Method. We created a working group of experts within the Spanish Anaesthesia and Reanimation Incident Reporting System (SENSAR) to prepare a series of recommendations through a non-systematic review. These recommendations were validated by an expert panel of 31 anaesthesiologists through two rounds of an adaptation of the Delphi Method where more than 70% agreement was required. Results. The resulting recommendations include previous evaluation, material and staffing needs for sedation for procedures, post-sedation recommendations and activity and quality control advice. Conclusion. We present patient centred recommendations for the safe use of sedation for out of the operating room procedures from the point of view of the professionals with the most experience in its administration. We believe that these can be used as a guide to reduce variability and increase patient safety in the organisation of healthcare (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Postigo Morales, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Palli, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arnal Velasco, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Corsini, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero García, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rey Martínez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La demanda de administración de sedación para procedimientos en entornos alejados de quirófano ha crecido extraordinariamente y cada vez requiere un abordaje más complejo. Por diferentes motivos, hoy en día la atención para estas sedaciones está sujeta a mucha variabilidad. Creemos que es necesaria una aproximación a ella desde la seguridad del paciente más que desde intereses corporativos o economicistas. Método. Dentro del Sistema de Notificación en Seguridad en Anestesia y Reanimación (SENSAR) se constituyó un grupo de trabajo de expertos para la redacción de una serie de recomendaciones a través de una revisión no sistemática. El resultado de dicho esfuerzo fue validado mediante 2 rondas de encuestas siguiendo una adaptación del método Delphi ante un panel de expertos de 31 anestesiólogos. Resultados. Las recomendaciones resultantes incluyen la valoración previa, los requisitos materiales y de personal para la sedación del procedimiento, las recomendaciones para después del procedimiento, registros de actividad y controles de actividad y calidad. Tras las 2 rondas Delphi, fueron aprobadas por más del 70% de los miembros del panel de expertos. Conclusión. Presentamos unas recomendaciones para la administración segura de sedación en procedimientos fuera de quirófano centradas en el paciente y elaboradas con el criterio de los profesionales con mayor conocimiento en la administración de la misma y que puede servir como base para la reducción de la variabilidad y mejora de la seguridad del paciente en la organización de la atención sanitaria en este ámbito (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;63(10): 577-587, dic. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157977</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recomendaciones de seguridad del paciente para sedaciones en procedimientos fuera del área quirúrgica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33095^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52865^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52865^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33095^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52865^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22870</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11621^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11621^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30213^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
