<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117733</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Non surgical treatment in Dupuytren´s contracture with collagenase from Clostridium hystoliticum</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Dupuytren's contracture causes a progressive loss of hand function, being surgery the treatment of choice. The injection of a solution composed by two different collagenases, isolated and purified by Clostridium histolyticum bacteria, performs a selective lysis of collagen in the pretendinous cord. We show our experience in the treatment of the disease, by injecting collagenase in 15 patients as a non-surgical option. This treatment has proven to be a minimally invasive, effective and safe in reducing contractures in the joints metacarpophalangeal, proximal interphalangeal or both. It also eliminates the cost of hospitalization and postoperative complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Ortega, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espejo-Ortega, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Rosado, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mármol-Soler, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valera-Núñez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos-Lozada, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>De Juan-Pérez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Murillo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La contractura de Dupuytren origina una pérdida progresiva de la función de la mano. Su tratamiento de elección es quirúrgico. La inyección de una solución compuesta por dos colagenasas distintas aisladas y purificadas a partir de la bacteria Clostridium histolyticum realiza lisis selectiva del colágeno en la cuerda pretendinosa. Presentamos nuestra experiencia en el tratamiento de la enfermedad mediante la inyección de dicha colagenasa en 15 pacientes como opción no quirúrgica. Se trata de un tratamiento mínimamente invasivo, eficaz y seguro en la reducción de las contracturas de Dupuytren, tanto en las articulación metacarpofalángica como en la interfalángica proximal, al tiempo que elimina los gastos de ingreso hospitalario y las complicaciones del postoperatorio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;39(3): 247-254, jul.-sept. 2013. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117733</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento no quirúrgico de la contractura de Dupuytren con colagenasa de Clostridium hystoliticum</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4447^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38560</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33888</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31813^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
