<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158132</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-5967</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Positive parenting. Psychoeducational group of parents of infants from 0 to 12 months</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present our experience conducting a psychoeducational group of parents of 0 to 12 month babies carried out in coordination between Primary Healthcare Centre and Mental Health Services. The project is based on two main ideas. First, that the year of life is essential for further development of a child. Second, the role that the parents play is vital; their parental style may mark the growth of their children. The term 'positive parenting' is a concept that defines a healthy rising style. Other related constructs are good enough mother and enabling environment (Winnicott), secure attachment (Bowlby) or metalizing skills (Peter Fonagy) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Fernández, Aurelio J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esparza del Valle, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos la experiencia de un grupo piscoeducativo de madres y padres de bebés de 0 a 12 meses realizado en coordinación entre atención primaria y especializada (salud mental). Hemos puesta en marcha este proyectos guiados por dos ideas. La primera es que el primer año de la vida de los niños es fundamental para su posterior desarrollo. Y la segunda, el papel que juegan los padres es muy importante: su estilo de crianza puede marcar el crecimiento de sus hijos. La parentalidad positiva es un concepto que define una forma saludable de criar. Otros constructos relacionados son madre suficientemente buena y ambiente facilitador (Winnicott), apego seguro (Bowlby) o capacidad de mentalizar (Peter Fonagy) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psiquiatr. psicoter. niño adolesc;(60): 39-44, jul.-dic. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158132</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Parentalidad positiva. Grupo psicoeducativo de madres y padres de bebés de 0 a 12 meses</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4573^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29907^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2719^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35120</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2698^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31198</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
