<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155093</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Systematic review of research on teaching tennis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present work consists of a systematic review of studies related to training tennis. The articles are identified, categorized and analyzed pointing out their characteristics and synthesizing the main topics and their content. In order to do this, we have looked at two of the databases with greater international recognition, Scopus and Web of Science. A total of 87 scientific articles were selected. The results show quantitative aspects such as the authorship of the articles, the magazines where the articles have been published, the type of research, the techniques used for collecting data or the main research topics. In addition, the work includes a qualitative analysis focused on the content of the 5 themes identified: the implementation of specific tennis skills and the progression in the difficulty of learning tennis, teacher&#146;s feedback and methodological guidelines used for training tennis, the use of technological resources in teaching technical skills, psychological training to improve performance, and perceptual anticipation, decision - making and game context. Finally, the work concludes describing some practical guidelines derived from the results of the research that can contribute to the improvement of training tennis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nieblas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente trabajo consiste en una revisión sistemática sobre los estudios relacionados con la enseñanza del tenis. Se identifican, categorizan y analizan los artículos señalando sus características y sintetizando los principales temas de investigación y su contenido. Para ello, se ha consultado dos de las bases de datos con mayor reconocimiento internacional, como son Scopus y Web of Science. Se seleccionaron un total de 87 artículos científicos. Los resultados muestran aspectos cuantitativos como pueden ser la autoría de los artículos, las revistas donde han sido publicados, el tipo de investigación, las técnicas de recogida de datos utilizadas o los temas de investigación. Además, se hace un análisis cualitativo centrado en el contenido de los 5 temas identificados, que son: la ejecución de las habilidades específicas del tenis y la progresión en la dificultad de su aprendizaje, el feedback del profesorado y las directrices metodológicas en la enseñanza de la técnica del tenis, el uso de recursos tecnológicos en la enseñanza de las habilidades técnicas, el entrenamiento psicológico para la mejora de la ejecución, y la anticipación perceptiva, la toma de decisiones y el contexto de juego. Finalmente, entre las conclusiones, se presentan algunas orientaciones prácticas derivadas de los resultados de las investigaciones revisadas que pueden contribuir a la mejora de la enseñanza del tenis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;16(2): 111-124, 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155093</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión sistemática de la investigación sobre la enseñanza del tenis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27850^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
