<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113594</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of lifeguard fatigue on the first 4 minutes of cardiopulmonary resuscitation after water rescue</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the effect of lifeguard fatigue on the quality of cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR) after water rescue Methods: Sixty professional lifeguards (30 men, 30 women) trained at the University of A Coruña and the University of Vigo in Spain participated in 2 tests. In the first test, the participants were rested when they performed 4 minutes of CPR. In the second, they undertook 4 minutes of CPR immediately after rescuing a mannequin from the water. The Resusci Anne Skill Reporter mannequin (Laerdal) was used to produce a computerized record of the total number of compressions and ventilations as well as the percentages of each type of maneuver the lifeguards performed correctly and incorrectly. Results: In both rested and fatigued conditions, the participants performed fewer correct compressions (absolute numbers and percentages) as CPR continued over the assigned minutes. After a water rescue, the total number of compressions increased (when rested, 75.4; when fatigued, 84.2) (P&lt;.001), while the percentage of correct ventilations decreased (rested, 55.1%; fatigued, 34.7%; (P&lt;.001) and correct compressions (rested, 77.5%; fatigued, 63.6%)(P&lt;.001).Conclusions: Lifeguard fatigue after a water rescue negatively affects CPR quality. We recommend that a rested lifeguard should perform CPR whenever possible (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palacios Aguilar, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romo Pérez, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barcala Furelos, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abelairas Gómez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar el efecto de la fatiga física provocada por un rescate acuático sobre la calidad de la reanimación cardiopulmonar (RCP).Método: Sesenta socorristas profesionales (30 hombres y 30 mujeres) formados en las Universidades de A Coruña y Vigo realizaron dos tests: el primero consistió en la realización de cuatro minutos de RCP en condiciones de reposo, y en el segundo realizaron RCP durante cuatro minutos inmediatamente después de un rescate acuático. Se utilizó el maniquí Laerdal Resusci Anne® con Laerdal PC Skill Reporting para registrar las compresiones y ventilaciones totales, las correctas e incorrectas y sus porcentajes. Resultados: En reposo y en fatiga se observó un descenso en el número de compresiones correctas y en su porcentaje conforme trascurrían los minutos de RCP. Tras el rescate acuático, aumentaron las compresiones totales (reposo: 75,4, fatiga: 84,2; p &lt; 0,001),descendió el porcentaje de ventilaciones correctas (reposo: 55,1%, fatiga: 34,7%;p &lt; 0,001) y el de compresiones correctas (reposo: 77,5%; fatiga: 63,6%; p &lt; 0,001).Conclusiones: La fatiga física del socorrista, provocada por un rescate, afecta de forma negativa a la calidad de la RCP. Recomendamos, en la medida de lo posible, que se aun socorrista no fatigado el que inicie la RCP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);25(3): 184-190, jun. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113594</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de la fatiga física del socorrista en los primeros cuatro minutos de la reanimación cardiopulmonar posrescate acuático</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54837^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30213^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5325^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4395^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50246</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
