<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108835</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The management of breakthrough pain refractory to methadone and ketamine using a multimodal approach</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report the case of a 28 year-old patient with a giant cell sacral bone tumour with pelvic invasion for two years, who maintained an excellent functional status. During this time she was cared for by the Home Care Support Team, with two admissions to a chronic Palliative Care Unit. The patient was admitted to our acute Palliative Care Unit for the management of severe breakthrough pain in the right lower limb with 10/10 intensity, associated to severe oxicity induced by ketamine. The multiple pain crises were not adequately controlled with acombination of methadone, venlafaxine, gabapentin, acetaminophen, antiin&amp;#64258;ammatory drugs, steroids, diazepam, baclofen and ketamine. After an adequate clinical --- radiological identi&amp;#64257;cation of the origins of the pain crises, the pain was successfully controlled with a multimodal therapeutic approach. This approach included discontinuation of ketamine, opioid rotation tomorphine, titration of baclofen doses, palliative radiotherapy and biphosphonates (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barreiro Meiro, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez Olarte, Juan Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez de Lucas, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Noguera, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos el caso de una paciente de 28 años  de edad que padece un tumor óseosacro de células gigantes con invasión pélvica desde hace dos años  manteniendo un excelente estado funcional. Durante este tiempo ha sido tratada por su Equipo de Soporte de Atención Domiciliaria, con dos ingresos en una Unidad de Cuidados Paliativos de Media Estancia. La enferma accedió a nuestra Unidad de Cuidados Paliativos agudos para manejo de múltiplescrisis de dolor irruptivo en miembro inferior derecho de intensidad 10/10, asociadas a toxicidad grave inducida por ketamina. Dichas crisis no se controlaban con una combinación de metadona,venlafaxina, gabapentina, paracetamol, antiin&amp;#64258;amatorios, esteroides, diazepam, baclofeno y ketamina. Tras una adecuada identi&amp;#64257;cación clínico-radiológica de la etiología de las crisis de dolor, se obtuvo un adecuado control del mismo mediante un abordaje terapéutico multimodal. Dicho abordaje incluyó la retirada de la ketamina, rotación opioide a mor&amp;#64257;na, optimización de las dosis de baclofeno, radioterapia paliativa y bisfosfonatos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;19(2): 48-52, abr.-jun. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108835</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dolor irruptivo refractario a ketamina y metadona resuelto con abordaje multimodal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1442^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12823^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7815^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8866^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10334^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1884^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22164</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
