<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121034</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Scarlet fever outbreak in a public school in Granada in 2012</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Scarlet fever is a streptococcal disease characterized by a skin rash in children. It can be endemic, epidemic or sporadic. In April 2012, the headmaster of a primary school in Granada reported an outbreak of scarlet fever in the school. Objective: To describe an outbreak of scarlet fever, analyse its epidemiological and clinical characteristics, and present the preventive measures taken to control it. Patients and methods: A case-control study was conducted using an ad hoc questionnaire, developed or this purpose. The R program, Epidat 3.1 and Microsoft Excel were used for the statistics analysis. Results: There were 13 cases and 30 controls. The attack rate was 3.9%. There was a statistically significant difference for the variable &#145;&#145;relative affected&#146;&#146;. Conclusion: There has been a confirmed outbreak of person-to-person transmitted scarlet fever, and the main risk factor was having a relative with tonsillitis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Romero, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Diz, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Prada, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Colina López, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almagro Nievas, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Huertas Martínez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La escarlatina es una enfermedad estreptocócica que se caracteriza por un exantema infantil. Puede ser endémica, epidémica o esporádica. En abril del 2012, los responsables de un colegio de infantil y primaria de Granada notificaron un brote de escarlatina en el centro educativo. Objetivo: Describir el brote de escarlatina, analizar las características epidemiológicas y clínicas del mismo y exponer cuáles fueron las medidas de prevención que se tomaron para su control. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio de caso-control. Se elaboró una encuesta para la ocasión. Se usaron los programas R, Epidat 3.1 y Microsoft Excel. Resultados: Estudio compuesto por 13 casos y 30 controles. La tasa de ataque fue 3,9%. Solo se encontró asociación con la variable «familiares afectados». Conclusión: Se ha producido un brote confirmado de escarlatina con transmisión persona a persona, cuyo principal factor de riesgo fue tener un familiar con faringoamigdalitis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);80(4): 249-253, abr. 2014. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121034</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Brote de escarlatina en un colegio público de infantil y primaria en Granada en 2012</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13677^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28589^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28461</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12923^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13684^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
