<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043777</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-1285</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Extractions and indications of dental extractions in rural chilean population give 11 to 30 years</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: In spite of high end dental technology and the progressive increase in the amount of Dentists in our Country, the precarious standard of oral health in the rural population have stayed throughout the time, specially in ethnic groups such as Mapuche population. The objective of the present study is to describe and to quantify dental extractions in permanent dentition in rural population. Methodology: A descriptive study was performed, selecting the 100% of subjects who received dental attention at "Consultorio Chol-Chol", (IX Region, Chile). The sample in this research were formed by subjects between 11 and 30 years. All of them received complete dental attention during years 2001 to 2003. The diagnoses were made by two experienced dentists in absence of x-ray support (procedure made according to instruments and equipment available). The condition of each dental piece was evaluated excepting wisdom teeth. Results: 181 clinical card files were analyzed; 36.42% were male with average age of the sample of 18.27 years. 143 subjects presented absence of one or more teeth at the time of the examination, 117 subjects were treated with dental extractions as part of the complete therapy. At the end of the dental treatment 167 (92,2%) subjects presented absence of permanent teeth, with an average of 5.6 teeth when dental treatment was completed. Conclusion: For the sample composed by adolescents and young adults the lack of oral health reported an absence and loss of teeth. Further complex rehabilitations of their dentures must be performed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Thomas, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soto, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alveal, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuentes, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alister, JP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olate, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: A pesar de la creciente tecnología odontológica y el progresivo aumento de la cantidad de odontólogos, el precario estándar de salud oral de la población rural se ha mantenido a lo largo del tiempo. El objetivo de esta investigación es describir y cuantificar las exodoncias de piezas dentarias permanentes en población rural. Metodología: Se realizó un estudio de tipo descriptivo seleccionando el 100% de los sujetos atendidos en el Consultorio Chol-Chol, (IX Región) de 11 a 30 años de edad que obtuvieron su alta integral durante los años 2001 y 2003. Los diagnósticos fueron realizados por dos odontólogos experimentados en ausencia de apoyo radiográfico (procedimiento realizado de acuerdo al instrumental y equipos disponibles). Se evaluó el estado de cada una de las piezas dentarias exceptuando los terceros molares. Resultados: Fueron analizadas 181 fichas clínicas de los cuales el 36,42% fueron del sexo masculino, siendo la edad media de la muestra 18,27 años. 143 sujetos presentaron piezas perdidas en el momento del examen, a 117 sujetos se les indico extracción de piezas dentales permanentes. Al finalizar el tratamiento 167 (92,2%) sujetos presentaron ausencia de piezas dentarias permanentes, con un promedio de 5,6 piezas al finalizar el alta integral. Conclusión: Los pacientes adolescentes y adultos jóvenes en condiciones de ruralidad presentan alta frecuencia de patologías orales que determinan la exodoncia de las piezas dentales. Estos pacientes necesitaran a corto plazo extensas rehabilitaciones para recuperar su sistema estomatognático (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av Odontoestomatol;22(2): 119-124, mar.-abr. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043777</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Extracciones e indicaciones de extracciones dentales en población rural chilena de 11 a 30 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14473^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2722^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12797^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28452</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3745^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3745^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30057^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14473^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14473^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14473^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
