<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052384</identifier>
<setSpec>0303-8874</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sudden cardiorrespiratory arrest in adults with acute epiglottiti. Report of 2 cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report two adult cases of sudden cardiorespiratory arrest because an acute epiglottitis that ocurred in our hospital. Although it is an uncommon pathology nowdays with good prognosis generally, we try to call the attention about this complication which can happen of unforseeable way even in previous absence of respiratory obstruction. One of the patients required coniotomy in ICU due to impossibility of orotracheal intubation (OI) and the other died in spite of an urgent performance</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Palomino, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora Santos, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo Romero, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blasco Huelva, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pantoja Hernández, C. G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pino Rivero, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos dos casos reales acontecidos en nuestro Hospital de parada cardiorrespiratoria brusca en sendos adultos con diagnóstico de epiglotis aguda. Aunque se trata de una patología poco común en la actualidad y de buen pronóstico en general pretendemos llamar la atención sobre esta complicación, que puede ocurrir de manera imprevisible incluso en ausencia previa de compromiso respiratorio. Uno de los pacientes requirió cricotomía en UCI por imposibilidad de intubación orotraqueal (IOT) y el otro fue éxitus a pesar de la actuación urgente practicada</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Otorrinolaringol Ibero Am;34(1): 1-8, ene.-feb. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052384</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Parada cardiorrespiratoria súbita en adultos con epiglotitis aguda. Presentación de dos casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30213</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6475^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4906^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4906^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3431^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12552^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4906^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14530^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12552^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
