<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116026</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality of hospital discharge reports in terms of current legislation and expert recommendations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the quality of hospital discharge reports (HDRs) taking into account current legislation and the conclusions of the consensus on hospital discharge reports in medical specialities in 11 community hospitals in Andalusia (Spain). Material and methods: A cross-sectional study of 1,708 HDRs was carried out. We determined the presence or absence of the various items required by current legislation and by the recommendations of the above-mentioned consensus. Results: A total of 97.4% (95% confidence interval [95% CI]: 96.5-98.2) of the HDRs were classified as satisfactory according to the stipulations of current legislation. However, when the assessment was based on the consensus, the rate of adequacy fell to 72.1% (95% CI: 70.0-74.3). A notable finding was the absence of the duration of treatment after hospital discharge in 39.4% of the HDRs. Conclusions: HDRs show an excellent level of compliance with the data required by current regulations, but their intrinsic quality needs to be improved (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grupo para el Análisis de la Calidad del Informe de Alta Hospitalaria en los Hospitales de Alta Resolución de Andalucía</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Conocer la calidad de los informes de alta hospitalaria respecto a la legislación vigente y el consenso para la elaboración de informes de alta hospitalaria en especialidades médicas en 11 hospitales de Andalucía. Material y métodos: Estudio transversal de 1708 informes de alta hospitalaria. Analizamos la presencia o no de los diferentes ítems requeridos tanto por la legislación actual como por las recomendaciones del consenso. Resultados: El 97,4% (intervalo de confianza del 95% [IC95%]: 96,5-98,2) de los informes de alta hospitalaria fueron catalogados como adecuados si nos ajustamos a los requisitos que contempla la legislación vigente. Si la evaluación era respecto al consenso, el porcentaje de adecuación descendía al 72,1% (IC95%:70,0-74,3). Destaca la ausencia de la duración del tratamiento tras el alta en el 39,4% de los informes. Conclusiones: Los informes de alta hospitalaria ofrecen un excelente grado de cumplimentación de los datos exigidos por la normativa vigente, pero deben mejorar en su calidad intrínseca (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;27(5): 450-453, sept.-oct. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116026</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de los informes de alta hospitalaria respecto a la legislación vigente y las recomendaciones consensuadas por expertos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d55136^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3285^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5707^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54376</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10545^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
