<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120764</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perception, knowledge and attitudes of Emergency and Mental Health nurses regarding alcoholism and other drug dependencies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Nursing professionals who treat alcoholic patients in the Emergency and Mental Health units of hospitals in the Balearic Islands. Materials and method: a descriptive transversal multicenter study with nurses in the Emergency and Mental Health units of five hospitals in the Balearic Islands. For data collection, the Seaman-Mannello Scale was used, validated into Spanish, which measures the knowledge and attitudes of Nursing professionals regarding alcoholism and alcohol intake. Results: 150 questionnaires were collected, out of a universe of257. Out of these, 99.1% had become in contact with drug dependent persons during their professional experience. Almost 75% of them had had difficulties when managing them (20.6% due to lack of protocols, and 17.1% due to lack of resources). The factors which made patient care difficult were: lack of knowledge, attitude by the professional and social perception, lack of communication skills, previous experiences, organization and type of unit where they worked, and personal opinions. When they had difficulties, they consulted other professionals to clarify their doubts; only 7.1% used scientific databases as a reliable source of information. Conclusions: nurses perceive alcoholic patients as sick persons who need therapy. Lack of knowledge is the factor with the highest negative impact on patient care offered to drug dependent patients, while attitudes appear to a lesser extent. Organization aspects and place of work are also involved (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Simonet Bennassar, Margarida</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina Mula, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carnicero Viñals, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Sánchez, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilardell Balasch, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Trujillo, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nuez Aspas, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montalbán Romero, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castaño Fernández, Ana Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Medina, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Clar Aragón, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz Álvarez, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Alabarce, Juan Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gelabert Binimelis, Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: describir las percepciones, conocimientos y actitudes delos profesionales de Enfermería que tratan pacientes consumidores de alcohol en las unidades de Urgencias y Salud Mental de hospitales de las Islas Baleares. Material y método: estudio descriptivo transversal multicéntrico sobre las enfermeras de los servicios de Urgencias y Salud Mental de cinco hospitales de las Islas Baleares. Para la recogida de los datos se utilizó la escala validada al castellano de Seaman e Mannello, que mide los conocimientos y las actitudes de los profesionales de Enfermería con relación al alcoholismo y al consumo del alcohol. Resultados: se recogieron 159 cuestionarios de un universo de257. El 99,1% había tenido contacto con personas con drogodependencias durante su experiencia profesional. Cerca del 75% había tenido dificultades a la hora de atenderlos (20,6% por falta de protocolos y 17,1% por la falta de recursos). Los aspectos que dificultaban la atención eran: falta de conocimientos, actitud del propio profesional y percepción social, falta de habilidades en la comunicación, experiencias previas, organización y tipo de servicio donde trabajaba y opiniones personales. Cuando tenían dificultades, consultaban a otros profesionales para resolver sus dudas; solamente un 7,1% acudía a bases de datos científicas como fuente confiable de información. Conclusiones: la enfermera percibe al paciente alcohólico como una persona enferma que necesita terapia. El déficit de conocimientos es el factor que más negativamente influye en la atención que se presta al drogodependiente, las actitudes aparecen en menor medida. El aspecto organizativo y lugar de trabajo también intervienen (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;17(2): 22-31, mar. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120764</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Percepción, conocimientos y actitudes de las enfermeras de urgencias y salud mental frente al alcoholismo y otras drogodependencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29633</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12005^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23897</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30140^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
