<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133643</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-7823</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Considering the abundant literature specifically on the subject, what point can there be in writing yet another study that analyses the consequences of the mastectomy in women who have either been diagnosed with breast cancer previously or have a well-founded, genetics based fear of developing it at some point in the future due to the precedents in their family? In this paper, we review some notable studies on the psychological impact of the mastectomy (whether as a form of secondary prevention against cancer or as a prophylactic measure) compared to what is known as 'conservative surgery' (lumpectomy), in order to value the consensus or the dissent among the researchers. Our hypothesis is that a change of tendency has taken place in the patients with breast cancer in their perspective of the mastectomy, coinciding with the turn of the century (and the millennium), perhaps due to the widespread practice of mammary reconstructive surgery after the resection, which mitigates the trauma (imaginary, symbolic and physical) of the amputation without reconstruction (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Sánchez, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">¿Qué sentido puede tener escribir un trabajo más -dada la abundante literatura específica sobre ello-, que analice las consecuencias de la mastectomía en mujeres que o bien han sido diagnosticadas previamente de un cáncer de mama o bien tienen un fundado temor genético a desarrollarlo en un futuro indeterminado a tenor de los antecedentes familiares que poseen? Repasaremos algunos trabajos destacados sobre el impacto en el psiquismo de la mastectomía (sea ésta como forma de prevención secundaria frente al cáncer o sea profiláctica) en comparación con la llamada 'cirugía conservadora' (lumpectomía, tumorectomía), a fin de valorar el consenso o el disenso entre los investigadores. Nuestra hipótesis de trabajo es que se ha producido en las pacientes con cáncer de mama un cambio de tendencia en su perspectiva de la mastectomía coincidente con el cambio de siglo (y milenio), tal vez debido a la generalización de la cirugía reconstructiva mamaria tras la resección, lo que mitiga el alcance traumático (imaginario, simbólico y físico) de la amputación sin reconstrucción (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pap. psicol;36(1): 62-73, ene. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133643</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos psíquicos de la mastectomía (preventiva y terapéutica). Cambios en la percepción de las mujeres con cáncer de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29995^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1853^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8580^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
