<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80724</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-0921</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Knowing how many old people live alone or in the company of other elderly persons helps the social services professionals to assess the range of potential risk situations among the elderly. This study presents the procedures followed in Girona for that purpose and reveals: a) how many people over 64 live alone according to sex and age; b) how many people over 64 live alone or exclusively with other older people according to the social services zones in which the city is segmented by. Method: Municipal census data is analysed (INE - National Statistics Institute, 2005). Results: 13.94% of the inhabitants of Girona are older than 64 and 40.10% of them are males.The city has 2.795 elderly people living alone and the most of them are women (78.67%). Most of the people living alone are between 70 and 84 years old, although the rate of loneliness indicates that such a tendency is directly proportional to age, and that it only begins to reverse itselfat 94 years of age. The elderly people who live by two or more persons older than 64 represents the 37.08%. Discussion: The profile of women of advanced age living alone, as well as the growing number of households made up exclusively of elderly persons, calls for new perspectives on care forthe elderly, of which social service professionals must be properly informed and with which they must deal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salamó, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aymerich, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas, Ferran</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: Conocer cuántos mayores viven solos o en compañía de otros ancianos permite a los Equipos Básicos de Atención Social Primaria (EBASP) de los municipios, aproximarse a la incidencia de situaciones de riesgo potencial entre el colectivo de mayores así comoa posibles demandas de servicios. El presente trabajo presenta el procedimiento seguido para tal fin en Girona y dar a conocer: a) cuántos mayores de 64 años viven solos en función del sexo y la edad; b) cuántos mayores de 64 años viven solos o en compañía de otra persona anciana, en los EBASP entre los que se sectoriza la ciudad. Método: Se analizan los datos del padrón municipal de habitantes de la ciudad (INE, 2005). Resultados: El 13.94% de los habitantes de Girona son mayores de 64 años y el 40.10% de ellos son hombres. La ciudad tiene contabilizados 2.795 ancianos que viven solos y la mayoría de ellos son mujeres (78.67%). Las edades donde se contabilizan más situaciones de soledad se sitúan entre 70 y 84 años, si bien las tasas de soledad indican que la tendencia a vivir soloes directamente proporcional a la edad, no invirtiéndose esta tendencia hasta los 94 años. El 37.08% de los mayores de 64 años de la ciudad conviven exclusivamente con otra persona anciana. Discusión: El perfil de mujer mayor viviendo sola y en edades avanzadas, así como el creciente número de hogares formados exclusivamente por ancianos, plantea un panorama nuevo por lo que respecta a la atención a los mayores, que ha de ser debidamente conocido y abordado por los responsables de servicios sociales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. multidiscip. gerontol;18(1): 6-11, ene.-mar. 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80724</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ser mayor y vivir solo o en compañía de otra persona anciana. Detección de necesidades y situaciones de riesgo potencial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32193^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33920^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13330^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8308^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6863^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
