<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147854</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacy of a reconciliation intervention by a specialized pharmacist to resolve medication-related problems of elderly patients admitted to an emergency department short-stay unit: a randomized clinical trial</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine the effect on medication-related problems (MRPs) of a process of medication reconciliation carried out by a specialized pharmacist for patients aged 65 years or older admitted to an emergency department short-stay unit (SSU). Methods. Randomized clinical trial of 17 months (February 2013&#150;June 2014) in the SSU of a hospital emergency department. Patients were aged 65 years or older at high risk of MRPs. A total of 130 patients were randomized to a control group (n = 65) or the intervention group (n = 65). The reconciliation process (intervention) was carried out by a specialized pharmacist. The main outcome was the number of MRPs resolved in each group. Results. A total of 3081 medications for 130 patients were reviewed. The patients&#146; mean (SD) age was 79 (7.6) years and 66 (50.8%) were men. Discrepancies affecting 1901 medications (61.7%) were detected. The distributions of age, sex, and number of medication discrepancies were similar in the control and intervention groups. A total of 213 MRPs were detected; 110 (51.6%) were in the control group and 103 (48.4%) in the intervention group (P = .380). Through the pharmacist&#146;s reconciliation, significantly more of the MRPs were resolved in the intervention group (83.5%) than in the control group (26.4%) (P &lt; .001). Conclusions. Medication reconciliation by a specialized pharmacist in the emergency department reduces MRPs for at-risk elderly patients in a SSU (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Piqueras Romero, Clara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segura Fragoso, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calleja Hernández, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calderón Hernanz, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juárez González, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berrocal Javato, María Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar el efecto en los problemas relacionados con la medicación (PRM) de la intervención de un farmacéutico centrada en la conciliación de medicación (CM) en los pacientes 65 años ingresados en una unidad de corta estancia (UCE) vinculada a un servicio de urgencias hospitalario (SUH). Método. Ensayo clínico controlado y aleatorizado de 17 meses de duración (febrero 2013-junio 2014) realizado en la UCE de un SUH. Se incluyeron pacientes 65 años con alto riesgo de sufrir PRM. Ciento treinta pacientes fueron asignados aleatoriamente a un grupo control (n = 65) o a un grupo de intervención (n = 65). El tipo de intervención realizada fue la CM mediante un farmacéutico especialista. La variable de resultado principal fue la frecuencia de PRM resueltos en ambos grupos. Resultados. Se revisaron un total de 3.081 medicamentos en 130 pacientes con una edad media de 79 (DE 7,6) años, de los cuales 66 (50,8%) fueron hombres. Se registraron discrepancias en 1.901 (61,7%) de los medicamentos. Los grupos control y de intervención no tuvieron diferencias significativas respecto a edad, sexo y número de discrepancias encontradas. Se detectaron un total de 213 PRM, 110 (51,6%) en el grupo control y 103 (48,4%) en el grupo de intervención (p = 0,380). La intervención del farmacéutico redujo los PRM de forma estadísticamente significativa (grupo de intervención 83,5% vs grupo control 26,4%; p &lt; 0,001). Conclusiones. La CM mediante la incorporación de un farmacéutico especialista reduce los PRM de los pacientes ancianos de alto riesgo de PRM ingresados en una UCE (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);27(6): 364-370, dic. 2015. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147854</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ensayo clínico controlado y aleatorizado para evaluar el efecto que tiene la intervención de un farmacéutico especialista en los problemas relacionados con la medicación de pacientes ancianos ingresados en una unidad de corta estancia de urgencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4421^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4419</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52955^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54220^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11016^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32388</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
