<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120545</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-1637</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this article is to present practical references to determine the maturational stages in the orthodontic practice, on the basis of clinical and scientific evidence. Dental age is useful to identify the adolescence period when all four first premolars have completely erupted. When the purpose is to preview the remaining potential growth in order to plan orthopedic treatment in girls, menarche can be easily identified in the clinical exam. Menarche represents a late event in adolescence as it occurs anytime during the descending curve of the growth spurt. At last, bone age, determined by the identification of ossification centers in hand-wrist or periapical radiographs, or cervical vertebrae in lateral radiographs, is a guide to determine the best time for either orthopedic or surgical treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santos, E. C. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva, G. F. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lara, T. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bertoz, F. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Partiendo de las evidencias clínicas y científicas, el presente artículo tiene como objetivo presentar, en medio a la profusión de las informaciones académicas, referenciales simples y prácticos para la determinación del estadio de maduración en la clínica ortodóncica. La edad dentaria constituye una herramienta útil en la identificación de la adolescencia cuando los primeros cuatro premolares erupcionan. La edad de la menarquia, reservada a las jóvenes, obviamente, representa un evento tardío dentro de la adolescencia, ya que ocurre en algún momento en la curva descendente del estirón de crecimiento. Por último, la edad ósea, determinada mediante el análisis de los centros de osificación visualizados en radiografías de la mano, del dedo pulgar a través de una radiografía periapical y en telerradiografías en norma lateral, por la evaluación de las vértebras cervicales, esclarece con mayor precisión el potencial de crecimiento remaneciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ortod. esp. (Ed. impr.);47(4): 255-266, oct.-dic. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120545</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Edades Biológicas aplicables en la clínica ortodóncica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8615</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5246^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23231</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
