<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125406</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical course after five years of insulin therapy in patients with type 2 diabetes in Spain: Results of the EDIN study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives The primary study objective was to assess the proportion of patients with type 2 diabetes and an HbA1c value &amp;#8804;6.5% from the start of insulin therapy to five years later in the outpatient setting in Spain. Materials and methods This was an observational, multicenter, naturalistic study with retrospective collection of clinical data. Investigators were endocrinologists or internal medicine specialists from all over Spain. During standard clinical care, patients started insulin therapy, which was continued for at least 5 years. Results The clinical records of 405 patients were reviewed. The final analysis set included records from 346 patients. At baseline (start of insulin therapy), 51.2% of patients were female; mean (SD) age was 64.6 (9.0) years; body mass index, 29.8 (4&#150;5) kg/m2; time since diagnosis, 8.8 (6.8) years; HbA1c, 9.4% (1.5); fasting glucose, 223.7 (55.9) mg/dL; and mean 2-hour postprandial  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Reviriego, Jesus</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Angel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tofe, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos El objetivo principal fue valorar el porcentaje de pacientes con diabetes tipo 2 y un nivel de HbA1c &amp;#8804; 6,5% desde el inicio de la insulinoterapia y hasta 5 años después en el marco ambulatorio en España. Materiales y métodos Se trató de un estudio multicéntrico, observacional y naturalista en el que los datos clínicos se recopilaron de forma retrospectiva. Los investigadores participantes en este estudio eran endocrinólogos o médicos internistas de toda España. En el transcurso de la atención médica habitual los pacientes iniciaron un tratamiento con insulina que continuó durante un periodo mínimo de 5 años. Resultados Se llevó a cabo una revisión de las historias clínicas de 405 pacientes. En la muestra final para el análisis se incluyeron las historias clínicas de 346 pacientes. Al inicio del estudio (comienzo de la insulinoterapia) el 51,2% de los pacientes eran mujeres, con una media (DE) de edad(..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;61(7): 369-376, ago.-sept. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125406</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución clínica a 5 años desde el inicio de la insulinoterapia en pacientes con diabetes tipo 2 en España: resultados del estudio EDIN</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31669</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22190^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1503^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51716^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37656</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
