<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130931</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5187</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Frontal fibrosing alopecia and lichen planopilaris: are statins a pathogenic factor?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Frontal fibrosing alopecia (FFA) is characterized by the recession of the frontotemporal hair line constituting a rare form of scarring alopecia that predominantly affects postmenopausal women. Is currently considered a variant of lichen planopilaris (LPP).Objective: To determine the possible statistical association between taking statins and the development of FFA/LPP. Material and methods: A case-control study unpaired was undertaken in the Department of Dermatology at Hospital Clínico Universitario in Valencia(Spain) during a period of 7 years between February 2004 and December 2010 and included 20 patients diagnosed with FFA/LPP along with 22controls.Results: Of the 20 cases reported, 15 were on statin therapy, having been introduced prior to the development of alopecia in 12 of them. In 12patients, diagnosis was confirmed histologically. We have seen the stabilization of the disease on drug withdrawal. By statistical analysis was obtained an odds ratio of 2,16 with a confidence interval of 95% (1,58-7,44).Conclusions: According to data from our study and considering its limitations, taking a statin could doubles the risk of developing FFA/LPP, although more studies are needed to support this hypothesi (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montesinos-Villaescusa, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bella-Navarro, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pellicer-Oliver, Z. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Paredes, E. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jordá-Cuevas, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Rodríguez, A. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Hernández, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La alopecia frontal fibrosante (AFF) se caracteriza por la recesión de la línea frontotemporal del cabello constituyendo una forma poco frecuente de alopecia cicatricial que afecta fundamentalmente a mujeres posmenopáusicas. Actualmente se considera una variante de liquen planopilar (LPP).Objetivo: Determinar la posible asociación estadística entre la toma de estatinas y el desarrollo de AFF/LPP. Material y métodos: Estudio de casos y controles no emparejados llevado a cabo en el Servicio de Dermatología del Hospital Clínico Universitario de Valencia durante un período de 7 años, comprendido entre febrero de 2004 y diciembre de 2010, en el que se incluyeron 20 pacientes diagnosticados de AFF/LPP junto a 22 controles. Resultados: De los 20 casos recogidos, 15 estaban en tratamiento con estatinas, habiendo sido introducidas previamente al desarrollo de la alopecia en 12 de ellos. En 12 pacientes se confirmó el diagnóstico histológicamente. Hemos podido comprobar la estabilización del cuadro al retirar el fármaco. Mediante el análisis estadístico se obtuvo una odds ratio de 2,16 con un intervalo de confianza del 95% (1,58-7,44).Conclusiones: Según los datos de nuestro estudio y teniendo en cuenta sus limitaciones, el tomar una estatina podría multiplicar por dos el riesgo d edesarrollar AFF/LPP, aunque serán necesarios más estudios que apoyen esta hipótesis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. cután. ibero-lat-am;41(5): 210-217, sept.-oct. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130931</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alopecia frontal fibrosante y liquen plano pilar: ¿son las estatinas un factor etiopatogénico?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33014^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8186^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d508^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201311</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
