<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85624</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cerebral venous sinus thrombosis in a pregnant woman</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cerebral venous sinus thrombosis is an infrequent disease, which presents with a remarkably wide spectrum of clinical signs and symptoms (headache, nausea, seizures, focal neurological deficits and coma). Common etiologies include hypercoagulable states. In pregnancy and the puerperium, procoagulant states appear due to the physiological changes that occur in these periods. The clinical presentation and prognosis of cerebral venous sinus thrombosis varies. We present the case of a 29-year-old pregnant woman (21 weeks) who was admitted to hospital because of nausea and vomiting and who was referred to the neurology department because of a severe headache. Head magnetic resonance angiography revealed cerebral venous sinus thrombosis. The patient was treated with nadroparin and enoxaparin, which improved the symptoms. After delivery, the treatment was changed to coumarin drugs, with improvement on magnetic resonance angiography imaging. Correct diagnosis is essential for the prognosis of this disease; the changes typical of pregnancy must not be confused with neurological symptoms (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González de Merlo, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ángel,   C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serna,  M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Salas, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tello,  A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amézcua,  A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La trombosis de senos venosos cerebrales (TSVC) es una enfermedad infrecuente. Se presenta con un amplio espectro de signos y síntomas clínicos (dolor de cabeza, náuseas, fiebre, déficits neurológicos focales y coma). Las posibles etiologías incluyen estados de hipercoagulabilidad. El embarazo y el puerperio, debido a sus cambios fisiológicos, son estados procoagulantes. Tiene diferentes presentaciones clínicas y pronóstico. Presentamos el caso de una gestante de 29 años de 21 semanas que fue ingresada por un cuadro de náuseas y vómitos acompañado de una intensa cefalea, por lo que fue remitida al Servicio de Neurología. La resonancia magnética (RM) con angiografía reveló una TSVC. Fue tratada con nadroparina y enoxaparina con mejoría en los síntomas; después del parto, el tratamiento se sustituyó por dicumarínicos y se observó una mejoría en la imagen de la RM con angiografía. Es muy importante el correcto diagnóstico para el pronóstico de esta enfermedad, así que no debemos confundir alteraciones propias del embarazo con síntomas neurológicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);37(3): 109-111, mayo-jun. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85624</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trombosis de senos venosos cerebrales en gestante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13232^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33361^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
