<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156787</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Internalizing and externalizing personality and subjective effects in a sample of adolescent cannabis users</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cannabis is the illicit substance most widely used by adolescents. Certain personality traits such as impulsivity and sensation seeking, and the subjective effects experienced after substance use (e.g. euphoria or relaxation) have been identified as some of the main etiological factors of consumption. This study aims to categorize a sample of adolescent cannabis users based on their most dominant personality traits (internalizing and externalizing profile). Then, to make a comparison of both profiles considering a set of variables related to consumption, clinical severity and subjective effects experienced. From a cross-sectional design, 173 adolescents (104 men and 69 women) aged 13 to 18 asking for treatment for cannabis use disorder in an Addictive Behavior Unit (UCAD) from the hospital were recruited. For the assessment, an ad hoc protocol was employed to register consumption, the Millon Adolescent Clinical Inventory (MACI) and the Addiction Research Center Inventory (ARCI) 49- item short form were also administered. Factor analysis suggested a two-profile solution: Introverted, Inhibited, Doleful, Dramatizing (-), Egotistic (-), Self-demeaning and Borderline tendency scales composed the internalizing profile, and Submissive (-), Unruly, Forceful, Conforming (-) and Oppositional scales composed the externalizing profile. The comparative analysis showed that the internalizing profile has higher levels of clinical severity and more subjective effects reported than the externalizing profile. These results suggest the need to design specific intervention strategies for each profile (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lluís Matalí, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Fernández, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castellano-Tejedor, Carmina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Haro, Josep Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Sánchez, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lleras, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cánnabis es la sustancia ilícita más consumida por los adolescentes. Determinados rasgos de personalidad, como la impulsividad y la búsqueda de sensaciones, así como los efectos subjetivos experimentados tras el consumo (p.e. euforia o relajación), se han identificado como algunos de los principales factores etiológicos de consumo. Este estudio tiene por objetivo categorizar a una muestra de adolescentes consumidores de cánnabis en función de sus rasgos de personalidad más predominantes (perfil internalizante y externalizante) para, posteriormente, realizar una comparación de ambos perfiles a partir de un conjunto de variables asociadas al consumo, la gravedad clínica y los efectos subjetivos experimentados. A partir de un diseño transversal, se reclutaron 173 adolescentes (104 hombres y 69 mujeres) de 13 a 18 años, que demandaron tratamiento por Trastorno por Uso de Cánnabis en la Unidad de Conductas Adictivas (UCAD) del Hospital. Para la evaluación se utilizó un protocolo ad hoc para registrar el consumo, el Inventario Clínico para Adolescentes de Millon (MACI) y la versión abreviada del Addiction Research Center Inventory (ARCI)-49. El análisis factorial sugirió una solución en 2 perfiles: las escalas Introvertido, Inhibido, Pesimista, Histriónico (-), Egocéntrico (-), Autopunitivo y Tendencia límite forman el perfil internalizante, y las escalas Sumiso (-), Rebelde, Rudo, Conformista (-) y Oposicionista el externalizante. El análisis comparativo mostró que el perfil internalizante presenta mayores niveles de gravedad clínica y reporta más efectos subjetivos que el externalizante. Estos resultados sugieren la necesidad de diseñar estrategias de intervención específicas para cada perfil (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);28(4): 231-241, 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156787</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Personalidad internalizante y externalizante y efectos subjetivos en una muestra de adolescentes consumidores de cánnabis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10742</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d301^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22937^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
