<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59889</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Choriocarcinoma of the Lung</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Primary choriocarcinoma of the lung is an extremely rare condition with a fatal outcome in most patients. We report the case of a 31-year-old woman with cough, chest pain, and hemoptysis, whose chest radiograph displayed nodules in the right upper lobe. After study and an unsuccessful attempt at histological characterization of the lesions, exploratory surgery was indicated. The patient underwent lobectomy and lymphadenectomy after diagnosis of a malignant process in the intraoperative biopsy. The definitive diagnosis was choriocarcinoma. Gonadal involvement was ruled out and the patient was referred to the oncology department for adjuvant therapy. She remains free of disease after 42 months.Although choriocarcinoma of the lung is extremely rare and it is hard to establish a standard treatment, in cases of localized disease, surgical resection followed by chemotherapy seems to be useful and can achieve long survivals(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Lahera, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guadalajara Labajo, Héctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nistal Martín de Serrano, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Pelillo, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Sánchez-Giron, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corpa Rodríguez, María Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El coriocarcinoma primitivo de pulmón es una entidad extraordinariamente infrecuente, con evolución fatal en la mayoría de los pacientes. Se presenta el caso de una mujer de 31 años con tos, dolor torácico y hemoptisis, en cuya radiografía se apreciaron nódulos en el lóbulo superior derecho. Tras estudio e intento de filiación histológica de las lesiones, sin resultado, se indicó exploración quirúrgica y se practicó una lobectomía más linfadenectomía tras el diagnóstico de malignidad en la biopsia perioperatoria. El diagnóstico definitivo fue de coriocarcinoma. Se descartó que hubiera afectación ginecológica y se remitió a la paciente a oncología para tratamiento complementario. No hay evidencia de enfermedad a los 42 meses.Si bien esta enfermedad es muy rara y resulta difícil establecer un tratamiento estandarizado, en la enfermedad localizada parece útil la resección quirúrgica seguida de quimioterapia, con las que pueden conseguirse supervivencias elevadas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;45(3): 153-155, mar. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59889</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Coriocarcinoma de pulmón</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37264^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37264^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
