<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043636</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-7606</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Avulsion of part of a phalanx, carpal tunnel syndrome and Dupuytren's contracture. Coincidence or causal relationship?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In most cases, the etiology of carpal tunnel syndrome    (CTS) and of Dupuytren's contracture are unknown.    However, here both diseases are presented associated in    the hand of a woman that several months before had    suffered the avulsion of part of a phalanx. Comparing these    facts with the data from the literature, the conclusion is that    the avulsion has been either the cause of the CTS or its    direct trigger in a woman that probably had some    anatomical predisposition for the disease; this conclusion is    even clearer for the initial stage of Dupuytren's contracture    in this woman, because both appeared after the trauma, its    causal relationship is coherent with the scientific    knowledge, given that similar situations have been    described, and because the woman lacked most of the risk    factors associated in the literature with the idiopathic CTS    or with the idiopathic Dupuytren's contracture</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortega Pérez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la mayoría de los casos, el origen del síndrome    del túnel carpiano (STC) y el de la contractura de    Dupuytren son desconocidos, sin embargo aquí presentamos    la asociación de ambos padecimientos en la mano de    una enferma que pocos meses antes había sufrido la avulsión    de parte de una falange en ella. Al comparar los    hechos con los datos de la bibliografía científica, concluimos    que la avulsión fue la causa del STC o bien su desencadenante    directo en una mujer que tendría alguna predisposición    anatómica a padecerlo. La conclusión es aún    más clara para la contractura de Dupuytren en estadio inicial    en esta lesionada. Ambas enfermedades aparecieron    después del traumatismo, su relación causal es coherente    con los conocimientos científicos, se han publicado ya    casos similares y esta mujer carecía de la mayoría de los    factores de riesgo descritos en la bibliografía tanto para el    STC como para la contractura palmar idiopáticos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. med. forense;11(40): 107-111, abr. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043636</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Avulsión de parte de una falange, síndrome del túnel carpiano y contractura de Dupuytren. ¿Coincidencia o relación causal?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2392^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10481^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9672^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5519^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10481^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6378^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6382^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4447^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2392^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5519^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
