<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94861</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The role of platybasia in trigeminal neuralgia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Summary. Introduction. The vascular compression of a nerve is known to be the most important cause of idiopathic trigeminal neuralgia (ITN) by most authors. However, several cases of skull base deformities in patients with ITN have been reported in our bibliographic review. Aim. To compare the existence of platybasia between a group of patients with ITN and a randomized control group. Subjects and methods. Twenty-five patients with ITN and twenty-five control subjects were X-rayed and their basal angles were measured and compared. Results. The basal angle measured to investigate the existence of platybasia is significantly greater in the ITN group than in the control group. Platybasia was found in 10 patients with ITN. However, only two cases of platybasia were reported in the control group. Therefore in our study we have found that the incidence of  platybasia in patients with ITN is significantly increased. Conclusion. Our data demonstrated that platybasia has an important role in the pathogenesis of the ITN by altering the normal anatomy of the nerves and vessels within the posterior fossa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sempere, A. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortés Vela, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto Navarro, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baño Ruiz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Botella Asunción, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abarca Olivas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen. Introducción. La gran mayoría de autores considera que la neuralgia del trigémino idiopática (NTI) está causada por la compresión de un vaso sobre el nervio. Sin embargo, en la bibliografía se recogen algunos casos de neuralgia del trigémino asociados a deformidades de la base del cráneo, entre las cuales se encuentra la platibasia. Objetivo. Investigar la influencia de un tipo de deformidad de la base del cráneo, la platibasia, en la etiopatogenia de la compresión vascular que se considera causante de la NTI. Sujetos y métodos. Se realizan radiografías laterales de cráneo a 25 pacientes con diagnóstico  de NTI, así como a 25 controles sanos para medir el ángulo basal y compararlos. Resultados. El ángulo basal medido para investigar la existencia de platibasia fue significativamente mayor en el grupo con NTI, aunque la platibasia estaba presente en sólo 10 pacientes. Sólo dos controles mostraban dicha deformidad. Por tanto, la diferencia de incidencia en platibasia entre ambos grupos de pacientes fue estadísticamente significativa. Conclusión. Los datos obtenidos en nuestro trabajo apoyan la teoría de que la platibasia influye en la etiopatogenia de la NTI, probablemente al alterar la disposición habitual de las estructuras vasculonerviosas alojadas en la fosa posterior (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;49(12): 630-632, dic. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94861</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de la platibasia en la neuralgia del trigémino</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32869^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11413^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3404^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14676^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9601^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
