<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166400</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recommendations on clinical indications for myocardial perfusion gated SPECT</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Spanish Society of Cardiology's Clinical Practice Guidelines on Nuclear Cardiology have not been revised since 1999. Correspondingly, this article describes the class-I and class-IIa indications of the American College of Cardiology (ACC)/American Heart Association (AHA)/American Society for Nuclear Cardiology (ASNC), which have a grade-A or grade-B level of supporting evidence. In addition, details are given of the 27 appropriateness criteria of the American College of Cardiology Foundation (ACCF)/ASNC expert committee, along with additional comments which the authors of this review thought were appropriate to make at this time (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Candell-Riera, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coma-Canella, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diego-Domínguez, Maximiliano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León, Gustavo de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jurado-López, José Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albert-Bertran, Francesc X</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde 1999 no se había realizado ninguna revisión de las Guías de actuación clínica de la Sociedad Española de Cardiología en Cardiología Nuclear, por lo que en este artículo exponemos las indicaciones clase I y IIa de la American College of Cardiology/American Heart Association/American Society of Nuclear Cardiology (ACC/AHA/ASNC) con nivel de evidencia A o B, junto con las 27 indicaciones consideradas adecuadas por el Comité de expertos de la American College of Cardiology Foundation/American Society of Nuclear Cardiology (ACCF/ASNC) y los comentarios que hemos considerado oportuno añadir los firmantes de este artículo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);8(supl.B): 58b-64b, 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166400</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recomendaciones sobre las indicaciones clínicas de la gated-SPECT de perfusión miocárdica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53211^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53214^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53211^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200800</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
