<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048982</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pharmaceutical care and Transversality in the Study of School of Pharmacy of the University of Costa Rica</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">After a long evolving process, Pharmaceutical Care has become the transversal axis of the curriculum of the School    of Pharmacy of the University of Costa Rica, who has redefi ned its focus of study, as well as the pedagogic approach    of the curricular work. With this transversality, the patient becomes the center in which all the knowledge, attitudes,    aptitudes and skills promoted in the students, convey. With this, it is pretended to develop a better pharmacist who can    more properly fi nd his place in modern society</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Badilla Baltodano, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Después de un largo proceso evolutivo, la Atención Farmacéutica se ha convertido en el eje transversal del plan de    estudios de la Facultad de Farmacia de la Universidad de Costa Rica, quien ha redefi nido su objeto de estudio así    como el abordaje pedagógico del quehacer curricular. Con esta transversalidad, el paciente se convierte en el centro en    el que convergen todos los conocimientos, actitudes, aptitudes y destrezas que se promueven en el estudiante. Con esto    se pretende producir un mejor farmacéutico que encuentre más adecuadamente su sitio en la sociedad actual</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;47(3): 313-320, 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048982</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Atención Farmacéutica, transversalidad en la Facultad de Farmacia de la Universidad de Costa Rica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4582^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4582^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12961^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3379^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12961^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4584^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4583^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4582^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4582^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13726^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12961^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
