<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146161</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Somatotype joint mobility and ranges of hip and knee of college students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: several studies indicate a consistency between the physical inactivity and low levels of mobility in hip and knee joint. Objective: to determine the differences in the motion range of the hip and knee joint between the different classifications of somatotype in students of Pedagogy in Physical Education of the Universidad Autónoma de Chile, campus Temuco. Methods: the sample included 102 physical education students (31.3% female), somatotype was obtained through the protocol of the International Society for the Advancement of Kinanthropometry (ISAK) and the motion range of the hip and knee joint (ROM) using a universal goniometer. Results: the mean somatotype was endo-mesomorphic (4.8 - 3.4 - 2) for the women and meso-endomorphic (3.5 - 5.7 - 2) for the males, while the ROM evaluation indicated that the 50% of the students presented mobility values of joint lower than the normal ones. Furthermore, the endo-mesomorphic women showed lower ROM values of medial rotation of the right hip (45.5 ° ± 10.2 °; P = 0.0125, t = 2.732) and left hip side rotation (41.7 ° ± 10.3 °; P = 0.0256; p = 2.402) than the women meso-endomorphic. Conclusion: the results shows a relationship between the somatotype and hip ROM in the women, showing that in the women the most favorable results of joint mobility are related with a greater muscle mass. In contrasts, no significant differences were observed in men. It is important to encourage the development of joint mobility exercises according to the specific needs of each sex (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Sandoval, Alan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lagos Del Canto, Loreto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aravena Turra, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera-Valenzuela, Tomás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bruneau Chávez, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Godoy-Cumillaf, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valdés-Badilla, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grandón Fuentes, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durán Agüero, Samuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: diversas investigaciones señalan una coherencia entre la falta de actividad física con menores niveles de movilidad articular en cadera y rodilla. Objetivo: determinar las diferencias en los rangos de movilidad articular de cadera y rodilla entre las distintas clasificaciones de somatotipo, en estudiantes de Pedagogía en Educación Física de la Universidad Autónoma de Chile, sede Temuco (EFUA). Material y método: la muestra incluyó 102 estudiantes de educación física (31,3% mujeres), se obtuvo el somatotipo a través del protocolo de la International Society for the Advancement of Kinanthropometry (ISAK), y los rangos de movilidad articular de cadera y rodilla (ROM) utilizando un goniómetro universal. Resultados: el somatotipo promedio para mujeres EFUA fue endomesomorfo (4,8 - 3,4 - 2) y para varones EFUA mesoendomorfo (3,5 - 5,7 - 2), mientras que la evaluación de ROM señala que el 50% de los estudiantes presentó valores de movilidad articular inferiores a lo normal. Además, las mujeres EFUA clasificadas como endomesomorfas manifiestan valores más bajos de ROM para la rotación medial de cadera derecha (45,5°±10,2°; P=0,0125; t=2,732) y rotación lateral de cadera izquierda (41,7°±10,3°; P=0.0256; t=2.402) al compararlas con las mujeres EFUA mesoendomorfas. Conclusión: existe relación entre el somatotipo y los ROM de cadera en las mujeres EFUA, quienes manifiestan resultados más favorables de movilidad articular a mayor masa muscular, sin encontrarse diferencias significativas en los varones EFUA. Es importante propiciar el desarrollo de ejercicios de movilidad articular en función de las necesidades específicas de cada sexo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(6): 2903-2909, dic. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146161</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Somatotipo y rangos de movilidad articular de cadera y rodilla en estudiantes universitarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29097^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7894^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13391</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6779^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52423^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
