<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81045</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7709</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">As it is well known stress fractures are frequent insportsmen and women. A stress fracture or fatiguefracture is defined as the break in the continuityof a normal bone as a result of the application ofrepetitive threshold force, or the break in the continuityof a bone as a result of repetitive normal force.When the micro fractures produced daily have notime to cure before the previous physical activitybegins again.The clinical case presented is the result of trainingwithout criteria to prepare for &#147;The North FaceUltra-Trail du Mont-Blanc&#148; (UTMB) 2006 and afollowing bad diagnostic through not knowing theextent of the race or the evaluation as such of thelesion(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Violan i Fors, Enric</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Como es sabido las fracturas de estrés son frecuentesentre los deportistas. La fractura de estrés ofractura de fatiga se denomina como la rotura enla continuidad de un hueso normal a consecuenciade la aplicación de fuerzas repetidas umbrales, orotura en la continuidad de un hueso a causa de laaplicación repetida de fuerzas normales. Cuandolas micro fracturas que se producen diariamente notienen tiempo de curar antes de la actividad físicaanterior empieza a producirse.El caso clínico que vamos a presentar es la consecuenciade un entrenamiento sin criterio para prepararla &#147;The North Face Ultra-Trail du Mont-Blanc&#148;(UTMB) del 2006 y un posterior mal diagnóstico alno conocer ni el alcance de la carrera ni la valoracióncomo tal de la lesión(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Peu;27(2): 75-87, abr.-jun. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81045</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fractura de stress en un skyrunner</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12793^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24657^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1273^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
