<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130201</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4008</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Coeliac disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Coeliac disease is a systemic autoimmune disorder that is triggered by the ingestion of gluten and associated prolamins in individuals with genetic susceptibility (mainly HLA), characterised by a variable combination of specific antibodies: gluten-dependent clinical manifestations, specific coeliac disease antibodies, HLA-DQ2 and/or DQ8 haplotype and enteropathy. The specific antibodies consist of anti-TG2 antibodies, including endomysial and deamidated gliadin peptide antibodies. In childhood and adolescence, the intestinal biopsy could be omitted in symptomatic subjects with anti-TG2-IgA antibody titres &gt; 10 times the cut-off point, verified by a positive antibodies endomysial and HLA-DQ2 and/or DQ8, and only in this case, the diagnosis could be made and treatment started with gluten-free diets. In all the rest of the cases, a first intestinal biopsy, before withdrawal of the gluten diet, is mandatory to prevent incorrect diagnoses (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Isabel Polanco Allué, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad celíaca es una alteración sistémica de carácter autoinmune desencadenada por el consumo de gluten y prolaminas relacionadas en individuos con predisposición genética (principalmente HLA), caracterizada por una combinación variable de: manifestaciones clínicas gluten-dependientes, anticuerpos específicos de enfermedad celíaca, haplotipo HLA-DQ2 y/o DQ8 y enteropatía. Los anticuerpos específicos comprenden autoanticuerpos anti-TG2, incluyendo antiendomisio y antipéptidos deamidados de gliadina. En la infancia y adolescencia, la biopsia intestinal podría omitirse en sujetos sintomáticos con títulos de anticuerpos anti-TG2-IgA &gt; 10 veces el punto de corte, verificados por anticuerpos antiendomisio y HLA-DQ2 y/o DQ8 positivos, y solo en este supuesto se podría realizar el diagnóstico e iniciar la dieta sin gluten. En todos los demás casos, la primera biopsia intestinal, antes de retirar el gluten de la dieta, es obligatoria para evitar diagnósticos incorrectos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. lab. clín;7(4): 141-144, oct.-dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130201</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad celíaca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6116</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2481^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24411^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24411^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2481^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2481^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13078^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13078^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2481^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2481^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
