<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61440</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acute necrotizing esophagitis in an unstable patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Acute necrotizing esophagitis or black esophagusis a rare affection, described in the medical literaturesince 1990. Although its mechanism is not fully understood,ischemic compromise appears to be thefundamental physiopathological factor. When acutenecrotizing esophagitis is found in the endoscopic studyof an upper digestive haemorrhage, the prognosisis good. We present a case in which diagnosis of blackesophagus was an endoscopic finding, secondary to asituation of underlying hemodynamic instability, with afatal outcome(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Soler, W</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elizalde, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodrigo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gorraiz, B. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Eguaras, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La esofagitis necrotizante aguda o esófago negroes una afección rara, conocida en la literatura médicadesde 1990. Aunque su mecanismo no es del todo conocido,el compromiso isquémico parece ser el factorfisiopatológico fundamental. Cuando la esofagitis necrotizanteaguda es un hallazgo en el estudio endoscópicode hemorragia digestiva alta, sin desestabilizaciónhemodinámica, el pronóstico es bueno. Presentamosun caso en el que el diagnóstico de esófago negro fue unmero hallazgo endoscópico, secundario a una situaciónde inestabilidad hemodinámica subyacente, con resultadofatal(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;32(1): 113-116, ene.-abr. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61440</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Esofagitis necrotizante aguda en paciente inestable</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1024^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5031^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28919^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9527^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6623^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
