<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99424</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Criteria for between-care-level referrals of patients with vascular disease. semFYC-SEACV consensus document</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Spanish Society of Family and Community Medicine (semFYC) and the Spanish Society of Angiology and Vascular Surgery (SEACV), through a Joint Working Group, have prepared a document on between care-level referrals of patients with the main vascular diseases; peripheral arterial disease, venous insufficiency, and diabetic foot. The responsibilities and skills required at each care level have been defined, as well as the criteria for mutual referral and how to prioritise them. The preparation of this consensus document attempt to provide an efficient tool that may ensure the continuity of health care, always respecting the specific characteristics and needs of each health care area(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fuentes Camps, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Quesada, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piquer Farrés, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Nevárez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Sánchez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bellmunt Montoya, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Sociedad Española de Medicina Familiar y Comunitaria (semFYC) y la Sociedad Española de Angiología y Cirugía Vascular (SEACV) han elaborado, mediante un grupo de trabajo conjunto, un documento de derivación entre niveles asistenciales de los pacientes con las principales patologías vasculares: enfermedad arterial periférica, insuficiencia venosa y pie diabético. Se han definido las responsabilidades y habilidades requeridas de cada nivel asistencial y también los criterios de derivación mutua, así como los de priorización. La elaboración de este documento consensuado pretende aportar una herramienta eficiente que asegure la continuidad en la asistencia sanitaria, respetando siempre las particularidades y necesidades específicas de cada zona sanitaria(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;64(3): 135-145, mayo-jun. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99424</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Criterios de derivación entre niveles asistenciales de pacientes con patología vascular. Documento de consenso semFYC-SEACV</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19291^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15055^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17193^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
