<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113638</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Advances in percutaneous treatment of mitral regurgitation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Percutaneous techniques for the treatment of mitral regurgitation have aroused much interest in recent years. Percutaneous mitral annuloplasty can be performed indirectly by using devices implanted in the coronary sinus or directly by using a retrograde approach. However, as yet, the results of these techniques are scarce and some devices have a high complications rate. The most frequent percutaneous mitral valve repair technique consists of mitral leaflet plication by implanting 1 or more percutaneous clips (MitraClip) in an imitation of the Alfieri surgical technique. Clinical experience with this device is broader than that with any other. The MitraClip device is associated with improved mitral regurgitation in a high percentage of carefully-selected patients. However, the single randomized study performed to date (EVEREST) showed its efficacy to be less than that of surgical repair and we await the results of new randomized studies that should clarify which patient-type can benefit most from this technique. Other left ventricular remodeling devices, tendinous cord implantation, and leaflet ablation are currently undergoing preclinical development or first-in-human experimentation. Finally, the development of biological prostheses for percutaneous mitral valve replacement is at an early stage. Many promising experiments at the preclinical phase and initial experiments in humans will very probably multiply in the near future. However, the true role of this technique in treating mitral valve disease will have to be evaluated in appropriately designed randomized controlled studies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barbosa Ribeiro, Henrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodés-Cabau, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nombela-Franco, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urena, Marina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las técnicas percutáneas para el tratamiento de la insuficiencia mitral han generado gran interés en los últimos años. La anuloplastia mitral percutánea se puede realizar por vía indirecta a través de dispositivos implantados en el seno coronario o por vía directa a través de un acceso retrógrado. Sin embargo, los resultados de la anuloplastia percutánea son todavía escasos, dispares y asociados a una alta tasa de complicaciones con algunos dispositivos. La técnica más utilizada de reparación percutánea mitral consiste en la plicatura de los velos mitrales mediante la implantación de uno o varios clips percutáneos (MitraClip) imitando la técnica quirúrgica de Alfieri. Este dispositivo, que actualmente acumula la mayor experiencia clínica, se asocia a una mejoría de la insuficiencia mitral en un alto porcentaje de pacientes bien seleccionados. Sin embargo, su eficacia se ha demostrado inferior a la de la reparación quirúrgica en el que hasta el momento es el único estudio aleatorizado (EVEREST), y se está a la espera de los resultados de nuevos estudios aleatorizados que clarifiquen qué tipo de pacientes pueden obtener mayor beneficio con esta técnica. Otros dispositivos de remodelado de ventrículo izquierdo, implantación de cuerdas tendinosas o ablación de valvas se encuentran en fase de desarrollo preclínico o primeras experiencias en humanos. Finalmente, el desarrollo de prótesis biológicas para reemplazo mitral percutáneo está en una fase incipiente, hay múltiples experiencias prometedoras en fase preclínica y las primeras experiencias en humanos proliferarán muy probablemente en un futuro próximo. Los estudios aleatorizados, sin embargo, deberán establecer el verdadero papel de esta técnica en el tratamiento de la valvulopatía mitral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;66(7): 566-582, jul. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113638</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Avances en el tratamiento percutáneo de la insuficiencia mitral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54235^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9133^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2866^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9133^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9133^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9133^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23248^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2866^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23248^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54235^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54235^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23233^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54235^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2866^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
