<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76038</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Motor fluctuations and dyskinesias in Parkinson' s disease: variables that discriminate both complications in a sample of 285 patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. A large proportion of patients with Parkinson&#146;sdisease suffer fluctuations and dyskinesias in thecourse of the disease. The present study explores the variablesthat predict the appearance of these complications.Patients and methods. This is a cross-sectionalstudy that studies 285 patients with Parkinson&#146;s disease.Patient's age, date of diagnosis and of treatment with levodopaand motor situation (UPDRS III) were recorded.Drugs and doses were documented. Finally, levodopaequivalent dose in those patients using agonists or prolongedrelease formulations was calculated.Results. Mean age of the patients was 71.1 years(±9.1). Disease duration was 8.7 years (±11.8). A total of118 patients (41.4%) presented motor fluctuations, and61 patients (21.4 %) had dyskinesias. Two discriminantanalytical models were established. In the first model,the dependent variable was the presence of fluctuations,and three variables significantly discriminated betweenthe two groups: the levodopa equivalent dose, the durationof treatment with levodopa and the motor situation.In the second model the presence of dyskinesias constitutedthe dependent variable. The only variable selectedby this model was the levodopa equivalent dose.Discussion. The duration of treatment with levodopa,the doses of agonists and levodopa and the motor situationdifferentiate patients with fluctuations from thosewithout them. In the case of dyskinesias, only theagonists and levodopa doses were selected by the analyticalmodel (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rouco, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garametndi, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tijero, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zarranz, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Esteban, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velasco, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lezcano, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Una gran proporción de los pacientescon enfermedad de Parkinson van a presentar fluctuacionesy discinesias con el desarrollo de la enfermedad. El objetivodel presente trabajo es estudiar las variables que predicen laaparición de estas complicaciones.Pacientes y métodos. El estudio es de tipo transversal.Se estudiaron 285 pacientes con enfermedad de Parkinson. Seregistró la edad, fecha del diagnóstico y del tratamiento conlevodopa y situación motora (UPDRS III). Se recogían losfármacos que tomaban y sus posologías. Finalmente se calculabala dosis equivalente de levodopa en aquellos que tomabanagonistas o formulaciones retard.Resultados. La edad media de los pacientes era de 71,1años (±9,1). La duración de la enfermedad era de 8,7 años(± 11,8). En total 118 pacientes (41,4 %) presentaban fluctuacionesmotoras y 61 pacientes (21,4 %) tenían discinesias.Se realizaron dos modelos de análisis discriminante:en el primero la variable dependiente fue la presencia defluctuaciones; tres variables discriminaban de forma signitificativaentre ambos grupos: la dosis equivalente de levodopa,el tiempo en tratamiento con levodopa y la situaciónmotora. En el segundo modelo se utilizaba la presencia dediscinesias como variable dependiente. La única variableseleccionada por el modelo fue la dosis equivalente de levodopa.Discusión. El tiempo en tratamiento con levodopa, ladosis de agonistas y levodopa y la situación motora discriminana aquellos que tienen fluctuaciones de los que no laspresentan. En el caso de las discinesias sólo se seleccionó ladosis de agonistas y levodopa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;23(8): 494-498, oct. 2008. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76038</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fluctuaciones motoras y discinesias en la enfermedad de Parkinson: variables que discriminan ambas complicaciones en una muestra de 285 pacientes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33528^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33528^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34315^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34315^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
