<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037243</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Thrombolysis in ischemic stroke: an approach based on accessibility and sustainability</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the first semester of 2003, the European Agency for the Evaluation of Medicinal Products approved the use of thrombolysis for the treatment of ischemic stroke within 3 hours of onset. This approval was based on evidence of the effectiveness and efficiency of this treatment, given that one out of every seven patients treated recovers from the neurological deficit, which in turn leads to almost complete ability to perform activities of daily life. The importance of this recovery is clear, given that ischemic stroke is the most common cause of permanent disability in industrialized countries, affecting nearly two and a half million citizens in the European Union. The approval of thrombolytic treatment in ischemic stroke poses several challenges to physicians, which can be summarized as a strengthening of patient accessibility and equity within a context of sustainable growth and a reasonable period of time. These objectives are feasible if we understand that the required resources and teams of health professionals already exist in the Spanish public health model. What is required is to coordinate them effectively and to develop alliances and agreements among medical specialties, as well as among different services involved in the care of stroke. Thrombolytic treatment for ischemic stroke could be an opportunity for improvement since it provides the possibility of putting this integral approach into practice</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vázquez, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murillo, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabré, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarrete, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Agencia Europea del Medicamento aprobó en el primer semestre del año 2003 el empleo de la trombólisis en el ictus isquémico en las 3 primeras horas evolutivas. La base para esta aprobación fue la evidencia objetiva de su efectividad y eficiencia, dado que 1 de cada 7 pacientes tratados con trombólisis se recuperaba de su déficit neurológico, lo que suponía a su vez una recuperación prácticamente completa en las actividades de la vida diaria. La importancia de esta recuperación se evidencia si se tiene en cuenta que el ictus isquémico constituye la primera causa de discapacidad en los países industrializados, afectando en la Unión Europea a cerca de 2 millones y medio de ciudadanos. Para los profesionales de la medicina la aprobación de la trombólisis en el ictus isquémico supone diversos retos que se pueden resumir en potenciar la accesibilidad y la equidad dentro de un contexto de crecimiento sostenible y en un período razonable. Estos objetivos son posibles si se entiende que tanto los recursos como los equipos humanos adecuados para hacerlo existen en nuestro modelo sanitario, y que basta la coordinación adecuada de ellos, junto con el desarrollo de alianzas entre las especialidades médicas y entre los diversos servicios implicados en el tratamiento de estos pacientes. La importancia de la aprobación de la trombólisis en el ictus es que puede convertirse en una opción de mejora al ofrecer una oportunidad de llevar a la práctica este pensamiento integrador basado en los principios enumerados</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;20(3): 161-164, abr.-may. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037243</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La trombólisis en el ictus isquémico: un enfoque basado en la accesibilidad y la sostenibilidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2585^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31002^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6448^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32441</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24892^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
