<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-168406</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Frontal muscle miectomy: an alternative to reduce frontal wrinkles</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and Objective. The skin, subcutaneus and osseus changes over time are characteristic of the ageing face. Loss of soft tissue elasticity, volumetric changes, and facial muscular activity are largely responsible for facial wrinkles, and is the treatment of these that are the most frequent request of patients wanting to look younger. The objective of this study is to describe an alternative surgical technique to treat frontal wrinkles with less morbidity and longer results. Methods. Thirty-one patients from 37 to 75 years old were submitted to frontal miectomy from 2003 to 2007. The incision was divided on superior eyelid, precapilar and transcapilar. Results. Patients submitted to this technique had short recovery time with edema around 5 to 7 days. They returned to their normal activities in 7 days. No patients had intra or postoperative complications. All patients were satisfied with the result. Conclusions. Frontal horizontal wrinkles treatment with frontal miectomy is a quick and minimally invasive procedure, with a long term result  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nduka, Charles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brock, Ryane S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viterbo, Fausto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y Objetivo. Los cambios cutáneos, subcutáneos y óseos son característicos del rostro envejecido a través del tiempo. La pérdida de elasticidad del tejido blando, los cambios volumétricos y la actividad facial muscular, son en gran parte responsables de las arrugas faciales y su tratamiento es la petición más frecuente de los pacientes que quieren un rejuvenecimiento facial El objetivo de este estudio es describir una técnica quirúrgica alternativa para tratar arrugas frontales con menos morbilidad y resultados más duraderos. Material y Método. Recogemos un total de 31 pacientes entre los 37 y 75 años de edad intervenidos mediante miectomía frontal entre los años 2003 y 2007. La incisión fue dividida sobre el párpado superior, precapilar y transcapilar. Resultados. El tiempo de recuperación postoperatoria fue corto, con edema en torno a los 5 a 7 días; retornaron a sus actividades habituales en 7 días. Ningún paciente tuvo complicaciones intra o postoperatorias. Conclusiones. El tratamiento de arrugas horizontales de la frente con miectomía frontal es un procedimiento rápido, mínimamente invasivo, y que ofrece un resultado satisfactorio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;43(3): 247-253, jul.-sept. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-168406</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Miectomía frontal: una alternativa para reducir arrugas frontales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24879^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23818^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33569^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5679^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5253^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4555^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
