<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159850</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Living with a wet colostomy: a study on quality of life</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study aimed to describe the sociodemographic profile and evaluate the life quality of a patient with permanent wet colostomy. It is a case study that deeply investigated the problems and needs of a patient with a wet colostomy and determined strategies to solve or ease the identified problems. The results were structured in related categories to sociodemographic data of the patient and the evaluation of their quality of life. The participant demonstrated to be well suited to the conditions to carry a wet colostomy. The acceptance of the colostomy patient with less than a year is a discontent. Those who already had the colostomy for many years can better adapt to the new condition. This study allowed to know and understand about the quality of life of a patient who has been living with a colostomy for many years, being able to offer valuable interventions to this public in later practices (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carvalho, Nalma Alexandra Rocha de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miranda, Sara Machado</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Noleto, Isabela Ribeiro de Sá Guimarães</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benício, Claudia Daniella Avelino Vasconcelos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luz, Maria Helena Barros Araújo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>pt</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio tuvo como objetivo trazar el perfil sociodemográfico y evaluar la calidad de vida de un paciente con ostomía húmeda permanente. Este es un estudio de caso que investigó a fondo los problemas y necesidades de una paciente con ostomía húmeda y ha determinado estrategias para resolver o mitigar los problemas identificados. Los resultados se han estructurado en categorías relacionadas con los datos sociodemográficos de la paciente y a la evaluación de su calidad de vida. La participante se mostró bien adaptada a las condiciones de portadora de ostomía húmeda. La aceptación del paciente portador de ostomía con menos de un año es de descontento, ya aquellos con el estoma durante varios años se pueden adaptar mejor a la nueva condición. El estudio posibilitó conocer y comprender acerca de la calidad de vida de una paciente durante muchos años con un estoma y por lo tanto puede proponer intervenciones valiosas a este público en sus prácticas posteriores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;20(46): 165-170, sept.-dic. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159850</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conviviendo con una estoma húmedo: un estudio acerca de la calidad de vida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23206^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52527</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
