<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82979</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of magnetic resonance imaging in prostate cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the last decade, technical advances in magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) have made it the technique of choice in the overall management of patients with suspected or confirmed prostate cancer. MR makes it possible to acquire information about morphology and function in the same examination by using techniques like spectroscopy, diffusion, and dynamic sequences with intravenous contrast material administration. Moreover, MRI enables both focused study of the prostate gland and of regional and/or whole-body involvement, depending on the clinical indications, in less than an hour. The main clinical indications for MRI of the prostate are a) staging local, regional, and/or remote disease; b) detecting prostate cancer or guiding prostate biopsy in cases of clinical suspicion or negative findings in previous biopsy specimens; and c) monitoring the response to treatment. It is important to know the different protocols with specific MRI sequences for the prostate, depending on the different clinical indications, to ensure that they are performed and interpreted correctly. This article provides up-to-date information about the use of MRI for the study of the prostate to show how the morphological and functional information can be used in clinical practice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Comet, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilanova, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garcia-Figueiras, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barceló, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boada, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los avances técnicos de la resonancia magnética (RM) en la última década hacen que se considere la técnica de elección en el manejo global del paciente con sospecha o diagnóstico de cáncer de próstata. La RM permite combinar información morfológica y funcional al mismo tiempo mediante la aplicación de secuencias como la espectroscopia, difusión y secuencias dinámicas con contraste endovenoso en el mismo estudio. La RM permite no solo focalizar el estudio en la glándula sino valorar también la extensión regional a toda la pelvis o a todo el cuerpo dependiendo de la indicación clínica, en menos de 1 hora de exploración. Las principales indicaciones clínicas de la RM de próstata son: a) estadificación local, regional o a distancia; b) detección o guía para biopsia diagnóstica ante la sospecha clínica o resultado negativo en biopsias previas; y c) monitorización terapéutica. Es preciso conocer los distintos protocolos con secuencias específicas en RM de próstata, dependiendo de las diferentes indicaciones clínicas, para su correcta realización e interpretación. Este artículo pretende ser una actualización en la utilización de la RM de próstata en el manejo del cáncer de próstata, describiendo un enfoque útil que permita aplicar la información morfológica y funcional en la práctica clínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);52(6): 513-524, nov.-dic. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82979</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de la resonancia magnética en el cáncer de próstata</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37550^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13440^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13440^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11915^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3306^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37550^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
