<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054234</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Placebo effect and pain: brain bases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. All pharmacological treatment is surrounded by a psychosocial context that contributes in part to the outcome of the therapy. The placebo effect is the improvement observed after a simulated treatment in which the subject, without his or her knowledge, is exposed only to the psychosocial context surrounding the treatment, without receiving the pure «pharmacodynamic» effect of the medication. The aim of this paper is to examine which brain regions and neurochemical mechanisms are responsible for the analgesia resulting from the placebo.     Method and results. Recent studies using functional neuroimaging methods have suggested that when expectations of analgesia arise because of a simulated treatment (placebo) there is an increase in the activity of the dorsolateral and orbitofrontal prefrontal cortices. These increments are detected early on, before the experience of pain, which suggests that these structures could be part of a system that is involved in the cognitive control of pain. Several studies have found that once the subject experiences the nociceptive stimulus, the placebo causes a significant reduction in the activity of cortical regions classically associated with nociceptive processing, mainly the anterior insula and the rostral cingulate. In these regions the attenuation of the pain processing seems to be mediated by the release of opioids.    Conclusions. In placebo analgesia at least two anatomically differentiated cerebral systems work together. The guiding mechanism, which appears to be located prefrontally, is activated first. This system would influence other cortical regions (cingulate and insula), attenuating the processing of nociceptive information at these higher levels</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramos, J. M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Cualquier tratamiento farmacológico está rodeado por un contexto psicosocial que contribuye parcialmente al resultado de la terapia. El efecto placebo es la mejora que se observa tras un tratamiento simulado en el que, sin saberlo el sujeto, éste se ve expuesto exclusivamente al contexto psicosocial que rodea al tratamiento sin beneficiarse del efecto «farmacodinámico» puro del fármaco. El objetivo del presente trabajo es revisar qué regiones cerebrales y qué mecanismos neuroquímicos son responsables de la analgesia inducida por placebo.     Método y resultados. Estudios muy recientes, empleando técnicas de neuroimagen funcional, han sugerido que cuando se desarrollan expectativas de analgesia por un tratamiento simulado (placebo) se produce un aumento de la actividad de la corteza prefrontal dorsolateral y orbitofrontal. Estos incrementos se detectan anticipatoriamente antes de la experiencia de dolor, lo que sugiere que dichas estructuras podrían formar parte de un sistema comprometido en el control cognitivo del dolor. Una vez el sujeto experimenta el estímulo nociceptivo, diversos estudios han observado que el placebo produce una reducción de actividad importante en regiones corticales clásicamente asociadas al procesamiento nociceptivo, ínsula anterior y cíngulo rostral, principalmente. En estas regiones la atenuación del procesamiento del dolor parece estar mediada por la liberación de opioides.    Conclusiones. En la analgesia por placebo se coordinan, al menos, dos sistemas cerebrales anatómicamente diferenciados. El mecanismo inductor parece localizarse prefrontalmente activándose en primer lugar. Este sistema ejercería influencia sobre otras regiones corticales (cíngulo e ínsula) atenuando en estos niveles superiores el procesamiento de información nociceptiva</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;22(2): 99-105, mar. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054234</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto placebo y dolor: bases cerebrales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6330^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11350^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30601^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31907^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d715^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d714^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20196^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24834</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14065^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32103^s22007</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
