<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144850</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Risk of malignancy in thyroid nodules with atipia of undetermined significance</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Prevalence of malignancy among cytologies with atypia of undetermined significance (Bethesda category iii) is variable, ranging from 5%-37% in the different studies. There is thus no agreement on whether FNA should be repeated or surgery should be performed in these cases. The aim of this paper was to analyze the risk of malignancy in order to establish the most adequate clinical approach. Material and methods: We analyzed 431 thyroid cytologies performed at our hospital since the introduction of Bethesda System (from January 2011 to September 2014), of which 32 (7.1%) were labeled as category iii. The second FNA, when performed, and the histological results after surgery were reviewed. Results: Twenty-three patients (82.1%) underwent thyroidectomy, while repeat FNA was performed in the remaining 5 patients (17.9%). Cytology was reported as benign (category ii) in 3 (60%) and as unsatisfactory (category i) in 2 (40%), who underwent thyroidectomy. Thirteen of the 25 (52%) surgical thyroid specimens showed no malignancy, while differentiated thyroid carcinomas were found in 12 (48%): papillary cancer in 10 (83.3%), follicular cancer in 1 (8.3%), and papillary cancer with follicular areas in 1 (8.3%). The risk of malignancy of Bethesda category iii in our patients was 42.9%-48.0%. Conclusion: We recommend thyroidectomy for all patients with of cytological Bethesda category iii (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Vázquez, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Miguel Fraile, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Penín Álvarez, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barragáns Pérez, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La atipia de significado incierto o lesión folicular de significado incierto (categoría iii del sistema de Bethesda, 2007) tiene una prevalencia de malignidad variable en los distintos estudios (5-37%), y por tal motivo no existe en la actualidad un consenso sobre el manejo adecuado de este resultado: repetir PAAF o cirugía. El objetivo del siguiente trabajo es analizar el riesgo de malignidad en nuestro medio de dichos nódulos para determinar la actitud clínica más adecuada. Material y métodos: Desde la implantación del sistema Bethesda en el Hospital Xeral de Vigo (enero de 2011) hasta septiembre de 2014 se analizaron 431 citologías, de las cuales el 7,1% (32/430) fueron etiquetadas de categoría iii. Se revisó el resultado de la segunda citología cuando se repitió la PAAF y el resultado histológico posquirúrgico de los operados. Resultados: En 23 (82,1%) pacientes se indicó la realización de una tiroidectomía y en los 5 restantes (17,9%), la repetición de la PAAF. La citología resultó benigna (categoría ii) en 3 de ellos (60%) e insatisfactoria (categoría i) en 2 (40%). De los 25 pacientes tiroidectomizados, incluidos los 2 operados tras el resultado de la segunda PAAF, las piezas quirúrgicas de 13 (52%) fueron benignas y las de otros 12 (48%) demostraron un carcinoma diferenciado de tiroides: 10 (83,3%) con cáncer papilar de tiroides, uno (8,3%) con cáncer folicular de tiroides y uno (8,3%) con cáncer papilar con áreas de patrón folicular. En nuestros pacientes el riesgo de malignidad de las citologías calificadas como categoría iii está entre el 42,9 y el 48% . Conclusión Recomendamos que todos los pacientes con citologías categoría iii de Bethesda se sometan a tiroidectomía.(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;62(10): 507-510, dic. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144850</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Riesgo de malignidad de los nódulos tiroideos con atipia de significado incierto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29779^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38338^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22696^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11665^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14353^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
