<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157915</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Practical management of periprosthetic leakage in patients rehabilitated with a Provox® 2 voice prosthesis after total laryngectomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: Periprosthetic leakage of liquids is a common complication in patients rehabilitated with voice prostheses. Our objective was to describe and review the results of procedures for treating periprosthetic leakage. Materials and methods: This was a retrospective analysis of 41 patients rehabilitated with Provox® 2 voice prostheses between 1997 and 2015. We describe 3 techniques: periprosthetic silicon collar placement, injection of hyaluronic acid into the tracheoesophageal wall and the combination of the 2 techniques. We present a method to reduce the diameter of the tracheoesophageal fistula by removing the voice prosthesis and placing a nasogastric tube through the fistula. Results: In the 3 groups treated with silicone collar (n = 5, 13 procedures), hyaluronic acid injection (n = 5, 9 procedures) and the combination of both techniques (n = 3, 5 procedures), we observed an increase in prosthesis lifespan of an average of 56 days (range 7-118 days), 32 days (range 3-55 days) and 63 days (range 28-136 days), respectively. The tracheoesophageal fistula diameter reduction was performed in 100% (n = 6) of patients. Conclusions: The use of silicone collars, injection of hyaluronic acid into the tracheoesophageal wall and the combination of both techniques for the treatment of periprosthesis leakage increase the lifespan of the prosthesis. Temporary prosthesis removal and placement of nasogastric tube has also been shown effective in our experience. These techniques are simple, inexpensive and reproducible, thereby reducing healthcare costs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín-Oviedo, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinacho Martínez, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Friedlander , Eviatar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Poletti Serafini, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Guirado, Tomás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Scola Yurrita, Bartolomé</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: La fuga periprótesica de líquidos es una complicación frecuente en pacientes rehabilitados con prótesis fonatorias. Nuestro objetivo es describir y revisar los resultados de procedimientos para el tratamiento de la fuga periprotésica. Materiales y métodos: Análisis retrospectivo de 41 pacientes rehabilitados con prótesis fonatorias Provox® 2 entre 1997 y 2015. Descripción de 3 técnicas: colocación de arandela de silicona periprótesis, inyección de ácido hialurónico en la pared traqueal y la combinación de ambas técnicas. Se presenta un método para reducir el diámetro de la fístula fonatoria mediante retirada de la prótesis y colocación de sonda nasogástrica a través de la fistuloplastia. Resultados: En los 3 grupos tratados mediante arandela de silicona (n = 5, 13 procedimientos), inyección de ácido hialurónico (n = 5, 9 procedimientos) y la combinación de ambas técnicas (n = 3, 5 procedimientos), observamos un aumento de la vida útil de las prótesis en una media de 56 días (rango 7 a 118 días), 32 días (rango de 3 a 55 días) y 63 días (rango 28 a 136 días) respectivamente. La reducción del diámetro fistuloplastia se produjo en el 100% (n = 6) de los pacientes tratados. Conclusiones: El uso de arandelas de silicona, inyección de ácido hialurónico en la pared traqueoesofágica y la combinación de ambas técnicas, para el tratamiento de la fuga periprótesis de líquidos aumenta la vida útil de las prótesis. La retirada protésica temporal y la colocación de sonda nasogástrica también se ha mostrado efectiva en nuestra experiencia. Estas técnicas son sencillas, económicas y reproducibles y reducen el gasto sanitario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;67(6): 301-305, nov.-dic. 2016. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157915</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo práctico de fugas periprótesis en pacientes rehabilitados con prótesis fonatorias tipo Provox®2 tras laringectomía total</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8010^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6972^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8004^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31154^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7602^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19574</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
