<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84624</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Frequently accidents and injury at school</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">During the time we have been in a private company that provide schools with medical care, we were surprised by the frequent and constant phone calls received to ask for our services. This fact made us take the decision to carry out a survey to find out the accidents and the most frequent injuries.  According to the retrospective study we realized throughout two different academic courses in several schools in Cantabria, the 3.23% of the students have any accidents or injuries. We found out children between 11 and 15 have the highest accident rate, being 10.8 % higher when boys (rather than girls) are involved. The most common injuries are contusions 42.85%, followed by sprains 23.45%, being blows the reason in 42% of the cases, and surprisingly, acts of aggression in 1%. It was also unexpected to learn that gyms, where children are taught in physical education, have the highest percent on accident rate. All these inquiries lead us to think that age, play and sports are determinant factors in the accidents happened in the school area(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez González, Vanesa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gautier Vargas, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Durante el tiempo de nuestra actividad en una empresa privada de asistencia sanitaria que presta servicios a diversos centros escolares, nos llamó la atención las frecuentes y constantes llamadas recibidas procedentes de los mismos. Ante esta inquietud y preocupación tomamos la decisión de realizar un estudio con el fin conocer los accidentes y lesiones más frecuentemente producidos. Se trata de un estudio retrospectivo observacional realizado durante dos cursos escolares en diversos colegios de Cantabria. Observamos que sufre accidentes y lesiones el 3,23% de los escolares. Los niños se accidentan más que las niñas (un 10,8%) y el grupo de edad de mayor accidentalidad comprende desde los 11 hasta los 15 años; siendo las lesiones más frecuentes las contusiones, 42,85% seguidas de los esguinces, 23,45%. Las causas son, en su mayor parte, golpes (42%) y llama la atención que se producen en un 1% por agresiones de otros. Así también, es llamativo que el lugar donde mayormente se ocasionan los accidentes y lesiones sea el gimnasio, lugar de actividad de asignatura curricular. Los resultados nos indican que la edad, el deporte y el juego constituyen factores determinantes para la accidentalidad en el ámbito escolar(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;34(1): 26-31, ene. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84624</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Accidentes y lesiones más frecuentes en edad escolar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23889^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12953^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28461</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12953^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d62</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201101</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
