<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82114</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of continuing care in a rural health centre in the Vera area of Caceres province, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective is to determine the characteristics of emergency care demand in the rural health area of Vera. Material and methods. A descriptive epidemiological, cross-sectional study, based on collecting the data contained in the records of each of the emergencies seen in the Villanueva Health Centre,Vera, from 1st January 2005 to 1st January 2006. We collected the following variables: gender, age, time, date, reason for consultation, and type of assistance and hospital referral. Results. A total of 5677 patients were seen, with an average of 15.6 per day (or 473/month) with no sex differences. Most, 93.1%, were resolved at the Health Centre, while 6.8%, were referred to Hospital, as the main cause was problems associated with musculoskeletal system movement. Results. Most of the demand is dealing with non-serious diseases, therefore care work in Primary Care Health Centres should be focused on health education impacting positively on knowledge, attitudes and behaviour of the population. Conclusions. The user profile that demand continuing care is that of a young person, active employee who complains of injuries and respiratory problems on leaving their workplaces (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tobajas Belvís, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tobajas Belvís, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateos Iglesias, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tobajas Pizarro, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández del Valle, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo fue determinar las características de la demanda asistencial en la atención continuada en una zona de salud rural de la Comarca de la Vera. Material y métodos. Estudio epidemiológico descriptivo y transversal, basado en la recogida de los datos que figuran en los libros de registro de cada una de las urgencias atendidas en el Centro de Salud de Villanueva de la Vera, desde el 1 de Enero de 2005 al 1 de Enero de 2006. Material y métodos. Se recogieron las siguientes variables: sexo, edad, hora, fecha, motivo de consulta, tipo de asistencia y derivación hospitalaria. Resultados. Se atendieron un total de 5.677 pacientes con una media de 473,08/mes y 15,6/día sin diferencia entre ambos sexos. Resultados. Un 93,1% se resolvieron en el centro de salud, mientras que un 6,8%, se derivaron al hospital de referencia siendo el primer motivo de traslado los problemas relacionados con el aparato locomotor. Resultados. La mayoría de la demanda corresponde a patologías no graves, por lo que nuestra labor asistencial, en los centros de atención primaria, debería estar enfocada hacia la educación para la salud influyendo positivamente en conocimientos, actitudes y conductas de la población. Conclusiones. El perfil de usuario que demanda atención continuada es el de una persona joven, trabajador activo que consulta por traumatismos y problemas respiratorios a la salida de sus centros de trabajo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);36(8): 426-430, oct. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82114</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración de la Atención Continuada en un Centro de Salud Rural de la Comarca de la Vera en la provincia de Cáceres</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50230</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32616^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32616^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32616^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3184^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3184^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
