<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112147</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-2841</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The provision of the temporary disability is a limited public property for which it better management all of us professionals, managing and social agents have to be implicated. The incessant rise of the cost in the provision have led to reforms and legislative adjustments in the systems to be sustainable and lasting that are based in cuts in the legal duration process and in the biggest loading of the  company together whit the largest competence in INSS and AMAT, each time more limiting the role of professionals health primary assistance. It&#146;s existed a disagreement in the first level care respect its competence in this subject and meanwhile the presentation it isn&#146;t been adequately controlled and to continuous in this way anyone will be a  beneficiary. Maybe the contribution of the ethical principles can help to resolve these discrepancy and we could do it better incorporating directly, correctly and effectively to the diary clinic practice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Agudo, Mª P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morenilla, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Atance, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, N Mª</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agudo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La prestación de la incapacidad temporal es un bien público limitado para cuya mejor gestión hemos de estar todos, profesionales, gestores y agentes sociales implicados. El aumento incesante de los costes en la prestación ha conllevado reformas y ajustes legislativos en el sistema que lo hagan sostenible y perdurable, que se han basado en recortes en la duración legal de los procesos y en la mayor carga de la empresa junto con mayor competencia del INSS y AMAT, limitando cada vez más el papel de los profesionales de atención primaria. Existe desacuerdo en el primer nivel asistencial al respecto de su competencia en esta materia y mientras tanto la prestación no está siendo adecuadamente controlada y de seguir, así nadie va a ser beneficiario. Quizás la aportación de los principios éticos pudiera ayudarnos a resolver estas discrepancias y podríamos hacerlo mejor incorporándolos de forma cierta, correcta y efectiva a la practica clínica diaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. prev;17(4): 25-29, oct.-dic. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112147</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La incapacidad temporal (IT). Una prestación en discusión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32027^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13327</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36358</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
