<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046145</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prognostic significance of pin and atypical small acinar proliferation on transrectal ultrasound guided prostate biopsy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To review the incidence of PIN and Atypical Small Acinar Proliferation (ASAP) on first biopsy, the risk tofind cancer on following biopsies and what is the importance given to this findings, analizing how frequently and how long after the initial finding this patients are rebiopsied. Method: We selected 6000 patients who underwent TRUS biopsy between 1994 and 2002. Patients with prior cancer diagnosis were not included. 861 of them underwent more than one biopsy, adding up to a total of 7127 biopsies. A descriptive study h as been done including percentages and percentiles for qualitative variables, mean and median for continuous variables. Results: Incidence of cancer on the first biopsy was 39,1% .PIN and ASAP are stable or slightly increase from 2 and 2,1% respectively on the first biopsy to more than 6% on the fourth and fifth ones. Mean time between biopsies when ASAP or PIN are the initial findings is 180 ± 221,6 and 264 ± 213,8 days respectively. Just 42 and 40% of patients with prior PIN or ASAP diagnose are rebiopsied. On subsequent biopsies 45 and 40% of cancers were respectively found. Conclusions: Presence of PIN or ASAP implies a higher cancer risk on subsequent biopsies; in spite of that, less than half of them are biopsied again. Performing two more biopsies or an amplified biopsy can find most of the tumors associated</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz Mayayo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García González, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayayo Dehesa, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burgos Revilla, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Patrón Rodríguez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Revisar la incidencia de Neoplasia Intraepitelial Prostática (PIN) y Atípia Glandular Focal (AGF) en primera biopsia, el riesgo de estos pacientes de padecer cáncer en biopsias sucesivas y qué importancia se concede a estos hallazgos analizando con qué frecuencia son rebiopsiados estos pacientes y cuánto tiempo después del hallazgo inicial. Método: Estudio retrospectivo sobre 6.000 pacientes biopsiados entre 1994 y 2002. No se han incluido pacientes con diagnóstico previo de cáncer. De los 6.000 pacientes 861 se han rebiopsiado en alguna ocasión sumando en conjunto 7.127 biopsias. Se ha realizado un estudio descriptivo que incluye los porcentajes y percentiles para variables cualitativas y medidas de tendencia central para las variables cuantitativas continuas. Resultados: La incidencia de cáncer en la primera biopsia fué del 39,1%. Las cifras de PIN o AGF se mantienen estables o aumentan progresivamente desde un 2 y 2,1% respectivamente en la primera biopsia hasta más del 6% en la cuarta y quinta biopsia. La media de tiempo entre biopsias en el caso de encontrar AGF o PIN en el diagnóstico inicial es de180 ± 221,6 y 264 ± 213,8 días respectivamente. Sólo el 42 y el 40% de pacientes con diagnóstico inicial de PIN o AGF se rebiopsian, encontrando finalmente un 45 y un 40% de tumores en las posteriores biopsias respectivamente. Conclusión: La presencia de PIN o AGF implica un mayor riesgo de cáncer en biopsias posteriores; a pesar de ello menos de la mitad vuelven a biopsiarse. La realización de dos biopsias posteriores o una biopsia ampliada localiza la mayoría de los tumores asociados</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;30(4): 359-366, abr. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046145</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Significación pronóstica del PIN y la atípia glandular focal en la Biopsia Transrectal Ecodirigida de Próstata</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32640^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
