<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163886</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Boston questionnaire assessment as work for screening in pathology  carpal tunnel syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: Boston questionnaire includes referring to pain, discomfort, numbness, weakness, tingling and functionality of the hand and wrist that the patient should respond. The aim of the study is to evaluate the Boston questionnaire as a screening technique for labour carpal tunnel syndrome. Material and methods: a case-control study in workers of distribution sector. We used the following statistical techniques: Chi square, T-test, ROC curves and logistic regression. Results: it showssignificant differences in all items between cases and controls, the overall difference between the two groups scoring 11 points. The risk 2016of STC is six times higher if rate between 15 and 25 and thirty-seven times if you scored above 25 if it is scored below 15. Conclusions: the questionnaire Boston is established as a very useful tool in the screening of STC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garrido Lahiguera, Ruth</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Ferreres, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andani Cervera, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balbastre Tejedor, Maribel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Pajares, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: el cuestionario de Boston incluye referidas al dolor, molestias, pérdida de sensibilidad, debilidad, hormigueo y funcionalidad de la mano y muñeca que debe responder el paciente. El objetivo del trabajo es evaluar el cuestionario de Boston como técnica de screening para síndrome del túnel carpiano laboral. Material y métodos: estudio de casos y controles. La población del estudio pertenecen al sector de distribución Se han utilizado las siguientes técnicas estadísticas: Chi cuadrado, T de Student, curvas ROC y regresión logística. Resultados: muestran diferencias significativas en todos sus ítems entre casos y controles, siendo la diferencia global de puntuación entre ambos grupos de 11 puntos. El riesgo de padecer STC es seis veces superior si se puntúa entre 15 y 25 y treinta y siete veces superior si se puntúa por encima de 25 que si se puntúa por debajo de 15. Conclusiones: el Cuestionario de Boston se constituye como una herramienta muy útil en el screening de STC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;26(1): 31-38, mar. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163886</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración del cuestionario de Boston como screening en patología laboral por síndrome del tunel carpiano</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54190</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2392^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28162^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
