<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058928</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Multidisciplinary management of elderly patients with heart failure in a day hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. To evaluate the utility of a day hospital managed by a multidisciplinary heart failure (HF) team composed of nurses, geriatricians and internal physicians in the reduction of hospital readmission of elderly patients with HF who are not selected by their left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF).                 Material and methods. 182 patients with mean age of 76 years and decompensated HP who required admission in internal medicine and geriatric wards were included. A total of 51 patients were followed up in a day hospital, where education, phone access, drug titration and use of parenteral diuretics were performed. Readmission due to HF at 3 months post-hospitalization was measured. A bivariate analysis was performed in both groups using parametrics test (p &lt; 0.05) and a Kaplan Meier analysis using log rank.                 Results. A total of 61% were women. Mean NYHA class was 2.75 ± 0.44. LVEF &lt; 45% was found in 40%. Prescription rate of beta blockers was significantly higher in the intervention group (93% vs 24%; p &lt; 0.001) as well as ACE-inhibitors and ARB prescription rates (96% vs 72%, p = 0.002). Readmission rate due to HF in the first 90 days after discharge was lower in the intervention group (11% vs 28%; p = 0.020). HF admission free time was longer for these patient than those managed with conventional care (85.12 days versus 76; log rank; p = 0.026).                 Discussion. Multidisciplinary intervention carried out by generalist physicians and HF nurses in a day hospital is useful to reduce HF admission in elderly patients not selected by their LVEF</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Méndez Bailón, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Alonso, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez de Oteyza, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Rivas, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Audibert Mena, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conthe Gutiérrez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Evaluar la utilidad de un hospital de día llevado por un equipo multidisciplinar integrado por enfermería especializada en insuficiencia cardíaca (IC), un geriatra y médicos internistas en la reducción de ingresos de pacientes ancianos con IC no preseleccionados por fracción de eyección (FEVI).                 Material y métodos. Se incluyeron 182 pacientes con una edad media de 76 años con IC descompensada que requirieron ingreso en Medicina Interna y Geriatría. Cincuenta y un pacientes recibieron seguimiento en el hospital de día, donde se realiza educación, optimización del tratamiento, acceso telefónico y tratamiento diurético parenteral ante descompensaciones. Se midió el reingreso por IC a los 3 meses posthospitalización. Se realizó un análisis bivariante usando pruebas paramétricas (p &lt; 0,05) y el análisis de Kaplan Meier.                 Resultados. El 61% de los pacientes eran mujeres. La clase funcional media de los pacientes según la New York Heart Association (NYHA) fue de 2,75 ± 0,44 y la FEVI era &lt; 45% en el 40% de los casos. La tasa de prescripción de bloqueante beta fue más alta en el grupo de intervención (n = 51) que en el grupo control (93% frente a 24%; p &lt; 0,001), igualmente ocurrió con la prescripción de inhibidores de la enzima convertidora de la angiotensina o antagonistas de los receptores de angiotensina II (96% frente a 72%; p = 0,002). Los pacientes del grupo de intervención tuvieron menor frecuencia de reingreso por IC a los 90 días de seguimiento (28% frente a 11%; p = 0,020). El tiempo libre de reingreso fue superior en estos pacientes que en aquéllos seguidos convencionalmente (85,12 días frente a 76; log rank; p = 0,026).                 Discusión. La intervención multidisciplinar de enfermeras junto con médicos generalistas en un hospital de día constituye una opción válida en el manejo de pacientes ancianos no preseleccionados por FEVI pues reduce el reingreso hospitalario por IC</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;207(11): 555-558, dic.2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058928</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo de la insuficiencia cardíaca en pacientes ancianos a través de la implantación de un hospital de día multidisciplinar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10221</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3648</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
