<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-63065</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs induce the inhibition of prostaglandin synthesis, which can cause constriction of the fetal ductus arteriosus in the pregnancy. We report two cases of antenatal closure of ductus arteriosus with severe pulmonary hypertension following maternal ingestion of nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (niflumic acid and acetylsalicylic acid) in the last days before delivery. To our knowledge, this is only the second case in literature describing antenatal closure of ductus arteriosus after the administration of niflúmic acid. Prescription of nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs must be avoided during pregnancy. Fetal echocardiography must be monitored in those women treated with nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Luna, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Menéndez Hernando, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco Sánchez, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chacón Aguilar, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chimenti Camacho, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los antiinflamatorios no esteroideos inhiben la síntesis de prostaglandinas y producen una vasoconstricción del conducto arterioso fetal durante la gestación. Presentamos los casos de dos recién nacidos con hipertensión pulmonar grave secundaria a cierre ductal. En las semanas previas al parto, una de las madres había recibido tratamiento con ácido acetilsalicílico y la otra, con ácido niflúmico. Éste es el segundo caso descrito en la literatura médica de cierre ductal intraútero tras administración de ácido niflúmico. La ingestión de antiinflamatorios no esteroideos durante el embarazo está desaconsejado. No obstante, en las gestantes tratadas se debe realizar una monitorización continua, y la ecocardiografía fetal es de gran utilidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);68(4): 357-360, abr. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-63065</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7155^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27938^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10738^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28209^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
