<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61223</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sociodemographic variables and lifestyle as predictors of self-perceived health in immigrants in the Basque Country [Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To explore the importance of socio-demographicfactors as well as life-style and their influence in self-rated healthof Maghribian, Sub-Saharian, Latin-American and non-Communitarian European immigrant groups living in the BasqueCountry (Spain).Methods: Descriptive cross-study with a convenience sampleof 689 persons, consisting of 219 Maghribians (31.8%),152 Sub-Saharians (22.1%), 167 Latino(a)s (24.2%) and 151non-Communitarian Europeans (21.9%). Data base have beencompleted with data collected using the 2002 Regional BasqueHealth Interview Survey (ESCAV 2002). The multivariateanalysis was performed by using the dicotomic logistic regression(software SPSS 13).Results: We found that 64.2% of Maghribian, 78.7% of Sub-Saharian, 66.1% of Latin-American and 67.1% of non-CommunitarianEuropean assessed their health as very good orgood. The significantly associated variables (p &lt; 0.05 and p&lt; 0.01) with self-rated health were collective membership, sexand age. Persons belonging to the Sub-Saharian collective showeda stronger advantage of positively self-assessed health(OR = 2.08; 95%CI: 1.29-3.36). This advantage was also foundamong men of all four collectives (OR = 2.16, 95%CI: 1.54-3.02) and in persons in the age of 33-38 years (OR = 3.13,95%CI: 1.71-5.73). Those variables remained significant in themultivariate analysis.Conclusions: Our results demonstrated the importance of consideringdifferences in the health status and in self-rated healthamong immigrant groups, as well as the variables associatedwith those differences, when developing community-basedhealth strategies(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pereda Riguera, Celina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Álvarez, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Senhaji, Meftaha</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lanborena Elordui, Nerea</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Investigar la importancia de los factores sociodemográficosy de los estilos de vida en la autovaloración de lasalud en los inmigrantes de origen magrebí, subsahariano, latinoamericanoy europeo no comunitario del País Vasco.Métodos: Estudio descriptivo transversal con una muestraformada por 219 magrebíes (31,8%), 152 subsaharianos(22,1%), 167 latinoamericanos (24,2%) y 151 europeos no comunitarios(21,9%). La herramienta para la recopilación dedatos fue la Encuesta de Salud de la Comunidad Autónomadel País Vasco (ESCAV&#146;2002). El análisis multivariante se realizócon regresión logística dicotómica (soporte SPSS 13).Resultados: Para la autovaloración de la salud, el 64,2% delos magrebíes, el 78,7% de los subsaharianos, el 66,1% de loslatinoamericanos y el 67,1% de los europeos declararon teneruna salud muy buena o buena. Las variables asociadas significativamente(p &lt; 0,05 y p &lt; 0,01) a la autovaloración de lasalud fueron la procedencia, el sexo y la edad. Ser subsaharianomostró mayor ventaja para una mejor valoración de la salud(odds ratio [OR] = 2,08; intervalo de confianza del 95% (IC95%):1,29-3,36). La ventaja también se observó para los hombres(OR = 2,16; IC95%: 1,54-3,02) y la edad, especialmente en losde 33-38 años (OR = 3,13; IC95%: 1,71-5,73). En el análisismultivariante, dichas variables mantuvieron su significación.Conclusiones: Los resultados muestran la importancia de considerarel estado de salud percibida en los diferentes colectivosde inmigrantes e identificar las diferencias, así como lasvariables asociadas, para poder desarrollar actuacionesorientadas a mejorar la salud en estos grupos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;22(5): 404-412, oct. 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61223</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variables sociodemográficas y estilos de vida como predictores de la autovaloración de la salud de los inmigrantes en el País Vasco</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14563^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13329</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23661</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35120</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36372</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35159</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14563^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
