<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057039</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nursing care in patients undergoing radiological surgery. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report the case of a 73-year-old man with medical diagnoses of long-standing diabetes mellitus, chronic ischemia of the lower limbs and intermittent claudication, for which the patient had been treated with minimally invasive radiological surgery. On arrival at the radiology unit, the patient had nursing diagnoses of anxiety and fear. Intraoperatively, the client had nursing diagnoses of pain, urine retention and infection risk. At discharge, a collaboration problem was detected and hemorrhagic risk. The patient received individualized nursing care. Interventions were planned following the nursing intervention classification (NIC) and the expected results for these interventions followed the Nursing Outcomes Classification (NOC) taxonomy. The application of an appropriate nursing care plan contributes to making the patient's hospital stay easier, more comfortable and less traumatic</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Mateos, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcaraz-Baños, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernal-Páez, Fernando Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armero-Barranco, David</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta el caso clínico de un paciente varón de 73 años, con los diagnósticos médicos de diabetes mellitus de larga evolución, isquemia crónica de miembros inferiores y claudicación intermitente, al que se le ha tratado con cirugía mínimamente invasiva radiológica. A su llegada a la unidad de radiología, el paciente presenta los diagnósticos enfermeros de ansiedad y temor; durante el intraoperatorio dolor, retención urinaria y riesgo de infección, y al alta de la unidad se detecta el problema de colaboración y el riesgo de hermorragia. Se le prestan cuidados enfermeros individualizados, y se planifican las intervenciones según las clasificaciones NIC (Nursing Intervention Classification) y los resultados esperados de estas intervenciones según la taxonomía NOC (Nursing Outcomes Classification). La aplicación de un correcto plan de cuidados enfermeros ayuda a que la estancia del paciente en el quirófano sea más fácil, confortable y menos traumática</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);17(4): 215-220, jul. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057039</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuidados enfermeros a pacientes intervenidos mediante cirugía radiológica. Caso clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19270^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7547^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9922^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24850^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7592^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200707</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
