<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137297</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Old history of cannabis and recent preventive practices</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The paper analyses the information provided to the EMCDDA by Reitox Focal Points. The information relates to recent developments in drugs prevention programmes for cannabis consumption. It also includes an historical perspective on the use of the substance. The text points out that in the cannabis arena prevention is not the principal debate in Europe. This is also the case for the treatment of cannabis consumption. The paper highlights a common trend in the context of the criminal justice systems. This trend is an increase in alternative measures to prison for cannabis consumers in the EU Member states (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Merino, PP</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se analiza las informaciones facilitadas por los puntos focales del European Monitoring Centre for drugs and drug addiction (EMCDDA) en cada uno de los estados miembros de la UE. La información hace referencia a los desarrollos recientes en los programas de prevención del uso de cannabis. Incluye también una reflexión histórica acerca de los usos de esta substancia. El texto señala que en el ámbito del cannabis la prevención no es el debate principal en Europa. Este es también el caso para el tratamiento del consumo de cannabis. Llama la atención sobre el impulso que las medidas alternativas a la prisión para los consumidores y poseedores de cannabis están tomando en los estados miembros de la Unión Europea (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);12(supl.2): 275-280, 2000. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137297</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vieja historia del cannabis y recientes prácticas preventivas en Europa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5158</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22937^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14138^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53387^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22937^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
