<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59580</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Enzymatic vitrectomy by intravitreal autologous plasmin injection as initial treatment for macular epiretinal membranes and vitreomacular traction syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To determine the effectiveness of intravitrealplasmin injection in the treatment of macular epiretinalmembranes (MEM) and vitreomacular traction syndrome(VMTS) without associated pars plana vitrectomy.Methods:Design: Interventional, prospective, case seriespilot study.Patients: Seven patients were enrolled in the study,4 with MEM and 3 with VMTS.Treatment: 0.2 ml of autologous plasmin intravitreallyinjected under topical anesthesia was administered to all patients. The plasmin was obtained by a simplifiedmethod with urokinase.Main outcome measures: Degree of detachment ofthe MEM and the VMTS measured by optical coherencetomography (OCT), and the best correctedvisual acuity (Snellen scale) before and one monthafter the plasmin injection.Results: The follow-up period was completed byall the patients. The MEM remained attached to theretina in all cases, as measured either by biomicroscopyor OCT. The VMTS was completely detachedfrom the foveal area in all cases, with the disappearanceof secondary tractional retinal folds and recoveryof the normal macular anatomic architecture asmeasured by OCT. Visual acuity was not modifiedin any of the MEM patients, and improved in allVMTS patients. No adverse effects were observed.Conclusion: In our case series, intravitreally injectedautologous plasmin was not effective in the treatmentof MEM, but resolved VMTS successfully, improvingthe visual acuity and releasing the retinal tractionwithout the need for associated pars planavitrectomy. Larger studies to confirm the efficacy ofthis technique and the possibility of success afterrepeated injections are warranted(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salom, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quijada, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Llopis, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cervera, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Delpech, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Udaondo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar si la inyección intravítrea de plasmina es efectiva en el tratamiento de las membranas epirretinianas maculares (MEM) y el síndrome de tracción vitreomacular (STVM), sin necesidad de asociar vitrectomía quirúrgica.Material y método: Diseño: Estudio piloto prospectivo, de intervención, serie de casos.Pacientes: Siete pacientes, cuatro con membranaepirretiniana macular y tres con síndrome de tracciónvitreomacular.Tratamiento: Inyección intravítrea de 0,2 ml de plasmina autóloga bajo anestesia tópica. La plasminafue obtenida por un método simplificado modificado por adicción de uroquinasa.Principales medidas: Grado de separación de la membrana epirretiniana de la retina medido portomografía de coherencia óptica (OCT) y la mejor agudeza visual corregida (escala Snellen), antes y almes de la inyección de plasmina.Resultados: Todos los pacientes completaron el seguimiento de 1 mes. La membrana epirretiniana(MEM) permaneció oftalmoscópicamente adherida, sin cambios ni separación del plano de la retina. Sin embargo, en los casos con síndrome de tracciónvitreomacular (STVM), la membrana se despegó del área foveal, desapareciendo los pliegues retinianostraccionales secundarios, y normalizando la mácula la estructura anatómica. La agudeza visualno se modificó en ninguno de los casos de membrana epirretiniana y mejoró en los casos de síndromede tracción vitreomacular. No se observaron efectos secundarios.Conclusión: La inyección intravítrea de plasmina autóloga como tratamiento inicial previo a la vitrectomíaquirúrgica, en la serie de casos estudiada, parece ineficaz en las membranas epirretinianasmaculares, y más eficaz en el síndrome de tracción vitreomacular, mejorando en este último la agudeza visual y consiguiendo el despegamiento al menosparcial de la membrana. Estudios más amplios son necesarios para confirmar su eficacia y la posibilidad de incrementar la misma con reinyeccionesperiódicas de plasmina(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;84(2): 91-100, feb. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59580</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vitrectomía enzimática por inyección intravítrea de plasmina autóloga como tratamiento inicial de las membranas epirretinianas maculares y el síndrome de tracción vitreomacular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33767^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33357^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5231^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33357^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30897^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30897^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5231^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30897^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15223^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24366^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24366^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15223^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
