<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113835</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Identifying rural sexual assault service strengths, concerns and educational needs in rural and aboriginal communities Alberta, Canada</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Women in rural communities do not regularly receive comprehensive health care following sexual assaults, resulting in increased rates of mental illness, substance abuse, re-victimization, and chronic health problems. Additionally, women are at risk for secondary victimization, the stigmatization and re-victimization that results from the responses of others to the assault. Secondary victimization is amplified when victims must be transported out of a rural community for treatment, receive delays in services, when professionals react negatively towards them, or provide incomplete services. A research study sought to find ways of addressing these risks and understanding the educational resources needed for crisis care workers in rural and Aboriginal communities. The findings from focus group interviews with interdisciplinary professionals in rural Alberta, Canada, identified strengths, challenges and priority educational needs for those caring for sexual assault victims(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jakubec, Sonya L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carter-Snell, Catherine J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Skanderup, Judy</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ofrim, Jenny</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las mujeres en las comunidades rurales no reciben regularmente la atención integral de salud debida después de haber sufrido agresiones sexuales, lo que resulta en un aumento de las tasas de enfermedad mental, abuso de sustancias, revictimización, y problemas de salud crónicos. Además, las mujeres corren el riesgo de una victimización secundaria, de una estigmatización y de una revictimización derivada de las respuestas de los otros a la agesión. La victimización secundaria aumenta cuando las víctimas deben ser transportadas fuera de la comunidad rural para su tratamiento, debido a las demoras en los servicios, cuando los profesionales reaccionan de forma negativa hacia ellas, o sencillamente prestan unos servicios incompletos. Un estudio de investigación se hace necesario para abordar estos riesgos y comprender la necesidad de recursos educativos para los trabajadores que están a cargo de la crisis en las comunidades rurales y de aborígenes. Los hallazgos de las entrevistas de grupo con profesionales interdisciplinarios en las zonas rurales de Alberta, Canadá, identificaron algunas fortalezas, pero también revelan desafíos y la prioridad de una educación necesaria para aquellas personas que cuidan de las víctimas de agresión sexual(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;12(31): 409-426, jul. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113835</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Identificación de las fortalezas, preocupaciones y necesidades educativas del Servicio Rural de Agresión sexual en las comunidades rurales y aborígenes de Alberta (Canadá)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13122^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12797^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13323^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d378^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19101^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51928^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13323^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51928^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13122^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32616^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19101^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
