<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147628</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Development deficit risks in the late premature newborn: Evaluation at 48 months using the Ages &amp; Stages Questionnaires®</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Lack of specific monitoring protocols hinders the knowledge of the impact of late prematurity on delayed psychomotor development. The objective of this study is to evaluate this at 48 months and compare it with those born at term. Population and methods: A retrospective cohort study was conducted on 90 late preterm (PT) and 89 term (AT) healthy children at 48 months, assessed by the Ages &amp; Stages Questionnaires® (ASQ-3). Continuous variables described using mean and standard deviation compared with the t Student t test for independent samples. The categorical variables were described as frequencies and proportions, compared with the Chi-square test of independence. A cut-off was determined for the total score of ASQ-3 able to discriminate the risk of developmental deficit by a ROC analysis. A step-wise logistic regression model identified the associated risk factors. Results: The mean scores for each domain and overall ASQ-3 score showed no differences between groups. However, when analyzing the probability density for the ASQ-3 total score of &amp;#8804;251 points, 15 PT (16.6%) and 4 AT (4.5%) showed risk of psychomotor deficits, and late prematurity and lack of breastfeeding were significantly associated factors. Conclusions: There is an increased prevalence of risk of development deficit in the PT, which justifies considering this population at risk and establishing effective monitoring programs. It should be further investigated whether this risk corresponds to the entire population, or if there are biological factors or perinatal history that makes them more vulnerable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sala, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Demestre, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Raspall, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vila, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morillas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schonhaut, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Nadal, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La ausencia de protocolos específicos de seguimiento dificulta el conocimiento de la repercusión de la prematuridad tardía en el desarrollo psicomotor. El objetivo es evaluarlo a los 4 años y compararlo con los nacidos a término (AT). Población y método: Estudio de cohortes retrospectivo de 90 prematuros tardíos (PT) y 89 AT sanos, a los 48 meses, evaluados mediante el Ages &amp; Stages Questionnaires® (ASQ-3). Las variables continuas se describen mediante media±DE comparadas con el test de la t de Student para muestras independientes; las variables categóricas, mediante frecuencias y proporciones, comparadas con el test de independencia de la chi al cuadrado. Se determinó un punto de corte para la puntuación total del ASQ-3 capaz de discriminar el riesgo de déficit del desarrollo mediante un análisis ROC. Una selección step-wise para el modelo de regresión logística determinó los factores de riesgo asociados. Resultados: Las puntuaciones medias de cada dominio y de la puntuación global del ASQ-3 no mostraron diferencias entre ambos grupos. Sin embargo, al analizar la densidad de probabilidades para la puntuación global del ASQ-3 &amp;#8804; 251 puntos, 15 PT (16,6%) y 4 AT (4,5%) mostraban riesgo de déficit psicomotor, y la prematuridad tardía y la ausencia de lactancia materna resultaron factores asociados significativamente. Conclusiones: Hubo una mayor prevalencia de riesgo de déficit en el desarrollo en los PT, lo que justifica considerar esta población de riesgo y establecer programas de seguimiento eficientes. Debe seguirse investigando si este riesgo corresponde a toda la población o si existen factores biológicos o antecedentes perinatales que los hacen más vulnerables (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);84(1): 39-45, ene. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147628</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Riesgo de déficits en el desarrollo en los prematuros tardíos: evaluación a los 48 meses mediante el Ages &amp; Stages Questionnaires®</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28614</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7410^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38857^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22228^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
