<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-62839</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: To describe the evolution of prostate cancer mortality in Spain during the period 1991-2005. Subjects and methods: A trend analysis for age standardized mortality rates (European standard population) was performed, using joinpoint regression analysis, which allows estimation of the annual percent change of rates and to find significant changes in such trend. Results: Age standardized mortality rates in Spain reached their peak value in 1996. The joinpoint analysis identified two different periods in the trend of the age standardized rates: a first one of increase in rates between 1991 and 1996 (2.1% annual increase) and a second period starting in 1996, in which rates decline at an annual rate of 2.7%.Conclusion: The tendency of prostate cancer seen in Spain resembles that of industrialized areas, with an increase in its age standardized death rates that suffers a downturn by the end of the past decade. Mortality declines for prostate cancer are now evident in 14 out of the 17 Autonomous Communities. Increases in PSA screening and better treatment of early-stage disease, possibly acting in combination, remain plausible hypotheses (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barrero Candau, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Domínguez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vigil Martín, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cayuela, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir la evolución de la mortalidad por cáncer de próstata en España en el periodo 1991-2005. Sujetos y métodos: Realizamos un análisis de tendencia de las tasas estandarizadas de mortalidad (población estándar Europea) mediante análisis de regresión &#147;joinpoint&#148;, el cual nos permite estimar el porcentaje de cambio anual de las tasas y localizar cambios significativos en la tendencia. Resultados: Las tasas de mortalidad estandarizada alcanza su máximo valor en 1996. El análisis &#147;joinpoint&#148; identifica dos periodos diferentes en la tendencia de las tasas estandarizadas: uno inicial de incremento entre 1991 y 1996 (2,1% de incremento anual) y un segúndo periodo comenzando en 1996, en el que las tasas descienden un -2,7% anual. Conclusión: La tendencia de la mortalidad por cancer de prostata en España es similar a la de otras áreas industrializadas, con un incremento en las tasas estandarizadas que sufren un descenso hacia el final de la década pasada. El descenso en la mortalidad por cáncer de próstata es ahora evidente en 14 de las17 Comunidades Autónomas. El incremento del cribaje oportunistico con PSA y una mejora en el tratamiento, posiblemente actuando en combinación, constituye la hipótesis más plausible (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;32(2): 184-189, feb. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-62839</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200802</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
