<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165829</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Improving treatment adherence: One of the most effective ways of increasing patient survival in secondary prevention</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In secondary cardiovascular prevention, the degree of control of cardiovascular risk factors in European countries is inadequate and poor treatment adherence appears to be one of the causative factors. Good adherence has been associated with a 20% reduction in the risk of cardiovascular disease and a 38% decrease in all-cause mortality. Patients with poor adherence have a three-fold increased risk of death. However, adherence to treatment involving preventive drugs (e.g. aspirin, beta-blockers, angiotensinconverting enzyme inhibitors and statins) is only around 50% 1 year after hospital discharge. The World Health Organization defines treatment adherence as the degree to which an individual&#146;s behavior with respect to taking medications or implementing recommended dietary or lifestyle changes corresponds with the actions health-care professionals have agreed with the patient. There is no ideal way of measuring adherence but it is recommended that the Haynes-Sackett test and the Morisky-Green 8-item questionnaire should be used in clinical practice. Nevertheless, the reference standard remains the pill count, with good adherence being considered an intake more than 80% of that prescribed. Strategies for ensuring better treatment adherence, increasing the degree of disease control and reducing health-care costs include improving communication between doctors and patients, facilitating the continuity of care by collaborating with primary care staff, involving other health-care professionals (e.g. pharmacists) and developing fixed-dose combination therapies, such as the polypill (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Orozco Beltrán, Domingo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En prevención secundaria cardiovascular, el grado de control de los factores de riesgo cardiovascular es deficiente en los países europeos y la falta de adherencia terapéutica parece ser uno de los factores causales. La buena adherencia se asocia a un 20% de disminución del riesgo de enfermedad cardiovascular y un 38% de disminución de mortalidad por cualquier causa. Los pacientes con mala adherencia multiplican por 3 el riesgo de mortalidad. Sin embargo, la adherencia a los fármacos preventivos (ácido acetilsalicílico, bloqueadores beta, inhibidores de la enzima de conversión de la angiotensina, estatinas, etc.) ronda el 50% 1 año después del alta hospitalaria. La Organización Mundial de la Salud define adherencia terapéutica como el grado en que el comportamiento de una persona, con respecto a tomar la medicación o seguir una recomendación dietética o de cambio de estilo de vida, concuerda con las prescripciones del profesional sanitario consensuadas con el paciente. No existe un método ideal para medir la adherencia, pero se recomienda para la práctica clínica la pregunta de Haynes-Sackett y el cuestionario de Morisky-Green de ocho ítems. No obstante, el patrón de referencia sigue siendo el recuento de comprimidos, y se considera buena adherencia el consumo de más del 80% de la prescripción. Mejorar la comunicación entre médicos y pacientes, facilitar la continuidad asistencial mediante la colaboración con atención primaria, involucrar a otros profesionales sanitarios (farmacéuticos) y el desarrollo de terapias combinadas a dosis fijas, como la polypill, son estrategias que pueden mejorar la adherencia terapéutica y el grado de control y reducir los costes sanitarios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);15(supl.E): 12e-18e, 2015. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165829</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mejorar la adherencia: una de las acciones más eficientes para aumentar la supervivencia de los pacientes en prevención secundaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38788^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33014^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4400</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22832^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32281</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53262^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27951^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
