<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76631</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of the pressure ulcers in a Basic Zone of Health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The pressure ulcers (PU) represent an important problem of healthin all the welfare levels, but a volume of them need continued care from the community.The aim of our study is to know the period of prevalence of the pressureulcers and its distribution among other characteristics that we find in our BasicZone of Health. Material and methods: A cut was realized for retrospective periodof prevalencia in Piloña's BZH (Asturias) for the interval of time from01/09/2004 to 31/08/2005 both included. The population to study belongs to8475 inhabitants, (information of the Municipal poll updated in 2005) ofwhich 4339 were women. There were 2644 persons over 65 years old of which853 are over 80 years old. It is a dispersed, aged population and in regressionwith an index of dependence of 0,69. Was considered to be PU's case anyone thatshould consist in the record of the Clinical History of Primary care, an electronicformat OMI - AP 6.0, of our Team of Primary care for the studied period.Results: There were studied 33 PU (32 patients) of which 20 (60,60 %) womenwere suffering them. The middle ages were of 88,21 + - 9,98 years. The raw periodof prevalencia (RP) of PU for the whole of the population was 0,39 % and thereason of prevalencia woman / male was of 1,48. For groups of age in &lt;65 yearsold the absolute frequency (AF of the wounds was of 1 (3 %) ulcers and the RPwas 0,02 %. In&gt; 65 years old the FA was 32 (97 %) ulcers and the RP of 1,22%. In the group of 80 and more years old the AF was 29 (88 %) ulcers and theRP of 3,40 %. 69 % of the persons with PU was included in the service ofDomiciliary Attention and the RP of period of PU for the population included in (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Con Redondo, Juan de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Cuervo, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las úlceras por presión (UPP) representan un importante problemade salud en todos los niveles asistenciales, pero un volumen importantede las mismas precisan de cuidados continuados desde la comunidad. Elobjetivo de nuestro estudio es conocer la prevalencia de período de las UPP ysu distribución entre otras características que se encuentran en nuestra zonabásica de salud. Material y métodos: Se ha realizado un corte de prevalenciade período retrospectivo en la ZBS de Piloña (Asturias) para el intervalo detiempo comprendido entre el 1 de septiembre de 2004 y el 31 de agosto de2005, ambos inclusive. La población estudiada es de 8.475 habitantes (datosdel Padrón Municipal actualizado en 2005) de los cuales 4.339 fueron mujeres.Mayores de 65 años eran 2.644 personas, de las cuales 853 son mayoresde 80 años. Se trata de una población dispersa, envejecida y en regresión conun índice de dependencia de 0,69. Se consideró caso de UPP todo aquel queconstaba como tal en el registro de la historia clínica de Atención Primaria,formato electrónico OMI-AP 6.0, de nuestro Equipo de Atención Primariapara el período estudiado. Resultados: Se estudiaron 33 UPP (32 pacientes)de las cuales 20 (60,6%) las padecía mujeres. La edad media fue de 88,21 ±8,98 años. La prevalencia cruda (PC) del período de UPP para el total de lapoblación fue del 0,39% y la razón de prevalencia mujer/varón fue de 1,48.Por grupos de edad en &lt; 65 años la frecuencia absoluta (FA) de lesiones fuede una úlcera (3%) y la PC fue de 0,02%. En &gt; 65 años la FA fue de 32 úlceras(97%) y la PC del 1,22%. En el colectivo de 80 y más años la FA fue de29 úlceras (88%) y la PC del 3,4%. El 69% de las personas con UPP estabaincluido en el servicio Atención Domiciliara y la PC del período de UPP para (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);20(2): 92-97, abr. -jun. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76631</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de úlceras por presión en una zona básica de salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
