<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102380</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Contact Sensitization to Allergens in the Spanish Standard Series at Hospital Costa del Sol in Marbella, Spain: a Retrospective Study (2005-2010)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The prevalence of contact allergy to different compounds can vary according to the population studied, the technique used, and the materials employed in patch tests. The Spanish Contact Dermatitis and Skin Allergy Research Group (GEIDAC) has proposed a panel of 29 allergens for use in patients with suspected allergic contact dermatitis. Objective: To determine the prevalence of contact sensitization in a group of Spanish patients and to analyze potential associations with sociodemographic and clinical variables (sex, age, site of lesions, occupation, and diagnosis of atopic dermatitis). Material and methods: A retrospective study of patients with suspected contact dermatitis was undertaken at Hospital Costa del Sol in Marbella, Spain, for the period between January 1, 2005 and December 31, 2010; 839 patients were included in the analysis. Patch tests were carried out with 34 allergens, including the 29 compounds that comprise the Spanish standard panel proposed by the GEIDAC. Results: Sensitization to at least 1 allergen in the panel was observed in 48% of patients. Women had a higher frequency of sensitization than men (56.9% vs 33.1%). The hands were the most commonly affected site (36.1%). The most frequently involved allergens were nickel sulfate (25.9%), potassium dichromate (7.6%), thiomersal (5.1%), cobalt chloride (4.5%), and fragrance mix I (3.8%). In contrast, preservatives such as paraben mix (0.1%), imidazolidinyl urea (0.1%), diazolidinyl urea (0.2%), and quinoline mix (0.2%) had low rates of sensitization. Sensitization to sesquiterpene lactones and methyldibromo glutaronitrile (euxyl K 400) were not observed. Conclusions: Our results are similar to those previously reported for Spanish patients. The low level of sensitization to certain allergens such as most preservatives and sesquiterpene lactones may suggest that their use in standard patch test series should be reconsidered(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Morano, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar Bernier, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivas-Ruiz, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernal-Ruiz, A. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Troya-Martín, M. de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La prevalencia de la alergia de contacto a los diferentes compuestos puede variar dependiendo de la población estudiada, de la técnica y del material empleado en las pruebas epicutáneas. En España el Grupo Español de Investigación en Dermatitis de Contacto y Alergia Cutánea (GEIDAC) ha propuesto una batería de 29 alérgenos para estudiar a los pacientes con sospecha de dermatitis de contacto alérgica. Material y métodos: Análisis retrospectivo de 839 pacientes con sospecha de dermatitis de contacto, realizado en el Hospital Costa del Sol desde el 1 de enero de 2005 hasta el 31 de diciembre de 2010. Para ello se utilizaron pruebas epicutáneas estándar de 34 alérgenos en las que estuvieron incluidos los 29 compuestos de la batería estándar española propuesta por el GEIDAC. Objetivo: Valorar la prevalencia de la sensibilización de contacto entre los pacientes estudiados y estudiar su asociación con factores sociodemográficos (sexo, edad, localización, ocupación) y clínicos (dermatitis atópica). Resultados: El 48% de los pacientes presentó sensibilización al menos a uno de los alérgenos testados. Las mujeres presentaron una frecuencia de sensibilización más elevada que los hombres (56,9 vs. 33,1%). La localización afectada con mayor frecuencia fue la mano (36,1%). Los alérgenos más frecuentes fueron sulfato de níquel (25,9%), dicromato potásico (7,6%), tiomersal (5,1%), cloruro de cobalto (4,5%) y mezcla de fragancias I (3,8%). Por el contrario, se detectó una baja frecuencia de sensibilización a conservantes como mezcla de parabenos (0,1%), imidazolidinil urea (0,1%), diazolidinil urea (0,2%) y mezcla de quinoleínas (0,2%). No se registraron sensibilizaciones para lactonas sesquiterpénicas y metildibromoglutaronitrilo (euxyl K400). Conclusiones: Nuestros resultados son similares a los previamente publicados a nivel nacional. La baja sensibilización a ciertos alérgenos, como la mayoría de conservantes y las lactonas sesquiterpénicas, podría hacer necesario reconsiderar su utilidad como alérgenos en futuras series estándar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;103(3): 223-228, abr. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102380</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sensibilización de contacto a alérgenos de la serie estándar en el Hospital Costa del Sol: Estudio retrospectivo (2005-2010)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4553^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22604^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4553^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3894^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22631^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23089</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22604^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22604^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
