<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74762</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Surgical treatment of facial hemangiomas in children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hemangiomas are the most common soft-tissue tumorsin childhood. They occur in approximately 5-10% of one-year-oldchildren. Despite their frequency, the pathogenesis of these tumorsis not completely clear. Conservative management usually is proposedfor hemangiomas that occur in childhood, but the occurrence ofthese tumors on the face can result in severe complications and maybe an indication for treatment. We report four patients who receivedsurgical treatment before the age of seven years for severecomplications, including repeated bleeding, distortion of adjacentstructures, and vision disorders. The surgical techniques dependedon the location and size of the lesion(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Báez Arias, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estrada Sarmiento, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Terán Quiñones, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Virelles Espinosa, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los hemangiomas son los tumores de tejido blando más comunesen la infancia. Ocurren aproximadamente en el 5-10% de los niños deun año de edad. A pesar de la frecuencia de estos tumores, su patogénesisno está completamente esclarecida. Aunque el manejo conservador es usualmentepropuesto para los hemangiomas que ocurren en la infancia, la presenciade estos tumores en la cara puede resultar en complicaciones severasy proporcionar una indicación para el tratamiento. En este trabajo mostramoscuatros pacientes que recibieron tratamiento quirúrgico antes de los sietesaños por las complicaciones severas que incluían sangramientos repetidos,distorsión de las estructuras adyacentes y trastornos visuales. Las técnicasquirúrgicas dependieron de la localización y tamaño de la lesión(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;30(4): 274-280, jul.-ago. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74762</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento quirúrgico de los hemangiomas faciales en niños</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6542^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33572^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5246^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6542^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200808</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
