<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116049</identifier>
<setSpec>2254-2884</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparative study on patients treated with post-dilution on-line haemodiafi ltration, different fl ow rates of dialysis fluid, real dialysis time and prescribed time</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The dialysis dose (DD) is a key element of dialysis adequacy and affects survival of patients undergoing dialysis. Some elements standing out concerning the DD are: dialysis time, blood flow rate (Qb), transfer area coefficient (KOA) and dialysate flow rate (Qd). The aim of this study is to find out whether Qd 800 ml / min and 240 minutes prescribed time is more effective than Qd 500 ml / min and 240 minutes prescribed time and also to compare Qd 500 ml/min and 240 minutes of real dialysis time. Patients and Methods. A transversal prospective study was conducted of a population in dialysis, inclusion criteria being an adult treated with post-dilution on-line haemodiafiltration and sufficient blood flow rate. In all patients was performed 18 consecutive sessions varying Qd and time as follows: Stage 1: 6 sessions Qd 800 ml/min and prescribed time 240 minutes (F1) Stage 2: 6 sessions Qd 500 ml/min and prescribed time 240 minutes (F2) Stage 3: 6 sessions Qd 500 ml/min and real dialysis time 240 minutes (F3) Statistical analysis performed using SPSS 13.0 for Windows. Quantitative variables were expressed as mean, standard deviation and range, and qualitative variables expressed as frequency and percentage. Results 432 sessions analysed getting higher Kt and reinfusion volume (VTR) in stage 3 in relation to other stages. No significant difference between stage 1 and 2. Discussion and conclusions: No differences in dialysis efficacy Qd 500 ml / min versus Qd 800 ml / min. Nevertheless, increasing 10 minutes in each session, the dialysis dose increases 2.77 litres and VTR increases 9%, halving this way the number of patients that don&#146;t reach 20 litres reinfusion volume. All this achieved with a lower fee due to the size difference bicarbonate concentrate packaging(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aznar Barbero, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bel Cegarra, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>David Pagan Escribano, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bartolomé García Nicolás, Asensio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Badallo Mira, María Magdalena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La dosis de diálisis es un elemento fundamental en la diálisis adecuada y en la supervivencia del paciente. Entre los elementos que influyen en la misma destacan: tiempo, flujo sanguíneo (Qb), coeficiente de transferencia de masa de urea (KoA) y flujo del baño (Qd). El objetivo es evaluar si con Qd 800 ml/ min y tiempo programado 240 minutos conseguimos mayor eficacia que con Qd 500 ml/min y tiempo programado 240 minutos y con Qd 500 l/min y tiempo efectivo 240 minutos. Pacientes y métodos Estudio prospectivo sobre población prevalente en hemodiálisis, con criterio de inclusión pacientes mayores de edad en hemodiafiltración on-line postdilucional con flujo sanguíneo adecuado. En cada paciente se realizan 18 sesiones consecutivas variando Qd y tiempo con siguiente esquema: Fase 1: 6 sesiones con Qd 800 ml/min y tiempo programado 240 minutos. Fase 2: 6 sesiones con Qd 500 ml/min y tiempo programado 240 minutos, Fase 3: 6 sesiones con Qd 500 ml/min y tiempo efectivo 240 minutos. El análisis estadístico se realiza mediante SPSS 13.0 para Windows. Las variables cuantitativas se expresan como media, desviación estándar y rango. Las variables cualitativas, como frecuencia y porcentaje. Resultados Analizamos 432 sesiones obteniendo Kt y Volumen total de reinfusión (VTR) mayores en la fase 3 del estudio con respecto a las otras dos, no existiendo diferencias significativas entre la fase 1 y 2. Discusión y conclusiones No existen diferencias en la eficacia dialítica entre Qd 500 ml/min y Qd 800 ml/min, mientras que con el aumento de 10 minutos de media en cada sesión, se incrementa la dosis de diálisis en 2,77 litros y el VTR en un 9%, reduciendo a la mitad el número de pacientes que no logran los 20 litros de volumen de reinfusión. Y esto, con un menor coste adicional especialmente por las diferencias de envasado del bicarbonato (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. nefrol;16(3): 155-160, jul.-sept. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116049</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio comparativo en pacientes en Hemodiafiltración en línea postdilucional de alta eficacia con diferentes flujos de líquido dializante, tiempo programado y tiempo real</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31418^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31418^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31418^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3982^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31418^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31418^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3982^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23606^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23606^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
