<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142217</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Levels of obesity, fasting glycemia and physical condition in chilean students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Chile has drastically altered eating patterns and physical activity. The main nutritional problem faced by Chilean society is overweight, which arises progressively from an early age. The aim of this study is to determine the nutritional status and compare fitness levels and fasting glucose in students. Patients and methods: a descriptive cross-sectional comparative study was conducted, making a comparison by gender and nutritional status, with 100 students (56 men and 44 women) aged 12-15 years old. Body composition, fasting glucose and fitness were evaluated. Results: women had a higher prevalence of overweight and obesity than men (22.73% and 19.65%). In the comparison of gender differences statistics were reported in one repetition maximum (1RM) (p = 0.001), abdominal strength (p = 0.004) and velocity (p = 0.001), there were no significant differences in body mass index (BMI) (p = 0.24) and fasting glucose (p = 0.99). In the comparison of nutritional status, the students classified as obese had a higher waist perimeter (p = 0.001), more time to walk 400 m (p = 0.008). There were no significant differences in other variables. Conclusions: women have a higher prevalence of overweight and obesity than men. Obese students have a waist circumference more elevated, more time to walk 400 meters (p =&lt; 0.05) and they have increased levels of basal glucose (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guzmán Guzmán, Iris Paola</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos Jara, Christian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez-Campillo, Rodrigo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ríos Lagos, Gonzalo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Inostroza, Hugo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Floody, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jerez Mayorga, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caamaño Navarrete, Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: en Chile se han modificado drásticamente los patrones de alimentación y de actividad física. El principal problema nutricional que enfrenta la sociedad chilena es el exceso de peso, que se presenta en forma progresiva desde temprana edad. El objetivo del estudio es determinar el estado nutricional y comparar los niveles de condición física y glicemia en ayuno de los escolares. Pacientes y métodos: se realizó un estudio descriptivo-comparativo de corte transversal, realizando una comparación por género y estado nutricional, con 100 escolares (56 hombres y 44 mujeres) de entre 12 a 15 años de edad. Se evaluó la composición corporal, la glucosa en ayuna y la condición física. Resultados: las mujeres presentaron mayor prevalencia de sobrepeso y obesidad que los hombres (22,73% y 19,65%). En la comparación de género se reportaron diferencias estadísticas en una repetición máxima (1RM) (p = 0,001), resistencia abdominal (p = 0,004) y velocidad (p = 0,001); no existieron diferencias significativas en el índice de masa corporal (IMC) (p = 0,24) ni en glucosa en ayunas (p = 0,99). En la comparación del estado nutricional, en los escolares clasificados como obesos se observó un perímetro de cintura más elevado (p = 0,001) y mayor tiempo para recorrer 400 m (p = 0,008); no existieron diferencias significativas en las demás variables. Conclusiones: las mujeres presentan una mayor prevalencia de sobrepeso y obesidad que los hombres. Los escolares obesos presentan un perímetro de cintura más elevado, mayor tiempo para recorrer 400 metros (p = &lt; 0,05) y poseen niveles aumentados de glucosa basal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(6): 2445-2450, jun. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142217</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Niveles de obesidad, glicemia en ayuno y condición física en escolares chilenos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37656^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55220^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1503^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28461</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55220^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
