<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-29451</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Space-occupying cerebellar infarcts: surgical or conservative treatment?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Space-occupying cerebellar infarcts (SOCI) make up a subgroup within the ischemic pathologies of the brain which are generally well tolerated clinically and usually respond well to medical treatment. Yet, in some cases, due to their volume and localisation, they can be accompanied by a progressive deterioration that requires surgical treatment. We report the clinical cases of two patients with SOCI that illustrate both therapeutic alternatives. Case reports. We describe the case of a 65- year-old male patient with vertiginous syndrome, inability to walk and headache. Computerised axial tomography (CAT) scanning showed a SOCI in the left hemisphere that displaced the 4th ventricle, effaced the cisterns and gave rise to the hydrocephalus. The patient improved clinically with medical treatment and a week later was able to walk unaided. We also describe the case of a 75-year-old female patient with symptoms of deterioration in the level of consciousness. CAT and magnetic resonance scans showed an extensive SOCI in the right hemisphere with displacement of the 4th ventricle, effacement of the perimesencephalic cisterns and triventricular hydrocephalus. A suboccipital craniectomy was performed, along with excision of any necrotic material and duroplasty. At 24 h the patient expressed herself coherently and followed orders. She presented ataxia and dysmetry on the right-hand side following the operation, which were compensated with rehabilitating therapy. Conclusions. Our clinical case reports illustrate the alternatives available when dealing with patients with cerebellar infarct that show expanding clinical-radiological characteristics. These patients must be carefully controlled because of the risk of clinical deterioration, in which case timely surgical intervention can increase their survival (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los infartos cerebelosos expansivos (ICE) forman un subgrupo dentro de la patología isquémica cerebral, generalmente bien tolerado clínicamente y habitualmente con buena respuesta al tratamiento médico. Sin embargo, en determinados casos, por su volumen y localización, pueden asociarse a un deterioro progresivo que precise de tratamiento quirúrgico. Presentamos los casos clínicos de dos pacientes con ICE que ilustran las dos alternativas de tratamiento. Casos clínicos. El primer paciente, de 65 años, presenta un síndrome vertiginoso, incapacidad para la marcha y dolor de cabeza. En la tomografía computarizada (TC) apreciamos un ICE en el hemisferio izquierdo que desplaza el IV ventrículo, borra las cisternas y origina hidrocefalia. Con tratamiento médico, el paciente experimentó mejoría clínica y, al cabo de una semana, pudo deambular de forma independiente. La segunda paciente, de 75 años, presenta una clínica de deterioro del nivel de conciencia. La TC y la resonancia magnética mostraron un extenso ICE en el hemisferio derecho con desplazamiento del IV ventrículo, borrado de cisternas perimesencefálicas e hidrocefalia triventricular. Se llevó a cabo una craniectomía suboccipital, exéresis de material necrótico cerebeloso y plastia dural. A las 24 h la paciente se expresaba con coherencia y obedecía órdenes. Presentó ataxia y dismetría derecha tras la cirugía, compensadas con tratamiento rehabilitador. Conclusiones. Nuestros casos clínicos ilustran las alternativas ante aquellos pacientes con infarto cerebeloso con características clinicorradiológicas de expansión. Estos pacientes deben controlarse cuidadosamente por el riesgo de deterioro clínico, en cuyo caso la cirugía precoz puede aumentar su supervivencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;38(2): 133-136, ene. 2004. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infarto cerebeloso expansivo: ¿tratamiento quirúrgico o conservador?</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Conte, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Millán Corada, AM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortés, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prat, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-29451</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7882</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2583</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3321</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2568</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13419</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33112</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6350</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14065</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200401</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
