<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129338</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnostic Usefulness of the Cytological Study of the Transport Buffer in Transrectal Prostate Core Biopsies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: To evaluate the diagnostic usefulness of the cytological study of the transport buffer in the diagnosis of prostate adenocarcinoma in transrectal core biopsies. Methods A total of 256 consecutively biopsied patients have been included in the analysis, 100 of them diagnosed of prostate adenocarcinoma. The procedure included the cytological analysis of the transport buffer and conventional histology.  Cytological evaluation was performed in a blind way by the same pathologist. Results: Overall sensitivity, specificity, and positive and negative predictive values to detect malignancy in the cytological slides were 54%, 98%, 94% and 76%, respectively. When restricted the analysis to cases with Gleason score higher than 8, sensitivity and negative predictive value increased to 85% and 97%, respectively. Similarly, when the analysis focused exclusively to cases with more than 5 mm of cancer in the biopsy, sensitivity and positive predictive value increased to 66% and 96%, respectively. Conclusions: This study shows that whilst specificity was maintained in 98%, sensitivity, and positive and negative predictive values significantly improved in high grade and high volume adenocarcinomas. Our findings confirm that the cytological study of the transport buffer may complement the histology in the diagnosis of prostate adenocarcinoma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Caamaño, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lecumberri, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arruza, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cáceres, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larrinaga, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, JI</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: Evaluar la utilidad diagnóstica del estudio citológico del tampón de transporte en el diagnóstico de adenocarcinoma de próstata en biopsias por punción transrectal. Métodos: Un total de 256 pacientes biopsiados consecutivamente se han incluido en el análisis, 100 de ellos diagnosticados de adenocarcinoma de próstata. El procedimiento incluyó el análisis citológico del tampón de transporte y la histología convencional. Se realizó evaluación citológica de una manera ciega por el mismo patólogo. Resultados: La sensibilidad, especificidad y valores predictivos positivos y negativos globales para la detección de malignidad en los portaobjectos citológicos fueron 54, 98, 94 y 76%, respectivamente. Cuando se restringió el análisis a los casos con una puntuación de Gleason superior a 8 la sensibilidad y el valor predictivo negativo aumentaron a 85 y 97%, respectivamente. Del mismo modo, cuando el análisis se centró exclusivamente en los casos con más de 5 mm de cáncer en la biopsia la sensibilidad y el valor predictivo positivo aumentaron a 66 y 96%, respectivamente. Conclusiones: Este estudio muestra que mientras que la especificidad se mantuvo en el 98% la sensibilidad y los valores predictivos positivos y negativos mejoraron significativamente en los adenocarcinomas de alto grado y de alto volumen. Nuestros hallazgos confirman que el estudio citológico del tampón de transporte puede complementar la histología en el diagnóstico de adenocarcinoma de próstata (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;38(9): 566-570, nov. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129338</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad diagnóstica del estudio citológico del tampón de transporte en biopsias por punción prostática transrectal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29170^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14011^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201411</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
