<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166316</identifier>
<setSpec>2174-0852</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Short form of the Spanish adaptation of the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background/Objective: The State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI) is one of the assessment instruments that are most widely used by psychologists around the world and is the seventh most broadly used by clinical psychologists in Spain. Although several short forms of the STAI have been developed since its creation, none are available for the Spanish general population. The aim of the present study was to develop and validate a short form of the STAI. Method: To achieve this, we administered the full STAI to 1,157 healthy adults, and 30 patients with generalized anxiety disorder. We conducted a discriminant analysis using such groups. Results: We obtained a selection of four items for state anxiety and four items for trait anxiety and compared it to other short forms through a confirmatory factor analysis. The short form obtained with the discriminant analysis showed the best fit for Spanish samples. Conclusions: these eight items can be used to facilitate the state and trait anxiety assessment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Buela-Casal, Gualberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillén-Riquelme, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes/objetivos: El State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI) es uno de los instrumentos de evaluación más empleados por psicólogos en todo el mundo y el séptimo más utilizado por psicólogos clínicos en España. Desde su creación, se han llevado a cabo varias versiones breves del mismo; pese a ello, no existe ninguna para población general con muestra española. El objetivo del presente artículo es establecer y validar una versión breve. Método: Para ello, se aplicó el STAI completo a 1.157 adultos y 30 pacientes con trastorno de ansiedad generalizada. Mediante dichos grupos, se realizó un análisis discriminante. Resultados: Para la ansiedad estado y rasgo, respectivamente, se obtuvieron reducciones de cuatro ítems y se compararon con otras versiones breves mediante análisis factorial confirmatorio. La versión establecida mediante análisis discriminante muestra el mejor ajuste en muestra española. Conclusiones: estos ocho ítems pueden ser usados para facilitar la evaluación de la ansiedad estado y rasgo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int. j. clin. health psychol. (Internet);17(3): 261-268, sept.-dic. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166316</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Versión breve de la adaptación española del State-Trait Anxiety Inventory</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10746^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
