<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158410</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5735</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">More on interpretation (I). Reasoning and truth</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Any interpretation must be based upon a theory of the reality to be interpreted while constituting, in turn, a theory or hypothesis of the interpreted reality. An interpretation is an inference, specifically a pragmatic inference and not a deductive one. Foremost among pragmatic inferences is abduction, retroduction or hypothesis in their different degrees of proximity to truth according to the empirical support on which they are based, in other words, to borrow Umberto Eco&#146;s terminology, overcoded, undercoded and creative abductions. As every interpretation involves approaching truth to a greater or lesser degree, it becomes imperative to define precisely the limits of the concept. With this goal, three concepts closely related to truth are examined: the concepts of verisimilitude, validity and probability. The conclusion of this analysis is that, given that it is not possible to access truth in its totality, truth becomes what Popper called a regulatory principle, being the concept of verisimilitude more realistic and applicable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díez Patricio, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Toda interpretación ha de estar basada en una teoría de la realidad a interpretar y constituye, a su vez, una teoría o hipótesis de la realidad interpretada. Una interpretación es una inferencia, concretamente una inferencia pragmática, no deductiva. Entre las inferencias pragmáticas la principal es la abducción, retroducción o hipótesis en sus diferentes grados de acercamiento a la verdad según el apoyo empírico en que se sustente, a saber, en la terminología de Umberto Eco, abducciones hipercodificadas, hipocodificadas y creativas. Como toda interpretación supone un mayor o menor acercamiento a la verdad, es imprescindible la delimitación y precisión de este concepto. Para ello, hemos discutido tres conceptos estrechamente relacionados con el de verdad como son los de verosimilitud, validez y probabilidad. El resultado de esta discusión es que, como no es posible acceder en su totalidad a la verdad, ésta se constituye en lo que Karl Popper denomina un principio regulador, siendo más realista y aplicable el concepto de verosimilitud (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Neuropsiquiatr;36(130): 363-382, jul.-dic. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158410</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Más sobre la interpretación (I). Razonamiento y verdad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28635</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28426</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8304</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14746</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
