<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163119</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Differences Between Men and Women in Chronic Scratching: A Psychodermatologic Study in Lichen Simplex Chronicus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Chronic scratching is common to many skin disorders. Being a female and presenting a high level of psychopathology are risk factors for chronic scratching. Yet, it is unclear why. Certain personality characteristics that are more prevalent in women are also known to influence emotional states (i.e. emotional tension). Objective: The present study aims to explore whether these personality styles might help understand why gender and emotional distress are associated with scratching. Material and methods: We compared the personality patterns of 103 patients (69.9% women) diagnosed with Lichen Simplex Chronicus, against a sample of healthy individuals. Results: Significant differences were found in the personality styles of men and women with LSC. Women were more pessimistic, oriented to fulfil the needs of others, traditional, insecure, submissive, and reserved, with moderate (d= .43) to strong (d= .96) size effects ranges. Some of these differences, such as in traditionalism, dutifulness, other-orientation, and pessimism, were also observed when compared with healthy men and women, with small (d= .03) to moderate (d= .47) size effects ranges. Conclusions: These psychological factors may help explain the mechanisms underlying gender differences in chronic scratching, at least in Lichen Simplex Chronicus. The findings might open new avenues for research and treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Brufau Redondo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corbalán Berná, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suso-Ribera, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Brufau, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El rascado crónico es común a varias enfermedades dermatológicas. Ser mujer y presentar niveles elevados de psicopatología son factores de riesgo para el rascado crónico. Sin embargo, aún se desconoce la causa de esta relación. Ciertas características de personalidad relacionadas con el estrés son más prevalentes en mujeres. Objetivo: Explorar si los estilos de personalidad pueden explicar las diferencias entre hombres y mujeres en las variables psicológicas asociadas con el rascado crónico. Material y métodos: Comparamos los perfiles de personalidad de 103 pacientes (69,9% mujeres) diagnosticados de liquen simple crónico y una muestra de sujetos sanos. Resultados: Se encontraron diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre hombres y mujeres con liquen simple crónico, siendo las mujeres más pesimistas, orientadas a los demás, tradicionales, inseguras, sumisas y reservadas en cuanto a sus emociones negativas, con rangos del tamaño del efecto entre moderados (d = 0,43) y altos (d = 0,96). También se encontraron entre la muestra de liquen simple crónico y los controles, como por ejemplo en tradicionalismo, sumisión, orientación al otro y pesimismo, con rangos del tamaño del efecto entre bajos (d = 0,03) y moderados (d = 0,47). Conclusiones: Estos hallazgos podrían ayudar a explicar los mecanismos subyacentes a las diferencias de sexo en rascado crónico, al menos en el liquen simple crónico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;108(4): 354-360, mayo 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163119</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias de personalidad entre hombres y mujeres con liquen simple crónico. Implicaciones para la conducta de rascado crónico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11976^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9643^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10743^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9643^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
