<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128940</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Teaching experience of the anesthesiology training unit at Hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Health care in Spain has improved progressively and professionals are now required to meet competency levels that safeguard the citizen&#146;s right to health protection. To achieve this, instructors in residency training programs and resident physicians themselves are calling for a common framework for training to ensure quality and consistency. Given the scarcity of articles related to training in our journal and following the First Meeting of Residency Program Instructors of the Sociedad Española de Anestesiología y Reanimación (SEDAR), there has arisen a need to explain how SEDAR&#146;s training unit is organized. Methods: In order to facilitate the sharing of experiences of those involved in training anesthesiology medical residents, we undertook a descriptive analysis of our hospital&#146;s curriculum. Results: The structure and operation of the department are described in this report. The results of anonymous surveys completed annually show the satisfaction of residents (9.4 out of 10) and physicians (8.7 out of 10). An audit by the Ministry of Health showed that the curriculum met 100% of the required criteria(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moure García, e. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Besada Estévez, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reverón Gómez, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejera Concepción, R. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bravo García, P. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: La sanidad en España ha evolucionado hacia una mejora de la calidad, exigiendo a los profesionales que cumplan los niveles de competencia necesarios para salvaguardar el derecho a la protección de la salud de los ciudadanos. Para alcanzarlos, las Unidades Docentes y los Médicos Residentes demandan un marco común de formación que garantice la calidad y la uniformidad de la docencia. Dado el escaso número de publicaciones en nuestra revista relacionadas con la docencia y tras la Primera Reunión de Tutores de Anestesiología y Reanimación de la SEDAR, surgió la inquietud por dar a conocer cómo tenemos organizada nuestra Unidad Docente. Métodos: Con el objetivo de facilitar el intercambio de experiencia de los implicados en la formación de los Médicos Internos Residentes de Anestesiología, Reanimación y Terapéutica del Dolor realizaremos un análisis descriptivo de la formación en nuestro hospital. Resultados: Se describe la estructura y funcionamiento. Las encuestas anónimas realizadas anualmente por los residentes (9,4 puntos sobre 10) y facultativos (8,7 sobre 10) muestran la aceptación del sistema. Además en una auditoría docente del Ministerio de Sanidad se ha cumplido el 100% de los criterios exigidos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;58(4): 223-229, abr. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128940</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia de la unidad docente de Anestesiología y Reanimación del Hospital Universitario Nuestra Señora de Candelaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30213^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d787^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6940^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6940^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6939^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6940^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6939^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24419</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30213^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d787^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5280^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
