<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161454</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Benefits of early specialized nutritional support in malnourished patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objective. Disease related malnutrition (DRM) is highly prevalent in Spain, affecting 23% of in-hospital patients, and is associated with clinical complications. Specialized nutritional support (SNS) can reduce these complications. Material and methods. Prospective study carried out in standard clinical practice conditions to test if SNS during the first 5 days of hospitalization, or subsequently, was associated to a lower length of stay or reduced complications in patients with a NRS-2002 score&amp;#8805;3 points. Results. In the group of patients who initiated early SNS, the length of stay was 8.83 days shorter than in the group with a later introduction (95% CI 3.55-14.10); nevertheless, the higher prevalence of male and oncological patients in this group could have impacted the results. A tendency towards a statistically significant lower mortality rate and a reduced amount of total complications was described. Conclusion. The early introduction of SNS (within the first 5 days of hospitalization) in patients with DRM was associated with a 32.4% reduction in the length of stay (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Piedra León, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amado Señaris, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morán López, Jesús Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beneítez Moralejo, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luengo Pérez, Luis Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Enciso Izquierdo, Fidel Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo. La desnutrición relacionada con la enfermedad (DRE) presenta una prevalencia del 23% en el medio hospitalario español y se asocia a complicaciones clínicas. El soporte nutricional especializado (SNE) puede reducir estas complicaciones. Material y métodos. Estudio prospectivo en condiciones de práctica clínica habitual que compara la reducción de la estancia y las complicaciones en pacientes con NRS-2002&amp;#8805;3 puntos que recibieron SNE durante los 5 primeros días de ingreso (precoz) o posteriormente. Resultados. El grupo con SNE precoz presentó una estancia media 8,83 días inferior al grupo con introducción tardía (IC 95% 3,55-14,10), si bien este grupo mostró un predominio de pacientes varones y con enfermedad oncológica que pudo influir en los resultados. Se describió una tendencia no estadísticamente significativa a la reducción de la mortalidad y las complicaciones totales. Conclusión. La introducción precoz (primeros 5 días) del SNE en DRE se asoció a una reducción del 32,4% de la estancia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);148(7): 303-307, abr. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161454</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Beneficios del soporte nutricional especializado precoz en pacientes con criterios de desnutrición</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14209^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25401^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23862^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32108^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4645^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16541</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
