<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88928</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparison of 2 methods of clinical data collection, one using the PAINOUT</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: To compare postoperative pain intensity and incidence of adverse events when the evaluation is performed by a visual numerical scale completed by the patient (PAINOUT), or using a verbal numerical scale completed by ward nurses or the staff of the acute pain unit. Methods: Fifty-two postsurgical patients of both sexes (age range 31-80 years) admitted to the general surgery ward were sequentially recruited and evaluated on postoperative day 1. All patients were assessed using both questionnaires, which measure postoperative outcomes using scales of 0 to 10; values &gt;= 4 were considered clinically relevant. The test and Cohen coefficient were used for statistical analysis. Results: Using the PAINOUT questionnaire, the mean maximum intensity of referred pain was 5.40 (range, 0-10) and the minimum intensity was 1.83 (range, 0-5). Mean values obtained with the verbal numerical scales used by staff on the ward and in the pain clinic were 3.76 (range, 0-10) and 0.97 (range, 0-5), respectively. The differences between the 2 methods of pain assessment were statistically (P = .006) and clinically significant. When evaluating nausea with PAINOUT questionnaire, all patients provided a response; in 88.5% the intensity was less than 4. Six patients reported nausea on the PAINOUT but not in the UDA questionnaire. Moreover, 61% of patients reported drowsiness/sedation in PAINOUT instrument, whereas none reported that effect on the verbal scale. Conclusions: The intensity of pain and adverse events is significantly higher when the patient evaluates and records its intensity on visual numerical scales compared with verbal numerical scales(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-López, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domingo Vicent, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puig Riera de Conías, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montes Pérez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dürsteler, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Comparar la intensidad del dolor postoperatorio y la incidencia de efectos adversos cuando la evaluación se realiza mediante una escala numérica visual completada por el propio paciente (PAINOUT) y una escala numérica verbal utilizada por el personal de la unidad de hospitalización/unidad de dolor agudo (UH/UDA). Métodos: Participaron 52 pacientes postquirúrgicos de ambos sexos, rango de edad 31-80 años, reclutados secuencialmente en la UH de cirugía general y evaluados durante las primeras 24 horas del postoperatorio utilizando los dos cuestionarios. Ambos tienen un rango del 0- 10 y valores &gt;=4 fueron considerados clínicamente relevantes. Resultados: En PAINOUT, la media de la intensidad máxima de dolor referido fue de 5,40 (rango 0-10) y la de la intensidad mínima de 1,83 (0-5); en la escala verbal numérica UH/UDA los valores fueron 3,76 (rango 0-10) y 0,97 (0-5), respectivamente. Las diferencias entre los dos métodos de evaluación del dolor fueron estadísticamente (p = 0,006) y clínicamente significativas. Al evaluar las náuseas mediante el PAINOUT, todos los pacientes registraron una respuesta por escrito y en el 88,5% de los pacientes la intensidad fue &lt; 4; seis pacientes refirieron náuseas en el PAINOUT, pero no en el cuestionario UH/UDA. Además, un 61% de pacientes registró cansancio/sedación &gt;= 4 en PAINOUT y ninguno en la evaluación UH/UDA. Conclusiones: La intensidad del dolor y los EA son significativamente mayores cuando el propio paciente evalúa y registra su intensidad mediante escalas numéricas visuales comparadas con las escalas numéricas verbales(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;58(5): 273-278, mayo 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88928</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de dos métodos para la recogida de datos clínicos utilizando el cuestionario de PAINOUT (base de datos europea para la gestión del dolor postoperatorio)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201105</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
