<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136446</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4603</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Objectivity of the electroglottography. Clinical and investigative applications in the voice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present article demonstrates the objectivity of electroglottography as an instrument for assessment and therapeutic monitoring of vocal deficiencies. Research has been designed in a retrospective and observational way, with systemic review methodology based on publications from thesis, dissertations, monographs and papers in English, Portuguese and Spanish indexed in Pubmed, SciELO, Ebsco Host, Scopus and Cochrane databases, as well as specialized journals such as ASHA, Journal of Voice, Medline, CEFAC and Redalyc. It presents a conceptualization of electroglottography and the description of the procedure, technique, methodology and interpretation, considering the need to achieve optimal applicability of everything presented theoretically (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calvache Mora, Carlos Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente artículo demuestra la objetividad de la electroglotografía como instrumento para la evaluación y seguimiento terapéutico de deficiencias vocales. Se desarrolla un diseño de investigación observacional y retrospectivo, bajo la metodología de revisión sistémica, a partir de publicaciones de tesis, disertaciones, monografías y artículos de revistas en inglés, portugués y español en las bases de datos PubMed, SciELO, Ebsco Host, Scopus y Cochrane, además de revistas especializadas como la ASHA, Journal of Voice, MedLine, CEFAC y Redalyc. Presenta una conceptualización de la electroglotografía, así como la descripción del procedimiento, de la técnica, de la metodología y de la interpretación, teniendo en cuenta la necesidad de lograr una óptima aplicabilidad de todo lo presentado teóricamente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. logop. foniatr. audiol. (Ed. impr.);35(3): 134-142, jul.-sept. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136446</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Objetividad de la electroglotografía. Aplicaciones clínicas e investigativas en la voz</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15235^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10894^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27926^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27926^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27926^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27926^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6075^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27926^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52965^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15233^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4638^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
