<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135898</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-6585</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Risk factors, diagnosis and treatment of peri-implant disease: A literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The aim of this paper is to deepen the knowledge of peri-implant disease and existing treatments described in the literature. Material and methods: Literature review of peri-implant disease based on a search in databases like PubMed and Medline using keywords "periimplantitis, mucositis, tabaquism, oral microbiota, occlusal overload, surgical treatment, antimicrobial therapy, detoxification, regenerative therapy, bone defects". Development and discussion: Analysis of risk factors, diagnosis and treatment of peri-implant disease. Conclusions: Factors such as tabaquism or a history of periodontitis, along with poor oral hygiene are the main causes of peri-implant disease. A correct diagnosis of the cause and the appropriate choice of therapy may stop the progression of peri-implant disease. Following treatment done, it will be very important to do the periodic controls and maintenance of proper oral hygiene (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gil Pulido, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segura Andrés, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Faus López, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferreiroa Navarro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agustín Panadero, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente González, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El objetivo de este trabajo es profundizar en el conocimiento de la enfermedad periimplantaria y los tratamientos existentes descritos en la literatura. Material y método: Revisión bibliográfica de las enfermedades periimplantarias, basada en una búsqueda en bases de datos Pubmed, Medline y Cochrane Library, utilizando como palabras clave "periimplantitis, mucositis, tabaquism, oral microbiota, occlusal overload, surgical treatment, antimicrobial therapy, detoxification, regenerative therapy, bone defects". Desarrollo y discusión: Análisis de los factores de riesgo, el diagnóstico y el tratamiento de las enfermedades periimplantarias. Conclusiones: Los factores como el tabaco o una historia de periodontitis, junto con una mala higiene oral, son las principales causas de las enfermedades periimplantarias. Un correcto diagnóstico de la etiología, así como, la adecuada elección de la terapéutica, pueden detener el avance de la enfermedad periimplantaria. Tras el tratamiento realizado, será muy importante el control periódico y el mantenimiento de una correcta higiene oral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. periodoncia implantol. oral;27(1): 25-36, abr. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135898</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Periimplantitis y mucositis periimplantaria. Factores de riesgo, diagnóstico y tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53959^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55394</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30063^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13668^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53959^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
