<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88395</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Urethral stricture in women. Morphofunctional diagnosis and treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: The objective of this article is to describe the diagnosis of bladder outlet obstruction in women and the treatment of urethral stricture as a cause thereofMETHOD: A bibliographic review was performed in the Medline (PubMed) data base on articles published on the diagnosis of bladder outlet obstruction in women and the treatment of urethral stricture in the 1989-2009 period.RESULTS: The prevalence of obstruction in women varies between 2.7% and 23% in the literature. The gold standard for diagnosis is the videourodynamic study. 78% of obstructions are functional, and only 6.8% are secondary to urethral stricture. Stricture commonly affects the urethral meatus and the distal third of the urethra, the most frequent cause being yatrogenic, secondary to surgery for incontinence, urethral dilations and traumatic catheterisation. The treatment of urethral stricture will depend on the location and length of the stricture, the length of the healthy proximal urethra, bladder neck integrity and the coexistence of incontinence. The repeat failure of non-invasive techniques and the presence of partial or total urethra defects will be subsidiary to urethral reconstruction techniques by means of flaps or grafts, although the technique of choice is still controversial.CONCLUSION: The diagnosis of bladder outlet obstruction in women is limited by the absence of clearly defined urodynamic parameters. Urethral stricture is an infrequent cause of obstruction, the treatment of which may constitute a therapeutic challenge. Early stricture relapse may constitute grounds for considering early surgical reconstruction. Vaginal flaps are the cornerstone of urethral reconstructions. Extensive vulvar scarring may require the use of grafts(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Capitan, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrera, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña, Enrique de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llorente, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: El objetivo del presente artículo es la descripción del diagnóstico de la obstrucción infravesical en la mujer y el tratamiento de la estenosis uretral como causa de la misma.MÉTODO: Se realizó una revisión bibliográfica en la base de datos de Medline (PubMed) de los artículos publicados sobre el diagnóstico de la obstrucción infravesical en la mujer y el tratamiento de la estenosis uretral en el periodo 1989-2009.RESULTADOS: La prevalencia de obstrucción en la mujer varía en la literatura entre el 2,7 y el 23%. El patrón de referencia para su diagnóstico es el estudio videourodinámico. El 78% de las obstrucciones son de carácter funcional y sólo un 6,8 % son secundarias a la estenosis uretral. La estenosis afecta comúnmente al meato uretral y el tercio distal de la uretra, y la causa más frecuente es la iatrogénica, secundaria a cirugía de la incontinencia, dilataciones uretrales y la cateterización traumática. El tratamiento de la estenosis de uretra dependerá de la localización y longitud de la estenosis, la longitud de la uretra sana proximal, la integridad del cuello vesical y la coexistencia de incontinencia. El fracaso repetido de técnicas no invasivas y la presencia de defectos parciales o totales de uretra serán subsidiarias de técnicas de reconstrucción uretral mediante colgajos o injertos, aunque la técnica de elección es motivo de controversia.CONCLUSIÓN: El diagnóstico de la obstrucción infravesical en la mujer está limitado por la ausencia de parámetros urodinámicos claramente definidos. La estenosis uretral es una causa infrecuente de obstrucción cuyo tratamiento puede constituir un desafio terapéutico. La recidiva precoz de la estenosis debería ser motivo para considerar la reconstrucción quirúrgica precoz. Los colgajos vaginales constituyen la base de las reconstrucciones uretrales. La cicatrización vulvar extensa pueden hacer necesaria la utilización de injertos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;64(2): 97-104, mar. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88395</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estenosis de uretra en la mujer. Diagnóstico morfo-funcional y tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14924^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14923^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7231</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
