<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117219</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neuropsychiatric disorders in a case of a brain injury due to an air gun shot</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Neuropsychiatric consequences after traumatic brain injury can appear in many forms, even years after the event. Several syndromes have been described that lead to disability and a decrease in the quality of life to a varying degree of patients and relatives. These can be difficult to diagnosis and treat. In fact, there are records in literature of changes in premorbid personality traits including, mood and affectivity, anxiety, post-traumatic stress, psychotic disorders, and cognitive dysfunction. Symptoms like low motivation, lack of interest in surroundings and idea-verbal and affective lack are attributable to some of these syndromes. We present the clinical case of a 38 year old man previously diagnosed with antisocial personality disorder who, after attempted suicide by an air gun shot, suffered frontoparietal trauma with subsequent brain abscess. During his evolution he had different complications and neuropsychiatric consequences of traumatic brain injury. Changes could be observed in previous personality traits, post-traumatic psychotic disorder, and finally cognitive impairment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodulfo Lafuente, Juan Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Garrido, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Molero, M. Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-ligero, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez León, Fátima</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las secuelas neuropsiquiátricas tras un traumatismo craneoencefálico (TCE) pueden ser muy variadas e incluso aparecer años después del mismo. Se han descrito síndromes diversos que producen un grado variable de discapacidad y descenso en la calidad de vida percibida de pacientes y familiares, y que pueden presentar dificultades diagnósticas y de manejo terapéutico. Así, se registran en la literatura médica cambios en los rasgos de personalidad premórbidos, en el humor y en la afectividad, ansiedad, estrés postraumático, trastornos psicóticos y disfunción cognitiva, entre otros. Síntomas como la escasa motivación, la falta de interés por el entorno y el déficit ideoverbal y afectivo son atribuibles a varios de estos síndromes. Se presenta el caso de un varón de 38 años de edad, previamente diagnosticado de trastorno disocial de la personalidad que, tras intento autolítico por disparo con carabina de aire comprimido, sufre un traumatismo frontoparietal con un absceso cerebral posterior. Durante su evolución presentó de manera sucesiva distintas complicaciones y secuelas neuropsiquiátricas del TCE, observándose modificación de sus rasgos caracteriales previos, trastorno psicótico postraumático y finalmente deterioro cognitivo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);20(4): 70-74, oct.-dic. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117219</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos neuropsiquiátricos en un caso de lesión cerebral por carabina de aire comprimido</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24895^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1956^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24895^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1956^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1956^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d991^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1714^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d991^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1714^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1956^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
