<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050551</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Inner and outer root configuration. Its importance on root canal treatment prognosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">394 teeth were studied whose external shape, total lenght and mesiodistal and vestibular palatine diameters were measured. The internal shape was also assessed making transversal cuts of. The roots a the third levels of the cervical, middle and apical. This experience allowed us to show with anatomic grounds the non sufficient preparation of the canals that many endodontic schools propose when they work with low caliber instruments at the apical level. It is more convenient to use more important calibres alone the whole length of the canal, respecting the root anatomy</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blustein, D. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Joaquín Poladian, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fueron estudiadas 394 piezas dentales de las cuales se midieron la configuración externa; la longitud total y los diámetros mesiodistal y vestibulopalatino; y la configuración interna haciendo cortes transversales de las raíces a nivel de los tercios cervical, medio y apical.    Este experiencia nos permitió demostrar con fundamentos anatómicos la insuficiente preparación de los conductos que proponen muchas escuelas endodónticas al trabajar con instrumental de bajo calibre a nivel apical. Siendo conveniente utilizar calibres más importantes en toda la longitud del conducto, respetando la anatomía radicular</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);24(2): 78-86, abr.-jun. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050551</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Configuración radicular externa e interna. Su importancia en el éxito del tratamiento endodóntico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14485^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12765^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33126</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32617^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
