<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162968</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8799</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Functional implications of the strength training on older adult: a literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aging is a set of processes, inherent of living beings, of which induce loss of capacity to adapt into the environment by decreased functionality. It is associated to a declivity of the functions of the musculoskeletal and neuromuscular systems converging in degrowth of all expressions of muscular strength, including maximum, power and the reaction time. The functional capacity makes reference to a multidimensional quality, however, for the particular aspect of physical functioning, it is considered as the physiologic capacity to perform activities of daily living safely and independently, without provoking exhaustion. To fight the phenomena that promote the continued loss of functional capacity, they require strategies that promote benefits in musculoskeletal and neuromuscular systems, especially if you manage to decrease the speed of deterioration, benefit the quality of life, functional independence and influence increased life expectancies. Both older men and women, the different modalities of strength training can constitute a proper strategy to combat these effects. The purpose of this review article was to systematize the alterations of skeletal muscle during aging and the derivatives muscular adaptations of the different strength training in older adults systems, based on the most conspicuous and relevant scientific literature. The synthesis of results justifies the importance of the application of strength training to avoid sarcopenia, dynapenia and optimize the functional capacity in older adults. Is paramount the knowledge on muscle characteristics (morphological and neuromuscular) necessary in the implementation of the different modalities of training. The adaptations provided by the reagent system training, showing greater functional benefits for older adults, collated with traditional training modalities and the power training (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Suarez Landazabal, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Polo Gallardo, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva Correa, Cleiton</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rebolledo-Cobos, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juliao-Castillo, Jesse</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El envejecimiento es un conjunto de procesos, inherente a los seres vivos, los cuales inducen a la pérdida de la capacidad de adaptación al ambiente mediante la disminución de la funcionalidad. Está asociado a un declive de las funciones de los sistemas osteomuscular y neuromuscular, convergiendo en el decrecimiento de todas las expresiones de la fuerza muscular, incluyendo la máxima, la potencia y también el tiempo de reacción. La capacidad funcional hace referencia a una cualidad multidimensional, sin embargo, para el aspecto particular de funcionalidad física, se considera como la capacidad fisiológica  para realizar las actividades de la vida diaria de forma segura y autónoma, sin provocar agotamiento. Para batallar los fenómenos que promueven la perdida continua de la capacidad funcional, se requieren de estrategias que promuevan beneficios en los sistemas osteomuscular y neuromuscular, especialmente sí logran disminuir la velocidad de deterioro. Las diferentes modalidades de entrenamiento de la fuerza pueden constituir una estrategia adecuada para combatir estos efectos. El objetivo de presente artículo de revisión fue sistematizar las alteraciones del músculo esquelético durante el envejecimiento y las  adaptaciones musculares derivadas de los diferentes sistemas entrenamiento de la fuerza en adultos mayores, con base a la literatura científica más conspicua. La síntesis de resultados justifica la importancia de la aplicación del entrenamiento de la fuerza para evitar la sarcopenia y optimizar la capacidad funcional en adultos mayores. Es de suma importancia el conocimiento sobre las particularidades musculares (morfológicas y neuromusculares) necesarias en la implementación de las diferentes modalidades de entrenamiento. Las adaptaciones proporcionadas por el sistema de entrenamiento reactivo, muestran mayores beneficios funcionales para los adultos mayores, cotejado con las modalidades de entrenamiento tradicional y de potencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. med. deporte;34(177): 31-39, ene.-feb. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162968</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implicaciones funcionales del entrenamiento de la fuerza en el adulto mayor: una revisión de literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54694^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28940^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
