<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120353</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of the social context on the body image perception of women undergoing breast cancer surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In Western cultures, female breasts are strongly related to the world of sexuality and physical attractiveness, although this can vary according to the social context. Objective: To determine the influence of social context on the body image perception of women undergoing breast cancer surgery. Material and method: An observational, descriptive and cross-sectional study was performed. Study settings were the State Oncology Center of the ISSEMyM (Social Security Institute of the State of Mexico and its Municipalities) in Toluca (Mexico) and San Cecilio University Hospital in Granada (Spain). The study sample comprised 72 mastectomized females, 30 from Mexico and 42 from Spain. Data were gathered on their sociodemographic variables, self-reported personal and family clinical histories, and scores on the validated Hopwood Body Image Scale (BIS). Results: In the Spanish group of mastectomized women, 67.7% were in active employment compared with 43.3% of the Mexican group, a significant difference (p &lt; 0.05). Body image perception was superior in women connected to the world of work and with a higher educational level. The women in a more developed social context had a significantly (p &lt; 0.05) better body image perception. Conclusions: The social context of masectomized women affects their body image perception, which is influenced by their occupation and educational level (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Neri Sánchez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Valverde, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar Cordero, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mur Villar, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El pecho de la mujer está muy relacionado en la cultura occidental con el mundo de la sexualidad y el atractivo físico, aunque puede variar en función del contexto. Objetivo: Determinar la influencia del contexto social en la percepción de la imagen corporal de las mujeres intervenidas de cáncer de mama. Material y método: Se llevó a cabo un estudio observacional, descriptivo y transversal. Los escenarios del estudio estuvieron constituidos por el Centro Oncológico Estatal del ISSEMyM en la ciudad de Toluca (México), y el Hospital Clínico San Cecilio de la ciudad de Granada (España). La totalidad del universo estuvo formado por 72 mujeres mastectomizadas. De ellas, 30 correspondieron a México y 42 a España. Se recogieron datos de variables sociodemográficas y las mujeres respondieron a preguntas sobre su historia clínica personal y familiar. Se aplicó la Escala validada BIS (Body Image Scale) de Hopwood. Resultados: El 67,7% mujeres mastectomizadas españolas se encuentran activas laboralmente en comparación al 43,3% de las mujeres mexicanas. Diferencia estadísticamente significativas en los dos grupos (p &lt; 0,05). En la medida en que las mujeres se vinculan al mundo laboral e incrementan su nivel de escolaridad, la aceptación de la imagen corporal muestra mejores resultados. Las mujeres que viven en contextos sociales desarrollados tienen una mejor percepción de su imagen corporal. Con una diferencia significativa de (p &lt; 0,05). Conclusiones: El contexto social influye en la percepción de la imagen corporal de las mujeres intervenidas de cáncer de mama. La ocupación laboral y el grado de escolaridad fueron determinantes de la percepción de la misma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;28(5): 1447-1452, sept.-oct. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120353</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia del contexto social en la percepción de la imagen corporal de las mujeres intervenidas de cáncer de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4592</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16054^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1853</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8580^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
