<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-67962</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1473</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">During last 50 years chemotherapy has played a very important part in the cancer treatment. However succes or failures of news drugs in one particular cancer its difficult to predict. In vitro chemo-sensitivity is an attractive method for knowing about responses of a tumor to ChT treatment and assess the best dose in the patient with cancer. Objective. To know brain tumors sensitivity againstantineoplastic drugs. Methods. Five differents drugs (carmustin, camptotecin, taxol, hydroxyurea and tamoxifen) were tested on short-term cultures from 7 patients with Glioblastoma multiforme, 15 patients with meningiomas and one patient with meduloblastoma. For testing chemosensitivity we used MTT assay, and we measured optic density by spectophotometry to 450 nm. Results. A total of 49 measurement were done, getting44 valids dose-result curves. For each drug we used from 10-2 M to 10-12 M gap, and IC50 result was representative of tumor sensitivity to the drug. Conclusion. our data support MTT assays like valid method for measuring in vitro chemosensitivity in brain tumors to news drugs</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gil-Salú, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez-Pascual, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bosco-López, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Requena, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palomo, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez-Villar, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Escobar, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Durante los últimos 50 años la quimioterapia (QT)ha jugado un importante papel en el tratamiento del cáncer. Sin embargo, el éxito o fracaso de nuevas drogas para un determinado tipo de cáncer es difícil de predecir. La quimio sensibilidad in vitro es un método atractivo para conocer a priori si ese tumor responderá a una pauta de QT y para determinar la dosis óptima de tratamiento en los enfermos con cáncer. Objetivo. Conocer la sensibilidad de tumores cerebrales frente a determinados fármacos antineoplásicos. Material y métodos. Se ensayaron 5 fármacos diferentes (carmustina, camptotecina, taxol, hidroxiureay tamoxifeno) en los cultivos primarios obtenidos de7 pacientes con glioblastoma multiforme, 15 pacientescon meningiomas y un paciente con medulo blastoma. Para estudiar la quimiosensibilidad se empleó el test del MTT, midiendo la densidad óptica por espectofotometríaa 450 nm. Resultados. Un total de 49 mediciones fueron realizadas, obteniendo 44 curvas dosis-respuesta válidas. Se emplearon concentraciones desde 10-2 M hasta 10-12 M para cada fármaco ensayado, obteniendo IC50 en cada caso como valor representativo de la sensibilidad del tumor a la droga. Conclusiones. El test MTT se muestra válido para medir la quimio sensibilidad in vitro de tumores cerebrales a nuevos fármacos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurocirugia (Astur);19(1): 5-11, ene.-feb. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-67962</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1958^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1958^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d974^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31846^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8750^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22884^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200802</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
