<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100585</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Identification and bibliometric characterization of research groups in the cardio-cerebrovascular field, Spain 1996-2004</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. The abundance of macro-level studies on scientific production in the field of biomedicine in Spain only serves to highlight the scarcity of micro-level studies reporting on the activity of research groups&#150;the basic units of the science and technology system. This lack of information may well be explained by the ambiguity inherent in the &#147;research group&#148; concept and by the existence of synonymous and homonymous bibliographic signatures that confuse the correspondence between these and the real authors. The aim of this study is to describe bibliographic production in cardio-cerebrovascular research and identify research groups active in the field. Methods. Using Thomson-Reuters&#146; National Citation Report for Spain database and the National Library of Medicine Medical Subject Headings thesaurus, we defined the field of cardio-cerebrovascular research and identified research groups through coauthorship analysis supported by the opinions of an expert. Groups were described in terms of bibliometric indicators of activity and visibility. Results. Ninety-three groups made up of 772 different authors were identified from an initial subset of 6540 publications on cardio-cerebrovascular research. The groups we identified came mainly from the healthcare sector and the universities and were mostly located in the autonomous regions of Catalonia and the Community of Madrid. The scientific production attributable to the groups presented indicators of visibility above the mean for biomedicine. Conclusions. Collaboration between the healthcare sector and the universities dominated cardio-cerebrovascular research, although international collaboration rates were poor, standing at levels below the mean for biomedicine (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Suñén-Pinyol, Eduard</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cervelló, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camí, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez-Vásquez, Raúl I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. La abundancia de estudios macro sobre la producción en biomedicina en España pone de manifiesto la escasez de estudios micro que informan sobre la actividad de grupos de investigación, unidad básica del sistema de ciencia-tecnología. Entre las dificultades que explicarían dicha escasez, cuentan la ambigüedad del concepto de «grupo de investigación» y la existencia de firmas bibliográficas sinónimas y homónimas que falsean la correspondencia entre firmas bibliográficas y autores. El objetivo del presente estudio es caracterizar la producción bibliográfica en el campo cardio-cerebrovascular e identificar los grupos de investigación en esta área de estudio. Métodos. Empleando la base de datos National Citation Report for Spain de Thomson-Reuters y el tesauro Medical Subject Headings de la National Library of Medicine, se definió el área cardio-cerebrovascular, y posteriormente se identificó los grupos de investigación mediante el análisis de coautorías y el concurso de un experto. Los grupos se caracterizaron bibliométricamente empleando indicadores de actividad y visibilidad. Resultados. Se identificó un total de 93 grupos, formados por 772 autores distintos, a partir de un subconjunto inicial de 6.540 publicaciones en tema cardio-cerebrovascular. Los grupos detectados procedieron principalmente del sector sanitario y universitario, y se concentraron en las comunidades de Cataluña y Madrid. La producción científica atribuible a los grupos presentó indicadores de visibilidad superiores a la media del ámbito de biomedicina. Conclusiones. La colaboración entre los sectores sanitario y universitario predominó en el área cardio-cerebrovascular; por el contrario, la colaboración internacional es una asignatura pendiente, con índices bajos en comparación con la media de biomedicina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;65(7): 642-650, jul. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100585</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Caracterización bibliométrica de la producción bibliográfica de los grupos de investigación cardio-cerebrovascular, España 1996-2004</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1325^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50117</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50089</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201207</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
