<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118111</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hospital mortality due to acute poisoning: EXITOX 2012</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Death registers are a tool for planning public health care interventions, but data on deaths due to acute poisoning are scarce in Spain. We report a descriptive study based on a cross-section of patients who died from acute poisoning in2012 in 8 Spanish public hospitals and whose deaths were recorded in the EXITOX register. Of the 14 registered cases, 7(50%) were suicides; 71% were men, and the mean age was 59.1 years. Caustic substances comprised the largest category (35.7%) of toxic agents, followed by medications (21.4%), and street drugs (21.4%). The mortality rate was0.5 deaths/100 000 inhabitants. Specific antidotes were used in 28.6% of the cases. In 71%, there was a clear relationship between death and acute poisoning. The EXITOX register, even with its limitations, seems to provide an appropriate tool for understanding mortality due to acute intoxication in Spain (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Puiguriguer, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echarte, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dueñas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cordoba, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nogué, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burillo-Putze, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los registros de mortalidad son un instrumento para la planificación de las actuaciones en el ámbito de la salud pública. A pesar de ello, los datos sobre fallecimientos por intoxicación aguda en España son escasos. Se presenta un estudio descriptivo, de encuesta transversal, de pacientes fallecidos en el año 2012 como consecuencia de una intoxicación aguda en 8 hospitales públicos españoles, incluidos en el registro EXITOX. Se registraron 14 casos, con una edad media de 59,1 años, 71% varones y de causa suicida en el 50%. Los cáusticos fueron el principal grupo de tóxicos implicado(35,7%), seguido de los fármacos (21,4%) y las drogas de abuso (21,4%). La tasa de mortalidad por intoxicación fue de 0,5 casos/100.000 habitantes. Se utilizaron medidas terapéuticas toxicológicas específicas en el 28,6%. Se consideró como indudable la relación entre intoxicación y fallecimiento en el 71%. Aún con las limitaciones existentes, el registro EXITOX parece ser una herramienta adecuada para conocer la mortalidad por intoxicación aguda en España (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);25(6): 467-471, dic. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118111</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mortalidad hospitalaria por intoxicación aguda en España (EXITOX 2012)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54899</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30047^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11471^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28096^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
