<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88371</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cost of childhood asthma in Spain: a cost evaluation model based on the prevalence</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Asthma is the most common chronic disease in childhood, reduces the quality of life of children and their families, and produces high social and health care costs. In Spain, the cost of managing paediatric asthma is unknown. Objective: To estimate the cost of managing paediatric asthma in Spain and to examine its variability depending on asthma severity. Patients and methods: The cost of asthma in children under 16 years in 2008 was estimated by building a costs assessment model including the factors that influence the cost of asthma in children: prevalence, distribution of disease severity, age, frequency of resources use depending on severity, and the cost of each resource. A sensitivity analysis was conducted to evaluate the underlying uncertainty depending on the variability of the estimators of resource use, the unit cost of each resource, and the prevalence. Results: According to the model, the total cost of paediatric asthma in Spain is around 532 million euros, with a range of 392 to 693 million euros. Direct costs (health care costs) represent 60% of the total costs, and indirect costs (carer time), 40%. The mean annual cost per child with asthma is 1,149 euros, ranging from 403 euros for the mildest category of the disease to 5,380 euros for the most severe. Conclusions: The cost of paediatric asthma in Spain is very high and depends on disease severity. Although the most important costs are for the health care system, indirect costs are not negligible (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz Vazquez, C. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Galdó, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonillo Perales, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Yarza, E. G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blasco Bravo, A. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lázaro y de Mercado, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El asma es la enfermedad crónica más frecuente en la infancia, disminuye la calidad de vida de los niños y sus familiares, y produce elevados costes sociales y sanitarios que en España no se conocen. Objetivo: Estimar el coste del manejo del asma en pediatría en España y estudiar su variabilidad en función de la gravedad. Pacientes y métodos: Se estimó el coste del manejo del asma en menores de 16 años en 2008, construyendo un modelo de evaluación de costes considerando los factores de los que depende: prevalencia, distribución de la gravedad, edad, frecuencia de utilización de recursos según la gravedad, y coste de cada recurso. Se realizó un análisis de sensibilidad para evaluar la incertidumbre subyacente dependiente de la variabilidad en los estimadores de utilización de recursos, del coste unitario de cada recurso y de la prevalencia. Resultados: El coste total del asma en pediatría en España es de unos 532 millones de euros, pudiendo oscilar entre 392 y 693 millones de euros. Los costes directos (costes sanitarios) representan el 60% del coste total y los costes indirectos (tiempo de cuidador) el 40%. El coste medio anual por niño asmático es 1.149 euros, y oscila entre 403 euros para la categoría de gravedad más leve y 5.380 euros para la más grave. Conclusiones: El coste del asma en pediatría en España es muy elevado y depende de la gravedad de la enfermedad. Los costes más importantes son los del sistema sanitario, pero los costes indirectos no son despreciables (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);74(3): 145-153, mar. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88371</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Coste del asma en pediatría en España: un modelo de evaluación de costes basado en la prevalencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
