<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98336</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Questionnaire for Obsessive Compulsive Disorder Diagnosis (Q-OCDD): description and psychometric properties</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper describes the Questionnaire for Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder Diagnosis (Q-OCDD)&#146; based on diagnostic criteria of DSM-IV. Decision criteria to classify a subject into one of three categories (OCD, Symptomatic, Asymptomatic) are described and two studies of some of its psychometric properties are shown in the non clinical and clinical group. Study 1 (non clinical group: 48 males and 190 females) determines: (a) agreement (k= 1) between two OCD inter-scorers, (b) convergent validity between Q-OCDD and Y-BOCS and MOCI. Convergent/divergent validity of Q-OCDD with Y-BOCS shows homogeneity in the Y-BOCS scores in the Asymptomatic and Symptomatic groups, there being a higher number of significant differences from the OCD group. Convergent validity of Q-OCDD with MOCI shows differences between the Asymptomatic and any one of the other two groups in all scales except in Slowness. Study 2 (clinical group: 11 males and 6 females) shows: (a) inter-scorer reliability (k= 0.87), (b) convergent/divergent validity between Q-OCDD (with or without OCD) and Y-BOCS. There are statistically significant differences in the means of obsessions, compulsions and total between subjects with or without OCD, (c) the following values: sensitivity 78.6%, specificity 100.0%, and diagnostic efficiency 82.35% (From diagnoses established by clinical interview and Q-OCDD)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rivas Moya, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gavino Lázaro, Aurora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Planas Domínugez, Amanda</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se describe el &#147;Cuestionario de diagnóstico del trastorno obsesivo-compulsivo&#148; (CUDIATOC) que operativiza los criterios diagnósticos del DSM-IV. Se describen las reglas de decisión que permiten asignar una persona a una categoría (tOC, Sintomático, Asintomático) y se presentan dos estudios de algunas de sus propiedades psicométricas en grupos no clínico y clínico, respectivamente. El estudio 1, en un grupo no clínico formado por 48 hombres y 190 mujeres, muestra la: (a) concordancia (k= 1) entre dos evaluadores, (b) validez convergente/ discriminante entre CUDIATOC y las escalas de Y-BOCS y MOCI. Con Y-BOCS hay homogeneidad en las puntuaciones entre los grupos Asintomático y Sintomático, existiendo diferencias significativas a partir del grupo TOC. Con MOCI hay diferencias entre el grupo Asintomático y los otros dos en todas las escalas excepto Lentitud. El estudio 2, en un grupo clínico formado por 11 hombres y 6 mujeres, muestra la: (a) fiabilidad (k= 0,87), (b) validez convergente/discriminante entre CUDIATOC e Y-BOCS, habiendo diferencias estadísticamente significativas en las medias de obsesiones, compulsiones y total entre personas con y sin TOC, (c) validez de criterio de CUDIATOC con una entrevista clínica, siendo sensibilidad 78,6%, especificidad 100,0% y eficiencia diagnóstica 82,35% (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;17(2): 231-255, mayo-ago. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98336</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuestionario de diagnóstico del trastorno obsesivo compulsivo (CUDIATOC): descripción y propiedades psicométricas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3223^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9956^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9955^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
