<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95447</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Percutaneous radiofrequency ablation with artificial ascites for hepatocellular carcinoma adjacent to the diaphragm</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Surgical resection is the first-line curative treatment of hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC). However most patients are unable to undergo surgical resection because of advanced tumoral stage, severe liver dysfunction or poor clinical status. Therefore, image-guided tumor ablation techniques have been introduced for the treatment of unresectable HCC. Among them, radiofrequency ablation (RFA) has been demonstrated to be an effective alternative curative therapy. However, local ablative therapy for tumors located close to structures such as the diaphragm or gastrointestinal tract is technically challenging because of the risk of collateral thermal damage to nearby structures or incomplete treatment of the HCC resulting from poor visibility on sonography. The introduction of artificial ascites can separate adjacent organs from the tumor and improve the sonic window. The aim of this study was to evaluate the feasibility, safety and efficacy of RFA with artificial ascites for HCC adjacent to the diaphragm (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castillo Grau, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Arranz, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Adán Merino, Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Gamarra, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olveira Martín, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora Sanz, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Robledo, Juan Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gea Rodriguez, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La cirugía constituye la primera línea de tratamiento curativo en el hepatocarcinoma (CHC). Sin embargo, una gran mayoría no se puede beneficiar de la misma debido al avanzado estadio tumoral, disfunción hepática severa o mala condición clínica. Por ello, se han introducido varias técnicas de ablación guiadas por imagen. Entre ellas, la radiofrecuencia percutánea (RFp) constituye una alternativa eficaz como tratamiento curativo. Sin embargo, la localización de la lesión cerca de estructuras como el diafragma o el tracto gastrointestinal, limita esta técnica debido al riego de daño térmico colateral y a un tratamiento incompleto por mala visualización. La introducción de ascitis artificial previa puede separar el CHC de los órganos adyacentes y mejorar la ventana acústica. El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar la viabilidad, seguridad y eficacia de la RFp con ascitis artificial para el tratamiento del CHC adyacente al diafragma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;33(10): 709-715, dic. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95447</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Creación de ascitis artificial para el tratamiento mediante radiofrecuencia percutánea del hepatocarcinoma cercano al diafragma</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31855^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10719^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8287^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
