<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94304</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">In-group bias in the classroom: The role of co-ethnic and other-ethnic peers and multiculturalism</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study among 322 native Dutch and 193 Turkish-Dutch early adolescents examined ethnic in-group bias in relation to two different aspects of the classroom context: the (aggregated) actual group evaluations of co-ethnic and other-ethnic classmates, and the multicultural classroom climate. Multilevel analyses showed that the in-group evaluation of co-ethnic peers was positively related to in-group bias, and that the out-group evaluation of co-ethnic peers had a negative effect. This latter effect was mediated by the children&#146;s own out-group attitude. The in- and out-group evaluations of other-ethnic peers had no unique effects on in-group bias. Multicultural classroom climate had a negative effect on the in-group bias of native Dutch children but not of Turkish-Dutch children. Results show that in-group bias is uniquely affected by in-group peers and by the normative school context (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Verkuyten, Maykel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Thijs, Jochem</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este estudio se analizó el sesgo endogrupal en 322 holandeses nativos y 193 turco-holandeses, todos preadolescentes, en relación con dos aspectos diferentes del contexto en el aula: las evaluaciones reales (totales) hacia compañeros co-étnicos y de otro grupo étnico, y el clima multicultural en el aula. Los análisis multinivel mostraron que las evaluaciones endogrupales de los iguales co-étnicos estaban relacionadas positivamente con el sesgo endogrupal y que las evaluaciones exogrupales de los iguales co-étnicos tenían un efecto negativo. Este último efecto estuvo mediado por la actitud de los propios niños hacia el exogrupo. Las evaluaciones sobre el endogrupo y el exogrupo de los compañeros del otro grupo étnico no tuvieron efectos únicos sobre el sesgo endogrupal. El clima multicultural tuvo un efecto negativo sobre el sesgo endogrupal en el grupo de holandeses nativos pero no en los turco-holandeses. Los resultados muestran que el sesgo endogrupal estuvo afectado únicamente por los iguales del endogrupo y por el contexto normativo escolar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;27(3): 662-669, oct.-dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94304</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El sesgo endogrupal en el aula: el papel de los compañeros de la misma etnia, de otra etnia y el multiculturalismo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23904^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6276</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32786</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11724</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23904^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23904^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24872</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13304^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23904^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38413^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23896^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
