<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043918</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nephrolithiasis and topiramate</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Topiramate (TPM) is a new antiepileptic drug whose multiple mechanisms of action justify both itsbroad therapeutic spectrum and its increasingly widespread use in childhood epilepsy. TPM acts as a carbonic anhydraseinhibitor and, although this does not affect its effectiveness as an antiepileptic, it does account for certain side effects such asnephrolithiasis. The frequency of nephrolithiasis secondary to TPM in childhood is unknown and we have only found reportsof five cases in children. Case reports. We describe two cases of medication-resistant infantile epilepsy &#150; a 3-year-old femalewith Dravet&#146;s syndrome and a male aged 4.5 years with Lennox-Gastaut syndrome. In both cases the decision was made tointroduce TPM as add-on therapy after a prolonged therapeutic programme; a high degree of effectiveness was achieved inboth patients. Nevertheless, the two patients developed nephrolithiasis secondary to TPM, which in the second case wasrelated to the simultaneous treatment with adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH), while no known favouring factor was foundin the first patient. Conclusions. We outline the physiopathogenic mechanism explaining nephrolithiasis secondary to TPM,the risk factors involved and the therapeutic and preventive options available in dealing with this side effect, which occurs ina low percentage of cases but which usually means stopping administration of this therapy. We therefore believe it necessaryto analyse the risk factors for nephrolithiasis before prescribing the drug and we suggest that generalised preventivemeasures should be implemented, especially in children who are carriers of encephalopathies or conditions that reduce mobility</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Domingo-Jiménez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alarcón-Martínez, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escudero-Rodríguez, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Costa, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cao-Avellaneda, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas-Fernández, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puche-Mira, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El topiramato (TPM) es un nuevo antiepilépticocuyo mecanismo de acción múltiple justifica tanto su amplioespectro terapéutico como su empleo cada vez mayor en la epilepsiainfantil. Aunque no influye en su eficacia antiepiléptica, elTPM inhibe la anhidrasa carbónica, efecto que es el responsablede reacciones adversas como la nefrolitiasis. La frecuencia de lanefrolitiasis secundaria al TPM en la infancia es desconocida yúnicamente hemos encontrado cinco casos comunicados en niños.Casos clínicos. Se presentan dos casos de epilepsia infantil refractariaal tratamiento farmacológico, una niña de 3 años con síndromede Dravet y un niño de 4,5 años con síndrome de Lennox-Gastaut,en los que después de un prolongado programa terapéutico sedecide introducir TPM en terapia añadida, obteniendo en ambospacientes un elevado grado de eficacia. No obstante, los dos desarrollannefrolitiasis secundaria al TPM, que en el segundo casorelacionamos con el tratamiento simultáneo con hormona corticotropa(ACTH) no existiendo un factor favorecedor conocido en elprimero. Conclusiones. Se hace una exposición del mecanismo fisiopatogénicode la nefrolitiasis secundaria al TPM, de los factoresde riesgo implicados y de las opciones terapéuticas y preventivasde este efecto adverso, que representa un porcentaje muy bajo, peroque obliga usualmente a prescindir de esta alternativa terapéutica,por lo que creemos que se deben analizar los factores de riesgode nefrolitiasis antes de prescribir este fármaco y que se debengeneralizar las medidas preventivas, especialmente en los niñosportadores de encefalopatías o de patologías que reduzcan la movilidad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;42(2): 91-94, ene. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043918</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nefrolitiasis y topiramato</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5768^s22003</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24371^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24371^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5768^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5768^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
