<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115633</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation by focus groups on women's expectations and perceptions during the birth process</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: Delivery care giving is undergoing excessive interventionism today, not supported by scientific evidence, neglecting organisational aspects and individualisation. This study analyses the perception of mothers during their delivery, postpartum and breastfeeding periods in the Galician Health Service, in order to inform and help to improve this service. Material and methods: A total of 14 focus group meetings were held (one in each Galician public hospital), consisting of women who, in 2008, delivered by vaginal delivery or those who were not scheduled for a caesarean section. Results: The process of birth analysis can identify a sequence of important elements both positive and negative, for mothers, and may lead to suggestions for improvement. Their experiences and opinions, especially in aspects such as participation in decision-making, mechanisation of labour and lactation, may help to conduct an assessment of the maternity ward operating. When investigating expectations and demands from users, information from perceived quality is received, and also mothers&#146; experience is shared. Conclusions: Mothers call for humanity, empathy, information and participation. Facing the implementation of these elements, the key processes for working harder are the dilation stage and hospital staying (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Sanisidro, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varela-Mallou, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferreiro-Losada, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Romero, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rial-Boubeta, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Clavería-Fontán, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Actualmente el proceso de atención al parto es objeto de un excesivo intervencionismo, no siempre avalado por la evidencia científica, y descuidándose aspectos organizativos y de humanización. Pretendemos analizar la percepción y expectativas de las madres en la atención a su parto, puerperio y lactancia en los hospitales públicos del Servicio Gallego de Salud, para informar y facilitar la mejora de de este servicio en ellos. Material y métodos. Se realizaron 14 grupos focales (uno por cada hospital público de Galicia), compuestos de mujeres que dieron a luz en el año 2008 mediante parto vaginal o cesárea no programada. Resultados. Se analiza el proceso del parto, identificando secuencialmente los elementos importantes para las madres, positivos y negativos, y las propuestas de mejora. Sus vivencias y opiniones, especialmente en aspectos como su participación en la toma de decisiones, la tecnificación del parto y la lactancia han permitido llevar a cabo una evaluación del funcionamiento del área de maternidad. Al investigar las expectativas y demandas de las usuarias se ha obtenido información de la calidad percibida, y se ha respondido a la necesidad de las madres de compartir su experiencia de parto. Conclusiones. Las madres demandan un trato más humano, empatía, más información y participación. Los procesos clave en los que se debe realizar un mayor esfuerzo en la aplicación de estos elementos son la dilatación y la estancia en la planta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;28(5): 291-299, sept.-oct. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115633</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación mediante grupos focales de las expectativas y percepciones de las mujeres durante el proceso del parto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30727^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30727^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38861^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38861^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30727^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22239^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
