<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131631</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The influence of differences between father and mother on adolescent adjustment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper analyzes how the differences between father and mother in affection, promotion of autonomy, disclosure, solicitation and knowledge influence on substance use (tobacco, alcohol and cannabis) and psychological well-being (health-related quality of life and life satisfaction).The sample was composed of 10170 boys and girls aged 13 to 18 years from two-parent families who participated in 2006 edition of Health Behaviourin School-aged Children (HBSC) study. Results indicated that adolescents whose both parents had high values for the different family dimensions used less substance and scored higher in psychological well-being. In contrast, the adjustment of adolescents whose both parents had low values for the different family dimensions was worse. Specifically, the most important dimension for substance use was parental knowledge and for psychological well-being was parental affection; adolescent disclosure was only relevant for alcohol use and quality of life, and parental promotion of autonomy for quality of life (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Iglesias, Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo se centra en analizar cómo influyen en el consumo de sustancias (tabaco, alcohol y cannabis) y el bienestar psicológico adolescente (calidad de vida relacionada con la salud y satisfacción vital) las diferencias entre el padre y la madre en afecto, promoción de la autonomía, revelación, interés y conocimiento. La muestra estuvo compuesta por 10170 chicos y chicas españoles de 13 a 18 años de familias biparentales que participaron en la edición 2006 del estudio Health Behaviour in School-aged Children (HBSC). Los resultados mostraron que los adolescentes que indicaron que su padre y madre coincidían en presentar altos niveles en las dimensiones familiares analizadas consumieron menos sustancias y tuvieron mejor bienestar psicológico. Por el contrario, el ajuste de los adolescentes cuyos progenitores (padre y madre) tenían bajos niveles en esas dimensiones familiares fue peor. Concretamente, la dimensión más importante para el consumo de sustancias fue el conocimiento parental y para el bienestar psicológico lo fue el afecto parental; la revelación adolescente solo fue relevante para el consumo de alcohol y la calidad de vida, mientras que la promoción parental de la autonomía lo fue para la calidad de vida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;31(1): 367-377, ene. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131631</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La influencia de las diferencias entre el padre y la madre sobre el ajuste adolescente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10479^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
