<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140725</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Determinants and economic cost of patient absenteeism in outpatient departments of the Costa del Sol Health Agency</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. To identify factors related to the people, the process and the context that determine patient compliance with their appointments in the ambulatory outpatient services in the Costa del Sol Health Care Agency; and to obtain the profile of patients who fail to keep their appointments, the reasons for this failure and an estimation of its economic cost. Methods. Observational multicenter case-control study, through a survey carried out on patients with an appointment in the ambulatory outpatient services during 2013 and 2014, and analysis of the cost per appointment. Results. In total, 882 patients participated in the study (294 cases and 588 controls). The main reasons for missing an appointment were forgetting about it (29, 6%; n=87), and failure in communication (16%; n=47). A shorter time period before the appointment and older age were significantly associated with fewer absences, as well as the fact of having attended more consultations in the past year. The economic cost was more than 3 million euros for a non-attendance rate of 13.8%. Conclusions. Young patients who usually do not visit outpatient clinics are at greatest risk of absence from scheduled appointments in our health area. The main reasons for absenteeism are preventable and interventions such as improved communication procedures or appointment reminder systems could be beneficial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rivas Ruiz, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jabalera Mesa, ML</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Asencio, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. Identificar los factores de la persona, el proceso y el contexto que influyen en el cumplimiento de las citas de consultas externas en la Agencia Sanitaria Costa del Sol, describiendo el perfil del paciente que no acude a su cita, los motivos del absentismo y realizando una estimación del coste económico. Método. Estudio observacional, multicéntrico de casos y controles, mediante encuesta a pacientes citados en consultas ambulatorias durante 2013 y 2014 y análisis de costes por consultas. Resultados. Participaron en el estudio 882 pacientes (294 casos y 588 controles). El olvido (29,6%; n=87) y el fallo en la comunicación (16%; n=47), fueron los principales motivos manifestados por los pacientes absentistas. Una menor demora en la cita y la edad avanzada se asociaban significativamente con menos ausencias, al igual que haber frecuentado más las consultas en el último año. El coste económico fue superior a 3 millones de euros para una tasa de inasistencia del 13,8%. Conclusiones. Los pacientes jóvenes que no frecuentan habitualmente las consultas constituyen el grupo de mayor riesgo de ausencia a las citas programadas en nuestra área sanitaria. Los principales motivos del absentismo son evitables y podrían beneficiarse de intervenciones como la mejora de los procedimientos de comunicación o sistemas de recordatorio de citas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;38(2): 235-245, mayo-ago. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140725</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores determinantes y coste económico del absentismo de pacientes en consultas externas de la Agencia Sanitaria Costa del Sol</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33118^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29345^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1077</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10554^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33118^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10546^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d555^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
