<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108391</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Peritoneal dialysis in diabetic patients: indications, advantages and possible complications</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Peritoneal dialysis arises as an alternative to hemodialysis. It uses the patient&#146;s own peritoneum as a dialytic membrane and its practice is simple. After creating permanent access to the abdominal cavity, fixed solutions with suitable volume and appropriate length of time are instilled. There are different perfusion regimens, being the continuous the most popular. Most patients can use the technique because contraindications are infrequent. Vascular access is not needed, and greater hemodynamic stability than hemodialysis is provided. On the other hand, glucose overload may deteriorate glycemic control, although intraperitoneal insuline may diminish this effect. In the diabetic patient it is advisable promptly start substitute therapy. Long term studies show patient survival of at least that of haemodialysis patients. However, the survival of the technique is usually shorter, showing no differences until after 5 years of treatment. In summary, in diabetic patients, peritoneal dialysis lead to similar or even better survival than hemodialysis, specially in the first years of treatment(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Ramón, R. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguel Carrasco, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La diálisis peritoneal surge como una alternativa a la hemodiálisis. Utiliza el propio peritoneo como membrana dialítica y su práctica es sencilla. Tras realizar un acceso permanente a la cavidad abdominal, se instilan las soluciones prefijadas con un volumen y una permanencia adecuados. Existen diferentes procedimientos, siendo los regímenes continuos los más empleados. La mayoría de pacientes pueden realizar la técnica, ya que las contraindicaciones son escasas. No precisa de acceso vascular y proporciona mayor estabilidad hemodinámica que la hemodiálisis. Por otro lado, la sobrecarga de glucosa puede empeorar el control glucémico, aunque la administración intraperitoneal de insulina parece disminuir este efecto. En el paciente diabético es aconsejable un inicio precoz de la terapia sustitutiva. En estudios a largo plazo, la supervivencia del paciente es como mínimo superponible a la de los pacientes en hemodiálisis. Sin embargo, la supervivencia de la técnica en general es menor, si bien no suelen existir diferencias hasta pasados 5 años. En resumen, en los pacientes diabéticos la diálisis peritoneal ofrece igual o mejor supervivencia que la hemodiálisis, sobre todo en los años iniciales del tratamiento(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;26(4): 242-247, jul.-ago. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108391</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diálisis peritoneal en pacientes diabéticos: indicaciones, ventajas y posibles complicaciones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
