<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74652</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment for fibrous dysplasia when associated with hemophilia C: A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Fibrous Dysplasia is a benign bone disease that changesnormal bone tissue for a proliferation of connective fibrous tissue.It is thought that an alteration of the Gs&amp;#945; gene is the main causeof the disease.Hemophilia C is a rare inherited blood disease leading to abnormalhemorrhages in affected patients. They have a factor XI deficiency.It is the least frequent of all hemophilias. It is a recessive autosomaldisease, affecting both men and women.A 13 year-old patient developed fibrous dysplasia in right uppermaxilla. The patient started with pain on chewing hard food. Shehad vestibular swelling and reddening of the right side of the palate.She had a discrete factor XI deficiency (heterozygotic). She neededspecial preparation before the lesion could be removed because ofher deficiency.It has been discovered that the mutation of gene Gs&amp;#945; (GNAS1) isthe reason for fibrous dysplasia. This gene is in chromosome 20q.The cause of hemophilia C is a factor XI deficiency due to a mutationin the FXI gene in chromosome 4. Perhaps these two rare diseasesare related, because both are unusual diseases and both are in thesame patient(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rosario Regalado, R. del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salazar Fernández, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Creo Martínez, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borrego Luque, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín Lapeira, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La displasia fibrosa es una enfermedad ósea benigna que cambiael tejido óseo normal por una proliferación de tejido conectivo. Se piensaque la alteración del gen Gs&amp;#945; es la principal razón de la enfermedad.La hemofilia C es una enfermedad sanguínea, hereditaria rara, que provocahemorragias en pacientes afectos. Es autonómica recesiva, por lo quehombres y mujeres pueden estar afectos.Paciente de 13 años que desarrolla una displasia fibrosa en maxilar superiorderecho que empieza con dolor durante la masticación de alimentosduros. Presenta abombamiento de vestíbulo y enrojecimiento de paladarderecho.Presenta un déficit discreto de factor XI (heterocigoto). Por ello, necesitauna preparación especial antes de extirpar la lesión debido a su déficit.Se ha descubierto que la razón de la displasia fibrosa es la mutación delgen Gs&amp;#945; (GNAS1) que está en el cromosoma 20q.La causa de la hemofilia C es el déficit del factor XI debido a una mutacióndel gen FXI en el cromosoma 4. Quizás estas dos raras enfermedades tenganuna relación, porque ambas se presentan en el mismo paciente(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;29(6): 375-380, nov.-dic. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74652</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de la displasia fibrosa asociada a hemofilia C: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20180^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4220^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8605^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5273^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5493^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
