<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148014</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New evaluating methods of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: adaptation for damage and incapacity evaluation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease is the most common chronic respiratory disease and the one that most often can lead to disability. Spirometry is the traditional way to assess the severity of the disease. But its clinical presentation is not homogeneous and it is known that there is no good correlation between spirometry results and the clinical situation of the patient. In recent years, evaluating methods for the disease have been developed by combining certain parameters, i.e. making a multidimensional assessment. This way, the prognosis and severity of the disease is much better predicted. Physicians like us, who do assessment of disability, must know and manage these tools to make our accurate assessments. Two of these tools are given, the derivative of the GOLD Initiative and the one developed in Spain, the GesEPOC. This application and its use is further explained in the evaluation of the disability (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Lorenzo, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maneiro Higuera, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica es la patología crónica respiratoria más frecuente y que con más frecuencia puede producir incapacidad. La manera tradicional de evaluar la gravedad de la enfermedad es mediante la espirometría. Pero la presentación clínica de la enfermedad no es homogénea y se conoce que no hay una buena correlación entre los resultados de la espirometría y la situación clínica real del enfermo. En los últimos años se han desarrollado procedimientos para evaluar la enfermedad combinando varios parámetros, o sea haciendo una evaluación multidimensional. Esto consigue predecir mucho mejor el pronóstico y la gravedad de la patología. Los médicos que hacemos evaluación de la incapacidad debemos conocer y manejar estas herramientas para hacer nuestras valoraciones más precisas. Se presentan dos de estas herramientas la derivada de la Iniciativa GOLD y la desarrollada en España, la GesEPOC. Se explica su aplicación y su uso en la evaluación de la incapacidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;61(240): 367-377, jul.-sept. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148014</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevos métodos de valoración de la enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica, su adecuación a la evaluación del menoscabo y la incapacidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55021^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
