<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049838</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish scientific publications on drug dependence in the European Union context: 1976-2000</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to analyse scientific literature on drug dependence (DD). Method: Spanish articles about DD published in 1976-2000 as indexed by PsycINFO were analysed, and compared with the rest of European Union (EU) countries in 2000. Results and Discussion: PsycINFO is useful compare countries because it includes the name of institution and country. The number of publications on DD from EU and Spain increased between 1976 and 2000. The Spanish scientific production onDD has increased more than that of the EU. 501 references of Spain and 4,324 of the other 14 EU countries were collected. From 1990, the Spanish production stands for about 10% of that of the EU. EU articles were published in 13 languages and those from spain in three: spanish, english and French. Apart from English, Spanish was the only language with an increase in use. EU works were published in 521 journals and those from Spain in 100; in both cases, they tended to concentrate in journals specialised in DD and psychiatry. Foreing journals that published more articles by Spanish authors have a high impact factor. In 1996-2000, the collaboration index of authors was 3.24 in the EU and 3.49 in Spain. The Autonomous Communities with more production were Catalonia, Madrid, Galicia, and Andalucia. The University was the most represented institution, followed by hospitals and alcohol and drug addiction treatment centres</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Carbonell, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bellés, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guardiola, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beranuy, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar la producción científica sobre dependencia de drogas (DD). Método. Se analizaron los artículos españoles sobre DD publicados en 1976-2000 indizados en PsycINFO y se comparó con la producción de los otros países miembros de a Unión Europea (UE) en 2000. Resultados y discusión: PsycINFO es útil para compara países porque incluye el nombre de la institución y el país. El número de publicaciones de la UE y de España en DD aumentó entre 1976 y 2000. La producción científica española en DD ha crecido más que la de la UE. Se recuperaron 501 referencias de España y 4.324 de los otros países de la UE. A partir de 1990, la producción española representa alrededor del 10% de la de la UE. Los artículos de la UE se publicaron en 13 idiomas y los de España en 3: castellano, inglés y francés. Además del inglés, el castellano fue el único idioma cuyo uso creció. Los trabajos de la UE se publicaron en 521 revistas y los de España en 100; en ambos casos, tendieron a concentrarse en revistas específicas sobre DD y psiquiatría. Las revistas extranjeras que publicaron más artículos de autores españoles tienen un factor de impacto elevado. En 1996-2000, el índice de colaboración de autores fue 3,24 en la UE y 3,49 en España. Las comunidades autónomas más productivas fueron Cataluña,Madrid, Galicia y Andalucía. La Universidad fue la institución más representada, seguida de los hospitales y los centros de tratamiento de adicción a alcohol y drogas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);18(2): 119-134, abr. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049838</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La producción científica española sobre dependencia de drogas en el contexto de la Unión Europea: 1976-2000</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5160^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33619^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28904^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
