<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76262</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treating severe acute anemia due to vaginal bleeding in the Jehova&#146;s Witness: a report of 2 cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">For reasons of religious belief, Jehova&#146;s Witnesses donot accept blood transfusions or the infusion of bloodproducts. In situations in which severe, life-threateninganemia develops, patient refusal to receive a transfusioncan create serious ethical and legal problems. Theprinciple of patient autonomy, which implies the freedomto accept or reject treatment, comes into conflict with thephysician&#146;s obligation to safeguard the patient&#146;s life usingall means possible. We report 2 cases of severe anemia inJehova&#146;s Witnesses. One was due to menorrhagia and theother to postpartum bleeding. The physician should beaware of alternatives to infusion of blood products andknow how to cope with an unexpected critical event inthese patients. The measures we took were effective in ourpatients. In the case of menorrhagia, hormone treatmentis effective when the woman wishes to preserve the abilityto conceive and avoid surgery (endometrial ablation andhysterectomy). In postpartum bleeding refractory toconservative treatment, selective embolization of bleedingvessels may make it unnecessary to resort to moreaggressive treatment, such as obstetric hysterectomy(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gredilla, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Ferrer, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Serrano, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canser, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gilsanz, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los Testigos de Jehová (TJ) no aceptan la transfusiónsanguínea ni la administración de derivados hemáticosdebido a sus creencias religiosas. En situaciones de anemiaextrema, con riesgo vital para el paciente, si ésterechaza la transfusión puede producirse un grave conflictoético y legal, enfrentándose el principio de autonomíadel paciente, que implica la libertad para rechazaro aceptar un tratamiento médico, y el deber delmédico de salvaguardar la vida del paciente utilizandotodos los medios a su alcance. Presentamos dos casos deanemia grave, uno por menorragia y otro por hemorragiapuerperal, en mujeres TJ. Debemos conocer los tratamientosalternativos a la transfusión de hemoderivados(en nuestras dos pacientes fueron eficaces), y sabercómo actuar ante una situación crítica inesperada eneste tipo de pacientes. En la menorragia, el tratamientohormonal es efectivo cuando la mujer quiere preservarla fertilidad y evitar la cirugía (ablación endometrial ehisterectomía); en la hemorragia postparto refractariaal tratamiento conservador, la embolización selectiva delos vasos sangrantes puede evitar la necesidad de actitudesterapéuticas más agresivas como la histerectomíaobstétrica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;56(10): 632-634, dic. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76262</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de anemia aguda grave por hemorragia vaginal en la testigo de Jehová: a propósito de dos casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3496^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8764^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8764^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1831^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8764^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1831^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3496^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7202^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37712</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1831^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
