<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143835</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adherence to Mediterranean diet and bone health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Several studies have concluded that incidences of osteoporosis and osteoporosis-related fractures vary across the European Union, the lowest incidence being reported in the Mediterranean area. The beneficial effect is mainly attributed to a specific eating pattern. The Mediterranean diet contain a complex array of naturally occurring bioactive molecules with antioxidant, anti-inflammatory and alkalinising properties that may contribute to the bone-sparing effect of the Mediterranean diet. Objective: The purpose of this review is to examine the evidence to date on the effects of Mediterranean diet on bone health. Methods: The search for articles came from extensive research in the following databases: PubMed, Scopus and Web of Science. We used the search terms «Mediterranean diet», «adherence», «fruit and vegetable», «olive oil», «fish», «legume», «cereal», «alcohol», «bone», «osteoporosis», «fracture», and combinations, such as «Mediterranean diet and bone» or «Mediterranean diet and fracture». Results: A limited number of studies have examined the relationship between Mediterranean Diet and bone health, and they have reported conflicting results. On the one hand, adherence to a traditional MeDi has been associated with higher bone mineral density and lower fracture risk. The results of these studies could be attributed to the combined beneficial effects of individual components of the Mediterranean diet. On the contrary, several studies failed to show any association between adherence to the MeDi and indices of bone mass. Conclusions: Further large-scale studies are required to clarify the effect of Mediterranean diet on bone health, in order to establish the role of this diet in the prevention of osteoporosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rivas Velasco, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Pérez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Se han encontrado diferencias en los valores de incidencia de osteoporosis y fracturas relacionadas entre los países de la Unión Europea, siendo menor en los países de la zona mediterránea. Este hecho se atribuye principalmente a un patrón de alimentación específica común. La dieta mediterránea contiene un complejo conjunto de componentes bioactivos con propiedades antioxidantes, anti-inflamatorias y alcalinizantes que pueden contribuir al efecto de esta dieta en la salud ósea. Objetivo: El propósito de esta revisión es examinar la evidencia hasta la fecha sobre los efectos de la dieta mediterránea sobre la salud ósea. Métodos: Se realizó una búsqueda en la literatura científica utilizando las siguientes base de datos: PubMed, Scopus and Web of Science. Utilizamos los términos de búsqueda «Dieta Mediterránea», «adhesión», «frutas y verduras», «aceite de oliva», «pescado», «legumbres», «cereal», «alcohol», «hueso», «osteoporosis», «fractura», y combinaciones, como «Dieta Mediterránea y el hueso» o «Dieta mediterránea y fracturas». Resultados: Existe un número limitado de estudios que analicen la relación entre el seguimiento de la Dieta Mediterránea y la salud ósea, mostrando resultados contradictorios. Diversos trabajos han mostrado que la adherencia a una dieta mediterránea tradicional se asociado con una mayor densidad mineral ósea y un menor riesgo de fractura en población adulta. Los resultados de estos estudios podrían atribuirse a un efecto beneficioso combinado de los componentes individuales de la dieta mediterránea. Por el contrario, en otros trabajos no se ha encontrado ninguna asociación entre la adherencia a la dieta mediterránea y los índices de masa ósea. Conclusiones: Se requieren más estudios a gran escala para aclarar el efecto de la dieta mediterránea sobre la salud ósea, con el fin de establecer el papel de la dieta en la prevención de la osteoporosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;29(5): 989-996, mayo 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143835</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adherencia a la dieta mediterránea y salud ósea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37653^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1876^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1876^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54019^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
