<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59825</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Response to stopping azathioprine in Crohn &amp; apos; s patients on combined treatment with infliximab</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The use of immunomodulatory agents has changed the management of inflammatory bowel disease. Immunosuppressive drugs (mainly thiopurines) and biological treatments (mainly monoclonal antibodies against TNF&amp;#945;) are currently most frequently and earlier used. The recent report of new cases of the rare and almost always fatal hepatosplenic T-cell lymphoma in young patients on combined therapy with azathioprine/6-mercaptopurine and infliximab suggests that the optimal strategies for reducing increased risk of side-effects need to be urgently assessed. Patients and method: We report the effects of stopping immunosupressants in four Crohn&#146;s disease patients previously treated with azathioprine and infliximab for 6&#150;12 months as combined therapy. The appearance of infusion reactions due to immunogenicity and the loss of efficacy of infliximab are evaluated. Results: No adverse events attributable to immunosuppression cessation or changes in infliximab efficacy have been noted during a 6-month evaluation period. Conclusions: Stopping immunosuppressant therapy in Crohn&#146;s patients with a previous good response to combination therapy (azathioprine and infliximab) does not result in an increased risk of adverse events or loss of infliximab efficacy. Our results must be confirmed in larger and longer studies. Until the pathogenic role of this combined therapy in the incidence of hepatosplenic T-cell lymphoma is clearly defined, we consider that monotherapy with infliximab after a period on combined treatment is a safe and effective strategy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín De Carpi, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varea, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: el uso de fármacos inmunomoduladores en la enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal ha cambiado su manejo. Los tratamientos inmunosupresores (fundamentalmente tiopurinas) y biológicos (especialmente los anticuerpos monoclonales contra el factor de necrosis tumoral alfa) son utilizados cada vez con más frecuencia y más precozmente. La descripción de nuevos casos de linfoma hepatoesplénico de células T en pacientes jóvenes tratados con combinación de azatioprina/6-mercaptopurina e infliximab de manera prolongada hace necesaria la revisión de las actuales estrategias para evitar los posibles efectos secundarios de la inmunosupresión intensiva. Pacientes y método: presentamos los efectos de suspender la inmunosupresión en 4 pacientes afectos de enfermedad de Crohn tras un periodo de 6&#150;12 meses en tratamiento combinado con azatioprina e infliximab. Se valora la aparición de reacciones adversas plausiblemente inmunogénicas y la pérdida de eficacia del infliximab tras suspender la azatioprina. Resultados: no se han producido cambios en la eficacia de infliximab en monoterapia ni se han objetivado reacciones de hipersensibilidad en los 6 meses siguientes a la suspensión. Conclusiones: la retirada del tratamiento inmunosupresor en pacientes afectos de Enfermedad de Crohn con buena respuesta previa al tratamiento combinado con azatioprina e infliximab no conlleva un mayor riesgo de reacciones de hipersensibilidad ni se acompaña de pérdida de la eficacia del infliximab. Por el tamaño reducido de nuestra muestra y el seguimiento limitado, los resultados deberán confirmarse en estudios más amplios y prolongados. Hasta que se defina exactamente el efecto patogénico de dicha combinación en la aparición de neoplasias, el paso a monoterapia con infliximab es una maniobra segura y eficaz (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);70(3): 271-277, mar. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59825</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Respuesta a la suspensión de azatioprina en pacientes con enfermedad de Crohn en terapia combinada con infliximab</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1394^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d906^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7344^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4419</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
