<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137540</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-5151</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Phenol alcohol technique for treating ingrown toenails. Healing throught time and complications for a sample of over 65</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The phenol alcohol chemical matricectomy is a surgical technique used for the definitive treatment of ingrown toenail. Aims. The objectives of the study were: 1.- Quantify the average healing time of patients in the sample subjected to matricectomy the nail art of phenol alcohol and 2. - Calculate the frequency of major complications of this procedure in our sample. Methods. To a sample of 44 patients for undergoing ingrown toenail from January 1, 2007 to January 1, 2012, and calculated the average healing time. The next step was to hold a draw with the complications that appeared between 0-60 days, and between 61-365 days, and calculated the frequency of occurrence of each of them in our sample. Results. - It was found that the average healing time was days. The complications were rare, being seroma the major complication (6,81%). Highlighting the low rate of recurrence rate was obtained: 0% of total recurrence and of 4.54% partial recurrence. Conclusions. - Is a technique widely studied and controversial, it has undergone many changes. The performance of the technique as we described in our study provides very satisfactory results, with a low rate of complications and recurrences. Therefore we can conclude that it is a valid and effective for the treatment of ingrown toenail (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lasanta Lacalzada, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyes Martín, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La matricectomía química por fenol alcohol es una técnica quirúrgica usada para el tratamiento definitivo de la uña encarnada. Objetivos. Los objetivos del estudio fueron: 1.- Cuantificar el tiempo medio de curación de los pacientes de la muestra sometidos a una matricectomía parcial de la uña por técnica fenol alcohol y 2.- Calcular la frecuencia de aparición de las principales complicaciones de éste procedimiento en nuestra muestra. Métodos. Se seleccionó una muestra de 44 pacientes intervenidos de uña encarnada durante el período de tiempo comprendido entre el 1 de enero del 2007 y el 1 de enero del 2012, y se calculó el tiempo medio de curación. El siguiente paso fue realizar unas tablas con las complicaciones que aparecieron entre los 0-60 días, y entre los 61-365 días, y se calculó la frecuencia de aparición de cada una de ellas en nuestra muestra. Resultados. Se obtuvo que el tiempo medio de curación fue de 30,4 días. Las complicaciones fueron escasas, siendo el seroma una de las principales complicaciones (6,81%). Destacar el bajo índice de recidivas que se obtuvo: 0% recidiva total y 4,54% de recidiva parcial. Conclusiones. Es una técnica muy estudiada y controvertida, que ha sufrido numerosas variaciones. La realización de la técnica tal y como la describimos en nuestro estudio nos proporciona unos resultados muy satisfactorios, con un bajo índice de complicaciones y recidivas. Por ello podemos concluir que es una técnica válida y eficaz para el tratamiento de la uña encarnada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. int. cienc. podol. (Internet);9(2): 75-84, 2015. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137540</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Técnica fenol alcohol para el tratamiento de uñas encarnadas. Tiempo medio de curación y complicaciones para una muestra de mayores de 65 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9454^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33403^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d904^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d431^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
