<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111712</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Crossed cerebellar diaschisis. Study of a patient by magnetic resonance imaging and positron emission tomography</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Crossed cerebellar diaschisis is a functional deficit in an area that is remote from that of a supratentorial brain lesion, although the two are anatomically and functionally connected. Deactivation of the contralateral cerebellar hemisphere occurs and is believed to be caused by a transneuronal metabolic depression of the cortico-ponto-cerebellar pathway. A reduction in the blood flow in the brain takes place and this gives rise to a diminished oxygenation of the cerebellar hemisphere. This finding can be evaluated by different functional imaging methods.  Case report. A 32-year-old female, without any relevant events in her personal history, presented an extensive supratentorial ischaemic lesion on the right-hand side. An MR angiography scan was performed, in which the homolateral middle cerebral artery and internal carotid artery were not identified. With no specific causation and suspecting a probable  case of vasculitis (two days after the first ischaemic episode, the patient suffered another one in the left-hand occipital area, although this time it was smaller and clinically asymptomatic), a positron emission tomography/computerised tomography (PET/CT) scan was performed. The results revealed hypoenhancement of the radiotracer in the contralateral cerebellar hemisphere, which was interpreted as hypometabolism.  Conclusions. Determined by a possible prognostic value in the presence of crossed cerebellar diaschisis in supratentorial vascular episodes, with respect to the final clinical outcome of the patients, it is interesting to take this possibility into account when evaluating patients with an acute cerebrovascular accident, either by means of PET/CT, MR imaging (perfusion) or CT (perfusion) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Turjanski, Alexis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meli, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blumenkrantz, Yamila</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soria, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salas, Ezequiel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La diasquisis cerebelosa cruzada es una deficiencia funcional en un área remota a la de una lesión cerebral supratentorial, pero anatómica y funcionalmente conectadas. Se produce una desactivación del hemisferio cerebeloso contralateral, y se considera que la causa una depresión metabólica transneuronal de la vía corticopontocerebelosa. Existe una reducción del flujo sanguíneo cerebral y, por consiguiente, de la oxigenación del hemisferio cerebeloso. Este hallazgo puede evaluarse a través de diferentes métodos de imágenes funcionales. Caso clínico. Mujer de 32 años, sin antecedentes personales relevantes, que presentó una extensa lesión isquémica supratentorial derecha. Se estudió mediante angiorresonancia, en la que no se identificaron la arteria cerebral media y la arteria carótida interna homolaterales. Sin etiología específica, pensando en una probable vasculitis (dos días después del inicial, la paciente sufrió otro episodio isquémico en el área occipital izquierda, de menor tamaño y clínicamente asintomático),  se realizó una tomografía por emisión de positrones/tomografía computarizada (PET/TC) y se observó hipocaptación del radiotrazador del hemisferio cerebeloso contralateral, interpretado como hipometabolismo. Conclusión. En función de un posible valor pronóstico en la presencia de diasquisis cerebelosa cruzada en episodios vasculares supratentoriales, con respecto al resultado clínico final de los pacientes, es interesante tener presente esta posibilidad en la evaluación de pacientes con accidente cerebrovascular agudo, ya sea mediante PET/TC, resonancia magnética (perfusión) o TC (perfusión) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;56(8): 425-428, abr. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111712</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diasquisis cerebelosa cruzada. Estudio de una paciente con resonancia magnética y tomografía por emisión de positrones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2563^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34228^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1043^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38793^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
