<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105016</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Increased bone mineral density in patients with tertiary hyperparathyroidism after total parathyroidectomy and autotransplantation of the parathyroid gland</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction Changes in bone metabolism and bone mineral density are observed in renal transplant patients with tertiary hyperparathyroidism. The objective of this work was to analyse the increase in bone mineral density, as well the laboratory results, after total parathyroidectomy and autotransplantation in renal transplant patients with tertiary hyperparathyroidism. Material and methods A retrospective study was conducted in which the bone mineral density values at femoral and lumbar level were analysed, together with the serum levels of calcium, phosphorous, parathyroid hormone (PTH), and alkaline phosphatase in 13 renal transplant patients with tertiary hyperparathyroidism before and after total parathyroidectomy and autotransplantation of the parathyroid glands. Results Parathyroidectomy is associated with an increase in bone mineral density at femoral and lumbar level, with an increase of 8.6±6.7% at lumbar level, and 4±16.1% at femoral level. The decrease in calcium after the parathyroidectomy was 2.8mg/dL (95% CI; 1.9-4). The decrease in PTH was 172pg/mL (95% CI; 98-354) and the decrease in alkaline phosphatase was 229 U/L (95% CI; 70-371).Conclusions Total parathyroidectomy and autotransplantation of the parathyroid glands in renal transplant patients with tertiary hyperparathyroidism increases the bone mineral density. Furthermore, the calcium, PTH and alkaline phosphatase returned to normal in the long-term (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ochagavía Cámara, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres García, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Pernaute, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Robin-Lersundi, Alvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez-Valladares, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción En los pacientes trasplantados renales con hiperparatiroidismo terciario se observan alteraciones del metabolismo óseo así como un descenso de la densidad mineral ósea. El objetivo de este trabajo fue analizar el incremento de la densidad mineral ósea, así como los resultados analíticos tras la paratiroidectomía total y autotrasplante en pacientes trasplantados renales con hiperparatiroidismo terciario. Material y métodos Estudio retrospectivo en el que se analizaron los valores de la densidad mineral ósea a nivel femoral y lumbar, así como los niveles séricos de calcio, fósforo, hormona paratiroidea (PTH) y fosfatasa alcalina en 13 pacientes trasplantados renales con hiperparatiroidismo terciario antes y después de la realización de paratiroidectomía total y autotrasplante de glándula paratiroides. Resultados La paratiroidectomía se asoció a un incremento de la densidad mineral ósea a nivel femoral y a nivel lumbar. El incremento de la densidad mineral ósea a nivel lumbar fue de 8,6±6,7% y de 4±16,1% a nivel femoral. El descenso de calcio tras la paratiroidectomía fue de 2,8mg/dl (IC 95%:1,9-4). El descenso de PTH fue de 172pg/mL (IC 95%:98-354) y el descenso de fosfatasa alcalina fue de 229 U/l (IC 95%:70-371).Conclusiones La paratiroidectomía total y el autotrasplante de glándula paratiroides en pacientes trasplantados renales con hiperparatiroidismo terciario incrementa la densidad mineral ósea. Asimismo, se observa una normalización de las cifras de calcio, PTH y fosfatasa alcalina a largo plazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);90(6): 382-387, jun.-jul. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105016</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incremento de la densidad mineral ósea en pacientes con hiperparatiroidismo terciario tras paratiroidectomía total y autotrasplante de glándula paratiroides</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32334^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2147^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29078^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14573^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7140^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d471^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10494^s22070</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201207</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
