<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147131</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-3703</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">B-HCG  levels on day 12 after embryo transfer as a predictor of ongoing pregnancy in IVF cycles</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: The aim of our study is to find a value of &amp;#946;-HCG to predict the outcome of pregnancies in a single hormone determination in our population. As secondary objectives, we will assess whether this value has to be adjusted for BMI and age of the patient. Setting: Patients subjected to an IVF cycle at our center Hospital Universitari de Girona Dr. Josep Trueta, between July 2010 and December 2013. Design: Retrospective and descriptive study. Material and methods: A total of 50 cycles with a positive &amp;#946;-HCG the day 12 after the embryo tranfer were analyzed with respect to pregnancy outcome from a total of 139 patients subjected to an IVF cycle at our center between July 2010 and December 2013. Results: The differences in the level of &amp;#946;-HCG at day 12 are statistically significant between different groups based on gestational outcome (p&lt;0,05). Comparing only viable pregnancies with nonviable pregnancies the differences are even more significant. With a &amp;#946;-HCG 300,53 average for viable pregnancies and average &amp;#946;-HCG for nonviable 88,66 (p&lt;0,01). The ROC curve suggests that a value of &amp;#946;-HCG 77 mIU / ml would be a good level to predict a viable pregnancy with a sensitivity of 90.63 % and a specificity of 80 %. There are not statistically significant differences in the value of &amp;#946;-HCG in terms of BMI or age. Conclusions: With a value of &amp;#946;-HCG of 77mUI/ml or more, we can better guide the patient and provide for a successful pregnancy, helping to plan medical management and reduce maternal anxiety. This value, in addition and according to our study, does not need to be adjusted for age or BMI of the patient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Castaño, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonmatí Santané, Alexandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Navarro, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Encontrar un valor de &amp;#946;-HCG que prevea el resultado evolutivo de la gestación en una única determinación hormonal en nuestra población. Como objetivos secundarios nos planteamos valorar si ese valor tiene que ser ajustado en función del IMC y de la edad de la paciente. Ámbito: Pacientes sometidas a un ciclo FIV en nuestro centro Hospital Universitari de Girona Dr. Josep Trueta, entre julio de 2010 y diciembre de 2013. Diseño: Estudio retrospectivo descriptivo. Material y métodos: Se incluyen 50 ciclos con &amp;#946;-HCG positiva a los 12 días de la transferencia embrionaria de un total de 139 pacientes sometidas a un ciclo FIV en nuestro centro entre julio de 2010 y diciembre de 2013. Resultados: Las diferencias en el nivel de &amp;#946;-HCG el día 12 son estadísticamente significativas entre los diferentes grupos en función del resultado gestacional (p&lt;0.05). Si comparamos solamente las gestaciones viables con las gestaciones no viables las diferencias son todavía más significativas. Con una &amp;#946;-HCG media de 300,53 para las gestaciones viables y una B-HCG media de 88,66 para las no viables (p&lt;0,01). La curva ROC sugiere que un valor de &amp;#946;-HCG de 77 mUI/ml sería un buen nivel para prever una gestación viable, con una sensibilidad del 90,63% y una especificidad del 80%. No existen diferencias estadísticamente significativas del valor de &amp;#946;-HCG en función del IMC ni de la edad. Conclusiones: Con un valor de &amp;#946;-HCG igual o superior a 77mUI/ml podemos orientar mejor a la paciente, y prever una gestación exitosa, ayudando a planificar el manejo médico así como disminuir la ansiedad materna. Este valor, además, y según nuestro estudio, no necesita ser ajustado por edad o IMC de la pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. iberoam. fertil. reprod. hum;32(4): 45-49, oct.-dic. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147131</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La determinación de B-HCG el día 12 de la transferencia embrionaria como predictor del resultado gestacional en técnicas de Reproducción Asistida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5416^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29201^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5416^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29201^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52018^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52018^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52018^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52018^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29201^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29201^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
