<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135485</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Occupational disease relapses in apopulation register (1989-1998)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To analyze the principal characteristics and determinants of occupational disease relapses in a population register. Material and methods: The study material is the data base of the Register of Occupational Diseases of the Navarre Institute of Occupational Health in the period 1989-1998. Non parametric statistics tests and unconditional logistic regression were performed to model the relationship between socioprofessional factors and risk of occupational disease recurrence. Results: During the study period, 22% of the 4,547 cases of reported occupational diseases were relapses of previous cases. The highest percentage of relapses included asthma and skin diseases, but the musculo-skeletal diseases represented the highest overall figure. The highest incidence occurred in the manufacturing of motor vehicles (7 relapses per 1000 workers yearly) and the principal nosologic entity has been the fatigue of tendinous pods. The average age among relapse cases was 40.3 years. In 75% of cases the relapse is produced within 9 months following the initial process, even though the time interval between relapses was smaller for occupational asthma, under 2 months in 75% of cases (p = 0,005). Middle age, long exposure time, motor vehicle manufacture, greater companies as well as skin and respiratory diseases were found to increase relapse risk in the first year after initial diagnosis, after adjustment for the confounding factors. Conclusion: The professional disease relapses indicate an emerging problem of occupational health, suggesting an insufficient modification of work conditions after the verification of the damage. They are produced largely in young adults in a short period of time after the initial case, with pathologies for which effective risk prevention measures are available, including early diagnosis and early removal from exposure to offending agents (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Artieda, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Layana, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beloqui, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Analizar las principales características y determinantes de las recaídas de enfermedad profesional en un registro poblacional. Material y métodos: Los datos se obtuvieron del Registro de enfermedades profesionales del Instituto Navarro de Salud Laboral en el período 1989-1998. En el análisis se han empleado pruebas estadísticas no paramétricas y regresión logística no condicional para identificar los factores de riesgo de presentación de recaídas. Resultados: En el período de estudio, un 22% de las 4.547 enfermedades profesionales declaradas fueron recaídas de un proceso previo. Asma y enfermedades cutáneas presentaron el mayor porcentaje de recaídas, si bien las enfermedades musculoesqueléticas registraron el mayor número absoluto. La mayor incidencia se ha registrado en la fabricación de vehículos de motor (siete recaídas anuales por cada mil trabajadores) y la principal entidad nosológica ha sido la fatiga de vainas tendinosas. La media de edad en las recaídas ha sido de 40,3 años. En el 75% de casos la recaída se produce en los nueve meses siguientes al proceso inicial, si bien el intervalo de tiempo entre recaídas ha sido menor en el asma profesional, inferior a dos meses en el 75% de casos (p = 0,005). Se asociaron a un mayor riesgo de recaída las edades intermedias, las empresas de más de 25 trabajadores, la fabricación de vehículos de motor, un tiempo de exposición al riesgo superior a dos años y el presentar patología cutánea o respiratoria. Conclusiones: Las recaídas de enfermedades profesionales suponen un problema emergente de salud laboral, que sugieren una insuficiente modificación de las condiciones de trabajo tras constatar el daño. Se producen principalmente en adultos jóvenes en un breve período de tiempo tras el proceso inicial, con patologías que disponen de medidas eficaces de prevención, como el diagnóstico precoz y cese de exposición al agente nocivo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. prev. riesgos labor. (Ed. impr.);3(2): 55-60, abr.-jun. 2000. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135485</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recaídas por enfermedades profesionales en un registro poblacional de declaración de casos (1989-1998)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33619^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54493^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54493^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54493^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54493^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33619^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
