<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85718</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The social construction of grief in mis carriage</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to ascertain the different experiences of grief in women whohave suffered spontaneous abortions during the first trimester of pregnancy.Specific objectives: to identify the different representations ofmotherhood, life and death of women who have suffered miscarriages;to explore women&#146;s perceptions of the female body; to understand the relationshipbetween coping mechanisms in the face of a miscarriage andrepresentations of motherhood, death and corporality.Methods: exploratory study, using a qualitative and phenomenologicalstrategy, from a gender perspective. Scope of the study: obstetric emergenciesservice of the Hospital of Fuenlabrada, this service being the referenceservice for the cities of Fuenlabrada, Humanes and Moraleja deEnmedio, all belonging to Area 9 of the Community of Madrid. Study subjects:theoretical sampling, by means of selective coding according to predeterminedcategories; the study participants being women diagnosedwith miscarriage who attended the emergency service of the Hospitalof Fuenlabrada, as well the Nursing staff of the obstetric emergenciesservice, operating rooms and reanimation. Procedures: field work. Datacollection was structured in three consecutive phases and the proceduresselected were participant observation (ethnographic context of thethree cities and intensive observation of the hospital setting), 16 in-depthinterviews and 9 semi-structured interviews with Nursing professionals.Data analysis: theory based on following Corbin and Strauss. The softwareprogramme Atlas ti. 5.0. was used. Ethical considerations: all participantshave been verbally informed by the research team and havesigned the informed consent form (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Huete, María Eloísa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín Morales, Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campo Cecilia, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Sánchez, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: conocer las diferentes vivencias del duelo en las mujeres conpérdida fetal espontánea en el primer trimestre de gestación. Objetivosespecíficos: identificar las distintas representaciones sobre la maternidad,la vida y la muerte de las mujeres con abortos espontáneos; explorar laspercepciones sobre el cuerpo femenino de las mujeres; comprender la relaciónque existe entre los mecanismos de afrontamiento ante un embarazono evolutivo y las representaciones sobre la maternidad, la muertey la corporalidad.Métodos: es de carácter exploratorio, utilizando una estrategia de tipocualitativa y fenomenológica, con perspectiva de género. Ámbito de estudio:el entorno del servicio de urgencias obstétricas del Hospital deFuenlabrada, pertenecientes al Área 9 de la Comunidad de Madrid.Sujetos de estudio: el muestreo fue teórico, a través de la codificaciónselectiva según categorías preconcebidas, siendo los participantes del estudiolas mujeres diagnosticadas de embarazo no evolutivo que acudíanal servicio de urgencias del Hospital de Fuenlabrada, así como el personalde Enfermería de los servicios de urgencias obstétricas, quirófanos yreanimación. Procedimientos: trabajo de campo. La recogida de datos seplanteó en tres fases consecutivas y los procedimientos seleccionadosfueron la observación participante (contexto etnográfico de los tres municipiosy observación intensiva del medio hospitalario), 16 entrevistasen profundidad y 9 entrevistas semiestructuradas al personal de Enfermería.Análisis de los datos: teoría fundamentada siguiendo a Corbin y Strauss.Se utilizó el programa informático Atlas ti. 5.0. Consideraciones éticas:todos los participantes han sido informados verbalmente por el equipo investigadory han firmado el consentimiento informado, aprobado por(..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;13(6): 25-32, jul. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85718</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La construcción social del duelo en el aborto espontáneo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35153</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23274</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201007</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
