<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91415</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cardiovascular health in women: The role of anger and its expression</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The relationships between anger expression (in, out, and control) and cardiovascular health (emotional distress, cardiovascular symptoms reported, and preventive health behaviors) were analyzed in 327 women (range 17-60 years). The same criteria (N= 218), as well as blood pressure (BP) registered in medical checkups (N= 90) were recorded one year later. Four groups according to anger-in and anger-control scores, going from the most hostile (high anger-in and low anger-control) to the least hostile (low anger-in and high angercontrol) were considered. The results indicated that the most hostile group, with the least adaptive anger expression, presented worst cardiovascular health than the other three groups, at both temporal moments. Furthermore, the presence of women with pathological BP levels was higher in the groups of high anger-in. These data ratify the role of anger expression, especially its repression (anger-in) and the lack of adequate canalization or control in women&#146;s cardiovascular health from a prospective design. Appropriate management of anger feelings and the practice of preventive health behaviors can protect women from cardiovascular problems (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-García, Ana M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanjuán, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, M. Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rueda, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se analizaron las relaciones entre expresión de la ira (interiorizada, exteriorizada y controlada) y salud cardiovascular (malestar emocional, informe de síntomas cardiovasculares y conductas de prevención) en 327 mujeres (rango 17-60 años). Un año después, se registraron en la muestra los mismos criterios (N= 218), así como la presión sanguínea (PS) obtenida en revisiones médicas (N= 90). Se formaron cuatro grupos en función de las puntuaciones en ira interiorizada (ira-in) y en control de la ira, desde el más desadaptativo en su expresión de la ira (alta ira-in y bajo control) hasta el más adaptativo (baja irain y alto control). Los resultados mostraron que el grupo con una ira más desadaptativa presentaba peor salud cardiovascular que el resto de grupos, en ambos momentos temporales. Asimismo, la presencia de mujeres con niveles patológicos de PS fue mayor en los grupos altos en ira-in. Los datos apoyan el papel de la represión de la ira y la falta de su adecuada canalización o control, en la salud cardiovascular de la mujer desde un diseño prospectivo. Se concluye que una correcta regulación de los sentimientos de ira y la práctica de conductas preventivas pueden proteger a la mujer frente a la presencia de problemas cardiovasculares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);23(4): 593-598, oct.-dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91415</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Salud cardiovascular en la mujer: el papel de la ira y su expresión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55111^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d797^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
