<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036221</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Erectile dysfunction: objectives and interventions in the nursing consultation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Worldwide, erectile dysfunction (ED) affects 16% of men aged between 20 and 75 years. Although ED is under-diagnosed, effective treatment (demonstrated in up to 91% of cases) is available. Most cases of ED can be dealt with in primary care through sexual counseling and orally administered drugs. &#150;Because of their knowledge and access to patients, primary care nurses can participate in diagnosis and treatment, especially in patients who smoke, are diabetic or hypertensive and/or who chronically take medication. If necessary, nurses can also refer patients to other health professionals. &#150;The application of nursing methodology is fundamental to increasing efficiency in identifying patients with ED and to improving treatment results. This can be developed in the nursing consultation where rapport with the patient can be established</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sáez Crespo, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Piédrola, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro Molina, Mariano</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La disfunción eréctil es un problema de salud mundial que afecta al 16% de los varones con edades comprendidas entre los 20 y los 75 años. Aunque suele ser poco diagnosticado, hay un tratamiento eficaz demostrado hasta en el 91% de los casos. La mayoría de las disfunciones eréctiles son abordables en atención primaria, mediante el consejo sexual y el tratamiento con fármacos por vía oral. La enfermera de atención primaria, por su conocimiento y accesbilidad al paciente, puede colaborar a establecer el diagnóstico y el tratamiento, especialmente en pacientes diabéticos, hipertensos, fumadores y/o los que toman medicación crónica y, en su caso, derivarlos a otros profesionales. La aplicación de la metodología enfermera es un instrumento fundamental para aumentar la eficacia en la captación de los pacientes con disfunción eréctil y mejorar los resultados de los tratamientos. Todo ello puede desarrollarse en la consulta enfermera, donde se crea un clima relacional adecuado</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);15(1): 43-49, ene. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036221</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Disfunción eréctil: objetivos e intervenciones en la consulta de enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29491^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
