<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61716</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Lifestyle, socioeconomic status and morbidity in postmenopausal women with grade II and III obesity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Obesity has become a major public health problem in all western countries, and its prevalence is increasing. This condition is associated with a higher prevalence of diabetes mellitus, hypertension, and coronary heart disease; furthermore, obesity is a risk factor for mortality. Objective: To study the association of some prevalent diseases (diabetes mellitus, thyroid disease, obesity, hypertension, inflammatory rheumatic disease, urolithiasis), the distribution of some lifestyle factors (tobacco, alcohol and caffeine consumption and physical activity during leisure time) and the prevalence of poverty in a population of postmenopausal women in the Canary Islands with obesity class II or III (BMI &gt; 35). A personal interview was performed in all patients. A questionnaire was administered to assess their lifestyles and current medication use. The women&#146;s medical records were reviewed to confirm the existence of certain diseases. A complete physical examination was performed in all patients. Weight and height were measured with the patient dressed in light clothing. Blood samples were obtained with the patient in a fasting state for subsequent analysis. Poverty was defined according to the criteria of the Spanish National Institute of Statistics Results: Women with obesity class II or III were older (56.8 ± 11 vs 53.9 ± 11.6 years, p = 0.02), shorter (153.7 ± 6.3 vs 156.9 ± 36.1 cm, p = 0.001), heavier (89.6 ± 9.3 vs 66.6 ± 10.4 kg, p = 0.001) and had a greater body surface than controls (1.73 ± 0.13 vs 1.54 ± 0.13 m2, p = 0.001). Alcohol and tobacco consumption were lower in obese women than in controls. Obese women drank more coffee and took less physical activity during leisure time than controls. The prevalence of hypertension &#150;36% vs 17.9%, p = 0.001, odds ratio [OR] [95% confidence interval (IC)] = 2.57 (1.564.24)&#150;, diabetes mellitus &#150;24.4% vs 11.3%, p = 0.001, OR = 2.52 (1.47-1.05)&#150; and hypothyroidism &#150;14.3% vs 8%, p = 0.04; OR = 1.91 (0.99-3.68)&#150; was higher in obese women than in controls. More than half lived in rural areas and were below the poverty threshold Conclusions: More than half of postmenopausal women with obesity class II or III were below the poverty threshold and lived in a rural area. In these women there was a lower consumption of alcohol and tobacco, lesser physical activity during leisure time, and a higher prevalence of diabetes mellitus, hypertension and hypothyroidism than in control postmenopausal women (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sablón González, Nery</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pablos Velasco, Pedros de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saavedra Santana, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Rodríguez, Mary Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sosa Henríquez, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguel Ruiz, Emilio de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro Medina, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: La obesidad es un importante problema de salud pública en todos los países occidentales y su prevalencia va en aumento. La obesidad se asocia a otras enfermedades como la diabetes mellitus, la hipertensión arterial y la cardiopatía isquémica y por sí misma es un factor de riesgo que incrementa la mortalidad. Objetivos: Conocer qué proporción de las mujeres canarias posmenopáusicas con obesidad de grados II y III (índice de masa corporal [IMC] = 35) se encuentra por debajo del umbral de la pobreza y estudiar en esa misma población la prevalencia de diabetes mellitus, enfermedad tiroidea, obesidad, hipertensión arterial, enfermedad reumática inflamatoria, urolitiasis y fracturas óseas por fragilidad (totales, vertebrales y no vertebrales), la distribución de una serie de estilos de vida (consumos de tabaco, de alcohol y de cafeína y actividad física realizada durante el tiempo libre), y el nivel socioeconómico. Método: Estudio observacional transversal. Se entrevistó personalmente a todas las pacientes y se les aplicó un cuestionario dirigido a conocer su estilo de vida. Asimismo se revisó su historia clínica para documentar la prevalencia de las enfermedades. También se les efectuó una exploración física detenida y se las talló y pesó con ropa ligera. Asimismo se les extrajo sangre en ayunas para realizar una analítica general. El criterio de pobreza aplicado fue el establecido por el Instituto Nacional de Estadística Resultados: Las mujeres con obesidad mórbida tenían mayor edad (56,8 ± 11 frente a 53,9 ± 11,6 años; p = 0,02), menor talla (153,7 ± 6,3 frente a 156,9 ± 36,1 cm; p = 0,001), mayor peso (89,6 ± 9,3 frente a 66,6 ± 10,4 kg; p = 0,001) y mayor superficie corporal que las controles (1,73 ± 0,13 frente a 1,54 ± 0,13 m2; p = 0,001). Estas mujeres consumían menos alcohol y tabaco y más café, y eran más sedentarias que las mujeres del grupo control. También tenían mayor prevalencia de hipertensión arterial (el 36 frente al 17,9%; p = 0,001; odds ratio [OR] = 2,57; intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 1,56-4,24), diabetes mellitus (el 24,4 frente al 11,3%; p = 0,001; OR = 2,52; IC del 95%, 1,47-1,05) e hipotiroidismo (el 14,3 frente al 8%; p = 0,04; OR = 1,91; IC del 95%, 0,99-3,68). Más de la mitad de las mujeres con obesidad mórbida vivían en un hábitat rural y se encontraban por debajo del umbral de la pobreza. Conclusiones: Más de la mitad de las mujeres posmenopáusicas con obesidad mórbida están por debajo del umbral de la pobreza y viven en un hábitat rural. Consumen menos alcohol y tabaco, son más sedentarias y presentan una mayor prevalencia de diabetes mellitus, hipertensión e hipotiroidismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;56(5): 227-232, mayo 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61716</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estilo de vida, nivel socioeconómico y morbilidad en mujeres posmenopáusicas con obesidad de grados II y III</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28631^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4422</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31161^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7217^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11641</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200905</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
