<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91504</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychiatric reform after 25 years the general Law of Health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The paper analyzes the situation of the psychiatric reform 25 years of the General Health Law. The author wonders what has been done and what has been left undone, on the degree of implementation of the Communitymodel that adopts the law and its future sustainability. It highlights, among the strengths, the loss of hegemony of the psychiatric hospital and the great development of alternative resources, and seeks to explain the reason for the inadequacies of care, policy and training, as well as threats: the changes in the management of social and health services, increased privatization of services, the theoretical impoverishment and changing demands of the population(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Desviat, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El artículo analiza la situación de la reforma psiquiátrica a los 25 años de la Ley General de Sanidad. Se pregunta por lo que se ha hecho y lo que se ha dejado de hacer; por el grado de implantación del modelo comunitario que adopta la Ley y por su sostenibilidad futura. Entre las fortalezas se señalan la pérdida de hegemonía del hospital psiquiátrico y el gran desarrollo de recursos alternativos, y se trata de explicar el porqué de las insuficiencias asistenciales, normativas y formativas, así como de las amenazas: los cambios producidos en la gestión de los servicios sociales y sanitarios, la creciente privatización de los servicios, la precarización teórica y los cambios en la demanda de la población(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;85(5): 427-436, sep.-oct.2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91504</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La reforma psiquiátrica 25 años después de la Ley General de Sanidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31424^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31424^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1714^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31424^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31424^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1714^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3190^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3190^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1714^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3190^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3190^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50003</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
