<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121865</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prior health advice to immigrants who travel to visit family and friends</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Immigrants who make or plan journeys to visit their families in their countries of origin (immigrants -visiting friends and relatives, I-VFR) have a higher risk of acquiring travel associated diseases than other travellers. The main aim of this study is to analyse the knowledge of the immigrant population on the need to receive health advice (HA) before making international journeys in general and in particular before travelling to their country of origin. Design: Observational, multicentre study. Setting: Ten Family Doctors from 10 Health Centres in Catalonia and Aragon participated. Participants: A total of 555 immigrants &amp;#8805;15 years of age, who consulted their Family Doctor and agreed to answer a questionnaire. Opportunity sampling was used. Results: A total of 389 (70.1%) of those surveyed considered it necessary to receive HA before making an international journey, 406 (73.2%) were I-VFR and 145 (35.7%) had requested HA prior to the journey, mostly from their Family Doctor (n=60; 41.1%).Almost two-thirds (261, 65.2%) of the subjects did not seek HA, with the most common reason being that they did not consider it necessary (173, 42.6%).Conclusions: I-VFR do not usually request HA prior to travelling, basic due to considering it unnecessary. When they do request it, they are very often initially directed to their Family Doctor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Roca, Carme</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valerio, Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrasco, Clara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solsona, Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gimeno-Feliu, Luis Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Los inmigrantes que realizan o proyectan viajes para visitar a sus familiares en sus países de origen (inmigrantes-visiting friends and relatives [I-VFR]) tienen un riesgo superior a adquirir enfermedades relacionadas con el viaje que otros viajeros. El objetivo principal de este estudio es analizar los conocimientos de la población inmigrante sobre la necesidad de recibir consejo sanitario (CS) antes de realizar viajes internacionales en general y, específicamente, antes de viajar a sus países de origen. Diseño: Estudio observacional y multicéntrico. Emplazamiento: Participaron 10 médicos de familia de 10 Centros de Salud de Cataluña y Aragón. Participantes: Quinientos cincuenta y cinco inmigrantes &amp;#8805; 15 años de edad, que consultaron a su médico de familia y accedieron a responder un cuestionario. Se realizó un muestreo oportunista. Resultados: Consideraban necesario recibir CS antes de realizar un viaje internacional 389 (70,1%) personas; 406 (73,2%) eran I-VFR y 145 (35,7%) habían solicitado CS previamente al viaje, con mayor frecuencia a su médico de familia (n = 60; 41,1%).No habían solicitado CS 261 (65,2%) sujetos, siendo el motivo más frecuente por considerarlo innecesario 173 (42,6%). Conclusiones: Los I-VFR no suelen solicitar CS previo a viajar, fundamentalmente por considerarlo innecesario. Cuando lo solicitan, con gran frecuencia se dirigen en primera instancia a su médico de familia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;46(4): 198-203, abr. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121865</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consejo sanitario previo a inmigrantes que viajan para visitar a familiares y amigos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50219</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50218</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30706</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
