<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74044</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1582</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the evolution in the diagnosis andtreatment of the occult breast carcinomas presented asmetastatic lymph node.Patients and methods: Thirteen women diagnosed andtreated of lymph node metastasis of breast cancer without primaryfocus localization.Results: Ten patients were treated with conservativesurgery and radiotherapy of the breast, presenting afavourable evolution. The 3 women that were treated onlywith hormonotherapy, had carcinomatous mastitis after fewyears.Conclusions: Mammography is still the gold standard testto study breast cancer. RNM and PET can help to localize occultbreast cancer. Lymphadenectomy and radiotherapy of thebreast is a good treatment in most cases, opposite to the classicalradical mastectomy(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Encinas, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bengoechea, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Biete, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Verge, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fumanal, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arcusa, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Valorar la evolución en el diagnóstico y tratamientodel carcinoma oculto de mama que se presenta comometástasis ganglionar.Pacientes y método: Trece mujeres diagnosticadas y tratadaspor haber presentado metástasis ganglionar de un carcinomade mama, sin localizar el foco primario.Resultados: Las 10 pacientes a las que se pudo aplicar cirugíaconservadora y radioterapia, evolucionaron favorablemente.Las tres que sólo recibieron hormonoterapia presentaronmastitis carcinomatosa a los pocos años.Conclusiones: Aunque la mamografía sigue siendo la exploraciónprincipal, la RNM y el PET ayudan a localizar algunoscarcinomas ocultos. Se confirma que el tratamiento consistenteen una linfadenectomía y radioterapia de la mama, esel de elección en la mayoría de los casos, frente a la cirugía radicalclásica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. senol. patol. mamar. (Ed. impr.);22(1): 10-13, 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74044</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución en el diagnóstico y tratamiento del carcinoma oculto de mama con metástasis ganglionar (T0 pN1): ratificación de la propuesta terapéutica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8374^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8374^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19257^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19257^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19257^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19257^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29141^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19257^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23307^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200900</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
