<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166621</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relevance of the socioeconomic and health context in patient satisfaction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine which factors of the socioeconomic and health contexts influence the perception of the satisfaction of the population with the health services. Methods: The data come from the European Health Survey of 2009. In the 22,188 subjects surveyed, the relationship between the perception of satisfaction with the health services received and the individual and contextual variables was studied, applying a multilevel analysis. Results: The factors of the socioeconomic and health contexts that influence satisfaction are: higher rates of low level of studies where the perception of excellence is less likely (odds ratio [OR]: 0.48-0.82) and dissatisfaction is more prevalent (OR: 1.46-1.63). Likewise, the proportion of unsatisfied citizens is lower when per capita expenditure on health services is very high (&gt;1400 &#128;) (OR: 0.49-0.87) and the ratio &#147;primary health care physicians/inhabitants&#148; is high (&gt;60) (OR: 0.500.85). In addition, the prevalence of dissatisfaction describes a positive linear trend with the unemployment rate (OR: 1.12; p=0.0001) and the relative magnitude of the services sector (OR: 1.03; p=0.001). By contrast, this linear trend is negative as the Health Care Coverage Ratio increases (OR: 0.88; p=0.04). Conclusions: The individual factors that determine patient satisfaction are: sex, age, mental health and country of birth. In addition, there are differences in patient satisfaction among the autonomous communities according to socio-economic determinants such as GDP per capita, low-level study rates, unemployment rates or number of inhabitants/doctor's ratio. User satisfaction studies as well as being adjusted for individual variables such as sex, age or health level should also take into account characteristics of the socioeconomic environment of the geographic area where they reside (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Romero, Shirley</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gascón Cánovas, Juan J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parra Hidalgo, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salmerón Martínez, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monteagudo Piqueras, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar qué factores de los contextos socioeconómico y sanitario influyen sobre la percepción de la satisfacción de la población con los servicios de salud. Método: Los datos provienen de la Encuesta Europea de Salud de 2009. En los 22.188 sujetos encuestados se estudió la relación entre percepción de la satisfacción con los servicios sanitarios recibidos y las variables tanto individuales como contextuales, aplicando un análisis multinivel. Resultados: Los factores de los contextos socioeconómico y sanitario que influyen sobre la satisfacción son las mayores tasas de población sin estudios, en la cual la percepción de excelencia es menos probable (odds ratio [OR]: 0,48-0,82) y la insatisfacción es más prevalente (OR: 1,46-1,63). Asimismo, la proporción de personas insatisfechas es menor cuando el gasto per cápita en servicios sanitarios es muy elevado (&gt;1400 &#128;) (OR: 0,49-0,87) y la ratio entre médicos de atención primaria de salud y habitantes es alta (&gt;60) (OR: 0,50-0,85). Además, la prevalencia de insatisfacción describe una tendencia lineal positiva con la tasa de paro (OR: 1,12; p=0,0001) y la magnitud relativa del sector servicios (OR:1,03; p=0,001). Por el contrario, esta tendencia lineal es negativa conforme aumenta el índice de cobertura de la prestación sanitaria (OR: 0,88; p=0,04). Conclusiones: Los factores individuales que determinan la satisfacción del paciente son el sexo, la edad, la salud mental y el país de nacimiento. Además, hay diferencias en la satisfacción del paciente entre las comunidades autónomas de acuerdo con determinantes socioeconómicos, como el producto interior bruto per cápita, las tasas de población sin estudios, las tasas de paro o la ratio número de habitantes/consultorios. Los estudios de satisfacción del usuario, además de ajustarse por variables individuales como el sexo, la edad o el nivel de salud, también deberían tomar en consideración características del entorno socioeconómico del área geográfica de residencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;31(5): 416-422, sept.-oct. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166621</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relevancia del contexto socioeconómico y sanitario en la satisfacción del paciente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d55453^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16665</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
