<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-26855</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Esophagoscopy in adults. Our experience and literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We are reporting our 12 years-experience about the extraction, by rigid esophagoscopy, of esophageal foreign bodies in adults. Between 1990 and 2002 we have performed 62 esophagoscopies under general anesthesia corresponding 39 to women and 23 to men with 68 years-old average. A series of variables have been studied: personal history, clinical symptoms, type of foreign body and evolutive period. Besides, we have analysed the esophageal location and complications of the surgery such as ulcerations and perforations. The number of procedures have decreased to a great extent because of flexible endoscopy which is the first choice technique. Actually only less than 15% of all emergencies for that pathology require a rigid esophagoscopy in our Hospital (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sanidad y Ediciones (SANED, S.L.)</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos nuestra experiencia de 12 años en la extracción, mediante esofagoscopia rígida, de cuerpos extraños esofágicos en adultos. Entre 1990 y 2002 hemos realizado 62 esofagoscopias bajo anestesia general de las que 39 correspondían a mujeres y 23 a varones, con una media de edad de 68 años. Estudiamos una serie de variables preoperatorias: antecedentes personales, sintomatología clínica, tipo de cuerpo extraño y tiempo de evolución. Además analizamos la localización esofágica y complicaciones de la cirugía como ulceraciones y perforaciones. El número de procedimientos ha disminuido en gran medida gracias a la endoscopia flexible que constituye la técnica de primera elección. Actualmente sólo menos del 15 por ciento de todas las urgencias por esta patología precisan una esofagoscopia rígida en nuestro Hospital (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;54(9): 642-645, nov. 2003. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Esofagoscopia en adultos. Nuestra experiencia y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Trinidad Ruíz, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Palomino, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo Romero, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blasco Huelva, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pino Rivero, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcos García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-26855</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5683^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29389</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200311</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
