<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98349</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevention of eating disorders in pre-adolescents girls: effectiveness of a multi-session interactive program at one year follow-up</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of this paper was to determine the efficacy of a program applied to 115 girls in 1st and 2nd grade in Secondary Obligatory Education (ESO) (average age=12.71; SD=0.72) in six sessions to prevent the onset of eating disorders. Pre-, post-program and after a one-year follow-up, the EAT-40 and BSQ were applied. Additionally, a questionnaire was created to assess the capability of identifying risk factors in ED development. The results were contrasted with those obtained from a group of girls (N= 69) in the same grades and of the same age (average age=14.36; SD=0.54) who did not participate in the prevention program (PP). Participants were already showing very low scores on both questionnaires from the pre-program. The effects of the intervention were scarce, although it was observed that a high capability of identifying risk factors had been acquired. When compared to the non-participants and after the one-year follow up, the participants showed significant lower eating and body image pathologies. The program has proven its efficacy both in short and long-term and the ideal school year to apply it is 2nd grade ESO</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Avargues Navarro, Mª Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez San Gregorio, Mª Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>del Río Sánchez, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borda Mas, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Pérez, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo es determinar la eficacia de un programa de prevención (PP) para el desarrollo de TCA, aplicado en seis sesiones a 115 chicas de 1º y 2º de ESO (edad media= 12,71; DT= 0,72). Pre, post-programa y al año de seguimiento se aplicaron el EAT-40 y el BSQ. Post-programa, se administró una encuesta que evaluaba la capacidad para identificar la influencia de factores de riesgo. Los resultados al año de las chicas de 2º de ESO ya en 3º de ESO, se contrastaron con los obtenidos por un grupo de chicas (n= 69) del mismo curso (edad media= 14,36; DT= 0,54) no participantes en el PP. Las participantes mostraron puntuaciones muy bajas en ambos cuestionarios desde el pre-programa. Los efectos de la intervención fueron escasos, aunque se observó una alta capacidad adquirida en identificar la influencia de los factores de riesgo. En comparación con las no participantes, las participantes presentaban al año de seguimiento significativamente menos patología alimentaria y de la imagen corporal. En conclusión, el PP ha mostrado su eficacia a corto y largo plazo y el curso idóneo para su aplicación es 2º de ESO (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;17(3): 499-521, sept.-dic. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98349</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevención de los trastornos de la conducta alimentaria (TCA) en chicas preadolescentes: eficacia de un programa multisesión e interactivo en el seguimiento a un año</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23896</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24382^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1853</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
