<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96414</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interpersonal perception, personality, and academic achievement: a dyadic approach for the study of undergraduate performance</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present work deals with the quantification of group characteristics by means of dyadic indices. Specifically, the aim of the present study was to explore whether dyadic and individual measures of interpersonal perceptions and personality could be related to academic achievement when dealing with project groups in a real academic setting. 88 undergraduate students formed 22 groups of four people to carry out a course report. After working together throughout the semester, participants filled in an Interpersonal Perception Questionnaire and NEO-FFI and the course report was assessed. Results showed that some dyadic measurements of interpersonal perceptions are associated to the marks obtained in the course report. Furthermore, an exponential regression function is proposed accounting for 50.3% of group marks variance. The predictive results found in the scientific literature revised, that follows an individualistic approach, are no larger than 18%. The results of the present study concur with previous results obtained in a laboratory context supporting the usefulness of the dyadic approach for the study of groups (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Solanas, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrés, Amara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salafranca, Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente trabajo trata sobre la cuantificación de características grupales mediante índices diádicos. Concretamente, el objetivo del presente estudio fue explorar la posible relación entre indicadores diádicos e individuales de percepción interpersonal y personalidad y el rendimiento académico en grupos de trabajo en un contexto académico real. 88 estudiantes universitarios formaron 22 grupos de cuatro personas para llevar a cabo un trabajo de curso. Tras trabajar juntos durante el semestre, los participantes contestaron a un Cuestionario de Percepción Interpersonal y al cuestionario de personalidad NEO-FFI y el trabajo de curso fue evaluado. Los resultados muestran que algunos índices diádicos de percepción interpersonal están asociados a las puntuaciones obtenidas en el trabajo de curso. Además, se propone un modelo de regresión exponencial que explica el 50.3% de la variabilidad en las notas de los grupos. Los resultados para predecir el rendimiento en grupos encontrados en la literatura científica, siguiendo una perspectiva individual, no son mayores de 18%. Los resultados del presente estudio concuerdan con resultados previos obtenidos en un contexto de laboratorio y dan apoyo a la perspectiva diádica para el estudio de grupos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;28(1): 97-106, ene.-abr. 2012. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96414</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Percepción interpersonal, personalidad y rendimiento académico: un enfoque diádico para el estudio del rendimiento de los estudiantes universitarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4562^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10742^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10743^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30184^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4562^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10662^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4562^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10743^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10662^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4562^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
