<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152590</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-7546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Health-related physical fitness in Brazilian adolescents from a small town of German colonization</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To identify the health-related physical fitness profile of Brazilian adolescents (10&#150;17 years) living in a small town of German colonization and to describe the prevalence of those with low levels of physical fitness according to sex and age. Method. This is a school-based cross-sectional epidemiological study conducted with all adolescents (10&#150;17 years) enrolled in five public schools of São Bonifácio, Brazil. The study included 277 adolescents (145 boys and 132 girls). The FITNESSGRAM® test battery was applied for the assessment of percent body fat, flexibility, muscle strength/endurance and cardiorespiratory fitness. Results. Higher mean values of percent body fat and flexibility (p &lt; 0.01) were found in girls; boys showed higher means (p &lt; 0.01) for pull-up and cardiorespiratory fitness tests. The prevalence of adolescents with low levels of physical fitness was high for percent body fat (boys: 29.3%, girls: 31.8%, p = 0.75), flexibility (boys: 26.9%, girls: 54.5%, p &lt; 0.01), muscle strength/endurance (curl-up: 37.9% of boys and 45.5% of girls, p = 0.25; modified pull-up: 47.6% of boys and 54.5% of girls, p = 0.30) and cardiorespiratory fitness (boys: 28.0%, girls: 36.9%, p = 0.15). As for the overall physical fitness, 75.7% of boys and 88.9% of girls did not meet the minimum recommended values (p = 0.01). Conclusion. Effective intervention programs are necessary to promote changes in the health-related physical fitness profile of adolescents from São Bonifácio, Brazil (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Petroski, EL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva, DAS</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Minatto, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Identificar el perfil de aptitud física y salud de adolescentes brasileños (10 a 17 años) de una pequeña ciudad de colonización germánica, así como describir la prevalencia de aquellos con baja aptitud física de acuerdo al sexo y la edad. Método. Estudio epidemiológico transversal de base escolar realizado con todos los adolescentes (10 a 17 años) de cinco escuelas públicas de San Bonifacio, SC (n = 277; 145 niños), en 2010. Se utilizó la batería de tests FITNESSGRAM® para evaluar la porcentaje de grasa corporal, la flexibilidad, la fuerza/resistencia muscular y la aptitud cardiorrespiratoria. Resultados. Se encontró un mayor porcentaje medio de grasa corporal y de flexibilidad (p &lt; 0.01) en las niñas; en los niños se obtuvieron mayores porcentajes medios en dominadas y en los test de aptitud cardiorrespiratoria (p &lt; 0.01). La prevalencia de adolescentes con baja aptitud física fue elevada para la grasa corporal (niños: 29.3%; niñas: 31.8%; p = 0.75), para la flexibilidad (niños: 26.9%; niñas: 54.5%; p &lt; 0.01), para la fuerza/resistencia muscular (test de abdominales: 37.9% de los niños y 45.5% de las niñas, p = 0.30) y para la aptitud física cardiorrespiratoria (niños: 28.0%; niñas: 36.9%; p = 0.15). En cuanto a la aptitud física general, 75.7% de los niños y 88.9% de las niñas no alcanzaron los valores mínimos recomendados (p = 0.01). Conclusión. Son necesarios programas efectivos de intervención para la promoción de cambios en el perfil de aptitud física relacionada con la salud de adolescentes de San Bonifacio, SC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. andal. med. deporte;9(2): 67-74, jun. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152590</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aptitud física relacionada con la salud en adolescentes brasileños de una pequeña ciudad de colonización germánica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30280^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28453^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
