<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126829</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-5967</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Early autism, mirror neurons, empathy, sensory integration, intersubjectivity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this work, the author briefly reviews the recent contributions to neuroscience, as well as the psychology and the psychopathology of the development, showing that a dialogue is possible between these different disciplines and hoping that a pathway is opened to confronting early childhood autism in an integrative manner. Nowadays we know, thanks to the advances of epigenetics, the recent discoveries about the cerebral plasticity and mirror neurons, as well as those derived from the cerebral neurogenic study, that the brain and mental development of the human being is the result of the interaction between the genetic-biological-constitutional and the psychosocial and socio-cultural environment in which we live (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Larbán Vera, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este trabajo, el autor repasa brevemente las aportaciones recientes de las neurociencias, así como de la psicología y psicopatología del desarrollo, mostrando que un diálogo es posible entre estas diferentes disciplinas, esperando que se abra camino un abordaje integrador del autismo temprano infantil. Hoy día sabemos, gracias a los avances de la epigenómica, los recientes descubrimientos sobre la plasticidad cerebral y las neuronas espejo, así como los derivados del estudio de la neurogénesis cerebral, que el desarrollo psíquico y cerebral del ser humano es el resultado de la interacción entre lo genético-biológico-constitucional y el entorno psicosocial y socio-cultural en el que vivimos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psiquiatr. psicoter. niño adolesc;(54): 79-91, jul.-dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126829</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Autismo temprano, neuronas espejo, empatía, integración sensorial, intersubjetividad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2717</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54420^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6955</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
