<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134909</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Applicability of the visceral adiposity index (VAI) in predicting components of metabolic syndrome in young adults</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Metabolic syndrome (MS) is one of the main risk factors for cardiovascular diseases (CVD) and identifying its components in young adults may constitute an important prevention tool. Objective: Analyzing applicability of the Visceral Adiposity Index (VAI) for predicting components of MS in young adults. Methods: Cross-sectional survey with 444 individuals, mean age 25.6±6.5, 77.7% females. We obtained data on weight, height, waist circumference (WC), body fat percentage (BF%), fasting glycemia, triglycerides (TG), total cholesterol (TC), HDL cholesterol (HDL-c), LDL cholesterol (LDL-c), and blood pressure (BP), as well as information on their lifestyles. Body Mass Index (BMI), Waist-to-Height Ratio (WHR) and VAI were calculated. Adiposity measurements were compared to the MS components, and for VAI, we determined the predictive capacity of MS components occurrence and the area below the ROC curve. Results: VAI correlated to glucose (r=0.136), HDL-c (r=-436), and TG (r=0.825) in females, and amongst men, it correlated to glucose (r=0.258), HDL-c (r=-0.550), TG (r=0.897), and DBP (r=0.290). An increased VAI was associated to an increased risk of abdominal obesity (OR=1.86), hypertriglyceridemia (OR=30.74), and low HDL-c (OR=3.95). Among obesity indicators, VAI presented a larger area below the curve for increased TG and low HDL-c. Conclusion: VAI presented an association to MS components in males and females with an increased risk of abdominal obesity, hipertriglyceridemia, and low HDL-c, proving to be a good MS components predictor even among healthy young adults (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vogel, Patrícia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Eckhardt, Cristiane</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dal Bosco Morelo, Simone</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schuster, Jéssica</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El síndrome metabólico (SM) es uno de los principales factores de riesgo de enfermedades cardiovasculares (ECV), y la identificación de sus componentes en los adultos jóvenes puede constituir una importante herramienta de prevención. Objetivo: Analizar la aplicabilidad del Visceral Adiposity Index (VAI) para la predicción de componentes del SM en adultos jóvenes. Métodos: Estudio transversal con 444 individuos, edad 25,6 ± 6,5, 77,7% del sexo femenino. Se obtuvieron datos sobre el peso, talla, circunferencia de cintura (CC), el porcentaje de grasa corporal (%GC), glucemia, triglicéridos (TG), colesterol total (CT), colesterol HDL (HDL-c), colesterol LDL (LDL-c), y la presión arterial (PA), así como información sobre sus estilos de vida. Se calculó Índice de Masa Corporal (IMC), la proporción de cintura a la altura (PCA) y VAI. Mediciones de adiposidad se compararon con los componentes del SM, y por VAI, se determinó la capacidad predictiva de ocurrencia de los componentes de SM y el área a bajo la curva ROC. Resultados: VAI se correlaciona a la glucosa (r= 0,136), HDL-c (r=-436) y TG (r=0,825) en las mujeres y entre los hombres, se correlaciona a la glucosa (r=0,258), HDL-c (r=-0,550), TG (r=0,897), y la PAD (r= 0,290). Un aumento de VAI se asoció a un mayor riesgo de obesidad abdominal (OR=1,86), hipertrigliceridemia (OR=30,74), y bajo HDL-c (OR=3,95). Entre los indicadores de obesidad, VAI presentó una mayor área bajo la curva de aumento de triglicéridos y bajos niveles de HDL-c. Conclusión: VAI presentó una asociación a los componentes del SM en hombres, y em mujeres con un mayor riesgo de obesidad abdominal, hipertrigliceridemia y bajos niveles de HDL-c, demostrando ser un buen predictor de componentes de SM, incluso entre adultos jóvenes sanos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;30(4): 806-812, oct. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134909</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicabilidad del visceral adiposity index (VAI) en la predicción de componentes del síndrome metabólico en adultos jóvenes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53563^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d280^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
