<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126279</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-0599</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The study looked at the effect of psychoeducational treatment in a group of patients with schizophrenia and their families at the Center of Mental Health of Vallecas (CSMV), in Madrid. The analysis followed patients during a 1-year period with regard to the following variables: self-care, social conscience of disease, selfesteem, and social relations and integration. A parallel group meeting took place with the families of the patients during a six-week period, in which they were informed and educated on the mental disease and how to prevent crisis in their relatives (i. e. the patients). A cuasi-experimental study was carried out to follow the progress of the patients with regards to the variables mentioned, both before the treatment and upon completion of it. Significant improvements were noticed in most of the variables considered, and there also was a noticeable decrease in the number of hospitalizations. The results of the study suggest that psychoeducational care is useful as part of the treatment for patients with schizophrenia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Basurte Villamor, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Mellizo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mellizo Cuadrado, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Olmos, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jarne García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este trabajo se ha estudiado el efecto de tratamiento psicoeducativo en un grupo de pacientes con esquizofrenia y sus familias en el Centro de Salud Mental de Vallecas (CSMV) en Madrid. La intervención se ha hecho con los pacientes durante un año en los siguientes aspectos: autocuidados, conciencia de enfermedad, autoestima y habilidades sociales. Paralelamente a las familias se las ha reunido durante seis semanas consecutivas, en las que se ha dado información acerca de la enfermedad mental y cómo prevenir crisis en sus  familiares.Se ha realizado un estudio cuasiexperimental para  observar la situación de los pacientes en los aspectos mencionados antes del tratamiento y al finalizar éste. Se ha encontrado una mejoría significativa en casi todas las variables estudiadas y una disminución de ingresos hospitalarios. Los resultados obtenidos sugieren que los abordajes psicoeducacionales son de utilidad como parte del tratamiento para personas con esquizofrenia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psiquiatr;19(4): 137-142, abr. 2003. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126279</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento psicoeducativo en pacientes con esquizofrenia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13031^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52882^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5300^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
