<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60218</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Childhood enuresis: the importance of a correct intervention</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Nocturnal Enuresis is a common illness in childhood that involves psychological and self-esteem problems. However, enuresis is often misunderstood. Objective: 1. Review the main epidemiologic and clinical characteristics of a group of enuretic children. 2. Follow up of these patients from admission until discharge from hospital. Material and methods: Descriptive, retrospective study including 67 children sent to the out patient department during 199-2005 for enuresis. Epidemiological, clinical and treatment data were recorded before and after visiting the specialist. Results: 67 patients were reviewed: 76,1% were found to have Monosyptomatic Nocturnal Enuresis (MNE) and 23,9% were found to have enuretic syndrome. In this study we present 51 cases of MNE (66,7% male and 33,3% female under the age of fourteen years). There was a family history of nocturnal enuresis in 80,4%. In our experience we founded that only 47,1% had received treatment before they arrived at hospital. Psychosocial evaluation was normal in 94,1% and physical examination in 92,2%. In 78,4% of the patients routine exams were carried out. The most frequent treatments were: behavioral intervention, desmopressin 845,1%) and desmopressin + cholinergic antagonists (33,35%). Secondary effects related to desmopressin were observed in 11,8%. 74,5% of the subjects mad a good recovery from enuresis. Conclusions: it is important to make patient and family aware of this problem and to promote the early treatment of MNE. Basic psychosocial examination and physical examination are usually normal in MNE. Routine exams can be reduced to an urine exam. The treatment can be over long duration and the early detection of secondary effects is basic to avoid treatment abandonment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Acosta Gordillo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cormenzana Carpio, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez Fernández, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espino Aguilar, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la enuresis nocturna monosintomática (ENM) es una enfermedad muy frecuente en la infancia que favorece la aparición de problemas psicológicos y de autoestima; sin embargo, sigue siendo una entidad infravalorada. Objetivos: 1. Conocer las características epidemiológicas y clínicas de una serie de niños enuréticos. 2. Seguir la evolución de estos pacientes desde que acudieron a nuestra consulta hasta el alta. Material y métodos: Estudio descriptivo retrospectivo incluyendo 67 niños derivados a una consulta hospitalaria durante los años 1997-2005 por presentar enuresis. Se recogieron los datos epidemiológicos, clínicos y terapéuticos antes y después de la visita a una consulta especializada. Resultados: Se revisaron 67 pacientes. 76,1% correspondieron a ENM y 23,9% a síndrome enurético. Presentamos 51 casos de ENM (66,7% niños y 33,3% niñas). Existían antecedentes familiares en el 80,4%. Solo el 47,1% había recibido tratamiento previo. La valoración psicosocial resultó normal en el 94,1% y la exploración física en el 92,2%. En el 78,4% se solicitaron pruebas complementarias. Los tratamientos más empleados fueron: pauta básica, desmopresina (45,1%) y desmopresina más anticolinérgicos (33,35%). Aparecieron efectos secundarios relacionados con la desmopresina en el 11,8%. Se curó el 74,5%. Conclusiones: Es necesario concienciar al paciente a sus familiares de este problema y fomentar el tratamiento precoz de la ENM. En la ENM la valoración básica psicosocial y la exploración física son casi siempre normales. Los exámenes complementarios pueden reducirse a un examen de orina. Recordar que el tratamiento requiere tiempo y detectar precozmente sus efectos secundarios es fundamental para evitar el abandono del mismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;64(4): 276-282, jul.-ago. 2008. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60218</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Euresis infantile: la importancia de una correcta intervención</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32307^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26532</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52131^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52131^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1543^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52131^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200808</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
