<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79840</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Elevated neuregulin-1 and ErbB4 protein in the prefrontal cortex of schizophrenic patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Neuregulin-1 (NRG1) and its receptor, ErbB4, have been implicated in schizophrenia at both gene and transcript levels. The present investigation compared NRG1 and ErbB4 protein levels in prefrontal cortical (PFC) cytoplasmic and nuclear fractions among normal, schizophrenic, bipolar and major depressed subjects from the Stanley Consortium. We used immunoblotting procedures to examine potential NRG1 and ErbB4 immunoreactive bands, but specifically quantified NRG1 immunoreactive signals at 42, 48 and 53kDa and ErbB4 immunoreactive signals at 21, 55, 60 and 180kDa. PFC cytoplasmic 53kDa NRG1 protein levels were significantly increased (¡­20%) in schizophrenic patients relative to each of the other subject groups. We also detected diagnostic effects on PFC cytoplasmic full-length (180kDa) ErbB4 protein levels, and post hoc tests revealed that these quantities were significantly increased (¡­30%) in schizophrenic patients relative to normal and to depressed subjects. In addition, we examined the levels of potential ErbB4 cleavage products at 21, 55 and 60kDa relative to those of full-length ErbB4 in the PFC fractions. We detected trends for diagnostic effects on PFC cytoplasmic 21kDa/180kDa and 55kDa/180kDa ratios, and post hoc tests revealed that these ratios were significantly reduced in schizophrenic patients relative to normal individuals. Our investigation suggests that schizophrenia-associated NRG1 and ErbB4 mRNA elevations also occur at the protein level and may be specific to schizophrenia. We hypothesize that ErbB4 proteolytic processing may also be altered in schizophrenia, yielding altered ratios of functionally distinct forms of ErbB4. Published by Elsevier B.V(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Beltaifa, Senda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Shannon Weickert, Cynthia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Thompson, Mia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Webster, Maree J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chong, Victor Z</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Law, Amanda J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La neurregulina 1 (NRG1) y su receptor, ErbB4, se han implicado en la esquizofrenia tanto a nivel genético como de transcripción. En la presente investigación se compararon los niveles de proteína NRG1 y ErbB4 en las fracciones citoplasmática y nuclear de tejido de la corteza prefrontal (CPF) entre individuos sanos, esquizofrénicos, con trastorno bipolar y con depresión mayor procedentes del Stanley Consortium. Utilizamos procedimientos de inmunotransferencia para examinar las posibles bandas inmunorreactivas de NRG1 y ErbB4, pero cuantificamos específicamente las señales inmunorreactivas de NRG1 a 42, 48 y 5kDa y las de ErbB4 a 21, 55, 60 y 180kDa. Se identificó un aumento significativo (alrededor del 20%) de los niveles de proteína NRG1 citoplasmática de 53kDa en CPF de pacientes esquizofrénicos en comparación con los otros grupos de sujetos. También detectamos efectos diagnósticos sobre los niveles de proteína ErbB4 citoplasmática (180kDa) en su forma entera en CPF, y las pruebas post hoc revelaron que estas cantidades eran significativamente mayores (alrededor del 30%) en pacientes esquizofrénicos en comparación con los sanos y lo deprimidos. Además, en fracciones de CPF examinamos los niveles de los posibles productos de la hidrólisis de ErbB4 a 21, 55 y 60kDa en comparación con ErbB4 citoplasmático en su forma entera. Detectamos tendencias de efectos diagnósticos sobre los cocientes citoplasmáticos 21kDa/180kDa y 55kDa/180kDa en CPF y las pruebas post hoc revelaron que estos cocientes eran significativamente más bajos en pacientes esquizofrénicos en comparación con los individuos sanos. La presente investigación sugiere que los aumentos de ARNm de NRG1 y ErbB4 también se producen a nivel proteico y podrían ser específicos de la esquizofrenia. Formulamos la hipótesis de que en esta enfermedad también podría estar alterado el procesamiento proteolítico de ErbB4, lo que depararía una alteración de los cocientes de las formas funcionalmente diferentes de este receptor(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);17(2): 54-62, abr.-jun. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79840</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aumento de los valores de las proteínas neurregulina 1 y ErbB4 en la corteza prefrontal de pacientes esquizofrénicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34465^s22065</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30601^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3610^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30601^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1714^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3610^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1714^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1824^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34465</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34465^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
