<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91452</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of individual differences in faking</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In recent years, change scores obtained under neutral conditions and under faking-inducing conditions have become one of the main alternatives for operationalizing faking. A pending issue regarding these measures is the relevance of individual differences under similar conditions of pressure. This study proposes a simple approach based on the classic test theory that allows the issue to be rigorously assessed. The approach, from which three indices are derived, is based on a pre-test post-test design with a control group, and models the amount of change as an individual parameter. The proposal is applied to an empirical study in personality, and some interesting initial results are obtained (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferrando Piera, Pere Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Anguiano Carrasco, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos años, las puntuaciones de cambio obtenidas entre condiciones neutrales y condiciones de presión se han convertido en una de las principales alternativas para medir el falseamiento. Una importante cuestión aún pendiente relacionada con dichas puntuaciones es la relevancia de las diferencias individuales cuando las condiciones de presión son similares. El presente estudio propone un procedimiento, relativamente simple, y basado en la teoría clásica del test, para evaluar de forma rigurosa esta cuestión. El procedimiento, del que se derivan tres índices, se basa en un diseño pre-test post-test con grupo control y modela la magnitud de cambio como un parámetro individual. La propuesta se aplica en un estudio empírico en personalidad que proporciona resultados iniciales de interés (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);23(4): 839-844, oct.-dic. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91452</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de las diferencias individuales en falseamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10742^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7381</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
