<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110308</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cost-effectiveness analysis of fixed dose antihypertensive drugs</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The aim of this study is to compare the efficiency of different fixed-dose combinations of renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (RAAS) blockers and calcium channel blockers, to use it as a guide to assist the rational prescribing in antihypertensive therapy. Methods. The efficacy of each drug was obtained from intervention studies randomized, double-blind, made with these combinations and a utility-cost modeling from the model proposed and used by NICE. The perspective of our analysis is the National Health System and the time horizon is long enough to achieve therapeutic goals. Main outcome measures. Cost per mmHg reduction in BP, percentage of reduction necessary to achieve the therapeutic goals for hypertension control and cost, and finally quantity and quality of life gained with these treatments in patients with hypertension, diabetes. Results. We studied three fixed-dose combinations: amlodipine/olmesartán, amlodipine/valsartan and manidipine/delapril. The cost per mmHg systolic BP ranged from 24.93 to 12.34 &#128;/mmHg, and diastolic BP ranged from 34.24 to 18.76 &#128;/mmHg, depending on the drug used. For an initial value of 165mmHg systolic BP the most efficient treatment to achieve the therapeutic goal of hypertension control (&lt;140mmHg) is manidipine/delapril with a cost of 67.76 &#128;. The use of these drugs to control diabetic and hypertensive patients resulted in all cases being cost-effective (more effective and lower cost compared to &#147;no treatment&#148;). Manidipine/delapril showed the best relation cost-utility (1,970 &#128;/QALY (quality-adjusted life year)) followed by amlodipine/olmesartan and amlodipine/valsartan (2,087 and 2,237 &#128;/QALY, respectively)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Agua Soler, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morata García de la Puerta, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Ruiz, A. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ávila Lachica, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Divisón Garrote, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montesinos Gálvez, A. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Comparar la eficiencia de las combinaciones en dosis fijas del bloqueo del SRAA con antagonistas del calcio, para que sirva como guía de ayuda a la prescripción racional del tratamiento antihipertensivo. Metodología. La eficacia de cada uno de los medicamentos ha sido obtenida de los estudios de intervención aleatorizados, doble ciego, realizados con estas combinaciones y una modelización de coste utilidad a partir del modelo propuesto por el NICE. La perspectiva de nuestro análisis es la del Sistema Nacional de Salud y el horizonte temporal ha sido un tiempo suficiente para alcanzar objetivos terapéuticos. Mediciones principales Coste por mmHg de descenso de la PA; porcentaje de descenso necesario para alcanzar los objetivos terapéuticos de control de la HTA y su coste y, finalmente, cantidad y calidad de vida ganada con estos tratamientos en pacientes hipertensos-diabéticos. Resultados. Se estudiaron 3 combinaciones fijas: amlodipino/olmesartán, amlodipino/valsartán y manidipino/delapril. Respecto a la PAS el coste por mmHg de PA reducido osciló entre 24,93 y 12,34 &#128;/mmHg, y para la PAD los costes fueron de 34,24 y 18,76 &#128;/mmHg, dependiendo del fármaco empleado. Para una cifra inicial de PAS de 165mmHg hay 3 opciones terapéuticas que pueden alcanzar la cifra de objetivo terapéutico (&lt; 140mmHg), siendo la más eficiente manidipino/delapril con 67,76 &#128;. Estos fármacos fueron coste-efectivos respecto al no tratamiento en el control de pacientes hipertensos diabéticos. El medicamento que mostró mejor relación coste-utilidad fue manidipino/delapril (1.970 &#128;/AVAC) seguido de amlodipino/olmesartán y amlodipino/valsartán (2.087 y 2.237 &#128;/AVAC)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);39(2): 77-84, mar. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110308</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis coste-eficacia de los antihipertensivos en dosis fijas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31495^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31495^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3376^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31495^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3380^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
