<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129887</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Rhabdomyolysis and severe hepatotoxicity due to a drug-drug interaction between ritonavir and simvastatin. Could we use the most cost-effective statin in all human immunodeficiency virus-infected patients?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction Drugs like statins may induce rhabdomyolysis. Simvastatin and lovastat in have a high hepatic metabolism and their potential toxicity could be increased by interactions with other drugs that reduce their metabolism. Patients and methods A case-report is presented of an HIV-infected patient treated with antiretroviral drugs who developed a rhabdomyolysis-induced renal failure and liver toxicity when simvastatin was substituted for atorvastatin. A literature review is also presented. Results The patient required hospital admission and showed a favorable response after hydration and urine alkalinization. There were 4 additional cases published of which there was one death. Conclusions Drug-drug interactions can increase the risk of statin induced rhabdomyolysis. In order to evaluate them properly, physicians at all levels of clinical care should be aware of all drugs prescribed to their patients and the contraindicated combinations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pericas, Juan Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Letang, Emili</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bastida, Carla</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Also, Maria Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miró, Josep Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tuset , Montse</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción Una de las posibles etiologías de la rabdomiólisis son los fármacos, y entre ellos, las estatinas. Especialmente simvastatina y lovastatina tienen un elevado metabolismo hepático, por lo que están más sujetas a interacciones con otros fármacos que puedan reducir su metabolismo y aumentar su toxicidad. Pacientes y métodos Se describe un caso clínico de una paciente infectada por el VIH en tratamiento antirretroviral que desarrolló rabdomiólisis, insuficiencia renal y hepatotoxicidad grave tras la sustitución de atorvastatina por simvastatina. Se revisan los casos descritos en la literatura. Resultados La paciente requirió ingreso hospitalario y evolucionó favorablemente tras hidratación y alcalinización de la orina, recuperando su estado basal. Existen 4 casos publicados, de los cuales uno falleció. Conclusiones Las interacciones farmacológicas pueden aumentar el riesgo de rabdomiólisis por estatinas. Para evaluarlas es necesario que los facultativos de todos los niveles asistenciales conozcan todos los fármacos que reciben los pacientes y las asociaciones contraindicadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;32(9): 579-582, nov. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129887</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rabdomiólisis y hepatotoxicidad grave por interacción entre ritonavir y simvastatina. ¿Puede emplearse la estatina más coste-efectiva en todos los pacientes infectados por el virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33014^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33420^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12617^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38332^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53500^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4409</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201411</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
