<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165113</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality of school age children&#146;s diet influence in blood and anthropometric parameters related to health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Due to the global increase of overweight and obesity especially among youth and adolescents it is necessary to know what factors can help to fight against these diseases from an early age. The purpose of this study was to determine the quality of schoolchildren&#146;s diet and how it can influence blood and anthropometric parameters related to health. Methods: Personal (age, gender and birth date), anthropometric (weight, height, fat body mass, %fat body mass, lean body mass and bone weight), blood (glucose, cholesterol and triglycerides) and diet quality through KIDMED questionnaire data were collected. Results: These results showed that a high percentage of students have a poor quality diet or that could be improved (51.1%) being highest percentage in boys than girls (56% vs 46.1%). No differences were found in anthropometric and blood parameters among students with different levels of diet quality. Conclusions: Therefore, the quality of the diet was analysed independently in isolation so is not an indicator of change. It is necessary to know other related factors that could change these parameters (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Camacho-Cardeñosa, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olcina Camacho, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brazo-Sayavera, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Guardado, Ismael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Timón Andrada, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcos-Serrano, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camacho-Cardeñosa, Alba</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: Debido al aumento global del sobrepeso y la obesidad, especialmente entre jóvenes y adolescentes, se hace necesario conocer los factores modificables que pueden ayudar a combatir estas patologías desde una edad temprana. El objetivo de este estudio fue determinar la calidad de la dieta de escolares y ver su influencia en parámetros sanguíneos y antropométricos relacionados con la salud. Métodos: Se recogieron datos personales (edad, sexo y fecha de nacimiento), antropométricos (peso, talla, circunferencia de la cintura y circunferencia de la cadera, cantidad de masa grasa, %graso, cantidad de masa libre de grasa y peso óseo), sanguíneos (concentración de glucosa, colesterol y triglicéridos) y de calidad de la dieta a través del cuestionario KIDMED. Resultados: Los resultados demostraron que un porcentaje elevado de escolares tienen una dieta de mala calidad o que podría mejorarse (51,1%), siendo más elevado en niños que en niñas (56% vs 46,1%). No se encontraron diferencias significativas en los parámetros antropométricos y sanguíneos estudiados entre los escolares con diferentes niveles de calidad de la dieta. Conclusiones: La calidad de la dieta, analizada de forma independiente y aislada, no es un indicador de cambio; se necesitan conocer otros factores que de forma integrada puedan modificar estos parámetros (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;22(3): 0-0, jul.-sept. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165113</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de la calidad de la dieta de escolares sobre parámetros sanguíneos y antropométricos relacionados con la salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d16508^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2181^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35173</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56120</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50314</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55675</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
