<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108698</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Beginning of military nursing in the Spanish military aviation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">2011 marks the first century of the Spanish military aviation, since 1911 is considered its initial year. The objective of this study is to present the first military nursing professionals that carried out their jobs in the health care of the early Spanish Air Force. The development of this study presents a basic historiographic story, linking the evolutions of health care and the Spanish military aviation, and covering the early professionals of nursing in aviation units back in 1928 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Saumell Bonet, Jaime E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez González, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velo Serrano, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Davó Devesa, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernabé Jiménez, Héctor</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se ha recordado en 2011 el centenario de la aviación militar española, al considerarse 1911 como el año que marca su inicio. El objetivo de este trabajo ha sido presentar a los primeros profesionales de enfermería militares que desempeñaron su cometido en la atención al personal de la aviación militar española. En el desarrollo del trabajo se ha tratado de conformar un relato historiográfico básico que entrelazara la evolución de la enfermería y la aviación militar en España, documentando los primeros profesionales de enfermería militares en unidades de aviación en 1928 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;16(33): 30-37, mayo-ago. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108698</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inicios de la enfermería militar en la aviación militar española</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9076^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11799</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6835</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1371</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51708</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
