<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98972</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Labor accidents in the province of Malaga. Participation of the ethyl alcohol and the drugs of abuse</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This work corresponds to a descriptive observational study of work accidents occurred in the province of Malaga between October 2003 and December 2006, resulting in death and which were autopsied in the Institute of Legal Medicine of Malaga. We have analyzed all those circumstantial variables that, in one way or another, play a role in the pathogenesis of these lesions, emphasizing in the participation of ethyl alcohol and drug abuse. We described 17 cases positive to ethylic alcohol, cannabis or cocaine and the absence of safety measures in the worker. All this with the purpose of establishing a few behavior guidelines which as far as possible, may help to anticipate, and even to diminish the number of this type of accidents that, unfortunately, in full 21stcentury are still very high (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Agua Soler, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Ruiz, Sebastián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Socias, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Campoy, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente trabajo se corresponde con un estudio observacional descriptivo de los accidentes de trabajo ocurrido en la provincia de Málaga entre Octubre de 2003 y Diciembre de 2006, con resultado de muerte y que fueron autopsiados en el Instituto de Medicina Legal de Málaga. En él hemos analizado todas aquellas variables circunstanciales que, de una forma u otra, desempeñan algún papel en la etiopatogenia de este tipo de lesiones, haciendo hincapié en la participación del alcohol etílico y las drogas de abuso. Se describen 17 casos positivos a alcohol etílico, cannabis o cocaína y destácala ausencia de medidas de seguridad en el trabajador. Todo ello con la finalidad de establecer unas pautas de conducta que permitan, en la medida de lo posible, ayudar a prevenir e incluso a disminuir el número de estos accidentes que, por desgracia, en pleno siglo XXI se vienen cobrando todos los años un número no desechable de vidas humanas, con la tragedia que ello supone (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;57(224): 242-255, jul.-sept. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98972</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Accidentes laborales en la provincia de Málaga. Participación del alcohol etílico y las drogas de abuso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29063^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13018^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23892^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1352^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
