<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96833</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-0740</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Placental abruption as a complication of the external cephalic version: a case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In 3-4% of the pregnancies that reach term, the baby is in breech presentation.The external cephalic version (ECV) is a procedure used forturning a baby from a breech or transverse position to a cephalic position. This procedure is a simple, effective and safe method; hence it frequently avoids the need for performing caesarean sections. For this reason, several prestigious international societies highly recommend theuse of this technique. We present a case report where a 37-week firsttimemother underwent a successful ECV procedure, however a placental abruption occurred, consequently an urgent caesarean section was carried out. The follow up of both, the mother and the new born, were normal and they were discharged four days after the surgery.The ECV is a simple and easy technique, however, it does not imply that clinicians should not act with extreme caution while performing this technique in order to avoid secondary complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Picado, Amanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, Henar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerra, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el 3-4% de los embarazos a término, el feto se encuentra en presentación podálica. La versión cefálica externa (VCE) es una maniobra que se utiliza para convertir una presentación podálica o transversa en una presentación cefálica. Por su sencillez, eficacia y seguridad, es un método avalado por diversas sociedades de prestigio internacional. Exponemos el caso de una primípara de 37 semanas de gestación a la que se le realizó de manera programada una VCE con éxito, pero que concluyó con un desprendimiento de placenta y una cesárea de urgencia. La evolución de la madre y el niño fue normal y ambos fueron dados de alta 4 días después. La VCE es una técnica fácil y útil para disminuir el número de cesáreas pero no está exenta de riesgos, por lo que es fundamental contar con un equipo sanitario experimentado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Matronas prof;12(2): 54-57, abr.-jun. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96833</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desprendimiento de placenta como complicación de la versión cefálica externa: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15114^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1971</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d40</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15114^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
