<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101737</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neonatal hyperinsulinism due to new mutation of ABCCS gene with evolution towards hypoinsulinemic diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The have been described recently activating mutations in ABCC8 and KCNJ11 genes that are related wyth  hypoglycemic hyperinsulinism that subsequently change to hypoinsulinemic diabetes. We present a case of congenital neonatal hyperinsulinism caused by a new mutation in ABCC8 gene that changed to a hypoinsulinemic diabetes after 4 years of evolution. A macrosomic female newborn with severe hypoglycaemia and hyperinsulinemia with good response to diazoxide was followed in our Unit. Subsequently the patient remains compensated and the medication could be discontinued without symptoms of relapses of hypoglycaemia. Along the period of evolution and when the patient suffered intercurrent infectious episodes she showed tendency to present with low glycemia but without of documented hypoglycaemia, hyperinsulinemia or ketosis that did not respond to medication. When she was 5 years old the patient developed glucose intolerance with postprandial hyperglycaemia nad with an oral glucose tolerance curve compatible with hypoinsulinemic diabetes mellitus. Genetic analysis showed Thr1515Ala mutation in heterozygosis in exon 37 of the ABCC8 gene responsible of coding SUR1 protein that has not been previously described. The possible mechanisms involved in the modification of the clinical phenotype from an state of hyperinsulinemic hypoglicaemia to a state of hypoinsulinemia and diabetes are discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Baldellou Vázquez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Rigual, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez de Nanclares Leal, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rebage Moisés, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Iñiguez, J. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armendáriz Cuevas, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lou Francés, G. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Labarta Aipuz, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Jiménez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Marín, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Recientemente se han descrito mutaciones activadoras de los genes ABCC8 y KCNJ11 causantes de hiperinsulinismo hipoglucémico seguido del desarrollo de una diabetes hipoinsulínica posterior. Se presenta un caso de hiperinsulinismo congénito neonatal por nueva mutación el gen ABCC8 con evolución hacia una diabetes hipoinsulínica al cabo de cuatro caos de evolución. Se trata de una recién nacida macrosómica afecta de hiperinsulinismo con una expresión clínica importante ya que inicialmente presentaba hipoglucemias e hiperinsulinemias severas con buena respuesta al diazóxido. Posteriormente fue estabilizándose la situación metabólica, llegando a retirarse la medicación sin apenas recaídas importantes. A continuación y coincidiendo con procesos infecciosos intercurrentes, se apreciaba tendencia a descender las glucemias sin llegar a presentar hipoglucemias e hiperinsulinemias francas y sin cetosis, que no respondieron a la medicación. Finalmente, a los cinco años de edad aparece una intolerancia a la glucosa con hiperglucemias postprandiales y una sobrecarga oral de glucosa patológica indicativa de una evolución a diabetes mellitus hipoinsulínica. Se detectó la mutación Thr1515Ala en heterocigosis en el exón 37 del gen ABCC8 responsable de la codificación de la proteína SUR1 que no hemos encontrado descrita en la literatura revisada. Se discute el posible mecanismo por la cual se pasa de un estado de hiperinsulinismo hipoglucémico  a hipoinsulinismo o diabetes hipoinsulínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;68(1): 53-58, ene.-feb. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101737</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hiperinsulinimso neonatal por nueva mutación del gen ABBCC8 con evolución hacia diabetes hipoinsulínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d38055^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9346</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31437^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7127^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4010^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19165^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
