<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97839</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Health planning in rheumatic diseases. Elaboration of a master plan for rheumatic and musculoskeletal diseases of Catalonia</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Surís, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puente, María Luisa de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pueyo, María J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Auleda, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larrosa, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Background: Rheumatic diseases (RDs) are among the most common chronic health problems of the Catalan adult population. They cause important problems for individuals, their families and for the society overall, with high direct and indirect economic costs. The Department of Health of Catalonia promoted the creation of a Master Plan for the rheumatic diseases, as a tool for planning an integral approach to these problems. Objective: To present the work methodology that has been used in the development of the Master Plan and its final proposals. Methods: First an analysis of the burden caused by these problems in our community was performed and the objectives of the Plan were established. Later, strategic lines were defined and work groups organized to analyze proposals for improvement, which after consensus were accepted. Results: The proposals of the Plan comprise actions in the scope of prevention, rationalization in the use of resources and the formation of professionals among others. Changes in the health care model for RDs were proposed in order to improve specialized and primary care coordination with clinics and musculoskeletal functional units. Conclusions: The Master Plan recommends actions to improve the attention of the population through operative planning and the services to different providers. The Master Plan will establish the health policy action lines directed against these disorders(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);8(2): 72-77, mar.-abr.2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97839</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Planificación en enfermedades reumáticas. Elaboración del Plan director de las enfermedades reumáticas y del aparato locomotor de Cataluñaa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28302^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12630^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6908^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28302^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12630^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6436^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6436^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6436^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
