<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162104</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Local anesthesia with sedation as elective procedure in day ucise groin hernioplasty: quick postoperative recovery, high security and saving resources</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Local anesthesia with sedation (LAS) is the &#145;gold standar&#146; anesthetic technique in open groin hernioplasty, even if raquidea anesthesia (RA) is actually the most frequent anesthesia technique at the moment. LAS could contribute several advantages in this procedure especially in day case surgery. The main goal of this report is to show the benefits of LAS for groin hernioplasty regarding postoperative recovery times and outcomes in an only outpatient surgery unit. Material and methods: A 25 LAS group and a 25 RA group were enrolled in this observational retrospective comparative study. The clinical status (ASA), anesthetic technique, the Postanesthetic recovery Unit (PARU) recovery time, time before discharge, and time required to normal activity were compared. Any postoperative outcome was recorded. Results: All patients were operated as planned. Recovery times were shorter in the LAS group. Outcomes were more infrequent as well less severe in the LAS group. Conclusion: This report demonstrates that LAS is the most suitable anesthetic technique for unilateral open groin herniorraphy in Day case (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palos Campos, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arance García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Estévez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cordero Lorenzo, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Archilla, AM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Docobo Durántez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La anestesia local con sedación (ALS) se considera la técnica &#145;gold estándar&#146; en la hernioplastia inguinal unilateral abierta, a pesar de que la anestesia raquídea (AR) sigue siendo la técnica más empleada en la práctica clínica diaria. La ALS parece aportar importantes ventajas con respecto a la AR, especialmente en el ámbito de la cirugía sin ingreso (CSI). El objetivo de este trabajo es demostrar los beneficios de ALS frente a AR en la hernioplastia inguinal en cuanto a los tiempos postoperatorios y las complicaciones postoperatorias en una unidad quirúrgica que realiza el 100 % de su actividad en régimen de Cirugía Mayor Ambulatoria (CMA). Material y método: 25 pacientes sometidos a hernioplastia inguinal con ALS y 25 con AR fueron incluidos en un estudio observacional retrospectivo comparativo. El estado clínico (ASA), el tipo de anestesia, los tiempos de recuperación en la Unidad de Recuperación Postanestésica (URPA), en la Unidad de Readaptación al Medio (URM) y durante su convalecencia en domicilio fueron comparados. Se registró cualquier complicación detectada en el periodo postoperatorio hasta el alta definitiva en ambos grupos. Resultados: Todos los pacientes fueron intervenidos según lo previsto. El tiempo de estancia media en URPA y URM, así como el tiempo transcurrido para recuperar la actividad normal tras la intervención, fueron significativamente inferiores en el grupo ALS. Las complicaciones fueron menos frecuentes y menos severas en el grupo ALS. Conclusión: Este trabajo afianza la ALS como técnica más adecuada que la AR para la intervención de hernia inguinal unilateral abierta en régimen de CMA (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;22(1): 10-14, ene.-mar. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162104</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La anestesia local con sedación como técnica de primera elección en la cirugía de hernia inguinal en régimen ambulatorio: rápida recuperación postoperatoria, alta seguridad y optimización de recursos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11621^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52865^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54711^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6711^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d783^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
