<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054951</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical variability and characteristics of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder in girls</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) is a neurobiological condition essentially characterised        by inattention, hyperactivity and impulsiveness, and has a prevalence of around 5%. Because it is a biological disorder, both        boys and girls with ADHD display these same symptoms, but more boys are diagnosed with ADHD (in a ratio of 3 to 1). Aim.        To examine the differences between the two sexes, their prevalence and possible female subtypes in ADHD. Patients and        methods. We conducted a retrospective study of 172 patients of both sexes who were attended as hospital neuropaediatric        outpatients in the year 2004 according to Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders (DSM-IV-TR) criteria. Their        ages ranged between 4 and 14 years and they were divided into three groups: under 6, between 6 and 10, and from 11 to 14        years old. The girls were subdivided into four subtypes, in order of greater to lesser prevalence: shy, hypersociable, hyperactive        and changeable. Results. Both sexes showed the same response to methylphenidate. Only the group of boys presented        other comorbidities such as negativism and conduct disorders; approximately 25% of them required treatment with atypical        neuroleptic drugs. Conclusions. a) Girls have certain specific clinical manifestations within the three common symptoms; b)        methylphenidate is equally effective in both sexes; c) only boys display other disorders such as negativism and conduct        disorders; and d) the brains of males and females are quite similar, but symptoms are expressed differently depending on        environments and levels</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valdizán, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mercado-Undanivia, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mercado, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El trastorno por déficit de atención/hiperactividad (TDAH) es una entidad neurobiológica caracterizada        fundamentalmente por la inatención, la hiperactividad y la impulsividad y tiene una prevalencia aproximada del 5%. Al        ser una alteración biológica, tanto niños como niñas con TDAH presentan estos mismos síntomas, pero se diagnostican más        varones con TDAH (en una proporción de 3 a 1). Objetivo. Comprobar las diferencias entre ambos sexos, su prevalencia y los        posibles subtipos femeninos en el TDAH. Pacientes y métodos. Estudio retrospectivo de 172 pacientes de ambos sexos, atendidos        en consulta externa de neuropediatría hospitalaria en el año 2004 según los criterios del Manual diagnóstico y estadístico        de los trastornos mentales (DSM-IV-TR), con edades comprendidas entre los 4 y los 14 años de edad y divididas éstas en        tres grupos: menos de 6 años, entre 6 y 10 años y de 11 a 14 años. Las niñas se subdividieron en cuatro subtipos según el        orden de mayor a menor prevalencia: tímida, hipersociable, hiperactiva y cambiante. Resultados. Ambos sexos tuvieron igual        respuesta al metilfenidato. Sólo el grupo de los chicos presenta otras comorbilidades como negativismo y trastornos de conducta;        de ellos, un 25% aproximadamente necesitó un tratamiento con neurolépticos atípicos. Conclusiones. a) Las niñas tienen        unas manifestaciones clínicas específicas bajo los tres síntomas comunes; b) El metilfenidato es igual de eficaz en ambos;        c) Los niños son los únicos que muestran otros trastornos como negativismo y problemas de conducta; y d) El cerebro de mujeres        y hombres es bastante similar, pero la expresión de los síntomas es distinta dependiendo de los ambientes y los niveles</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;44(supl.2): S27-S30, mar. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054951</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características y variabilidad clínica del trastorno por déficit de atención/hiperactividad en niñas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
