<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104820</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Risk factors of bloodstream infections associated with parenteral nutrition in pediatric patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: One of the complications of parenteral nutrition (PN) is bloodstream infection (BSI) associated with catheter, unknown the most important risk factors in our country. Objective: To determine risk factors of BSI associated with PN in pediatric patients in public hospitals of Santiago, Chile. Patients and methods: In two public hospitals all newborns and children receiving PN were analyzed retrospectively, from January 2002 to December 2005. The study group (SG) was formed by all those with blood cultures (+) during the administration of PN. We selected two controls for each case, children with PN and blood cultures (-) (control group, CG). We used parametric, nonparametric and logistic regression to analyze data. Results: There were 58 cases and 130 controls. Children of the SG received PN for longer days than CG: 24 (7-934) vs. 10 days (7-152) (p &lt; 0.001), presented a higher rate of malnutrition (44.4% vs. 31%, chi2, p &lt; 0.05) and received more frequently PN by central venous catheter than peripheral catheter (GE: 60.3% and 6.9% vs. GC: 40.9% and 16.9% respectively, chi2, p &lt; 0.01), without differences between newborns and older children. The stepwise logistic regression showed that the only significant variable was the duration of PN in weeks (OR: 1.55,95% CI 1.28 to 1.9; p &lt; 0,05). Conclusions: The blood stream infections associated with parenteral nutrition in children in public hospitals of Santiago, are associated with longer duration of parenteral nutrition and in less degree to the child's nutritional compromise (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Balboa Cardemil, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo Durán, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Una de las complicaciones de la nutrición parenteral (NP) es la infección sanguínea (IS) asociada a catéter, se desconoce los factores de riesgo más importantes en nuestro medio. Objetivo: Determinar los factores de riesgo de las IS asociadas a NP en pacientes pediátricos en hospitales de Santiago de Chile. Pacientes y métodos: En 2 hospitales públicos se analizaron retrospectivamente todos los recién nacidos (RN) y niños que recibieron NP entre enero del 2002 y diciembre del 2005. El grupo estudio (GE) son todos aquellos con hemocultivos (+) durante la administración de NP. El grupo control (GC) correspondió a 2 controles por cada caso, niños con NP y hemocultivos (-). Para el análisis estadístico se usaron pruebas paramétricas, no paramétricas y regresión logística. Resultados: Se obtuvieron 58 casos y 130 controles. Los niños del GE recibieron NP por más tiempo que GC: 24 (7-934) vs 10 días (7-152) (p &lt; 0,001); presentaban mayor desnutrición (44,4% vs 31%, chi2; p &lt; 0,05) y recibieron con mayor frecuencia NP por un CVC que uno periférico (GE: 60,3% y 6,9% vs GC: 40,9% y 16,9% respectivamente, chi2; p &lt; 0,01); sin diferencias entre RN y niños mayores. La regresión logística paso a paso demostró que la única variable significativa fue la duración de NP en semanas (OR: 1,55; IC 95% 1,28-1,9; p &lt; 0,05). Conclusiones: Las infecciones sanguíneas asociadas a nutrición parenteral en niños de hospitales públicos de Santiago, están asociadas a mayor duración de la nutrición parenteral y en menor grado al compromiso nutricional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;26(6): 1428-1424, nov.-dic. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104820</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores de riesgo de infecciones del tracto sanguíneo asociadasa alimentación parenteral en pacientes pediátricos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53052^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30401^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23583^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
