<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136212</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Juvenile Angiofibroma</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Alobid, Isam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guilemany, José-María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernal-Sprekelsen, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Juvenile angiofibroma (JA) is a benign tumor associated with young males. Recent studies have associated JA with genetic changes, while others suggest that this entity is a vascular malformation. These tumors grow through slowly progressive local extension,  starting at the basisphenoid and the sphenopalatine foramen. Invasion into the infratemporal fossa, the cavernous sinus or intracranial region may occur. The vascular supply comes mainly from the internal maxillary artery. There are no typical symptoms; however, unilateral nasal obstruction and recurrent epistaxis are present. Computed tomography scan and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) are required to assess tumoral extension and to plan the surgical approach. MRI is mandatory to assess tumoral recurrence during follow-up. In the last decade a change in the surgical paradigm has taken place. Most authors now consider Fisch stages I and II to be removable by the endoscopic approach and some authors even use this approach with type IIIA tumors. The recurrence rate is lower with the endoscopic approach than with external approaches. Thus, the high morbidity associated with external approaches has been considerably reduced, and these approaches are now reserved for extensive JA. Preoperative embolization diminishes intraoperative bleeding, enabling piecemeal resection. Rates of recurrence or persistence have not been increased by endoscopic procedures.  The present article provides an overview of JA and discusses our own results with endoscopic approaches, as well as those of other authors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;58(supl.1): 84-95, oct. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136212</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Angiofibroma juvenil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31656^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6409^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31656^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24794^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28002^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31656^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24794^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6409^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28002^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
