<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113799</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Antifungal prophylaxis in the postoperative period of lung transplant surgery in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives To examine the type and duration of antifungal prophylaxis provided during the postoperative period of lung transplant recipients, together with the most frequent complications during admission to Intensive Care Units in Spain. Patients and methods A questionnaire was developed including demographic data on each transplant center, the type of antifungal prophylaxis used, its duration, and the most frequent complications. The questionnaire was distributed among the 7 Spanish national lung transplant centers, followed by analysis of the results obtained. Results All 7 centers completed the questionnaire. All of them provided universal prophylaxis in lung transplant patients. Monotherapy was the most widely used protocol (5/7; 71.4%), with amphotericin B in liposomal or conventional form being the most frequent drug, administered via the inhalatory route. In the case of combination therapy, a great diversity of drugs was observed. The most frequently administered second choice drug was anidulafungin (3/7; 43%), followed by voriconazole (2/7; 28.5%). Antifungal therapy was maintained on an indefinite basis by 43% of the centers. Invasive fungal infection (IFI) in the postoperative period of transplantation during admission to the Intensive Care Unit was suspected in 5-10% of the cases but was confirmed in less than 5%.Among other complications registered in these patients in the Intensive Care Unit, the most frequent problems were respiratory infections (5/7; 71.5%).Conclusions Antifungal prophylaxis during the postoperative period of lung transplantation is provided on a universal basis, though consensus is lacking as to the drug of choice, the administration route and the duration of such treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Network PLUTO (Postoperative Lung Transplantation)</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos Analizar qué tipo de profilaxis antifúngica se realiza durante el postoperatorio a los receptores de un trasplante de pulmón, la duración y las complicaciones más frecuentes durante la estancia en las unidades de críticos de España. Pacientes y métodos Se elaboró una encuesta que incluía datos demográficos de cada centro trasplantador, tipo de profilaxis antifúngica, duración y complicaciones más frecuentes. Se distribuyó a los 7 centros nacionales con programas de trasplante pulmonar y posteriormente fue analizada. Resultados Los 7 centros contestaron a la encuesta. Todos ellos realizan profilaxis universal en los trasplantados pulmonares. La monoterapia es la modalidad más utilizada (5/7; 71,4%), siendo la anfotericina B en forma liposomal o convencional el fármaco más utilizado, administrándose por vía inhalatoria. Si se realiza terapia combinada existe una gran diversidad en cuanto a los fármacos utilizados. Si se recurre a un fármaco como segunda elección el más utilizado es la anidulafungina (3/7; 43%), seguido del voriconazol (2/7; 28,5%). El 43% de los centros mantienen la profilaxis antifúngica de forma indefinida. Al analizar la incidencia de la infección fúngica invasiva (IFI) en el postoperatorio del trasplante durante su estancia en las unidades de críticos se evidenció en un 5-10% como diagnóstico de sospecha pero documentándose en menos de un 5%.Entre otras complicaciones que presentan estos pacientes en las unidades de críticos se observa que las más frecuentes son las infecciones respiratorias (5/7; 71,5%).Conclusiones Se realiza profilaxis antifúngica durante el postoperatorio de un trasplante pulmonar de forma universal pero no existe un consenso sobre el fármaco de elección, la vía de administración y la duración de la misma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);37(3): 201-205, abr. 2013. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113799</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Profilaxis antifúngica en el postoperatorio de trasplante de pulmón en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29477^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
