<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145224</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Coordintating between the renal transplant unit and the non-transplant nephrology department</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Patients with stabilized kidney transplant receive optimal management care when there is effective coordination between the transplant centre and the community nephrologist (Evidence level C). A good coordination with regular interactive communication between the transplant centre and community nephrologist is very positive for patients and beneficial to the transplant centre and community nephrologist (Evidence level C). Many of the clinical objectives for management of kidney transplant recipients are similar to those related to chronic kidney disease patients (Evidence level C). A good coordination between the transplant centre and community nephrologist needs organizational requirements and clinical management protocols (Evidence level C). When irreversible renal allograft failure occurs, the community nephrologist must assume the preparation for dialysis as with other patients with advanced chronic kidney disease: choose dialysis methods, create arteriovenous fistulae or place peritoneal catheter and identify dialysis treatment centre. Moreover, the transplant centre and the community nephrologist will jointly decide the best moment to start dialysis or the possibility of preemptive kidney transplant (Evidence level C) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oppenheimer, Federico</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campistol, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Alba,  Thaïs</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García García, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El paciente con trasplante renal estabilizado recibe un manejo clínico óptimo del sistema sanitario cuando se coordinan las Unidades de trasplante renal (UTR) con los Servicios de Nefrología del hospital de referencia (nivel de evidencia C). La buena coordinación entre las UTR y los Servicios de Nefrología del hospital de referencia supone ventajas para el paciente y tiene interés para el Servicio de Nefrología y la UTR (nivel de evidencia C). Muchos de los objetivos clínicos del paciente trasplantado renal son similares a los del paciente con insuficiencia renal crónica (IRC) controlado en los Servicios de Nefrología de los hospitales de referencia (nivel de evidencia C). La buena coordinación entre la UTR y el Servicio de Nefrología precisa requerimientos organizativos y protocolización del manejo clínico compartido (nivel de evidencia C). Cuando comienza a desarrollarse el fracaso irreversible del injerto renal, el Servicio de Nefrología del hospital de referencia debe ofrecer la preparación para la diálisis como al resto de pacientes con IRC avanzada: elección de la técnica de diálisis, realización de fístula arteriovenosa o catéter peritoneal según el caso, e identificación del centro de tratamiento. Asimismo, habrá que decidir conjuntamente con la UTR el mejor momento para empezar la diálisis o, incluso, si el paciente se puede beneficiar de un trasplante renal anticipado que hiciera innecesario el ingreso en diálisis (nivel de evidencia C) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;29(supl.1): 72-77, 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145224</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Coordinación entre unidad de trasplante renal y servicio de nefrología no trasplantador</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6913^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9591</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200900</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
