<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110148</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Primary, non-metastatic gastrointestinal stromal tumour surgery: Results of the GRISK study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: Radical surgery is the standard treatment for localised gastrointestinal stromal tumours (GIST). A series of primary GIST, their treatment and pre-established risk of recurrence after their follow-up is evaluated. Material and methods: A retrospective, descriptive and multicentre study was conducted on primary, non-metastatic GIST operated on between June 2007 and December 2008. The variables of greater relevance were analysed, including, location, size, mitotic index, and NHI and AFIP recurrence prognostic criteria, and their correlation with the disease-free survival (DFS) of the patients. Results: The series included 141 patients with a mean age of 65 years. The most frequent GIST location was in the stomach (70.8%) and small intestine (22.9%), and with a mean tumour size of 6.7 cm (0.5-35 cm). The surgery was R0 in 97.2% of cases ( laparoscopic approach, 21.5%). The distribution according to NHI/Flescher criteria was, high (31.95%),and intermediate (26.4%), and according to AFIP/Miettinen criteria it was, high (22.9%) and intermediate (12.5%). After a mean follow-up of 20.3 months, there was a 7.1% (10 cases)recurrence, with only 2 cases belonging to the group with a «low risk» using the NHI and AFIP prognostic criteria. The DFS at one year was 95.5% and 91.5% at 2 years. Conclusions: The series showed a high DFS and a good correlation with both the Flescher and the Miettinen criteria. However, the risk of recurrence varied according to the AFIP criteria(intermediate/high, 58.3%), or the AFIP criteria (intermediate/high, 35.4%) which included the tumour location. For this reason, we consider these latter criteria as the most adequate for assessing the prognostic risk of GIST recurrence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Artigas Raventós, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lucena de la Poza, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Pousa, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Medina, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz de Liaño Argüelles, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Hernández, Juan Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La cirugía radical es el tratamiento estándar en el GIST primario localizado. Se valora una serie de GIST primarios, su tratamiento y el riesgo preestablecido de recaída tras seguimiento de los mismos. Material y métodos Estudio retrospectivo multicéntrico y descriptivo de GIST primarios no metastásicos intervenidos entre junio de 2007 y diciembre de 2008. Se analizan las variables de mayor relevancia: localización, tamaño, índice mitótico y criterios pronóstico de recidiva NHI y AFIP y su correlación con la supervivencia libre de enfermedad (SLE) de los pacientes. Resultados Serie de 141 pacientes, edad media 65 años, con GIST de localización más frecuente en estómago (70,8%) e intestino delgado (22,9%) y con tamaño medio tumoral de 6,7cm (0,5-35). La cirugía fue R0 en el 97,2% de los casos (abordaje laparoscópico 21,5%). Distribución según criterios de NHI/Flescher: alto (31,95) e intermedio (26,4%), y según criterios AFIP/Miettinen: alto (22,9%) e intermedio (12,5%). Tras un seguimiento medio de 20,3 meses se detectó recaída en 7,1% (10 casos) perteneciendo tan solo 2 casos al grupo de «bajo riesgo» por criterios pronóstico NHI y AFIP. La SLE a un año fue del 95,5% y a los 2 años del 91,5%.ConclusionesLa serie mostró una alta SLE y una buena correlación con los criterios pronóstico tanto de Flescher como de Mietinen. No obstante, el riesgo de recaída varió siguiendo los criterios de NIH (intermedio/alto 58,3%) o los criterios de AFIP (intermedio/alto 35,4%) que incluyen la localización del tumor. Por ello consideramos estos últimos criterios como los más adecuados para la valoración prónostica de riesgo de recidiva del GIST (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);91(2): 96-102, feb. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110148</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cirugía de los tumores del estroma gastrointestinal primarios no metastásicos. Resultados del estudio GRISK</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9557^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38616^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7577^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13662^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38616^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
