<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85970</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Scheuermann's disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present two cases of two patients diagnosed Scheuermann's disease after a detailed anamnesis and complete physical examination, and with the help of a simple conventional radiology. This is usually a casual finding as most patients are often asymptomatic, but in both cases there was a persistent dorsal-lumbar pain initially attributed to work effort or poor posture, which made them go to the family doctor. Initially, the radiological findings are irregularities in the upper of most or all of the vertebrae, sclerosis and formation of cartilaginous nodules in a lateral x-ray projection. In some cases where the lesions are progressing, it is noted that the vertebrae become wedge-shaped, so that the normal dorsal kyphosis increases to a pathological level (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marcos Aldea, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baré Mañas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fabra Noguera, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilà Moneny, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos dos casos clínicos de dos pacientes diagnosticados después de una detenida anamnesis y exploración física completa, y con la ayuda de una simple radiología convencional, de enfermedad de Scheuermann. Habitualmente es un hallazgo casual, pues la mayoría de las veces son pacientes asintomáticos, pero, en estos dos casos es a raíz de un dolor dorsal-lumbar persistente, inicialmente atribuido a esfuerzo en el trabajo o a una mala postura, que al persistir les hace acudir al médico de familia. Inicialmente los hallazgos radiológicos consisten en irregularidades del margen superior de la mayoría o de todas las vértebras, esclerosis y formación de nódulos cartilaginosos en una proyección radiológica lateral. En los casos en los que las lesiones progresan, se observa que las vértebras adquieren forma de cuña, de tal manera que la cifosis dorsal normal aumenta a un grado patológico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);37(2): 93-95, feb. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85970</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad de Scheuermann</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8657^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12927^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12927^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8657^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12927^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10200^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10185^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13505^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10185^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10200^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13505^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
