<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120671</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Errors and myths in feeding and nutrition: Impact on the problems of obesity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The increase in obesity prevalence cannot be explained by a sudden and generalized change in human genome. It is certainly due to the modification of lifestyle habits and especially of the diet, as well as a lack of physical activity and sedentary living. Changes in the feeding pattern and the subsequent unbalance in the caloric profile of the diet may have had great importance in the occurrence of obesity. &amp;#8232;The social pressure in relation to the body image, the desire to have a slim body, and the fear to gain weight present in the current society have given way to the proliferation of myths and errors regarding pretentiously weight-losing foods and the appearance of miracle diets and dietary complements with magic results on weight loss. Weight-losing foods such as grapefruit, pineapple, apple, cucumber, wholemeal bread or drinking water while fasting are among the most popular and with less scientific evidence errors and myths. On the other hand, miracle diets cause more harm than good and their success is based on weight loss, but not fat loss, since they initially induce dehydration and a decrease in the muscle mass. The intervention study described here shows, once again, that when someone takes a hypocaloric diet he/she will lose weight and that the supplements tried with a satiating, lipolytic and supposedly weight-losing effect do not modify the weight loss produced by the hypocaloric diet. The main therapeutic tools available to fight against obesity are dietary therapy, which is a must in the program, education and behaviour modification, increased physical activity, to fight against sedendarism, and some pharmacological therapy available. The best solution to all these problems that have a great repercussion on the society surely is the development of wide and prolonged informational and educational campaigns in the field of nutrition (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zamora Navarro, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Llamas, Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El aumento de la prevalencia de obesidad no podría ser explicada por un cambio repentino y generalizado en el genoma de la población. Sin duda, se debe a la modificación de los hábitos de vida y, especialmente, de la alimentación, así como a la falta de actividad física y a la vida sedentaria. Los cambios en el modelo de alimentación y el consecuente desequilibrio en el perfil calórico de la dieta pueden haber tenido gran importancia en la aparición de la obesidad La presión social en relación con la imagen corporal, el deseo de poseer cuerpos estilizados y el miedo a engordar presentes en la sociedad actual, han dado lugar a la proliferación de mitos y errores sobre alimentos supuestamente adelgazantes, a la aparición de dietas milagrosas y de complementos dietéticos con resultados mágicos sobre la pérdida de peso. Entre los errores y mitos más extendidos y con evidencia científica se incluyen alimentos que supuestamente adelgazan, como pomelo, piña, manzana, pepino, pan integral, o beber agua en ayunas. Por otro lado, las dietas milagrosas provocan más perjuicios que beneficios, su éxito radica en la pérdida de peso, que no de grasa, pues inicialmente producen deshidratación y disminución de la masa muscular. El estudio de intervención descrito en este capítulo, demuestra, una vez más, que cuando un individuo ingiere una dieta hipocalórica pierde peso, y que los suplementos con efectos saciantes y lipolíticos ensayados, supuestamente adelgazantes, no modifican la pérdida de peso producida por la dieta hipocalórica. Las principales herramientas terapéuticas de las que se dispone para luchar contra la obesidad son el tratamiento dietético, base irrenunciable de la terapia, la educación y modificación de la conducta, el incremento de la actividad física, la lucha contra el sedentarismo y la escasísima terapia farmacológica disponible. La mejor solución frente a todos estos problemas, de una gran repercusión para la sociedad, es sin duda el desarrollo de amplias y duraderas campañas de información y formación en el campo de la nutrición (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;28(supl.5): 81-88, sept. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120671</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Errores y mitos en alimentación y nutrición: impacto en la problemática de la obesidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52939^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9422</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32738^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1541</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4071</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
