<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036852</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pediatrics in Uruguay. A brief outline</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article describes them main features on the Health Services in Uruguay. A brief analysis is done on the social-historic context in which the modern Uruguay and the original sanitary structures are developed. The main demographic and epidemiological characteristics and their tendencies throughout the XX century are described. Public and private Health Care subsectors are described. With very different costs, and so with very different resources, they achieve obviously different results. Main tendencies in the private subsector are analyzed. It ends with a Decalogue of the system "pathologies" and the lines that should be followed to achieve universality and equity</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Portillo Rodríguez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se hacen una breve reseña histórica, social y política del país y un breve análisis del contexto socio-histórico en el cual se constituyen el Uruguay moderno y la conformación original de la atención sanitaria. Se analizan de forma comparative los principales indicadores sanitarios y demográficos. Se describen las principales características de los servicios de Atención a la Salud de Uruguay. Se presentan los subsectores público y privado, responsables de la atención a la salud de la población. Cada uno de ellos, con gasto muy diferente y, por lo tanto, con recursos muy diferentes, logra resultados obviamente distintos. Se concluye con un decálogo de "patologías" del sistema y se sugieren las líneas que debieron recorrerse para el logro de la universalidad y la equidad en la atención a la salud</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;7(25): 115-127, ene.-mar. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036852</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La pediatría en Uruguay. Una breve reseña</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30585^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14985</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20208^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33543^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30598^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
