<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81787</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-8831</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cost-effectiveness analysis of the administration of palivizumab as prophylaxis of severe bronchiolitis due to respiratory syncytial virus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Several clinical trials of palivizumab have shown a decrease of hospitalizations for severe respiratory syncytial virus infection. However, its high price makes it necessary for an evaluation to be done. Objective. The objective of this study was to assess the efficacy of the administration of palivizumab on the prophylaxis of severe bronchiolitis related to respiratory syncytial virus. Method. A cost-effectiveness analysis was performed by means of a decision analysis model. We used a payer perspective, a one-year and life expectancy time horizon, and a 3% discount rate. Direct costs were included (drug, administration, and hospital admission), and several sensitivity analyses were performed. Results. Incremental cost-effectiveness ratios obtained were between 17,337.10 and 68,380.77 &#128; per avoided hospitalization, and between 166,721.18 and 1,476,568.81 &#128; per life year gained. For premature infants younger than 32 weeks of gestational age, the price of a 3-dose treatment should be 400 &#128; (133.33 &#128; per dose) to obtain a ratio lower than 30,000 &#128; per life year gained; the price of a 3-dose treatment should be 140.08 &#128; (46.69 &#128; per dose) to obtain a ratio cheaper than the cost of a 5 in-hospital days. Conclusions. Even in the most favorable scenario, the cost of the treatment with palivizumab is much higher than the cost of a complete hospitalization episode, and the incremental cost per life year gained is much higher than commonly accepted thresholds(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Altés, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pons, Joan M. V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paladio, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tebé, Cristian</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. Existen diversos ensayos clínicos sobre el palivizumab que muestran una reducción de las hospitalizaciones en niños a Anàlisi cost-efectivitat de l&#146;administració del palivizumab en la profilaxi de les bronquiolitis greus per virus respiratori sincicial Anna García-Altés 1,2,3, Núria Paladio 3,4, Cristian Tebé 3,4, Joan M.V. Pons 3,4 1 Fundación Instituto de Investigación en Servicios de Salud. 2 Agència de Salut Pública de Barcelona. 3 CIBER Epidemiología y Salud Pública (CIBERESP). 4 Agència d&#146;Avaluació Tecnologia i Recerca Mèdiques. Barcelona riesgo de infección grave por virus respiratorio sincitial. Sin embargo, su alto precio de venta al público hace que sea necesaria su evaluación. Objetivo. El objetivo de este estudio es analizar la eficiencia de la administración del palivizumab en la profilaxis de las bronquiolitis graves por virus respiratorio sincitial. Método. Se ha realizado un análisis coste-efectividad de la administración del palivizumab mediante un modelo de análisis de decisiones. La perspectiva de análisis utilizada es la del financiador, el horizonte temporal de 1 año y de toda la esperanza de vida de los niños, y la tasa de descuento del 3%. Se han incluido los costes directos (fármaco, administración e ingreso hospitalario) y se han realizado diversos análisis de sensibilidad. Resultados. Las ratios coste-efectividad incrementales obtenidos están entre 17.337,10 y 68.380,77 &#128;/ingreso evitado, y entre 166.721,18 y 1.476.568,81 &#128;/año de vida ganado. Para los prematuros menores o iguales a 32 semanas de edad gestacional, el precio de un tratamiento de tres dosis tendría que ser de 400 &#128; (133,33 &#128; por dosis) para obtener una ratio inferior a 30.000 &#128;/año de vida ganado; el precio de un tratamiento de tres dosis tendría que ser de 140,08 &#128; (46,69 &#128; por dosis) para que la ratio sea menor que el coste de 5 días de ingreso hospitalario. Conclusiones. Incluso en el caso más favorable, el coste del tratamiento con palivizumab es muy superior al de todo el ingreso hospitalario y el coste incremental por año de vida ganado es muy superior a los umbrales comúnmente aceptados(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. catalan;70(2): 57-64, mar.-abr. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81787</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis coste-efectividad de la administración del palivizumab en la profilaxis de las bronquiolitis graves por virus respiratorio sincitial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22851^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31081^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31081^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30313^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30313^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30313^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22851^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30313^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
