<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118920</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish adaptation of Yamagishi General Trust Scale</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The significance that trust has in social exchange relationships has led to a growing amount of literature dealing with this phenomenon at a theoretical and an applied level. With the aim of conducting trust research by means of an instrument with established reliability and validity, the General Trust Scale (Yamagishi &amp; Yamagishi, 1994) was translated into Spanish. The sample comprised 626 participants. Results indicate that the Spanish adaptation has satisfactory psychometric properties: test's reliability (&amp;#945; =.862) and items' discrimination (a &amp;#8805; 1.58). There was no differential item functioning regarding the participants&#146; gender, but differences aroused as regards to their age. The relationship with several dispositional and behavioral variables was assessed, being significant its correlation with agreeableness (r =.376) and, for the women, also with Openness to Experience (r =.135) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Molina, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montoro, Alejandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Román, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Shih, Pei-Chun</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La confianza es, por su importancia en las relaciones sociales, un fenómeno de gran interés tanto a nivel teórico como aplicado. En este articulo presentamos la adaptación al castellano de uno de los instrumentos más utilizados en el investigación sobre confianza: la Escala de Confianza General de Yamagishi &amp; Yamagishi (1994). Un total de 626 participantes respondieron al cuestionario. Los resultados indican que las propiedades psicométricas de la versión en castellano son satisfactorias tanto a nivel de escala (&amp;#945; =.862) como a nivel de items (a &amp;#8805; 1.58). No se observo funcionamiento diferencial de los items respecto al sexo, si respecto a la edad. En cuanto a la relación entre la medida de Confianza y otras variables disposicionales y conductuales, se obtuvieron correlaciones significativas con Cordialidad (r = .376), y en mujeres también con Apertura a la Experiencia (r = .135) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;30(1): 302-307, ene.-abr. 2014. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118920</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación al castellano de la Escala de Confianza General de Yamagishi</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37622^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
