<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125476</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5735</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The residences for persons with Several Mental Disorder as a Therapeutic-Rehabilitation resource</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The development of housing places for people with SMD is becoming an important factor in the consolidation of community care in mental health. Residences should be considered as a psychosocial rehabilitation place, modifying a dysfunctional psychosocial situation that negatively affects quality of life and social integration of the patient. In this line arises the present study in order to assess the evolution of the residents admitted to Roger de Llúria, Begur and Tres Pins residences (managed by the Mental Health Foundation CPB) in its first two years of admission to the mental health centre and being able to define improvement aspects on users. Material and Method: From an initial sample of 88 residents (admitted during the years 2009-2011). Comparing the variations during the required time of psychiatric admission, use of community rehabilitation resources, clinical stability, performing ADLs and quality of life (social and personal), taking as values the collected information during the year preceding their incorporation into the residence and the two years of relationship. Results: We could affirm that staying at residences favours users&#146; clinical stability, reducing the number of admissions and their length of stay. The resident improves in ADLs functioning, health habits and personal relationships, regaining his citizen ship status, more active and self-sufficient. The improvement in social and occupational residents adjustment is reflected in the increasing of rehabilitation resources used and a greater participation in community life (both inside and outside the residence) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, Bibiana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vegué Grilló, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrats Alabau, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Córdoba, M. Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lascorz Fierro, David</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El desarrollo de lugares de vida para personas con TMG está significando un factor importante en la consolidación de la atención comunitaria en Salud Mental. Las residencias deben considerarse como un lugar de rehabilitación psicosocial, al modificar una situación psicosocial disfuncional que influye negativamente en la calidad de vida y en la integración social del paciente. En esta línea se plantea el presente estudio con El objetivo: de evaluar la evolución de los residentes ingresados en las residencias Roger de Llúria, Tres Pins y Begur, (gestionadas por la Fundación de Salud Mental CPB), en sus dos primeros años de ingreso y poder definir los aspectos de mejoría en los usuarios. Material y Método: La muestra inicial es de 88 personas (usuarios ingresados durante los años. (2009- 2011). Se comparan las variaciones en el tiempo de ingreso psiquiátrico, la utilización de recursos de rehabilitación comunitaria, la estabilidad clínica, la realización de Actividades de la Vida Diaria (AVD) y la calidad de vida (desarrollo personal y social); tomando como valorares la información recogida durante el año anterior a su incorporación a la residencia y a los dos años de vinculación. Resultados y Conclusiones: Se puede afirmar que la estancia en las residencies favorece la estabilidad clínica del usuario, reduciendo el número de ingresos y su tiempo de estancia. El residente mejora en el funcionamiento general en las AVD, hábitos de salud y relaciones personales, recuperando su estatus de ciudadano, más activo y autónomo. La mejora en el ajuste social y ocupacional se refleja en el aumento de recursos de rehabilitación utilizados y la mayor participación en la vida comunitaria (tanto dentro como fuera de la residencia) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Neuropsiquiatr;34(123): 521-538, jul.-sept. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125476</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las residencias para personas con Trastorno Mental Grave como un recurso Terapéutico-Rehabilitador</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13036^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6934^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12467^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12468^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12467^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6445^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13036^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
