<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145392</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical utility and psychometric properties of Prefrontal Symptoms Inventory (PSI) in acquired brain injury and degenerative dementias</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The cognitive, emotional and behavioural alterations secondary to acquired brain injury and degenerative dementias can be quantitatively and quantitatively appraised by administering self-reports that ask both patients and reliable informants about the difficulties patients have in their everyday life. Subjects and methods. The Prefrontal Symptoms Inventory (PSI) and the Modified Memory Failures in Everyday Life Questionnaire (MFE-30) were administered to 174 paired participants: 87 patients with brain damage or degenerative dementias and their 87 reliable informants. In addition to the psychometric goodness of the tests, the study also explored the clinical usefulness of applying these questionnaires to patients and their informants in order to obtain a rate of discrepancy in the scores as a measure of anosognosia. Results. The results show how applying the PSI-20 (20 items) or the PSI (46 items), whether administered together with the MFE-30 (30 items) or not, is a very useful procedure for assessing the symptoms in individuals with acquired brain injury or degenerative dementias, since it yields a great deal of information about patients&#146; difficulties in their daily life. Conclusions. We recommend that, in addition to the compulsory neuropsychological assessment, questionnaires or inventories of symptoms like those proposed here should be carried out, due to the fact that they offer a number of advantages from the clinical point of view, as well as being efficacious and effective in economic terms (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Sánchez de León, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedrero Pérez, Eduardo J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Méndez, Laura M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozoya Delgado, Paz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gálvez, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las alteraciones cognitivas, emocionales y comportamentales secundarias al daño cerebral adquirido y las demencias degenerativas pueden valorarse cuantitativa y cualitativamente mediante la administración de autoinformes que interroguen &#150;a pacientes e informadores fiables&#150; sobre las dificultades de los pacientes en la vida cotidiana. Sujetos y métodos. Se administró el inventario de síntomas prefrontales (ISP) y el cuestionario de fallos de memoria en la vida cotidiana modificado (MFE-30) a 174 participantes emparejados: 87 pacientes con daño cerebral o demencias degenerativas y sus 87 informadores fiables. Se exploró, junto con la bondad psicométrica de las pruebas, la utilidad clínica de la aplicación de estos cuestionarios a pacientes e informadores para obtener un índice de discrepancia de las puntuaciones como medida de la anosognosia. Resultados. Los resultados muestran cómo aplicar el ISP-20 (20 ítems) o el ISP (46 ítems), sean o no administrados conjuntamente con el MFE-30 (30 ítems), resulta un procedimiento muy útil para la valoración de la sintomatología en los individuos con daño cerebral adquirido o demencias degenerativas, al proporcionar una gran cantidad de información sobre las dificultades de los pacientes en la vida cotidiana. Conclusiones. Se recomienda, junto con la obligada evaluación neuropsicológica, la cumplimentación de cuestionarios o inventarios de síntomas como los propuestos, dado que presentan ventajas desde el punto de vista clínico, además de resultar eficaces, efectivos y eficientes en términos económicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;61(9): 387-394, 1 nov., 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145392</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad clínica y propiedades psicométricas del inventario de síntomas prefrontales (ISP) en el daño cerebral adquirido y las demencias degenerativas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3008^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30601^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1951^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30601^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8838^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8838^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1951^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1951^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3008^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
