<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-168664</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Actividad de la telomerasa en pacientes en etapas de 2-5D con enfermedad renal crónica</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Molecular mechanisms of increased cardiovascular mortality in chronic kidney disease (CKD) associated with biological age are not well understood. Recent studies support the hypothesis that common factors responsible for this phenomenon are cellular aging and telomere dysfunction. Objectives: The purpose of this study was to investigate the relation between telomerase activity and CKD stages. Methods: The study included 120 patients who were followed-up for CKD stage 2-5D, composed of 30 patients of each stage and 30 healthy volunteers without any known disease who were admitted to our hospital for routine check-ups. Telomerase activity in peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC) was measured using the TRAP assay. Results: A significant difference was observed for telomerase activity in PBMC between groups. The detected levels were lowest in the healthy control group (0.15±0.02), and highest in CKD stage 5D patients (0.23±0.04). In CKD patients, telomerase activity in PBMC was positively correlated with the CKD stage, serum creatinine, potassium and parathormone levels, and negatively correlated with estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR), body mass index (BMI), platelet count and serum calcium levels. According to the linear regression analysis, independent predictors for high telomerase activity in CKD patients were eGFR and BMI. Conclusion: Telomerase activity in PBMC increases with advancing CKD stage in CKD patients. Increased telomerase activity in PBMC is associated with eGFR and BMI(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aynali, Ayse</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aridogan, Buket</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Inal, Salih</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kidir , Veysel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Altuntas, Atila</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tugrul Sezer, Mehmet</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: Los mecanismos moleculares responsables del aumento de la mortalidad cardiovascular en la enfermedad renal crónica (ERC) asociada a la edad biológica no se conocen bien. Los estudios recientes apoyan la hipótesis de que los factores comunes responsables de este fenómeno son el envejecimiento celular y la disfunción telomérica. Objetivos: El objetivo de este estudio fue investigar la relación entre la actividad de la enzima telomerasa y los estadios de ERC. Métodos: El estudio incluyó a 120 pacientes que fueron seguidos para la ERC en los estadios 2-5D; cada estadio incluyó a 30 pacientes y a 30 voluntarios sanos sin ninguna enfermedad conocida que fueron admitidos en nuestro hospital para los controles periódicos. La actividad de la telomerasa en células mononucleares de sangre periférica (CMSP) se midió usando el método de TRAP. Resultados: Se observó una diferencia significativa en la actividad telomerasa en las CMSP entre los diferentes grupos. Los niveles más bajos fueron los del grupo de controles sanos (0,15±0,02) y los más altos los del grupo de pacientes con ERC en el estadio 5D (0,23±0,04). En los pacientes con ERC, la actividad telomerasa en las CMSP se correlacionó positivamente con el estadio de ERC y los niveles plasmáticos de potasio, hormona paratiroidea y creatinina, y se correlacionó negativamente con la tasa de filtración glomerular estimada (eTFG), el índice de masa corporal (IMC), el recuento de plaquetas y el calcio en suero. Los predictores independientes para la actividad telomerasa alta en pacientes con ERC fueron la eTFG y el IMC, de acuerdo con el análisis de regresión lineal. Conclusión: La actividad telomerasa en CMSP aumenta con el avance en el estadio de ERC. El aumento de la actividad telomerasa en CMSP se asocia con la eTFG y el IMC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;37(6): 592-597, nov.-dic. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-168664</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Telomerase activity in patients with stage 2-5D chronic kidney disease</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32593^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32593^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
