<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121365</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Needs and Attitudes of Primary Care Physicians coping with Administrative Management of Occupational Diseases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Goals: Since 2007 Spanish legislation mandates primary care physicians to report suspected occupational diseases for the purpose of occupational disease surveillance by the Social Security system. This paper presents the sensibility, attitudes and knowledge needs they express about the occupational origin of these conditions. Methods: We analyzed texts and commentaries generated by students and teachers who joined two different editions of an online course, "Occupational Diseases for Primary Care Physicians", developed on electronic campus of the National School of Occupational Health (Institute of Health Carlos III) promoted and funded by the Ministry of Health, among others. Results: Participants expressed concerns regarding to: i) their lack of specific knowledge, ii) the absence of items in electronic medical records that could facilitate the detection of possible work-related pathologies; and iii) limited communication among the various stakeholders. Conclusions: Primary care physicians expressed interest in learning more about how to establish the work-relatedness of disease, and offer suggestions aimed at improving their fund of knowledge, facilitating their access to expert consultation, highlighting the occupational exposure component of the medical history in primary care, and improving communication among all stakeholders (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Figueroa, M. Josefa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Cid, Matilde</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gamo-González, M. Fe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delclós-Clanchet, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Desde 2007 la normativa relativa a la gestión por la Seguridad Social de las Enfermedades Profesionales y al sistema de información para su vigilancia epidemiológica, asigna a los médicos en Atención Primaria un papel como comunicadores a partir de su "sospecha diagnóstica". Este trabajo pretende mostrar algunas de sus necesidades expresadas en relación al conocimiento específico y sus actitudes y sensibilización en su práctica cotidiana respecto al origen laboral de estas patologías. Métodos: Para ello, hemos analizado los textos generados en la interacción entre los alumnos y tutores participantes en 2 ediciones de un curso online ("Enfermedades Profesionales para Médicos de Atención Primaria") realizado sobre el campus electrónico de la Escuela Nacional de Medicina del Trabajo del Instituto de Salud Carlos III, promovido y financiado por el Ministerio de Sanidad, entre otros. Resultados: Los participantes expresan su inquietud en relación con: i) su falta de conocimientos específicos, ii) la carencia de utilidades o instrumentos habilitados en las historias clínicas informatizadas para orientarles en el diagnóstico de procesos "presumiblemente" laborales, y iii) los problemas de comunicación entre los actores del sistema. Conclusiones: Destacamos su interés por saber cómo establecer el origen laboral de algunos procesos en un sentido amplio, más allá de la determinación de Enfermedad Profesional, y cómo apuntan soluciones que contemplarían: aumentar sus conocimientos, facilitarles el asesoramiento por expertos, hacer más visible lo laboral en la historia clínica de atención primaria y habilitar canales de comunicación eficaces con el resto de implicados en la gestión de las enfermedades profesionales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;59(233): 393-404, oct.-dic. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121365</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Necesidades y actitudes de los facultativos de Atención Primaria frente a la gestión de las enfermedades profesionales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32818^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55139^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
