<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139099</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of thought stopping and cognitive defusion on discomfort and the ability to deal with negative thoughts</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Modern behavioral therapies have claimed that thought stopping is an ineffective technique. This study compares the effectiveness of thought stopping and cognitive defusion on self-reported discomfort and the ability to deal with negative thoughts. 60 participants were randomly assigned to three groups: thought stopping, cognitive defusion and control group. Results from our study indicate that both techniques significantly reduced self-reported discomfort compared to the control group and there were significant differences between techniques in self-perceived ability to deal with thoughts and in self-perceived usefulness, with better results for thought stopping. Our results support that thought stopping, if properly trained, is at least as efficient as cognitive defusion. The authors discuss the mechanisms underlying both techniques and highlight the relevance of functional analysis to select the techniques to be applied to deal with negative thoughts (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calero Elvira, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernánez marcos, Tatiana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las nuevas terapias conductuales han criticado la eficacia de la detención del pensamiento. En este estudio se compara la eficacia de la detención del pensamiento y la defusion cognitiva sobre el malestar informado y el manejo de los pensamientos negativos. Los 60 participantes fueron asignados aleatoriamente a tres grupos: detención del pensamiento, defusion cognitiva o grupo control. Encontramos que ambas técnicas reducían significativamente el malestar informado en comparación con el grupo control y que existían diferencias significativas entre ambas técnicas en capacidad para manejar los pensamientos y en utilidad percibida, con mejores resultados para la detención del pensamiento. Se concluye que la detención del pensamiento es al menos tan eficaz como la defusion cognitiva, si es entrenada adecuadamente en sesión. Se discuten los mecanismos de funcionamiento y se resalta la importancia de considerar el análisis funcional para seleccionar las técnicas aplicadas para el manejo de pensamientos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;23(1): 107-126, ene.-abr. 2015. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139099</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de la detención del pensamiento y la defusión cognitiva sobre el malestar y el manejo de los pensamientos negativos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9534</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9955</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29210</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14230</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
