<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126372</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hemodynamic monitoring in the critically patient. Recomendations of the Cardiological Intensive Care and CPR Working Group of the Spanish Society of Intensive Care and Coronary Units</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hemodynamic monitoring offers valuable information on cardiovascular performance in the critically ill, and has become a fundamental tool in the diagnostic approach and in the therapy guidance of those patients presenting with tissue hypoperfusion. From introduction of the pulmonary artery catheter to the latest less invasive technologies, hemodynamic monitoring has been surrounded by many questions regarding its usefulness and its ultimate impact on patient prognosis. The Cardiological Intensive Care and CPR Working Group (GTCIC-RCP)of the Spanish Society of Intensive Care and Coronary Units (SEMICYUC) has recently impulse the development of an updating series in hemodynamic monitoring. Now, a final series of recommendations are presented in order to analyze essential issues in hemodynamics, with the purpose of becoming a useful tool for residents and critical care practitioners involved in the daily management of critically ill patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grupo de Trabajo de Cuidados Intensivos Cardiológicos y RCP de la SEMICYUC</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La monitorización hemodinámica nos permite obtener información sobre el funcionalismo cardiovascular del paciente crítico, por lo que constituye una pieza fundamental en la aproximación diagnóstica y en la guía terapéutica del paciente con hipoperfusión tisular. Desde la aparición del catéter de arteria pulmonar hasta el desarrollo reciente de tecnologías mínimamente invasivas, la monitorización hemodinámica se ha rodeado de interrogantes en cuanto a su utilidad y su impacto final sobre el pronóstico de nuestros pacientes. El Grupo de Trabajo de Cuidados Intensivos Cardiológicos y RCP (GTCIC y RCP) de la SEMICYUC ha impulsado recientemente la realización de la serie de «Puesta al día en monitorización hemodinámica» y ha querido además desarrollar unas recomendaciones que pretenden analizar cuestiones fundamentales en la valoración cardiovascular del paciente crítico, con la intención final de ser una herramienta útil para residentes, intensivistas y otros profesionales que afrontan el manejo diario de estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);38(3): 154-169, abr. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126372</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Monitorización hemodinámica en el paciente crítico. Recomendaciones del Grupo de Trabajo de Cuidados Intensivos Cardiológicos y RCP de la Sociedad Española de Medicina Intensiva, Crítica y Unidades Coronarias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2361</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30213^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53214^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6590^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9183^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
