<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140247</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Newborn Screening in the Autonomous Community of Aragon. Practical Guidelines</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Early detection screening programs for metabolic, endocrine and congenital diseases are conducted in all autonomous communities, thus reducing the morbimortality and disabilities associated, by detecting diseases that present no clinical symptoms at the time of birth but subsequently, and which will leave major neurological consequences if not diagnosed and treated on time. This is an easy technique, conducted by nurses, but which requires adequate training, because there are still claims by newborn screening labs regarding the reception of poorly impregnated samples, where the volume of blood absorption cannot be ensured, either due to insufficient sample or inadequate soaking. The objective of this article is to review the technique of sample collection, in order to contribute to improving the knowledge of nurses regarding the newborn heel prick, for an improvement in the quality of the blood drop samples obtained (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vaz Rodríguez, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Estrella, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En todas las comunidades autónomas se llevan a cabo programas  de detección precoz de enfermedades metabólicas, endocrinas y congénitas, reduciéndose así la morbimortalidad y discapacidades asociadas al detectarse enfermedades que no se manifiestan clínicamente en el momento del nacimiento, sino que lo hacen posteriormente y que, si no son diagnosticadas y tratadas a tiempo, dejan secuelas neurológicas importantes. Se trata de una técnica sencilla realizada por enfermeras/os, pero para la que se precisa de una formación adecuada, dado que todavía se refiere por parte de los laboratorios de cribado neonatal la recepción de muestras mal impregnadas, en las que no puede asegurarse el volumen absorbido de sangre, bien por muestra insuficiente o inadecuadamente embebida. El objetivo de este artículo es revisar la técnica de recogida de muestras a fin de contribuir a mejorar el conocimiento de enfermeros/as en cuanto a la punción del talón del recién nacido para mejorar la calidad de las muestras de gotas de sangre obtenidas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;18(6): 58-62, jul.-ago. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140247</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cribado neonatal en la Comunidad Autónoma de Aragón. Guía práctica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4782^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29480^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23957^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8836^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
