<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131448</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Venipuncture versus heel puncture for metabolic screening in newborns</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to explore the efficacy of heel puncture and venipuncture procedures for conducting metabolic screening tests in newborns. Method: bibliographic search of research articles and reviews addressing the objectives posed, both in Spanish and in English, without any time limitation. The following databases were used: Cochrane Library, Pubmed, Uptodate, Embase, Fisterra, Scielo, Cuiden, Cuidatge, Tripdatabase, Bandolier, the Elservier platform, and Encuentra. Results: according to the literature reviewed, the test duration and number of punctures necessary were also lower with venipuncture. There were no differences in terms of number of cases with false positive results. Pain scores were lower in venipuncture than in heel puncture, from a statistic point of view. The procedure duration is three times longer for heel puncture. Conclusions: according to the results obtained, venipuncture is more effective than heel puncture for conducting metabolic screening in newborns, because it causes less pain, less injuries, a lower number of punctures, less time is required for the test, and no differences in terms of false positive results have been observed. A change in protocol should be considered, and blood extraction should be conducted by venipuncture instead of heel puncture, because there is higher scientific support for the former (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valero Alcón Enfermera, Vanessa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: explorar la eficacia de los procedimientos de punción en el talón y punción venosa para la realización de la prueba de cribado metabólico en el recién nacido. Método: búsqueda bibliográfica de trabajos de investigación y revisiones que abordaran los objetivos planteados, tanto en es-pañol como en inglés, sin límite temporal. Las bases de datos utilizadas fueron: Cochrane Library, Pubmed, Uptodate, Embase, Fisterra, Scielo, Cuiden, Cuidatge, Tripdatabase, Bandolier, la plataforma de Elsevier y la base de datos Encuentr@. Resultados: según la literatura revisada, la duración de la prueba y el número de pinchazos necesarios fueron también menores con la venopunción. No hubo diferencias en cuanto al número de casos con falsos positivos Las puntuaciones de dolor fueron inferiores desde el punto de vista estadístico en la venopunción frente a la punción del talón. La duración del procedimiento es tres veces más en la punción en el talón. Conclusiones: atendiendo a los resultados obtenidos, la punción venosa es más eficaz que la punción en el talón para la realización del cribado metabólico en recién nacidos, dado que pro-duce menos dolor, menos traumatismos, menor número de pin-chazos, menor tiempo requerido para la prueba y no se han observado diferencias en cuanto a los falsos positivos. Se debería considerar el cambiar el protocolo y realizar la extracción sanguínea mediante una venopunción en lugar de la punción del talón, puesto que es lo que mayor respaldo científico tiene (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;17(10): 24-27, dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131448</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Venopunción versus punción en el talón para el cribado metabólico en recién nacidos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29480^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32650^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24296^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8836^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
