<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73843</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evidence-based review of steroid therapy for back pain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the effectiveness of steroid injections associated or not with local anesthesia via the cervical, thoracic, lumbar or caudal epidural routes in cervical, thoracic, lumbar and sacral facet joints and spinal branches, as well as in the sacroiliac joint, in the treatment of back and upper and lower extremity pain. Material and methods: The following terms were used for the search: &#147;epidural steroid injections or blocks&#148;, &#147;caudal injections or blocks&#148;, &#147;selective nerve root injections or blocks&#148;, &#147;transforaminal injections or blocks&#148;, &#147;facet injections or blocks&#148;, &#147;medial nerve blocks&#148; and &#147;low back pain&#148;. The search was performed in the Trip Database, SUM Search, National Guidelines Clearinghouse, Cochrane and centers drawing up clinical practice guidelines. Clinical practice guidelines with levels of evidence, systematic reviews, meta-analyses and cross references among publications reviewed in Spanish or English from 1979 to 2009 were accepted. Results: Five clinical practice guidelines and nine systematic reviews were selected. Analysis of these articles indicated that intradiscal injections cannot be recommended in the treatment of chronic low back pain. The evidence on lumbar, cervical and thoracic medial branch injection in the treatment of lumbar, cervical and dorsal back pain is moderate for short&#151; and long-term improvement. The evidence for sacroiliac joint injection is limited. Cervical interlaminar epidural injection provides significant and prolonged relief in chronic intractable cervical pain. There is level II-2 evidence for lumbar interlaminar epidural steroid injection, without fluoroscopy, in providing short-term relief and level II evidence for long-term relief. Transforaminal epidural steroid injection is effective in post laminectomy syndrome (level IV evidence). There is moderate evidence for short&#151; and long-term improvement in cervical radicular pain...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Neira, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la efectividad de la infiltración con corticoides asociados o no a los anestésicos locales por vía epidural cervical, torácica, lumbar, caudal, en las facetas y ramas espinales cervicales, torácicas, lumbares y sacras, así como en la articulación sacroilíaca, en el tratamiento del dolor de espalda, y extremidades superiores e inferiores. Material y métodos: Los términos que se utilizaron para la búsqueda de la información fueron: &#147;epidural steroid injections o blocks&#148;, &#147;caudal injections o blocks&#148;, &#147;selectivenerve root injections o blocks&#148;, &#147;transforaminal injections o blocks&#148;, &#147;facet injections o blocks&#148;, &#147;medial nerve blocks&#148; y &#147;low back pain&#148;. Se realizó una búsqueda en: Trip Database,SUM Search, National Guidelines Clearing house, Cochrane y centros elaboradoresde guías de práctica clínica. Se aceptaron guías de práctica clínica con niveles de evidencia, revisiones sistemáticas, estudios metaanálisis y referencias cruzadas entre las publicaciones revisadas en español e inglés desde 1979 hasta 2009. Resultados: En la revisión se seleccionaron 5 guías de práctica clínica y 9 revisiones sistemáticas. De su análisis se desprende la recomendación de no realizar la infiltración intradiscal en el tratamiento de la lumbalgia crónica. La evidencia de la infiltración de la rama medial lumbar, cervical y torácica en el tratamiento de la lumbalgia, cervicalgia y dorsalgia es moderada a corto y a largo plazo. La evidencia de la infiltración intraarticular sacroilíaca es limitada. La infiltración epidural interlaminar cervical tiene un efecto significativo en el alivio del dolor crónico intratable de origen cervical y proporciona un alivio prolongado. La infiltración epidural lumbar interlaminar con corticoides, sin fluoroscopia, tienen un nivel de evidencia (NE) II-2 y un NE II en el alivio a largo plazo. La infiltración epidural transforaminal con corticoides es eficaz en el síndrome poslaminectomía (NE IV)...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;16(6): 352-359, ago. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73843</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión del tratamiento con corticoides en el dolor de espalda según la medicina basada en la evidencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30952^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
