<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136440</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0620</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Self-harm in children placed in a court-mandated holding and education centre. Analysis socio-demographic variables and influence of implementation of judicial measures</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To analyze and understand the existence of self-harming behavior in a holding centre for minors. Methods: Review of self-harm cases detected in a population of 94 inmates in 2013. Results: 26.5% of young offenders have conducted some form of self harm. 28% of individuals with self-harming behaviors have more than 6 episodes over the period of internment. Self-beating is the most common type of self-harm performed by this group. Inmates serving sentences in the therapeutic section tend to present spillover effects in terms of self-injury. Discussion: The population held in prison show higher percentages of self-harm than amongst the general population. The chosen type of behavior is determined by the institution. Inmates that present greater mental fragility tend to perform these behaviors and in greater number (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: conocer y analizar la existencia de conductas autolesivas en un centro de internamiento para menores. Material y métodos: revisión de los casos detectados de autolesión en una población de 94 internos durante el año 2013. Resultados: el 26.5% de los internados ha llevado a cabo algún tipo de autolesión. El 28% de los individuos con conductas autolesivas presentan más de 6 episodios durante el tiempo de internamiento. El auto-golpeo es la opción fundamentalmente llevada a cabo por esta población. Los internos que cumplen la medida en sección terapéutica tienden a presentar efectos de contagio en materia de autolesión. Discusión: La población internada en centro penitenciario presenta mayor porcentaje de autolesiones que la población general. El tipo de conducta elegida está condicionada por la institución. Los internos que presentan mayor fragilidad mental tienden a llevar a cabo estas conductas y de forma más numerosa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. sanid. penit;17(2): 54-60, jul.-oct. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136440</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las autolesiones en menores internados en un Centro de Educación e Internamiento por Medida Judicial. Análisis de las variables sociodemográficas e influencia del cumplimiento de la medida judicial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d378^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29822^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29822^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1545^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11765^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11765^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29822^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37730^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11765^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36414</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31499^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
