<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101489</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Outbreak of measles in the population of Spanish origin in North Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">After being virtually eradicated in Europe, thousands of cases of measles in the population of Spanish origin have appeared in the last 3 years. We describe the cases diagnosed in the north of Madrid between January and June 2011. A total of 22 cases are reported, 18 of them grouped in 2 outbreaks (2 nurseries). The primary attack rate was 29% in the main outbreak. All cases were in unvaccinated patients (median = 14 months). Genotype D4 was predominant (95%). There was a 45% complication rate and 45% were admitted to hospitals. The Public Health Service recommended isolating cases and vaccinating susceptible contacts in advance. Health Centres established a specific protocol to respond to suspected cases. The Measles vaccination has been brought forward from 15 to 12 months in Madrid. Measles is a re-emerging disease in Europe. The coordinated management between public health and health facilities is essential to limiting outbreaks(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baquero-Artigao, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tagarro García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santiago García, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Rodrigo, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Bueno, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piñeiro Pérez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Cid, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herreros Fernández, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mosquera, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañete Díaz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Gil, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cilleruelo Ortega, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agúndez Reigosa, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Tras estar prácticamente erradicado en Europa, en los últimos 3 años han aparecido miles de casos de sarampión autóctono. Se describen los casos ocurridos en la zona norte de Madrid (enero-junio de 2011).Se informa de 22 casos, 18 de ellos agrupados en 2 brotes (2 escuelas infantiles). La tasa de ataque del principal fue del 29%.Todos fueron en pacientes no vacunados (mediana=14 meses). El genotipo predominante fue el D4 (95%). Hubo un 45% de complicaciones y un 45% de ingresos. El Servicio de Salud Pública recomendó aislar a los casos y vacunó anticipadamente a los contactos susceptibles. En los centros sanitarios se estableció un circuito específico para atender a los casos sospechosos. Se ha adelantado la vacunación triple vírica de los 15 a los 12 meses en la Comunidad de Madrid. El sarampión es una enfermedad re-emergente en Europa. El manejo coordinado entre Salud Pública y los centros asistenciales es fundamental para limitar los brotes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);76(6): 350-354, jun. 2012. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101489</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Brote de 22 casos de sarampión autóctono en la zona norte de Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8626^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23113^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8626^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8626^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28589^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35372^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12959</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
