<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88615</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Encapsulation assessment workshop with training specialists</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It presents the evaluation of the reflexive learning that carry out the students of the course of specialization &#147;Specialist&#146;s Degree in Industrial and Galenic Pharmacy&#148;, of Barcelona (University of Barcelona)., concretely for the educational module of elaboration of capsules. In the module there are given theoretical classes (not evaluated) and practical classes (in Workshop format). The teachers in no case are tutors, but mediators and coordinators of the learning, intervene guiding the problems that are appearing during the practices. For the assessment of the efficiency of the teaching method uses four outputs corresponding to the completion of a test at the beginning of practices and at the end of the same, an evaluation survey by students, and another survey by evaluation of teachers. The test results show that the proposed methodology is appropriate to enhance the knowledge gained in theory. With regard to the satisfaction of students and teachers to this new methodology, in both cases has been high(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grupo Consolidado de Innovación Docente de Tecnología Farmacéutica, nº IV-52</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta la evaluación de dos años académicos del workshop sobre encapsulación que realizan los alumnos del curso de especialización Título de Especialista de Farmacia Industrial y Galénica, (TEFIG) de Barcelona (Universidad de Barcelona). En el módulo se imparten clases teóricas (no evaluadas) y clases prácticas a partir de la propuesta Workshops realizada por los profesores. Los profesores del workshop actúan como mediadores y coordinadores del aprendizaje, encauzando los problemas que van apareciendo durante las prácticas. Para la valoración de la eficiencia del método docente propuesto se utilizan cuatro outputs que corresponden a la realización de un test al inicio de las prácticas y al final de las mismas, una encuesta de valoración por parte de los alumnos, una encuesta de valoración por parte de los profesores. Los resultados obtenidos en el test demuestran que la metodología propuesta es adecuada para afianzar los conocimientos adquiridos en teoría. En cuanto a la satisfacción de los alumnos y profesores ante esta nueva metodología, en ambos casos ha sido alta(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;51(supl.2): 30-37, mayo 2010. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88615</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación del workshop de encapsulación con especialistas en formación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4591^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
