<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-67633</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Family has always been considered a key milestone for the development of the human psyche. Furthermore, in relationship with mental disorders we know that certain aspects of family environment change the course of some of these disorders. This study has aimed to compare the family sestting perception of schizophrenic patients vs. other psychotic patients, their first-degree relatives and to see if the expression of the disorder is related with that perception. Method. The study included 112 subjects: 41 patients, 41 first-degree relatives and 30 normal controls. Patients were included in the group of as schizophrenic (n = 24) or non-schizophrenic psychosis (n = 17) following DSM-IV criteria diagnosis using the SCAN interview and were evaluated with the Family Environment Scale (FES) and PANSS. Descriptive analysis, group comparisons and correlation studies were used as statistical methods. Results. No statistically significant differences were found when comparing FES between both group of patients, nor between patients and relatives, although psychotic patients presented a tendency to score higher on almost all the FES scales and dimensions. We found significantly positive correlations between patients and their own relatives in the FES scales. Conclusions. Although not with statistical significance, non-schizophrenic psychotic patients and the irrelatives have a slightly different family environment perception than their schizophrenic counterparts: more conflictivity; more rule strictness and more planning needs. High levels of expressed emotion were related with a predominance of positive symptoms in psychotic patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vidal, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Zotes, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Labad, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortés, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Desde siempre se ha considerado la familia como un pilar fundamental en el desarrollo de la psiquehumana; y en relación con los trastornos mentales sabemos que ciertos aspectos del ambiente familiar modulan el curso de algunos de estos trastornos. El objetivo de este estudio es comparar la percepción del clima familiar entre pacientes esquizofrénicos y pacientes con otras psicosis entre sus familiares de primer grado y ver si el ambiente familiar guarda relación con la expresión del trastorno. Método. Se estudia a 112 sujetos: 41 pacientes, 41 familiares de primer grado y 30 controles. Los pacientes fueron diagnosticados dentro del grupo de las esquizofrenias (n=24) o del grupo de las psicosis no esquizofrénicas (n=17) sobre la base de los criterios DSM-IV mediante SCAN y se les aplicó la FES y la PANSS. Se utilizó la estadística descriptiva, la comparación de grupos y el estudio de correlaciones. Resultados. No se observan diferencias significativas al comparar la FES entre ambos grupos de pacientes ni entre pacientes y familiares, aunque sí se observa una tendencia en los pacientes a puntuar más alto que sus familiares en la mayoría de escalas y dimensiones. Se obtienen correlaciones positivas significativas al estudiar el grado de asociación de las escalas de la FES entre pacientes y familiares. Conclusiones. Aunque de manera no estadísticamente significativa, los pacientes con psicosis funcionales no esquizofrénicas presentan una percepción del ambiente familiar distinto que los pacientes esquizofrénicos y sus familiares: más conflictividad, más rigurosidad en las reglas y más necesidad de planificación. Niveles elevados de emoción expresada guardan relación con el predominio de la sintomatología positiva en pacientes psicóticos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;36(5): 271-276, sept.-oct. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-67633</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23905^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33140^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12946</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33140^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d346^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5300^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
