<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93574</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5187</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New drugs in the therapy of T-cell cutaneous lymphoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There is currently no curative treatment of cutaneous lymphomas in advanced stages. Historically these patients have been treated with chemotherapyregimens used in systemic lymphomas usually very toxic and with limited benefits. With the growing knowledge about the pathogenesis of cutaneouslymphomas it has been able to identify therapeutic targets and to develop new molecules that currently are being tested with promising results. This isthe case of histone deacetylase inhibitors (IHDAC) and the new monoclonal antibodies, among others. In the same way it has been found that usefuldrugs in other tumors, such as gemcitabine, bortezomib and liposomal doxorubicin are also active in the LCP-T, at least in preliminary studies. In thelast years, new drugs and therapeutic strategies are being added to our arsenal with the purpose of changing the natural history of this disease. In thisarticle we review the therapeutic advances in this field (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Izu Belloso, R. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Ruiz, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amutio Díaz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">No existe actualmente ningún tratamiento curativo de los linfomas cutáneos en estadios avanzados. Históricamente estos pacientes han sido sometidosa esquemas de quimioterapia utilizados en linfomas sistémicos generalmente muy tóxicos, y de beneficios muy limitados. Gracias al crecienteconocimiento de la etiopatogenia de los linfomas cutáneos se han podido identificar dianas terapéuticas y desarrollar nuevas moléculas que se estánprobando en la actualidad con resultados esperanzadores. Este el caso de los inhibidores de las histonas desacetilasas (IHDAC) y los nuevos anticuerposmonoclonales, entre otros. De la misma forma ha podido observarse que fármacos útiles en otros tumores, como gemcitabina, bortezomib odoxorubicina liposomal, también son activos en los LCP-T, al menos, en estudios preliminares. En los últimos años se están añadiendo a nuestro arsenalnuevos medicamentos y estrategias terapéuticas encaminadas a cambiar la historia natural de esta enfermedad. En este artículo revisamos los avancesterapéuticos en este campo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. cután. ibero-lat-am;39(2): 69-79, mar.-abr. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93574</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevos fármacos en el tratamiento de los linfomas cutáneos de células T</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29030^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6816</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
