<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79300</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0620</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">¿Do drug using inmates have social support?. A case study in an andalusian prison</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims: To discover and compare the social support received by drug-dependent inmates in a drug free program and otherinmates participating in a methadone maintenance program (MMP).Materials and methods: Transversal descriptive observational study carried out at Albolote Prison (Granada).The prison population at the time of the study was 1,763 inmates. The drug addicts were divided into two groups: those ina methadone maintenance program (MMP, 279 inmates) and those participating in a drug free program (58 inmates). A randomsample of 60 inmates in the MMP was obtained. All the members of the drug free program participated. The two groups wereinterviewed to discover more about their family structure, socio-economic level and qualifications. The MOS social supportsurvey was also used in a self applied format with assistance from the interviewer. The percentages obtained from each dimensionof the MOS questionnaire for each group was compared using Pearson&#146;s chi-square test.Results: The social network of the MMP group was a mean 13.2. In the drug free group it was 12.9. Value of p= 0.0047.Global support was low amongst 38 individuals (74.5%) in the MMP group and 9 (15.62%) in the drug free program. It wasnormal amongst 13 subjects (25.5%) in the MMP group and amongst 49 (84.38%) in the drug free group. Value of p=0.0001. All the dimensions of the MOS social support survey are higher amongst the drug free group: there are statistically significantdifferences with the MMP group.Conclusions: Inmates in the drug free program have (and they perceive this to be the case) a greater degree of social supportthan participants in the MMP(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herrera-Jáimez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antón-Basanta, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ottaviano-Castillo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Rodríguez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Máiquez-Pérez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Martínez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer y comparar el apoyo social que tienen los drogodependientes de una prisión incluidos en el programalibre de drogas y en el programa de mantenimiento con metadona (PMM).Material y metodo: Estudio observacional descriptivo transversal, realizado en el Establecimiento Penitenciario de Albolote(Granada).La población penitenciaria en el momento del estudio era de 1.763 reclusos. Los drogodependientes, se dividieron en dosgrupos: en programa de mantenimiento con metadona (PMM 279 reclusos) y en programa libre de drogas (58 reclusos). Se obtuvouna muestra aleatoria de 60 internos en el grupo en PMM. Participó toda la población del programa libre de drogas. A losdos grupos se les entrevistó a fin de conocer su estructura familiar, nivel socioeconómico y de estudios. También se aplicó elcuestionario MOS de apoyo social de forma autoaplicada asistido por entrevistador. Los porcentajes obtenidos de cada dimensióndel cuestionario MOS de los grupos se compararon mediante Chi cuadrado de Pearson.Resultados: La red social del grupo en PMM fue de media 13,2. En el grupo libre de drogas fue 12,9. Valor de p= 0,0047.El apoyo global fue bajo en 38 personas (74,5%) en el grupo en PMM y 9 (15,62%) en el grupo en programa libre de drogas.Siendo normal en 13 sujetos (25,5%) en el grupo en PMM y en 49 (84,38%) en el grupo incluido en el programa libre de drogas.Valor de p= 0,0001.Todas las dimensiones del cuestionario MOS de apoyo social son más elevadas en el grupo en programa libre de drogas,existiendo diferencias estadísticamente significativas con el grupo en PMM.Conclusiones: Los reclusos en programa libre de drogas tienen, y así lo perciben ellos, un mayor apoyo social que los queestán en PMM(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. sanid. penit;12(1): 13-20, 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79300</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Tienen apoyo social los reclusos drogodependientes? Estudio en una prisión andaluza</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11765^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11765^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8866^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
