<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82996</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Digital and densitometric radiographic study in swine jaws subjected to osteotomy using high and low drilling speeds with liquid cooling</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The influence of the type of rotary cutting instrument on bone repair after osteotomy in swine jaw, was evaluated using digital and densitometric radiographic examinations, at controlled times. Two cross-sectional dissections were made through the base of the right jaw, one using a high speed rotary instrument and the other using low speed, both with liquid cooling. After established periods the animals were sacrificed and their jaws removed for direct and indirect digital radiographic and densitometric studies using the CROMOX, DIGORA and ODR systems. In the initial periods (7 and 28 days) the bone density was higher in osteotomy areas performed with high rotation speeds, and in the final periods (60 and 90 days) the bone density was higher in the osteotomies performed with low rotation, indicating a better final bone repair with the use of low rotation. The qualitative analysis of the repair process was made by the ODR system which obtained three-dimensional and coloured digital images, which enable the bone thickness to be measured using an aluminium wedge. This showed that by twenty-eight days the bone repair was already apparently complete(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quirino Louzada, Mario Jefferson</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pescinini Salzedas, Leda María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monti, Lira Marcela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lima de Castro, Alvimar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se evaluó por medio de la radiografía digital y la densitometría, la influencia de un dispositivo de rotación para el corte en el proceso de curación del hueso después de osteotomías en mandíbulas de cerdos, a tiempos controlados. Se realizaron dos secciones transversales en la base de la mandíbula derecha, una con una alta velocidad de rotación y otra por la acción de baja velocidad, ambos con el líquido de irrigación. Tras los tiempos preestablecidos, los animales fueron sacrificados y sus mandíbulas retiradas para los estudios radiográficos y de densitometría radiológica con los sistemas digitales Cromox, Digora y ODR. En los períodos iniciales (7 y 28 días) el equivalente a la densitometría en milímetro de aluminio y la media de niveles de gris fueron más altos en la región de osteotomías hechas con alta rotación, y en los períodos finales (60 y 90 días) las mayores densitometrías fueron para osteotomías hechas con baja velocidad, lo que indica una mejor cicatrización final del hueso cuando se hace uso de la baja velocidad. El análisis cualitativo del proceso de reparación fue realizado por el ODR, lo que permitió la recopilación de imágenes digitales en color y en tres dimensiones, para la comparación del espesor del hueso con una cuña de aluminio, indicando que en los 28 días de curación del hueso, ya estaba evidente la completa reparación(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;32(3): 102-107, jul.-sept. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82996</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio digital radiográfico y densitométrico en mandíbulas de cerdos sometidos a osteotomía con alta y baja velocidad, con refrigeración líquida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8510^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10207^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33094^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10207^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9211^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8510^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12456^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d79^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5364^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11754^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3732^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8506^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8506^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
