<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73720</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-8831</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epstein-Barr virus and mycoplasma pneumoniae exanthema</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. One of the clinical manifestations of infectious mononucleosisis a polymorph exanthema due to Epstein-Barr virus,and occasionally to amoxicillin administration. It's unusual to findEpstein-Barr virus and Mycoplasma pneumoniae co-infectionwhere the only clinical manifestation is exanthema.Case report. A 6 years-old girl presented with macular and papularexanthema. Physical examination showed that she had exanthema,latero-cervical and occipital adenopathies, hepatomegaly (2cm) and fever (maximum temperature: 38.7ºC). Clinical and laboratorydata led to the diagnosis of infectious mononucleosis andMycoplasma pneumoniae co-infection.Comments. After reviewing medical literature, we think it's thefirst case described in children of Epstein-Barr virus and Mycoplasmapneumoniae co-infection without respiratory (pneumonia)or neurological (meningitis or transverse myelitis) complications(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vizmanos, Gerardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosell, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Capellà, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lázaro, Marisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, Juli</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barranco, Ferran</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Una de las manifestaciones de la mononucleosis infecciosaes el exantema polimorfo debido al virus Epstein-Barr(VEB) y desencadenado en ocasiones por amoxicilina. No es habitualencontrarse ante una coinfección por VEB y Mycoplasmapneumoniae en la que la principal manifestación clínica sea elexantema.Observación clínica. Presentamos el caso de una niña de 6 añoscon un exantema máculo-papuloso generalizado que varió en suforma de presentación. A la exploración física destacaban, apartedel exantema, adenopatías laterocervicales bilaterales y occipitales,hepatomegalia de 2 cm y fiebre (temperatura máxima: 38,7ºC).Los datos clínicos de la exploración física y los resultados analíticos(hemograma, fórmula leucocitaria, test de Paul-Bunnell y serolo-Exantema per virus Epstein-Barr i MycoplasmapneumoniaeGerardo Vizmanos 1, Marisa Lázaro 1, Óscar Rosell 2, Montserrat Capellà 1, Juli González 2,Ferran Barranco 21 ABS Alt Urgell Sud. 2 Servei de Pediatria; Fundació Sant Hospital. La Seu d'Urgell (Lleida)gías) condujeron al diagnóstico de mononucleosis infecciosa ycoinfección por Mycoplasma pneumoniae.Comentarios. Según la revisión de la literatura, es el primer casodescrito en niños de coinfección por VEB y Mycoplasma pneumoniaesin complicaciones respiratorias (neumonía) o neurológicas(meningitis o mielitis transversa)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. catalan;69(1): 20-22, ene.-feb. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73720</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Exantema por virus Epstein-Barr y mycoplasma pneumoniae</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5175^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5175^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9367^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9369^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33755^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9369^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33755^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7421^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5175^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7421^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7421^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7421^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7421^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
