<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79795</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Opioid switching and bioequivalent molecules</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Due to the alert created due to two important incidents that took place involving the clinical activity of doctors who treat pain (one is the switching of bioequivalent molecules, and the other is the directives issued by a Health Department on encouraging the use of morphine instead of other opioids as first choice analgesic opioid), the Working Group of the Spanish Pain Society, considering that both can affect the activities in clinical practices that do not adapt to the available scientific evidence, analysed these two facts, and based on the expert report by Dr. Cecilio Álamo in May 2009, entitled, the clinical switching of strong opioids, and after an in depth review of the national and international literature, as well as the position of European health institutions, including the French Medicines Agency and the Royal Pharmaceutical Society of Great Britain, issued as conclusions that: 1. We do not believe that the switching of strong opioids is justified whether they are generic or branded. 2. In view of the advantages provided by the new molecules with different formulas (oral as well as transdermal), we can state that there are other therapeutic options other than the use of morphine as a first choice analgesic opioid (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodrigo, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Busquets, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pozo, C. del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Ante la alerta creada por dos situaciones que inciden, de manera significativa, en el entorno de la actividad clínica de los médicos que tratan el dolor, y que son: por un lado, la intercambiabilidad de moléculas bioequivalentes y, por el otro, las directrices emitidas por alguna consejería de salud en el fomento del uso de morfina frente a otros opioides como analgésico opioide de primera elección, el Grupo de Trabajo de Opioides de la Sociedad Española del Dolor &#151;considerando que ambas pueden llevar a actuaciones en la práctica clínica que no se ajustan a la evidencia científica disponible&#151; analiza estos dos hechos a partir del informe de experto del Dr. Cecilio Álamo, realizado en mayo de 2009, sobre la intercambiabilidad clínica de opioides potentes. Tras una revisión en profundidad de la bibliografía disponible a nivel nacional e internacional, así como de la posición de instituciones sanitarias europeas, entre otras, la Agencia Francesa del Medicamento y la Royal Pharmaceutical Society del Reino Unido, emite las conclusiones siguientes: 1. No creemos justificada la intercambiabilidad de opioides potentes entre sí, ya sean genéricos o de marca. 2. Ante las ventajas que aportan las nuevas moléculas con diferentes formulaciones (tanto por vía oral como por vía transdérmica), podemos afirmar que hay otras opciones terapéuticas frente al uso de morfina como analgésico opioide de primera elección (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;17(2): 104-113, mar. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79795</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intercambiabilidad de opioides y moléculas bioequivalentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51464</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30149^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d715^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51451</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
