<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102745</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-0618</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Separation between toxin-producing and non-toxic clones of Microcystis aeruginosa using lectins</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Microcystis aeruginosa (the most widespread toxic cyanobacteria worldwide) occurs in dense blooms composed of toxin-producing and non-toxic strains. Current microscopy techniques monitoring of toxic cyanobacteria are unable to distinguish toxic and non-toxic strains. In contrast, a new assay using lectins is able to differentiate among the different M. aeruginosa strains based on microcystin production. We analyze thirty-five cultured strains of M. aeruginosa isolated from 4 different blooms in three water supply reservoirs and a lagoon as well as a lot of M. aeruginosa colonies directly collected from field samples. All non-toxic M. aeruginosa strains were positively bound with UEA-1 lectin and by several other lectins. In contrast, the most toxic strains remain unbound. This procedure also was successful in field samples. Although other techniques allow for the differentiation between toxic and non-toxic strains, none of them is as fast, simple and easy as lectin-binding pattern(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Rodas, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Costas, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Microcystis aeuruginosa (la cianobacteria tóxica más extendida mundialmente) es la responsable de &#147;blooms&#148; o floraciones que están compuestos por cepas tóxicas y no tóxicas. Las técnicas de microscopia utilizadas actualmente no permiten distinguir entre las cepas tóxicas y las no tóxicas. Por el contrario, un nuevo procedimiento empleando lectinas es capaz de diferenciar entre las cepas de M. aeruginosa basándose en la producción de microcistina. Se analizaron treinta y cinco cepas aisladas de M. aeruginosa aisladas de cuatro blooms diferentes en tres depósitos de abastecimiento de agua y en una laguna, así como una gran cantidad de colonias de M. aeruginosa directamente recogidos de muestras de campo. Todas las cepas no tóxicas de M. aeruginosa fueron marcadas positivamente con la lectina UEA-1  y por varias otras lectinas. Sin embargo, las cepas más tóxicas permanecieron sin marcar. Este procedimiento también tuvo éxito en muestras de campo. Aunque existen otras técnicas que permiten la diferenciación entre cepas tóxicas y no tóxicas, ninguna es tan rápida y simple como el marcaje por lectinas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Real Acad Farm;78(1): 123-137, ene.-mar. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102745</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferenciación entre clones productores de tóxina y no tóxicos de Microcystis aeruginosa mediante el uso de lectinas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8042^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9041^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8042^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38540^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38540^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38540^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8042^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8042^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9041^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
