<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99588</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Axillary lymph node as manifestation of recurrent ovarian cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Ovarian cancer is the gynecological tumor with higher mortality. The way of spread of this tumor most often is intraperitoneal, although distant metastases may occur by hematogenous via to other organs in the abdominal cavity. The appearance of metastatic axillary lymph nodes from ovarian carcinoma is a very rare finding. You should have a differential diagnosis  with other tumors, mainly breast carcinoma, since treatment and prognosis is very different. We report a 60 years patient under both surgical and chemotherapy treatment for high-grade serous adenocarcinoma (FIGO stage IIIC). After 15 months of the surgery has left axillary adenopathy suspicious subjected to FNA diagnosis of metastatic ovarian carcinoma. At the same time new episode of peritoneal carcinomatosis occurs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Camino, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Medrano, E. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias Valdés, E. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Reviriego, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Blanco, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arnal Burró, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cáncer de ovario es el tumor ginecológico que presenta mayor mortalidad. La vía de diseminación más frecuente de esta neoplasia es por vía intraperitoneal, aunque pueden aparecer metástasis a distancia por diseminación hematógena a otros órganos de la cavidad abdominal. La aparición de adenopatías axilares metastásicas de un carcinoma de ovario es un hallazgo muy infrecuente. Debe realizarse un diagnóstico diferencial con otro tipo de tumores, fundamentalmente el carcinoma mamario, ya que el tratamiento y el pronóstico resultan muy diferentes.  Presentamos el caso de una mujer de 60 años sometida a un tratamiento quirúrgico y quimioterápico por un adenocarcinoma seroso de alto grado (estadio IIIC de la FIGO). Tras 15 meses de la cirugía presenta una adenopatía axilar izquierda sospechosa que se somete a PAAF con diagnóstico de metástasis de carcinoma ovárico. Al mismo tiempo presenta nuevo episodio de carcinomatosis peritoneal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;15(1): 20-22, ene.-mar. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99588</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adenopatía axilar tumoral como manifestación de recidiva del cáncer de ovario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8384^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33161</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10724^s22064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10229^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1377^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36331</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
