<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118542</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Advice or prescription? Analysis of the pediatric recommendations in the healthy child program visits</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: reasoning the recommendations increases mothers&#146; adherence and satisfaction in the healthy child program visits. A recommendation can be considered an advice or a prescription according to its reasoning. Aims: in this study we described and analyzed the use of advice and prescription in the recommendations made by pediatricians to mothers in the healthy child program visits. We analyzed the quantity and quality of recommendations, its content and its relation to the visits&#146; duration, and the characteristics of the child and mother. Methods: we audio-taped 50 visits of five pediatricians and we classified, through content analysis, the recommendations in six categories: secondary prevention, primary prevention, health promotion, development, education and family relationships. Results: pediatricians made 4.37 recommendations per visit, 69% by their own initiative and 31% by mothers&#146; request. Pediatricians make recommendations mainly about health promotion (32.87%), secondary prevention (17.13%) and primary prevention (10.19%). The amount of recommendations was positively associated with the visit&#146;s length (M=16.10 minutes) and negatively related with child&#146;s age. The pediatricians used much more advice (70%) than prescription (30%). The effect of the mothers&#146; educational level wasn&#146;t observed. Conclusions: there was a great heterogeneity between pediatricians in all observed variables; this suggests that there exist different pediatric styles whose characteristics and effects deserve further investigation in future studies in order to help pediatricians to improve their professional practice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nunes, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayala, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: razonar las recomendaciones aumenta la adhesión y satisfacción de las madres en las consultas del programa de salud infantil. Una recomendación puede ser considerada consejo o prescripción según sea razonada o no. Objetivos: en el presente estudio describimos y analizamos el uso del consejo y la prescripción en las recomendaciones transmitidas a las madres en el ámbito del programa de salud infantil. Analizamos la cantidad y calidad de las recomendaciones, su contenido y su relación con la duración de la consulta, y con las características del niño y de la madre. Material y métodos: grabamos 50 consultas de cinco pediatras y, a través del análisis de contenido, clasificamos las recomendaciones en seis categorías: prevención secundaria, prevención primaria, promoción de la salud, desarrollo, educación y relación familiar. Resultados: los pediatras realizan 4,37 recomendaciones por consulta, el 69% por iniciativa propia y el 31% a petición de las madres. Los pediatras hacen sobre todo recomendaciones acerca de la promoción de la salud (32,87%), la prevención secundaria (17,13%) y la primaria (10,19%). La cantidad de recomendaciones está positivamente asociada con la duración de la consulta (M=16,10 minutos) y negativamente asociada con la edad del niño. Los pediatras utilizaron mucho más el consejo (70%) que la prescripción (30%). No observamos efecto del nivel de escolaridad de la madre. Conclusión: en todas las variables observadas existe una gran heterogeneidad entre los pediatras, lo que sugiere que existen estilos pediátricos diferentes cuyas características y efectos merecen ser investigados en trabajos futuros para ayudar a los pediatras a mejorar su práctica profesional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;15(60): e135-e143, oct.-dic. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118542</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Consejo o prescripción? Análisis de las recomendaciones pediátricas en las consultas del programa de salud infantil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28462^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53393^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36397</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
