<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80547</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A multidisciplinary approach to falls in a medium-stay hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveTo approach the problem of the falls in an average stay hospital; identifying the patients of greater risk; and find out the circumstances in which the falls occurred.Patients and methodsA descriptive study of all the patients who entered the Guadarrama Hospital (Madrid) during year 2007 (n=920). On admission, all patients were assessed using the Stratify falls risk scale, their cognitive and functional situation, unit of hospitalisation, record of falls and circumstances under which the falls occurred. The descriptive study and multivariate analysis was performed using the SPSS 16 statistics program.ResultsDuring the period of study 144 falls took place. There was a falls/admission incidence of 14.30%. The highest number of falls (22.1%) occurred in the Functional Recovery Unit (FRU) and patients with stroke being the group that suffered most falls (31%). Most falls were registered during the morning shift, with 51%. The greatest number of falls occurred from a chair (44%) and 66% of the patients had mobility limitations. A total of 34% of the patients had fallen previously. When the logistic regression analysis was made, the variables that remained with statistically significant association with falls, were: the Barthel index on admission (Exp &amp;#946; 2.5, 95%CI; 1.5&#150;4.2; P&lt;0,01) and the STRATIFY scale on admission (Exp &amp;#946; 1.67, 95%CI; 1.05&#150;2.66; P=0.02)ConclusionsThe chronic patients with greater functional deterioration are more prone to suffer falls. With respect to patient activity at the time of the fall, we can observe that most of them were seated and tried to stand up(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Minaya-Sáiz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salazar-de la Guerra, R. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano-Menor, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoAbordar el problema de las caídas en un hospital de media estancia, identificando a los pacientes de mayor riesgo y las circunstancias más habituales en las que se producen.Pacientes y métodosEstudio descriptivo de todos los pacientes ingresados en el Hospital Guadarrama durante el año 2007 (n=920). Se recogieron en una base de datos incluida en la historia informatizada del paciente: el STRATIFY al ingreso, la situación cognitiva y funcional, Unidad de Hospitalización, registro de las caídas y circunstancias en las que se produjeron. Se realizó el estudio descriptivo y análisis multivariante con el programa SPSS 16.ResultadosDurante el periodo de estudio se produjeron 144 caídas. La incidencia de caídas/ingreso fue de 14,3%, siendo la Unidad de Recuperación funcional la que mas caídas registra con un 22,01%, siendo los pacientes con ictus, con un 31%, el grupo de pacientes que más caídas sufrieron. El turno de la mañana ha sido el que mas caídas ha registrado, el 51%. El mayor número de caídas se produjeron desde la silla (44%). Un 34% de los pacientes habían sufrido caídas anteriores. Cuando se realizó el análisis de regresión logística, las variables que permanecieron con asociación estadísticamente significativa con caídas fueron: el índice de Barthel al ingreso (Exp &amp;#946; 2,5, IC del 95%: 1,5&#150;4,2; p&lt;0,01) y la escala de STRATIFY al ingreso (Exp &amp;#946; 1,67, IC del 95%: 1,05&#150;2,66; p=0,02).ConclusionesLos pacientes crónicos con mayor deterioro funcional son más propensos a sufrir caídas. En cuanto a la actividad en el momento de la caída, podemos observar que el mayor porcentaje de pacientes sufren la caída al tratar de levantarse(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;25(2): 106-111, mar.-abr. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80547</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abordaje multidisciplinar de las caídas en un hospital de media estancia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10542^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19050^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28096^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28940^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
