<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109999</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Salivary duct carcinoma: diagnostic clues, histology and treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Salivary duct carcinoma is a very rare, highly-malignant epithelial tumour. We present a case of a 75-year-old man with a rapidly- growing salivary duct carcinoma in the parotid gland, of one month's evolution. Histopathologically, salivary duct carcinoma is characterised by its resemblance to ductal carcinoma of the breast. It usually develops aggressively with possibilities of early distant metastasis and local recurrence. The tumour is managed with total parotidectomy, ipsilateral neck dissection and adjunctive radiation. In advanced cases, we recommend treatment with anti-Her-2 monoclonal antibodies such as trastuzumab (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Plá, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz Mojarrieta, Julia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pont, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brotons, Simón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vendrell, Juan B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrandis, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El carcinoma ductal salival es un tumor epitelial de alto grado, muy poco frecuente. Presentamos el caso de un varón de 75 años con carcinoma ductal salival de rápido crecimiento, en la glándula parótida, de un mes de evolución. Histopatológicamente se caracteriza por su gran similitud con el carcinoma ductal de mama. Suele tener un comportamiento muy agresivo, con recurrencia local y metástasis a distancia tempranas, por lo que hay que realizar parotidectomía total con vaciamiento cervical ipsilateral y radioterapia adyuvante. En casos avanzados se recomienda tratamiento con anticuerpo monoclonal selectivo para el HER-2/neu como trastuzumab (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;64(2): 150-153, mar.-abr. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109999</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Carcinoma ductal salival: claves diagnósticas, histología y tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22664^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38036^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9054^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22602^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
