<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152384</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychodynamic family therapy for anorexia nervosa</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Anorexia nervosa is a severe psychosomatic disorder, but one that is often deeply interwoven with family interactions. In some cases it also appears in a multigenerational context. Four levels of development of the illness must be differentiated: the biological (neurophysiological), social, family and the individual (psychic) levels. The family dynamics involved with this illness often have a high degree of impact on the therapeutic relationship and the dynamic of transference and countertransference. Clinical experiences and some research results on the family dynamics of anorexia are presented, as well as the steps for treatment. Questions of indications for family therapy sessions and their setting will also be discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Reich, Günter</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Von Boetticher, Antje</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cierpka, Manfred</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La anorexia nerviosa es un grave trastorno psicosomático, aunque muchas veces está íntimamente enlazado con las relaciones familiares. En algunos casos, también se produce en un contexto multifactorial, diferenciando cuatro niveles de desarrollo de la patología: el nivel biológico (neurofisiológico), el social, el familiar y el individual (psíquico). La dinámica familiar de la patología suele tener un elevado impacto en la relación terapéutica y en la dinámica de transferencia y contratransferencia. A continuación, se presentan la experiencia clínica y algunos resultados de estudios efectuados en las dinámicas familiares de la anorexia, así como también los pasos de su tratamiento. También se hablará sobre la indicación de las sesiones de terapia familiar y su ajuste al caso concreto. A través de las barricadas: entre profesores y estudiantes adolescentes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(27): 69-75, abr. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152384</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Terapia psicodinámica familiar de la anorexia nerviosa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33527^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55387^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33527^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33527^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55387^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24194^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24194^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38359^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24194^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12038^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5300^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12038^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12038^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5300^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
