<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162359</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Changes in Ventilatory Response to Exercise in Trained Athletes: Respiratory Physiological Benefits Beyond Cardiovascular Performance</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The beneficial impact of an 8-month competitive season on the ventilatory profile response to exercise in soccer players has never been evaluated. Material and methods: Ventilatory profile (evaluated by determining individual tidal volume [VT] relative to minute ventilation [VE] inflection points during exercise) and metabolic responses to incremental exercise were evaluated in 2 professional soccer teams before and after an 8-month competitive season. Results: No differences between teams in anthropometric characteristics or in resting cardiopulmonary variables, included oxygen uptake (VO2) and heart rate (HR), before and during the competitive season were found. At iso-speed, there were overall improvements in carbon dioxide output (VCO2), VE/VO2, VE/VCO2, VE and respiratory frequency (fR) during the season. The VT/VE inflection points 1 and 2 occurred with greater exercise time, HR, VO2, VCO2, VE and VT during the competitive season. Conclusions: Despite very high baseline performance and a negligible improvement in VO2, an 8-month competitive season improved ventilatory profile response to exercise in elite athletes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Laveneziana, Pierantonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dubé, Bruno-Pierre</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Di Paco, Adriano</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El efecto beneficioso de una temporada de competición de 8meses sobre el perfil ventilatorio en respuesta al esfuerzo no se ha evaluado en jugadores de fútbol. Material y métodos: Se evaluó el perfil ventilatorio (analizando los puntos de inflexión específicos del cociente entre el volumen corriente [VT] y la ventilación [VE] durante el esfuerzo) y la respuesta metabólica al esfuerzo gradual en 2 equipos de fútbol profesional, antes y después de una temporada de competición de 8 meses. Resultados: No se observaron diferencias entre equipos en las características antropométricas ni en las variables cardiopulmonares en reposo, incluidos el consumo de oxígeno (VO2) y la frecuencia cardíaca (FC). Durante la temporada de competición, a velocidad fija, se observaron mejorías globales en la producción de dióxido de carbono (VCO2), los cocientes VE/VO2 y VE/VCO2, la VE y la frecuencia respiratoria (FR). Los puntos de inflexión 1 y 2 del cociente VT/VE se observaron tras un mayor tiempo de ejercicio y mayores FC, VO2, VCO2, VE y VT durante la temporada de competición. Conclusiones: A pesar del elevado rendimiento inicial y de la escasa mejoría del VO2, la temporada de competición de 8 meses mejoró el perfil ventilatorio en respuesta al esfuerzo de estos deportistas de élite (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;53(5): 237-244, mayo 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162359</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambios en la respuesta ventilatoria al esfuerzo en deportistas entrenados: efectos beneficiosos sobre la fisiología respiratoria más allá del rendimiento cardiovascular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30732^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2361</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12563</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5178^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32868^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
