<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166581</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Economic impact of home birth vs. hospital delivery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: to understand and analyze the cost of home birth in comparison with hospital delivery, as well as the economic impact of home birth on the healthcare system in Spain, and whether it would be sustainable in our current economic scenario.  Method: a narrative review was conducted, based on a bibliographic literature search in PubMed, Cochrane, Hindawi, PLOS and CUIDEN, in Spanish and English, between January, 1999 and March, 2017. The search strategy consisted in combining the key DECS descriptors: normal delivery, labor, humanized birth, natural birth, and economic indicators, and the key terms &#145;home birth&#146; and &#145;cost of home birth&#146;. The search was refined through Boolean combinations of the previous terms. The study included articles which analyzed home birth among their research objectives. There was a separate analysis on the cost of implementing a new service to offer home care to pregnant women.  Results: fifteen (15) studies were analyzed, which met the inclusion criteria regarding the economic impact of home birth. The document review generated two categories of analysis of outcomes, differentiated in terms of the healthcare system origin: American and European healthcare systems, and the Spanish Health System.  Conclusions: home birth is more cost-effective than hospital delivery. The differences in the outcomes found are due to the differences between healthcare systems, their respective coverages, the expenses included, and the analysis methodology for economic costs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Aranda, M Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: conocer y analizar cuál es el coste del parto en casa en comparación con el parto hospitalario, cuál sería el impacto económico del parto domiciliario sobre el sistema sanitario en España y si sería sostenible en el actual escenario económico.  Método: se realiza una revisión narrativa a partir de la búsqueda bibliográfica de la literatura en PubMed, Cochrane, Hindawi, PLOS y CUIDEN, en español y en inglés, entre enero de 1999 y marzo de 2017. La estrategia de búsqueda consistió en combinar los descriptores clave DECS: parto normal, trabajo de parto, parto humanizado, parto natural e indicadores económicos y las palabras clave &#145;parto en casa&#146; y &#145;coste del parto en casa&#146;. Se afinó la búsqueda mediante combinaciones booleanas de los términos anteriores. Se incluyeron artículos que analizaban entre sus objetivos de investigación el parto domiciliario. Por separado se analizó el coste de la implantación de un nuevo servicio que contemplara la atención a la mujer gestante en su domicilio. Resultados: se analizaron 15 estudios que cumplían los criterios de inclusión sobre el impacto económico del parto en casa. La revisión documental generó dos categorías de análisis de resultados diferenciados según el origen del sistema de salud: sistemas sanitarios americanos y europeos y sistema sanitario español. Conclusiones: el parto en casa es económicamente más rentable que el parto en el hospital. Las diferencias en los resultados encontrados se deben a las diferencias existentes entre los distintos sistemas de salud, las coberturas soportadas por cada uno de ellos, los gastos incluidos y la metodología de análisis de los costes económicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;20(7): 68-74, sept. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166581</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto económico del parto en casa vs parto en el hospital</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31403^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36394</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16648^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9514^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3708^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32196^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
