<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89904</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evolution of vegetation size in left-sided endocarditis. Is it a prognostic factor during hospitalization</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective was to describe the vegetation changes in patients with endocarditis and evaluate their prognostic importance during hospitalization. We selected patients with left-sided endocarditis and two transesophageal echocardiograms separated by at least 8 days. Patients who required surgery or died during the first week after diagnosis of the disease were excluded. Patients were classified into three groups: I, patients whose vegetation increased in size (n=34); II, patients with vegetations that did not vary in size (n=62); and III, patients whose vegetation decreased in size (n=59). Patients whose vegetation increased in size more frequently required surgery. Multivariate analysis showed that the increase in the vegetation is independently associated with increased mortality: adjusted odds ratio, 4.12 (95% confidence interval, 1.14-14.9; P=.031) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manzano, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Román, José Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva, Jacobo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarriá, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilacosta, Isidre</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pozo, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo es describir la evolución de la vegetación en enfermos con endocarditis y evaluar su importancia pronóstica durante la hospitalización. Se seleccionó a pacientes con endocarditis izquierda y dos ecocardiogramas transesofágicos separados al menos 8 días. Se excluyó a los pacientes que precisaron cirugía o fallecieron durante la primera semana siguiente al diagnóstico. Se determinaron tres grupos: grupo I, pacientes cuya vegetación aumentó de tamaño (n=34); grupo II, pacientes con vegetaciones que no variaron (n=62), y grupo III, pacientes cuyas vegetaciones disminuyeron (n=59). Los pacientes del grupo I precisaron cirugía con mayor frecuencia. El incremento del tamaño de la vegetación se asoció de forma independiente a una mayor mortalidad: odds ratio ajustada=4,12 (intervalo de confianza del 95%, 1,14-14,9; p=0,031) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;64(8): 714-717, ago. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89904</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución del tamaño de la vegetación en la endocarditis izquierda. ¿Es un marcador pronóstico intrahospitalario?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4777^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1447^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d195^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24811</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23233^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
