<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106404</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Protective effect of melatonin and the lidocaine and prilocaine eutectic mixture in an ischemia reperfusion injury model in the microvascular cutaneous flap in rats</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Ischemia-reperfusion injury is a set of events developed since the introduction of ischemia in a tissue to subsequent reperfusion. It is a limiting condition and, to date, inevitable in any surgery involving tissue revascularization. In an attempt to find therapeutic measures against oxidative stress developed during this syndrome in microvascular flaps, we evaluated the antioxidant action of melatonin and local anesthetics lidocaine and prilocaine in a model of ischemia reperfusion in the microvascularized epigastric flap in rats. The indole and vasoactive drugs have a protective effect in the treatment of ischemia reperfusion injury, from both a biochemical and histological view, emphasizing their synergistic action mainly manifested as an increase in tissue neovascularization (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casado Sánchez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galache Collell, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San José Valiente, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Menchén, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rioja Torrejón, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar Melero, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padillo Ruiz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de isquemia reperfusión es el conjunto de sucesos desarrollados desde la instauración de la isquemia en un tejido hasta su posterior reperfusión. Se trata de una condición limitante y, hasta la fecha, inevitable, en toda cirugía que implique una revascularización tisular. En un intento por buscar medidas terapéuticas frente al estrés oxidativo desarrollado durante este síndrome en los colgajos microvascularizados, se valoró la acción del antioxidante melatonina y de los anestésicos locales lidocaína y prilocaína en un modelo de isquemia reperfusión en el colgajo epigástrico microvascularizado en ratas. Tanto el indol como los fármacos vasoactivos poseen un efecto protector en el tratamiento del síndrome de isquemia reperfusión, desde un punto de vista bioquímico e histológico, destacando su acción sinérgica manifestada principalmente como un incremento en la neovascularización tisular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;38(3): 195-206, jul.-sept. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106404</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto protector de la melatonina y del tratamiento tópico con la mezcla eutéctica de lidocaína y prilocaína en un modelo de isquemia reperfusión en el colgajo cutáneo microvascularizado en ratas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32666^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8188^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33519^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23813^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4255</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8718^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11754^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
