<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76191</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Having Cancer and desiring to become parents; bibliographical Review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Over these recent years, survival by patients who have suffered some kinds of cancer has increased due to advances in diagnostic techniques and in treatment. Many of these patients are youths who have yet to begin to form families or have not completed them. The possibility of having a child in the future is a very important topic for cancer patients. Infertility can be associated with the disease itself or its treatments. On the other hand, the development of assisted reproduction has made it possible to achieve a large number of pregnancies. All these factors have led to recommending to cancer patients who harbor reproductive desires to use methods to preserve their fertility before starting anti-cancer treatment. In spite of these findings, studies document that oncology teams do not treat fertility with patients as frequently as they contemplate other complications(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rivera-Alonso, Josefina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos años, la supervivencia de pacientes que han sufrido algunos tipos de cáncer ha aumentado debido al avance en las técnicas diagnósticas y en los tratamientos. Muchos de estos pacientes son jóvenes que no han empezado a formar una familia o no la han completado. La posibilidad de tener un hijo en el futuro es un tema muy importante para pacientes diagnosticados de cáncer. La infertilidad puede estar asociada a la propia enfermedad o a los tratamientos. Por otra parte, el desarrollo de la reproducción asistida ha permitido conseguir un gran número de gestaciones. Todo ello ha supuesto recomendar a pacientes oncológicos con deseos reproductivos que utilicen métodos para preservar la fertilidad antes de iniciar el tratamiento contra el cáncer. A pesar de todo, los estudios documentan que el equipo de profesionales en Oncología no trata la fertilidad con los pacientes con la frecuencia con la que se contemplan otras complicaciones(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;32(10): 668-674, oct. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76191</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tener cáncer y querer ser padres. Revisión bibliográfica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10528</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22877</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3675</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9916^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9916^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
