<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116298</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A new assessment for episodic memory. Episodic memory test and caregiver&#146;s episodic memory test</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: The purpose of the episodic memory test and the caregiver&#146;s episodic memory test is to evaluate episodic memory according to its definition in a way that is feasible for families and achieves high degrees of sensitivity and specificity. Methods and results: We administered a test consisting of 10 questions about episodic events to 332 subjects, of whom 65 had Alzheimer&#146;s disease (AD), 115 had amnestic MCI (aMCI) and 152 showed no cognitive impairment according to Reisberg&#146;s global deterioration scale (GDS). We calculated the test&#146;s sensitivity and specificity to distinguish AD from episodic aMCI and from normal ageing. The area under the ROC curve for the diagnosis of aMCI was 0.94 and the best cut-off value was 20; for that value, sensitivity was 89% and specificity was 82%. For a diagnosis of AD, the area under the ROC curve was 0.99 and the best cut-off point was 17, with a sensitivity of 98% and a specificity of 91%. A subsequent study using similar methodology yielded similar results when the test was administered directly by the caregiver. Conclusions: The episodic memory test and the caregiver&#146;s episodic memory test are useful as brief screening tools for identifying patients with early-stage AD. It is suitable for use by primary care medical staff and in the home, since it can be administered by a caregiver. The test&#146;s limitations are that it must be administered by a reliable caregiver and the fact that it measures episodic memory only (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernádez Fernández, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Álvarez de Sotomayor, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ojea Ortega, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Gónzalez, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: Valorar la memoria episódica, adaptándola a la definición del concepto, haciéndola asequible a las familias, y aplicándola con una alta sensibilidad y especificidad, es el concepto del test episódico y el test episódico del cuidador. Métodos y resultados: Se aplicó un test formado por 10 preguntas relacionadas con hechos episódicos a 332 sujetos, de los cuales 65 tenían enfermedad de Alzheimer (EA), 115 deterioro cognitivo leve amnésico (DCLa) y 152 no mostraron alteración cognitiva, según la escala de deterioro global (GDS) de Reisberg. Se calculó la sensibilidad y especificidad del test episódico para detectar EA frente a DCLa y normalidad. El área bajo la curva ROC para el diagnóstico de DCLa fue de 0,94 y el mejor punto de corte fue 20, valor con el que se obtuvo una sensibilidad del 89% y una especificidad del 82%. Con respecto al diagnóstico de EA, el área bajo la curva ROC fue de 0,99 y el mejor punto de corte fue 17, con el que se obtuvo una sensibilidad del 98% y una especificidad del 91%. Un estudio posterior con similar metodología demostró resultados similares cuando el test era pasado directamente por el cuidador. Conclusiones: El test episódico y el test episódico del cuidador son herramientas útiles como test breves de cribado para la captación de enfermos con EA en estadios iniciales, adecuadas para la utilización en atención primaria y en él domicilio, al poder ser pasado directamente por el cuidador. Las limitaciones del test vienen dadas por la necesidad de un cuidador fiable y por la medición exclusiva de la memoria episódica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;28(8): 488-496, oct. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116298</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Un nuevo test para la valoración de la memoria episódica. Test episódico y test episódico del cuidador</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d662^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32193^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54749</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
