<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039005</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Detection of encephalic death by BIS (bispectral index) monitoring</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Assess the BIS monitor (Bispectral index) as a detection method of encephalic death. Design. Prospective, observational study. Scope. Intensive Medicine Unit of a University Hospital. Patients and method. Sixteen (16) patients admitted non-consecutively to the Intensive Care Unit, with serious neurological condition and evolution to encephalic death (ED). A BIS monitor, model XP and "BIS Quatro" sensor were used. The BIS, suppression rate (SR), quality index of the signal and electromyographic activity values were recorded continuously. Results. The ED diagnosis was performed by neurological clinical examination and electroencephalogram in every case. In addition, transcranial Doppler was used in 11 patients. Coinciding with clinical deterioration, a slow decrease in the BIS value, together with increase in the SR, was observed. In all the patients in whom ED diagnosis was confirmed, the BIS showed values of 0 and suppression rates of 100. Only one patient had interferences, due to electromyographic activity, the same problem being detected when the conventional EEG was performed. After using a neuromuscular blocker, the BIS and SR values were 0 and 100, respectively. Conclusions. BIS is a non-invasive, simple and easy to interpret method. All patients diagnosed of ED, except one, had a BIS value of 0 and SR of 100, showing a perfect correlation with the other diagnostic methods used. The BIS cannot be used exclusively in the confirmation of ED, however it is a very useful tool, used as "alarm signal", since it detects the onset of cerebral incarceration early</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Taboada Costa, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cofiño Castañeda, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escudero Augusto, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parra Ruiz, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñiz Albaiceta, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Otero Hernández, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Valorar el monitor BIS (índice biespectral) como método de detección de muerte encefálica. Diseño. Estudio observacional prospectivo. Ámbito. Unidad de Medicina Intensiva de Hospital Universitario. Pacientes y método. Dieciséis pacientes ingresados de forma no consecutiva en la Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos, con patología neurológica grave, y evolución a muerte encefálica (ME). Se utilizó un monitor BIS, modelo XP y el sensor "BIS Quatro". Se registraron de forma continua los valores de BIS, tasa de supresión (TS), índice de calidad de señal y actividad electromiográfica. Resultados. El diagnóstico de ME se realizó mediante exploración clínica neurológica y electroencefalograma en todos los casos. Adicionalmente, en 11 pacientes, se utilizó el doppler transcraneal. Coincidiendo con el empeoramiento clínico, se objetivó un descenso paulatino del valor BIS, junto con un ascenso en la TS. En todos los pacientes en los cuales se confirmó el diagnóstico de ME, el BIS mostró valores de 0 y TS de 100. Sólo un paciente presentó interferencias, por actividad electromiográfica, detectándose el mismo problema al realizar el electroencefalograma convencional. Tras utilizar un bloqueante neuromuscular, los valores de BIS y TS fueron de 0 y 100 respectivamente. Conclusiones. El BIS es un método no invasivo, sencillo y de fácil interpretación. Todos los pacientes diagnosticados de ME, excepto uno, tenían un valor BIS de 0 y TS de 100, mostrando una perfecta correlación con los otros métodos diagnósticos utilizados. El BIS no puede ser utilizado de forma exclusiva en la confirmación de la ME, pero es una herramienta muy útil, empleada como "señal de alarma", ya que detecta precozmente el inicio del enclavamiento cerebral</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);29(5): 272-278, jun. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039005</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Detección de muerte encefálica mediante monitorización BIS (índice biespectral)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1952^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4641^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4648^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9183^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
