<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119201</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-4007</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interviewing young adolescent suspects: When to reveal incriminating information?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Recent research has demonstrated that the way in which interviewers reveal information/evidence to interviewees/suspects can produce noticeable differences between truthful and deceptive verbal statements. However, very little of this research has involved adolescents. In the present study, 12 to 14 year old adolescents were asked to commit (n = 26) or not to commit (n = 26) a mock crime and at interview to deny involvement in this crime. Prior to interview some information about each adolescent&#146;s behaviour was made available to the interviewer but this was not enough to enable determination of whether he or she had committed the crime. The interviewer revealed such information either at the beginning of the interview (the &#145;traditional method&#146;), at the end of the interview (as pioneered by the &#145;SUE&#146; technique), or gradually. The interviews were analysed for interviewees&#146; &#145;evidence omissions&#146; and &#145;statement-evidence contradictions&#146;. As predicted, liars omitted more crime-related information/details and their statements were significantly more inconsistent with the information/evidence known to/ disclosed by the interviewer. The timing of the interviewer&#146;s evidence revelation had a significant effect on liars&#146; mentioning during their free recall of some of this information and on the total number of details mentioned in free recall (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lingwooda, Jamie</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bullb, Ray</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Investigaciones recientes han demostrado que la forma en que los entrevistadores revelan información/ pruebas a los entrevistados/sospechosos puede producir diferencias considerables entre declaraciones orales verdaderas y falsas. Sin embargo, muy poca investigación se ha centrado en adolescentes. En este estudio se pidió a adolescentes de 12 a 14 años que cometieran (n = 26) o no cometieran (n = 26) un delito en un contexto de simulación y que negaran en una entrevista la participación en dicho delito. Previamente a la entrevista se le proporcionó al entrevistador cierta información sobre la conducta de cada adolescente, pero no era suficiente para establecer si había cometido el delito. El entrevistador revelaba dicha información bien al inicio de la entrevista (&#145;método tradicional&#146;), bien al final (como establece la técnica SUE) o gradualmente. En las entrevistas se analizó la &#145;omisión de pruebas&#146; y las &#145;contradicciones en la declaración&#146;. En consonancia con las predicciones, los mentirosos omitían más información/detalles relacionados con el delito y sus declaraciones eran significativamente más incongruentes con la información/pruebas conocidas/ reveladas por el entrevistador. La dosificación temporal con la que el entrevistador revelaba las pruebas tuvo un efecto significativo en la declaración de los mentirosos durante el recuerdo libre de la información y en el número total de detalles mencionados en el recuerdo libre (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Eur. j. psychol. appl. legal context (Internet);5(2): 141-146, jul. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119201</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La entrevista a adolescentes sospechosos: ¿cuándo revelar información incriminatoria?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8190</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14746</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7569^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3433^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
