<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141640</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5274</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Verbal expressions used by anaclitic and introjective patients with depressivesymptomatology: Analysis of change and stuck episodes within therapeutic sessions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A person&#146;s speech makes it possible to identify significant indicators which reflect certain characteristics of his/her personality organization, but also can vary depending on the relevance of specific moments of the session and the symptoms type. The present study analyzed 10 completed and successful therapeutic processes using a mixed methodology. The therapies were video&#150;and audio-taped, as well as observed through a one-way mirror by trained observers. All the sessions of each therapy were considered (N = 230) in order to identify, delimit, transcribe, and analyze Change Episodes (CEs = 24) and Stuck Episodes (SEs = 26). Each episode was made up by patients&#146; speech segments (N = 1,282), which were considered as the sampling unit. The Therapeutic Activity Coding System (TACS-1.0) was used to manually code each patient&#146;s verbalizations, nested within episodes and individuals, in order to analyze them using Hierarchical Linear Modelling (HLM). The findings suggest that anaclitic patients tend to use more verbalizations in order to ask for feedback or to be understood by their therapists (attune), whereas introjective patients tend to use more verbalizations in order to construct new meanings (resignify) during therapeutic conversation, but especially during SEs. Clinical implications to enrich the therapeutic practice are discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Krause, Mariane</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valdés, Nelson</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La manera como una persona habla permite dar cuenta de ciertos indicadores que reflejan características de su organización de personalidad, pero además estos pueden variar dependiendo de la relevancia de momentos específicos de la sesión y de la sintomatología de las pacientes. El presente estudio analizó 10 procesos terapéuticos completes y exitosos utilizando una metodología mixta. Todas las terapias fueron grabadas en audio y video, además de ser observadas por observadores entrenados a través de un espejo de visión unidireccional. Se incluyeron todas las sesiones de cada terapia (N = 230) con el fin de identificar, delimitar, transcribir y analizar los Episodios de Cambio (EC =24) y Episodios de Estancamiento (EE = 26). Cada episodio además está conformado por segmentos de habla de las pacientes (N = 1.282) los cuales se constituyeron finalmente nuestra unidad de análisis. La codificación manual de cada uno de estos segmentos de habla se realiza a través del Sistema de Codificación de la Actividad Terapéutica (SCAT-1.0), los cuales fueron anidados en episodios e individuos para analizarlos posteriormente con el Modelo Jerárquico Lineal (HLM). Los resultados sugieren que las pacientes analíticas usaron más verbalizaciones con el fin de solicitar feedback o ser entendidas por sus terapeutas (sintonizar), mientras que las pacientes introyectivas usaron más verbalizaciones con el fin de construir nuevos significados (resignificar) durante la conversación terapéutica, incluso durante los episodios de EE. Se discuten las implicancias clínicas para el quehacer terapéutico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. salud;26(2): 103-119, jul. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141640</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">/ Expresiones verbales usadas por pacientes anaclíticas e introyectivas con sintomatología depresiva: análisis de episodios de cambio y estancamiento durante las sesiones terapéuticas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3173</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10742^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7980</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11798</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15110</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
