<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99040</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Why living-donor renal transplant yields better outcomes than cadaver renal transplant?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: According to literature, patient and graft survival is better in living donor renal transplants (LRT) than in cadaver renal transplants (CRT). Objective: To study factors that determine the best results in LRT related to those of CRT, found in univariate studies. Patients and Methods: Renal transplants (RT) done in Catalonia during the 1990-2004 period, performed in patients over 17 years (135 LRT and 3.831 CRT), have been analyzed (retransplants were not included). The data come from the Renal Patients Transplant Registry (RMRC). Student¿s t-test and &amp;#967;2 test were used to compare means and proportions, respectively. To analyze univariate and multivariate survival, actuarial method and Cox regression have been used, respectively. Estimated creatinine clearance has been studied and its data have been showed through Selwood modified Analysis. Results: As it happens with other great RT patients series, the RMRC analysis, globally and without any adjustment, shows that patient and graft survival in LRT is better than that obtained with CRT. When we studied which variables explain these results, we found that main factors were smaller recipient age and the short time on dialysis. The great influence of both factors has been published in a large number of papers, explaining the differences obtained on the transplanted renal patient survival. Conclusions: Once adjusted the analysis by the different factors that influence the survival of the patient and the graft, there are no differences in the obtained results, since the best outcomes of the TRV are due to factors like the smaller recipient age and the advanced TR (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Registro de enfermos renales de Cataluña (RMRC)</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Según la literatura hay una mejor supervivencia del paciente e injerto en los trasplantes renales (TR) realizados con órganos procedentes de donante vivo. Objetivos: Estudiar los factores que determinan los mejores resultados en el trasplante de donante vivo (TRV) respecto al de donante cadáver (TRC), hallados en estudios univariados. Pacientes y métodos: Se analizan los primeros TR realizados en Cataluña en el período 1990-2004 en mayores de 17 años (135 TRV y 3.831 TRC). Los datos proceden del Registro de enfermos renales de Cataluña (RMRC). Se ha utilizado la t-Student para la comparación de medias y el test de la 2 para la de proporciones. Para el análisis univariado de la supervivencia se ha utilizado el método actuarial y la regresión de Cox para el multivariado. Se ha estudiado la depuración estimada de la creatinina y sus datos se han representado con el análisis de Selwood modificado. Resultados: Al igual que ocurre con las grandes series de trasplantados renales, el RMRC objetiva que, globalmente y sin ningún tipo de ajuste, el TRV presenta mejores resultados de supervivencia de paciente e injerto que el TRC. Cuando estudiamos los factores más relevantes para explicar estos resultados, obtenemos que los más determinantes son la menor edad del receptor y el menor tiempo en diálisis. Numerosas publicaciones han demostrado que ambos factores tienen una gran influencia sobre la supervivencia del paciente trasplantado renal, condicionando la diferencia en las supervivencias obtenidas. Conclusiones: Una vez ajustado el análisis por los diferentes factores que intervienen en la supervivencia del paciente y del injerto, no existen diferencias en los resultados obtenidos por los dos tratamientos, ya que los mejores resultados del TRV son debidos a factores como la menor edad del receptor y el TR anticipado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;28(2): 159-167, mar.-abr. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99040</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Por qué el trasplante renal de donante vivo da mejores resultados que el trasplante renal de donante cadáver?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33201^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19279^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
