<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053474</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analgesia for childbirth in a patient with Factor V Leiden mutation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Factor V Leiden mutation is the most common congenital        thrombophilic disorder, affecting between 5% and 8%        of the Caucasian population.        Pregnancy creates a state of hypercoagulability and all        factors that increase the risk of thrombosis should be considered,        as they may be cumulative. In recent years, the        diagnosis of new allelic variants of thrombophilic states        have increased the incidence of pregnant women receiving        anticoagulant therapy, with the anesthetic considerations        that implies.        We report the case of a 33-year-old woman with heterozygous        Leiden factor V mutation who was admitted with        spontaneous amniorrhexis in the 38th week of gestation.        She was taking low molecular weight heparin therapy. An        epidural catheter was inserted to provide analgesia for        labor, with all safety precautions to prevent an epidural        hematoma.        Epidural anesthesia is the technique of choice for        obstetric labor in patients with hypercoagulability        because of its effects of favoring blood flow and inhibiting        clot formation</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lafuente Ojeda, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Pérez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliva Perales, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo Villarroya, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puértolas Ortega, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo Villarroya,  J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La mutación del factor V Leiden, es la forma más frecuente        de trastorno trombofílico congénito, afectando al        5-8% de la población caucasiana.        La gestación supone, en sí misma, un estado de hipercoagulabilidad        que nos debe llevar a prestar especial        atención a todos aquellos factores de riesgo trombótico        que puedan sumarse. En los últimos años, el diagnóstico        de las nuevas variantes alélicas de los estados trombofílicos,        ha incrementado la incidencia de gestantes que        reciben anticoagulación con las consideraciones anestésicas        que ello conlleva.        Presentamos el caso de una mujer de 33 años de edad,        portadora heterocigoto de una mutación en el gen del        factor V Leiden, en tratamiento con heparina de bajo        peso molecular, que ingresa por amniorrexis espontánea        a la semana 38 de gestación. La paciente requirió analgesia        para el trabajo de parto, por lo que se le colocó un        catéter epidural cumpliendo los protocolos de seguridad        y prevención del hematoma epidural.        La anestesia epidural es la técnica de elección para        analgesia del trabajo de parto, en las pacientes con        hipercoagulabilidad, por sus efectos sobre la reología        vascular y su efecto antitrombótico</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;54(1): 41-44, ene. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053474</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Analgesia para trabajo de parto en paciente con mutación del factor V Leiden</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11690^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22170^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31485^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8657</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4258</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14312^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33772^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33361^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6737</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24296^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6558^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33361^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23557</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33772^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28857^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
