<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053579</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5274</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fear of Negative Evaluation Scale and Social Avoidance and Distress Scale: reliability and validity in a spanish adolescents sample</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this study is to explore the psychometric properties of the Fear of Negative Evaluation Scale (FNES) and the Social Avoidance and Distress Scale (SADS) in a sample of 1,012 Spanish adolescents attending school. First order factor analysis indicates the existence of a dominant factor (alpha= 085) in the FNES as well as five other less relevant factors, while the normalizing with Kaiser´s Oblimin rotation methos indicates that the SADS has two factors &#150; social avoidance and social distress, with alpha values of .77 and .73 respectively. TheFNES discriminated adolescents with and without psychopathologies in front of others with specific and generalized social anxiety, while the SADS discriminated each one of the four groups in front of the others. Both scales show adequate construct validity with distinct variables assessed through specific instruments measuring anxiety and social phobia along with other screening instruments</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zubeidat, Ihab</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sierra, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salinas, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio es examinar las propiedades psicométricas de la Escala de Miedo a la Evaluación Negativa (FNES) y la Escala de Evitación y Malestar Social (SADS) en una muestra de 1.012 jóvenes españoles escolarizados. El análisis factorial de primer orden señala la existencia de un factor dominante (alfa=0,85) para la FNES (y otros cinco de menor relevancia), mientras que el método de rotación normalización Oblimin con Kaiser indica que la SADS tiene dos factores (evitación social y malestar social) con valores alfa de 0,77 y 0,73, respectivamente. LA FNES discriminó entre adolescentes con y sin psicopatologías frente a otros con ansiedad social específica y generalizada, mientras que la SADS lo hizo entre cada uno de los cuatro grupos frente al resto. Ambas escalas muestran una validez de constructo adecuada con distintas variables evaluadas por instrumentos específicos de ansiedad fobia social y por otros de screening</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. salud;18(1): 57-81, 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053579</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Escala de Miedo a la Evaluación Negativa y Escala de Evitación y Malestar Social: fiabilidad y validez en una muestra de adolescentes españoles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5342^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13300^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
