<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037967</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Congenital rubella syndrome in Costa Rica: importance of active surveillance</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To identify cases of congenital rubella syndrome (CRS)and their form of presentation in children aged &lt; 3 months in the National Children&#146;s Hospital of Costa Rica between1996 and 2000.MethodsBetween 1996 and 2000, patients aged 1 day to 3 months with positive IgM serology for rubella, identified by means of the computerized database of the National Children&#146;s Hospital Laboratory, were selected. Their corresponding medical records were reviewed and the characteristics of these patients were analyzed. Results: Sixty-six children with positive serology were identified, of which 49 had a complete medical record that allowed review. Of these, 29 (60 %) were boys. The mean age at which IgM serology was requested was 33 days. The principal manifestations leading to serology were hepatospleno megaly, microcephaly and multiple congenital anomalies. The initial diagnosis was TORCH infection. Of the 49 patients, 45 were classified as CRS and four as infection with rubella. Conclusions: The present study highlights the need to increase active surveillance of CRS. Greater vigilance in applying the criteria for clinical diagnosis is required to allow an adequate degree of suspicion and early reporting of cases</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castillo-Solórzano, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morice-Trejos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ulloa-Gutiérrez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ávila-Agüero, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reef, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soriano-Fallas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Identificar los casos de síndrome de rubéola congénita(SRC) y su forma de presentación en niños menores de3 meses atendidos en el Hospital Nacional de Niños de1996 a 2000. Métodos: En el período de 1996 a 2000 se seleccionaron los pacientes de un día de edad a 3 meses, con un positivo de serologíaI gM por rubéola, identificados por medio del registro computarizado del laboratorio. Se revisó la historia clínica correspondiente, analizando las características delos pacientes. Resultados: Se identificaron 66 niños con serología positiva, 49 tenían historia clínica completa que permitió la revisión. De éstos, 29 (60 %) eran varones. La edad media en que se solicitó la serología fue de 33 días. La hepatosplenomegalia, la microcefalia y las polimalformaciones fueron las tres principales manifestaciones por las cuales se solicitó la serología. El diagnóstico inicial que predominó fue el TORCHS (toxoplasmosis, rubéola, citomegalovirus, herpes,sífilis). Tras la revisión final de los 49 casos, 45 pacientes se clasificaron como SRC y cuatro como infección por rubéola. Conclusiones: El presente estudio pone de manifiesto la necesidad dereforzar la vigilancia activa permanente del SRC. Se debe reforzar la búsqueda de signos y síntomas, así como los antecedentes maternos que permitan la sospecha adecuada y la comunicación oportuna de los casos de SRC</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);62(1): 43-47, ene. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037967</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de rubéola congénita en Costa Rica: importancia de reforzar la vigilancia activa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3379^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19342^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19342^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28442</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
