<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141746</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-2399</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Equivalent continuous noise level in neonatal intensive care unit associated to burnout syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Noise levels in neonatal intensive care units allow the appearance of symptoms associated with burnout such as stress, irritability, fatigue and emotional instability on health care personnel. The aim of this study was to evaluate the equivalent continuous noise levels in the neonatal intensive care unit and compare the results with noise levels associated with the occurrence of burnout syndrome on the care team. Continuous sampling was conducted for 20 days using a type I sound level meter on the unit. The maximum, the ninetieth percentile and the equivalent continuous noise level (Leq) values were recorded. Noise level is reported in the range of 51.4-77.6 decibels A (dBA) with an average of 64 dBA, 100.6 dBA maximum, and average background noise from 57.9 dBA. Noise levels exceed the standards suggested for neonatal intensive care units, are close to maximum values referred for noise exposure in the occupational standards and to noise levels associated with the onset of burnout; thus allowing to infer the probability of occurrence of high levels of noise present in the unit on the development of burnout in caregivers (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vélez-Pereira, AM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido Galindo, AP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camargo Caicedo, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los niveles de ruido en las unidades de cuidado intensivo neonatal facilitan la aparición de síntomas asociados al síndrome de burnout como estrés, irritabilidad, fatiga e inestabilidad emocional sobre el equipo asistencial. El objetivo del presente trabajo fue evaluar los niveles continuos equivalentes de ruido en la unidad de cuidado intensivo neonatal y comparar los resultados con los niveles de ruido asociados a la aparición del síndrome de burnout sobre el personal asistencial. Se realizó un muestreo continuo durante 20 días utilizando un sonómetro tipo I en la unidad. Se registraron los valores máximos, el percentil noventa y el nivel continuo equivalente de ruido (Leq). El nivel de ruido se reporta en un rango de 51,4-77,6 decibelios A (dBA) con un promedio de 64 dBA, un máximo de 100,6 dBA, y un ruido de fondo promedio de 57,9 dBA. Los niveles de ruido sobrepasan los estándares sugeridos para unidades de cuidado intensivo neonatal, se encuentran cercanos a los valores máximos de exposición a ruido contemplados en la normativa ocupacional y a los niveles de ruido asociados a la aparición de burnout; lo que permite inferir la alta probabilidad de incidencia de los niveles de ruido presentes en la unidad sobre el desarrollo del síndrome de burnout en el personal asistencial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Intensiva;26(3): 92-100, jul.-sept. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141746</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nivel continuo equivalente de ruido en la unidad de cuidado intensivo neonatal asociado al síndrome de burnout</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d16359^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9912^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24213^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32436^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30459^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
