<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61800</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validity of a Telephone Survey for Determining the Prevalence of Atopic Dermatitis and Its Seasonal Variation in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Atopic dermatitis is a eczematous disease of the skin with onset during childhood and subsequent flares. The UK Working Party (UKWP) defined the diagnostic criteria normally used for atopic dermatitis. The objective of this study was to assess the prevalence of atopic dermatitis according to these criteria. Methods. This was a 2-phase cross-sectional, epidemiologic computer-assisted telephone survey. Parents of children aged 14 years or less participated in the first phase to determine the prevalence of atopic dermatitis in Spain. In the second phase, 6 months later, parents of children with diagnosis of atopic dermatitis according to the UKWP diagnostic criteria in phase 1 were interviewed to assess seasonal variations in disease activity between the 2 phases. Results. In total, 1979 parents participated; 8.6 % of the children (95 % confidence interval, 7.4 %-9.8 %) were diagnosed with atopic dermatitis by telephone. Of these, 49.2 % had a family history of atopy and 41.3 % had been diagnosed with atopic dermatitis by a physician. Diagnosis by the physician and that made by interview agreed in 75.3 % of these cases. Of the factors associated with atopic dermatitis, it was found that increased body temperature, periods of stress, dust, use of/contact with wool or fiber clothes, and use of certain soaps and hygiene products showed seasonal variations. Conclusions. The estimated prevalence of atopic dermatitis in children between 0 and 14 years old in Spain was 8.6 %. Certain factors associated with disease flares showed seasonal variations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Díez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puig, Ll</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La dermatitis atópica (DA) es una enfermedad eccematosa de la piel que debuta en la infancia cursando a brotes. La UK Working Party definió los criterios diagnósticos de DA utilizados habitualmente. El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar la prevalencia de DA según estos criterios. Métodos. Estudio epidemiológico, transversal, mediante entrevista telefónica asistida por ordenador, con dos fases. Primera fase: participaron padres de niños &amp;#8804; 14 años, con objeto de calcular la prevalencia de la DA en España. Segunda fase: realizada 6 meses después, se entrevistó a aquellos padres con diagnóstico de DA en la primera fase según la UKWP, para determinar la existencia de estacionalidad en las lesiones de DA entre ambas fases. Resultados. Participaron 1.979 padres. Un total de 8,6 % (intervalo de confianza [IC]95 %: 7,4-9,8) de los niños fue diagnosticado de DA mediante entrevista telefónica. El 49,2 % de los niños tenía antecedentes familiares de atopia. El 41,3 % de los niños había sido diagnosticado de DA por un médico. En un 75,3 % coincidió el diagnóstico del médico con el realizado mediante entrevista. En este estudio se observó que, de los factores asociados a la DA, el aumento de la temperatura corporal, los periodos de estrés, el polvo, el uso/ contacto con prendas de lana o fibras y el uso de determinados jabones o productos de higiene personal presentan diferencias estacionales. Conclusiones. La prevalencia estimada de DA en niños de 0-14 años en España fue del 8,6 %. Algunos factores asociados a la exacerbación de la DA presentan carácter estacional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;100(4): 298-306, mayo 2009. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61800</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validez de una encuesta telefónica para determinar la prevalencia y la estacionalidad de la dermatitis atópica en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4553^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3893^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13700^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13700^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1856^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3893^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14067^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4553^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200905</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
