<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102372</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1972</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims. To analyze the cost  -usefulness and the efficiencyof the Units of Short Stay (UCE) understood as alternative to the hospitalization 24 hours 7 days ofthe week and his impact on the results in health. Material and methods. We retrieved studies analysing clinical effectiveness, efficiency and quality andrevision of selected references.Results. Low-quality evidence supports the hypothesis that SSUs are able to reduce overall length of stay in the whole hospital or department where they werecreated. There are not enough data to support any other advantages or benefits of SSUs when comparedwith other hospital units.Conclusions. This way, there exist information that indicatethe potential of the UCEs to improve the circuits of the complementary explorations, prescription,accomplishment and report, and of increasing the offer of attention health and social care in patients with medical sharp disease or chronicle sharpened. Furtherresearch is needed in order to define their exact role and to establish their optimal model (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Iglesias, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcos, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ceballos, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen. Analizar el coste &#150;utilidad y la eficiencia de las Unidades de Corta Estancia (UCE) entendidascomo alternativa a la hospitalización las 24 horaslos 7 días de la semana y su impacto sobre los resultadosen salud. Material y métodos. Búsqueda sistemática en Medlinee Índice Médico Español para evaluar datos relativos a estancia media, resultados clinicos y tasas dereingreso, entre otros. Resultados. Se observó que las UCE proporcionan cuidados de salud con efectividad. Además, se encontróevidencia de calidad baja que apoya que las UCE reducen la estancia media en el conjunto del hospital o del servicio considerado, sin encontrar evidencias que apoyen otros beneficios al compararlas con otro tipo de unidades de hospitalización.Conclusiones. Así, existen datos que indican la potencialidad de las UCEs para mejorar los circuitos de lasexploraciones complementarias, prescripción, realización e informe, y de aumentar la oferta de atenciónsociosanitaria extrahospitalaria en pacientes con enfermedad médica aguda o crónica agudizada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Todo hosp;(275): 15-18, jun. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102372</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La unidad de corta estancia (UCE) como herramienta para la mejora de la gestión hospitalaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6896^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54376^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
