<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60657</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: to describe the trends of use for opioid analgesics in theArea of Puertollano during the period 2001-2005, and to evaluate it as anoutcome measure after launching a Palliative Care Program in 2006.Method: an analysis of the five strong opioids most commonly prescribed.Data on use were obtained from the Pharmacy Service computerfiles. The prescription of opioid analgesics in primary, specialized, andhospital care were assessed and expressed as DHD (Defined Daily Dose per1,000 inhabitants per day) for the two first sanitary levels, and as DDD(Defined Daily Doses)/100 hospital stays for the third one, from 2001 to2006.Results: there is a gradual increase in the overall use of opioids thatmoves from 0.68 to 2.89 DHDs in primary care. The prescription of transdermalrelease opioids, which increased from 0.51 DHDs in 2001 to 2.80in 2006, should be highlighted. This represents 93% of total DHDs thisyear.DHDs prescribed by medical specialists increased in a more moderateway, from 0.02 to 0.06, and decreased slightly in 2006. Only oral morphineDHDs increased sharply in the past year, from 0.0003 DHDs in 2005 to0.0064 DHDs in 2006. Here, the DHDs for drugs administered in patchesaccount for almost the entire group too (99.2% in 2001), although itsshare declined slightly in 2006 (90.2%).In the hospital setting no correlation between DDDs used, eitheroverall or for each drug, and number of hospital stays was seen.However, in 2006 there was a significant increase in global consumption,particularly for morphine (60.8% of total DDDs/100 hospital stays),exceeding for the first time those of transdermal release opioids (31.6%)without a significant variation of case-mix warrants.Conclusions: there is continued growth in DHDs prescribed by bothspecialists and primary care physicians. However, hospital use evolves inan erratic manner. This behavior seems to be changing since palliativecare teams were implemented (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz Cortés, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sancho Zamora, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Maroto, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arteta Jiménez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ventura López, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: describir la evolución del consumo de analgésicos opioidesen el Área Sanitaria de Puertollano en el periodo 2001-2005 y evaluar elmismo tras la puesta en marcha en 2006 de un recurso de Cuidados Paliativoscomo medida de resultado.Método: análisis de los cinco opioides mayores más prescritos. Losdatos de consumo se obtuvieron del archivo informático del Servicio deFarmacia. Se evaluaron las prescripciones realizadas por Atención Primaria,médicos especialistas y en el hospital, expresado en DHD (dosis diariadefinida por mil habitantes por día) para los dos primeros niveles y enDDD (dosis diaria definida)/100 estancias para el tercero, entre los años2001-2006.Resultados: en Atención Primaria se observa un incremento progresivoen el consumo global de opioides, pasando de 0,68 a 2,89 DHD. Por fármacos,destaca la prescripción de opioides de liberación transdérmica, quese incrementa desde 0,51 DHD en 2001 hasta 2,80 DHD en 2006, representandoeste año el 93% de las DHD totales.Las DHD prescritas por médicos especialistas aumentan de forma másmoderada, de 0,02 a 0,06, y en 2006 disminuyen ligeramente. Sólo las demorfina oral se incrementan acusadamente en este último año, pasandode 0,0003 DHD en 2005 a 0,0064 DHD en 2006. También aquí las DHD defármacos administrados en parches suponen casi la totalidad del grupo(99,2% en 2001), aunque disminuye el porcentaje ligeramente en 2006(90,2%).En el ámbito hospitalario, no se observa correlación entre las DDDconsumidas, ni de manera global ni para cada uno de los fármacos, con elnúmero de estancias hospitalarias. Sin embargo en 2006 existe un incrementoimportante del consumo global y de morfina en particular (60,8%de las DDD/100 estancias totales), que supera por vez primera al de opioidesde liberación transdérmica (31,6%), sin que una variación apreciabledel case-mix lo justifique. (...) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;15(6): 346-350, nov.-dic. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60657</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución de la prescripción de analgésicos opioidesen atención primaria, especializada y hospitalaria delÁrea Sanitaria de Puertollano. 2001-2006</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4422^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d715^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10334^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
