<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152585</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recommendations of the Spanish Society of Cardio-Respiratory Rehabilitation (SORECAR) on rehabilitation after lung resection surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Lung resection surgery is the only curative option in the early stages of lung cancer but carries a high risk of perioperative morbidity and mortality. Proper surgical risk stratification and pre-surgical optimization of the patient's overall situation are key elements to reduce the risk of postoperative complications. Surgery, together with possible adjuvant therapies, may impact negatively on functional capacity and quality of life in many patients. Consequently, a group of experts was appointed by the Spanish Society of Cardio-Respiratory Rehabilitation (SORECAR) to review all the available evidence on functional assessment in surgical risk stratification and on pre- and postsurgery rehabilitation in order to create a document that applied their findings to clinical practice. As a result, an action plan has been defined for rehabilitation during the pre- and postsurgical stages of lung resection with instructions or recommendations presented as a checklist. The aim of creating this document was to enhance the role of rehabilitation after lung resection surgery and to agree on interventions in this area (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Ortún, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Cabello, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayordomo Riera, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La cirugía de resección pulmonar es la única opción curativa en las fases tempranas del cáncer de pulmón, pero sigue presentando una alta morbimortalidad perioperatoria. Una correcta estratificación del riesgo quirúrgico y una optimización de la situación general del paciente precirugía son elementos claves para disminuir el riesgo de complicaciones postoperatorias. Por otro lado, la cirugía junto a las posibles terapias adyuvantes impactan de manera negativa en la capacidad funcional y en la calidad de vida de muchos pacientes. Un grupo de expertos fue nombrado por la Sociedad Española de Rehabilitación Cardio-Respiratoria (SORECAR) para que realizaran una revisión de todas las evidencias disponibles sobre la evaluación funcional en la estratificación del riesgo quirúrgico y sobre la rehabilitación pre- y poscirugía de resección pulmonar y para que elaboraran un documento aplicándolas a la práctica clínica. Así se ha diseñado un protocolo de actuación en rehabilitación durante la fase pre- y poscirugía de resección pulmonar, con instrucciones o recomendaciones a modo de resumen. Con esto se pretende potenciar el papel de la rehabilitación en la cirugía de resección pulmonar y consensuar el modo de actuar en este campo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);50(2): 108-124, abr.-jun. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152585</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recomendaciones sobre rehabilitación en la cirugía de resección pulmonar de la Sociedad Española de Rehabilitación Cardio-Respiratoria (SORECAR)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28466^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29636</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1270^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30213^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1270^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
