<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105446</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Incidence, resource use and costs associated with postherpetic neuralgia: a population-based retrospective study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To determine the incidence rate, the treatment administered and the use of health resources and health, and their respective costs in patients with postherpetic neuralgia (PHN). Patients and methods. We performed an observational design, made from retrospective review of patient records from six primary care centers and one hospital. All patients &gt; 30 years consulting for PHN between 1/1/2007 and 31/12/2010  were included. Prepared two study groups according to presence / absence of PHN. Follow up was for one year. Main measures: socio-demographic, treatment and co-morbidity. The cost model differed direct healthcare costs (primary care/ specialist) and indirect (productivity). Statistical analysis: logistic regression models and analysis of covariance (p &lt; 0.05). Results. 1506 patients were recruited, age: 61.2 years female: 59.2%. 15.1% (n = 228, 95% CI = 8.1-22.1%) had a PHN  (incidence rate: 0.8/1,000 inhabitants/year; 95% CI = 0.7-0.9/1,000 population/year), and increased with age (&amp;#8805; 65 years:19.7%). The PHN was principally associated with: psychosis (OR = 3.9), dementia (OR = 2.3), depression (OR = 1.8) and  age (OR = 1.1), p &lt; 0.03. Drugs use was higher (5.3 vs. 3.3; p &lt; 0.001). The cost in primary care was 63.1% and 24.7% indirect. Total cost &#128;1827.1 vs. &#128;457.5 (p = 0.003), respectively, due to higher labour productivity losses (&#128;692.2 vs. &#128;62.4) and health costs (&#128;1135 vs. &#128;395.1); p &lt; 0.001. All cost components maintained these differences. Conclusions. PHN is a frequent complication. These patients have a significant economic burden. The cost increases with age (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Ronco, Julián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sicras Mainar, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez Nolla, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Artieda, Ruth</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar la tasa de incidencia, los tratamientos administrados y la utilización de recursos sanitarios y no sanitarios, y sus costes respectivos, en pacientes con neuralgia postherpética (NPH). Pacientes y métodos. Se efectuó un estudio observacional, realizado a partir de la revisión retrospectiva de registros de  pacientes de seis centros de atención primaria y un hospital. Se incluyeron todos los pacientes mayores de 30 años que demandaron atención por NPH entre el 1 de enero de 2007 y el 31 de diciembre de 2010. Se elaboraron dos grupos de estudio según la presencia/ausencia de NPH. El seguimiento fue durante un año, y las principales medidas fueron sociodemográficas, tratamientos y comorbilidad. El modelo de costes diferenció los costes sanitarios directos (atención primaria/ especializada) e indirectos (productividad laboral). Se realizó un análisis estadístico con modelos de regresión logística y  análisis de la covarianza (p &lt; 0,05). Resultados. Se reclutaron 1.506 pacientes, con una edad media de 61,2 años, de los cuales el 59,2% eran mujeres. El 15,1% (n = 228; intervalo de confianza al 95%, IC 95% = 8,1-22,1%) presentó NPH (tasa de incidencia: 0,8/1.000 habitantes/ año; IC 95% = 0,7-0,9/1.000 habitantes/año) y el porcentaje aumentó con la edad (&amp;#8805; 65 años: 19,7%). La NPH se asoció principalmente a psicosis (odds ratio, OR = 3,9), demencia (OR = 2,3), depresión (OR = 1,8) y edad (OR = 1,1); p &lt; 0,03. El uso de medicamentos fue superior (5,3 frente a 3,3; p &lt; 0,001). El coste en atención primaria fue del 63,1% y los costes indirectos del 24,7%. Los costes totales fueron de 1.827,1 frente a 457,5 euros (p = 0,003), respectivamente,  debido a mayores pérdidas de productividad laboral (692,2 frente a 62,4 euros) y costes sanitarios (1.135 frente a 395,1 euros; p &lt; 0,001). Todos los componentes del coste mantuvieron estas diferencias. Conclusiones. La NPH es una complicación frecuente. Estos pacientes presentan una importante carga económica y el coste aumenta con la edad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;55(8): 449-461, oct. 2012. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105446</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incidencia, uso de recursos y costes asociados a la neuralgia postherpética: estudio retrospectivo de base poblacional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50489^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6721^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31925^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
