<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118943</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Emergent drugs (III): hallucinogenic plants and mushrooms</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">An increase in the consumption of vegetable substances with a hallucinogenic effect has been observed. Some of these substances are associated with ancestral religious ceremonies, while many of them are legal or are partially regulated. Salvia divinorum is a powerful kappa receptor agonist, with dissociative and hallucinogenic properties, which startquickly and have a short duration. Kratom (Mytragyna speciosa) has mitragynine as its principal alkaloid, with stimulating effects at low doses (coke-like effect), and sedative effects(opiate-like effect) at high doses. Several deaths from its consumption have been detected. The consumption of hallucinogenic mushrooms appears in cyclic form, although there has been increase in their online offer. They are consumed in search of their hallucinogenic effects, above all those belonging to the family of psilocybes, which contain tryptamines with a hallucinogenic effect similar to LSD. Peyote (Lophophora psilocybes), a cactus rich in mescaline (trimet oxifeniletilamina),produces hallucinations of the five senses, and forms part of the religious culture of the North American Indians. Daturas, which are ubiquitous, produce anticholinergic symptoms and effects on the central nervous system (delirium, hallucinations, etc.), due to their high atropineand scopolamine content. Other substances used for their hallucinogenic effects include the drink known as ayahuasca, and seeds for preparing infusions like Ololiuqui, Morning Glory (Ipomoea violacea), Hawaian Baby Wood rose (Argyreia nervosa), Syrian Rue (Peganum harmala) and Iboga Rootbark (Tabernan the iboga) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hoffman, R. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Munné Mas, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Climent Díaz, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinillos, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Briz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burillo-Putze, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nogue Xarau, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se ha observado un aumento del consumo de sustancias vegetales con efecto alucinógeno, algunas de ellas asociadas a ceremonias religiosas ancestrales, siendo muchas de estas sustancias legales o con una regulación parcial. Salvia divinorum es un potente agonista de los receptores kappa, con propiedades disociativas y alucinógenas, de inicio rápido y corta duración. El Kratom (Mytragyna speciosa), posee como alcaloide principal la mitraginina, con efectos estimulantes a dosis bajas (efecto coca-like), y efectos sedativos (efecto opioide-like) a dosis altas. Se han detectado varias muertes asociadas a su consumo. El consumo de hongos alucinógenos aparece de forma cíclica, aunque se ha incrementado su oferta on-line. Se consumen buscando sus efectos alucinógenos sobre todo los pertenecientes a la familia de los psilocybes, los cuales contienen triptaminas con efecto alucinógeno, similar al LSD. El peyote (Lophophora williamsii), cactus rico en mescalina (trimet oxifeniletilamina), produce alucinaciones de los cinco sentidos, y forma parte de la cultura religiosa de los indios norteamericanos. Las daturas, de gran ubicuidad, producen un cuadro anticolinérgico y efectos sobre el sistema nervioso central (delirios, alucinaciones, etc), por su alto contenido en atropina y escopolamina. Otras sustancia utilizadas por sus efectos alucinatorios incluyen la bebida conocida como ayahuasca, y semillas para preparación de infusiones como el Ololiuqui, la Gloria de la mañana (Ipomoea violacea), la Rosa de Hawai (Argyreia nervosa), la Ruda borde (Peganum harmala), y la Iboga (Tabernan the iboga) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;36(3): 505-518, sept.-dic. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118943</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Drogas emergentes (III): plantas y hongos alucinógenos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6366</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36945</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23138</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d369</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24318^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9375</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
