<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037532</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-2760</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Deaths by human vascular trauma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Vascular trauma is cause of high mortality inside variety of        traumas that the population suffers. This is indirect        relationship to the caliber and place of the affected vessels,        as well as the time lapsed between the trauma and medical        action. The analysis of the data gathered in 291 deaths by        human vascular trauma was the objective of this study        carried out in a 10 - year's period. The highest percentage        was present during the weekends especially during the        evening from 6 pm to 6 am with 66.6% of the cases. Those        Anales de Cirugía Cardíaca y Vascular 2005;11(2):64-68        Correspondencia:        Yasmín Rodríguez Ríos        Villuendas, 208        Sta Clara. Villa Clara        50100 Cuba        Trauma vascular mortal        Original        produced by knife cut, represented 64.7%, followed by        traffic accident and firearms recorded 22.6% and 8.9%        respectively. The greatest number of cases, 227, died in        situ, 51 died in the hospital and 13 died on the way to        health unit. Homicides represented 58.1% and the suicidal        attempts 5.8%. The wounds of the thoracic vessels whit        41.9% greatest number of the deaths, followed by lesser        abdominal wounds with 24.7%, skull and extremities in        15.1% and the facial skull wounds in 3.2%. The data        offered show the incidence of vascular trauma as the cause        of mortality in the population, as well as the danger of the        weekends and evening schedule. Surveillance and safety        measures protection to the population should be reforced        to avoid the production of human vascular trauma</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lugo Jauriga, Bárbara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moro Rodríguez, Rubén T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Delgado, Rosendo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Ríos, Yasmín del Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Seco, Felicia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El trauma vascular es causa de alta mortalidad dentro de        la variedad de traumas que sufre la población. Esta en        relación directa al calibre y sitio del vaso afectado, así        como al tiempo transcurrido entre el trauma y la acción        médica. El análisis de los datos recopilados en 291 fallecidos        por trauma vascular mortal fue el objetivo de        este estudio realizado en un periodo de 10 años. La        mayor incidencia se presento en el grupo de 25 a 34        años, así como en el sexo masculino. Los fines de semana        acumularon los mayores por cientos de ocurrencia y        en especial en los horarios nocturnos de 6 pm a 6 am,        con el 66,6% de los casos. Los producidos por armas        blancas ocuparon el 64,7% de su etiología, seguido por        los accidentes del transito y las armas de fuego con el        22,6% y el 8,9%, respectivamente. El mayor numero de        casos, 227, fallecieron en el lugar del hecho, 51 en el        hospital y 13 en el trayecto hacia la unidad asistencial.        Los homicidios ocurrieron en el 58,1% y los intentos        suicidas en el 5,8%. Las heridas a nivel de los vasos        toráxicos con el 41,9% provocaron el mayor numero de        muertes, siguiéndoles en orden decreciente los abdominales        con el 24,7%, cráneo y extremidades en el 15,1%        para ambos y en menor proporción los cráneo faciales        con solo el 3,2%. Los datos ofrecidos muestran la importancia        que tiene el trauma vascular como causa de        mortalidad en la población, así como la peligrosidad de        los fines de semana y el horario nocturno. Las medidas        de vigilancia y protección a la población deben ser extremadas        para evitar la producción de los hechos causantes        de trauma vascular mortal</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. cir. card. cir. vasc;11(2): 64-68, mar.-abr. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037532</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trauma vascular mortal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34253^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34253^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34253^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5688^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5688^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34253^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5688^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15346^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15346^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34253^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
