<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129969</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Possibilities of access to canals in mandibular first premolars with complex anatomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Using an in vitro study, the possibilities to diagnose, locate and negotiate root canals in mandibular first premolars with different anatomical complexity were analyzed. Material and methods. 32 mandibular first premolars divided into two groups (A and B) of samples each were used. Group A consisted of teeth with low anatomical complexity and group B with evident complexity. Performed endodontic access, with K files the canals were localized along its length or as far as possible. After fixing the instruments in place with cyanoacrylate adhesive teeth were radiographed and with diamond disks four cross sections were obtained from the roots (Levels coronal, middle, and proximity of the apical foramen). On digitized images of each was determined percentage of not localized canals. A chi-square test was used. Results. It was found that the frequency of this variable was significantly higher (p &lt;0.05) in group A than in B, only in the middle and apical zone of the roots. These apparently incoherent findings should be because it is more difficult to find and canalize multiple canals in a single-rooted tooth than others where the root division is certainly more defined. Radiographic examination allowed a diagnosis about the anatomical complexities. Conclusions. The possibilities of finding and exploring the canals were paradoxically lower in low anatomical complexity teeth. Understanding aspects of the complex anatomy contributes to successful endodontics (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zampa, Carola</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gani, Omar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lía Arena, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Comba, Bernanada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Gabriel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Mediante un estudio in vitro, se analizaron las posibilidades de diagnosticar, localizar y canalizar los conductos radiculares en primeros premolares inferiores con distinta complejidad anatómica. Material y métodos. Se utilizaron 32 primeros premolares inferiores divididos en dos grupos (A y B) de 16 muestras cada uno. El grupo A estuvo compuesto por piezas de escasa complejidad anatómica y el B, por piezas de evidente complejidad. Realizado el acceso endodóntico con limas K, se canalizaron los conductos en toda su longitud o hasta donde fuera posible. Luego de fijar los instrumentos en su posición con un pegamento instantáneo y de radiografiar todas las muestra, se obtuvieron cuatro secciones transversales de las raíces (niveles coronario, medio, apical y proximidades del foramen) con discos diamantados. Sobre imágenes digitalizadas de todos ellos se estableció el porcentaje de conductos no canalizados). Se aplicó el test chi cuadrado. Resultados. Se comprobó que las diferencias entre grupos de esta variable, más frecuentes en el grupo A que en el B, eran significativas (p&lt; 0,05) solo en los sectores medio y apical de las raíces. Estos resultados, aparentemente incoherentes, se deberían a que es más difícil canalizar conductos múltiples en un diente   unirradicular que en otro donde la división radicular es más definida. El examen radiográfico permitió un diagnóstico aproximado de la complejidad anatómica. Conclusiones. Las posibilidades de localizar y explorar los conductos fueron paradójicamente menores en dientes de escasa complejidad anatómica. Conocer aspectos de la complejidad anatómica contribuye al éxito endodóntico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);31(2): 61-70, abr.-jun. 2013. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129969</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Posibilidades de acceso a los conductos en primeros premolares inferiores de anatomía compleja</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14461^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32617^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55116</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12764^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12765^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1666^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
