<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156104</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Microbiology, antibiotic susceptibility, and bacteraemia associated factors in acute prostatitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The aim of the study was to analyze the characteristics of patients with acute prostatitis presenting to the Emergency Department, the microbiological findings, antibiotic susceptibility, and bacteraemia associated factors. Methods. Observational and cohort study with prospective follow-up including patients with acute prostatitis presenting to the Emergency Department from January-December 2012. Data were collected for demographic variables, comorbidities, microbiological findings, antibiotic treatment and outcome. Results. Two hundred and forty one episodes of acute prostatitis were included. Mean age was 62.9 ± 16 years, a history of prostate adenoma was reported in 54 cases (22.5%) and prior manipulation of the lower urinary tract in 40 (17%). Mean symptoms duration was 3.38 ± 4.04 days, voiding symptoms were present in 176 cases (73%) and fever in 154 (64%). Seventy patients (29%) were admitted to the hospital and 3 died. From 216 urine cultures, 128 were positive (59%) and 24 (17.6%) out of 136 blood cultures. Escherichia coli was the main pathogen (58.6% of urine cultures and 64% of blood cultures) with resistant strains to fluoroquinolones, cotrimoxazole and amoxicillin/clavulanic in 27.7%, 22.9% and 27.7% of cases respectively. In the univariate analysis, only chills were associated to bacteraemia (p=0.013). At 30-day follow-up, patients with bacteraemia returned more frequently to the Emergency Department (p=0.037) and were more often admitted to the hospital (p=0.003). Conclusions. Patients with acute prostatitis discharged from the Emergency Department need clinical follow-up and monitoring of microbiological findings in order to assure an adequate antibiotic treatment. Return to Emergency Department and admission to the hospital were significantly more frequent among patients with bacteraemia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jacob, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llopis, Ferrán</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferré, Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Analizar las características de las prostatitis agudas atendidas en el servicio de urgencias, la microbiología, las resistencias antibióticas y los factores asociados a bacteriemia. Método. Estudio analítico observacional de cohorte con seguimiento prospectivo de las prostatitis agudas atendidas entre enero y diciembre de 2012 en el servicio de urgencias. Se incluyen los datos relativos a la edad, comorbilidad, episodios previos, clínica, microbiología, tratamiento y evolución. Resultados. Se registraron 241 episodios de prostatitis agudas con edad media 62,9±16 años, antecedentes de patología prostática en 54 casos (22,5%) y manipulación de la vía urinaria en 40 (17%). La duración de los síntomas fue de 3,38 ± 4,04 días, con clínica urinaria en 176 casos (73%) y fiebre en 154 (64%). Ingresaron 70 pacientes (29%) y se registraron 3 exitus. Se obtuvo aislamiento en 128 de 216 (59%) urinocultivos y 24 de 136 hemocultivos (17,6%). Escherichia coli se aisló en el 58,6% de los urinocultivos y 64% de los hemocultivos con cepas resistentes a quinolonas, cotrimoxazol y amoxicilina/clavulánico en el 27,7%, 22,9% y 27,7% de los casos respectivamente. En el análisis univariante la bacteriemia se asoció a la presencia de escalofríos (p=0,013) e incrementó la reconsulta en el servicio de urgencias (p=0,037) y el reingreso hospitalario a los 30 días (p=0,003). Conclusiones. Los pacientes con prostatitis agudas dados de alta del servicio de urgencias requieren seguimiento y monitorización para garantizar un tratamiento adecuado. La bacteriemia incrementa la reconsulta en el servicio de urgencias y el reingreso hospitalario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;29(4): 190-194, ago. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156104</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Microbiología, sensibilidad antibiótica y factores asociados a bacteriemia en la prostatitis aguda</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11915^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24244^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29181^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10553^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36322</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
