<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154952</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1582</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Microvesicles in breast cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Microvesicles (exosomes and microparticles) are subcellular bodies. They constitute a cell-to-cell signalling system, both locally and at a distance, and are able to carry both cell surface biomarkers and genetic material, influencing cell behaviour. These vesicles participate in tumorigenesis, including angiogenesis and amplification of tumour clones, among other processes. They have been identified in some clinical series as markers of poor prognosis and even as markers of cancer-associated complications such as thrombotic events. These subcellular bodies have a promising role as a 'transport vehicle' or 'signal vector' to selectively direct microRNA or molecules able to modify tumour behaviour, and may even have a therapeutic role, through transmission of proapoptotic factors or tumour suppressors, respectively. In addition, selective microvesicle ultrafiltration systems are under development, which are able to eliminate those microvesicles that play a precursor role in tumour development. The results obtained in breast cancer are scarce but promising, insofar as they open up new areas of knowledge in tumour biogenesis, due to their value both in early diagnosis and in tumour prognosis and even as predictive biomarkers. This article reviews the literature on the role of microvesicles in breast cancer, with special emphasis on related clinical studies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ayala de la Peña, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luengo-Gil, Ginés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morena Barrios, Pilar de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Garre, Elisa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las microvesículas (exosomas y micropartículas) son cuerpos celulares derivados que conforman un sistema de transmisión de señales entre células, tanto local como a distancia, capaces de portar tanto marcadores de superficie celular como material genético, interviniendo en el comportamiento celular. Participan en los procesos de tumorogénesis, desde la angiogénesis hasta la amplificación de clones tumorales, entre otros. Han sido identificadas en algunas series clínicas como factores de mal pronóstico o incluso marcadores de complicaciones asociadas al cáncer como los eventos trombóticos. Con un prometedor papel como vehículo de transporte para dirigir de forma selectiva microRNA o moléculas capaces de modificar el comportamiento tumoral, con un enfoque terapéutico, a través de la transmisión de factores proapoptóticos o supresores tumorales. Así como con el desarrollo de sistemas de ultrafiltración selectiva de microvesículas. En cáncer de mama son aún escasos los resultados obtenidos pero sí prometedores, en cuanto que abren una nueva línea de conocimiento en la biogénesis tumoral, por su valor tanto en diagnóstico precoz como en su asociación con el pronóstico tumoral e incluso como marcadores predictivos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. senol. patol. mamar. (Ed. impr.);29(3): 125-131, jul.-sept. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154952</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Microvesículas en cáncer de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55206^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24373^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52986^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52986^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55206^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52990^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
