<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118653</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">T-pattern detection in combat sports</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">By identifying and analysing temporal patterns (T-patterns) in behaviour, this study aims to detect technical errors and behavioural sequences in the kosoto gari judo throw, and, based on this, to propose changes to the way in which judo is taught. The participants (n = 50: 38 men and 12 women; Mage = 19.23 years, SD = 1.12) were students studying for a physical education and sports science degree with no previous experience of judo. This was a systematic observational study in which the students were filmed performing the kosoto gari technique. The results, derived from descriptive statistics and a sequential analysis of T-patterns conducted by means of Theme 5, revealed that the students committed a series of typical errors when learning to perform the throw. Furthermore, these errors often appeared in sequence, mainly involving a lack of balance, the position of the feet and hips/trunk, an incorrect reap and the final arm movement. The results can be used to propose movement sequences that would ensure that the throw is learnt correctly, and also to enable recommendations to be made regarding the use of feedback (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hileno, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto, Iván</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camerino, Oleguer</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Santiago, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lapresa, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de esta investigación es implementar el análisis y detección de las estructuras temporales de los acontecimientos deportivos o patrones temporales o T-pattern para detectar los errores técnicos y sus secuencias conductuales en la proyección de judo kosoto-gari y así proponer cambios metodológicos en los procesos de enseñanza del judo. Los participantes (n = 50; 38 hombres y 12 mujeres; M = 19.23 años; DE = 1.12), estudiantes del grado en CAFE sin experiencia previa en judo, se sometieron, a partir de un estudio observacional sistemático, a un registro en video de la ejecución de la técnica de estudio. Los resultados, determinados mediante estadística descriptiva y análisis secuencial de T-Patterns obtenido con el programa Theme 5, corroboran que existe una serie de defectos típicos que comete el sujeto en el aprendizaje de esta proyección, así como unas secuencias de errores en cadena, que básicamente afectan al desequilibrio, a la posición de los pies y cadera-tronco, a la incorrecta acción de siega y a la acción final de los brazos. Estos resultados nos permiten proponer, en el aprendizaje del judo, secuencias de movimientos que garanticen el éxito en la proyección y recomendaciones sobre la utilización del feedback (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;23(1): 147-155, ene.-jun. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118653</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Detección de T-patterns en la observación de deportes de combate</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12436</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1700^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29036^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1700^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33544^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
