<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036483</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Health related problems as cause of visits to hospital emergency departments</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE: Medication-related problems (MRPs) are health problems resulting-from patient pharmacotherapy failure that interfere with the expected outcome in the patient&#146;s health status. The aim of this study was to discover the health problems associated with the appearance of MRPs. PATIENTS AND METHOD: Patient interviews, together with the assessment of medical records were the sources of information used in the assessment and identification of MRPs. A validated questionnaire was used for the interviews; in order to classify the health problems found, the ICD-9 was used. RESULTS: 2,556 patients were interviewed over a period of one year at a hospital emergency department.2,261 of these cases were valid. Osteoarticular diseases, poorly defined signs and symptoms of illness, injuries and intoxications were the disorders most commonly associated with the appearance of MRPs. MRPs of necessity and effectiveness had a similar profile. MRP sof safety were more commonly associated with poorly defined signs and symptoms of illness, injuries and intoxications, as well as nervous, digestive and blood problems. CONCLUSIONS: Most frequent medication related health problems causing visits to hospital emergency departments were osteoarticular disorders, followed by poorly defined signs and symptoms of illness. Differences were observed in the diagnoses between the different dimensions and types of MRP</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zarzuelo Zurita, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baena Parejo, M. Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín Iglesias, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Faus Dáder, M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Martín, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Olmos, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">FUNDAMENTO Y OBJETIVO: Los problemas relacionados con los medicamentos (PRM) son problemas de salud que se producen como consecuencia de fallos de la farmacoterapia del paciente y que interfieren con los resultados esperados de salud. El objetivo de este trabajo es conocer los problemas de salud más frecuentes que constituyen PRM. PACIENTES Y MÉTODO: La entrevista con el paciente junto con la evaluación de la historia clínica son las principales fuentes de información para evaluar e identificar PRM. Se utilizó un cuestionario validado como instrumento para la entrevista y la CIE-9 para la clasificación de los problemas de salud encontrados. RESULTADOS: Se entrevistó a un total de 2.556 pacientes durante 1 año en el servicio de urgencias hospitalario, de los que se estudiaron 2.261 tras las exclusiones. Las enfermedades osteoarticulares, los signos y síntomas mal definidos y las lesiones y envenenamientos son los problemas más relacionados con la aparición de PRM. Los PRM de necesidad y efectividad mantienen un perfil similar. Los PRM de seguridad se asociaron más a signos y síntomas mal definidos y lesiones y envenenamientos así como a alteraciones nerviosas, digestivas y sanguíneas. CONCLUSIONES: Los PRM más frecuentes que son causa de consulta en un servicio de urgencias hospitalario son los osteoarticulares, seguidos de los signos y síntomas mal definidos. Se observan diferencias en los diagnósticos entre las distintas dimensiones de PRM y sus tipos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);124(7): 250-255, feb. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036483</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Problemas de salud relacionados con los medicamentos en un servicio de urgencias hospitalario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30279^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4421^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8677^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
