<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90705</identifier>
<setSpec>0465-546X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aims of this paper are: 1) to evaluate Spanishscientific publications on Occupational Health between1971 and 2007, based on data collected fromthe IME database; 2) to present the features relatedto authorship, and the connections and potentialcooperation among researchers; and 3) to determineemerging topics and main areas of interest.Through a derived search methodology, wehave carried out an exhaustive scanning of IMErecords on Occupational Health, selected accordingto relevance. The results of this search wereexported and analysed with the ProCite referencemanager. This procedure allowed us to perform asurvey of authorship and connections, and ananalysis of temporal sets by descriptors and categories.The results are 1,530 references of publicdocuments from 180 scientific journals, conferencesand book chapters. The average figure of authorsper article is 2.6. One third of the authorspublished only one article on the topic. The subjectmost frequently studied belongs to the field ofOrganizational Psychology.The conclusions we have arrived at are: 1)there is a high level of cooperation among authors,a low level of specialisation, as it refers both toauthorship and to journals where scientific papersare published; 2) a rising trend in the field of OrganizationalPsychology, with a clear increase in thisarea during the last four years (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso Arévalo, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Rodero, Helena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Castilla, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: evaluar la producción científicaespañola en salud laboral entre los años 1971 y 2007a partir de los datos recogidos en la base de datosIME. Establecer las características relativas a laautoría, filiación y nivel de cooperación de los investigadoresy determinar cuáles son las materias emergentesy cuáles son las áreas de interés principales.Método: a través de la metodología de búsquedaderivada se ha realizado un barrido, lo másexhaustivo y pertinente posible, en la base dedatos IME de los registros sobre salud laboral. Losdatos obtenidos han sido exportados y analizadosa través del gestor de referencias ProCite. Medianteel tabulado de los datos se realiza un estudio dela autoría y filiación, y se efectúa un análisis deseries temporales por descriptores y categorías.Resultados: 1530 referencias de documentospublicados procedentes de 180 revistas, congresosy partes de libros. El promedio de autores es de 2,6autores por artículo. Un tercio de los autores sóloha publicado un artículo sobre el tema. Las materiasmás estudiadas pertenecen al ámbito de la psicologíadel trabajo.Conclusiones: se constata un alto nivel de cooperaciónentre autores, así como una baja especialización,tanto en la autoría, como en las revistasen las que se publican los trabajos. Se observa unacurva ascendente en los temas relativos al campode la psicología del trabajo, con un notable incrementoen los últimos cuatro años (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;54(211): 61-73, jun. 2008. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90705</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Producción científica española sobre salud laboral indizada en el Índice Médico Español (IME)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13421^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28904^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50089</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
