<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154847</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-7606</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Functional and legal repercussions of an Organic personality disorder following a stroke</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The organic personality disorder causes a significant alteration of the habitual patterns of behavior displayed by the subject premorbidly, involving the expression of emotions, needs and impulses. We report the case of a 49-year-old woman who, after suffering a cerebral infarction, presented a transformation of her personality traits and previous values. She was previously a person with multiple fears, careful, methodical in her daily life. After the cerebral infarction she began to present conducts of provocation and major disinhibition, impulsiveness, minor tolerance to the frustration, minimal capacity of planning and resolution of problems. In addition, she was unable to preserve any work and lost the social relationships. Neuroimaging studies (CT, MR), EEG and a neuropsychological assessment were conducted. The obtained results are compatible with an Organic Personality Disorder disinhibited subtype, clinically characterized by emotional liability, disinhibited behavior and lack of impulses control. The organic personality disorder is a chronic irreversible disease that is affecting the self-government patient´s ability and therefore relevant forensic psychiatric aspects must be assessed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Ruiz, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Basterra-Gortari, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El trastorno orgánico de la personalidad supone una alteración significativa de las formas habituales del comportamiento premórbido, afectando particularmente a la expresión de las emociones, necesidades e impulsos. Se presenta el caso de una mujer de 49 años de edad que, tras padecer un infarto cerebral, presentó una transformación de su personalidad y de sus valores previos. Anteriormente era una persona con múltiples miedos, cuidadosa, metódica en su vida diaria. Tras el infarto comenzó a presentar conductas de provocación y una mayor desinhibición e impulsividad, menor tolerancia a la frustración, así como mínima capacidad de planificación y resolución de problemas. Además, fue incapaz de conservar ningún trabajo y perdió las relaciones sociales. Se realizaron estudios de imagen (tomografía computarizada (TC) y resonancia magnética (RM)), electroencefalograma (EEG) y una evaluación neuropsicológica. Los resultados obtenidos son compatibles con un trastorno orgánico de la personalidad subtipo desinhibido, caracterizado clínicamente por la tendencia a la labilidad emocional, la desinhibición conductual y la falta de control de impulsos. El trastorno orgánico de la personalidad es una afectación crónica e irreversible que está influyendo en la capacidad de autogobierno de la paciente, y por ello deben valorarse los aspectos psiquiátrico-forenses pertinentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. med. forense;21(3/4): 169-174, jul.-dic. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154847</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Repercusiones funcionales y legales de un trastorno orgánico de la personalidad tras un infarto cerebral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10742^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16925^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d991^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2583^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2583^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d991^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1907^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1907^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16925^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16925^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2583^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16925^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16925^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
