<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115050</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4466</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Private Institutes of &#147;pure&#148; Research Versus Public Policy on Science and Technology in Argentina (1943-1955)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In June 1943 took place a coup d&#146;etat in Argentina that initiated a process of confrontation between an important sector of academic scientists and the de facto military government. As a result, many scientists lost their positions at universities, between them a group of biomedical scientists led by the physiologist Bernardo Houssay, who was to be awarded the Nobel Prize in Physiology in 1947. From that moment on, supported by local philanthropists and the Rockefeller Foundation, Houssay&#146;s group began to promote the creation of a series of private research institutes. This process continued during the democratic government of Juan Perón (1946-1955). This article analyzes this &#147;project&#148; &#151;its motivations and objectives&#151; as a process of &#147;parallel&#148; institutionalization which was divergent from the initiatives promoted for science and technology by the public sector. This &#147;splitting&#148; of the institutionalization process, embodied in ideologies, institutional models and hardly compatible epistemic hierarchies, would have far-reaching consequences for the future development of research in Argentina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hurtado, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En junio de 1943 se produjo en la Argentina un golpe de Estado que inició un proceso de enfrentamientos entre un importante sector de científicos académicos y el gobierno militar de facto. Como resultado, muchos científicos perdieron sus cargos en las universidades, entre ellos el grupo liderado por el fisiólogo Bernardo Houssay, que iba a obtener el premio Nobel de Fisiología en 1947. A partir de ese momento, este grupo de médicos impulsaron la creación de una serie de institutos privados de investigación sostenidos por filántropos locales y por la Rockefeller Foundation. Este proceso continuó durante el gobierno democrático de Juan Perón (1946-1955). El presente artículo analiza este &#147;proyecto&#148; de creación de institutos privados &#151;sus motivaciones y objetivos&#151; como un proceso de institucionalización &#147;paralelo&#148; y divergente respecto de las iniciativas impulsadas para la ciencia y la tecnología desde el sector público. Este &#147;desdoblamiento&#148; del proceso de institucionalización, encarnado en ideologías, modelos institucionales y jerarquías epistémicas difícilmente compatibles, iba a tener consecuencias de largo alcance para el futuro desarrollo de la investigación en la Argentina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Asclepio;65(1): 1-17[10], ene.-jun. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115050</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Institutos privados de investigación &#147;pura&#148; versus políticas públicas de ciencia y tecnología en la Argentina (1943-1955)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1121^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50070</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6442^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11490</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12075^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12967^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38885</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
