<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78491</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Attitude of the adult patient with atopic dermatitis to the disease and its treatment: The ACTIDA Study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the attitude of adult patients with atopic dermatitis (AD) to their disease and its treatment. Material and methods: A multicenter, cross-sectional study was performed in patients with at least 2 outbreaks of AD in the previous year. Results: Two hundred twenty-seven dermatologists recruited 1441 analyzable patients, the majority women, with a mean of 3.6 outbreaks per year. Most of the patients (97.2%) indicated that they always or sometimes requested medical evaluation of a new outbreak. In the most recent outbreak, 72.2% had used combined therapy, regardless of the severity of the episode; 2-drug combinations were the most common. The majority of dermatologists prescribed combined therapy, most commonly a 2-drug combination for mild or minimal disease, and 3 or more drugs for moderate to very severe outbreaks. Conclusions: Treatments used by patients for an outbreak of AD are similar to those prescribed by dermatologists in recent outbreak (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferrer, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izu, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lleonart, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrando, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Betlloch, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: Conocer la actitud de los pacientes adultos frente a la dermatitis atópica (DA) y su tratamiento. Material y métodos: Estudio transversal, multicéntrico, realizado en pacientes con al menos 2 brotes en el último año. Resultados: Doscientos veintisiete dermatólogos reclutaron 1.441 pacientes analizables, mayoritariamente mujeres con 3,6 brotes al año de media. La mayoría de los pacientes (97,2%) indicó que solicitaba, al menos ocasionalmente, asesoramiento médico ante nuevos brotes. El 72,2% recurrió a la terapia combinada (TC) en el último brote, independientemente de su intensidad, siendo las combinaciones de 2 fármacos (TC2) las más utilizadas. Los dermatólogos indicaron mayoritariamente TC, siendo la TC2 más frecuente para formas leves y casi sin enfermedad, y la TC de más de 2 fármacos en brotes moderados a muy graves. Conclusiones: Los tratamientos empleados por los pacientes ante un brote de DA son similares a los indicados por los dermatólogos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;101(2): 143-150, mar. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78491</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actitud del paciente adulto con dermatitis atópica frente a su patología y tratamiento. Estudio ACTIDA</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3893^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3893^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3893^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32860^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7344^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23899</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
