<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93902</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The possibilities of expressive movement and creative dance tasks to provoke emotional responses</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Recent research has focused on the influence of emotions on sport performance, as well as on the state of wellbeing among those who engage in physical activity. The aim of this study was to analyse the emotional responses of students engaging in expressive movement and creative dance, as well as observe the influence of type of task on these responses. Eighty students from a degree course in physical activity and sport sciences participated in fourteen, fiftyminute expressive movement and creative dance sessions. After each session, the students all recorded in personal diaries the sensations and emotions they experienced during each task. The diaries were analysed by three researchers, who classified the emotions and the tasks. The results showed that engaging in this activity primarily provokes comments related to positive emotions and that type of task may condition the emotions experienced (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Planas, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dinusôva, Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torrents, Carlota</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateu, Mercé</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Actualmente existe un creciente interés por la influencia de las emociones en el rendimiento deportivo, así como en la actividad física relacionada con el bienestar. El objetivo de este estudio fue analizar las respuestas emocionales de estudiantes durante la práctica de Expresión Corporal y observar la influencia del tipo de tarea. 80 estudiantes de primer curso de Ciencias de la Actividad Física y el Deporte participaron en 14 sesiones de 50 minutos de Expresión Corporal. Escribieron un diario después de cada sesión, en el que se recogían las emociones y sensaciones experimentadas en cada tarea. Tres investigadoras los analizaron, clasificaron las emociones y las relacionaron con el tipo de tareas. Los resultados muestran que la práctica de la Expresión Corporal provoca eminentemente comentarios relacionados con emociones positivas y que el tipo de tarea parece condicionar las emociones que se desencadenan (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;20(2): 401-412, jul.-dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93902</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Posibilidades de las tareas de expresión corporal para suscitar emociones en el alumnado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7872</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3173</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3423</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33140^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53742^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
