<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054460</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Follicular cystitis. Case report and bibliographic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: To report one case of chronic follicular cystitis and to perform a bibliographic review on this pathology. CASE REPORT: We report a case of a 70-year-old woman with an irritative voiding syndrome over an eight-month period, with several previous episodes of urinary tract infection treated by her family doctor. Bullous lesions were found in the bladder mucosa on cystoscopy. Histological tests showed lymphoid follicles at the level of the bladder mucosa, leading to the diagnosis of follicular cystitis. RESULTS: Medical treatment was carried out with ciprofloxacin, vitamin A, and prednisone, which led to symptom remission. CONCLUSIONS: Follicular cystitis is an entity that belongs to the group of chronic cystopathies; it is a non-specific chronic inflammatory disease characterized by the presence of large number of plasmatic cells and lymphocytes in lymphoid follicles within the bladder mucosa and submucosa; pathologic study is necessary for the final diagnosis of this entity</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Parra Pérez, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lallave Martín, Fátima</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toledo Serrano, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateos Blanco, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Zambrana, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laguna Álvarez, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVOS    Aportar un caso clínico con diagnóstico de cistitis crónica folicular y revisión de la literatura existente sobre esta patología.         METODOS    Describimos el caso de una mujer de 70 años con síndrome miccional irritativo de 8 meses de evolución, con varios episodios previos de infección urinaria tratados por su médico de cabecera y en cuyo estudio se descubrió lesiones bullosas vesicales durante la cistoscopia; el estudio histológico demostró folículos linfoides a nivel de la mucosa vesical, permitiendo el diagnóstico de cistitis folicular.         RESULTADOS    Se inicio tratamiento médico con ciprofloxacino, vitamina A y prednisona remitiendo la sintomatología.         CONCLUSIONES    La cistitis folicular es una entidad que pertenece al grupo de las cistopatías crónicas, al tratarse de un proceso inflamatorio inespecífico crónico que se caracteriza por presentar a nivel de mucosa y submucosa células plasmáticas y linfocitos constituyendo folículos linfoides, siendo imprescindible el estudio histológico para diagnosticar esta patología</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;60(1): 77-80, ene.-feb. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054460</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cistitis folicular. Aportación de un caso y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3574^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3574^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
