<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165553</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characteristics of structural injuries in pediatric patients with focal epilepsy in a Honduran hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Epilepsy is the most commonly occurring neurological disorder in the world. The study of structural brain lesions is important to understand the secondary complications. In Honduras there is little information on this topic. Aim. To determine the characteristics and proportion of structural brain lesions in paediatric patients with focal epilepsy at the Hospital Escuela Universitario. Patients and methods. A descriptive, cross-sectional, retrospective-prospective study. The study population consisted of 162 paediatric patients with focal epilepsy who were treated in the paediatric neurology outpatient department between January 2015 and June 2016. On applying the eligibility and exclusion criteria, the universe of study comprised 102 patients with focal epilepsy. Results. 41% of the patients with focal epilepsy presented a structural lesion. The main locations of the structural lesions were the parietal lobe (12.8%), the occipital lobe (10.8%) and the frontal lobe (10.8%). An association was found between the presence of structural brain lesions and the presence of uncontrolled seizures, with statistical significance. The attributable risk was calculated and it was found that among patients with uncontrolled seizures, 67% had a structural lesion in the imaging study. Conclusions. The presence of uncontrolled seizures is associated to the presence of structural lesions in imaging studies, with a high attributable risk. Leukomalacia and cerebral ischaemia were the main findings that were reported. The predominant structural lesions in paediatric patients with focal epilepsy in the population studied are those related to events that take place during the peripartum period (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Varela-González, Douglas</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez-Izcoa, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fonseca, Marta I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La epilepsia es el trastorno neurológico con mayor ocurrencia en el mundo. El estudio de las lesiones estructurales cerebrales es importante para comprender las complicaciones secundarias. En Honduras existe poca información sobre este tema. Objetivo. Determinar las características y proporción de las lesiones estructurales cerebrales en los pacientes pediátricos con epilepsia focal del Hospital Escuela Universitario. Pacientes y métodos. Estudio descriptivo, transversal, retrospectivo-prospectivo. La población de estudio fue de 162 pacientes pediátricos con epilepsia focal, atendidos en la consulta externa de neurología pediátrica entre enero de 2015 y junio de 2016. Al aplicar los criterios de inclusión y exclusión, el universo de estudio se constituyó en 102 pacientes con epilepsia focal. Resultados. El 41% de los pacientes con epilepsia focal presentó lesión estructural. Las principales ubicaciones de las lesiones estructurales fueron el lóbulo parietal (12,8%), el lóbulo occipital (10,8%) y el lóbulo frontal (10,8%). Se encontró asociación entre la presencia de lesiones estructurales cerebrales y la presencia de crisis convulsivas no controladas, con significación estadística. Se realizó el cálculo de riesgo atribuible y se encontró que en los pacientes con crisis convulsivas no controladas, el 67% tenía lesión estructural en el estudio de imagen. Conclusiones. La presencia de crisis convulsivas no controladas se asocia a la presencia de lesiones estructurales en el estudio de imagen, con un riesgo atribuible alto. La leucomalacia y la isquemia cerebral fueron los principales hallazgos comunicados. Las lesiones estructurales predominantes en los pacientes pediátricos con epilepsia focal de la población estudiada son las relacionadas con eventos durante el periparto</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;65(3): 105-111, 1 ago., 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165553</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características de las lesiones estructurales en pacientes pediátricos con epilepsia focal en un hospital de Honduras</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30325^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6877^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9614^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
