<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045693</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Post-stroke depression (II): its differential diagnosis, complications and treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. Post-stroke depression (PSD) is the most frequent neuropsychiatric condition after a stroke. We review thedifferential diagnosis of PSD, PSD complications and the different therapeutic approaches to PSD. Development. Differentialdiagnosis includes post-stroke fatigue and the pseudo-depressive manifestations of strategic infarctions (apathy, aprosody,lack of self psychic activation syndrome, pathological crying syndrome). Functional and cognitive complications of untreatedPSD can be observed. Mortality in depressed stroke patients has been estimated between 3.5 and 10 times higher than in nondepressed stroke patients; suicide ideation can be observed in 11.3% of stroke patients. Clinical trials controlled with placebohave shown the efficacy of fluoxetine, nortriptiline, trazodone and citalopram in the treatment of PSD. Other therapeuticapproaches include cognitive and functional rehabilitation. Conclusion. PSD is a potentially treatable condition, infradiagnosed,that has a negative effect on cognitive function, functional recovery and survival in stroke patients. State of the artof PSD pharmacological treatment are selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors. However, there are no data showing neithersuperiority of one specific drug nor the best moment to start treatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carod-Artal, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. La depresión postictus (DPI) es el trastornoneuropsiquiátrico más frecuente tras un ictus. Revisamos el diagnósticodiferencial y las complicaciones asociadas a la DPI, asícomo las diferentes alternativas terapéuticas existentes. Desarrollo.El diagnóstico diferencial de la DPI incluye la fatiga postictusy las manifestaciones pseudodepresivas por infartos estratégicos(apatía, aprosodia, falta de activación psíquica, estados de labilidademocional). Existen complicaciones cognitivas y funcionalesasociadas a la DPI no tratada. La mortalidad en pacientes con ictusdeprimidos es 3,5-10 veces mayor que en aquellos no deprimidos,y la ideación suicida puede presentarse en un 11,3% de lossupervivientes de un ictus. Ensayos clínicos controlados con placebohan mostrado la eficacia de la fluoxetina, la nortriptilina, la trazodonay el citalopram en el tratamiento de la DPI. Otros abordajesterapéuticos incluyen la rehabilitación cognitiva y la propiarehabilitación funcional. Conclusión. La DPI es una condición potencialmentetratable, infradiagnosticada, que tiene un efecto negativosobre la función cognitiva, la recuperación funcional y lasupervivencia tras un ictus. El tratamiento farmacológico de primeraelección son los inhibidores selectivos de la recaptación deserotonina. Sin embargo, ningún estudio evidencia una superioridadde un fármaco específico sobre otro, ni el mejor momento parainiciar el tratamiento</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;42(4): 238-244, feb. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045693</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Depresión postictus (II). Diagnóstico diferencial, complicaciones y tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
