<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118941</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of ocular drugs in pregnancy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The information available on the safety of medicines in pregnant women is limited and must be suitably channeled. Medication that is applied topically or as eye drops can present relevant systemic absorption and cross the placenta barrier or enter maternal milk. We have reviewed ophthalmic medicines according to the fetal risk categories proposed by the classification of the Food and Drug Administration (FDA). We evaluate the medicines of choice in the most frequent ophthalmic pathologies, as well as the medicines that must be avoided (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rebollo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arruti, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcaine, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mezquita, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andonegui, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La información disponible sobre la seguridad de los fármacos en mujeres embarazadas es limitada y debe ser adecuadamente canalizada. Los fármacos de aplicación tópica o en colirio pueden presentar una absorción sistémica relevante y atravesar la barrera placentaria o pasar a la leche materna. Se realiza una revisión de los fármacos oculares según las categorías de riesgo fetal propuestas por la clasificación de la Food and Drug Administration (FDA).Se evalúan los fármacos de elección en las patologías oculares más frecuentes, así como los fármacos que deben evitarse (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;36(3): 479-487, sept.-dic. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118941</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso de fármacos oculares en el embarazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5443^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5231^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10063^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
