<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042430</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Primary endometriosis of the abdominal wall: an entity to be included in the differential diagnosis of abdominal wall masses</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Endometriosis consists of the presence of extrauterine endometrial tissue. It is usually localized in the pelvis, although it can also be found in other sites. Cutaneous localization is unusual and the most frequent form appears on scars from obstetric or gynecological interventions. It can, however, develop spontaneously, especially in umbilical or inguinal areas and can be confused with irreducible hernias or granulomas.  We present the cases of three patients with spontaneous endometriotic nodules of the abdominal wall. The lesions were located in the umbilical region in two patients and in the suprapubic area in one. In two patients clinical suspicion led to preoperative diagnosis, although diagnosis is usually established after histopathological analysis of the surgical specimen (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Caro, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomás, Federico</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Malagón, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parra, Pedro A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se denomina endometriosis a la presencia de tejido endometrial extrauterino. Su localización habitual es intrapélvica, aunque puede localizarse en otros lugares. La localización cutánea es rara y la forma más frecuente aparece sobre cicatrices de intervenciones ginecológicas u obstétricas, aunque puede aparecer de forma espontánea, sobre todo en la zona umbilical o inguinal, y puede confundirse con hernias no reductibles o granulomas. Presentamos los casos de 3 pacientes con nódulos endometriósicos espontáneos en las pared abdominal, dos en localización umbilical y otro suprapúbico, en dos de los cuales se pudo establecer el diagnóstico preoperatoriamente ante la sospecha clínica, aunque lo habitual es que el diagnóstico se establezca tras el estudio anatomopatológico de la pieza de resección (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);79(1): 64-66, ene. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042430</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Endometriosis primaria de pared abdominal, una enfermedad que debe ser considerada en el diagnóstico diferencial de las tumoraciones de la pared abdominal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4794^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4794^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
