<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122925</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Estimating the burden of disease due to permanent disability in Spain during the period 2009-2012</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Permanent disability (PD) is a major social and economic burden. The aim of this study was to determine the burden of disease due to PD. Methods: Using data from the Continuous Working Life Sample (CWLS) -a random sample consisting of 4% of the active members affiliated to the Social Security (SS) System in Spain (1.1 million members) which data come from administrative registries from the SS- the diagnosis of PD (2009-2012) was established from the information on the temporary sickness absence (TSA) episodes from 2009. The diagnoses were imputed if two criteria were fulfilled: long duration of TSA and short period of time between the TSA episode and PD. The burden of disease was estimated for cases with an established diagnosis of PD by using the potential years of working life lost (PYWLL), estimated as the difference between the legal retirement age (65 years) and the age at the start of a PD. Results: In the CWLS, 163,135 (13.6%9 individuals suffered a TSA episode in 2009, out of which 4,738 were granted a PD pension in the period of 2009-2012. The diagnosis was established for 3,073 (64.9%) cases. A large percentage of PD was produced by musculoskeletal (27.4%) and mental disorders (11.6%), likewise these diagnoses produced more PYWLL due to a PD: 11,086 (26.5%) and 7,052 (16.9%), respectively. Mental disorders produced PD at younger ages (median= 49 years of age). Conclusion: Mental and musculoskeletal disorders represent a major burden of disease produced by PD and measured by PYWLL. The diagnoses of PD should become available in order to estimate with more accuracy the PYWLL produced by PD and specific diagnoses (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez, José Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benavides, Fernando G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrée López, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Duran, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espallargues, Mireia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: La incapacidad laboral permanente (IP) supone una importante carga social y económica. El objetivo de este estudio fue estimar la carga de enfermedad debida a la IP en España. Métodos: A partir de la Muestra Continua de Vidas Laborales (MCVL) se imputó como diagnóstico de la IP (2009-2012) el de la incapacidad temporal (IT) iniciada en 2009 en los individuos que cumplieron dos criterios: larga duración de la IT y corta duración del período entre la IT y la IP. Para los casos con diagnóstico imputado se calculó la carga de enfermedad por IP a partir de los años potenciales de vida laboral perdidos (APVLP), definidos como la diferencia entre la edad de jubilación (65 años) y la edad de inicio de la IP. Resultados: Según la MCVL, 163.135 (13,6%) personas sufrieron de IT en 2009, de las cuáles a 4.738 (0,39%) se le reconoció una IP entre 2009-2012. Se pudo establecer el diagnóstico de IP en 3.073 (64,9%) casos. Las causas más frecuentes de IP fueron los trastornos musculo-esqueléticos (27,4%) y mentales (11,6%) que, asimismo, produjeron mayor cantidad de APVLP por IP: 11.086 (26,5%) y 7.052 (16,9%), respectiva- mente. Los trastornos mentales destacaron por producir IP a edades más jóvenes (mediana=49 años). Conclusiones: Los trastornos mentales y los musculo-esqueléticos representaron la mayor carga de enfermedad en individuos en situación de IP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;88(3): 349-358, mayo-jun. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122925</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estimación de la Carga de enfermedad por incapacidad laboral permanente en España durante en el período 2009-2012</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32711^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30935^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30392^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d44</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28397</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
