<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95858</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1473</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Long-term outcomes of lumbar microdiscectomy in a working class sample</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. In the treatment of the lumbar discherniaton (LDH) microdiscectomy constitutes one ofthe standard procedures. In the present study we haveanalyzed the clinical outcome of the lumbar microdis-cectomy in a series of worker patients who underwentsurgery in our service.Methods. Retrospective analysis and a 5-year followup, of a series of 142 patients operated on by means oflumbar microdiscectomy in the 2004-2005 period. Theclinical outcome was analyzed according to the &#147;Herronand Turner&#148; outline: pain reduction, use of medicaltreatment, restriction in the ability to perform physicalactivities, and return to work.Results. 116 men and 26 women, with an average ageof 37.9 and 45.4 years respectively, underwent surgerybecause of LDH. In the clinical aspect, sciatica waspredominant over low back pain in a ratio of three toone. The L5-S1 discal level was operated on in 68.3% ofthe cases. It was considered that occupational activitiesgave rise to damage in 107 patients (75.3%). Besides asymptomatic disc, there was an additional injured discin 44.3% of the cases. An initial unfavourable outcomewas seen in 42 patients (33%), 15 of which recoveredfrom in an interval of 3 months, and another fifteenwithin a one year period. A re-operation was (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Quiñones, J. V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arregui, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aso, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Consolini, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La microdiscectomía constituye un procedimiento estándar en el tratamiento de la hernia discal lumbar (HDL). En este estudio se ha analizado el resultado clínico de la microdiscectomía lumbar en una muestra de pacientes laboralmente activa, intervenidos en nuestro servicio. Material y métodos. Análisis retrospectivo y seguimiento durante 5 años, de una muestra de 142 pacien- tes intervenidos mediante microdiscectomía lumbar durante el bienio 2004-2005. El resultado clínico se evaluó en base al esquema propuesto por Herron y Turner, que evalúa la reducción del dolor, el uso de fármacos, la restricción de las actividades físicas y el regreso a la vida laboral. Resultados. 116 hombres y 26 mujeres, con edades medias de 37,9 y 45,4 años, respectivamente, fueron intervenidos por HDL. Clínicamente la ciatalgia pre- dominó sobre la lumbalgia en una proporción de 3 a 1. El nivel discal L5-S1 fue intervenido en el 68,3% de los casos. Se consideró el origen del padecimiento como accidente de trabajo en 107 pacientes (75,3%). En el 44,3% de la serie además del disco sintomático, existía un disco adicional afecto. Se apreció una evolu- ción postquirúrgica inicial desfavorable en 42 pacientes (33%), 15 de los cuales se recuperaron en el plazo de 3 meses, y otros quince a lo largo de un año. Fue preciso reintervenir a 16 pacientes por recidiva discal (11%). La reinserción laboral se consiguió en el 83,8% (119/ 142) de los pacientes  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurocirugia (Astur);22(3): 235-244, ene.-dic. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95858</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados a largo plazo de la microdiscectomía lumbar en una población laboralmente activa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31505^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7568^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9054^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201100</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
