<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99303</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8799</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Physiological response during sport climbing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Scaling is a sports activity that consists of the accomplishment of ascents on walls of strong slope using physical force, technical ability, psychological capacity and, generally, using special footwear as the only form of help. The search to overcome and dominate the sport, prompts the need to define and study characteristics of the climber. In doing so, it also provokes the need for improvement in methods and techniques used for training. During an ascent, quite demanding activities take place, in which the time of accomplishment ranges from between 2 to 7 minutes. 5/8 of that working time is spent in static positions (rests, decision making, safety settings, etc.) The remaining time is spent in overcoming movements. The consecutive muscular actions of support (isometric) and progression (isotonic)in the vertical position cause VO2 levels in turn to reach 20-25 ml/kg/min(with the ability to reach30ml/kg/min). These levels remain elevated in post-exercise time. There is an out of proportion increase of heart rate in relation to the VO2. The loss of take hold resistance has been correlated with lactate accumulation. The reached values range from 2.1 and 6.1 mmol/l, observing greater increasing difficulty of the route. This may indicate that the greater clearance of the metabolized substances, during recovery phase, increases the ability of repeating the efforts (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lancho, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Poblador, María S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez, Víctor M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La escalada es una actividad deportiva que consiste en la realización de ascensiones en paredes de fuerte pendiente valiéndose de la fuerza física, la habilidad técnica, la capacidad psicológica y, por lo general, utilizando como única ayuda un calzado especial. La búsqueda de la superación y del rendimiento deportivo, provocan la necesidad de definir y estudiar las características del escalador, así como la mejora de los métodos y técnicas empleados para el entrenamiento. Durante una ascensión, se producen actividades bastantes exigentes, en las que los tiempos de realización oscilan entre 2 y 7 minutos, donde 5/8 del tiempo de trabajo se emplea en posiciones estáticas (descansos, toma de decisiones, aseguramientos, etc.) y el tiempo restante en movimientos de superación. Las sucesivas acciones musculares de sostén (isométricas) y de progresión (isotónicas)en la vertical provocan valores de VO2 en torno a 20-25 ml/kg/min, pudiendo llegar a 30 ml/kg/min, manteniéndose elevados en el tiempo post -ejercicio, existiendo un incremento desproporcionado de la frecuencia cardiaca en relación alVO2. Las pérdidas de resistencia de agarre se han correlacionado con la acumulación de lactato. Los valores alcanzados oscilan entre 2,1 y 6,1 mmol/l, observándose mayores incrementos con la dificultad de la ruta. Parece indicar, que la mayor eliminación de las sustancias metabolizadas, durante las fases de recuperación, aumenta la capacidad de repetir los esfuerzos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. med. deporte;27(135): 48-56, ene.-feb. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99303</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Respuesta fisiológica durante la escalada deportiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1721^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
