<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133683</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5274</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Attending to dementia caregivers diverse needs: Contributions from cognitivebehavioral therapy and acceptance and commitment therapy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Looking after an elderly relative with dementia is associated with negative emotional consequences for caregivers. The present paper describes a cognitive-behavioral therapy (CBT) and an acceptance and commitment therapy (ACT) that were designed to reduce emotional distress in the caregiver. The objective of CBT is to modify dysfunctional beliefs and thoughts related to caregiving and to train caregivers to increase the frequency of gratifying activities; it also includes training in relaxation and in skills for seeking help. ACT involves working in particular on three aspects: on the identification of the caregiver&#146;s personal pattern of experiential avoidance and the alternative of acceptance of emotions, thoughts and feelings; on helping caregivers to identify their values and the barriers to acting in coherence with them; and on increasing caregivers&#146; motivation to commit themselves to their values and perform actions and activities coherent with those values (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Moreno, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Losada, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Fernández, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nogales González, Celia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez González, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Cuidar a un familiar mayor con demencia se asocia con consecuencias emocionales negativas para los cuidadores. En este trabajo se describe una terapia cognitivo-conductual (TCC) y otra de aceptación y compromiso (ACT) que han sido diseñadas para reducir el malestar emocional de los cuidadores. El objetivo de la TCC es modificar creencias y pensamientos disfuncionales relacionados con el cuidado y entrenar a los cuidadores en el aumento de la frecuencia de actividades gratificantes. Incluye además entrenamiento en relajación y en habilidades para pedir ayuda. A través de la terapia ACT se trabaja la identificación del patrón personal de evitación experiencial y la alternativa de la aceptación de emociones, pensamientos y sensaciones, se ayuda al cuidador a identificar sus valores y las barreras para la acción coherente con ellos y se trabaja para incrementar la motivación del cuidador para comprometerse con sus valores y llevar a cabo acciones coherentes con dichos valores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. salud;26(1): 41-48, mar. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133683</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Atendiendo a las variadas problemáticas de los cuidadores familiares de personas con demencia: aportaciones de la terapia cognitivo-conductual y de la terapia de aceptación y compromiso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14190^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14190^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14190^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14190^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
