<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88648</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hundred Sixty years teaching Applied Geology to Pharmacy. At the crossroads of Bologna Process</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The study of pharmaceutical and cosmetic mineral raw materials, their properties, their specificresearch methods, regulating norms and test for their use, and other new applications for the humanhealth that have been opened during the last decades owing to the development of Science andTechnology, has been a obligatory subject of teaching in the Pharmacy studies of the GranadaUniversity until the implantation of the new studies of Grade promoted by the Bologna Process.This communication relates the history of the subject "Applied Geology to Pharmacy", their differentdenominations and Professors who have had, analyzes in detail the current scientific content and itsfuture lines of research and challenges. All these discussions in the context of the role that has playeduntil today in the Faculty of Pharmacy as in the training of pharmaceutics. And to compose a scientificbasis and line of thinking, which allows to objectively analyze the current situation and future of thesubject "Applied Geology to Pharmacy"(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gámiz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez Crespo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Calvo-Flores, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín García, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Calvo-Flores, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Párraga, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El estudio de las materias primas farmacéuticas y cosméticas de origen mineral, sus propiedades,métodos de investigación específicos, normas de obligado cumplimiento para el uso y otros nuevosámbitos y aplicaciones de carácter sanitario que se han ido abriendo con el desarrollo de la Ciencia yla Técnica durante las últimas décadas, ha sido una asignatura de obligada impartición en los estudiosde Farmacia hasta la implantación del Nuevo Grado auspiciado por la puesta en práctica del PlanBolonia.En esta Comunicación se relata la historia de la asignatura, sus diferentes denominaciones y profesoresque ha tenido; se analizan en detalle sus contenidos científicos actuales y sus retos futuros: Todo elloen el marco del papel jugado hasta el presente en la Facultad de Farmacia en la formación delfarmacéutico, y para componer una base científica y argumental, que permita analizar objetivamente lasituación actual y las perspectivas futuras(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;51(supl.2): 324-330, mayo 2010. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88648</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ciento Sesenta años de Geología Aplicada a la Farmacia. En la encrucijada de Bolonia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4582^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4582^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4582^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3478^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51770^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5982^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51492</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51493</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
