<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055522</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Urodynamic findings in patients older than 65 years: experience in the Department 19 of the health-care area of Valencia (HCAV)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: This work tries to analyze the urodynamic studies performed in patients over the age of 65 years in the Department 19 of HCAV with the aim of reviewing our activity in this population segment between January 2001 and September 2006, and to perform a clinical-urodynamic correlation which will help to find a diagnosis avoiding the need to repeat urodynamic tests. METHODS: We perform a descriptive transversal study with retrospective analysis of data from patients older than 65 years who underwent urodynamic tests. Total population in this age range in our health-care department(HCD) (HCD 19) is 35.260 inhabitants (12% of total population)(Valencia health care agency. HealthcareManagement HCD 19. Alicante General University Hospital. May 2005). In this population 41% are males (14.620 people) and 59% females (20.637 people)RESULTS: Among males, the most frequent urodynamic finding is infravesical obstruction in almost half of the cases (48%), followed by bladder hyperactivity in 19%, and idiopathic bladder hyperactivity and urgency incontinencewith 10%, respectively. No reproducibility of the symptoms reaches 9% of the cases. On the other hand, in females the most frequent finding is mixed urinary incontinence in 25% of the cases, followed by bladder hyperactivity 17%, urgency incontinence 14% and stress urinary incontinence 13%. No reproducibility of the symptoms reached 11%. In the opposite extreme are intravesical obstruction and sphincter/detrusor dyssynergiawithout any case. CONCLUSIONS: We find that people between 70 and 75 years old are the population group undergoing a greater number of urodynamic tests in our area. The most frequent urodynamic tests performed at our departmentwas pressure/flow study with evaluation of post void residual. Urethra profile was reserved for recurrent stress urinary incontinence after surgery. Obstructive symptoms in males and mixed urinary incontinence in females were the most frequent causes for the indication of urodynamic tests. Our symptom no-reproduceability rates were below 10% of the cases</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Belvis Esclapes, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galiano Baena, Juan F. </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giner Santamaría, Claudio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero Romeu, Juan Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leivar Tamayo, Asier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lobato Encinas, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: En este trabajo se pretende analizar los estudios urodinámicos realizados en mayores de 65 años en el Departamento 19 de la Agencia Valenciana de Salud (AVS) a fin de revisar nuestra actividad en ese segmento poblacional adscrito, durante el periodo de enero del 2001 y septiembre del 2006 y realizar una correlación clínico-urodinámica que ayude a alcanzar un diagnóstico evitando la necesidad de repetición de pruebas urodinámicas. MÉTODOS: Para ello, se ha realizado un estudio descriptivo transversal con análisis retrospectivo de los pacientes mayores de 65 años a los que se ha realizado un estudio urodinámico. El total de la población comprendida en este rango de edad de nuestro Departamento Sanitario (D.S. número 19) es de 35260 habitantes (12% del total de la población). Agencia Valenciana de Salud. Dirección Asistencial Departamento Sanitario número 19. Hospital General Universitario de Alicante. Mayo 2005). Dentro de este grupo poblacional,el 41% son varones (14620 personas) y el 59% son mujeres (20637 personas). RESULTADOS: En varones, el hallazgo exploratorio urodinámico más frecuente es el de obstrucción infravesical en casi la mitad de los casos (48%), siendo en segundo lugar la hiperactividad vesical con un 19% y la hiperactividad vesical idiopática a la par de la IUU con un 10% de nuestra población masculina. La no reproductibilidad de los síntomas alcanza el 9% de los casos. Por otro lado, no se confirma ningún caso de IUM, urgencia sensitiva ni micción no coordinada en los varones. Por otro lado, en la mujer lo más frecuente es la IUM con un 25% de los casos, seguido de la hiperactividad vesical con un 17%, la IUU con un 14% y la IUE con un 13% de la población femenina. La no reproductibilidad de los síntomas alcanza el 11%. En el otro extremo se encuentra la obstrucción infravesical y la disinergia detrusor/esfinteriana en los que no se presenta en ningún caso. CONCLUSIÓN: Como conclusión encontramos que es la población entre 70 y 75 años el grupo poblacional al que se realizaron mayor número de exploraciones urodinámicas, en nuestro trabajo.El test urodinámico más frecuentemente practicado en nuestro Servicio fue el Estudio P/F con medición del residuo postmiccinal. El test de perfil uretral se reservó para la IUE recidivante tras cirugía previa. La sintomatología obstructiva en el varón y la IUM en la mujer fueron las causa que más condujeron a solicitar test urodinámicos. Nuestras tasas de no reproductibilidad de síntomas no superaron el 10% de los casos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;60(6): 656-663, jul.-ago. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055522</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hallazgos urodinámicos en mayores de 65 años: experiencia en el departamento 19 del Área Valenciana de Salud (AVS)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14963^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26426</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
