<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122551</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinicopathological and immunohistochemical findings in melanocytic matricoma. A case report and a review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The matricoma melanoma is a rare, recently described cutaneous neoplasm. It appears in elderly patients as a papulo-nodular pigmented lesion in areas with long standing exposure to the sun. The histopathological characteristics are a biphasic proliferation of both dendritic melanocytes and basaloid epithelial cells with varying nuclear atypia and mitotic activity, and numerous interspersed shadow cells. Immunohistochemical studies for  -catenin highlighted the morphology of the basaloid cells and focal expression of cytokeratins AE1/AE3, while studies for Melan A, HMB-45 and S-100 protein confirmed the dendritic melanocyte component. The clinicopathological and immunohistochemical findings and differential diagnosis of a new case are described, together with a review of the literature. Approximately only 12 cases have been previously reported(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Narváez Moreno, Basilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zulueta Dorado, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luján Rodríguez, David</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El matricoma melanocítico es una neoplasia cutánea inusual descrita recientemente. Clínicamente se presenta como una lesión papulo-nodular pigmentada en personas añosas, localizada en zonas con daño solar crónico. Histológicamente se caracteriza por una proliferación celular bifásica constituida por células dendríticas melanocíticas y células epiteliales de hábito basalioide con áreas focales de atipia citológica y figuras mitóticas dispersas entremezcladas con células en sombra. El estudio inmunohistoquímico muestra positividad del componente basalioide para  -catenina y focal para citoqueratinas AE1/AE3, mientras que las células dendríticas melanocíticas son positivas para Melan A, HMB45 y S-100. Presentamos los hallazgos clinicopatológicos, inmunohistoquímicos, diagnóstico diferencial y revisión de la literatura de un nuevo caso recientemente diagnosticado en nuestro servicio. En la actualidad existen aproximadamente 12 casos publicados en la literatura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;47(2): 122-126, abr.-jun. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122551</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Matricoma melanocítico: hallazgos clinicopatológicos e inmunohistoquímicos. Presentación de un caso y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19148^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31276^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
