<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102591</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8799</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Current exercise and type 2 diabetes (II)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus (T2DM) is a very common disease worldwide and represents an important cause of morbidity and mortality. Its incidence and prevalence have increased overall in recent decades and if urgent action is not taken the problem will grow with consequences for the patient&#146;s, health system and socioeconomic factors of the regions. It is shown that changes in lifestyle - regular exercise, healthy  weight and eating - can prevent the development of T2DM mainly in high-risk patients, provided that physical activity should be designed and carried out in a similar way to cohort studies successful. Similarly, the appropriate prescription of aerobic exercise and strength training in the diabetic is a cornerstone in their management, treatment, prognosis and control and has many benefits, not only in glycemic control but also in cardiovascular parameters, metabolic, anthropometric, psychosocial, etc. For all these reasons, this review covers in general, the global vision of diabetes, the role of exercise in the prevention of T2DM, the role of exercise in the treatment of T2DM, especially prescription of exercise, the mechanisms for improved glycemic control and relates some evidence based recommendations for the prevention and treatment of diabetes with aerobic exercise and strength training (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramón S, Gustavo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez T, Jhony</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez A, Jorge J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Diabetes Mellitus Tipo 2 (DMT2) es una enfermedad muy frecuente a nivel mundial y representa una causa importante de morbilidady mortalidad. Su incidencia y prevalencia han aumentado globalmente en las últimas décadas y si no se toman medidas urgentes la magnitud del problema crecerá con consecuencias para el paciente, el sistema de salud y los factores socioeconómicos de las regiones. Está demostrado que los cambios en el estilo de vida &#150; ejercicio regular, peso saludable y conducta alimentaria&#150; pueden prevenir el desarrollo de DMT2 principalmente en pacientes de alto riesgo, siempre y cuando, la actividad física se diseñe y se realice de forma similar a los estudios de cohorte exitosos. De manera similar, la adecuada prescripción del ejercicio aeróbico y de fuerza en el diabético es un pilar fundamental en su manejo, tratamiento, control y pronóstico y tiene múltiples beneficios, no sólo en el control glicémico, sino también en parámetros cardiovasculares, metabólicos, antropométricos, psicosociales, etc. Por todo lo mencionado, esta revisión abarca en general, la visión global de la diabetes, el papel del ejercicio en la prevención de la DMT2, el rol del ejercicio en el tratamiento de la DMT2, la prescripción especial del ejercicio, los mecanismos para la mejoría del control glicémico y relata algunas recomendaciones basadas en la evidencia para la prevención y el tratamiento de la DMT2 con el ejercicio aeróbico y el de fuerza (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. med. deporte;28(143): 188-1998, mayo-jun. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102591</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actualidad en ejercicio y diabetes tipo 2 (II)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32075^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53366^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37656</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
