<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125063</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1582</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors affecting intraoperative sentinel lymph node identification in patients undergoing surgery for breast cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. In some patients, the sentinel lymph node cannot be identified. The aim of our study was to analyze the various factors that affect its detection. Material and methods. Between June 2003 and June 2011, we conducted a prospective observational study in a series of 588 patients diagnosed with breast cancer without clinical axillary involvement. We collected data on epidemiological factors, tumoral size, histological type, the technique (radiotracer or dye), type of surgery (conservative or mastectomy), region of lymphatic drainage, preoperative isotope migration, localization system (type of gamma camera), lymph node involvement, and surgeon experience. Localization was performed using colloids marked with radiotracer (99mTc) and intraoperative dye administration (methylene blue) in 35% of the patients. Results. A total of 588 patients were studied. The mean age was 58 years, and the mean body mass index was 26.8. The most common tumor type was invasive ductal adenocarcinoma (54%). The sentinel lymph node could not be located in 22 patients (3.7%). Multivariate analysis showed that the factors significantly associated with failure to locate the sentinel lymph node were body mass index (P = .007), type of lymphatic drainage (P &lt; .001), and the absence of preoperative isotope migration (P &lt; .001). Conclusion. In this study, the factors associated with failure to identify the sentinel lymph node were body mass index and the absence of radioisotope migration. No association was found in other factors analyzed, such as age or surgeon experience (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lera, José Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miranda, M. del Coro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Existe un número de pacientes en las que no es posible la localización del ganglio centinela, y el objetivo de nuestro estudio fue analizar los distintos factores que afectan a su localización. Material y métodos. Entre junio de 2003 y junio de 2011 realizamos un estudio prospectivo observacional con una serie de 588 pacientes diagnosticadas de cáncer de mama, sin afectación axilar clínica. Se recogieron datos epidemiológicos, tamaño tumoral, tipo histológico y datos relativos al trazador linfático (radiotrazador o colorante), tipo de cirugía (conservadora o mastectomía), región de drenaje linfático (axilar, mamaria interna), migración preoperatoria del isótopo, sistema de localización con distintos tipos de gammacámara, la afectación ganglionar y la experiencia del cirujano. La localización se realizó mediante coloides marcados con radiotrazador (99mTc) y administración intraoperatoria de colorante (azul de metileno) en el 35% de los casos. Resultados. Se han intervenido 588 pacientes. La mediana de edad fue 58 años, índice de masa corporal medio 26,8. El tipo tumoral más frecuente fue el adenocarcinoma ductal invasivo (54%). En 22 pacientes no se pudo localizar el ganglio centinela (3,7%). El análisis multivariante muestra que el índice de masa corporal de las pacientes (p = 0,007), el tipo de drenaje linfático (p &lt; 0,001) y la no migración preoperatoria del isótopo (p &lt; 0,001) presentan una asociación significativa con la no identificación del ganglio centinela. Conclusión. Este estudio identificó el índice de masa corporal y la no migración del radioisótopo como factores asociados a la no localización del ganglio centinela. Por el contrario, no encontró asociación en otros factores propuestos, como la edad o la experiencia del cirujano (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. senol. patol. mamar. (Ed. impr.);27(3): 114-118, jul.-sept. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125063</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores implicados en la localización intraoperatoria del ganglio centinela en pacientes intervenidas por cáncer de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31593^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31593^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24338^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35392^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8374^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35392^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
