<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144424</identifier>
<setSpec>2254-2884</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of self-care in the hemodialysis vascular access</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Several studies have shown the lack of formation and, in consequence, the lack of self-care in renal patients in treatment with hemodialysis and with vascular access. Nursing must assume its rol of chronic patients coach in order they achieve a balanced state between their desires and what they must do, so they can assume the responsibility to self &#150;provide their own sef-care. The objective was to evaluate the knowledge that the patient has about the needs of care of his/her vascular access. Methodology: The current study was implemented in the Fresenius Sagunto Hemodialysis Center located in Canet D´en Berenguer town (Valencia). Two tools were used; a questionnaire for patients with an arteriovenous fistula, and another one for patients with a central venous catheter, in which it was included general aspects of self-care, actions to keep the vascular access in optimal state and general measures of application in case of emergency. The questionnaires were collected during the period between the first of June and the fifth of June in 2015. It was made a sampling by intentional selection; the collaboration of 57 patients was achieved. Results: The level of knowledge of the self-care of the vascular access from the patients was high in most of the cases. The patients were male the most of them, seniors, their civil status was married, they had a elementary level of studies, they had an arteriovenous fistula as a vascular access and they possessed quite experience in treatment time. Conclusions: We reach to the final conclusion that the raised hypothesis: &#147;a lack of self-care in the patient of Fresenius Sagunto Hemodialysis Center about his vascular access as a consequence of a lack of knowledge&#148; it can´t be kept in the sample of patients studied (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Araque, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sancho Cantus, David</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Diversos estudios han evidenciado la falta de formación y en consecuencia la falta de autocuidados en los pacientes renales sometidos a hemodiálisis y con acceso vascular. La enfermería debe asumir su rol de entrenadora de pacientes crónicos para que alcancen una situación de equilibrio entre sus deseos y lo que deben hacer, para que así puedan asumir la responsabilidad en la autoprovisión de los cuidados básicos del mismo. El objetivo fue evaluar los conocimientos que tiene el paciente sobre las necesidades de cuidado de su acceso vascular. Metodología: El presente estudio se realizó en el Centro de Hemodiálisis Fresenius Sagunto situado en la población de Canet D&#146;en Berenguer (Valencia). Se utilizaron dos instrumentos de medición; un cuestionario para pacientes con fístula arteriovenosa, y otro para pacientes con catéter venoso central, donde se incluyen aspectos generales del autocuidado, acciones para mantener el acceso vascular en óptimas condiciones y medidas generales de aplicación en caso de emergencia. Los cuestionaros fueron recogidos durante el periodo comprendido entre el 1 de junio y el 5 de junio del 2015. Se realizó un muestreo por selección intencionada y se consiguió la colaboración de 57 pacientes. Resultados: El nivel de conocimientos de autocuidados del acceso vascular de los pacientes fue alto en la mayoría de los casos. Los pacientes fueron predominantemente de sexo masculino, pertenecientes a la tercera edad, de estado civil casado, tenían un nivel de estudios básicos, tenían una fístula arteriovenosa como acceso vascular y disponían de bastante experiencia y tiempo de tratamiento. Conclusiones: Obtenemos como conclusión final que la hipótesis planteada: &#147;una deficiencia de autocuidados del paciente del centro de hemodiálisis Fresenius Sagunto sobre su AV como consecuencia de un déficit de conocimientos&#148; no se cumple en la muestra de pacientes estudiados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. nefrol;18(3): 157-162, jul.-sept. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144424</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración de autocuidados en el acceso vascular para hemodiálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30797^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54279^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2446</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13031^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
