<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84644</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Inverted colonic diverticula: An uncommon endoscopic finding</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND: The appearance of inverted colonic diverticula(ICD) is similar to that of elevated polypoid lesions. Theaim of this study was to describe the endoscopic characteristicsof ICD with a view to avoiding misdiagnosis, and to reportthe frequency of these lesions.MATERIAL AND METHOD: Using an endoscopic database, weretrospectively analyzed all patients who underwent colonoscopyat our institution between July 2001 and July 2004.Patients diagnosed with ICD were identified and both patientand ICD characteristics were recorded, including location,endoscopic characteristics, and the presence of synchronouscolon polyps.RESULTS: Among the 4508 colonoscopies performed in theselected period, 33 patients (0.7%) were diagnosed withICD. The mean age was 62.3 years, with a male-to-femaleratio of 1:1.2. Most ICD (89%) were in an area of multiplecolonic diverticula and 75% were located in the sigmoid colon.One patient had active bleeding directly from the inverteddiverticulum and was treated with injection therapy.The endoscopic characteristics of ICDs were described.There were no complications in this series.CONCLUSIONS: ICD is a rare endoscopic finding that can becomplicated by local bleeding. Misdiagnosis can be dangerousand biopsy or endoscopic resection could lead to seriouscomplications. The endoscopic criteria describedshould be considered to avoid the complications associatedwith biopsy or resection (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gobelet, Jaquelina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarrete, Claudio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáenz, Roque</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santander, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Waye, Jerome</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yazigi, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kinney, Timothy P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">INTRODUCCIÓN: El divertículo colónico invertido (DCI) tieneuna apariencia similar a las lesiones polipoideas elevadas. Elobjetivo del presente estudio es describir las característicasendoscópicas del DCI a fin de evitar errores en el diagnósticoy reportar la frecuencia de estas lesiones.MATERIAL Y MÉTODO: Se realizó un análisis retrospectivo detodos los pacientes que se sometieron a una colonoscopia entrejulio de 2001 y julio de 2004, usando una base de datosendoscópicos. Se incluyeron los pacientes con diagnóstico deDCI y se analizaron sus características. Con respecto alDCI, se registró la localización, las características endoscópicasy la presencia de pólipos colónicos sincrónicos.RESULTADOS: Entre las 4.508 colonoscopias realizadas, 33pacientes (0,7%) tuvieron el diagnóstico de DCI. La edadpromedio de los pacientes fue de 62,3 años, y hubo un levepredominio del sexo femenino con una relación 1:1,2. El89% de los DCI se localizó en un área de diverticulosis, y el75% se localizó en el colon sigmoides. Un paciente presentóuna hemorragia digestiva activa con su origen en el divertículoinvertido y se trató con inyectoterapia. Se describieronlas características endoscópicas del DCI. No se reportaroncomplicaciones en esta serie.CONCLUSIONES: El DCI es un hallazgo endoscópico raro quepuede complicarse por el sangrado local. El error diagnósticopuede ser peligroso y su biopsia o resección conllevarían gravescomplicaciones. Los criterios diagnósticos descritos deberíanconsiderarse para evitar la aparición de complicaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;31(5): 285-288, mayo 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84644</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Divertículo colónico invertido: un hallazgo endoscópico infrecuente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4304^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28919^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200805</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
