<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-67648</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To study bibliometric indicators of original articles published in the scientifi c journal Archivos de Prevencionde Riesgos Laborales during the period 1998-2007.Methods: From the bibliographical references of the 101 original articles published in the study period, the informationrelated to the year was abstracted, together with publication source, document type, language and publication country. Theobsolescence index (period during which half of the references were published), Price index (percentage of references less than fi ve years old) isolation index (percentage of references coming from the same country of the analyzed journal) andself-citation percentage were calculated, among others.Results: 2097 bibliographical references were analyzed. The average number of references per article is 21.4. The obsolescenceindex for all references was 6 years. Price index was 36.6%. 55.5% of the references came from English writtenpublications. The isolation index was 38.4%. Self-citation index was 4.8%.Conclusions: Results from this bibliometric analysis showed parameters similar to those of other Spanish journals inthearea of health sciences during the same period. Differences could mostly be explained by particular features related tothe area of the journal (occupational health) that make it different from other more clinically-based disciplines (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vicente Herrero, M. Teófi la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarasibar Ezcurrae, Helena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez Fernández, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejedo Benedicto, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monroy Fuenmayor, Nieves</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López González, Ángel Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Describir indicadores bibliométricos en relación con la bibliografía utilizada en los artículos originales publicadosen la revista Archivos de Prevención de Riesgos Laborales durante el periodo 1998-2007.Métodos: De las referencias bibliográfi cas de los 101 artículos originales publicados en el periodo de estudio se extraela información relativa al año, fuente de publicación, tipo de documento, idioma y país de publicación. Se calculan entreotros los índices de obsolescencia (periodo durante el cual se han publicado la mitad de las referencias), de Price (porcentajede referencias con menos de cinco años de antigüedad) y de aislamiento (porcentaje de referencias que provienen delmismo país que la revista analizada) y el porcentaje de autocita.Resultados: Se analizan 2097 referencias bibliográfi cas. La media de referencias por artículo es de 21,4. El índice de obsolescenciapara todas las referencias es de 6 años. El índice de Price es de 36,6%. El 55,5% de las referencias proceden detrabajos escritos en inglés. El índice de aislamiento es de 38,4%. El índice de autocita es de 4,8%.Conclusiones: El consumo de información de los originales publicados en la revista analizada muestra unos parámetrossimilares al de otras revistas españolas de ciencias de la salud en esos mismos años y en aquellos que se diferencia de ellas podríaexplicarse por las particularidades del área de la salud laboral, diferentes a las de otras disciplinas clínicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. prev. riesgos labor. (Ed. impr.);11(4): 172-178, oct.-dic. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-67648</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7432^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1662</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7432^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7432^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
