<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129377</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adverse reactions to human papillomavirus vaccine in the Valencian Community (2007-2011)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: In 2009, two cases of seizures in adolescents following quadrivalent human papillomavirus vaccine (qHPV) administration, generated important media attention, and adversely affected public trust in this vaccine. Our objectives were to describe suspected adverse reactions (SARs) reported to the Pharmacovigilance Centre in the Valencian Community (PCVC) after administration of HPV vaccine, and to compare reporting rates of syncope and seizures following this vaccine with those of other vaccines administered to girls aged 13-15 years. Material and methods: Descriptive study of SARs reported following this vaccine to the PCVC between 2007 and 2011. Results: The clinical symptoms most frequently reported were dizziness, headache, and syncope. Reporting rates of syncope or loss of consciousness and seizures with qHPV vaccine were 17 and 3.2 per 100,000 doses administered, respectively, and 15 and 1.6 for syncope or loss of consciousness and syncopal seizures occurred on the day of vaccination. The reporting rates of syncope or loss of consciousness and seizures were 6.4 and 0.4, for the other vaccines. Conclusions: Consistent with the media attention generated, and with results from other studies, the reporting rates of syncope or loss of consciousness and seizures were higher for the HPV vaccine than for other vaccines given in adolescence. Nevertheless, the overall information obtained on SARs following the qHPV vaccine suggests a good safety profile (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pastor Villalba, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tuells, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gomar Fayos, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez Domingo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Galán, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Vilar, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Olivas, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En 2009, 2 casos de convulsiones en adolescentes tras la administración de la vacuna tetravalente frente al virus del papiloma humano (VPH) generaron impacto mediático y afectaron negativamente la confianza del público en esta vacuna. Nuestros objetivos fueron describir las sospechas de reacciones adversas (SRA) notificadas al Centro Autonómico de Farmacovigilancia de la Comunidad Valenciana (CAFCV) tras la administración de la vacuna frente al VPH y comparar la tasa de notificación de síncope y convulsiones de esta vacuna con la de otras vacunas administradas en adolescentes. Material y métodos: Estudio descriptivo de las notificaciones de SRA relacionadas con esta vacuna recibidas por el CAFCV entre 2007 y 2011. Resultados: Las manifestaciones clínicas más comunicadas fueron mareos, cefalea y síncope. Las tasas de notificación de síncope o pérdida de conciencia y convulsiones con la vacuna frente al VPH fueron de 17 y 3,2 por 100.000 dosis administradas, respectivamente, y de 15 y 1,6 para síncope o pérdida de conciencia y convulsiones sincopales ocurridas el día de la vacunación. Las tasas de notificación de síncope o pérdida de conciencia y convulsiones fueron de 6,4 y 0,4 para otras vacunas. Conclusiones: Las tasas de notificación de síncope o pérdida de conciencia y convulsiones fueron mayores para la vacuna frente al VPH que para otras vacunas administradas en adolescentes; esto es consistente con la atención mediática originada por la vacuna y con hallazgos de estudios previos. No obstante, la información obtenida sobre las SRA a la vacuna sugiere un buen perfil de seguridad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);81(5): 303-309, nov. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129377</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Notificación de reacciones adversas a la vacuna frente al virus del papiloma humano en la Comunidad Valenciana (2007-2011)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52407^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54726</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35997^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4421^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33186</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201411</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
