<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113084</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Asperger disorder and autism spectrum disorder: from clarification to intervention in natural contexts</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Since its appearance in the official classificatory systems, the diagnosis of Asperger&#146;s Disorder has been the basis of numerous research studies aiming at its identification and differentiation from other development disorders (e.g., autism disorder). In a second stage, research studies were focused on the most effective intervention programmes to improve recovery. At present, both research and clinical practice are focused on intervention procedures that guarantee the transfer of results with an emphasis on their capacities (strong points), more than on their weaknesses (weak points). This article addresses, using a positive approach, the beneficial effects of the interventions in natural contexts which, starting from the symptoms and clinical characteristics, are focused on the strong points as a means to overcome difficulties</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Olivar Parra, José-Sixto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesia Gutiérrez, Myriam de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde su aparición en los sistemas clasificatorios oficiales, el diagnóstico del trastorno de Asperger ha sido fuente de numerosas investigaciones para su identificación y diferenciación con otros trastornos del desarrollo (p. ej., trastorno autista). Posteriormente, las investigaciones se centraron en los programas de intervención más eficaces para su recuperación. En el momento actual la investigación y la práctica clínica se centran en los procedimientos de intervención que garanticen la transferencia de resultados, haciendo énfasis en sus capacidades (puntos fuertes), más que en sus debilidades (puntos débiles). En el presente artículo se consideran los efectos beneficiosos de las intervenciones en contextos naturales, desde un enfoque positivo, que partiendo de los síntomas y características clínicas, se centran en los puntos fuertes como medio para superar sus dificultades (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;19(3): 643-658, sept.-dic. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113084</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastorno de Asperger y trastorno del espectro del autismo: de la clarificación diagnóstica a la intervención en contextos naturales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8776</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24868^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7282</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34570^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
