<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164844</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Outpatient parenteral antimicrobial therapy for infective endocarditis in patients over 80 years</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The incidence of infective endocarditis is progressively increasing, especially in elderly patients. Outpatient parenteral antibiotic therapy (OPAT) is being an excellent alternative for treatment, but advanced age is one of the relative contraindications. The aim of this study is to compare the characteristics and prognosis of patients less or more than 80 years, treated with OPAT. Material and methods. One hundred and ninety four pa-tients were included between 1996 and 2015, 31 of them older than 80 years. Results. The most frequently affected valve is the aortic one, mainly native valves. Most used antibiotics are ceftriaxone, ampicillin, cloxacillin and daptomycin. Differences in surgery (39.9% vs 9.7%, p=0.001) and use of infusion pump (55.2% vs 35.5%; p= 0.044) were observed, under 80 years and older respectively. No differences in readmissions and mortality were observed. Conclusions. OPAT could be considered an effective alternative for appropriately-selected elderly patients with infective endocarditis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ibarguren, Maialen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garcia, Rebeca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Goenaga, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kortajarena, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuertes, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Azkune, Harkaitz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibarguren, Oihana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Goyeneche, Muskilda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bustinduy, Maria Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La incidencia de la endocarditis infecciosa ha aumentado progresivamente, especialmente en pacientes de edad avanzada. La terapia antibiótica domiciliaria endovenosa (TADE) es una excelente alternativa de tratamiento, aunque la edad avanzada sea en algunas guías una contraindicación relativa. El objetivo de este estudio es comparar las características y el pronóstico de pacientes mayores y menores de 80 años tratados con TADE. Material y métodos. Fueron incluidos 194 pacientes entre los años 1996 y 2015, 31 de ellos con edades superiores a 80 años. Resultados. La válvula más frecuentemente afectada fue la aórtica, especialmente válvulas nativas. Los antibióticos más utilizados fueron la ceftriaxona, ampicilina, cloxacilina y daptomicina. Se observaron diferencias en cirugía (39,9% vs 9,7%, p=0,001) y en uso de bombas de infusión (55,2% vs 35,5%; p= 0,044), en los grupos menores y mayores de 80 años respectivamente. No se observaron diferencias significativas en reingresos y mortalidad. Conclusiones. La TADE podría considerarse una alternati-va adecuada en pacientes de edad avanzada con endocarditis infecciosa adecuadamente seleccionados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;30(4): 276-279, ago. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164844</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Terapia antibiótica domiciliaria endovenosa en pacientes mayores de 80 años con endocarditis infecciosa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4778^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4778^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3050^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19603^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d683^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31518^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6856^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
