<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054902</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship between standard automated perimetry and HRT, OCT and GDx in normal, ocular hypertensive and glaucomatous subjects</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To determine the correlations between    structural parameters of the optic nerve head and    the retinal nerve fiber layer (RNFL) obtained by    using a Heidelberg Retina Tomograph II (HRT II),    optic coherence tomography (OCT), and laser polarimetry    (GDX-VCC) and the perimetric indices of    standard automated perimetry (SAP) in normal,    ocular hypertensive and glaucomatous subjects.    Methods: Three hundred and eighty-nine patients    were enrolled in the study and classified into three    separate groups: 43 with normal eyes, 274 with    ocular hypertensive eyes and 72 with glaucomatous    eyes. Subjects were classified according to the basal    intraocular pressure and the SAP results. Pearson&#146;s    correlation coefficients were calculated between the    global perimetric indices, mean deviation (MD) and    pattern standard deviation (PSD), and structural    parameters of the RNFL and optic disc obtained by    using HRT II, OCT and GDX-VCC in the different    diagnostic groups. Results: Mild to moderate correlations were found    between the structural parameters measured by    HRT, OCT and GDX and the global perimetric indices,    in the glaucoma group. Mild or no significant    correlations were found in the normal and ocular    hypertensive groups. Correlations were stronger for    MD than for PSD. Parameters based on the study of    the retinal nerve fiber layer showed stronger correlations    than those based on the study of the optic    nerve head.    Conclusions: The relationship between structural    and functional measurements in glaucoma is weak    and therefore the results of these ancillary tests    should be interpreted together to increase diagnostic    accuracy</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Polo, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Peña, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferreras, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larrosa, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Honrubia, F. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar las correlaciones entre los    parámetros estructurales de la cabeza del nervio    óptico y CFNR obtenidos mediante la topografía    papilar (HRT II), la tomografía óptica de coherencia    (Stratus OCT 3000) y la polarimetría láser (GDx    VCC), con los índices globales de la perimetría    automatizada convencional en sujetos normales,    hipertensos oculares y con glaucoma.    Material y método: Trescientos ochenta y nueve    ojos fueron incluidos en el estudio y clasificados    en 3 grupos: 43 normales, 274 hipertensos oculares    y 72 glaucomas según los resultados de la presión    intraocular basal y la PA. Se calcularon las    correlaciones de Pearson entre los índices principales    de la PA, desviación media (DM) y desviación    estándar de la media (DSM), y los parámetros    morfométricos papilares y de la capa de fibras nerviosas    de la retina (CFNR) obtenidos con el HRT    II, OCT y GDx VCC, en los diferentes grupos    diagnósticos. Resultados: La mayoría de los parámetros estructurales    del HRT, OCT y GDx presentaron correlaciones    débiles o moderadas con los índices principales    de la PA, en el grupo de glaucomas. Los normales    e hipertensos mostraron correlaciones débiles    o no significativas. Las correlaciones fueron más    fuertes para la DM que para la DSM. Los parámetros    basados en el estudio de la CFNR presentaron    correlaciones más fuertes que los que se basaron en    el estudio de la cabeza del nervio óptico.    Conclusiones: La concordancia entre defectos del    campo visual y alteraciones de la cabeza del nervio    óptico o CFNR es débil, lo que justifica la interpretación    conjunta de la información aportada por las    pruebas estructurales y funcionales para evaluar con    mayor precisión el daño glaucomatoso</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;82(4): 197-208, abr. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054902</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre perimetría automatizada convencional y HRT, OCT y GDx en sujetos normales, hipertensos oculares y glaucomatosos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34724</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28204^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27900^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54195^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28204^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54195^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28204^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27900^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24367^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28053^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54195^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28053^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23316^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
