<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159380</identifier>
<setSpec>2173-2345</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The association of MMP1 1G&gt;2G polymorphism with aortic valve calcification</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The most common cause of aortic stenosis is active calcium accumulation in the valve cusps, which implies serious clinical consequences. Various extracellular matrix metalloproteases (MMPs) have been implicated in the development of this disease. Therefore, the possible association between a functional MMP1 polymorphism and the amount of calcium deposited on the aortic valve is studied. Patients and methods: 45 patients undergoing valve replacement were included in the study. The calcium content in valve cusps removed during surgery was determined by computed micro-tomography. DNA was extracted from peripheral blood samples for genotyping the -1607 1G&gt;2G polymorphism of MMP1 by PCR and subsequent digestion. Results: Significant differences were observed in the calcium content in aortic valves in individuals with different -1607 1G&gt;2G genotypes (p=0.042). Thus, 2G allele carriers (homozygous or heterozygous) present higher calcium levels measured as BMD (p=0.004) as well as BV/TV (p=0.002). The association with BV/TV was independent of sex, age, degree of renal function and anatomy of the valve (p=0.02). BMD tendency (p=0.07) was also observed. Conclusion: The association between 1G&gt;2G MMP1 polymorphism and calcium content of the aortic valve suggests that the 1G allele would have a protective effect against calcium deposits. These results support the importance of further study to confirm whether this polymorphism could be used as a possible predictor of aortic stenosis development (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llosa, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cannata-Andía, JB</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Román-García, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solache-Berrocal, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barral, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Naves-Díaz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La causa más frecuente de estenosis aórtica es la acumulación activa de calcio en los velos valvulares, lo que conlleva graves consecuencias clínicas. Diversas metaloproteasas de matriz extracelular (MMPs) han sido implicadas en el desarrollo de esta enfermedad. Por ello, se estudió la posible asociación entre un polimorfismo funcional de MMP1 y la cantidad de calcio depositado en la válvula aórtica. Pacientes y métodos: Se incluyeron en el estudio 45 pacientes sometidos a reemplazo valvular. El contenido en calcio de los velos de las válvulas extraídas en la cirugía se determinó mediante microtomografía computarizada. De muestras de sangre periférica se extrajo ADN para genotipar el polimorfismo -1607 1G&gt;2G de MMP1 por PCR y posterior digestión. Resultados: Se observaron diferencias significativas en el contenido en calcio de las válvulas aórticas en individuos con distintos genotipos de -1607 1G&gt;2G (p=0,042). Así, los portadores del alelo 2G (en homocigosis o heterocigosis) presentan valores más altos de calcio medido tanto como DMO (p=0,004) como BV/TV (p=0,002). La asociación con BV/TV fue independiente del sexo, la edad, el grado de función renal y la anatomía de la válvula (p=0,02), y se observó también una tendencia con la DMO (p=0,07). Conclusión: La asociación entre el polimorfismo 1G&gt;2G de MMP1 y el contenido en calcio de la válvula aórtica sugiere que el alelo 1G tendría un efecto protector ante el depósito de calcio. Estos resultados apoyarían la importancia de ampliar el estudio para confirmar si este polimorfismo se podría usar como un posible predictor del desarrollo de estenosis aórtica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. osteoporos. metab. miner. (Internet);8(4): 115-120, nov.-dic. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159380</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asociación del polimorfismo 1G&gt;2G de la MMP1 con calcificación de la válvula aórtica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54540^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6501^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1028^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11547</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24543^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52232^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
