<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123070</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness and Safety Beyond 10 Years of Percutaneous Transluminal Septal Ablation in Hypertrophic Obstructive Cardiomyopathy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: Percutaneous transluminal septal ablation is an alternative treatment in patients with hypertrophic obstructive cardiomyopathy. However, due to the relatively new introduction of this technique, there is no information on its very long term results (&gt;10 years).Methods: The present study included consecutive patients treated in 5 centers between 1998 and 2003.We analyzed clinical, hemodynamic, and echocardiographic data at baseline and follow-up. Results: A total of 45 patients were included; there were 31 (69%) women, the mean age was62.4 (14) years, and 39 patients (86.6%) showed functional class III or IV. Septal thickness was 21.8 (3.5) mm, the peak resting gradient on echocardiography was 77 (39) mmHg, and mitral regurgitation was at least moderate in 22 patients (48.8%). During hospitalization, permanent pacemaker implantation was required in 3 patients and ventricular perforation (by pacing lead) occurred in 1 patient, requiring surgery. After a follow-up of 12.3 years (11.0-13.5 years), 2 patients (4.4%) died from cardiac causes (heart failure and posttransplantation), 3 patients required an implantable cardioverter-de&amp;#64257;brillator (1 for primary prevention and 2 due to sustained ventricular tachycardia after cardiac surgery), and 2 underwent cardiac surgery (due to endocarditis and mitral regurgitation). In the last clinical review, functional class was I-II in 39 patients (86.6%) (P&lt;.0001), the peak resting gradient was 16 (23) mmHg (P&lt;.0001), and mitral regurgitation was absent or mild in 34 patients (75.5%) (P&lt;.03).Conclusions: The results of this study suggest that septal ablation is safe and effective in the very longterm. The procedure was not associated with a signi&amp;#64257;cant incidence of sudden death or symptomatic ventricular arrhythmias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Recalde, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zueco Gil, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piñón Esteban, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gimeno de Carlos, Federico</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sitges Carreño, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre Hernandez, José M. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernandez Rodriguez, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Masotti Centol, Monica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lerena Saenz, Piedad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabate Tenas, Manel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos La ablación septal percutánea es una alternativa terapéutica en la miocardiopatía hipertrófica obstructiva. Debido a su introducción relativamente reciente, no hay información sobre eficacia y seguridad a muy largo plazo. Este estudio multicéntrico evalúa sus resultados en seguimiento superior a 10 años. Métodos Se incluyó consecutivamente a pacientes tratados con ablación septal en cinco centros entre 1998 y 2003. Se han analizado datos clínicos, hemodinámicos y ecocardiográficos basales y de seguimiento. Resultados Se ha incluido a 45 pacientes (media de edad, 62,4 ± 14 años), de los que 31 eran mujeres y 39 (86,6%) estaban en clase funcional III - IV . El grosor del septo era 21,8 ± 3,5 mm; el gradiente máximo basal por ecocardiografía, 77 ± 39 mmHg, y la insuficiencia mitral era de grado al menos moderado en 22 pacientes (48,8%). Durante la hospitalización, 3 casos precisaron implante de marcapasos definitivo y 1 paciente sufrió perforación ventricular por electrodo de marcapasos, que requirió cirugía. Tras seguimiento de 12,3 (11,0-13,5) años, 2 pacientes (4,4%) sufrieron muerte cardiaca (insuficiencia cardiaca y postrasplante); 3, implante de desfibrilador automático implantable (1 caso por prevención primaria y 2 por taquicardia ventricular sostenida tras cirugía cardiaca), y 2, cirugía cardiaca (endocarditis e insuficiencia mitral). En la última evaluación clínica, la clase funcional era I - II en 39 (86,6%) (p &lt; 0,0001); el gradiente máximo basal, 16 ± 23 mmHg (p &lt; 0,0001), y la insuficiencia mitral, nula o ligera en 34 pacientes (75,5%) (p &lt; 0,03).Conclusiones Estos resultados a más de 10 años indican seguridad y eficacia a muy largo plazo para la ablación septal. No hubo incidencia significativa de arritmias ventriculares sintomáticas o muerte súbita (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;67(5): 353-358, mayo 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123070</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia y seguridad a más de 10 años de la ablación septal percutánea en la miocardiopatía hipertrófica obstructiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19021^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51716</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1150^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30797^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
