<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60153</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-2841</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To investigate the prevalence, characteristics and symptomatology related to the tobacco consumption in medicine students of the Universidad Juárez Autónoma de Tabasco.  (UJAT), Mexico. Methods: We made an observational, cross-sectional and descriptive study, developed in a random sample; to which a questionnaire was applied. Wich contained variables related to the smoking habit and the symptoms and signs showed. Results: 58,4% of the students declared to have smoked at least once in their life, of these the 27,1% referred to continue smoking. The smokers who consumed more than 10 cigarettes a day, showed greater risk of spots in teeth OR of 9,38 (IC 95% 1,42, 62,07). Conclusions. The prevalence of the smoking habit in medicine students of the UJAT is lower than the one reported by another university of Mexico, but higher than the one of a study made in Argentine students (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Martínez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero-Vázquez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lladó-Verdejo, A. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Investigar la prevalencia, características y sintomatología relacionada al consumo de tabaco en estudiantes de medicina de la Universidad Juárez Autónoma de Tabasco (UJAT), México. Métodos: Se trata de un estudio observacional, transversal y descriptivo realizado en una muestra aleatoria, a la cual se le aplicó un cuestionario que contenía variables relacionadas con el hábito de fumar y los síntomas y signos manifestados. Resultados 58,4% de los estudiantes encuestados refirieron haber fumado al menos una vez en su vida; de éstos, el 27,1% refirió continuar fumando. Los fumadores que consumían más de 10 cigarrillos al día presentaron mayor riesgo de manchas en los dientes, OR de 9,38 (IC95% 1,42, 6,07). Conclusiones. La prevalencia del hábito de fumar en los estudiantes de medicina de la UJAT es menor que la reportada por otra universidad de México, pero  mayor que la del estudio realizado en estudiantes argentinos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. prev;13(1): 14-19, ene.-mar. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60153</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia del tabaquismo y sintomatología asociada en estudiantes de Medicina de la Universidad Juárez Autónoma de Tabasco (México)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13724^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
