<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89010</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Surgical technique of the V-Y flaps en un case of patient with diabetic foot</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION. The neuropathic ulcer is the most frequent complication of the diabetic neuropathy appears on a point of pressure, that can be a deformed zone of the foot although its classic description is to plant, at level of the head of the metatarsals bone, end of the fingers, back of such, in the heel, accompanied by a diminution of the sensitivity of this zone, surrounded by painless hyperkeratosis, the perfusion of the foot is normal or is increased, the veins of the back can be expanded, the  hot skin and the pulses arterial tibial posterior and foot are concrete. The treatment of the diabetic foot and independently of the injury degree the therapeutic conduct is based on the following thing: metabolic control, control of the modifiable factors of risk (habit to smoke, arterial hypertension and dislipemic), worn orthopedic to eliminate pressure of the injured area, dressings in the injury (first of colagen, alginate, carboxi metil cellulose). Surgical treatments like desbridant of the injury,  grafts of skin, tenotomy of the flexor, decapitation of head of metatarsals, osteotomies, minor amputations of fingers, transposition of pediculated and V-Y flaps of calcaneus. Results: The report of a case is made where the use of the surgical technique of flaps V-Y was carried out to obtain the healing of the armor-piercing injury of badly plantar in a diabetic patient of  more than six months of evolution. Conclusions: We considered that the technique must continue being used and to compare it with other techniques to know the advantages that could report to us (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llanes Barrios, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valdés Pérez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tarragona, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco Pérez, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarigne, W</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">INTRODUCCIÓN. La úlcera neuropática es la complicación más frecuente de la neuropatía diabética aparece sobre un punto de presión, que puede ser una zona deformada del pie aunque su descripción clásica es plantar, a nivel de la cabeza de los metatarsianos, punta de los dedos, dorso de los mismos, en el talón, acompañado de una disminución de la sensibilidad de  esta zona, rodeada de hiperqueratosis indolora, la perfusión del pie es normal o está aumentada, las venas del dorso pueden estar dilatadas, la piel caliente y los pulsos arteriales tibial posterior y pedio son palpables. El tratamiento del pie diabético y con independencia del grado de lesión la conducta terapéutica se basa en lo siguiente: control metabólico, control de los factores de riesgo modificables (hábito de fumar, hipertensión arterial y dislipidemia), calzado ortopédico para eliminar presión   el área lesionada, apósitos en la lesión (matriz de colágeno, alginato, carboxi metil celulosa). Tratamientos quirúrgicos como desbridamiento de la lesión, injertos de piel, tenotomía del flexor, decapitación de cabeza de metatarsianos, ostectomías, amputaciones menores de dedos, transposición de colgajos pediculados y colgajos en V-Y de calcáneo. RESULTADOS.  Se realiza el reporte de un caso donde se llevó a cabo la utilización de la técnica quirúrgica de colgajo V-Y para lograr la cicatrización de la lesión de mal perforante plantar en un paciente diabético de más de seis meses de evolución.  CONCLUSIONES. Consideramos que la técnica debe continuar utilizándose y compararla con otras técnicas para conocer las ventajas que podría reportarnos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;12(3): 129-131, jul.-sept. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89010</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La técnica quirúrgica de colgajo V-Y. Presentación de un caso en paciente con pie diabético</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29585^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31512^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3948^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
