<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92671</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Biobanks and use of samples of human origin for surgical research. Current regulatory framework</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In recent years, there has been a growing interest in the development of biological samples and biobanks that make it easier for investigators to have access to quality samples and their associated clinical and epidemiological data. Thus, biobanks have become indispensible technological platforms for the development of both basic and clinical research. The properties of the biological sample as a support medium of personal and family information require that they are treated in accordance with new ethical standards. For this reason, the Law on Biomedical Research, provides a new regulatory framework in the process of obtaining samples and their storage for research purposes, where the consent of the source subject, data protection, the favourable opinion of a Research Ethics Committee, the prior taking out of an insurance policy against possible adverse effects, and the quality and safety requirements in the handling and management of these materials are key elements (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arias Díaz, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Arribas, María Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos años se ha despertado un interés creciente por el desarrollo de colecciones de muestras biológicas y biobancos que faciliten a los investigadores el acceso a muestras de calidad y a sus datos clínico-epidemiológicos asociados. Así, los biobancos se han convertido en plataformas tecnológicas indispensables para el desarrollo de la investigación tanto básica como clínica. Las propiedades de la muestra biológica como soporte de información personal y familiar requieren que sean tratadas de acuerdo a nuevos estándares éticos. Por ello, la Ley de Investigación Biomédica dota de un novedoso marco normativo al proceso de obtención de las muestras y a su almacenamiento con fines de investigación, donde el consentimiento del sujeto fuente, la protección de datos, el informe favorable de un comité de ética de la investigación, la contratación de un seguro previo ante posibles efectos adversos, y los requisitos de calidad y seguridad en el tratamiento y gestión de estos materiales son elementos clave (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);89(4): 207-212, abr. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92671</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Biobancos y utilización de muestras de origen humano en investigación quirúrgica. Marco normativo actual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19279^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31619^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
