<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147324</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nursing care and historical evolution: an integrative review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim is to identify the publications available in the literature about the history of nursing in the field of care provided by nurses. The method used included the integrative literature review, which is one of evidence-based practice resources. The search was conducted in August 2014, in the Virtual Library of Health. Were included articles that presented in titles or abstracts references to the history of nursing or the nursing care. Were excluded articles unrelated to the subject studied. For identification of the results it was decided to make a descriptive analysis of the publications and grouping of topics. It was found that the productions focus their writings on the contributions of Florence, religion and other for nursing. Moreover, prevailed discussions about the evolution of nursing through the ages and the history of care. It is understood that these findings are fundamental to locate the nurse in its history, since the nursing remains in progress and we are all actors in this art (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Corrêa, Ana Cândida Lopes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alves, Camila Neumaier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meincke, Sonia Maria Könzgen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soares, Marilu Correa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>pt</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo es identificar las publicaciones disponibles en la literatura sobre la historia de la enfermería en el ámbito de la atención prestada por los enfermeros. El método utilizado incluyó la revisión integradora de la literatura, que es uno de los recursos de la práctica basada en la evidencia. La búsqueda se realizó en agosto de 2014, en la Biblioteca Virtual de Salud. Fueran incluidos artículos que presentan en títulos o resúmenes referencias a la historia de la enfermería o la atención de enfermería. Se excluyeron los artículos no relacionados con el tema estudiado. Para la identificación de los resultados se decidió realizar un análisis descriptivo de las publicaciones y agrupación de los temas. Se encontró que las producciones centran sus escritos sobre las contribuciones de Florence, la religión y otros para la enfermería. Por otra parte, se impuso discusiones acerca de la evolución de la enfermería a través de los siglos y la historia de la atención. Se entiende que estos resultados son fundamentales para localizar el enfermero en su historia, ya que la enfermería sigue en curso y somos todos actores de esta arte (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;19(43): 83-94, sept.-dic. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147324</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El cuidado de enfermería y su evolución histórica: una revisión integrativa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50088</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12077^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6835</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
