<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041507</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Structure of commitment of customer and their relationship with the satisfaction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present paper intends to validate the organizational com-mitment´s customer construct as a multidimensional concept. The starting point are the tree theoretical perspectives traditionally use to study the commitment: affective, normative and continuance. Also, the influence of the commitment was analyzed in the user's satisfaction. In this study, a questionnaire a rating -scale with six questions were use to survey 223 customers of services non educational university students. Results show that the traditional perspectives (affective, normative and calculated) are important for the analysis of the commitment. Also, the data reflect that these categories can be organized in two macrodimensions (ethics and calculated), which influence significantly in the customer's satisfaction. Finally, the implications of these results are discussed and directions for future research are suggested</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salvador Ferrer, Carmen María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente artículo propone validar el constructo del com-promiso del cliente con la organización como un concepto multidimensional, tomando como punto de partida las perspectivas tradicionales: afectiva, normativa y calculada. Además, se analizó la influencia del compromiso en la satisfacción del usuario. En el estudio se utilizó un cuestionario aplicado a 223 usuarios de los servicios no docentes universitarios. Los resultados muestran que las perspectivas tradicionales (afectiva, normativa y calculada) son importantes para el análisis del compromiso de los clientes. También, los datos reflejan que estas categorías pueden organizarse en dos macrodimensiones (ética y calculada), las cuales influyen significativamente en la satisfacción del usuario. Por último, se discuten las implicaciones de los resultados y se sugieren algunas cuestiones a investigar</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;21(2): 316-322, dic. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041507</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validez predictiva de los componentes del compromiso del cliente y su relación con la satisfacción</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23896</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37555^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10660^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23899</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10662</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10538^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
