<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88748</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">You must be the change you want to see in the University</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Teaching and research, two missions of the University, will be discussed herein. Moreover, the interpersonalrelationships are fundamental in all human groups and the role of the leadership in theresearch group will be tackled according to the modern tendencies of the business world.The Spanish University has been too distanced from the social and economical reality. The approachof the European higher education system may overcome all these shortcomings, but the adaptationmay lead, to a greater or a lesser degree, to a transformation of the present education system. It is notclear that the Spanish universities have reached or are now being fully reaching the new configurationof the Bologna Declaration. They are rather in a temporary ambiguous situation, in which someprevious features remain with the new ones.In relation to the charismatic role of the leader within a group, aspects such as motivation, delegationof functions and resolution of conflicts warrant the greatest attention among the many values that mustenhance it.The University of Granada is a vast institution. The secret for this macro-structure to work is that itscomponents, each within its own status, be identified with its principles and be committed toobserving its functions, both particular and general. The secret of the success is illusion, work andgenerosity. Only thus, when work and collaboration implicating all its members is a better Universitypossible(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Campos Rosa, Joaquín M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Rubiño, M. Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se discutirán las dos primeras misiones de la Universidad, tales como la docencia y la investigación.Además, las relaciones inter-personales son fundamentales en todo grupo humano y se abordará elpapel del liderazgo en el grupo de investigación de acuerdo con las modernas tendencias del mundoempresarial.La Universidad española se encuentra en una situación excesivamente alejada de la realidad social yeconómica en la que vivimos. El enfoque del Espacio Europeo de Enseñanza Superior puede subsanarestas deficiencias, pero la adaptación conlleva, en mayor o menor grado, una transformación delmodelo educativo actual. Lo que no está claro es que las universidades españolas hayan alcanzado oestén en vías de alcanzar plenamente la nueva configuración de la Declaración de Bolonia. Más bienestán en una situación transitoria, ambigua, en la que permanecen rasgos anteriores con los nuevos.Con respecto al papel carismático del líder dentro de un grupo, merecen ser destacados aspectos talescomo la motivación, delegación y resolución de conflictos, entre los muchos valores que debenadornarlo.La Universidad de Granada es una institución muy grande. El secreto para que funcione esta macroestructuraes que cada uno de sus componentes, dentro de su status, se identifique con sus principios yse comprometa a cumplir con sus funciones, tanto particulares como generales. El secreto del éxito es la ilusión, trabajo y generosidad. Es así y sólo así, cuando el trabajo y la colaboración comprometidade todos sus miembros, dará lugar a una Universidad mejor(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;51(2): 57-67, abr.-jun. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88748</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sé tú el cambio que quieras ver en la Universidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4582^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8035</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4582^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37706</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4582^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4582^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12530^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4587^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4587^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4587^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4587^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12530^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
