<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95228</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9168</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Apolipoprotein A-II affects HDL apolipoprotein composition and HDL-mediated lipoprotein lipase activation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction Apolipoprotein (apo)A-II is the second most abundant HDL protein but its function remains largely unknown. Studies in humans and genetically-modified mice have demonstrated a role for apoA-II in triglyceride metabolism. The main objective of this study was to evaluate the relationship between apoA-II and HDL apolipoprotein composition, as well as HDL-mediated lipoprotein lipase (LPL) coactivation and plasma triglyceride concentration.Methods Eleven-hour fasting blood samples were taken from 32 healthy volunteers. Anthropometric data and lipid and apolipoprotein parameters were analyzed. HDL isolated by ultracentrifugation was incubated in the presence of a triolein-based emulsion and bovine LPL. In 14 of these volunteers, an additional blood sample was taken 3h after breakfast.Results ApoA-II concentration was directly correlated with plasma triglycerides (R=0.55, p&lt;0.05) and inversely correlated with the HDL-apoC-II+apoE/apoC-III ratio (R=&amp;#8722;0.43, p&lt;0.05). ApoA-II was also inversely correlated with HDL-mediated LPL coactivation (R=&amp;#8722;0.35, p&lt;0.05). ApoA-II concentration was directly correlated with plasma triglycerides 3h after the fat-loading test (R= 0.58, p&lt;0.05).Conclusion These results show that HDL-apoA-II levels play a crucial role in triglyceride catabolism and suggest that, at least in part, this is due to modulation of LPL activity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz García,  Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco-Vaca,   Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escolà-Gil, Joan Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos,  David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Julve,  Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción La apolipoproteína (apo) A-II es la segunda proteína cuantitativamente más importante de las HDL; sin embargo su función es poco conocida. Los estudios realizados en humanos y ratones modificados genéticamente han demostrado un efecto de la apoA-II sobre el metabolismo de los triglicéridos. El objetivo principal de este estudio es analizar la relación entre la apoA-II y la composición apolipoproteica de las HDL así como la capacidad de estas lipoproteínas de modular la actividad de la enzima lipoproteína lipasa (LPL) y, por tanto, la concentración de triglicéridos. Métodos Se recogieron muestras de sangre en 32 voluntarios sanos tras 11h de ayuno. Se recogieron los datos antropométricos y se determinaron los parámetros lipídicos y apolipoproteicos. Las HDL aisladas por ultracentrifugación fueron incubadas con una emulsión radioactiva de triglicéridos y LPL bovina. En 14 de los voluntarios, se obtuvo una muestra adicional de sangre, 3h después de un desayuno. Resultados La concentración de apoA-II correlacionó de forma positiva con la concentración de triglicéridos (R=0,55, p&lt;0,05) y de forma inversa con el cociente apoC-II+apoE/apoC-III en HDL (R=&amp;#8722;0,43, p&lt;0,05). La apoA-II también correlacionó inversamente con la capacidad de las HDL de modular la actividad LPL (R=&amp;#8722;0,35, p&lt;0,05). Por ultimo, la concentración de apoA-II correlacionó positivamente con los triglicéridos postprandiales (R=0,58, p&lt;0,05).Conclusión Estos resultados sugieren que la apoA-II en HDL tiene un papel importante en la regulación del metabolismo de los triglicéridos y sugieren que, en parte, ello es debido a la alteración en la capacidad de las HDL de modular la actividad LPL (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. arterioscler. (Ed. impr.);22(5): 192-197, sept.-oct. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95228</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La apolipoproteína A-II altera la composición apolipoproteica de HDL y su capacidad para activar la lipoproteína lipasa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8250^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53563^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14679^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8245^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30251^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
