<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036843</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Unique (or high resolution) consultation in Hospital and Primary Care pediatric centres: an instrument of improvement in health care quality</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Unique (or high resolution) consultation aims at resolving the health problem of a patientin only one day, as an efficiency alternative to conventional out patients consultations (in hospitals and primary health care centres). The objective is to make a diagnostic and therapeutic approach in the shortest time possible, empowering the first visits and reducing the second ones. For a standard consultation in the traditional model it would be necessary 3 days of healthcare attendance (one for the first visit, another for the complementary tests, and the third one for results and treatment), while unique consultations only need one day. We commen tthe advantages and disadvantages of unique (or high resolution) consultation in our health care pediatric context, like an instrument of improvement in health care quality: increases the satisfaction of the patients, improves the accessibility and reduces costs, and it has not been proved that it decreases the effectiveness, efficiency and security. The important question in this new model of outpatient consultations is if it is feasible in the actual health care system, with the complexity and over utilization of hospital and primary care pediatric centers</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González de Dios, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La consulta única (o de alta resolución) busca resolver el problema de salud de un paciente el mismo día de consulta, como una alternativa eficiente al modelo convencional de consultas externas (en el hospital y centros de Atención Primaria). El objetivo es realizar una aproximación diagnóstico-terapéutica en el menor tiempo posible, potenciando las primeras visitas y disminuyendo las segundas. Para una consulta estándar en el modelo tradicional se precisarían tres días de asistencia (uno para la primera visita, otro para realizar las pruebas complementarias, y un tercer día para recoger los resultados y el tratamiento indicado), frente a sólo uno en el caso de consulta única. Se comentan las ventajas e inconvenientes de la consulta única (o de alta resolución) en nuestro contexto sanitario pediátrico como un instrumento de mejora en la calidad asistencial: incrementa la satisfacción de los pacientes, mejora la accesibilidad y reduce los costes, y no se ha demostrado que disminuya la efectividad, eficiencia y seguridad. La pregunta importante que subyace en este nuevo modelo de consultas externas es si es factible en el actual sistema sanitario, con la complejidad e hiper-frecuentación de los centros hospitalarios y de Atención Primaria</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;7(25): 21-31, ene.-mar. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036843</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consulta única (o de alta resolución) en Pediatría Hospitalaria y en Atención Primaria: un instrumento de mejora en la calidad asistencial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10004^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29873</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
