<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128550</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dysembryoplastic neuroepithelial tumors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The dysembryoplastic neuroepithelial tumors tend to occur in Young patients, with partial complex partial seizures which is refractory to medical treatment. These are stable lesions, with defined histological features, specially with clinical data corroboration. Clinical cases. The clinical, imagiological, operative, and histopathological data of six patients with proved dysembryoplastic neuroepithelial tumors were reviewed. All patients had seizures with age at onset ranged 7 to 27 years. Five lesions were localed in the temporal lobe and one in the parietal lobe. Common features included cortical to subcortical location, low density in CT-scan, very low signal intensity on T1-weighed images and high signal on T2-weighted images. Calcification occurred in two lesions. And three showed contrast enhancement. Complete included oligodendroglial-like cells, glioneural component,and few cases showed dysplastic cortical disorganization. The postoperative period of follow &#150;yp ranged from 2 t 18 months. Four patients were seizure free, two of which had subtotal resection of the lesion. The remaining two patients maintained seizures. Conclusions. The clinical, imagiological and histopathological data of the six cases presented are generally compatible with those of the reports reviewed by the authors. The imagiological features are nonspecific. Surgical treatment permits histological diagnosis and epilepsy control (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vasconcelos, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rangel, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Xavier, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barroso, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reis, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carvalho, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Melo Pires, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los tumores disembrioplásicos neuroepiteliales ocurren en pacientes jóvenes con epilepsia de difícil control terapéutico. Son lesiones estables, con criterios histológicos precisos para el diagnóstico definitivo, en relación con los datos clínicos. Casos clínicos. Se presentan seis casos de tumores disembrioplásicos neuroepiteliales, con revisión retrospectiva de los datos clínicos, las características de imagen, las técnicas quirúrgicas y los criterios histológicos. Todos los pacientes presentaban epilepsia, y la edad de inicio variaba entre los 7 y los 27 años. La lesión se localizaba en el lóbulo temporal en cinco casos y en el lóbulo parietal en un caso. Todas las lesiones eran hipodensas, dos de ellas con calcificaciones. Todas eran hipointensas en T1 e hiperintensas en T2. El córtex estaba envuelto en todas las lesiones y en tres casos hubo captación del contraste. Se efectuó la exéresis total en tres casos y subtotal en los restantes. Las características histológicas incluían el componente típico de células &#145;tipo oligodendrocítico&#146;, el componente ganglionar y, en algunos casos, las características displásicas. En un control realizado entre los 2 y los 18 meses tras la cirugía, cuatro pacientes estaban sin crisis, en dos de ellos se había efectuado extirpación subtotal, mientras que los otros dos mantenían las crisis. Conclusiones. Los aspectos clínicos, de imagen e histológicos de los casos revisados concuerdan con las series publicadas y revisadas por los autores. Las características de imagen son inespecíficas. El objetivo de la cirugía, además del diagnóstico histológico, debe ser el control de la epilepsia, para lo cual no es obligatoria la exéresis total de la lesión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;30(5): 436-441, mar. 2000. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128550</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumores disembrioplásicos neuroepiteliales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1958^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31265^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14102^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4641</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1958^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14102^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14102^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31265^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1958^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31265^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
