<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113516</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Trends in the prevalence of extended-spectrum beta-lactamase-producing gram-negative bacilli in a teaching hospital in Madrid, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: The prevalence of extended-spectrum beta-lactamase (ESBL) producing gram-negative bacilli has increased in recent years. The aim of this study is to estimate the prevalence of infection/colonization due to theses microorganisms per 100 admissions and its trend during the period 2007-2010. Patients and methods: Prospective observational study of all patients admitted from January 2007 to December 2010 infected or colonized with ESBL-producing gram-negative bacilli at Hospital Universitario Ramón y Cajal. The prevalence of infection/colonization of ESBL-producing gram-negative rods was calculated according to the recommendations for metrics for multidrug-resistant organisms in healthcare settings of The Society for Healthcare Epidemiology of America and the Healthcare Infection Control Practices Advisory Committee. To analyse trends, Poisson regression was used (Joinpoint Regression Program Version 3.4.3, U.S. National Institutes of Health). Results: Through the study period there was an upward trend of prevalence of all the ESBL-producing gram-negative bacilli. The Poisson trend analysis indentified a significant inflection point in August 2009 (p = 0.014). Conclusion: The inflection point in the prevalence of the ESBL-producing gram-negative bacilli trend can be explained by a slowdown in the prevalence of some microorganisms such as ESBL-producing Klebsiella pneumonia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Robustillo Rodela, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedrero Pérez, Pelayo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pita López, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Agero Pérez, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monge Jodra, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cornejo Gutiérrez, Ana María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Vélez, Abel Ernesto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: La prevalencia de infección/colonización por bacilos gramnegativos productores de betalactamasas de espectro extendido (BGN-BLEE) ha aumentado en los últimos años. El objetivo de este estudio es estimar la prevalencia de infección/colonización de estos microorganismos por cada 100 ingresos hospitalarios y analizar su tendencia a lo largo del período 2007-2010. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio observacional prospectivo de todos los pacientes con infección y/o colonización por BGN-BLEE ingresados entre enero de 2007 y diciembre de 2010 en el Hospital Universitario Ramón y Cajal. Para el cálculo de la prevalencia de infección/colonización por BGN-BLEE se siguieron las recomendaciones de la guía de indicadores de microorganismos multirresistentes de The Society for Healthcare Epidemiology of America y el Healthcare Infection Control Practices Advisory Committe. El análisis de la tendencia se realizó mediante regresión de Poisson, con el programa Joinpoint Regression 3.4.3 del U.S. National Institutes of Health. Resultados: A lo largo del período de estudio se observó una tendencia ascendente de la prevalencia para el conjunto de BGN-BLEE. El análisis de la tendencia con regresión de Poisson identificó un punto de inflexión significativo en el mes de agosto de 2009 (p = 0,014) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);141(1): 8-12, jul. 2013. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113516</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tendencia de la prevalencia de bacilos gramnegativos productores de betalactamasas de espectro extendido en un hospital universitario de Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30074^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6241^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38654</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
