<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78788</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The Axial Diagnostic Criteria for Depression. Development, construct and predictive validity and reliability</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The authors have developed a new axial diagnostic criterion for depression (ADCD) made up of seven items: mood, motivation/interest, impulse/drive, liking/pleasure, daily job, energy and different quality. They have aimed to examine its predictive validity and reliability, psychometric properties and constructive validity. There are few studies that have examined the psychometric properties of other diagnostic criteria for depression currently in use. Material and methods. A total of 111 psychiatric outpatients who attended an out-patient clinic consecutively were interviewed. Sixty met the ICD-10 criteria for depressive episode and 51 formed a part of the control group: non-depressed psychiatric outpatients. For the interview, the authors used a brief self-administered questionnaire (IDASD) in which the patients indicated how they felt. Each item had a Visual Analogue Scale so that the subjects could quantify their answers. Results. Four or more items are needed for the ADCD to correctly diagnose depression. At least two of these should belong to a group of three items that were extracted using a discriminant function (mood, energy and different quality).                                     The ADCD constructed in this way has a 0.93 sensitivity and 0.82 specificity, with a kappa reliability of 0.76 and a proportion of total cases correctly classified ranging from 88% to 93%. Specificity reaches up to 0.92 when the control group is formed exclusively by symptom-free psychiatric out patients. A factor analysis reveals that the ADCD is a one-dimensional model that has good construct validity (0.69).It also has good alpha reliability (alpha = 0.92), elevated consistency of the two halves of the test (R = 0.91) and a high test-retest correlation (r = 0.67).The ADCD diagnostic agreement between two psychiatrists who use the IDASD as a data source is very high (K: 1.00). Conclusions. The ADCD/IDASD system offers a valid and reliable procedure to diagnose depression. It also has an excellent internal architecture, good construct validity and internal consistency. These data are much more than what can be said about other more used diagnostic criteria, which lack this information (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cordero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zamarro, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos-Brieva, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los autores desarrollan un nuevo Criterio diagnóstico para la depresión (CDAD) compuesto por siete ítems: ánimo, motivación/interés, impulso, gusto/placer, trabajo cotidiano, energía y distinta cualidad. Se proponen examinar su validez predictiva, y fiabilidad, así como sus propiedades psicométricas y su validez constructiva. Existen pocos estudios que hayan examinado las propiedades psicométricas de otros criterios diagnósticos para la depresión actualmente en uso. Material y métodos. Entrevistan a 111 pacientes psiquiátricos atendidos consecutivamente en régimen ambulatorio. Sesenta cumplían los criterios para episodio depresivo de la CIE-10 y 51 formaban parte del grupo de control: enfermos psiquiátricos no deprimidos. Utilizan para ello un breve cuestionario autoaplicado (IDASD) donde los pacientes señalan cómo se encuentran. Cada ítem tiene una escala analógico visual para que los sujetos cuantifiquen sus respuestas. Resultados. Para que el CDAD diagnostique correctamente depresión, debe exigírsele reunir cuatro ítems o más. De ellos, al menos dos deben pertenecer a un grupo de tres ítems que fueron extraídos mediante una función discriminante (ánimo, energía y distinta cualidad). El CDAD así construido tiene una sensibilidad de 0,93 y una especificidad de 0,82, con una fiabilidad kappa de 0,76 y una proporción de casos totales acertados del 88% al 93%.Cuando el grupo de control está formado exclusivamente por pacientes psiquiátricos asintomáticos, la especificidad sube hasta 0,92. Un análisis factorial revela que el CDAD es unidimensional y tiene una buena validez de constructo (0,69). También tiene una buena fiabilidad alfa (alfa= 0,92), una consistencia por la prueba de las dos mitades elevada (R = 0,91) y una correlación test-retest alta (r=0,67).                                                      El acuerdo diagnóstico CDAD entre dos psiquiatras que utilizan como fuente de datos el IDASD es muy alta (K: 1,00). Conclusiones. El sistema CDAD/IDASD ofrece un procedimiento para diagnosticar depresión valido y fiable. También posee una excelente arquitectura interna, una buena validez de constructo y consistencia interna. Estos datos son mucho más de lo que se puede decir de otros criterios diagnósticos más al uso, de los que se carece de esta información (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;37(6): 306-319, nov.-dic. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78788</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El Criterio diagnóstico axial para la depresión.  Desarrollo, validez constructiva, validez predictiva y fiabilidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7569^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
