<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101464</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Life skills and drug use among Mexican adolescent students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A cross-sectional study was carried out with the purpose of validating seven life skills scales reported in the literature as related to drug-abuse prevention, and which identify differences between these skills among non-user adolescent students and users of alcohol, tobacco, cannabis and inhalants. The sample was made up of 425 adolescents, 196 (46.1%) male and 229 (53.9%) female. These participants were randomly selected from a private high school in the state of Morelos, and their mean age was 15.8 years, with a standard deviation of 1.97. To measure skills we used the scales validated in this survey, while patterns of drug use were measured with a scale based on the National Addiction Survey (2008) indicators. Results showed that students who did not use alcohol, tobacco, cannabis or inhalants scored higher in skills of empathy, future orientation and peer pressure resistance, compared to those who had used these substances in the last month. On the basis of these findings it would seem necessary to develop drug-abuse prevention programs for high school students based on a life skills training approach(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez De La Barrera, Citlalli</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se realizó un estudio transversal cuyo objetivo fue validar siete escalas de habilidades para la vida que la literatura reporta como relacionadas con la prevención del consumo de drogas; que sirvieran para identificar diferencias en dichas habilidades, en adolescentes estudiantes no consumidores y consumidores de alcohol, tabaco, marihuana e inhalables. La muestra estuvo constituida por 425 adolescentes, 196 (46.1%) hombres y 229 (53.9%) mujeres, estudiantes de nivel medio superior del Estado de Morelos, seleccionados de manera aleatoria con una media de edad de 15.8 años y una desviación estándar de 1.97. Para medir las habilidades se utilizaron las escalas validadas en este estudio; para medir el patrón de consumo de drogas se utilizaron los indicadores de la Encuesta Nacional de Adicciones (2008). Los resultados mostraron que los estudiantes no consumidores de alcohol, tabaco, marihuana e inhalables obtuvieron puntajes más altos en las habilidades de empatía, planeación del futuro y resistencia a la presión a diferencia de los consumidores en el último mes. Con base en estos hallazgos, se identifica la necesidad de desarrollar programas de prevención de adicciones para estudiantes adolescentes basados en un enfoque de habilidades para la vida(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);24(2): 153-160, abr.-jun. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101464</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Habilidades para la vida y consumo de drogas en adolescentes escolarizados mexicanos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12953^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24318^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24318^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28461</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24318^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
