<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79258</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Depression, gender and systemic manifestations in chronic inflammatory bowel diseases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this study was to assess the relation between depression, gender and systemic manifestations in chronic inflammatory bowel diseases. With this aim, 106 patients (57 with Crohn disease and 49 with ulcerative colitis) were divided into 4 groups: men with extraintestinal manifestations (n= 10), men without extraintestinal manifestations (n= 36), women with extraintestinal manifestations (n= 15), and women without extraintestinal manifestations (n= 45). Depression was assessed with the Beck Depression Inventory. The results reveal significant effects both in the systemic manifestations factor (F= 28,33; p&lt;0.01), and in the interaction between systemic manifestations and gender (F= 5,2; p&lt;0.05); the gender factor, in contrast, was nonsignificant (F= 0,28; p&gt;0.05). The finding of higher levels of depression in patients with systemic manifestations, particularly in men, underlines the need for psychological intervention aimed at detection and effective treatment.(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bueno, Ana M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Simón, Miguel A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El propósito de este trabajo fue evaluar la relación existente entre depresión, género y manifestaciones sistémicas en las enfermedades inflamatorias crónicas del intestino. Con esta finalidad, 106 pacientes (57 con enfermedad de Crohn y 49 con colitis ulcerosa) fueron divididos en 4 grupos: varones con manifestaciones extraintestinales (n= 10), varones sin manifestaciones extraintestinales (n= 36), mujeres con manifestaciones extraintestinales (n= 15) y mujeres sin manifestaciones extraintestinales (n= 45). La evaluación de la depresión se llevó a cabo mediante el Inventario de Depresión de Beck. Los resultados obtenidos muestran la existencia de efectos significativos tanto en el factor manifestaciones sistémicas (F= 28,33; p&lt;0,01), como en la interacción entre manifestaciones sistémicas y género (F= 5,2; p&lt;0,05); el factor género, por el contrario, no resultó significativo (F= 0,28; p&gt;0,05). El hallazgo de niveles superiores de depresión en los pacientes con manifestaciones sistémicas, particularmente en los varones, pone de relieve la necesidad de una intervención psicológica dirigida a su detección y tratamiento eficaz(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);22(2): 208-212, 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79258</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Depresión, género y manifestaciones sistémicas en las enfermedades inflamatorias crónicas del intestino</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7573^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5924</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23971^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23971^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7573^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7573^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
