<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149606</identifier>
<setSpec>0556-6177</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dietary interview: a useful tool for data collection</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Dietary interview is a very useful tool in the process of evaluating the nutritional state of a person and, of course, in the process of dietary counseling, particularly in the case of patients suffering from chronic conditions. The complexity of gathering information at individual or population level requires different models of questionnaires and tools to enhance the identification of the data collected. The current paper is based on the consensus document about dietary interview, made by a working group created during the 1st Meeting of the Spanish Dietitians&#146; and Nutritionists&#146; Association held in Barcelona 2002 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salvador, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miserachs, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palma, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilà, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Illan, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puchal, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La entrevista dietética es una herramienta imprescindible en el proceso de evaluación del estado nutricional del individuo y, por supuesto, en cualquier planteamiento de intervención dietética, especialmente en el abordaje de tratamientos dietéticos en enfermos crónicos. La complejidad de la recogida de información tanto a nivel individual como en estudios nutricionales poblacionales, requiere de modelos de cuestionarios consensuados y de herramientas que faciliten la identificación de la información recogida. El siguiente artículo se ha basado en el documento de consenso sobre entrevista dietética, elaborado por un grupo de trabajo constituido durante el I Congreso de la Asociación Española de Dietistas y Nutricionistas, Barcelona, 2002 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Med Univ Navarra;50(4): 46-55, 2006. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149606</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Entrevista dietética. Herramientas útiles para la recogida de datos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28598</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
