<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038126</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Therapy with continous subcutaneous insulin infusion in the pediatric age</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Children and adolescents with type 1 diabetes mellitus are usually    treated with multiple daily insulin injections (MDI). Although    continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion (CSII) has been used    extensively for several years in adult diabetic patients, it has been    used less frequent in children and adolescents. But in the recent    years, CSII is used more often in the pediatric age, specially in sev-eral    contries. CSII enables patients with type 1 diabetes to get closer    to physiological insulin secretion over 24 hours. This system    allows individualization of the insulin dose. Unacceptable glycemic    control in spite of MDI has been usually an indication for switching    to CSII. Several studies have suggested that CSII in children and    adolescents could provides better glycemic control, reduces the    risk of severe hypoglycemia and led to lesser weight gain than MDI.    CSII therapy in the pediatric age has been proved to be safe, effec-tive    and well accepted by children and adolescents with type 1 diabetes    and also by their families</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Capapé, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrio, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Colino, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Children and adolescents with type 1 diabetes mellitus are usually treated with multiple daily insulin injections (MDI). Although continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion (CSII) has been used extensively for several years in adult diabetic patients, it has been used less frequent in children and adolescents. But in the recent years, CSII is used more often in the pediatric age, specially in several countries. CSII enables patients with type 1 diabetes to get closer to physiological insulin secretion over 24 hours. This system allows individualization of the insulin dose. Unacceptable glycemic control in spite of MDI has been usually an indication for switching to CSII. Several studies have suggested that CSII in children and adolescents could provides better glycemic control, reduces the risk of severe hypoglycemia and led to lesser weight gain than MDI. CSII therapy in the pediatric age has been proved to be safe, effective and well accepted by children and adolescents with type 1 diabetes and also by their families</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;21(1): 38-43, ene.-mar. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038126</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento con infusión subcutánea continua de insulina en la edad pediátrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22523^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7181^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7181^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
