<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102363</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1972</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of diabetes on hospital consumption</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze the impact of diabetes on hospital resources utilization by inpatients. Method: We analyzed all the episodes of hospitalisation in the year 2006 of a tertiary hospital by means of the Basic Minimun data Set (CMBD).We studied demographic characteristics, case-mix, and use of hospital services for   patients with and without diabetes. Results: A total of 28.383 episodes of hospitalisation wereregistered and out of these: 14.11 % were diabetic patients.  Out of the total episodes, 66.4 % were emergency admissions with a hospital mortality rate of 6.2 %. Of these patients 24 % had more than one episode of hospitalisation during the study time period. The mean stay in the hospital was 10.26 days. Variables such as the complexity, the number of secondary diagnosis, sex, type of admission and the type of GRD&#146;S affects the mean hospital stay in these patients.  Conclusions: Diabetic patients account for more than 14 % of hospital admissions, and have a higher average stay than non-diabetics (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sesé, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrera, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abad, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rabanaque, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar el impacto de la diabetes en el consumo de recursos hospitalarios. Método: Se analizaron todos los ingresos de un hospital  terciario en 2006, registrados en el conjunto mínimo básico de datos (CMBD). Se estudiaron las características demográficas, de complejidad y de uso de servicios de pacientes con y sin diabetes. Resultados: En el 14,11 % constaba el diagnóstico de  diabetes. El 66,4 % fueron ingresos urgentes y un 6,2 % fallecieron en el hospital. El 24 % tuvo más de un ingreso durante el año de estudio. La estancia media fue de 10,26 días frente a los 7,72 de los no diabéticos (p &lt; 0,001). Complejidad, número de diagnósticos  secundarios, sexo, tipo de ingreso y tipo de GRD influyeron en la duración de la estancia. Conclusiones: El diagnóstico de diabetes es frecuente en los pacientes hospitalizados (14 %) y estos pacientes presentan estancias más elevadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Todo hosp;(274): 4-8, mayo 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102363</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de la diabetes en la carga hospitalaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34906</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28096^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
