<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102542</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">&#147;Man in the barrel syndrome&#148; (brachial diplegia as a variant of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis): a case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">&#147;Man in the barrel&#148; syndrome describes an uncommon clinical picture of bilateral proximal brachial paralysis with preserved mobility of lower limbs and sensitivity. This is generally due to supratentorial lesions, and lesions of the encephalic trunk or spinal cord have been described less frequently. We report the case of a 75-year old woman with bilateral proximal brachial paralysis and pain in an uncommon variant of the onset picture of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis. We describe her evolution and treatment, stressing the rapid progression of her condition, this being uncommon in this variant(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>d&#146;Ors, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sancho-Miñana, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torralba, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elía, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valero, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibañez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome del «hombre en barril» describe un cuadro clínico poco frecuente de diplejía braquial proximal bilateral con movilidad conservada de miembros inferiores y preservación de la sensibilidad, generalmente se debe a lesiones supratentoriales, de forma menos frecuente se han descrito casos de lesiones del tronco encéfalo o de la médula. Presentamos un caso de una mujer de 75 años con dolor y paresia braquial proximal bilateral de miembros superiores como variante poco frecuente de cuadro clínico de inicio de una esclerosis lateral amiotrófica. Describimos sus peculiaridades, evolución y tratamiento, destacando la rápida progresión de la enfermedad, no siendo usual en esta variante(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);46(3): 236-238, jul.-sep.2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102542</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome del «hombre en barril» (diplejía braquial como variante de esclerosis lateral amiotrófica): a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10480^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d704^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33413^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d704^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1942^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10480^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d704^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d704^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
