<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146394</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Participatory intervention in the management of psychosocial risks</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Malaga Transport Company down a psychosocial risk management based on integration, participation, continuous improvement, self-reliance and teamwork. In which ensures the integration of the management of occupational safety through a common policy with Quality and Environmental Systems in Integrated Management System. And in which the participation of the various members of the organization through the various committees is a basic pillar for the operation thereof and achievement of objectives. It also arises as the company's strategic objectives the improvement of employee, reduced absenteeism and accident reduction. To achieve these objectives we develop a model Systematic and continuous measurement of psychosocial risk assessment for ten years has proven to be a very valid method for early detection of deviations and to the effective management of these risks. The implementation of the Communication Plan Vertical and Horizontal, along with the Training Plan and the creation of the various working committees have been enablers for participation and active involvement of all staff of the company and thus the assumption of self-responsibility and continuous improvement, which is evidenced by the measures adopted and the effectiveness of the results (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Márquez Matito, José Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villalobos Antequera, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Escalona, María Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Empresa Malagueña de Transportes establece un modelo de gestión de riesgos psicosociales fundamentado en la integración, participación, mejora continua, autorresponsabilidad y trabajo en equipo. En el cual se garantiza la integración de la gestión de la prevención de riesgos laborales mediante una política común con los Sistemas de Calidad y Medioambiente en un Sistema Integrado de Gestión. Y en el que la participación de los distintos miembros de la organización a través de las distintas comisiones es un pilar básico para el funcionamiento del mismo y logro de los objetivos. Así mismo se plantea como objetivos estratégicos de la empresa la mejora del Clima Laboral, la reducción del absentismo y la reducción de la accidentabilidad. Para conseguir estos objetivos se desarrolla un Modelo de Medición Sistemática y continuo de evaluación de riesgos psicosociales que ha demostrado durante diez años ser un método muy válido para la detección precoz de desviaciones y para la gestión eficaz de este tipo de riesgos. La implantación del Plan de Comunicación Vertical y Horizontal, junto con el Plan de Formación y la creación de las distintas Comisiones de Trabajo han sido elementos facilitadores para conseguir la participación e implicación activa de todo el personal de la empresa y con ello la asunción de autorresponsabilidad y mejora continua, que queda evidenciada en las medidas adoptadas y la eficacia de los resultados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;59(supl.extr): 28-35, 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146394</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervención participativa en la gestión de riesgos psicosociales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8035</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32048^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d44</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12720^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32782^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32782^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12720^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51292</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36300^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51560</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54367</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201300</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
