<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89480</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Chronic eosinophilic pneumonia: presentation of a case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Chronic eosinophilic pneumonia is a rare condition of unknown origin. It was not until 1969 when Carrington et al defined it as a disease separate from the group of diseases associated with lung disease and eosinophilia. We describe a case of a young woman who presented with a chronic cough followed by a fever. Additional tests showed peripheral eosinophilia in bronchoalveolar lavage with 60% eosinophils. Chest x-rays showed bilateral infiltration in the upper lobes. Corticosteroid therapy improved the picture, the patient still remains asymptomatic (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villafañe Olmedo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Campos, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arroyo Domingo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Arroyo, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La neumonía eosinófila crónica es una entidad poco frecuente de etiología desconocida. Hasta 1969 Carrington y colaboradores no la definen como una entidad propia separándola del grupo de enfermedades que asocian patología pulmonar y eosinofilia. Se describe un caso de una mujer joven que presentó un cuadro de tos crónica seguida de fiebre. Las pruebas complementarias demostraron eosinofilia periférica y en el lavado broncoalveolar 60% de eosinófilos. Las radiografías de tórax mostraron infiltración bilateral en lóbulos superiores. El tratamiento con corticoides mejoró el cuadro, permaneciendo la paciente asintomática hasta la actualidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);37(6): 321-323, jun.-jul. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89480</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neumonía eosinófila crónica: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4881^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4881^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4884^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4881^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4881^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4884^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12094^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32824^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12094^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12094^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32824^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32824^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201107</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
