<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108797</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Improving the quality of spiritual care as a dimension of palliative care:  the report of the Consensus Conference</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A Consensus Conference sponsored by the Archstone Foundation of Long Beach, California, was held February 17-18, 2009, in Pasadena, California. The conference was based on the belief that spiritual care is a fundamental component of quality palliative care. This document and the conference recommendations it includes builds upon prior literature, the National Consensus Project Guidelines, and the National Quality Forum Preferred Practices and Conference proceedings (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Virani , Rose</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sulmasy, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prince-Paul , Maryjo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nelson-Becker, Holly</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baird, Pamela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bull , Janet</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrell , Betty</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Handzo , George</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chochinov , Harvey</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Otis-Green , Shirley</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puchalski, Christina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pugliese , Karen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los días 17 y 18 de febrero de 2009, en Pasadena (California, Estados unidos), se celebró una Conferencia de Consenso patrocinada por la Fundación Archstone de Long Beach (California). La conferencia se basó en el convencimiento de que el cuidado espiritual es un componente fundamental de los cuidados paliativos. Este documento, así como las recomendaciones que incluye de la conferencia, se basa en documentación previa, las directrices del Proyecto Nacional de Consenso, la Guía de Buenas Prácticas del Foro Nacional de Calidad y en presentaciones de la propia conferencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;18(1): 20-40, ene.-mar. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108797</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La mejora de la calidad de los cuidados espirituales como  una dimensión de los cuidados paliativos:  el informe de la Conferencia de Consenso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37619</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36317</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54376</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
