<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039797</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fibromyalgia and its diagnosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Fibromyalgia or fibromyalgic syndrome (FMS) is a clinical picture of unknown origin that is characterized by generalized, incapacitating and chronic pain together with the demonstration in the physical examination of previously defined points in which moderate pressure causes pain, called fibromyalgia tender points (FTP). FMS lacks objective, analytic imaging or pathological data, so that its diagnosis is based exclusively on subjective data, such as that the pain reported by the patient and the pain caused by the FTP pressure. Although the fibromyalgia classification criteria of the American College of Rheumatology are not diagnostic criteria, they have been extensively used to diagnose FMS in patients with chronic diffuse arthromyalgias. Fibromyalgia diagnosis reduces the patient's anxiety, avoiding complementary expensive and unnecessary tests and it allows the patient to share his/her fears, illnesses and expectations with other human beings who suffer the same problem</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Andreu, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La fibromialgia o síndrome fibromiálgico (SFM) es un cuadro clínico de origen desconocido que se caracteriza por dolor generalizado, incapacitante y crónico, junto con la demostración en la exploración física de unos puntos previamente definidos en los que la presión moderada desencadena dolor, denominados puntos sensibles de la fibromialgia. El SFM carece de datos objetivos, analíticos, de imagen o anatomopatológicos, por lo que su diagnóstico se basa exclusivamente en datos subjetivos, como son el dolor que cuenta la paciente y el dolor desencadenado mediante la presión de los puntos sensibles de la fibromialgia. Aunque los criterios de clasificación de fibromialgia del American College of Rheumatology no son criterios diagnósticos, se han utilizado extensamente para diagnosticar de SFM a las pacientes con artromialgias crónicas difusas. El diagnóstico de fibromialgia reduce la angustia del paciente, evita pruebas complementarias costosas e innecesarias y permite al paciente compartir sus temores, dolencias y expectativas con otros seres humanos que padecen su mismo problema</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;205(7): 333-336, jul. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039797</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La fibromialgia y su diagnóstico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38045^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38045^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24650^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24650^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19551^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19551^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
