<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137414</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Academic stress and physical, psychological and behavioral factors in Mexican public university students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The capacity to cope with academic stress can be deemed as vulnerable in some students who have shown several alterations. The article reports on the relationship among academic stress and symptomology. Results were compared between men and women. A survey of 527 public university students was taken in Mexico, with the Academic Stress Inventory using the Rossi Classification. Data were analyzed with multiple regression and it was deter-mined that academic overload and class participation were predictors of physical symptoms; mandatory and group work as well as insufficient time, academic overload, and class participation were predictors of psychological symptoms while mandatory work, academic overload and classroom participation and massification were predictors of behavioral symptoms. In addition, women showed a higher frequency of academic stress and of physical and psychological symptoms. So a timely identification of conditions that generate stress may lessen symptoms in students such as drowsiness, fatigue, migraines, absenteeism, restlessness, anxiety and/or memory problems (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pozos-Radillo, Blanca Elizabeth</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acosta-Fernández, Martín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Plascencia Campos, Ana Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Preciado-Serrano, María de Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilera V, María de los Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La capacidad de afrontamiento ante el estrés académico puede verse vulnerable en algunos estudiantes, manifestando varias alteraciones. Este artículo reporta la relación entre el estrés académico y sintomatología. Se compara los resultados entre hombres y mujeres. Se encuestó aleatoriamente a 527 estudiantes de una universidad pública en México. Con el Inventario de Estrés Académico y se utilizó la clasificación de Rossi. La regresión múltiple determinó que la sobrecarga académica y participación en clase fueron predictoras de síntomas físicos; trabajos obligatorios y en grupo, falta de tiempo, sobrecarga académica y participación en clase con síntomas psicológicos; trabajos obligatorios, sobrecarga académica, participación en clase y masificación en el aula con síntomas comportamentales; las mujeres presentan mayor frecuencia de estrés académico, síntomas físicos y psicológicos. Identificar oportunamente la presencia de condiciones generadoras de estrés puede prevenir síntomas, como somnolencia, fatiga, migraña, absentismo, inquietud, ansiedad, o problemas de memoria en estudiantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;21(1): 35-42, ene.-jun. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137414</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrés académico y síntomas físcios, psicológicos y comportamentales en estudiantes mexicanos de una universidad pública</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13700</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33525^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
