<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93867</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validity for use in research on vascular diseases of the SIDIAP (Information System for the Development of Research in Primary Care): the EMMA study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. Information in primary care databases can be useful in research, but the validity of these data needs to be evaluated. We sought to analyze the validity of the data used in the EMMA study based on data from the Information System for the Development of Research in Primary Care. Methods. We compared the prevalence of cardiovascular risk factors observed in EMMA&#151;hypertension, diabetes, hypercholesterolemia (and its treatments), obesity, and smoking&#151;with equivalent data from the Registre Gironí del Cor (REGICOR), a population-based study that uses standardized methodology, in 2000. We also compared the incidence rates of vascular diseases and its association with these risk factors in a 5-year follow-up. Results. We analyzed data from 34 823 participants included in EMMA and 2540 REGICOR2000 study participants aged 35 to 74. The prevalence of risk factors did not differ significantly between the 2 studies, except for the prevalence of former smokers in men, which was higher in REGICOR2000 (24.7% [95% confidence interval, 23.9%-25.5%] vs 30.1% [95% confidence interval, 27.1%-33.1%]), and the proportion of patients with lipid-lowering and antihypertensive therapy, which was higher in EMMA (46.9% vs 32.7% and 8.7% vs 6.3%, respectively). There were no differences between the 2 studies when comparing the incidence of vascular diseases (2.1% in both studies in men and 1.18% [95% confidence interval, 0.7%-1.7%] in REGICOR2000 vs 0.75% [95% confidence interval, 0.64%-0.87%] in EMMA in women) and its association with risk factors. Conclusions. The prevalence of cardiovascular risk factors and their association with the incidence of vascular disease observed in the EMMA study are consistent with those observed in an epidemiological population-based study with a standardized methodology (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto-Alhambra, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí, Ruth</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos, Rafel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grau, Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bolíbar, Bonaventura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elosua, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Gil, Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quesada, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marrugat, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vila, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sala, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fina, Francesc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hermosilla, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balló, Elisabet</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosell, Magdalena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Las bases de datos clínicas de atención primaria ofrecen un gran potencial para la investigación. Nuestro objetivo es analizar la validez de los datos del estudio EMMA, basado en el Sistema de Información para el Desarrollo de Investigación en Atención Primaria. Métodos. Se compararon las prevalencias de los factores de riesgo cardiovascular &#151;hipertensión, diabetes mellitus, hipercolesterolemia (y sus tratamientos), obesidad y tabaquismo&#151; observadas en el EMMA con datos equivalentes del estudio Registre Gironí del Cor (REGICOR) en el año 2000. También se compararon la incidencia de enfermedad vascular y su asociación con dichos factores de riesgo en un seguimiento a 5 años. Resultados. Se analizaron datos de 34.823 participantes de 35 a 74 años incluidos en el EMMA y 2.540 participantes del estudio REGICOR2000. Las prevalencias de los factores de riesgo no difirieron significativamente entre los dos estudios, excepto para la prevalencia de exfumadores varones, que fue superior en el REGICOR2000 (el 24,7% [intervalo de confianza del 95%, 23,9-25,5%] frente al 30,1% [intervalo de confianza del 95%, 27,1-33,1%]) y la proporción de hipertensos tratados y pacientes con tratamiento hipolipemiante, que fueron superiores en el EMMA (el 46,9 frente al 32,7% y el 8,7 frente al 6,3%, respectivamente). No se observaron diferencias entre uno y otro estudio en la comparación de la incidencia de enfermedad vascular (varones, el 2,1% en ambos estudios; mujeres, el 1,18% [intervalo de confianza del 95%, 0,7-1,7%] en el REGICOR2000 frente al 0,75% [intervalo de confianza del 95%, 0,64-0,87%] en el EMMA) ni en su asociación con los factores de riesgo. Conclusiones. Las prevalencias de los factores de riesgo cardiovascular y su relación con la incidencia de enfermedades vasculares observada en el EMMA concuerdan con las observadas en un estudio epidemiológico estandarizado de base poblacional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;65(1): 29-37, ene. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93867</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validez del Sistema de Información para el Desarrollo de la Investigación en Atención Primaria (SIDIAP) en el estudio de enfermedades vasculares: estudio EMMA</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19350</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52871</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201201</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
