<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136049</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Venous thrombosis of atypical location in patients with cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Venous thromboembolism (VTE) is a complication that frequently occurs in patients with neoplastic diseases. Several models have therefore been developed to identify patient subgroups diagnosed with cancer who are at increased risk of developing VTE. The most common forms of thromboembolic episodes are deep vein thrombosis in the lower limbs and pulmonary thromboembolism. However, venous thrombosis is also diagnosed in atypical locations. There are few revisions of unusual cases of venous thrombosis. In most cases, VTE occurs in the upper limbs and in the presence of central venous catheters, pacemakers and defibrillators. We present the case of a patient diagnosed with breast cancer and treated with surgery, chemotherapy and radiation therapy who developed a thrombosis in the upper limbs (brachial and axillary) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sáenz de Miera Rodríguez, Andrea</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quindós Varela, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López López, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos Balea, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antolín Novoa, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barón Duarte, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad tromboembólica venosa (ETEV) es una complicación que se presenta con frecuencia en los pacientes con enfermedades neoplásicas; por ello se han desarrollado varios modelos para identificar subgrupos de pacientes diagnosticados de cáncer con riesgo aumentado de desarrollar ETEV. Las localizaciones más frecuentes de los episodios tromboembólicos son la trombosis venosa profunda en miembros inferiores y la tromboembolia pulmonar, sin olvidar que se diagnostican trombosis venosas en localizaciones atípicas. Apenas hay revisiones sobre trombosis venosas inusuales; en la mayoría de los casos, la localización más frecuente es en miembros superiores y en relación con la presencia de catéteres venosos centrales, marcapasos y desfibriladores. Presentamos el caso de una paciente diagnosticada de cáncer de mama y tratada con cirugía, quimioterapia y radioterapia que presentó una trombosis en miembros superiores (humeral y axilar) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);144(supl.1): 38-40, ene. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136049</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trombosis venosa de localización atípica en pacientes con cáncer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29995^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8580^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53542^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
