<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140011</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anthropometric differences related to genders and age in the elderly</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: anthropometry facilitates the evaluation of the risks associated with reduced lean body mass, as well as of excess adiposity. However, very little is known regarding the anthropometric standards among the elderly and the differences observed between the genders and among the various age groups Objective: to compare indicators and indices anthropometrics of the elderly by gender and age group. Methods: a cross-sectional study was undertaken using a representative probability sample, involving 621 elderly. We evaluated the weight, height, circumferences (waist, hip, calf and arm); body mass index, body adiposity index, waist-hip ratio and waist-stature ratio. Results: women were found to have a higher mean body mass index, waist-stature ratio, body adiposity index and arm circumference (p0.05). Weight, and calf and arm circumferences were observed to be lower in the older age groups (p0.05). Conclusion: the total and peripheral body mass, for the men, in particular, was lower among the older subjects. Central adiposity did not differ among the age groups in both the genders (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ribeiro, Andréia Queiroz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Priore, Sílvia Eloiza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franceschinni, Sylvia do Carmo Castro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rezende, Fabiane Aparecida Canaan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la antropometría facilita la evaluación de los riesgos asociados con la masa corporal magra reducida, así como con el exceso de adiposidad. Sin embargo, se conoce muy poco acerca de las diferencias antropométricas observadas entre los géneros y entre los grupos de edad en los ancianos. Objetivo: comparar indicadores e índices antropométricos de los ancianos por género y grupo de edad. Métodos: estudio transversal, con una muestra de 621 ancianos. Se evaluó el peso, la talla, circunferencias (cintura, cadera, pantorrilla y brazo), índice de masa corporal, índice de adiposidad corporal, relación cintura-cadera y cintura-talla. Resultados: se encontró que las mujeres tienen un promedio mayor de índice de masa corporal, relación cintura-talla, índice de adiposidad corporal y circunferencia del brazo (p0,05). Se observaron peso y circunferencias de pantorrilla y brazo menores en los grupos de mayor edad (p0,05). Conclusión: la masa corporal total y periférica, para los hombres, en particular, fue menor entre los sujetos de mayor edad. La adiposidad central no fue diferente entre los grupos de edad en ambos géneros (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(2): 757-764, ago. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140011</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias antropométricas relacionadas con géneros y edad en los ancianos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16508^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38802^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1860^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50314</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38802^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55675</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51214^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
