<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123614</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ulcers of lower limb veins: venous ulcers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The lower extremity vascular ulcers currently represent a major public health problem, particularly because of different situations: the chronic nature of the injury, a poor response to treatment, recurrence rates, high absenteeism, poor training in some cases of the health staff that treats, etc. Lower extremity ulcers mean a serious personal, family, health and social problem, with a significant expenditure of human and material resources. Since the prevalence and incidence of lower extremity vascular ulcers is high worldwide, it is necessary to go into detail about the knowledge of the epidemiology and to favour, in different countries, the creation of interdisciplinary research groups that addresses issues related to risk factors, pathogenesis, treatment, health care costs, quality of life and, above all, specialized training aimed at health professionals (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moraleja Millán, Tania</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Jábega, Rosa Mª</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateos García, Marina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bas Caro, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Corral, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Herranz, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las úlceras vasculares de extremidad inferior representan actualmente un importante problema de salud pública, determinado por distintos factores: el carácter crónico de las lesiones, una baja respuesta al tratamiento, la frecuencia de recidivas, el elevado absentismo laboral, la deficiente formación que en algunos casos presenta el personal sanitario encargado de su tratamiento, etc. Todo ello hace que las úlceras de extremidad inferior supongan un grave problema personal, familiar, sanitario y social, con un gasto importante de recursos materiales y humanos. Dado que la prevalencia e incidencia de las úlceras vasculares de extremidad inferior es muy elevada a nivel mundial, se impone la necesidad de profundizar en el conocimiento epidemiológico de las mismas y de que los países favorezcan la creación de grupos de investigación interdisciplinar donde se aborden cuestiones relacionadas con los factores de riesgo, etiopatogenia, terapéutica, gasto sanitario, calidad de vida y, sobre todo, formación especializada dirigida a los profesionales de la salud (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;37(5): 321-328, mayo 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123614</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Úlceras vasculares de extremidad inferior. Úlceras venosas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13421</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15050^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8049^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15050^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
