<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79471</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patterns and harms of pharmaceutical drug use among ecstasy users in Australia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: There has been a significant incursion of prescription drugs in to the club scene worldwide. The concomitant use of ecstasy and pharmaceutical drugs is associated with potentially serious health related harms. This has ramifications for people who deliberately combine pharmaceutical drugs with ecstasy to achieve a specific effect and for people legitimately using pharmaceutical drugs for a health condition who may incidentally use ecstasy. This exploratory study had the broad aim to investigate the patterns and harms of concomitant use of pharmaceutical drugs and ecstasy, and to explore participants&#146; experiences when visiting a General Practitioner (GP). Methods: In-depth interviews were conducted with 30 ecstasy/pharmaceutical drug users. Results: Users reported deliberately combining stimulants (dexamphetamine, methylphenidate (e.g. Ritalin®)), antidepressants and sildenafil (e.g. Viagra®) for non-medical purposes with ecstasy. A wide range of effects were reported. Several clear relationships emerged between the use of pharmaceutical drugs and ecstasy, and the distinctions between these in terms of motivations for use andconsequences are discussed. The attitudes of GPs were professional and non-judgemental and there was little reluctance among participants to disclose illicit drug use. Screening for illicit drug use was limited. Implications: Findings have important implications for clubbers in regard to harm reduction strategies and highlight a number of areas for future research (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Copeland, Jan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dillon, Paul</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silins, Edmund</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: en el ambiente de las discotecas de todo el mundo existe un aumento significativo del uso de medicamentos con receta. El consumo conjunto de éxtasis y fármacos se asocia con daños potencialmente graves para la salud. Esto tiene ramificaciones en el caso de personas que combinan de forma deliberada los fármacos con el éxtasis para lograr un determinado efecto y en quienes toman legalmente fármacos por problemas de salud y de vez en cuando consumen éxtasis. Este estudio exploratorio se propone investigar los hábitos y daños del consumo concomitante de fármacos y éxtasis y explorar las experiencias de los participantes cuando visitan al médico de cabecera (MC). Método: se entrevistó a fondo a 30 consumidores de éxtasis/fármacos. Resultados: los consumidores admitieron la combinación deliberada de estimulantes (dexanfetamina, metilfenidato [p.e. Ritalín]), antidepresivos y sildenafil (p.e. Viagra®) con éxtasis por motivos no médicos. Se descubrió una amplia gama de efectos. Aparecieron claras relaciones entre el consumo de fármacos y éxtasis, y se analizaron las distinciones entre ellos en términos de motivaciones para el consumo y consecuencias del mismo. Las actitudes de los MC fueron profesionales y sin prejuicios, y los participantes mostraron escasa resistencia a reconocer el consumo de drogas ilegales. Se limitó el cribado de drogas ilegales. Consecuencias: Los resultados tienen importantes repercusiones para el público de las discotecas en lo referente a estrategias de reducción del daño y en el descubrimiento de una serie de ámbitos para futuras investigaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);21(4): 347-362, oct.-dic. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79471</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pautas y problemas derivados del consumo de fármacos entre los consumidores de éxtasis en Australia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23605^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4409</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
