<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126079</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7113</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The T oxicology science in the postgraduate studies at the University of V igo</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Educational issues have always been very relevant aspects in Toxicology Department at the University of Vigo, especially taking into account the hanges that the Spanish University has suffered in recent years in relation to the European Higher Education Area. In this regard, professors, assistant professors and lectures from this Department are actively involved in different activities organized by the Training and Educational Innovation Department every academic year. In addition, several subjects are taught in two official postgraduate programs: a) Neuroscience, and b) Food Science and Technology, and two Masters: a) Science and Technology for the Conservation of Fishery Products, and b) Prevention of Occupational Risks, from the Toxicology Department (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lafuente, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el área de Toxicología de la Universidad de Vigo, los temas docentes siempre han sido de especial importancia, sobre todo, teniendo en cuenta los cambios que viene sufriendo la Universidad española en los últimos años en relación al Espacio Europeo de Educación Superior. En este sentido, durante cada curso académico, el profesorado de esta área de conocimiento participa activamente en las diversas actividades or ganizadas por el Vicerrectorado de Formación e Innovación Educativa. Además, el profesorado de Toxicología de la Universidad de Vigo imparte docencia de postgrado en dos Programas Oficiales de Postgrado: a) Neurociencia, y b) Ciencia y Tecnología Alimentaria, y en dos Máster: a) Ciencia y Tecnología de la Conservación de Productos de la Pesca, y b) Prevención de Riesgos Laborales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. toxicol;27(1/2): 1-5, 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126079</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La Toxicología en los estudios de postgrado de la Universidad de Vigo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4571^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4571^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4568^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4571^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4568^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4568^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14509^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9654^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14509^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
