<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147206</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Development and preliminary psychometric characteristics of the PODIUM questionnaire for recreational marathon runners</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this research was to develop a comprehensive and psychometrically adequate measure of recreational marathon runner&#146;s psychological state during the few days and hours prior to the race. The questionnaire was developed in Spanish. In Study 1, Participants were 1060 recreational runners aged 18-67 years. Exploratory factor analysis revealed five dimensions reflective of motivation, self-confidence, anxiety, perceived physical fitness, and perceived social support. In two subsequent studies, the psychometric properties of a refined version of this measure were examined. In study 2, an independent sample of 801 recreational runners (aged 17-63 years) completed the questionnaire. Confirmatory factor analysis and alternative model testing supported a six-factor model. Internal consistency was .72 to .90. In support of construct validity, the self-confidence scale correlated positively with perceived physical fitness, motivation scale correlated positively with social support and self-confidence, and anxiety correlated negatively with motivation and self-confidence factors. In study 3, an independent sample of 22 recreational marathon runners (aged 28- 47 years) responded to the PODIUM and MOMS. Additionally, another independent sample of 36 recreational runners (23-57 years) responded the to PODIUM and CSAI-2 scales. In support of concurrent validity of PODIUM, the motivation scale correlated with MOMS, and the anxiety and the self-confidence scales correlated with CSAI-2 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Buceta, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larumbe, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perez-Llantada, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lopez de la Llave, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de esta investigación era desarrollar un instrumento en español, que fuera completo y adecuado psicométricamente, para la medida del estado psicológico de los corredores de maratón durante los días y horas previos a la carrera. En el estudio 1 participaron 1060 corredores aficionados de 18 a 57 años. El análisis factorial exploratorio mostró cinco dimensiones que reflejaban motivación, autoconfianza, ansiedad, percepción del estado físico y apoyo social percibido. En dos estudios posteriores se examinaron las propiedades psicométricas de una versión depurada de esta medida. En el estudio 2 completaron el cuestionario 801 corredores aficionados (17-63 años) de una muestra independiente. El análisis factorial confirmatorio con modelos alternativos apoyó un modelo de seis factores. La consistencia interna fue de .72 a .90. En apoyo de la validez de constructo, la escala de auto-confianza correlacionó positivamente con la percepción del estado físico, la escala de motivación correlacionó positivamente con el apoyo social y la auto-confianza, y la ansiedad correlacionó negativamente con los factores motivación y auto-confianza. En el estudio 3, una muestra independiente de 22 corredores aficionados (28-47 años) cumplimentaron los cuestionarios PODIUM y MOMS. Adicionalmente, otra muestra independiente de 36 corredores aficionados (23-57 años) cumplimentaron el PODIUM y el CSAI-2. En apoyo de la validez concurrente del PODIUM, la escala de motivación correlacionaba con el MOMS, y las escalas de ansiedad y auto-confianza correlacionaban con el CSAI-2 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;15(3): 41-52, oct. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147206</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desarrollo y características psicométricas preliminares del cuestionario PODIUM para corredores populares de maratón</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12793^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
