<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115703</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Knowledge of the team of nursing on insertion and maintenance of the central catheter of peripheral insertion in just born</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the knowledge of the nursing team on the insertion and the handling of the PICC. Method: Descriptive, documentary and field study. The locale was the ICU Newborn of the HUCF, July to December of 2011. 48 professionals of the nursing staff were part of the study. Results: It was observed that part of the professionals are unaware of the correct definition of PICC, have doubts on the vein of first choice for punction, period of permanence, syringe to be used and permeabilization of the catheter. Conclusion: The permanent education is able to fill the gaps, to be part of the work process, to provide reflection and updating of the daily practices of the worker (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Versiani, Clara de Cássia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva Bretas, Tereza Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>ilva Fagundes, Magna Ferreira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marques Andrade, Frederico</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar el conocimiento del equipo de enfermería sobre la inserción y manipulación del PICC. Método: Estudio descriptivo, documental y de campo. El escenario fue la Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos Neonatal (UTIN) del Hospital Universitario Clemente de Faria, de Montes Claros, Minas Gerais, Brasil entre julio y diciembre de 2011. Participaron 48 profesionales de enfermería. Resultados: Se comprobó que una parte de los profesionales desconocen la definición correcta del PICC, tienen dudas sobre la vena de primera elección para la punción, período de permanencia, tipo de jeringa a ser utilizada y permeabilización del catéter. Conclusión: La formación contínua es capaz de llenar las lagunas, formar parte del proceso de trabajo, proporcionar reflexión y actualización de las prácticas en el cotidiano del profesional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;12(32): 11-29, oct. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115703</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conocimiento del equipo de enfermería sobre la inserción y mantenimiento del catéter central de inserción periférica en recién nacidos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54279^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29480^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30642^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30642^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29480^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30797^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2710^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23183^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22859^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
