<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151422</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Theory and practice of informed consent</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Informed consent is the process of communication between the professional (medical staff and/or investigator) and patient culminating in the decision regarding a particular intervention. However, in our country the concept of informed consent is usually limited to the document that must be signed by the patient to undergo diagnostic or therapeutic procedures riskier. This consent is best understood as a process rather than an event, and also it usually gives consent on care processes rather than on specific events: the acceptance of a process involves a tacitly acceptance of the different components that are usually part of this process. There are many steps in the care process in which a simple permission could be enough, not needing a specific and formal consent... finally, contrary to the usual practice, the acceptance document of consent should be short, clear and understandable, flexible, and with the ability to adapt to the circumstances and the patient&#146;s wishes as far as possible and, all in an atmosphere of trust and verbal information that enables the patient, not forced to confront all the information, to delegate decisions on the professional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valle Rivero, María Luisa del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz Rubiales, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferreira Alonso, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández González, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Por consentimiento informado se entiende el proceso de comunicación entre el profesional (personal sanitario y/o investigador) y el enfermo que culmina en la decisión respecto a una intervención concreta. Sin embargo, en nuestro medio el concepto de consentimiento informado se suele limitar al documento que se pasa a firmar al paciente que va a someterse a procedimientos diagnósticos o terapéuticos de mayor riesgo. Igual que este consentimiento se entiende mejor como un proceso que como un acto, también el consentimiento se suele dar sobre procesos asistenciales más que sobre actos concretos: la aceptación de un proceso supone de manera tácita aceptar los diferentes componentes habituales de este proceso. Son muchos los pasos del proceso asistencial en los que esta aceptación se entiende mejor como un sencillo permiso que como un consentimiento complejo&#133; Por último, en contra de la práctica habitual, el documento de aceptación del consentimiento debería ser breve, claro y comprensible, flexible y con capacidad de adaptarse a las circunstancias y los deseos del paciente dentro de lo posible y, todo ello, en un clima de confianza e información verbal que permita que el paciente que delegue las decisiones en el profesional no se vea obligado a afrontar toda la información (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad Bioet;27(89): 69-78, ene.-abr. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151422</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Teoría y práctica del consentimiento informado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d55386^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55386^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55386^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37688^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23920</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54382^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54382^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
