<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167774</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-755X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Review of neuropsychology of child abuse: Neurobiology and neuropsychological profile in maltreated children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Childhood is stage that is vulnerable to stressful situations, such as abuse. Childhood maltreatment is an adverse environmental factor that may disrupt the neurological development and determine child's brain maturation, leading to cognitive deficits persistent in adulthood. The profile of maltreated children profile features problems in attention, memory, language, and intellectual development, school failure, and high prevalence of internalizing and externalizing problems. Disruptions in neurogenesis, myelinization, synaptogenesis, and neuronal pruning processes, as well as subsequent damage in hippocampus, amygdala, cerebellum, hypothalamus, and cerebral cortex, are the neurobiological physiopathological basis of the said cognitive profile (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mateos-Mateos, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amores-Villalba, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La infancia es una etapa especialmente vulnerable a situaciones estresantes, tales como el maltrato. El maltrato infantil es un factor ambiental adverso, capaz de trastocar el proceso del neurodesarrollo y condicionar la maduración cerebral del menor, desembocando en unos déficits cognitivos persistentes incluso en la vida adulta. El perfil neuropsicológico de niños maltratados se caracteriza por problemas de atención, memoria, lenguaje, desarrollo intelectual, fracaso escolar y elevada prevalencia de trastornos internalizantes y externalizantes. Fallos en los procesos de neurogénesis, mielinización, sinaptogénesis y poda neuronal, así como los posteriores daños en el hipocampo, amígdala, cerebelo, cuerpo calloso, hipotálamo y corteza cerebral son la base neurobiológica sobre la que se asienta dicho perfil cognitivo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. educ. (Madr.);23(2): 81-88, jul.-dic. 2017. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167774</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión de la neuropsicología del maltrato infantil: la neurobiología y el perfil neuropsicológico de las víctimas de abusos en la infancia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2696^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52949^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19621^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56095^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
