<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125759</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The interpretation of transference. A place intime, a time in that place</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The author parts from the clinical fact of the diverse transferential qualities that can be developed by the same patient, and differentiates them around two points of reference: 1) his tendency towards deadly repetition and/or more libidinally saturated repetition that is open to the possibility of mourning and transformation (psychic change); 2) his symbolic quality or level of mentalization. The author also assumes that the analysis-interpretation of the above can only be undertaken in collusion with the patients symbolic functioning and, thus, proposes a work construction, recuperation, maintenance of the setting as a duplication of the apparatus to think the toughts, guareanteeing the thirdness of said functioning. The author presents the clinical history of an analytic process in which this work, based on containing, rhythm, sequence and proposal of meaning and uncertainty inherent to triangulation, is combined with interpretation with sufficiently constituted symbolic level (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Puchades, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El autor parte del hecho clínico de la diversidad de calidades transferenciales susceptibles de ser desarrolladas por un mismo paciente, diferenciándolas en torno a dos referentes: 1) su tendencia a la repetición mortífera y/o a la repetición en tanto más saturada libidinalmente y abierta a la posibilidad de duelo y transformación (cambio psíquico); y 2) su calidad simbólica o nivel de mentalización. Asume, así mismo, que el análisis-interpretación de las mismas sólo puede llevarse a cabo en connivencia con el funcionamiento simbólico del paciente y, en consecuencia, propone un "trabajo de construcción, recuperación, mantenimiento" del encuadre en tanto duplicación del aparato para pensar los pensamientos, garante de la terceridad y de dicho funcionamiento. Presenta el historial clínico de un proceso analítico en el que puede verse cómo se combina dicho trabajo, basado en la contención, el ritmo, secuencia y propuesta de significado e incertidumbre inherentes a la triangulación, con interpretaciones de nivel simbólico suficientemente constituido (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(53): 75-111, ene.-abr. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125759</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La interpretación de la transferencia: un lugar en el tiempo, un tiempo en ese lugar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8776^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53745^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14382</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
