<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125064</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1582</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of lipofilling to improve the results of breast surgery: our experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To present our series of patients who underwent the lipofilling technique in the University General Hospital of Ciudad Real (Spain). Material and methods. A descriptive, retrospective study was carried out in series of patients who underwent surgery for breast cancer and who were candidates for breast reconstruction using autologous fat graft between 2010 and 2012. The variables analyzed were age, first surgery performed, adjuvant treatment, mean weight of grafted fat, mean operating time, length of hospital stay, and complications in the short-term (within 7 days) and long-term (past 7 days). Results. Our series consisted of 40 women with a mean age of 44.9 years (40-54). The mean length of hospital stay was 23 h without complications in the short- or long-term. Fifteen (37.5%) patients reported sinking volume loss. In 6 patients, the procedure was repeated. Conclusion. In our 2-year experience, autologous fat can be a useful technique to allow regeneration of affected areas, providing elasticity to tissues in patients with cosmetic defects after breast cancer. One-third of the patients experienced a loss of volume during follow-up (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rabadán-Ruiz, Lorenzo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Santos, Esther Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-García, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manzanares-García, M. Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Fernández, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo-García, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Presentar nuestra serie de pacientes en los que se ha llevado a cabo la técnica de lipofilling en el Hospital General Universitario de Ciudad Real. Material y métodos. Estudio descriptivo, retrospectivo de una serie de pacientes intervenidas quirúrgicamente por cáncer de mama y candidatas a reconstrucción mamaria mediante injerto autógeno de grasa, en el período de tiempo comprendido entre 2010 y 2012. Las variables analizadas fueron: edad, primera intervención quirúrgica realizada, tratamiento adyuvante, peso medio de grasa injertada, tiempo medio operatorio, tiempo de hospitalización, así como complicaciones a corto (en los primeros 7 días) y largo plazo (pasados los primeros 7 días). Resultados. Nuestra serie consta de un total de 40 pacientes mujeres, con una edad media de 44,9 años (40-54). El tiempo medio de hospitalización fue de 23 h, sin complicaciones a corto ni a largo plazo. Quince (37,5%) pacientes han referido pérdida de volumen con hundimiento del lecho quirúrgico durante el seguimiento. Seis casos se han sometido de nuevo al procedimiento. Conclusión. En nuestra experiencia durante 2 años, el autotrasplante de grasa puede ser una técnica conveniente que permita la regeneración de áreas afectadas, proporcionando elasticidad a los tejidos en pacientes con defectos estéticos tras cáncer de mama. En una tercera parte de las pacientes hubo pérdida de volumen durante el seguimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. senol. patol. mamar. (Ed. impr.);27(3): 119-122, jul.-sept. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125064</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso del lipofilling en la mejora de los resultados de la cirugía de la mama. Nuestra experiencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29995^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14573^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29995^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29995^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29995^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8580^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8580^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d284^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
