<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142529</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anthropometric secular changes among two cohorts of healthy infants aged 0-2 years born in 1993 and 2009</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To accomplish a longitudinal anthropometric study in two different cohorts of healthy children (from birth to 2 years of age) who were born in 1993 and 2009. The possible appearance of secular changes within this period is analyzed. Material and methods: Weight, height and body mass index (BMI) at birth and ages 3, 6, 9, 12, 15, 18 and 24 months in two different cohorts of healthy children born in 1993 (459 males and 425 females) and 2009 (460 males and 481 females) have been registered and analyzed. Results: Average values for weight and BMI in 1993 cohort were significantly higher (p &lt; 0.05) than those in 2009 cohort beyond 6 months of age in females and 9 months of age in males, up to 24 months of age. There were no statistically significant differences among average values of registered height in every period of age within both cohorts. Conclusions: The comparison of anthropometric data among two different cohorts of healthy children born in 1993 and 2009 in similar social and health conditions shows a &#147;secular change&#148; in a negative sense regarding weight and BMI, without affecting height (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Durá Travé, Teodoro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallinas Victoriano, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ulibarrena Ascarza, Noelia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guembero Esarte, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Realizar un estudio antropométrico longitudinal en dos cohortes de niños sanos, desde el nacimiento hasta los 2 años de edad, nacidos en los años 1993 y 2009; analizándose los cambios seculares que pudieran haberse dado durante este intervalo de tiempo. Material y métodos: Se han registrado retrospectivamente y comparado los pesos, tallas e índice de masa corporal (IMC) al nacimiento y a las edades de 3, 6, 9, 12, 15, 18 y 24 meses, de dos cohortes de niños sanos nacidos en los años 1993 (459 varones y 425 mujeres) y 2009 (460 varones y 481 mujeres). Resultados: Los valores medios de los pesos e IMC de la cohorte del año 1993 eran significativamente superiores (p &lt; 0,05) respecto a los de la cohorte del año 2009 a partir de los 6 meses de edad en las mujeres y de los 9 meses de edad en los varones y hasta los 24 meses de edad. En ambos sexos, no existían diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre los valores medios de las tallas registradas en cada una de las edades consideradas entre ambas cohortes. Conclusiones: Al comparar los datos antropométricos entre dos cohortes de niños sanos nacidos en los años 1993 y 2009 en condiciones socio-sanitarias similares se ha advertido un &#147;cambio secular&#148; con sentido negativo en lo que respecta al peso e IMC, sin afectarse la talla (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;30(2): 314-320, ago. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142529</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambios seculares antropométricos entre dos cohortes de niños sanos de 0 a 2 años de edad nacidos en 1993 y 2009</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6278</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16508</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
