<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108413</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pacifier sucking habit and associated dental changes: Importance of early diagnosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The non-nutritive sucking habits are a physiological activity during the first months of life of a child, but if they persist afterwards, these habits can affect the development of dental occlusion. The aim of this study was to determine the frequency of past pacifier-sucking habits in a sample of school children and its role in the genesis of dental malocclusion in primary dentition, as well as to follow up these alterations until the next phase of the dentition (mixed dentition). Material and methods: We performed a longitudinal epidemiological study on a sample of 225 children from age 2 to 10 years in the Basque Autonomous Region. Data were obtained by means of a questionnaire of children habits, filled in by parents, and clinical tests carried out on the children, recording the presence of alterations in dental occlusion, such as anterior open bite and posterior crossbite. Results: We found a significant increase of malocclusion in the primary dentition of children who prolonged the pacifier-sucking habit. If this habit was abandoned early, anterior open bites improved, while posterior crossbites clutch remained or even got worse. Conclusions: The pacifier sucking habit influences the development of the teeth, thus, it is necessary to detect early changes in order to prevent the establishment of dental malocclusion(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gorritxo Gil, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco Varas, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los hábitos de succión no nutritiva constituyen una actividad fisiológica durante los primeros meses de vida del niño, pero si se mantienen pueden afectar el desarrollo de la oclusión dentaria. El objetivo del presente trabajo ha sido conocer en una muestra de niños escolares la frecuencia del hábito de succión del chupete, su papel en la génesis de maloclusiones dentales en la dentición temporal y realizar un seguimiento de estas alteraciones hasta la siguiente fase de la dentición (dentición mixta). Material y métodos: Se ha realizado un estudio epidemiológico longitudinal sobre una muestra de 225 niños de edades comprendidas entre los 2 y los 10 años en la comunidad autónoma vasca. Los datos se han obtenido mediante un cuestionario de hábitos dirigido a los padres y las exploraciones clínicas realizadas a los niños, registrando la presencia de alteraciones en la oclusión como: mordida abierta anterior y mordida cruzada posterior. Resultados: Se ha encontrado un incremento significativo de las maloclusiones estudiadas en dentición temporal en los niños que mantenían el hábito de succión del chupete. Las mordidas abiertas anteriores mejoraban al abandonar el hábito tempranamente; sin embargo, las mordidas cruzadas posteriores se mantenían o empeoraron, aunque se había producido el abandono del hábito de succión. Conclusiones: El hábito de succión del chupete influye en el desarrollo de la dentición por lo que se hace necesario la detección precoz de las alteraciones que se presenten con el fin de prevenir la instauración de maloclusiones dentales(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);77(6): 374-380, dic. 2012. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108413</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hábito de succión del chupete y alteraciones dentarias asociadas. Importancia del diagnóstico precoz</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8483^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37600^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13777</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3832</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
