<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134048</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Platelet-Rich Plasma: Applications in Dermatology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In recent years, the use of platelet-rich plasma has increased notably in a range of diseases and settings. Uses of these products now go beyond skin rejuvenation therapy in patients with facial ageing. Good outcomes for other dermatological indications such as skin ulcers and, more recently, alopecia have been reported in case series and controlled studies. However, these indications are not currently included in the labeling given that stronger scienti- fic evidence is required to support their real benefits. With the increased use of these products, dermatologists need to become familiar with the underlying biological principles and able to critically assess the quality and outcomes of the studies of these products in different skin diseases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Santos, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conde Montero, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez Fernández, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La aplicación del plasma rico en plaquetas ha experimentado un notable auge en los últimos años en una amplia variedad de enfermedades y situaciones clínicas. Su empleo en dermatología va más allá de su asociación con el envejecimiento facial. En la literatura se pueden encontrar series de casos y estudios controlados que muestran buenos resultados en aplicaciones diversas, como las úlceras cutáneas y, más recientemente, la alopecia. Sin embargo, estas indicaciones no están reconocidas en la ficha técnica en el momento actual, a falta de poder demostrar sus beneficios reales con mayor evidencia científica. Ante la expansión en el uso de esta técnica resulta fundamental el conocimiento de sus fundamentos biológicos y la evaluación de la calidad y de los resultados de los trabajos que estudian su aplicación en diferentes enfermedades cutáneas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;106(2): 104-111, mar. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134048</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Plasma rico en plaquetas: aplicaciones en dermatología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3900^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13264^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3900^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13264^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3900^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52020^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54211^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54211^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3900^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d508^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52020^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d508^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
