<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153285</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bone marrow invasion in multiple myeloma and metastatic disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the spine is the imaging study of choice for the management of bone marrow disease. MRI sequences enable us to integrate structural and functional information for detecting, staging, and monitoring the response the treatment of multiple myeloma and bone metastases in the spine. Whole-body MRI has been incorporated into different guidelines as the technique of choice for managing multiple myeloma and metastatic bone disease. Normal physiological changes in the yellow and red bone marrow represent a challenge in analyses to differentiate clinically significant findings from those that are not clinically significant. This article describes the findings for normal bone marrow, variants, and invasive processes in multiple myeloma and bone metastases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vilanova, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luna, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La resonancia magnética (RM) de columna es la exploración de elección para el manejo de la patología de la médula ósea. La RM incluye secuencias morfológicas y funcionales para poder integrar la información en el estudio de la patología infiltrativa del mieloma múltiple y metástasis óseas del raquis, desde la detección, estadificación y monitorización terapéutica. En la actualidad, la RM de cuerpo entero se está integrando en las distintas guías como la técnica de elección en el manejo del mieloma múltiple y enfermedad metastásica ósea. Los cambios fisiológicos de la médula amarilla y roja suponen un reto en el análisis para diferenciar hallazgos clínicamente significativos de los hallazgos clínicamente no significativos. El presente artículo describe las características en RM de los hallazgos fisiológicos, variantes y procesos infiltrativos de la médula ósea para el manejo del mieloma múltiple y las metástasis óseas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);58(supl.1): 81-93, abr. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153285</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infiltración de la médula ósea, mieloma múltiple y enfermedad metastásica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9293^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1878^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1878^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13515^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13515^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9293^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
