<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84379</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Meniscal disorders in the immature knee</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Intra articular knee injuries in the pediatric age, classically considered as rarer than those occurring in adulthood, has seen a rise in consultations due especially to an increased participation of children in «extreme sports» and an improved diagnosis of these injuries. There are few studies that establish the prevalence of knee injuries prior to maturity; however, arthroscopic studies have found a heightened frequency of anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) ruptures, meniscal tears and osteochondral fractures secondary to patellofemoral instability. The authors in this study update these pathologies and provide their experience in diagnostic and treatment of meniscal lesions in pediatric age. The most frequent meniscal injuries are the traumatic tears, but discoid meniscus, cysts and hipermobility are also discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vidal, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cubillo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las lesiones postraumáticas de la rodilla en los niños, aunque raras, han aumentado su frecuencia en los últimos tiempos, debido a la mayor participación deportiva de la población juvenil. Los autores analizan el diagnóstico y tratamiento de las lesiones meniscales durante el crecimiento y su diagnóstico diferencial con patología meniscales, menisco discoideo, quiste meniscal y menisco hipermóvil, características de la juventud (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);19(1): 43-49, ene.-mar. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84379</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lesiones meniscales durante el crecimiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1189^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14364^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1870^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14364^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14365^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7893^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7893^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14364^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6278^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19395^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19395^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
