<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76369</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1780</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Place conditioning in rats and ethanol</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">One of the most common procedures used toassess the hedonic value of a drug is the conditioned place (CP) which explores thepreference or the aversion towards a previously drug paired context. In this paper wereport on the different apparatus, procedures and dependant measures used on CP and themain results found using ethanol. Finally we present a CP between-within subjects experimenton rats. The experiment consisted in three phases: (1) Pre-Test, we measured the animal&#146;spreference towards both contexts black place (BP) and white place (WP); (2) Conditioning,each animal received ethanol (dose: 0.5g/kg, i.p.) paired with the non preferred contextand saline paired with the preferred context on alternate trials. A control group receivedvehicle in both contexts; (3) Post-Test same as pre-test. In both tests the time spent in eachcontext was measured. The ethanol treated group reversed its place preference, whereasthe saline group kept its initial preference. From this study we inferred that under thisdose, ethanol has a positive hedonic value(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cuenya, Lucas</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kamenetzky, Giselle Vanesa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elisabeth Mustaca, Alba</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedrón, Valeria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Uno de los procedimientos usados con animales no humanos para conocer el valor hedónicode las drogas es el condicionamiento de lugar (CL) en el cual se evalúa la preferencia oaversión hacia un contexto asociado previamente con una droga, inferido por el tiempode permanencia en ese lugar, en comparación con otro asociado a un vehículo (salina). Eneste trabajo informaremos sobre distintos aparatos, procedimientos, medidas dependientesutilizadas en el CL y los resultados principales hallados con el uso de etanol. Finalmentese presenta un experimento de CL con ratas en el cual se utilizó un diseño intra-intersujeto.Consistió en tres fases: (1) pre-test, preferencia de las ratas hacia dos contextos: lugarnegro (LN) y lugar blanco (LB); (2) condicionamiento, cada animal del grupo experimentalrecibió ensayos alternados de etanol (dosis 0.5 g/kg) asociados al contexto no preferidoy solución salina al preferido; los del grupo control, recibieron salina asociado a amboscontextos; (3) post-test igual al pre-test. En ambas pruebas se midió el tiempo de permanenciade las ratas en cada contexto. Los animales tratados con etanol revirtieron lapreferencia de lugar, mientras los del grupo salina no la modificaron. De este estudio seinfiere que bajo la dosis utilizada, el etanol tiene un valor hedónico positivo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int. j. psychol. psychol. ther. (Ed. impr.);7(3): 321-333, 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76369</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Condicionamiento de lugar en ratas y etanol</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d431</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5657</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3238</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
