<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047777</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Echinacea</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">herbs by the autochthonous populations of North America. Severaltribes (Cheyenne, Choctaw, Dakita, Ponca, Sioux, Winnebago)use this herb as a remedy to fight respiratory infections and snakebites. After the European colonisation, its use extended throughoutthe United States to be later exported to Europe, where it becamevery popular in the early XX century.Currently, the echinacea herb is used to reduce the symptoms andduration of the common cold and flu. This is the most researcheduse in clinical trials, explaining why the German E Commission(regulatory organisation on medicinal herb consumption in Germany)has approved its use for that indication.The World Health Organisation based on a review of papers publisheduntil 1999, also supports the use of this herb both for respiratoryand urinary infections.The consumption of Echinacea, based on purely theoretical foundations,would be contraindicated in patients with any type of autoimmunedisease</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Serrano Ruiz, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">poblacionesautóctonas de América del Norte. Numerosas tribus (Cheyenne,Choctaw, Dakota, Ponca, Sioux, Winnebago) la utilizaban comoremedio para las infecciones respiratorias y las mordeduras deserpientes. Tras la colonización europea, su uso se extendió por todoslos Estados Unidos y posteriormente se importó a Europa,donde alcanzó una gran popularidad a principios del siglo XX.Actualmente, la Echinacea se utiliza para reducir los síntomas yduración del resfriado común y de la gripe. Éste es el uso más estudiadopor medio de ensayos clínicos, de ahí que sea la indicaciónaprobada por la German E Comisión (organismo reguladordel consumo de plantas medicinales en Alemania).La Organización Mundial de la Salud, basándose en una revisiónde los estudios publicados hasta 1999, respalda también su usotanto para infecciones respiratorias como urinarias. Además de estosusos, los estudios in vitro con Echinacea apuntan a un posibleefecto sobre el sistema inmunológico, lo que se traduciría en unincremento de la respuesta ante infecciones.El consumo de Echinacea, en función de planteamientos puramenteteóricos, estaría contraindicado en pacientes con cualquiertipo de enfermedad autoinmune</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;9(6): 50-52, jul. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047777</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Echinacea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12560^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34147</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29482</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
