<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88467</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Retinal autofluorescence imaging in patients with pseudoxanthoma elasticum</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">PurposeTo evaluate the autofluorescence findings in patients diagnosed with pseudoxanthoma elasticum.Material and methodsA prospective study was conducted on 18 eyes of 9 patients who had ocular pathology andfollowed up in the pseudoxanthoma elasticum (PSX) unit of our hospital. We evaluated the best corrected visual acuity (BCVA), colour and autofluorescence photography (AF), and fluorescein angiography (FA) in patients with choroidal neovascularitation.ResultsOf the 9 patients, 7 were women and 2 were men. The mean age was 40 +/- 14 years. The BCVA ranged from 1 to 0.01 (Mean 0.65 +/- 0.4).All patients showed PSX injuries. Angioid streaks (AS) 18 (100%), peau d&#145;orange 16 (87.5%) and pigmented fibrotic plates 5 (31,5%). We observed different hypoautofluorescence patterns (RPE atrophy), of which 2 of them were AS patterns (irregular lines with hyperautofluorescence speckled in its interior and edges, or bands with lobulated lesions inside and hyperautofluorescence at the edges), and finally widespread areas of hypoautofluorescence, larger than observed by ophthalmoscope.ConclusionsAutofluorescence in patients with PSX is an easy method to evaluate the initial level of ophthalmoscopic involvement and its subsequent progression. The extensive changes in the retinal pigment epithelium (RPE) suggests the important role of this in the physiopathology of the disease(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Soler, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Campos, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morillo, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Fernández, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valdivieso, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">PropósitoEvaluar las lesiones funduscópicas con autofluorescencia en pacientes diagnosticados de pseudoxantoma elástico (PSX).Material y métodoSe realizó un estudio prospectivo de 9 pacientes (18 ojos), en seguimiento por la unidad de PSX de nuestro hospital, que presentaban dolencia ocular. Evaluamos mejor agudeza visual corregida (MAVC), fotografía en color y con autofluorescencia (FA), así como angiografía fluoresceínica (AFG) en los casos que presentaban neovascularización coroidea (NVC).ResultadosDe los 9 pacientes, 7 eran mujeres y 2 hombres. Edad media de 40,5 +/- 14, MAVC desde la 1 a 0,01 (media=0,65 +/- 0,4). Todos los pacientes (18 ojos) presentaban lesiones del PSX: estrías angioides (EA) en 18 (100%), fondo en «piel de naranja» en 16 (87,5%) y placas fibrogliales pigmentadas en 5 ojos (31,5%). Observamos diferentes patrones de hipoautofluorescencias (atrofia de epitelio pigmentario), dos que se corresponderían a EA (líneas anfractuosas con moteado hiperautofluorescente en su seno y bordes, o bien bandas con lesiones lobuladas en su seno e hiperautofluorescencia en sus bordes) y por último grandes placas hipoautofluorescentes, de mayor tamaño que las observadas funduscópicamente.ConclusionesLa autofluorescencia en los pacientes con PSX es un método fácil para valorar el grado de afectación funduscópica inicial y su posterior evolución. La gran afectación del epitelio pigmentario retiniano (EPR), que hemos observado, nos sugiere el importante papel que juega este, en la fisiopatología de esta enfermedad(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;86(1): 8-15, ene. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88467</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Imágenes funduscópicas con autofluorescencia en pacientes con pseudoxantoma elástico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11998^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d804^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13433^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201101</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
