<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155006</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1837</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hypertensive crisis and sudden change of vision in young patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The sudden change in vision is a medical emergency that must be evaluated immediately to rule out important institutions as systemic vasculitis or ischemic stroke. Its association with hypertensive crisis makes it necessary to rule out accelerated-malignant hypertension, which is accompanied by other retinal disorders (exudates and hemorrhages) and adrenal involvement. Nonarteritic anterior ischemic optic neuropathy (AION) is another entity to consider, as is it not uncommon in the young (12.7% in a series of 848 cases). Its association with hypertension has been described in 32% of cases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cortés Fernández, MS</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Castillejos, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armario,  P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La alteración brusca de la visión es una urgencia médica en la cual se deben descartar entidades como la vasculitis sistémica, el ictus isquémico y la hipertensión acelerada-maligna. La neuropatía isquémica óptica anterior (NOIA) no arterítica es otra entidad a tener en cuenta, ya que no es infrecuente en jóvenes (12,7% en una serie de 848 casos). Se ha descrito su asociación con la hipertensión arterial en un 32% de casos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Hipertens. riesgo vasc;33(3): 111-113, jul.-sept. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155006</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Crisis hipertensiva y alteración brusca de la visión en el paciente joven</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15187^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27729^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7153^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53543^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30893^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1333^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
