<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151739</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9168</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epigenetics in atherosclerosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The association studies based on candidate genes carried on for decades have helped in visualizing the influence of the genetic component in complex diseases such as atherosclerosis, also showing the interaction between different genes and environmental factors. Even with all the knowledge accumulated, there is still some way to go to decipher the individual predisposition to disease, and if we consider the great influence that environmental factors play in the development and progression of atherosclerosis, epigenetics is presented as a key element in trying to expand our knowledge on individual predisposition to atherosclerosis and cardiovascular disease. Epigenetics can be described as the discipline that studies the mechanisms of transcriptional regulation, independent of changes in the sequence of DNA, and mostly induced by environmental factors. This review aims to describe what epigenetics is and how epigenetic mechanisms are involved in atherosclerosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guardiola, Montse</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallvé, Joan C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribalta, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zaina, Silvio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los estudios de asociación basados en genes candidato llevados a cabo durante décadas han servido para visualizar la influencia del componente genético en enfermedades complejas como la arteriosclerosis y también para evidenciar la interacción entre diferentes genes y, especialmente, la de estos con factores ambientales. Incluso con el conocimiento acumulado, aún queda camino por recorrer para descifrar la predisposición individual a la enfermedad y, si tenemos en cuenta la gran influencia que los factores ambientales juegan en el desarrollo y la progresión de la arteriosclerosis, la epigenética se nos presenta como un elemento clave para ampliar nuestro conocimiento de la predisposición individual a la arteriosclerosis. La epigenética se puede describir como la disciplina que estudia los mecanismos de regulación transcripcional independientes de la secuencia del ADN, mayoritariamente inducidos por factores ambientales. Esta revisión pretende describir qué es la epigenética y de qué manera los mecanismos epigenéticos participan en la arteriosclerosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. arterioscler. (Ed. impr.);28(2): 102-119, mar.-abr. 2016. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151739</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Epigenética en la arteriosclerosis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53247</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38372</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37535^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33163^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23282^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
