<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149643</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A systematic review of economic evaluations of pacemaker telemonitoring systems</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: Over the last decade, telemedicine applied to pacemaker monitoring has undergone extraordinary growth. It is not known if telemonitoring is more or less efficient than conventional monitoring. The aim of this study was to carry out a systematic review analyzing the available evidence on resource use and health outcomes in both follow-up modalities. Methods: We searched 11 databases and included studies published up until November 2014. The inclusion criteria were: a) experimental or observational design; b) studies based on complete economic evaluations; c) patients with pacemakers, and d) telemonitoring compared with conventional hospital monitoring. Results: Seven studies met the inclusion criteria, providing information on 2852 patients, with a mean age of 81 years. The main indication for device implantation was atrioventricular block. With telemonitoring, cardiovascular events were detected and treated 2 months earlier than with conventional monitoring, thus reducing length of hospital stay by 34% and reducing routine and emergency hospital visits as well. There were no significant intergroup differences in perceived quality of life or number of adverse events. The cost of telemonitoring was 60% lower than that of conventional hospital monitoring. Conclusions: Compared with conventional monitoring, cardiovascular events were detected earlier and the number or hospitalizations and hospital visits was reduced with pacemaker telemonitoring. In addition, the costs associated with follow-up were lower with telemonitoring (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villegas-Tripiana, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Villegas, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Saborido, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Catalán-Matamoros, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Robles-Musso, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: En la última década, la telemedicina aplicada a la monitorización de marcapasos cardiacos ha experimentado un extraordinario crecimiento. Se desconoce si esta tecnología tiene una eficiencia diferente de la convencional. El objetivo del estudio es realizar una revisión sistemática analizando la evidencia disponible con respecto al consumo de recursos y los resultados en salud en ambas modalidades de seguimiento. Métodos: La búsqueda se realizó en 11 bases de datos y se incluyeron estudios publicados hasta noviembre de 2014. Los criterios de inclusión fueron: a) diseño experimental u observacional; b) estudios basados en evaluaciones económicas completas; c) pacientes con marcapasos, y d) telemonitorización comparada con la modalidad hospitalaria. Resultados: Siete estudios cumplían los criterios de inclusión, con información sobre 2.852 pacientes con una media de edad de 81 años; el bloqueo auriculoventricular era la principal indicación. En la telemonitorización, los eventos cardiovasculares se detectan y tratan 2 meses antes, con lo que se reduce en un 34% el número de hospitalizaciones, así como las visitas rutinarias y de urgencias al hospital. No hubo diferencias intergrupales significativas en calidad de vida percibida o número de eventos adversos. El coste de la telemonitorización es un 60% menor que el de la monitorización hospitalaria. Conclusiones: En la telemonitorización de marcapasos, los eventos cardiovasculares se detectan antes y disminuyen las hospitalizaciones y el número de visitas al hospital. Además, con la telemonitorización se reducen los costes asociados al seguimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;69(2): 125-133, feb. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149643</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión sistemática de evaluaciones económicas de los sistemas de telemonitorización en los marcapasos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30481^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30057^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10326^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30176^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32137^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
