<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110173</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nutritional status among hospitalized children with mixed diagnoses at a referral teaching hospital in Manizales, Colombia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Despite advances in the treatment of malnutrition in pediatric hospitals, this remains a problem that must be recognized and to call the attention of academia and health authorities to be handled in time. Objective: To evaluate the nutritional status of hospitalized children at a referral teaching hospital and to describe the current prevalence of malnutrition. Methods: The study was conducted during the months of February, March and April 2010 at the University Hospital Rafael Henao Toro Colombian Red Cross in Manizales, Colombia, South America. We evaluated all patients admitted to a day of each month by calculating the Z score of the, weight for age, height or length for age, body mass index, mid-arm circumference, triceps and subscapularfolds for children under 5 years and height for age and body mass index for school children and adolescents. Results: A total of 174 children (age 1-216 mo) were evaluated during the 3-days survey. There were 52.8% children less than 60 months old, 17.2% between 61 and 120 months and 29.9% over 121 months. There were 44.3% females and 55.7% males. Children from the urban residence were 83.3% and 16.6% were rural. The overall prevalence of underweight was 27%, stunting 22.4%, wasting 16.6% and overweight and obesity 6.3%. Males less than five years old were more affected than older children. Rural children were more affected than urban children. The prevalence of overweight children was greater in children 61-120 months than other ages. Conclusion: Given the observed levels of malnutrition, it takes up a system for early identification of children hospitalized with nutritional risk in order to provide adequate and timely support and prevent hospital-acquired malnutrition. This requires the use of previously validated pediatric protocols (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villegas Galarza, AL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santafé Sánchez, LR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Rodríguez, DA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Correa, CH</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: A pesar de los avances en el tratamiento de la malnutrición en hospitales pediátricos, éste sigue siendo un problema que debe ser reconocido y que debe llamar la atención de la academia y de las autoridades de salud con el fin de ser manejado a tiempo. Objetivo: Evaluar el estado nutricional de los niños internados en un hospital pediátrico universitario de referencia y describir la prevalencia de malnutrición. Métodos: El estudio fue realizado durante los meses de Febrero, Marzo y Abril del 2010 en el Hospital Universitario Rafael Henao Toro de la Cruz Roja Colombiana en Manizales-Colombia-Sur América. Se evaluaron todos los pacientes internados en un día de cada mes mediante el cálculo del puntaje Z del peso para la edad, la estatura o longitud para la edad, el índice de masa corporal, la circunferencia media del brazo y los pliegues tricipital y subescapular para niños menores de 5 años y la estatura para la edad y el índice de masa corporal para escolares y adolescentes. Resultados: En total se evaluaron 174 niños entre 1 y 216 meses de edad. El 52,8% fueron menores de 60 meses, el 17,2% entre 61 y 120 meses y el 29,9% mayores de 121 meses. Un 44,3% fueron mujeres y un 55,7% hombres. El 83,3% de los niños eran procedentes de área urbana y el 16,6% de área rural. La prevalencia de desnutrición global fue de 27%, desnutrición crónica 22,4%, desnutrición aguda 16,6% y 6,3% de sobrepeso y obesidad. Los más afectados fueron los niños y niñas procedentes del área rural y los niños menores de 5 años. La prevalencia de sobrepeso fue mayor en niños en edades de 61 a 121 meses de edad. Conclusión: Dados los niveles de malnutrición observados, se necesita instaurar un sistema para la identificación temprana de los niños hospitalizados con riesgo nutricional con el fin de proveer un soporte adecuado y oportuno y evitar la malnutrición adquirida en el hospital. Para ello se requiere el uso de protocolos pediátricos previamente validados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;27(5): 1451-1459, sept.-oct. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110173</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estado nutricional en niños hospitalizados con diagnósticos mixtos en un hospital universitario de referencia en Manizales, Colombia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6278</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23583^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3137^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2711^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24212^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
