<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156777</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-7615</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Scientific production in cannabis and tobacco consumption by means of the Web of Science</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this paper is to quantify scientific productivity on cannabis and tobacco consumption by means of bibliometric indicators, in order to learn and determine what state the research in this field is in and to identify the collaborative networks of authors who have published articles on this topic and journals used by researchers to publish their work. The papers covered by the study were obtained from the databases of the Web of Science. 1,008 works were published, the predominant type of document being original papers and review articles, which together represent almost 95% of all production. The first article recovered dated from 1981 and it is observed that since 2000, there has been a steady increase in the number of papers published, which confirms the interest awakened in this issue and the need to promote research in this field. The journals most often used to publish articles have been Drug and Alcohol Dependence, Addictive Behaviors and Addiction, which are included in the category Substance Abuse of the database Journal Citation Reports (JCR) of the Social Science Citation Index (SSCI) and positioned in the first quartile in this subject category (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Osca-Lluch, Julia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo es cuantificar mediante indicadores bibliométricos la productividad científica sobre el consumo de cannabis y tabaco, con el fin de conocer y determinar el estado en que se encuentra la investigación en este campo e identificar las redes de colaboración de autores que han publicado artículos sobre este tema y las revistas utilizadas por los investigadores para publicar sus trabajos. Los trabajos objeto de estudio se han obtenido de las bases de datos de la Web of Science. Se publicaron 1.008 trabajos, siendo la tipología documental predominante los artículos originales y los artículos de revisión, que juntos suponen casi el 95% de toda la producción. El primer artículo recuperado data de 1981, y se observa, partir del año 2000, un aumento constante en el número de trabajos publicados, que viene a confirmar el interés despertado en este tema y la necesidad de potenciar la investigación en este campo. Las revistas más utilizadas para publicar los artículos han sido Drug and Alcohol Dependence, Addictive Behaviors y Addiction, que están incluidas en la categoría Substance Abuse de la base de datos Journal Citation Reports (JCR) del Social Science Citation Index (SSCI) y posicionadas en el primer cuartil dentro de esta categoría temática (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. drogodepend;41(3): 29-45, 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156777</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Producción científica en consumo de cannabis y tabaco a través de la Web of Science</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50088</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55441^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55441^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2220</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9672^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19621^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22937^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19621^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22937^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
