<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138475</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidural spinal abscesses. Review of a clinical serie</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The spinal abscess is an infrequent infectious complication whose diagnosis is often delayed, therefore bringing about significant morbidity and death rates. In the last years, its incidence has raised progressively. The objective of this work is to present the clinical features of a series of spinal abscesses. Method: The clinical histories of all patients diagnosed of spinal cord abscess were evaluated retrospectively. Results: We obtained seven cases, with a 5/2 male/female proportion, all subjects being over 50 years old. Incidence was 0.58/10,000 admissions per year. All patients debuted with local pains, but only 6/7 (90%) had fever. Focal neurological signs appeared in all patients within the first 0-5 day-period; they were weakness (86%) and sensitive alterations (43%). The most frequent germ was Staphylococcus aureus ( 5 0%). Diabetes mellitus existed in 5/7 cases (71.5%). Four patients were treated by surgery; three of them (75%) had flaccid motor deficit as sequel and the other died. Medical treatment alone was maintained in 3/7 (43%); two experienced partial improvement without recovery of the motor functions and another died. Conclusions: Spinal epidural abscess is a rare, although serious, disease. For this reason, we should maintain a high level of suspicion when a patient has spinal or radicular pain associated with systemic symptoms such as fever or deterioration in the general state of health, especially in patients &gt;50 years under weakening situations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Toledo, VA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pi, OF</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego, JH</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Román, MP</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El absceso espinal constituye una complicación infecciosa poco frecuente que conlleva una morbimortalidad significativa y que se diagnostica tardíamente. En los últimos años su incidencia ha experimentado un aumento progresivo. El objetivo de este trabajo es presentar las características clínicas de una serie de abscesos espinales. Método. Se evaluaron de forma retrospectiva las historias clínicas de todos los pacientes con diagnóstico de absceso espinal. Resultados. Se obtuvieron siete casos, con una proporción hombre/mujer de 5/2, todos de edad superior a 50 años. La incidencia fue de 0,58/10.000 ingresos/año. El inicio fue con algias locales en 7/7 casos, asociando fiebre 6/7 (90%); la clínica neurológica apareció en 7/7 al cabo de 0-5 días en forma de paresia (86%) y alteraciones sensitivas (43%). El germen más frecuente fue Staphylococcus aureus ( 5 0%). En 5/7 ( 7 1 , 5%) existía una diabetes mellitus previa. En 4/7 (57% ) s e practicó cirugía, presentando tres de ellos (75%) un déficit motor flácido como secuela; uno fue exitus. En 3/7 (43% ) se mantuvo sólo tratamiento médico, dos experimentaron una mejoría parcial sin recuperación de las funciones motoras y otro acabó en exitus. Conclusiones. El absceso espinal epidural es una patología infrecuente, aunque grave, por lo que se debe mantener un alto nivel de sospecha en todo paciente con dolor espinal o radicular asociado a síntomas sistémicos como fiebre o deterioro del estado general, sobre todo en pacientes mayores de 50 años con alguna situación debilitante (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;23(2): 85-90, mar. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138475</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abscesos espinales epidurales. Revisión de una serie clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34159^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13590^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13501^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13590^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13590^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34159^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13501^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34159^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34159^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13501^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13501^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
