<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056980</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5665</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Therapeutical angiogenesis in patients with critical leg ischemia. Phase II study with injection of AC133+ cells mobilized with G-CSF from peripheral blood. Follow-up of three first cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Chronical arterial disease (CAD) is an extremely        incapacitating illness which affects 3-5% of the male        population above 60 years-old. Actually, cell therapy is an        alternative that causes great expectation for the treatment        of the peripheral ischemias. The aim of the present study        was to analyze the efficiency and security of autologous        AC133+ cells on promoting limb revascularization in patients        with critical CAD.        Material and Methods: Three patients with critical CAD        were included and followed up to date. The patients were        subjected to mobilization of hematopoietic precursors from        the bone marrow to peripheral blood with G-CSF. Later, the        autologous endothelial stem cells AC133+, extracted and        selected from blood through the CliniMACS® (Miltenyi        Biotec) system, were injected intramuscularly. The patients        were followed for 6 months as the study&#146;s protocol and clinical,        functional, hemodynamic, anatomical and quality of        life variables were evaluated.        Results: The process of mobilization, collection and infusion        of the endothelial stem cells was well tolerated. Through        the follow-up there were no amputations and there was objective as well as subjective improvement of some        studied variables.        Conclusion: So far and with three included patients, the        process of administration of the AC133+ cells has shown        security and lack of complication, although we have to be        cautious on correlating cell therapy with clinical improvement.        With the inclusion of new patients and their mid        term follow-up we shall clarify the clinical effect of the        AC133+ cells</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Guijo, F. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Porras, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barros, M. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano, F. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>del Cañizo, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La insuficiencia arterial crónica de las extremidades        inferiores es una enfermedad extremadamente        incapacitante y que afecta un 3,5% de los varones mayores        de 60 años. En el momento actual, la terapia celular        es una alternativa de reciente aplicación que presenta        grandes perspectivas en el tratamiento de las isquemias        periféricas. El objetivo del presente estudio fue analizar la        seguridad y eficacia de las células AC133+ autólogas en        promover la revascularización de MMII en pacientes con        isquemia crítica de las EEII.        Material y Métodos: Se han incluido 3 pacientes con isquemia        crítica de las extremidades inferiores que fueron        sometidos a movilización de células hematopoyéticas desde        la médula osea a la sangre periferica (SP) a través del        G-CSF. Posteriormente, los progenitores endoteliales autólogos        AC133+, extraídos y seleccionados desde SP mediante        el sistema CliniMACS® (Miltenyi Biotec), fueron inyectados        intramuscularmente. Se hizo un seguimiento de        los pacientes durante 6 meses según el protocolo del estudio,        valorándose variables clínicas, funcionales, hemodinámicas,        anatómicas y de calidad de vida. Resultados: El proceso de movilización, recolección y infusión        de los progenitores endoteliales fue bien tolerado.        A lo largo del seguimiento no se ha producido ninguna        amputación y hubo mejoría objetiva y subjetiva de algunas        de las variables estudiadas.        Conclusión: Hasta el momento y con tres enfermos incluidos        en el estudio el proceso de administración de las células        AC133+ se ha mostrado seguro y sin complicaciones,        entretanto hemos de ser prudentes en correlacionar la terapia        celular y mejoría clínica. Con la inclusión de nuevos        pacientes y su seguimiento a medio plazo seguramente se        nos aclarará el efecto clínico de las células AC133+</dc:description>
<dc:source>MAPFRE med;18(3): 180-189, jul.-sept. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056980</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Angiogénesis terapéutica en pacientes con isquemia crítica crónica de las extremidades inferiores. Estudio fase II mediante inyección de células AC133+ obtenidas de sangre periférica movilizadas con G-CSF. Seguimiento de tres primeros casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7678^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38327^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29897^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55362^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36500^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
