<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154695</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Customer equity management in a professional player&#146;s agency: how much is worth my current player&#146;s base?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Traditionally, basketball players&#146; agents and players&#146; agents companies in general take decisions about their represented players based on reports, statistics or even premonitions. The future and potential economic revenues that are obtained from the players are more a desire than a variable to take decisions. A methodology to assess and cluster players from a basketball player agent is provided in this paper. Particularly, when, how much and how to invest in basketball players&#146; portfolios according to their current and potential value and economic revenues. Data were obtained from one of the most important international basketball players&#146; agents firm. They represent mainly players and coaches from all around the world, mainly the European and American Professional Championships (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martin Ruiz, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rondán Cataluña, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cepeda Carrión, Gabriel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Tradicionalmente, las agencias de deportistas profesionales y las de baloncesto en particular, toman decisiones sobre sus representados basándose en informes, estadísticas, e incluso corazonadas. Los potenciales ingresos futuros que se obtienen de los jugadores son más un deseo que una variable para tomar decisiones. Presentamos en este articulo una metodología para valorar y segmentar jugadores de una agencia de jugadores de baloncesto profesionales. Concretamente, tratamos de responder a las preguntas de cuándo, cuánto y cómo invertir en la cartera de jugadores profesionales atendiendo a su valor económico actual y a sus potenciales ingresos económicos futuros. Los datos fueron obtenidos de una de las más importantes agencia de jugadores de baloncesto a nivel internacional. Esta empresa representa principalmente a jugadores y entrenadores de todo el mundo, fundamentalmente de ligas profesionales europeas y norteamericanas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;25(supl.1): 11-14, 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154695</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gestión de clientes en una agencia de deportistas profesionales: ¿Cuánto vale tu cartera de clientes?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11796^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10554^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11796^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
