<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112168</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interactions between antihypertensive drugs and food</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: A drug interaction is defined as any alteration, pharmacokinetics and/or pharmacodynamics, produced by different substances, other drug treatments, dietary factors and habits such as drinking and smoking. These interactions can affect the antihypertensive drugs, altering their therapeutic efficacy and causing toxic effects. The aim of this study was to conduct a review of available data about interactions between antihypertensive agents and food. Methods: The purpose of this review was to report an update of main findings with respect to the interactions between food and antihypertensive drugs by way of a search conducted in PubMed, which yielded a total of 236 articles initially. Results: After excluding different articles, which were not focusing on the specific objective, the main results refer to interactions between antihypertensive drugs and food (in general) as well as between antihypertensive agents and grapefruit juice. Discussion: Food may affect the bioavailability of antihypertensive drugs and this should be carefully considered. Advising patients to remove the grapefruit juice from their diet when treatment with these drugs seems to be the best recommendation. Given these interactions and the associated potential adverse effects the anamnesis must include detailed information about the specific eating habits of the patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jáuregui-Lobera, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jáuregui-Garrido, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: la interacción de medicamentos se define como cualquier alteración, farmacocinética y/o farmacodinámica, producida por diferentes sustancias, otros tratamientos, factores dietéticos y hábitos como beber y fumar. Estas interacciones pueden afectar a los fármacos antihipertensivos, alterando su eficacia terapéutica y causando efectos tóxicos. El objetivo de este estudio fue realizar una revisión de los datos disponibles acerca de las interacciones entre los fármacos antihipertensivos y los alimentos. Métodos: El objetivo de esta revisión fue proporcionar una puesta al día sobre los principales resultados con respecto a las interacciones entre alimentos y fármacos antihipertensivos mediante una búsqueda realizada en PubMed, que dio lugar inicialmente a un total de 236 artículos. Resultados: Tras la exclusión de diferentes artículos que no estaban centrados en el objetivo específico, los resultados principales se refieren a las interacciones entre los fármacos antiarrítmicos y alimentos en general y entre dichos fármacos y el zumo de pomelo. Discusión: Los alimentos pueden afectar a la biodisponibilidad de los fármacos antihipertensivos y ello debe ser considerado cuidadosamente. Advertir a los pacientes que supriman el zumo de pomelo en su dieta cuando están en tratamiento con estos fármacos parece la mejor recomendación. Dadas estas interacciones y sus potenciales efectos adversos, la anamnesis debe incluir información detallada sobre los hábitos alimentarios de los pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;27(6): 1866-1875, nov.-dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112168</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Interacciones entre fármacos antihipertensivos y alimentos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32247</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37115^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51396</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
