<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155094</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of spanish Master university related college of sport science</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this study is to provide an overview of the state of the Spanish Masters related to sports science, getting to know them in depth to establish quality markers, and allowing to quickly obtain simple and an overall assessment of each. The objectives of this study are: a) analyze the Academic Structure of Spanish university official Master related sports science; b) analyze the properties Teachers Teaching their teaching; c) to analyze the type of evaluation of the subjects that compose it. To do this, forty-four Masters located by the National Agency for Quality Assessment and Accreditation (ANECA), through its official web pages were studied. In matters involving faculty, database Theses (Theseus) was also used. The results given the study indicate that: a) all studied the masters of subject and general management of a year-long classroom study with majority the afternoon or morning / afternoon, develop throughout the week, and the main measure of access is the transcript; b)Most master&#146;s degrees analyzed, have no goals, nor powers, nor defined career paths, or offer internships; c) its average price is &#128; 5151, with 34 places available , and adjusted service stations in their claims; d) The number average teacher thesis is two, with a majority of men in the teaching teams; e) as to the characteristics of the subjects are usually not reflected in their teaching guides. In conclusion it can be stated that these issues need to be adjusted to provide a higher quality service (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villarejo, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Angulo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Coll, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La finalidad del presente estudio es aportar una visión global del estado de los Másteres españoles relacionados con las ciencias del deporte, conseguir conocerlos en profundidad, para poder establecer marcadores de calidad, que permita obtener de forma rápida y sencilla una valoración general de cada uno de ellos. Los objetivos del presente estudio son: a) analizar la Estructura Académica de los Másteres oficiales universitarios españoles relacionados con las ciencias del deporte; b) analizar las Características del Profesorado que imparte su docencia; y c) analizar el Tipo de Evaluación de las asignaturas que lo componen. Para ello, se estudiaron cuarenta y cuatro Másteres localizados en la Agencia Nacional de Evaluación de la Calidad y Acreditación (ANECA), a través de sus páginas webs oficiales. En cuestiones relacionadas con el profesorado, se utilizó también la base de datos de Tesis Doctorales (TESEO). Los resultados que arroja el estudio señalan que: a) la totalidad de los másteres estudiados son de temática general y gestión, de un año de duración, presenciales, con horario mayoritario de tarde, o mañana/tarde, se desarrollan a lo largo de la semana, y el criterio principal de acceso es el expediente académico; b) la mayoría de los másteres universitarios analizados, no presentan objetivos, ni competencias, ni definen salidas profesionales, ni ofrecen prácticas externas; c) su precio medio es de 5151&#128;, con 34 plazas ofertadas, y ajustados al EESS en cuanto a sus créditos; d) El número de tesis medio por profesor es de dos, con mayoría de hombres en los equipos docentes; y e) en cuanto a las características de las asignaturas, no suelen ser reflejadas en sus guías docentes. Como conclusión se puede señalar que es necesario ajustar estos aspectos para ofrecer un servicio de mayor calidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;16(2): 125-136, 2016. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155094</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de los Másteres universitarios españoles relacionados con las ciencias del deporte</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4568^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13421^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
