<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94572</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Retinol, &amp;#946;-carotene, &amp;#945;-tocopherol and vitamin D status in Europeanadolescents; regional differences an variability: A review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Currently, blood levels to define vitamin deficiency or optimal status in adolescents are extrapolated from adults. This may be not adequate as vitamin requirements during adolescence depend on the process of sexual maturation, rapid increasing height and weight, among other factors. In order to establish the state of the art, Medline database (www.ncvi.nlm.nih.gov) was searched for studies published in Europe between 1981 and 2010related to liposoluble vitamin status in adolescents. A comparison of the vitamin status published in there viewed articles was difficult due to the lack of studies, lack of consensus on cut-off levels indicating deficiency and optimal vitamin levels and the different age-ranges used. In spite of that, deficiency prevalence varied for vitamin D (13-72%), vitamin A (3%), E (25%) and &amp;#946;-carotene (14-19%). Additional factors were considered as possible determinants. We conclude that it is necessary to establish a consensus on acceptable ranges and cut-offs of these vitamins during adolescence. Representative data are still missing; therefore, there is a high need to get deeper into the investigation on liposoluble vitamins in this population group (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valtueña, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Gross, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Breidenassel, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Folle, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la actualidad, los diferentes valores sanguíneos que definen un estado óptimo o deficiente de vitaminas liposolubles en los adolescentes son extrapolados de los adultos. Sin embargo, podría no ser lo adecuado debido a que los requerimientos vitamínicos de los adolescentes están marcados por el proceso de maduración sexual y crecimiento entre otros factores. Para establecer el punto de partida, la base de datos Medline (www.ncvi.nlm.nih.gov) ha sido el medio utilizado para la búsqueda de los estudios publicados sobre el estado en vitaminas liposolubles en adolescentes europeos entre los años 1981 y 2010. Compararlos diferentes resultados obtenidos en los diferentes estudios fue difícil debido a la carencia de estudios, a la falta de consenso en los puntos de corte que indican deficiencia y estado óptimo y a los diferentes rangos de edad utilizados. A pesar de esto, en función de los estudios, se observa una variabilidad en la prevalencia de deficiencia de vitamina D (13-72%), vitamina A (3%), E (25%) y &amp;#946;-caroteno (14-19%). Otros factores adicionales fueron considerados como posibles determinantes del estado vitamínico. Se identifica la necesidad de establecer un consenso sobre los rangos aceptables y puntos de corte de estas vitaminas para este grupo de población y profundizar en la investigación de las vitaminas liposolubles en el periodo de la adolescencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;26(2): 280-288, mar.-abr. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94572</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36123^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32985^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15208^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15202^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16539^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
