<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108095</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5187</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Update on primary focal hiperhidrosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Primary focal hyperhidrosis (PFH) is an idiopathic pathology that affects 2.8% of the population and causes strong impact on social life, and daily activities of patients with the disease. When you suspect that a patient may suffer primary focal hyperhidrosis must perform a carefully history and physicalexamination to exclude secondary causes of hyperhidrosis. Afterwards the affected area is delimited by the Minor test and we can evaluate the effects of the disease in the patient&#146;s quality of life through a variety of test. There are many effective treatments for PFH: topical treatments, iontophoresis, botulinum toxin injection, microwave, systemic treatments and surgical treatments. Each of these treatments has different characteristics, knowledge of these features will allow us to indicate to each patient the best treatment based on the severity, location and psychological impact of PFH and get a satisfactory outcome for both the patient and the physician (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Fernández, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Oliva, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hiperhidrosis focal primaria (HFP) es una patología de origen idiopático que afecta a un 2,8% de la población y que origina un fuerte impacto en la vida social, laboral y personal de los individuos que la padecen. Cuando sospechamos que un paciente puede presentar una HFP debemos realizar una anamnesis y exploración física minuciosas para descartar causas secundarias de hiperhidrosis. Posteriormente delimitaremos el área afectada mediante el test de Minor y podemos valorar la afectación que produce la enfermedad en la calidad de vida del paciente a través de distintos test. Existen múltiples tratamiento eficaces para la HFP: tratamientos tópicos, iontoforesis, infiltración de toxina botulínica, microondas, tratamientos sisté-micos y tratamientos quirúrgicos. Cada uno de estos tratamientos tiene características distintas, el conocimiento de estas características nos permitirá pautar a cada paciente el tratamiento más indicado en función de la severidad, localización y repercusión psicológica de la HFP y así obtener un resultado satisfactorio tanto para el paciente como para el médico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. cután. ibero-lat-am;40(6): 173-180, nov.-dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108095</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actualización en hiperhidrosis focal  primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7126^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1930^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9060^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28148^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
