<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043755</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Isolation of group a Beta-hemolytic Streptococcusin children with perianal dermatitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Perianal dermatitis due to group A beta-hemolytic streptococcus is a rare diagnosis in pediatrics. Clinical manifestations include erythema, edema, and perianal pruritus associated with vulvovaginitis or balanitis, painful defecation, constipation, anal fissures, purulent discharge, and/or rectal bleeding.                 Material and methods: A descriptive, observational, prospective study was conducted between May, 2004 and April, 2005. In children presenting to the emergency room with erythema, edema, and perianal pruritus, a rapid streptococcal antigen test and bacterial cultures of their perianal secretions were obtained. Patients with a positive result in the rapid test were treated with oral phenoxymethylpenicillin (40-50 mg/kg/day) for 10 days, after which clinical and bacteriological evaluations were conducted.                 Results: Of the 24 patients presenting with erythema, edema, and perianal pruritus, 19 patients (12 boys and 7 girls), aged between 6 months and 4 years (median age: 30 months), tested positive for group A beta-hemolytic streptococcus. Nine patients also presented with constipation, 5 with anal fissures, 4 with rectal bleeding, 2 with vulvovaginitis, and 1 with streptococcal pharyngoamygdalitis. Outcome was favorable in 85 % of the patients, and perianal isolation of group A beta-hemolytic streptococcus was negative after treatment in 95 %.                 Conclusions: In patients presenting with erythema, edema, and perianal pruritus, perianal streptococcal dermatitis should be ruled out. The rapid test for streptococcal antigen detection is a quick and reliable method for this diagnosis. The antibiotic of choice is oral penicillin</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Echeverría Fernández, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Sánchez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Míguez Navarro, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez López, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Menchero Oliva, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marañón Pardillo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La dermatitis perianal causada por estreptococo betahemolítico del grupo A (SBHGA) es un diagnóstico poco frecuente en pediatría. Clínicamente cursa con eritema, edema y prurito perianal, y puede asociar vulvovaginitis o balanitis, dolor a la defecación, estreñimiento, fisuras perianales, secreción purulenta y/o rectorragia.                 Material y método: Estudio descriptivo, observacional y prospectivo realizado entre los meses de mayo de 2004 y abril de 2005. En los niños que acudieron a urgencias por eritema, edema y/o prurito perianal se realizó una prueba rápida de detección de antígeno estreptocócico y un cultivo bacteriano de secreciones perianales. Aquellos casos con determinación rápida positiva fueron tratados con fenoximetilpenicilina oral (40-50 mg/kg/día) durante 10 días, y al finalizar el tratamiento se efectuó un control clínico y bacteriológico del paciente.                 Resultados: De los 24 casos analizados que acudieron por eritema, edema y/o prurito perianal, un total de 19 pacientes (12 niños y 7 niñas) con edades comprendidas entre los 6 meses y los 4 años (media: 30 meses) presentaron determinación positiva para SBHGA. Un total de 9 casos asociaban estreñimiento, cinco fisuras perianales, cuatro rectorragia, dos vulvovaginitis y uno faringoamigdalitis estreptocócica. El 85 % de los pacientes evolucionaron favorablemente, y tras el tratamiento se negativizó el aislamiento perianal de SBHGA en el 90 % de los casos.                 Conclusiones: En aquellos pacientes que presenten eritema, edema y/o prurito perianal se ha de descartar dermatitis perianal estreptocócica. La prueba rápida de detección de antígeno estreptocócico es un método rápido y fiable para su diagnóstico. El tratamiento antibiótico de elección es la penicilina oral</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);64(2): 153-157, feb. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043755</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aislamiento de estreptococo betahemolítico del grupo A en niños con dermatitis perianal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13677^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13684^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11977^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1009^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3892^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
