<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161721</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Placental abscess and bacteraemia in a pregnant woman</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bacteraemia during pregnancy is associated with increased maternal and foetal morbidity and mortality. Our goal was to conduct a literature review of this infection apropos of a case of bacteraemia caused by Streptococcus anginosus in the second trimester with a finding of placental abscess in the complementary study. Due to the physiological changes that take place during pregnancy, pregnant women have an increased susceptibility to infections. The symptomatology of bacteraemia is nonspecific in this patient group and the infection typically manifests with fever and constitutional symptoms. The therapeutic approach consists of early imitation of intravenous antibiotics based on third-generation cephalosporins for at least two weeks. Early management is important to minimize the risks to mother and foetus (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Albi González, MV</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo Trechera, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albareda Landivar, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Rubio, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Adiego Burgos, MB</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La bacteriemia durante la gestación es una condición que se asocia a un incremento de la morbimortalidad maternofetal. Nuestro objetivo es realizar una revisión bibliográfica a propósito de un caso de bacteriemia en una gestante de segundo trimestre por Streptococcus anginosus, con hallazgo en el estudio complementario de un absceso placentario. La gestación está asociada con aumento de susceptibilidad a infecciones debido a los cambios fisiológicos que acontecen durante la misma. La sintomatología de la bacteriemia es inespecífica en este grupo de pacientes, manifestándose de forma típica con fiebre y síntomas constitucionales. El tratamiento se basa en una temprana instauración de antibioterapia intravenosa con cefalosporinas de tercera generación durante al menos 2 semanas. Un manejo temprano es fundamental para minimizar los riesgos tantos maternos como fetales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);44(2): 86-88, abr.-jun. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161721</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Absceso placentario y bacteriemia en gestante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11691^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d41^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23587^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36617^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13677^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11354^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
