<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83259</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Socio-economic inequalities in children's mental health in Catalonia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To analyse socio-economic and health status factors associated with poor mental health in a representative sample of children 4 to 14 years old in Catalonia. Methods: The data comes from a subsample of the Catalan Health Interview Survey 2006 (CHIS) (n=1821). Proxy-respondents, mainly mothers, answered the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ). The SDQ dimension scores and the Total difficulties score were analysed by socio-demographics and health status factors. Multivariate linear regression models were fitted to analyse the influence of socio-economic and health status factors on mental health. Results: In general, being in a disadvantaged family, single-parent families, a family whose mother had lower level of education, and those children reporting physical health problems, have been factors associated with worse child mental health in most of SDQ dimension scores. Factors associated with Total difficulties were, being a girl (beta coefficient: &amp;#8722;1.6), from disadvantaged social classes (group IV&#150;V: 1.6), at lower level of maternal education (mother's educational primary level or less: 1.2), being in a single-parent family (1.5), and reporting health problems (3 or more health problems: 3.9). Conclusions: Children from disadvantaged families, and single-parent families are at higher risk of worse mental health than their counterparts in the advantaged groups. The study contributes to collecting information for monitoring and approaching mental health in children (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Aguilà, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mompart Penina, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brugulat Guiteras, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rajmil, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina Bustos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Sanz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Analizar los factores socioeconómicos y de salud asociados a la salud mental infantil en una muestra representativa de población de 4&#150;14 años de edad de Cataluña. Métodos: Los datos provienen de la submuestra infantil de la Encuesta de Salud de Cataluña 2006 (n=1.821). La madre, el padre o la persona encargada del menor respondió el cuestionario de salud mental infantil Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ). Se analizaron las puntuaciones de cada dimensión del SDQ y las dificultades totales según los factores socioeconómicos y de salud del niño/a. Se ajustaron modelos de regresión lineal múltiple. Resultados: En general, pertenecer a una familia de clase social desfavorecida, monoparental, con nivel de estudios de la madre menor que universitario y declarar problemas de salud fueron los factores asociados a una peor salud mental infantil en la mayoría de las dimensiones del SDQ. Los factores asociados a las dificultades totales fueron ser chica (coeficiente &amp;#946;: &amp;#8722;1,6), pertenecer a las clases sociales menos favorecidas (grupo IV-V: 1,6), con menor nivel de estudios materno (nivel de estudios primario o menos: 1,2), pertenecer a una familia monoparental (1,5) y declarar más problemas de salud (3 o más problemas: 3,9). Conclusiones: Los niños y las niñas de familias con nivel socioeconómico menos favorecido y de familias monoparentales se encuentran a riesgo de presentar peor salud mental. El estudio aporta información útil para la monitorización y el abordaje de los problemas de salud mental infantil (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);73(5): 233-240, nov. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83259</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desigualdades sociales en la salud mental infantil en Cataluña</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34658</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56095^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33118^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201011</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
