<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84844</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION: the surgery of the inguinal hernia is characterized by its high frecuency and small morbidity and mortality. When performed as a day-case procedure it should bring the benefits of the short stay surgery without further complications. It will produce a smaller disturbance to the social and affective situation of the children by minimally altering their daily life and relationship. This work aims to analyse our experience in this field. PATIENTS AND METHODS: from January1995 to December 2000 we have operated on 85pediatric patients with inguinal hernia as a day case procedure. The usual performed technique has been herniotomy. All entered the perioperatory circuit of our Unit of Short Stay Surgery. RESULTS: only 3 patients required admission during 24 hours because of nausea and vomiting. None required admission after being discharged. The phone survey, carried out at 24hours after hospital discharge, yielded a satisfactory state at home in all cases. The relapse rate has been 0 in the long term. DISCUSSION: this study has shown good results not only by the few complications registered but also regarding the satisfactory assessment stated by the family in the quality survey (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cuadra Cestafe, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Errasti Alustiza, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sardón Ramos, J. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sierra Esteban, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muriel López, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campo Cimarras, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">INTRODUCCIÓN: La cirugía de la herniainguinal tiene una alta incidencia y escasa morbimortalidad. Su realización de forma ambulatoria debería aportar los beneficios de la cirugía sin ingreso, sin añadir otras nuevas complicaciones. Así, en la edad infantil, se produce un menor trastorno en la situación socio-afectiva del niño, al alterar mínimamente su vida cotidiana y la de su entorno. El objetivo de este trabajo es analizar nuestra experiencia en este campo. PACIENTES Y MÉTODOS: desde Enero de1995 a Diciembre de 2000 hemos intervenido 85pacientes en edad pediátrica por hernia inguinal de forma ambulatoria. La técnica habitual realizada fue la herniotomía. Todos entraron en el circuito perioperatorio de nuestra Unidad de Cirugía sin Ingreso. RESULTADOS: sólo 3 pacientes precisaron ingreso 24 horas, siendo el motivo las nauseas ovómitos. Ninguno de los pacientes precisó reingreso tras abandonar el centro. La encuesta telefónica, realizada a las 24 horas de alta, recoge un resultado de estado satisfactorio en el domicilio en todos los casos. En el seguimiento a largo plazo la tasa de recidiva es 0.DISCUSIÓN: el estudio arroja un buen resultado, tanto por las mínimas complicaciones cosechadas, como por la valoración satisfactoria por parte de la familia en la encuesta de calidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;8(1): 18-21, ene.-mar. 2003. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84844</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cirugía ambulatoria de la hernia inguinal en edad pediátrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6711^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
