<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-27932</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bibliometric analysis of the reviews of Clinical Psychology published in Spanish</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This work is a bibliometric analysis of the reviews of Clinical Psychology published in Spanish in 2001 and 2002. The reviews are analyzed according to the number of articles that have been published, the nationalities of the signer authors, the index of authorship and the contents. There are differences in terms of their diversity and the number of countries that had collaborated. As, both the Revista Internacional de Psicología Clínica y de la Salud / International Journal of Clinical and Health Psychology and the Revista Argentina de Clínica Psicológica are the ones that have the greatest amount of authors whose nationalities are different from those of the original country of the review; there are a predominance of the articles shared by several authors; the contents of papers are especially of the areas Personality, Assessment and Psychological Treatment, Health Psychology and «Inter-área». Some final reflections are achieved about found results (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Buela-Casal, Gualberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agudelo, Diana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bretón-López, Juana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se realiza un análisis bibliométrico de las revistas de Psicología Clínica editadas en castellano en los años 2001 y 2002. Se analizan el número de artículos publicados, la nacionalidad de los autores, el índice de autoría y los contenidos de los trabajos. Los resultados muestran diferencias en la diversidad y número de países colaboradores, así, son la Revista Internacional de Psicología Clínica y de la Salud / International Journal of Clinical and Health Psychology y la Revista Argentina de Clínica Psicológica las que tienen mayor representación de autores de un país diferente al de origen de la revista. Predominan los artículos compartidos por varios autores, frente a los individuales; la mayoría de los artículos se clasifican dentro de las áreas de Personalidad, Evaluación y Tratamiento Psicológico, Psicología de la Salud e "Inter-área". Se realizan algunas reflexiones finales sobre las implicaciones y utilidades de los resultados encontrados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);15(4): 507-516, nov. 2003. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-27932</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis bibliométrico de las revistas de Psicologia Clínica editadas en castellano</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10742^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12023^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51780^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12021^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12022^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51780^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200311</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
