<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132493</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Short- and Long-term Prognosis of Previous and New-onset Atrial Fibrillation in ST-segment Elevation Acute Myocardial Infarction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives The impact of atrial fibrillation on the prognosis of myocardial infarction is still the subject of debate. We analyzed the influence of previous and new-onset atrial fibrillation on in-hospital and long-term prognosis in patients with acute myocardial infarction. Methods Prospective study of 4284 patients with ST-segment elevation acute myocardial infarction. We studied all-cause in-hospital and long-term mortality (median, 7.2 years) using adjusted models. Results In total, 3.2% of patients had previous atrial fibrillation and 9.8% had new-onset atrial fibrillation. In general, both groups of patients had a high baseline risk profile and an increased likelihood of in-hospital complications. The crude in-hospital mortality rate was higher in patients with previous atrial fibrillation than in those with new-onset atrial fibrillation (22% vs 12%; P &lt; .001; 30% vs 10%; P &lt; .001). The long-term mortality rate was 11.11/100 patient-years in patients with previous atrial fibrillation and 5.35/100 patient years in those with new-onset atrial fibrillation (both groups, P &lt; .001). New-onset fibrillation alone (odds ratio = 1.55; 95% confidence interval, 1.08-2.22) was an independent predictor of in-hospital mortality. Previous atrial fibrillation (hazard ratio = 1.24; 95% confidence interval, 0.94-1.64) and new-onset atrial fibrillation (hazard ratio = 0.98; 95% confidence interval, 0.80-1.21) were not independent predictors of long-term mortality. Conclusions New-onset atrial fibrillation during hospitalization is an independent risk factor for in-hospital mortality in acute myocardial infarction (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Galcerá-Tomás, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escudero-García, Germán</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Pastor, Ángela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Fernández, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Consuegra-Sánchez, Luciano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jaulent-Huertas, Leticia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Melgarejo-Moreno, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente-Gilabert, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos El impacto de la fibrilación auricular en el pronóstico del infarto de miocardio sigue siendo controvertido. Se analizó la importancia pronóstica de la fibrilación auricular previa y de nueva aparición (de novo) en el hospital y a largo plazo en el infarto agudo de miocardio. Métodos Estudio prospectivo de 4.284 pacientes con infarto agudo de miocardio con elevación del segmento ST. Se estudió la mortalidad por todas las causas hospitalaria y a largo plazo (mediana, 7,2 años) mediante modelos ajustados. Resultados El 3,2% de los pacientes tenían fibrilación auricular previa y el 9,8%, de novo. En general ambos grupos de pacientes tenían un perfil de mayor riesgo basal y mayor probabilidad de complicaciones intrahospitalarias. La mortalidad bruta hospitalaria fue mayor entre los pacientes con fibrilación auricular previa que en la de novo (el 22 frente al 12%; p &lt; 0,001; 30 frente al 10%; p &lt; 0,001). La densidad de incidencia de mortalidad a largo plazo fue de 11,11/100 pacientes-año en la fibrilación auricular previa y 5,35/100 pacientes-año en la de novo (ambos grupos, p &lt; 0,001). Únicamente la fibrilación auricular de novo (odds ratio = 1,55; intervalo de confianza del 95%, 1,08-2,22) fue predictor independiente de mortalidad hospitalaria. La fibrilación auricular previa (hazard ratio = 1,24; intervalo de confianza del 95%, 0,94-1,64) y la de novo (hazard ratio = 0,98; intervalo de confianza del 95%, 0,80-1,21) no resultaron predictores independientes de mortalidad a largo plazo. Conclusiones La fibrilación auricular de novo durante el ingreso es un factor independiente de mortalidad hospitalaria en el infarto agudo de miocardio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;68(1): 31-38, ene. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132493</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pronóstico a corto y largo plazo de la fibrilación auricular previa y de novo en pacientes con infarto agudo de miocardio con elevación del segmento ST</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
