<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129575</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intervention in elderly patients with multiple morbidities and multiple medications: results of the prescription and the quality of life</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To evaluate the effect of an intervention using STOPP/START criteria and the Garfinkel algorithm on prescription and the health-related quality of life (HRQoL) in elderly patients with multimorbidity and prescribed multiple medications. Material and method. A before-after intervention study on 381 patients over 67 years old and prescribed multiple medications by 71 Primary Care doctors. Intervention: The doctors were trained in the STOPP / START criteria and Garfinkel algorithm. Each doctor then reviewed all the drugs of their selected patients and then made appointments with them for an initial medical consultation and clinical assessment. Treatment was modified according to the criteria and the HRQoL measured using the SF-12 questionnaire. Two months later, in a second medical consultation, a new clinical assessment was made and the HRQoL was measured. The dimensions of the HRQoL between the first and the second consultation were compared using the paired Student-t test. Results. The intervention involved the removal of a mean of 1.5 drugs per patient. The dose was modified in 4% of drugs, and 8.9% of patients were prescribed a new drug. Non-Steroidal Anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAID), psychoactive drugs and proton pump inhibitors were the most modified. Social Function and Physical Component Summary of the HRQOL improved significantly (P &lt; .05) after intervention. Conclusion. The intervention using the Garfinkel algorithm and STOPP -START criteria improved HRQoL and reduced the number of prescribed drugs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Naveiro-Rilo, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flores-Zurutuza, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diez-Juárez, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alberte-Pérez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina-Mazo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Evaluar el efecto de una intervención a través de los criterios de STOPP/START y el algoritmo de Garfinkel sobre la prescripción y la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud (CVRS) en ancianos polimedicados con multimorbilidad. Material y método. Estudio de intervención antes-después en 381 pacientes mayores de 67 años polimedicados de 71 médicos de atención primaria. Intervención: se formó a los médicos en los criterios de STOPP/START y en el algoritmo de Garfinkel. Cada médico revisó todos los medicamentos de sus enfermos seleccionados, posteriormente los citó a una primera consulta para realizarles una valoración clínica, modificarles el tratamiento según los criterios y medirles la CVRS mediante el cuestionario Short-Form Health Survey-V2 (SF-12). A los 2 meses, en una segunda consulta, se les realizó una nueva valoración clínica y se midió la CVRS. Las dimensiones de la CVRS entre la primera y la segunda consulta fueron comparadas con la «t» de Student pareada. Resultados. La intervención supuso la retirada de 1,5 fármacos de promedio por enfermo. Se modificó la dosis en el 4% de fármacos; al 8,9% de los pacientes se les prescribió un fármaco nuevo. Los AINE, fármacos psicoactivos e inhibidores de la bomba de protones fueron los más modificados. Mejoraron significativamente (p &lt; 0,05) la función social y el componente sumario físico de la CVRS tras la intervención. Conclusión. La intervención mediante el algoritmo de Garfinkel y los criterios de STOPP/START conllevó una mejora de la CVRS y redujo el número de fármacos prescritos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;29(5): 256-262, sept.-oct. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129575</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervención en ancianos con multimorbilidad y polimedicados: resultados en la prescripción y en la calidad de vida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28940</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
