<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140364</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The influence of healthy lifestyle habits on weight status in school aged children and adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Overweight and obesity has high prevalence in children and adolescents in Spain. Objective: To determine the degree of influence of four modifiable factors (dietary habits, physical activity, sedentary and sleep) jointly on the weight status of a group of school children and adolescents in Madrid. Methods: 189 schoolchildren aged 6 to 16 years, who underwent an anthropometric study. To exercise the IPAQ questionnaire was used, establishing a minimum of one hour of exercise a day, as a recommendation, and two hours per day in case of sedentary, which took into account the hours of computer, consoles and TV. Sleep quality was assessed by collecting sleeping hours weekdays and weekend nap. Stating that school children should sleep 10 hours a day. The KIDMED Index was used for the diet quality, the score can be accessed from 0-12 and classified into 3 categories, it was regrouped for statistical measure. The first two results (0-7) as 'Bad adherence' and &amp;#8805; 8 value as 'Good adherence'. Results: 27.6% of students had excess weight. Conclusion: No significant differences were reported analyzing the four factors studied versus weight status among those who keep recommendations and excess weight, either individually or multifactor analysis was observed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Micó, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Megías, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bodega, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garicano, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Mauro, Ismael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grande, Graciela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García de Angulo, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fajardo, Diana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El sobrepeso y la obesidad alcanzan una alta prevalencia entre niños y adolescentes en España. Objetivo: Conocer el grado de influencia de cuatro factores modificables (hábitos alimentarios, práctica de actividad física, sedentarismo y horas de sueño) de forma conjunta sobre el estado ponderal de un colectivo de niños en edad escolar y adolescentes de Madrid. Metodología: 189 escolares, de 6 a 16 años, a los que se les realizó un estudio antropométrico. Para el ejercicio físico se usó el cuestionario IPAQ modificado, estableciéndose un mínimo de una hora de ejercicio al día, como recomendación, y de dos horas al día en el caso del sedentarismo, donde se tuvieron en cuenta las horas de ordenador, consolas y televisión. La calidad del sueño se valoró recogiendo las horas de sueño entre semana, siesta y fin de semana. Estableciendo que los niños en edad escolar deben dormir 10 horas al día. Para la dieta, se utilizó el Índice KidMed, la puntuación que se puede alcanzar de 0 a 12 y se clasifica en 3 categorías, se reagrupo para nuestra medida estadística. Los dos primeros resultados (0-7) como 'no cumple la adherencia' y &amp;#8805; 8 valor como 'si cumple la adherencia'. Resultados: El 27,6% de los estudiantes tenían exceso ponderal. Conclusión: No se observaron diferencias significativas al analizar los cuatro factores estudiados frente al estado ponderal, entre los aquellos que cumplían o no cumplían las recomendaciones y el exceso de peso, ni de forma individual ni multifactorialmente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(5): 1996-2005, mayo 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140364</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de hábitos saludables en el estado ponderal de niños y adolescentes en edad escolar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5284^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37653^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55220^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32738^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6278^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
