<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91309</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of postpartum depression and associated sociodemographic and obstetric factors. The hidden side of being a mother</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: to estimate the risk of postpartum depression (PPD)in a population of women in the postnatal period who were seenin an urban health centre of the Palencia health Area, to assessthe utility and ease of use of the Edinburgh Postnatal DepressionScale (EPDS) in the management of women in the postpartumphase, to identify if there is a relationship between thedetected risk of depression and sociodemographic, obstetricand psychosocial risk factors and to identify the knowledge andattitudes of women in the postnatal period regarding PPD.Material and method: descriptive study performed on womenwho attended the first post-partum visit at the midwife&#146;s consultationoffice over the course of one year (april 2007 to april2008). Two questionnaires were used: the Edinburgh PostnatalDepression Scale (EPDS) and a self-elaborated questionnaireon the knowledge and attitudes of women regarding thispathology. Sociodemographic, obstetric and social variableswere also studied.Results: 74 women were studied. The risk of postpartum depressionwas determined to be 18% (n=13). No statistically significantassociations between the different variables and therisk of PPD were found, except for marital status (increasedrisk of testing positive for PPD in the case of single women).86,4% (n=64) of surveyed women had previously heard aboutthe issue and 70,3% (n=52) consider it to be an importanthealth problem.Conclusions: the study coincides with the higher limit of publisheddata, which situate PPD at 10-20%. This highlights theimportance of early detection in our setting. The ease and lackof problems when filling out the questionnaire confirm thatthe EPDS scale is operative and useful as a PPD risk screeningmethod in Primary Care and should be applied to allwomen in the puerperium period (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pascual Tomé, Rosa M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Marín, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maestro González, M. Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: estimar el riesgo de depresión posparto (DPP) enuna población de puérperas atendidas en un centro de salud urbanodel Área de salud de Palencia, valorar la utilidad y facilidadde uso de la Edinburgh Postnatal Depresión Scale (EPDS)en la consulta de atención a la mujer en el postparto, identificarsi existe relación entre el riesgo de depresión detectado yfactores sociodemográficos, obstétricos y de riesgo psicosociale identificar los conocimientos y actitudes ante la DPP de laspuérperas.Material y método: estudio descriptivo realizado sobre las mujeresque acudieron a la primera visita posparto a la consulta dela matrona durante un período de un año (abril de 2007 a abrilde 2008). Se utilizaron dos cuestionarios: la Edimburgh PostnatalDepression Scale (EPDS) y otro de elaboración propiasobre conocimientos y actitudes ante esta patología. También seestudiaron variables sociodemográficas, obstétricas y sociales.Resultados: se estudiaron 74 mujeres. El riesgo de depresiónposparto detectado fue de un 18% (n=13). No se encontraronasociaciones estadísticamente significativas entre las diferentesvariables y el riego de DPP, excepto para el estado civil(un mayor de riesgo de test positivo si se era soltera). Un86,4% (n=64) de las encuestadas había oído hablar previamentesobre el tema y un 70,3% (n=52) lo consideran comoun importante problema de salud.Conclusiones: el estudio coincide con el límite superior delas cifras publicadas, que establecen la DPP en torno al 10-20%. Esto refuerza la importancia de la detección precoz ennuestro entorno. La comodidad y falta de problemas al rellenarel cuestionario confirma que la escala EPDS es operativay útil para utilizar como método de cribado del riesgo de DPPen Atención Primaria y debería ser aplicada a todas las puérperasde forma universal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;12(9): 50-54, nov. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91309</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de depresión pospartoy factores sociodemográficos y obstétricosasociados. La cara oculta de ser madre</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32776^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28162^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12080^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
