<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103406</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The corporal self-perception and BMI like indicators of the nutritional status</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate correlation and conformity between the IMC and PIC in university students who make the pre-professional practices in centers of primary health care in Carmen City, Campeche, Mexico. Design: Quantitative transverse analytical. Emplacement: Sanitary Centers of primary care in Carmen City, Campeche, Mexico. Participants: 227 university students of health sciences who make the pre-professional practices in centers of primary health care in Carmen City, Campeche. Principal measurements: Weight, height, age, sex, selection of anatomical models corresponding to the corporal perceived image (PIC). The information was analyzed using the program SPSS V.20.0, there being calculated the descriptive ones and the measures of correlation and conformity of Spearman and Kendall, respectively. Results: The average of the participant&#146;s age was of19.63 ± 1.68 years with an interval 17 to 25 years. The average for IMC was of 24.52 ± 4.84kg/m2, being of24.12 ± 4.68 kg/m2for women and 26.18 ± 5.20 kg/m2for men. The average value for PIC was of 26.04 ± 4.77kg/m2, being of 25.89 ± 4.96 kg/m2for women and26.68 ± 3.88 kg/m2for men. The correlation and the conformity between the IMC and the PIC turned out to be superior to 0.70, with one p &lt;0.001.Conclusion: Correlation and conformity´s values between PIC and IMC were bigger than brought for other authors. The women show trend to select similar images to his physical status, consistent condition with correlation and the conformity calculated for this kind (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Parra Pérez, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lara Severino, R. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zúñiga Juárez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Orri, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la correlación y la concordancia entre el IMC y la PIC en estudiantes universitarios que realizan sus prácticas pre-profesionales en centros de atención primaria en Ciudad del Carmen, Campeche, México. Diseño: Cuantitativo transversal analítico. Emplazamiento: Centros sanitarios de atención primaria de Ciudad del Carmen, Campeche, México. Participantes: 227 estudiantes universitarios de Ciencias de la salud en prácticas pre-profesionales en centros de atención primaria en Ciudad del Carmen, Campeche. Mediciones principales: Peso, talla, edad, sexo, selección de modelos anatómicos correspondiente a la imagen corporal percibida (PIC). Los datos se analizaron utilizando el programa SPSS V.20.0, calculándoselos descriptivos y las medidas de correlación y concordancia de Spearman y Kendall, respectivamente. Resultados: El promedio de edad de los participantes fue de 19.63 ± 1.68 años con un intervalo de 17 a25 años. El IMC medio fue de 24.52 ± 4.84kg/m2,siendo de 24.12 ± 4.68 kg/m2para las mujeres y 26.18± 5.20 kg/m2para los hombres. El valor medio de la PIC fue de 26.04 ± 4.77 kg/m2, siendo de 25.89 ± 4.96kg/m2para las mujeres y 26.68 ± 3.88 kg/m2para los hombres. La correlación y la concordancia entre el IMC y la PIC resultaron superiores a 0.70, con una p &lt;0.001.Conclusión: Los valores de correlación y concordancia entre la PIC y el IMC fueron mayores a lo reportado por otros autores. Las mujeres muestran tendencia a seleccionar imágenes similares a su condición física real, consistente con la correlación y la concordancia calculada para este género (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;32(2): 86-91, mar.-abr. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103406</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La autopercepción corporal y el IMC como indicadores del estado nutricional de estudiantes universitarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
