<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037563</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endometrial polyps. Is there a more conservative approach than transhysteroscopic removal?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJETIVE: To establish whether a more  conservative approach other than the transhysteroscopic removal of endometrial polyps is  possible, taking into account the relative        frequency of atypias and adenocarcinoma on the polyps removed.  FRAMEWORK: hysteroscopic surgery  undertaken in the outpatients surgical unit.  PATIENTS: 149 polypectomies carried out by hysteroscopy in the Outpatient Surgical Unit  (O.S.U.) of Dr. Peset University Hospital in Valencia between 2000 and 2002.  RESULTS: - The relative frequency of non-atypical  hyperplasia on the polyp was 34 %.  - The relative frequency of atypical hyperplasia on  the polyp was 4 %.  - The relative frequency of adenocarcinoma on the polyp was 0.6 %. CONCLUSIONS: Bearing these results in mind  and until the time when other prospective, more  specific, studies can provide more detailed data,  we must continue with our policy of using hysteroscopic surgery under general anaesthetic  to remove all those polyps that we cannot  eliminate by hysteroscopy in the doctor&#146;s surgery,  inasmuch as the potential risk of them becoming  malignant exceeds any risk of surgical  complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pellicer, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viñoles, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alama, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garayoa, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVOS: Establecer si es posible plantear   una actitud más conservadora que la resección        transhisteroscopica del pólipo endometrial valorando la frecuencia relativa de atipias y adenocarcinoma  sobre pólipo. MARCO: Intervenciones de histeroscopia   quirúrgica realizadas en la Unidad de Cirugía Sin  Ingreso (UCSI). PACIENTES: 149 polipectomías realizadas por  histeroscopia quirúrgica en la U.C.S.I. del Hospital  Universitario Dr. Peset de Valencia entre los años  2000 y 2002.  RESULTADOS: - La frecuencia relativa de hiperplasia sin atipias  sobre pólipo ha sido del 34 %.  - La frecuencia relativa de hiperplasia con atipias  sobre pólipo ha sido del 4 %.  - La frecuencia relativa de adenocarcinoma  sobre pólipo ha sido del 0.6 %.        CONCLUSIONES: A la vista de estos resultados  y hasta que otros estudios prospectivos y más  amplios aporten datos más concluyentes, debemos  continuar con nuestra política de extirpar  mediante histeroscopia quirúrgica bajo anetesia  general todos aquellos pólipos que no podamos eliminar por histeroscopia en consultorio, por  cuanto el potencial riesgo de malignización supera  el riesgo de las complicaciones quirúrgicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;10(1): 24-28, mar. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037563</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El pólipo endometrial. ¿Es posible plantear una actitud más conservadora que la resección transhisteroscópica?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4796^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4793^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24738^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4793^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4793^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11564^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4793^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4796^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11564^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
