<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86804</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness of transcranial Doppler ultrasonography for the detection of vasospasm in the anterior</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The anterior cerebral arteries are often affected by vasospasm secondary to subarachnoid haemorrhage. The effectiveness of transcranial Doppler ultrasonography to detect this complication has still not been accurately determined. Aim. To assess the usefulness of transcranial Doppler ultrasonography for diagnosing vasospasm of the anterior cerebral arteries in patients with subarachnoid haemorrhage. Patients and methods. We studied 56 patients between the 4th and 14th days of their subarachnoid haemorrhage; all of them were submitted to a contrast-enhanced neurovascular study and daily monitoring with transcranial Doppler ultrasonography. All the patients had a clinical degree of between 1 and 3 on the World Federation of Neurological Surgeons scale, 46 of them had aneurysms, and bleeding was intense in 20 cases (degree 3-4 on the Fisher scale). Results. The frequency of angiographic vasospasm was 41% in the anterior cerebral arteries. The mean flow velocities in patients with vasospasm were 84.5 cm/s. The maximum peaks of mean blood flow rate were obtained on the tenth day. Sensitivity was 57.9% for flow rates equal to or above 87.5 cm/s, and the predictive positive value was 66.6%. No significant relation was found between the findings of the transcranial Doppler ultrasonography scan, the degree of clinical symptoms and the intensity of bleeding in the computerised axial tomography scan. Conclusions. The overall precision of the test was good, the specificity and predictive negative value were excellent, but sensitivity was low (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Nellas, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Scherle, Claudio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las arterias cerebrales anteriores son ven afectadas con frecuencia por el vasoespasmo secundario a hemorragia subaracnoidea. La eficacia del ultrasonido Doppler transcraneal para detectar esta complicación no se ha determinado con exactitud. Objetivo. Comprobar la utilidad del ultrasonido Doppler transcraneal para diagnosticar el vasoespasmo de las arterias cerebrales anteriores en pacientes con hemorragia subaracnoidea.  Pacientes y métodos. Estudiamos 56 pacientes entre los días 4 y 14 de la hemorragia subaracnoidea, a los cuales se realizó un estudio neurovascular contrastado y monitorización diaria con Doppler transcraneal. Todos los pacientes se encontraban con grado clínico de la escala de la Federación Mundial de Cirujanos Neurológicos entre 1 y 3; 46 tenían aneurismas y en 20 el sangramiento fue intenso (grado 3-4 en la escala de Fisher). Resultados. La frecuencia de vasoespasmo angiográfico fue del 41% en las arterias cerebrales anteriores. Las velocidadesmedias del flujo en los enfermos con vasoespasmo fueron de 84,5 cm/s. Los picos máximos de velocidad de flujo media se obtuvieron en el décimo día. La sensibilidad fue del 57,9% para velocidades de flujo iguales o superiores a 87,5 cm/s, y el valor predictivo positivo fue del 66,6%. No se encontró relación significativa entre el resultado del Doppler transcraneal, el grado clínico y la intensidad del sangramiento en la tomografía axial computarizada. Conclusión. La precisión global de la prueba fue buena, la especificidad y el valor predictivo negativo fueron excelentes; sin embargo, la sensibilidad fue baja (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;50(5): 273-278, mar. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86804</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia del Doppler transcraneal para la detección del vasoespasmo en las arterias cerebrales anteriores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13733^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2573^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34270^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30991^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
