<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156134</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pseudoaneurysm associated with complicated pancreatic pseudocysts</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A pseudoaneurysm associated with a pseudocyst is a serious and unusual complication of chronic pancreatitis. Its treatment is complex due to its elevated mortality and the need for multidisciplinary management. Initial measures consist in locating the hemorrhage through computerized dynamic tomography and arteriography. The treatment of choice is controversial due to the lack of controlled studies. For managing hemorrhages in stable patients, the most accepted initial measure currently is arterial embolization. In the event of failure of the same, hemodynamic instability or the impossibility of drainage of the pseudocyst, surgery is the subsequent therapeutic option(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peño-Muñoz, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barber-Hueso, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cors-Ferrando, Rafa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sempere-García-Argüelles, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luján-Sanchis, Marisol</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durá-Ayet, Ana Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larrey-Ruiz, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El pseudoaneurisma asociado a pseudoquiste es una complicación grave e infrecuente de la pancreatitis crónica. Su tratamiento es complejo por su elevada mortalidad y la necesidad de un manejo multidisciplinar. La medida inicial consiste en la localización de la hemorragia mediante tomografía computarizada dinámica y arteriografía. El tratamiento de elección es controvertido por la ausencia de estudios controlados. Para el manejo de la hemorragia en pacientes estables, la medida terapéutica inicial más aceptada actualmente es la embolización arterial. Ante fracaso de la misma, inestabilidad hemodinámica o imposibilidad de drenaje del pseudoquiste la cirugía es la siguiente opción terapéutica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;108(9): 583-585, sept. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156134</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pseudoaneurisma asociado a pseudoquiste pancreático complicado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10380^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30856^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28918^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6623^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50479^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
