<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127925</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Refusal to medical interventions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Refusal to medical interventions is the not acceptance, voluntary and free, of an indicated medical intervention. What the physician should do in case of refusal? It is understandable that the rejection of a validated medical intervention is difficult to accept by the responsible physician when raises the conflict protection of life versus freedom of choice. Therefore it is important to follow some steps to incorporate the most relevant aspects of the conflict. These steps include: 1) Give complete information to patients, informing on possible alternatives, 2) determine whether the patient can decide (age, competency and level of capacity), 3) to ascertain whether the decision is free, 4) analyze the decision with the patient, 5) to persuade, 6) if the patient kept in the rejection decision, consider conscientious objection, 7) take the decision based on the named criteria, 8) finally, if the rejection is accepted, offer available alternatives (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palacios, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herreros, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pacho, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El rechazo a las actuaciones médicas es la no aceptación, voluntaria y libre, de una intervención médica indicada. ¿Qué debe hacer el médico ante el rechazo? Es comprensible que el rechazo a una actuación validada sea difícil de aceptar por el médico responsable cuando plantea el conflicto protección de la vida versus la libertad de elección. Por ello es importante seguir unos pasos que incorporen los aspectos más relevantes del conflicto. Estos pasos pueden ser: 1) dar información completa al paciente, informando sobre las posibles alternativas, 2) determinar si el paciente puede decidir (edad, capacidad legal y grado de competencia), 3) comprobar si la decisión es libre, 4) analizar la decisión con el paciente, 5) persuadirle, 6) si se mantiene en la decisión de rechazo, considerar la objeción de conciencia, 7) tomar la decisión en base a los criterios nombrados, 8) finalmente, si se acepta el rechazo, ofrecer las alternativas disponibles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;214(7): 389-395, oct. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127925</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rechazo a las actuaciones médicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d16765</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33618^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29106</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33618^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33618^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33618^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29140^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33618^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
