<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163212</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Engagement of nurses in their profession. Qualitative study on engagement</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To identify common issues of nurses with high engagement to enable us to develop the construct as it applies to nursing in more depth. Method: Based on the constructivist paradigm and with a phenomenological approach, a qualitative content analysis was conducted using an inductive approach. Participants were nurses working in direct care in different healthcare areas. The sample size was determined by data saturation and 15 participants were interviewed. Results: The units of meaning were grouped into 11 subcategories, and then into 7 categories termed vigour, dedication, reward, autonomy, social support, conciliation and attributes of nurses. Then these categories were grouped into 3 major themes: job characteristics, characteristics of organizations, and individual characteristics. Conclusions: Having high engagement does not mean ignoring the negative aspects of work and organizations. Nurses who maintain high engagement are also affected by the negative aspects, however the assessment of positive aspects such as enjoying the work, the meaning of being a nurse, reward and autonomy enable the process of depletion of engagement to be overcome. In view of the findings, we propose reconceptualising the construct, taking the features of nursing into account (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Sierra, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Castro, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Zaragoza, Fermín</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Identificar aspectos comunes de las enfermeras con elevado engagement, que nos permitan desarrollar con más profundidad el constructo aplicado a enfermería. Método: A partir del paradigma constructivista y con un enfoque fenomenológico, se llevó a cabo un análisis cualitativo del contenido, utilizando una aproximación inductiva. Las participantes fueron enfermeras que trabajaban en atención directa de diferentes ámbitos asistenciales. El tamaño de la muestra vino dado por la saturación de los datos y fue de 15 participantes a los que se les realizaron entrevistas semiestructuradas grabadas. Resultados: Las unidades de significado se agruparon en 11 subcategorías, estas a su vez en 7 categorías, que se han llamado vigor, dedicación, recompensa, autonomía, apoyo social, conciliación y cualidades de las enfermeras. Posteriormente estas categorías se agruparon en 3 grandes temas: características de los puestos de trabajo, características de las organizaciones y características individuales. Conclusiones: El hecho de tener un engagement elevado no significa ignorar los aspectos negativos del trabajo y de las organizaciones. Las enfermeras que mantienen el engagement elevado también se ven afectadas por los aspectos negativos, sin embargo, la apreciación de aspectos positivos como disfrutar con el trabajo, el significado de ser enfermera, la recompensa y la autonomía permiten superar el proceso de desgaste del engagement. A la vista de los resultados se propone una reconceptualización del constructo que contemple las particularidades de la enfermería (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);27(3): 153-162, mayo-jun. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163212</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implicación de las enfermeras en su profesión. Un estudio cualitativo sobre el engagement</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50207</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53819^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23591^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
