<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109522</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Association Between the Myeloperoxidase Gene Polymorphisms and the Susceptibility to Prostate Cancer: A Case-Control Study in a Chinese Population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: Prostate cancer (PCa) is the most common cancer among men in most western populations. The polymorphisms of the myeloperoxidase (MPO) gene have been correlated with abnormal MPO expression and increased risk of various types of cancers. Our study aimed to evaluate the association between the genetic polymorphisms and the risk of prostate cancer. Methods: Genotyping was carried out by using the genotyping system (MassARRAY iPLEX; Sequenom, Inc., San Diego, CA, USA) on 1,108 PCa patients and 1,525 cancer-free controls in a Chinese Han population. Results: Although one SNP (rs8082134, P &lt; 0.050) was significant, it is very rare and unstable. Other SNPs had no significant difference between genotype distributions in the PCa patients and the control group. Totally, SNPs in the MPO gene is not associated with PCa risk. Conclusion: Our data showed a limited association between the MPO SNPs and the susceptibility to PCa in population of Chinese Han population. The possible association of rs8082134 of MPO with PCa risk need further clarification (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Xu, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ding, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Liu, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Feng, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ding, Q</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes y objetivos: El cáncer de próstata (CaP) es el cáncer más común entre los hombres en la mayoría de las poblaciones occidentales. El gen de polimorfismos de la mieloperoxidasa (MPO) se ha correlacionado con la expresión anormal de la MPO y el aumento del riesgo de varios tipos de cáncer. Nuestro estudio ha tenido como objetivo evaluar la asociación entre los polimorfismos genéticos y el riesgo de cáncer de próstata. Métodos: La genotipificación se realizó mediante el sistema de genotipificación (MassARRAY IPLEX; Sequenom, Inc., San Diego, CA, EE. UU.) en 1.108 pacientes con CaP y 1.525 controles sin cáncer en una población china Han. Resultados: Aunque un PNS (rs8082134, p &lt;0,050) fue significativo, es muy poco común e inestable. Otros PNS no tuvieron diferencias significativas entre las distribuciones de los genotipos en los pacientes con CaP y el grupo control. En total, los PNS en el gen de la MPO no se asocian con el riesgo de CaP. Conclusión: Nuestros datos mostraron una asociación limitada entre los PNS de la MPO y la susceptibilidad al CaP en la población china Han. La posible asociación de rs8082134 de MPO con el riesgo de CaP necesita más aclaraciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;37(2): 79-82, feb. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109522</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asociación entre los polimorfismos de genes de mieloperoxidasa y la susceptibilidad a cáncer de próstata: un estudio caso-control en la población de nacionalidad china</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31878</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5974</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22496^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54727^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11910^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11910^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54727^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
