<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112578</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Physiological and molecular characterization of Phytophthora infestans isolates from the Central Colombian Andean Region</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Late blight, caused by Phytophthora infestans, is one of the most devastating diseases found in potato and tomato crops worldwide. In Colombia it also attacks other important crops: cape gooseberry and tree tomato. The knowledge of the pathogen population is determinant to effectively design control strategies. Aims. To determine the physiological and molecular characteristics of a set of Colombian P. infestans isolates. Methods. Strains isolated from Cundinamarca and Boyacá were examined for the level of resistance to mefenoxam and cymoxanil. Virulence was tested for all strains and crosses between A1 mating type, from different hosts, and the Colombian A2 mating type were tested for the production and viability of oospores in different substrates. Additionally, the molecular diversity of the avirulence gene Avr3a, the &amp;#946;-tubulin gene, and two single copy genes showing RxLR motif, was assessed. Results. We found all levels of mefenoxam sensitivity, with 48% of the strains resistant. A high diversity of races was detected and the population was genetically clonal. Colombian strains had the possibility of sexual reproduction. Conclusions. These results will help in optimizing the use of fungicides and deployment of resistance as control strategies and will contribute to broader studies on diversity of this pathogen(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Céspedes, María C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojas, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vargas, Angela M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Restrepo, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernal, Adriana J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales, Juan G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cárdenas, Martha E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. El tizón tardío, causado por Phytophthora infestans, es una enfermedad devastadora de la papa y el tomate a nivel mundial, y en Colombia también ataca otros cultivos como la uchuva y el tomate de árbol. El conocimiento de la población del patógeno es determinante para el diseño efectivo de estrategias de control. Objetivos. Determinar las características fisiológicas y moleculares de aislamientos colombianos de P. infestans. Métodos. El nivel de resistencia al mefenoxam y al cimoxamil fue evaluado en aislamientos de Cundinamarca y Boyacá. Se estimó su virulencia y se determinó la producción y viabilidad de oosporas en diferentes sustratos con cruces entre aislamientos A1 y el aislamiento colombiano A2. Además, se determinó la diversidad molecular en el gen de avirulencia Avr3a, el gen de la &amp;#946;-tubulina y otros dos genes de copia única con motivo RXLR. Resultados. Los aislamientos colombianos tuvieron la posibilidad de reproducirse sexualmente. Encontramos todos los niveles de sensibilidad al mefenoxam, con el 48% de los aislamientos resistentes. Se detectó una diversidad de razas y a nivel genético la población fue clonal. Conclusiones. Estos resultados ayudarán a optimizar el uso de fungicidas y reducir la resistencia como estrategias de control, además de contribuir al conocimiento de la diversidad de este patógeno(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;30(2): 81-87, abr.-jun. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112578</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Caracterización fisiológica y molecular de aislamientos de Phytophthora infestans de la región andina central colombiana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37540^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51204</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27485^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15176^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52999^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19538^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15176^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52999^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52999^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24244^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24244^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29761^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15176</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
