<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86595</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">An IRT assessment of Rotter&#146;s I-E scale: a new approach and some considerations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study assessed the functioning and measurement properties of Rotter&#146;s Locus of Control Scale in its Spanish version by using a new approach based on Item Response Theory. Our procedure allows us: (a) to detect the impact of response biases (acquiescence and social desirability); (b) to evaluate clearly the test dimensionality and structure; (c) to evaluate and understand the causes of some items&#146; inefficiency; and (d) to increase measurement precision. Globally, the results do not contradict those obtained in previous research, but allow some of the criticisms the scale had received to be qualified. Some recommendations for use are proposed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Anguiano-Carrasco, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Demestre, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chico, Eliseo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrando, Pere Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se evalúa el funcionamiento y propiedades de medida de la versión española de la escala de Locus de Control de Rotter; dicha evaluación utiliza un nuevo enfoque basado en la teoría de respuesta al ítem. Nuestro procedimiento permite: (a) detectar el impacto de los sesgos de respuesta (aquiescencia y deseabilidad social); (b) evaluar de forma clara la dimensionalidad y estructura del test; (c) evaluar las posibles causas del deficiente funcionamiento de algunos ítems; y (d) incrementar la precisión de la medida. Globalmente, los resultados no contradicen lo obtenido en estudios previos, pero permiten matizar algunas de las críticas que ha recibido la escala. Se proponen algunas recomendaciones para su uso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);23(2): 282-288, abr.-jun. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86595</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación TRI de la escala I-E de Rotter: un nuevo enfoque y algunas consideraciones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12025^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24535</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12025^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24872</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
