<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88777</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Follow-up of iliac diameter in patients after open abdominal aortic aneurysm repair with an aorto-aortic prosthetic graft</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Iliac artery aneurysms are uncommon and there is current no protocol for the follow-up. Aim: To evaluate the progress of the diameter of the iliac arteries by echo-doppler in patients undergoing abdominal aortic aneurysm (AAA) open repair with an aorto-aortic prosthetic graft. Material and methods: A cross-sectional study of patients undergoing AAA between January 1999 and March 2008, on whom an echo-doppler was performed to assess the diameter of iliac arteries. A total of 45 patients were included. The variables studied were: pre- and post-operative iliac diameter (angio-computerized tomography), vascular risk factors and comorbidities. Student t test, Chi-square test were performed and survival tables constructed. Results: The mean age was: 69 years (SD 6.8). Follow-up: 4.5 years (1.89). Preoperative mean size of iliac arteries: 13 mm (0.45), follow-up: 17 mm (0.52), p = 0.001. Overall, the diameter increased in 19 % iliac arteries during growth monitoring. There was a lower expansion rate in diabetic patients (0 %/24 %, relative risk [RR] 0.76, 95 % confidence interval [CI]: 0.7-0.9). We were unable to determine a time/expansion rate correlation. No patient required a repeat operation during the follow-up. Conclusion: Although our series showed a significant growth, the iliac arteries ultrasound follow-up is not justified, in this context, due to the low/no need for a subsequent surgical procedure(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Merino Mairal, O. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sena Ruiz, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano Vilardell, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riera Vázquez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los aneurismas de arteria iliaca después de la reparación de un aneurisma aórtico abdominal (AAA) son poco comunes y no se ha protocolizado el seguimiento del diámetro iliaco. Objetivo: Evaluar la evolución del tamaño de las arterias iliacas mediante eco-doppler en pacientes intervenidos de AAA e interposición de injerto recto. Material y métodos: Estudio transversal de pacientes intervenidos de AAA entre enero de 1999 y marzo de 2008 a los que se les realiza un eco-doppler para valorar el diámetro de las arterias iliacas. Se recogen 45 pacientes. Variables estudiadas: diámetro iliaco preoperatorio (angio-tomografía computarizada) y postoperatorio, así como factores de riesgo vascular y comorbilidades. Se realizan las pruebas de la t de Student, Chi 2 y tablas de supervivencia. Resultados: Media de edad: 69 años (desviación estándar [DE] 6,8). Seguimiento medio: 4,5 años (DE 1,89). Tamaño preoperatorio medio de arterias iliacas: 13 mm (DE 0,45), en el seguimiento: 17 mm (DE 0,52), p = 0,001. Un 19 % de las iliacas presentó crecimiento durante el seguimiento. Se observó un menor crecimiento en pacientes con diabetes mellitus (0/24 %, riesgo relativo [RR] 0,76; intervalo de confianza [IC] 95 %: 0,7-0,9). No se ha podido determinar una correlación tiempo/crecimiento. Ningún paciente precisó tratamiento durante el seguimiento. Conclusión: Aunque en nuestra serie se demuestra un crecimiento significativo durante el seguimiento, no está justificado un protocolo de seguimiento ecográfico de arterias iliacas en este contexto por la baja/nula necesidad de tratamiento quirúrgico posterior(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;62(6): 219-224, nov.-dic. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88777</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución del diámetro iliaco tras resección de aneurisma aórtico e interposición de injerto aorto-aórtico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14572^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7266^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1019^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14572^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1019^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1019^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7266^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
