<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055450</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Polipropilene strap: use in deepithelization in reduction mammaplasty</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Many methods have been used to make easy skin deepithelization in reduction mammaplasty. The most important is to provide a good tension in order to harvest the skin quickly, easier and without difficulties. Surely, this is the most tedious part of breast reduction, because you need a very good breast tension, so anything that can be done to hasten this step is welcome. We report the application of a polypropilene strap to improve breast tension and deepithelization in breast reduction. This retraction maneuver makes this step of the operation quicker and easier (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fidalgo Rodríguez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrera Sánchez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>De Piero Belmonte, G. H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rioja Torrejón, L. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Cecilia, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Muchos métodos han sido utilizados para facilitar la desepidermización en mamoplastias de reducción. Uno de los aspectos más importantes es proporcionar una adecuada tensión para hacer dicha tarea fácil y sin muchas dificultades. Sin duda, esa es la parte más tediosa de la reducción mamaria porque se necesita una buena tensión durante un tiempo. Por tanto, cualquier maniobra que facilite esta tarea, es bienvenida. Presentamos la aplicación de una brida de polipropileno con objeto de proporcionar tensión y desepidermización adecuadas en mamoplastias de reducción. Esta maniobra de retracción hace más fácil y rápido este paso de la intervención (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;33(2): 137-138, abr.-jun. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055450</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso de bridas de polipropileno para la desepidermización en mamoplastias de reducción</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32332^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d274^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29995^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29995^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11563^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
