<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78266</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characteristics of sudden death in inherited heart disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. Cardiomyopathy and channelopathy are major causes of sudden death (SD). The little information available on the context in which SD occurs has come from only a few referral centers. The objective was to investigate the circumstances surrounding SD in families with inherited heart disease. Methods. The study included 152 SD patients (mean age 43±19 years) from 103 families. The reasons for inclusion were resuscitated SD in 7%, recent SD in 8%, and a diagnosis of cardiomyopathy or channelopathy in a living relative in 72%. Also, 13% were athletes. Family trees were constructed and each death&#146;s circumstances were recorded. Autopsy and medical records were reviewed. Results. Overall, 18% of SDs occurred during physical exercise, 32% during normal daily activities, and 37% during rest or sleep. There was a significant association between male sex and SD: 111 males (73%) vs. 41 females (27%; P=.03). Exercise-related SD was associated with young age (P=.01). The percentage of SDs associated with exercise, stress or normal daily activities was significantly greater with cardiomyopathy than channelopathy (61% vs. 41%; P=.057). All athletes were male and the majority died during exercise (50% vs. 11% of non-athletes; P=.0002). Patients with Brugada syndrome had the highest percentage of SDs during rest or sleep (i.e. 47%). No clear trigger could be identified in 33%. Conclusions. SD was common in inherited heart disease, which accounted for a significant number of cases. Males clearly predominated over females (ratio 3:1) among SD cases (irrespective of pathological type). Most SDs occurred during exercise or normal daily activities in cardiomyopathies and during rest or sleep in channelopathies. The percentage of exercise-related SDs (i.e. 18%) was higher than expected (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gimeno, Juan R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alberola, Arcadi G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lacunza, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valdés, Mariano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliva, María J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabater, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saura, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Sánchez, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Las miocardiopatías (MCP) y las canalopatías (CP) son causas importantes de muerte súbita (MS). Existe poca información en la literatura sobre el contexto en el que se produce la MS, y proviene de unos pocos centros de referencia. El objetivo del presente trabajo es estudiar las circunstancias de la MS en familias con cardiopatías hereditarias. Métodos. Se registraron 152 casos de MS en un total de 103 familias (media de edad, 43 ± 19 años). Los motivos de inclusión fueron: MS resucitada, 7%; MS reciente, 8%; diagnóstico de MCP o CP en un familiar vivo, 72%. El 13% eran deportistas. Se trazaron árboles familiares y se recogieron los detalles sobre las circunstancias del fallecimiento. Se revisaron historias clínicas e informes autópsicos. Resultados. El 18% de las MS ocurrieron durante el ejercicio físico, el 32% en actividades cotidianas y el 37% en reposo/sueño. Hubo una asociación estadística entre el sexo varón y la MS (111 [73%] frente a 41 [27%]; p = 0,03). La MS relacionada con el ejercicio se asoció con la edad joven (p = 0,01). En el grupo de MCP se registró de forma significativa un mayor porcentaje de MS en relación con ejercicio/estrés/actividad cotidiana respecto al grupo de CP (el 61 frente al 41%; p = 0,057). Todos los deportistas eran varones y la mayoría de ellos fallecieron realizando ejercicio (el 50 frente al 11% de los no deportistas; p = 0,0002). El grupo de síndrome de Brugada presentó el porcentaje más elevado de MS en reposo/sueño (47%). En el 33% del total no fue posible identificar claramente el desencadenante. Conclusiones. La MS es frecuente en las cardiopatías hereditarias y supone un número importante de casos. Entre los casos de MS (independientemente del tipo de afección) los varones predominan claramente sobre las mujeres (3:1). La mayoría de las MS ocurrieron realizando ejercicio o una actividad cotidiana en las miocardiopatías y durante el reposo o el sueño en las canalopatías. El porcentaje de MS relacionadas con el ejercicio (18%) es superior al esperado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;63(3): 268-276, mar. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78266</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características de la muerte súbita en las cardiopatías hereditarias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6484^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52154^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6484^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30163^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52154^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52136^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52136^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52136^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6484^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30163^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30163^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30163^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52154^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6484^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
