<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59931</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Management of the agitated patient in the emergency department</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Agitated patients must be managed fairly often in routine emergency department practice. After safety measures are taken during initial assessment, a tentative diagnosis based on the cause of agitation (physical condition, underlying mental disorder, or extreme anxiety) should be made. That diagnosis will facilitate possible resolution of the problem through dialog with the patient or through physical restraint. If restraint is chosen, the manner of proceeding should be planned and at least 5 persons should be involved. The restraining maneuver is usually followed by administration of benzodiazepines, neuroleptic agents, or a combination of both in order to assure sedation. It is important to remember that these patients pose a threat to their families, emergency room staff, and themselves; therefore, they are candidates for voluntary or involuntary admission to a psychiatric unit. If that is the course of action chosen, admission must comply with the law and adequate restraint and sedation should be prescribed. All such actions should be recorded in the emergency department&#146;s report to the psychiatrist on duty, who will be the admitting physician  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casal Angulo, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Gallego, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sinisterra Aquilino, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Estarlich, María Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murcia Pérez, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los pacientes agitados son una situación clínica a la que con relativa frecuencia se enfrentarlos médicos en su práctica clínica. En la primera valoración, además de tomarlas oportunas medidas de seguridad, debemos de hacer un diagnóstico de presunción basado en el origen de la agitación (causa orgánica, trastorno mental subyacente o manifestación de una ansiedad extrema). Ello facilitará una posible resolución mediante un abordaje verbal o por el contrario se procederá a la contención mecánica. En caso de que se tome esta última decisión, se debe planificar con antelación y realizarla con al menos 5 personas. Dicha maniobra suele ser el paso previo a la contención con sedación farmacológica con benzodiacepinas, neurolépticos o una pauta combinada de ambos. Es necesario tener en cuenta el riesgo que suponen estos pacientes para su entorno familiar, el personal que lo atiende o incluso su propia vida, por lo que son candidatos a ingresar en unidades de psiquiatría de forma voluntaria o involuntaria. Si optamos por esta última, debe realizarse al amparo de la Ley, así como las medidas de contención y sedación adecuadas. Todas estas maniobras tienen que estar reflejadas con nuestro informe para el psiquiatra de guardia, que es quien realiza el ingreso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);21(2): 121-132, abr. 2009. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59931</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo inicial del paciente agitado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4712^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12032^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
