<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77808</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Thrombolytic therapy for acute ischemic stroke. Experience of SITS (Safe Implementation of Thrombolysis in Stroke) register</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Recently it has been demonstrated safety andefficacy of treatment with intravenous recombinant tissue-typeplasminogen activator (rt-PA) for acute ischemic stroke in Europe,however there are differences in different European countriesthat may have variations in the response to treatment. In thisstudy we reviewed the experience of thrombolytic therapy inSpain in a prospective observational register.Methods. The SITS-ISTR (Safe Implementation of Thrombolysisin Stroke-International Stroke Thrombolysis Register) is aregister to evaluate the safety and efficacy of routine use ofthrombolysis in acute ischemic stroke. This study analyzed thecontribution of Spanish patients.Results. A total of 16,049 patients were included in the registerbetween May 2002 and November 2007, of whom 1914(11.9%) from 42 Spanish centers. Spanish patients had more historyof diabetes, and less hypertension, atrial fibrillation, priorstroke, early signs of ischemia, and pretreatment with aspirin. Inrelation to the rest of countries, Spain had a higher percentage offunctional independence at 3 months (OR 1.09; 95 % CI: 1.02-1.15, p=0.01) although they have a slight increase in the numbersymptomatic hemorrhage (OR 1.29, 95% CI: 1.07-1.56, p=0.008),with no differences in the overall mortality (OR 0.99, 95 % CI:0.91-1.08, p=0.87).Conclusions. In Spain, treatment with rt-PA for ischemicstroke is safe and effective when administered within the first3 hours after symptom onset, and have a higher benefit than inthe rest of the world (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castillo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Sabín, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Yáñez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez-Tejedor, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dávalos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Recientemente se ha demostrado la seguridad yeficacia del tratamiento con activador del plasminógeno tisular recombinado(rt-PA) intravenoso para el ictus isquémico agudo en Europa,sin embargo existen diferencias en los distintos países europeosque pueden condicionar variaciones en la respuesta al tratamiento.En este estudio revisamos la experiencia del tratamiento trombolíticoen España recogido en un registro prospectivo internacional.Métodos. El estudio SITS-ISTR (Safe Implementation of Thrombolysisin Stroke-International Stroke Thrombolysis Register) se tratade un registro para evaluar la seguridad y la eficacia de uso rutinario dela trombólisis en el ictus isquémico agudo. En este estudio realizamosun análisis de la contribución de los centros y pacientes españoles.Resultados. Un total de 16.049 pacientes fueron incluidos en elregistro entre mayo de 2002 y noviembre de 2007, de los cuales 1.914(11,9 %) procedían de 42 centros españoles. Estos presentaban másantecedentes de diabetes y menos de hipertensión arterial, fibrilaciónauricular, ictus previo, signos precoces de isquemia, y tratamientoprevio con aspirina. En relación con el resto de países, los españolespresentaron un mayor porcentaje de independenciafuncional al cabo de 3 meses (Odds ratio [OR]: 1,09; intervalo deconfianza [IC] 95 %: 1,02-1,15; p = 0,01) a pesar de presentar un ligeroincremento en el número de hemorragias sintomáticas (OR:1,29, IC 95 %: 1,07-1,56, p = 0,008), sin observarse diferencias encuanto a la mortalidad global (OR: 0,99; IC 95 %: 0,91-1,08; p =0,87).Conclusiones. En España el tratamiento con rt-PA para el ictusisquémico es seguro y eficaz cuando se administra dentro de las3 primeras horas tras el inicio de los síntomas y presenta un beneficiosuperior al del resto del mundo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;24(5): 288-291, jun. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77808</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento trombolítico en el ictusisquémico agudo en España: experienciadel registro SITS (Safe Implementationof Thrombolysis in Stroke)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29633</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27786</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30438^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5478^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24892</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
