<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043971</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sclerosing sertoli cell tumor</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Sertoli cell tumor is an unfrequent neoplasmof the testis and the recently reported sclerosingvariant is even rarer, and seems to have a different prognosis.Patients and Methods: A 28 year-old man consultedthe urologist because of a slight increase in right testicularvolume. Echographic examination revealed an intratesticularsolid tumor, 1 cm in diameter. Radical orchiectomy showedan intratesticular sclerotic tumor composed by sheetsand cords of cuboidal benign appearing cells. Immunostainingsfor cytokeratins, vimentin, and calretinin were done.Atypia and mitoses were not found. An analysis of diagnosticmorphological criteria and clinical peculiarities describedin previous recent reports was done</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Etxegarai, Leire</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, José Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrés, Leire</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bilbao, Francisco José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ereño, Cosme</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se trata de un varón de 28 años de edad que acude alurólogo por presentar un leve aumento de volumen del testículoderecho. El estudio ecográfico muestra un tumor sólidointratesticular de aproximadamente 1 cm de diámetro. Lapieza de orquiectomía radical muestra un tumor con un grancomponente de fibrosis estromal en el que aparecen cordonesde células cuboideas sin atipia citológica ni mitosis, quemuestran positividad para citoqueratinas, vimentina y calretinina.El tumor de células de Sertoli es una neoplasia muypoco frecuente en el testículo. La variedad esclerosante, queha sido descrita recientemente, es aún más rara y comportadiferente pronóstico. En este trabajo se revisa los criteriosmorfológicos diagnósticos y las peculiaridades clínicasrecogidas recientemente en la literatura</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;38(2): 117-120, abr.-jun. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043971</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumor de células de Sertoli esclerosante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14115^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23533^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13086^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19167^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
