<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125556</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-7606</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Posttraumatic anisocoria simulation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In forensic practice is relatively common to find individuals who produce or exaggerate symptoms of disease, consciously, with the intention of making a profit. Sometimes, malformations or previous pathologies attributed to a new traumatic event. It is therefore necessary to be careful when establishing causation. Today we bring, the case of an individual who seeks to attribute the traumatic aftermath of an attack anisocoria. The Forensic Physician, with the collaboration of the Scientific Police, was able to demonstrate that the origin of the injury was before, not being able to establish a causal link (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez García, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quesada, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sibón Olano, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la práctica forense es relativamente frecuente encontrar individuos que elaboran o exageran síntomas de enfermedades, de manera consciente, con la intención de obtener una ganancia; en otras ocasiones atribuyen malformaciones o patologías previas a un nuevo evento traumático. Por ello es preciso ser minuciosos a la hora de establecer el nexo causal. Se presenta el caso de un individuo que pretende atribuir la secuela de anisocoria traumática a una agresión. El médico forense, con la colaboración de la Policía Científica, pudo demostrar que el origen de la lesión era previo, no pudiéndose establecer el nexo causal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. med. forense;20(1): 48-50, ene.-mar. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125556</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Simulación de anisocoria postraumática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28016^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8479^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38837^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24521^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24792^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
