<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104865</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of childhood obesity in Spain; National Health Survey 2006-2007</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Childhood Obesity has become a Public Health priority due to it high prevalence and consequences in health status. Objective: To estimate prevalence of obesity in the children included in the National Health Survey of 2006-2007and to determine its association with socioeconomic position and other socio-demographic variables. Methods: Cross-sectional study using data available from 6,139 Spanish children between 2-15 years old, Included in the National Health Survey. Parents or guardians reported weight and height to estimate obesity prevalence according to the International Obesity Task Force cut-offs for body mass index. Results: Obesity prevalence was 10,3% and overweight prevalence was 18,8%. Obesity was more prevalent in children from 4-5 years age (18,3%) and overweight in the 8-9 years stratus (25,5%). Overweight was more frequent in boys than girls (19,8% versus 17,8%; p = 0,04).Canary Islands, Ceuta and Melilla, Valencia and Andalusia were the Autonomous Communities with higher obesity prevalence in contrast with the Basque Country, Galicia and Madrid which showed the lowest prevalence. This distribution generates a north to south gradient in obesity prevalence. Both, obesity and overweight showed an inverse association with socioeconomic position (p &lt; 0,05). Conclusion: Childhood obesity rates in Spain accounts from ones of the highest in Europe, with a strong geographic and socioeconomic gradient. Priority should be given to effective interventions that can reach the most vulnerable groups as identified in this study, like restrictions on TV food advertising and tax reliefs to promote healthy eating (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valdés Pizarro, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Royo-Bordonada, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La obesidad infantil constituye una prioridad de Salud Pública dada su elevada prevalencia y sus consecuencias en la salud. Objetivo: Estimar la prevalencia de obesidad en los niños incluidos en la Encuesta Nacional de Salud de 2006-2007 y determinar su asociación con la posición socioeconómica y otras variables socio-demográficas. Métodos: Estudio transversal que recogió datos secundarios de la Encuesta Nacional de Salud, contando con una muestra representativa de 6.139 niños españoles de 2-15 años de edad. Se utilizó peso y talla reportados por los padres o tutores para estimar la prevalencia de obesidad según los puntos de corte para el índice de masa corporal recomendados por la International Obesity Task Force. Resultados: La prevalencia de obesidad fue de 10,3% y de sobrepeso de 18,8%. La obesidad fue más prevalente en los niños de 4-5 años (18,3%) y el sobrepeso en niños de8-9 años (25,5%). El sobrepeso fue más frecuente en niños que en niñas (19,8% versus 17,8%; p = 0,04). Canarias, Ceuta y Melilla, Valencia y Andalucía fueron las Comunidades Autónomas con mayor prevalencia de obesidad encontraste con el País Vasco, Galicia y Madrid que presentaron las más bajas, generándose un gradiente norte-sur en la prevalencia de obesidad. Tanto la obesidad como el sobrepeso presentaron una asociación lineal inversa con la posición socioeconómica (p &lt; 0,05).Conclusión: La prevalencia de obesidad infantil en España se sitúa entre las más altas de Europa y presenta importantes variaciones regionales y en función de factores socioeconómicos que deberían tenerse en cuenta para priorizar intervenciones dirigidas a los grupos más vulnerables, como restricciones a la publicidad alimentaria y exenciones de impuestos para promover una alimentación saludable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;27(1): 154-160, ene.-feb. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104865</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de obesidad infantil en España; Encuesta Nacional de Salud 2006-2007</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16508</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37738^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
