<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86314</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5735</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Metabolic syndrome and second generation antipsychotic agents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Although some second generation antipsychotic agents reduce the risk of extrapyramidal adverse effects against first generation agents, they have been associated to an increased incidence of metabolic syndrome. This syndrome is characterized by insulin resistance, abdominal obesity, atherogenic dyslipidemia (hypertriglyceridemia, decrease of HDL-cholesterol/ LDL-cholesterol ratio), arterial hypertension and a prothrombotic and proinflammatory state. Metabolic syndrome increases significantly the risk of cardiovascular illness and premature death. Therefore, a multidisciplinary approach to that syndorme´s prevention and treatment could result in a substantially impact upon the general state of patients meetings its criteria. We emphasize current physiopathological findings, increased risk with polytherapy (second generation antipsychotics and both second and first generation combination), current diagnostic criteria and monitoring of patients at risk. Our aim is to contribute to an early detection that possibilities implementation of pharmacological and non pharmacological multidisciplinary interventions(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cortés Morales, Benjamín</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Aunque algunos antipsicóticos de segunda generación reducen el riesgo de efectos adversos extrapiramidales frente a los de primera generación, su uso se ha asociado a la aparición de síndrome metabólico. Esta es una entidad caracterizada por resistencia a la insulina, obesidad abdominal, dislipidemia aterogénica (hipertrigliceridemia, disminución del colesterol- HDL y aumento del colesterol-LDL), hipertensión arterial y un estado protrombótico y proinflamatorio. El síndrome metabólico puede aumentar significativamente el riesgo de enfermedad cardiovascular y muerte prematura por lo que su abordaje multidisciplinar podría incidir sustancialmente en el estado de salud general de los pacientes que lo desarrollen. Se presenta en este trabajo una revisión de la asociación del síndrome metabólico y los antipsicóticos de segunda generación. Se revisan hipótesis y hallazgos actuales en la fisiopatología, el aumento de riesgo con la politerapia (con antipsicóticos de segunda generación y con combinaciones de fármacos), los criterios diagnósticos actuales y el seguimiento de pacientes con riesgo de desarrollarlo. Pretendemos contribuir a una detección temprana de este síndrome que facilite implementar intervenciones multidisciplinarias farmacológicas y no farmacológicas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Neuropsiquiatr;31(110): 303-320, abr.-jun. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86314</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome metabólico y antipsicóticos de segunda generación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23686^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23686^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23686^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5216^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
