<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59445</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intrauterine insemination in women with polycystic ovary syndrome and clomiphene citrate resistance</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the results of ovulation induction cycles with gonadotropins and intrauterine insemination (IUI) carried out in women with polycystic ovary syndrome (POS) resistant to clomiphene citrate. Material and methods: We performed an observational retrospective study of 462 ovulation induction cycles with IUI in women with SOP and clomiphene citrate resistance. Results: The clinical pregnancy rate was 11.9% per cycle initiated and 14.74% per insemination and 45.45% of the pregnancies terminated in abortion. The effective accumulative percentage of term pregnancies per cycle initiated was 8% for the 82 first cycle and 10.23% for insemination, increasing to 26.15% from the fifth cycle and to 32.24% from the fifth insemination. A total of 19.26% of the cycles was cancelled. Conclusions: IUI is a useful method in women with SOP who are resistant to clomiphene citrate, with similar results to those obtained with other indications. These patients have high abortion and cycle cancellation rates. The high abortion rate should prompt research into ways of reducing reproductive loss (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Criado, María  Setefilla</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Guadix, Bárbara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fontes Jiménez, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calderón Rodríguez, María Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Navarro, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Jurado Romero de la Cruz, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar los resultados del tratamiento mediante inducción de la ovulación con gonadotropinas e inseminación artificial intrauterina (IAC-IU) realizados en mujeres con síndrome de ovario poliquístico (SOP) resistentes al citrato de clomifeno (CC). Material y métodos: Estudio observacional retrospectivo de 462 ciclos de inducción de la ovulación con IAC-IU en mujeres diagnosticadas de SOP resistentes al tratamiento con CC. Resultados. La tasa de embarazo clínico fue del 11,9% por ciclo iniciado y del 14,74% por inseminación, finalizando en aborto el 45,45% de los embarazos. El porcentaje acumulativo efectivo de embarazo a término por ciclo iniciado fue del 8% al primer ciclo y del 10,23% por inseminación, manteniéndose en el 26,15% a partir del quinto ciclo y en 32,24% a partir de la quinta inseminación. Se canceló el 19,26% de los ciclos. Conclusiones: La IAC-IU es un método útil en mujeres con SOP resistentes al CC, con resultados similares a los obtenidos con otras indicaciones. Estas pacientes presentan altas tasas de aborto del primer trimestre y de cancelación de ciclo. Esta elevada tasa de aborto debe dar lugar al desarrollo de una línea de investigación que logre encontrar la pauta que disminuya la pérdida reproductiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);52(2): 81-88, feb. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59445</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inseminación artificial intrauterina en mujeres con síndrome de ovario poliquístico resistentes al citrato de clomifeno</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11519^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23290^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3020^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8862^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
