<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157538</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of the economic crisis on consumption of psychotropic drugs in Asturias (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess whether the economic crisis of 2008 has changed the consumption of anxiolytics, hypnotics-sedatives and antidepressants in Asturias (Spain). Method: We conducted a descriptive study of drug use from 2003 -2013. The defined daily doses of 1000 inhabitants per day (DHD) were calculated for anxiolytics, hypnotics-sedatives and antidepressants. Linear regression coefficients (b) of the DHD were obtained for the pre-crisis period (2003-2008) and the crisis period (2009-2013). Results: The consumption of anxiolytics increased by 40.25%, that of hypnotics by 88.11% and that of antidepressants by 80.93%. For anxiolytics: b-(2003-2008)=4.38 DDI/year and b-(2009-2013)=1.08 DDI/year. For hypnotics-sedatives: b-(2003-2008)=2.30 DDI/year and b-(2009-2013)=0.40 DDI/year. For antidepressants: b-(2003-2008)=5.79 DDI/year and b-(2009-2013)=2.83 DDI/year. Conclusions: The rise in consumption of the three subgroups during the crisis period was lower than that of the pre-crisis period. This study does not confirm the influence of the economic crisis on the rise in consumption of these drugs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nicieza García, María Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Lorenzo,  Julio C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rilla Villar, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez Gil, Patricio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar si la crisis económica de 2008ha comportado cambios en la evolución del consumo de ansiolíticos, hipnótico-sedantes y antidepresivos en Asturias. Método: Estudio descriptivo y de utilización de medicamentos durante 2003-2013. Se calcularon las dosis diarias definidas por 1000 habitantes/día (DHD) de ansiolíticos, hipnótico-sedantes y antidepresivos. Se obtuvieron coeficientes de regresión lineal (b) de las DHD de la etapa precrisis (2003-2008) y de la etapa de crisis (2009-2013). Resultados: El consumo de ansiolíticos creció un 40,25%, el de hipnóticos un 88,11% y el de antidepresivos un 80,93%. Para los ansiolíticos: b-(2003-2008)=4,38 DHD/año y b-(2009-2013)=1,08 DHD/año. Para los hipnótico-sedantes: b-(2003-2008)=2,30 DHD/año y b-(2009-2013)=0,40 DHD/año. Para los antidepresivos: b-(2003-2008)=5,79 DHD/año y b-(2009-2013)=2,83 DHD/año. Conclusiones: El incremento del consumo para los tres subgrupos en la época de crisis fue menor que en la época precrisis. No se confirma que la crisis económica haya influido aumentando el consumo de estos medicamentos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;30(6): 464-467, nov.-dic. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157538</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de la crisis económica sobre el consumo de psicofármacos en Asturias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7170^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14543^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53789</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4422^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12055^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55124^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
