<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-SMB-14175</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Daily hassles in childhood and their relationship with symptomatology and adaptation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study analyzed the relationship between daily hassles and psychological symptoms (externalizing and internalizing symptomatology) and school, social and family adaptation in childhood. The participants were 552 (53.4% boys and 46.6% girls), aged between 10-12 years (M= 10.91). Patients receiving treatment in mental health services and a community group were compared. Self-report questionnaires were administered: Children's Hassles Scale (CHS), Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ-Cas), Modified Depression Scale (MDS), School Adaptation Scale and Family Adaptation Scale. The average of daily hassles was 11, with six of them experiencing distress. Daily hassles were related to an increased presence of symptoms and lower levels of adaptation (p&lt; .01). The association between daily hassles and depressive symptoms were stronger in the clinical group than in the community one. Daily hassles explain from 21 to 39 percent of variance in symptomatology and from 5 to 41 percent in adaptation. Daily hassles are relevant for planning prevention and intervention strategies in Childhood (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calonge Romano, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Arias, M del Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rey Bruguera, Mayelin</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este trabajo se analizó la relación entre las situaciones estresantes cotidianas (SEC) y la sintomatología psicológica, exteriorizada e interiorizada, y la adaptación escolar, social y familiar en la infancia. El número de participantes fue de 552 (53,4% niños y 46,6% niñas), de entre 10 y 12 años (M= 10,91). Se comparó un grupo clínico de salud mental con un grupo comunitario. Se administraron autoinformes:"Escala de situaciones estresantes cotidianas en la infancia" (Children&#146;s Hassles Scale, CHS), "Cuestionario de capacidades y dificultades" (Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire, SDQ-Cas), "Escala de depresión modificada" (Modified Depression Scale, MDS), "Cuestionario de adaptación escolar" y "Cuestionario de adaptación familiar". Se registra una media de 11 SEC y seis vividas con malestar. Las SEC se relacionan con la presencia de sintomatología y una menor adaptación (p&lt; 0,01), siendo mayor la asociación con los síntomas depresivos en el grupo clínico. Las SEC explican del 21 al 39% de la varianza de la sintomatología y entre el 5 y el 41% de la adaptación. Las SEC son relevantes para planificar estrategias de prevención e intervención en la infancia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;25(3): 483-503, dic. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-SMB-14175</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Situaciones estresantes cotidianas en la infancia y su relación con la sintomatología y la adaptación</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
