<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98001</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Out-of-hospital emergencies: the suicidal patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Suicidal behavior has existed since mankind exists, however, positive or negative view of it has changed through different cultures. At present, poses a significant public health problem, and studied from different perspectives and areas of expertise, trying to give anoverview to understand this phenomenon so interesting, exciting and at times bewildering. Therefore, the objective of this study is to analyze the profile of people who commit a suicide in the city of Madrid and are treated in the outpatient emergency area. Methods: Observational,descriptive and retrospective study, framed in SAMUR-Civil Protection in 2008, analyzing all cases seen ideation, suicide attempt, whichhave involved an Advanced Life Support and Counselling Unit. We analyzed a sample of 96 suicidal patients, where 48.4% were attempted suicide, followed by 44.2% of suicides and suicidal ideation 7.4%, seen mainly in the months of March and May, morning session-afternoon, and in the district of Puente de Vallecas, intervention from Madrid 112 defendants in the highest percentage. Results: Establishing a patient profile suicide as male, 25-35 years, Spanish, single, with psychiatric disorders in treatment, but previous attempts, he had verbalized his intentions autolytic, taking as a trigger for the physical or mental illness itself, which chooses defenestration as autolytic method without thepresence of others, to which he was transferred to the Hospital and has a diagnosis of TBI, trauma or polytrauma. Conclusions: Knowledgeof the profile of the suicidal patient treated in different areas allows better known, the risk factors of suicidal behavior and may facilitatefuture preventive actions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pacheco Tabuenca, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Robles Sánchez, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La conducta suicida ha existido desde que la humanidad existe, sin embargo, la concepción positiva o negativa del mismoha cambiado a través de las diferentes culturas. En la actualidad, supone un grave problema de salud pública, y se estudia desde diferentesperspectivas y áreas de conocimiento, tratando de dar una visión global para poder entender este fenómeno tan interesante, apasionante y, en ciertos momentos desconcertante. Objetivo: Por tanto, el objetivo del presente estudio es analizar el perfil de las personas que cometen un acto suicida en la ciudad de Madrid y que son atendidos en el área de la emergencia extrahospitalaria. Método: Estudio observacional,descriptivo y retrospectivo, encuadrado en SAMUR-Protección Civil durante el año 2008, analizando todos los casos atendidos de ideación,tentativa y suicidio consumado donde han intervenido un Soporte Vital Avanzado y la Unidad de Asistencia Psicológica. Se ha analizado una muestra de 96 pacientes suicidas, donde el 48,4% fueron tentativas de suicidio, seguidos de un 44,2% de suicidios consumados y un 7,4% de ideación autolítica, atendidos principalmente en los meses de marzo y mayo, turno de mañana - tarde, y en el distrito de Puente de Vallecas, intervenciones demandadas desde Madrid 112 en su mayor porcentaje. Resultados: Se establece un perfil de paciente suicida como varón, de 25-35 años, español, soltero, con patología psiquiátrica en tratamiento, sin tentativas previas, que había verbalizado sus intenciones autolíticas, teniendo como factor desencadenante la propia enfermedad física o psíquica, que elige como método autolítico la defenestración sin presencia de otras personas, al cuál se le traslada al Hospital y presenta como diagnóstico principal TCE, trauma o politraumatismo. (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;67(4): 345-353, oct.-dic. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98001</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Emergencias extrahospitalarias: el paciente suicida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13792^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13791^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54296</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37735^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
