<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128446</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Criteria and norms for interpreting the Beck Depression Inventory-II (BDI-II)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper reports two studies providing criteria and norms to interpret scores on the Spanish adaptation of the BDI-II. The first study was aimed at validating the original BDI-II cut-off scores to distinguish levels of depression  severity and at finding the best cut-off scores for the Spanish adaptation. To getthese aims, 215 Spanish patients with a variety of psychological disorders filled out the BDI-II and a clinician-rated scale was administered by their psychologists to assess the severity of patients&#146; depression. The results of these clinician ratings validated the depression levels defined by the original BDI-II cut-off scores; in addition, by means of ROC curves, it was found that cut-off scores for the Spanish adaptation were practically equal to those for the original BDI-II. The aim of the second study was to develop tables of percentiles with three Spanish samples: 712 patients with psychological disorders, 569 adults from the general population and 727 university students. The advantages of the combined use of the proposed criteria and norms are discussed since they provide complementary  information (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gesteira, Clara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Vera, María Paz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presentan dos estudios que ofrecen criterios y baremos para interpretar las puntuaciones de la adaptación española del BDI-II. El objetivo del estudio 1 fuevalidar las puntuaciones de corte originales del BDI-II para distinguir distintos  niveles de gravedad de la depresión y buscar las mejores puntuaciones de corte para la adaptación española. Para ello, 215 pacientes españoles con diversos trastornos psicológicos completaron el BDI-II y se les aplicó una escala de heteroevaluación con la cual los psicólogos que les atendían valoraron lagravedad de su depresión. Los resultados de estas valoraciones validaron los niveles de depresión definidos por las puntuaciones de corte originales del BDI-II; además, mediante curvas ROC, se obtuvieron unas puntuaciones de corte para la adaptación española prácticamente iguales a aquellas. El objetivo del estudio 2 fue elaborar tablas de puntuaciones centiles a partir de tres muestras españolas: 712 pacientes con trastornos psicológicos, 569 adultos de la población general y 727 estudiantes universitarios. Se discuten las ventajas de la utilización combinada de los criterios y baremos propuestos, pues ambos ofrecen  información complementaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;22(1): 37-59, ene.-abr. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128446</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Criterios y baremos para interpretar el &#147;Inventario de depresión de Beck-II&#148; (BDI-II)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10746^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
