<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161292</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Giving information in the end-of-life-process. Whose responsibility?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: One of the most common ethical conflicts in health care and one which generates considerable suffering is whether or not to give clinical information to patients and their families at the end-of-life stage. Aim: The objective of this paper is to examine and interpret the giving of health information to people in the process of dying from the Nursing perspective. Method: This study is defined within the qualitative paradigm, and uses the interpretative hermeneutic-phenomenological method. The study setting is Andalusia Health Service health care centres in the city and province of Huelva, and carried out by health care professionals who work in Andalusia Health Service clinics and hospitals. Data have been gathered from contributions in a nominal group, discussion group, and interviews. Results: There is no consensus among palliative care professionals about whether it is helpful to provide the dying patient with accurate information. One of main difficulties cited by health care professionals was the fear of harming the patient, which in turn might have legal consequences. Supplying information to the patient is seen as a Nursing responsibility that must be managed as a team (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortega Galán, Ángela M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González de Haro, M Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: Uno de los conflictos éticos más frecuentes y generadores de sufrimiento en la atención sanitaria es la información a pacientes y familias en el final de la vida. Objetivo: El objetivo de este trabajo es explorar e interpretar la visión de la enfermería respecto a la información sanitaria proporcionada a las personas en el proceso de la muerte. Método: Esta investigación se enmarca en el paradigma cualitativo y utiliza el método fenomenológico-hermenéutico interpretativo. El escenario de la investigación lo han conformado los Centros Sanitarios del Servicio Andaluz de Salud en Huelva y su provincia, siendo las personas informantes profesionales vinculados a los hospitales y Centros de Salud correspondientes. La información se ha obtenido a través de las técnicas de grupo nominal, grupo de discusión y la entrevista. Resultados: En el ámbito de los cuidados paliativos no existe unanimidad entre los profesionales respecto a la conveniencia o no de facilitar información veraz a la persona enferma, siendo una de las dificultades importantes el miedo de los propios profesionales a hacer daño y a que esto se traduzca en una situación de inseguridad jurídica. La información se evidencia como una responsabilidad de enfermería que debe ser abordada en equipo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;24(2): 83-88, abr.-jun. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161292</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La información sanitaria en el proceso de la muerte: ¿a quién corresponde?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30048^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14746^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6904^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11797^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
