<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050960</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Long-term pelvic floor prolapse surgery outcomes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the long-term outcomes of pelvic floor prolapse surgery. Patients and methods: We recruited 252 patients who underwent surgery in Donostia Hospital between 2000 and 2001. There were 194 vaginal hysterectomies, 219 anterior colpoplasties, 218 posterior colpoplasties, 41 placements of tension-free vaginal tape associated with prolapse surgery, 15 colpopexies and three colpocleises. Follow-up was performed in November and December 2005. The patients were questioned about risk factors for pelvic organ prolapse, current symptoms, and subjective appraisal of surgical outcomes. A questionnaire on symptoms and quality of life was administered. The Pelvic Organ Prolapse Quantification System (POPQ) was used for pelvic examination. We defined surgical failure as a symptomatic prolapse or POPQ-S grade II or higher. Results: Five years after surgery, the reintervention rate was 2.7%. Surgical failure in one or more compartment was found in 28.18% of the examined women, distributed in 18.12% anterior, 4% apical and 11.4% posterior. Eighty-five percent of the interviewed patients had no sensation of prolapse. Urgency incontinence was reported by 17.1% and stress incontinence by 7.3%. Dyspareunia was found in 14.3%. In the subjective appraisal, 86.2% reported they were symptom-free, 6.3% felt marked improvement, 2.9% felt slight improvement, 1.96% experienced no change, 1.96% felt worse and 0.5% did not know. Conclusions: Our long-term outcomes are good compared with those of other series. There is little correlation between symptomatic and anatomical failure. Secondary symptoms of the surgery should be included in the appraisal of surgical outcome. Further studies should be carried out with a higher number of patients and long-term prospective follow-up to correctly define the criteria for surgical failure</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aizpitarte Gorrochategui, Iurdana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Becerro Cortizas, Ainhoa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez-Itza, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar los resultados de la cirugía del prolapso del suelo pélvico a largo plazo. Pacientes y métodos: Se seleccionó a 252 pacientes intervenidas en el Hospital Donostia entre 2000 y 2001. Se realizaron 194 histerectomías vaginales, 219 colpoplastias anteriores, 218 colpoplastias posteriores, 41 TVT (tension-free vaginal tape) asociadas a la cirugía del prolapso, 15 colpopexias y 3 colpocleisis. El seguimiento se realizó en noviembre y diciembre de 2005. Se incluyó una anamnesis dirigida a los factores de riesgo del prolapso, la sintomatología actual, la valoración subjetiva de los resultados y un cuestionario de síntomas y calidad de vida. Para el examen pélvico se utilizó el Pelvic Organ Prolapse Quantification System (POPQ-S). Se definió como fallo en la cirugía al prolapso sintomático o al grado II o superior del POPQ-S. Resultados: La tasa de reintervención tras 5 años de la cirugía fue del 2,7%. El 28,18% de las mujeres exploradas presentó fallo quirúrgico en uno o varios compartimentos, distribuido en un 18,12% anterior, un 4% apical y un 11,4% posterior. El 85% de las pacientes entrevistadas no tenía sensación de prolapso, el 17,1% refería clínica de incontinencia de urgencia y el 7,3%, clínica de esfuerzo; el 14,3% presentaba dispareunia. En la valoración subjetiva, el 86,2% referían curación, el 6,3% mejoría notable, el 2,9% mejoría discreta, el 1,96% igual, el 1,96% peor y el 0,5% no sabía. Conclusiones: Nuestros resultados a largo plazo son buenos en comparación con los de otras series. Hay poca correlación entre fallo anatómico y sintomático. En la valoración del resultado quirúrgico hay que incluir la aparición de nuevos síntomas secundarios a la cirugía. Es necesario realizar estudios con un mayor número de pacientes y a más largo plazo para poder definir correctamente los criterios de fallo quirúrgico</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);49(12): 701-711, dic. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050960</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultado de la cirugía del prolapso del suelo pélvico a largo plazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11824</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31203^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12508^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7225^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
