<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110924</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of technical devices and physiotherapy equipment requested in the ministry of education of the region of Murcia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background Care of students with physical disabilities in the school requires the intervention of several professionals. Of importance among them is the pediatric physiotherapist who evaluates the child's difficulties and the technical devices needed in the school environment. This study has aimed to analyze the technical devices requested in the Ministry of Education in the Region of Murcia. Material and method The data were collected using the model established for this purpose during the months of January to July 2010. A descriptive analysis was made of the data and the relationships between variables were assessed. Results A total of 143 requests were reviewed with a mean age of the children of 6.92 years. Murcia Teams had the highest percentage (27.3%). In relation to sex, 38.5% of the requests were for girls. Non-degenerative diseases and tetraplegia had the highest percentage regarding medical and functional diagnosis. There is a higher number of requests for individual technical devices, furniture, physiotherapy and mobility. Conclusions Differences were found between medical diagnosis, sex and educational levels. It is necessary go into greater depth regarding the social factors and the environment to improve the quality of life of children with motor disabilities (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montero-Mendoza, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hidalgo-Montesinos, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Conesa, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo La atención del alumnado con discapacidad motora en la escuela en la comunidad autónoma de Murcia requiere de la intervención de diferentes profesionales, entre los que destaca el fisioterapeuta pediátrico para valorar la dificultad que presenta el niño y las ayudas técnicas que necesita en el entorno escolar. El objetivo del estudio ha sido realizar un análisis de las ayudas técnicas solicitadas por los centros escolares en la Consejería de Educación de la Región de Murcia. Material y método Los datos fueron recogidos a través del modelo establecido al efecto, durante los meses de enero a julio de 2010. Realizamos un análisis descriptivo de los datos y se valoró la relación entre distintas variables. Resultados El número total de solicitudes revisadas es de 143, con una edad media de 6,92 años. Los equipos de Murcia presentan el mayor porcentaje (27,3%). En relación con el sexo, un 38,5% de solicitudes corresponden a niñas. En relación con el diagnóstico médico y el diagnóstico funcional, las enfermedades no degenerativas y las tetraplejías presentan el mayor porcentaje. Existe un mayor número de solicitudes referidas a ayudas técnicas individuales, mobiliario, fisioterapia y movilidad. Conclusiones Se han encontrado relaciones significativas entre el diagnóstico médico, el sexo y las etapas educativas. Es necesario profundizar en los factores sociales y en la mejora de la calidad de vida para valorar el grado de aceptación de las ayudas técnicas en el entorno del niño (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);35(2): 52-57, mar.-abr. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110924</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de las ayudas técnicas y del material de Fisioterapia solicitadas en la consejería de educación de la comunidad autónoma de Murcia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4943^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11247^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10166^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15254^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10160^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
