<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61563</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Improved effectiveness in the management of cardiovascular risk among type 2 diabetic patients in primary health care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To determine the impact of the implementation of a guidelines in theassessment of cardiovascular risk in high-risk patients (type2diabetes) in health centres, and to analyse the appropriateness of antihypertensive and antiplatelet treatment in diabetic patients.Design: Quasi-experimental, non-randomised, prospective study with concurrent control group.Placement: Two health centres in Málaga.Participants: General practitioners of the two centres.Interventions: The guideline was implemented through a multifaceted intervention in family physicians in the experimental centre.Main outcomes: Rate of cardiovascular risk assessment in high risk population. Secondary: appropriateness of antihypertensive and antiplatelet treatment.Results: Large differences were detected in the cardiovascular risk assessment, improving in the experimental group (74.36% vs. 7.63%; RR ¼ 9.74; 95%CI, 5.15&#150;18.43; P ¼.0001). Similarly, the antiplatelet use was more in line with the guidelines recommendations in theintervention group (51.28% vs. 36.44%; RR ¼ 1.407; 95%CI, 1.04&#150;1.89; P ¼.026), andin antihypertensive drugs, although with no statistical significance (80% vs. 66.27%;RR ¼ 1.207; 95%CI, 0.99&#150;1.46).Conclusions: A multifaceted intervention for the implementation of a guideline for the management of high risk cardiovascular patients, improves the adherence to effectiveinterventions by family physicians(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Orellana Lozano, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego Parrilla, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Jiménez, Leonor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viciana López, María Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hormigo Pozo, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Asencio, José Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos:                                  Determinar el impacto de la implementación de una guía en la valoración del riesgo cardiovascular de pacientes en alto riesgo (diabéticos tipo 2), y en la adecuación del tratamiento antihipertensivo y antiagregante.Diseño: Estudio semiexperimental, no aleatorizado, prospectivo, con grupo control concurrente.EmplazamientoDos centros de salud de Málaga.Participantes: Médicos de familia.Intervenciones: Implementación de la guía mediante intervenciones multicomponentes sobre los médicos de familia del centro experimental.Mediciones principales: Variable principal de resultado: grado de estimación del riesgo cardiovascular en población con elevado riesgo (diabéticos). Variables secundarias: adecuación del tratamiento antihipertensivo y antiagregante.Resultados: Se detectaron importantes diferencias en la estimación del riesgo cardiovascular a favor del grupo experimental (el 74,36 frente al 7,63%; riesgo relativo [RR]=9,74; intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 5,15&#150;18,43; p=0,0001). Las pautas de antiagregación se ajustaron más a las recomendaciones de la evidencia en el grupo intervención (el 51,28 frente al 36,44%; RR=1,407; IC del 95%, 1,04&#150;1,89; p=0,026), al igual que en antihipertensivos, aunque sin significación (el 80 frente al 66,27%; RR=1,207; IC del 95%, 0,99&#150;1,46.Conclusiones: Una estrategia de implementación multicomponente de una guía para el manejo de pacientes con elevado riesgo cardiovascular mejora la adherencia a intervenciones efectivas por parte de médicos de familia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;41(5): 240-245, mayo 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61563</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mejora de la efectividad en el manejo del riesgo cardiovascular de pacientes diabéticos tipo 2 en atención primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16735</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200905</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
