<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99012</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prognostic significance of hemoperitoneum in peritoneal dialysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">According to previous reviews, hemoperitoneum episodes appear in 6.1-8.4% of the peritoneal dialysis patients, and they are severe in a 20% of them. Due to the absence of severe hemoperitoneum in our peritoneal dialysis program, we retrospectively reviewed hemoperitoneum non-related with abdominal surgery or catheter placing. We analyzed its incidence, etiology, prognostic and clinical outcome, as well as the possible effect of recurrent hemoperitoneum on peritoneal function. A total of 132 patients were treated in our centre during a period of 173 months. Mean age at the beginning of peritoneal dialysis was 59 ± 17.1 years, 43.2% were females, and 22.8% of them were menstruating women. Twentytwo patients had at least one hemoperitoneum episode during follow-up, with an incidence of 17%. The mean time interval between the start of peritoneal dialysis and the first hemoperitoneum episode was 0,66 ± 0,94 years (range: 0.01-3.20 years). 73% were women. Most cases (59%) were due to menstruation. Remarkably, all the menstruating women presented hemoperitoneum at least once with a high incidence of recurrent episodes. The other hemoperitoneum episodes were mainly of unknown etiology (32% of patients), being this one the main cause in males. We only observed two more cases: a male who presented hemoperitoneum related to dicumarinic overdose and a female who presented hemoperitoneum due to mesenteric ischemia. All the 22 patients had a favourable outcome, except for the woman with mesenteric ischemia, what represented an incidence of 4.5% of severe hemoperitoneum. No significant association was found between episodes of hemoperitoneum and aspirin treatment, dicumarinic treatment or the presence of coagulopathy. There was no association either between recurrent hemoperitoneum and the number of peritonitis episodes, peritoneal function or technique survival. In conclusion, hemoperitoneum is a common and usually benign problem in peritoneal dialysis patients, frequently due to retrograde menstruation, and no deleterious long-term effects were found in patients with recurrent hemoperitoneum (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Garcíam, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ponz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blasco, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mañém, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valenzuela, MP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marquina, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Ocaña, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Según revisiones previas, entre el 6,1 y el 8,4% de los pacientes en diálisis peritoneal presentan episodios de hemoperitoneo y su pronóstico es grave hasta en un 20% de casos. Ante la ausencia de hemoperitoneos graves en nuestro programa de diálisis peritoneal, decidimos revisar retrospectivamente los hemoperitoneos no relacionados con la cirugía abdominal ni con la colocación del catéter. Analizamos su incidencia, etiología, pronóstico y evolución, así como el efecto del hemoperitoneo recurrente sobre la función peritoneal en 132 pacientes con edad media al iniciar diálisis peritoneal de 59 ± 17,1 años, de los que el 43,2% eran mujeres y, de éstas, un 22,8% tenían la menstruación. Durante el seguimiento, 22 pacientes tuvieron al menos un episodio de hemoperitoneo, con una incidencia del 17% y un tiempo medio en diálisis peritoneal hasta el primer episodio de hemoperitoneo de 0,66 ± 0,94años (rango: 0,01-3,20 años). El 73% eran mujeres. La menstruación fue la causa del 59% de los hemoperitoneos. El 32% fueron de etiología desconocida, siendo ésta la causa más frecuente en varones. Únicamente un varón presentó hemoperitoneo en relación a sobredosis de dicumarínicos y una mujer presentó hemoperitoneo secundario a una isquemia intestinal. La evolución fue favorable en todos ellos a excepción de la paciente con isquemia mesentérica, lo que supuso una incidencia de hemoperitoneos graves del 4,5%. El tratamiento antiagregante o anticoagulante y la presencia de coagulopatía no se relacionaron con la aparición de hemoperitoneo. Tampoco hubo relación entre el hemoperitoneo recurrente y el número de peritonitis, el deterioro de la función peritoneal y la supervivencia de la técnica. En conclusión, el hemoperitoneo es un problema frecuente en diálisis peritoneal y generalmente benigno, a menudo asociado a la menstruación, y sin efectos negativos a largo plazo en los pacientes con hemoperitoneo recurrente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;28(1): 73-76, ene.-feb. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99012</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Significado pronóstico del hemoperitoneo en diálisis peritoneal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6617^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8767</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22114</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200802</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
