<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72583</identifier>
<setSpec>0556-6177</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Breast cancer during pregnancy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">As women in western countries delay childbearing, it has been hypothesizedthat the incidence of breast cancer diagnosed during pregnancywill increase. Breast carcinoma during pregnancy(BCP) put the health ofthe mother in confl ict with that of the fetus. The aim is to give optimaltreatment to the mother to maximise the chances of survival, whilstminimising the risk of harm of the fetus.Few breast surgeons or oncologist develop expertise in this area owingthe rarity of the association.We report the epidemiology, pathology, clinical picture, therapeuticmanagement and fetal outcome of pregnant women with breast cancertreated in our institution (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Domínguez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quincoces, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Velloso, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Fraile, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Richter, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La asociación de cáncer de mama y embarazo se defi ne como la apariciónde un tumor maligno mamario en la gestación o durante el primer añoposparto. La frecuencia global oscila entre el 0.2 al 3.8% del total delos tumores malignos de la mama. El cáncer de mama se diagnostica,por término medio en 1 de cada 3000 gestaciones.Esta asociación plantea múltiples interrogantes y para su correcto tratamientoes necesario conocer una serie de aspectos generales, así comoevaluar la repercusión que tienen los distintos esquemas de tratamientooncológico sobre el embarazo y poder ofrecer secuencias terapéuticasaceptables y efi caces. A continuación se realiza una puesta al día detodos estos aspectos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Med Univ Navarra;52(1): 18-24, ene.-mar. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72583</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cáncer de mama durante el embarazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11693^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11693^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11693^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22968</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11693</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
