<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89259</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Emotional intelligence and suggestibility: effects on anxiety in female undergraduates</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present paper presents two empirical studies. The first one aims to explore the possible relationship between suggestibility (measured by the Inventory of Suggestibility, IS; González &#150; Ordi &amp; Miguel &#150; Tobal, 1999) and perceived emotional intelligence (PEI) (Trait Meta-Mood Scale, TMMS; Salovey, Mayer, Goldman, Turvey &amp; Palfai, 1995) in a sample of female undergraduate students. Based on the results of the first study, the second one examines the predictive and incremtnl capacity of PEI to explain anxiety levels (ISRA; Miguel- Tobal &amp; Cano- Vindel, 1986) after controlling for explained variance associated with suggestibility. Results show that there is a clear relationship between suggestibility and perceived emotional intelligence in the sense that higher levels of suggestibility are more related with higher levels of emotional attention and lower levels of emotional clarity and repair. Moreover, such results add evidence to the incremental validity of PEI when explaining levels of anxiety. Finally, several hypotheses on the underlying basis of the relationship between suggestibility and PEI and its negative effect on emotional adjustment are proposed and results are discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Berrocal, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salguero, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Ordi, H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente trabajo muestra los resultados de dos estudios empíricos En el primero de ellos se explora la relación entre sugestionabilidad (Inventario de Sugestionabilidad, IS; González-Ordi &amp; Miguel &#150; Tobal, 1999) e Inteligencia Emocional Percibida (IEP) (TRait Meta-Mood Scale, TMMS; Salovey, Mayer, Goldman,  Turvey &amp; Palfai, 1995) en una muestra de mujeres universitarias. A partir de estos resultados, un segundo estudio  examina la capacidad predictiva e incremental de los componentes de la IEP en la explicación del nivel de ansiedad (ISRA; Miguel-Tobal &amp; Cano-Vindel, 1986) tras controlar la varianza explicada por la sugestionabilidad. Los resultados obtenidos muestran la existencia de un claro patrón de relaciones entre la IEP y la sugestionabilidad, así el nivel de sugestionabilidad se relaciona con mayores niveles de atención emocional y menores  niveles de claridad y reparación. Además, los resultados del segundo estudio añaden evidencia sobre la validez incremental de la IEP en la explicación del nivel de ansiedad. Finalmente, se discuten los resultados y se proponen hipótesis acerca de las bases que subyacen a la relación entre sugestionabilidad e IEP y a su efecto negativo sobre el ajuste emocional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;14(2/3): 143-158, dic. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89259</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inteligencia emocional y sugestionabilidad. Efectos sobre el nivel de ansiedad en una muestra de mujeres universitarias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7528</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13790</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
