<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121909</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The main objective of this study was to retrospectively analyze the clinical, pathological, diagnostic and therapeutic elements related to the patients with thyroid carcinoma admitted to the Department of Endocrinology of the Hospital Infantil Universitario Niño Jesús form 1989 until 2004. Patients. Fourteen patients (11 girls (70%) and 3 boys (21%)) with thyroid carcinoma were studied. The mean age at diagnosis was 10.3 yrs (5-14 yrs); with six patients less than 6 yrs of age at diagnosis. Only one patient received irradiation in the neck-head area during bone marrow transplantation. Two patients had familial antecedents of Men syndrome type 2A. Results. The most important clinical sign was the existence of goiter with or without thyroid nodule (n=10; 71%). Among the other four patients, one exhibited cervical adenopathy (7%), two were diagnosed during follow-up of familial history of MEN syndrome type 2A (12%) and the remaining patient was diagnosed when pulmonary metastasis was observed in a thoracic X-ray (7%). The pathological diagnoses were as follows: papilar carcinoma (n=7; 50%), follicular carcinoma (n=2; 14%), medular carcinoma (n=2; 14%), follicular adenoma (n=1; 7%), toxic adenoma (n=1; 7%) and polyadenomatosis (n=1; 7%). In eleven patients the tumor was only localized in the thyroid gland (78%); while the presence of metastasis was evident in three patients (22%). In two cases it was gangliar and one case pulmonary and gangliar. All children were euthyroid, except the patient with toxic adenoma (clinical and biochemical hyperthyroidism). Surgical treatment was employed in all cases: total thyroidectomy with ganglionectomy in 12 cases (11 carcinomas and one polyadenomatosis) or hemithyroidectomy in two patients with adenoma. All patients with either papilar or follicular carcinoma received I131 after surgery and later levothyroxine to suppress TSH levels (&#133;) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pozo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Colmenero, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Calderón, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Argente, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montero, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo consiste en analizar de forma retrospectiva los aspectos clínicos, anatomopatológicos, diagnósticos y terapeúticos de los tumores tiroideos recogidos en el Servicio de Endocrinología del Hospital Infantil Universitario Niño Jesús desde 1989 a 2004. Pacientes. Un total de catorce pacientes han sido diagnosticados de patología tumoral tiroidea. Sólo uno de ellos había recibido irradiación ene l área cervicocefálica en el curso de un traplante de médula ósea. Dos pacientes tenían historia familiar de síndrome de MEN tipo 2ª. Resultados. La edad media al diagnóstico de los 14 pacientes revisados, 11 niñas (79%) y 2 niños (21%), fue de 10,2 años (5-14 años); de ellos, 6 tenían una edad inferior a 6 años al diagnóstico. El principal signo que condujo al diagnóstico fue la aparición de bocio con o sin modularidad tiroidea (n=10; 71%). De los restantes 4 pacientes, uno consultó por adenopatías cervicales (7%), dos fueron diagnosticados en el seguimiento por historia familiar de síndrome MEN2A (12%) y el último, que no presentaba bocio, pero sí adenopatías cervicales, fue diagnosticado casualmente al observarse metástasis pulmonares en una radiografía realizada por otro motivo (7%). Los diagnósticos anatomopatólogos fueron: carcinoma papilar (n=7; 50%), carcinoma folicular (n=2; 14%), carcinoma medular (n=2; 14%), adenoma folicular (n=1; 7%), adenoma tóxico (n=1; 7%) y poliadenomatosis (n=1,7%). En 11 de los pacientes el tumor estaba confinado al tiroides, mientras que 3 pacientes (22%) presentaban metástasis en el momento del diagnóstico, 2 ganglionares y uno ganglionares y pulmonares. Todos los pacientes, salvo el que presentó un adenoma tóxico (hipertiroidismo clínico y bioquímico), se encontraban eutiroideos. El tratamiento fue quirúrgico en el 100% de los casos: tiroidectomía total con limpieza ganglionar (11 carcinomas y 1 poliadenomatosis) o hemitiroidectomía (2 adenomas). Los pacientes con carcinoma papilar y folicular recibieron terapia ablativa con I131 tras la cirugía y, posteriormente, levotiroxina a dosis supresoras del TSH (&#133;) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;61(4): 282-287, jul.-ago. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121909</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumores tiroideos en la infancia: aspectos clínicos diagnósticos y terapéuticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12271^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22696^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14348^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14353^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
