<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81869</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Aetiology and management of diabetic peripheral neuropathy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aetiology. Painful diabetic neuropathy affects approximately 25% of diabetic patients, those treated with insulin and/or glucose lowering drugs, and is characterised by presenting as a distal symmetric neuropathy associated with chronic pain. Pathophysiology. The cause is generally vascular, which produces a lesion of the primary sensory nerves due to neuronal hypoxia and lack of nutrients. Symptoms. The onset is usually bilateral in the toes and feet. In cases where it is asymmetric, it progresses to be bilateral. It can gradually progress to the calves and the knees, in which case the patient may experience symptoms of pain and/or paresthesia both in the hands and feet (&#147;glove-stocking&#148; pattern). Symptoms. They describe the pain using diverse terms: burning, electric, deep, etc. Allodynia and hyperalgesia are less common. The pain intensity is usually gets worse at night. Symptoms. Other symptoms: vascular claudication, dysautonomic signs (skin colour, abnormal temperature, sweating), depression and anxiety, sleep disorders. Physical findings. Sensory loss and the loss or decrease in Achilles tendon reflex is characteristic in &#147;glove-stocking&#148;, although some patients who only have small nerve fibres involvement may have normal reflexes and vibratory sensitivity. Diagnosis. It is clinical. There is no need for electro-physiological studies when the history and physical findings are consistent with the diagnosis of painful diabetic neuropathy. Natural history. The natural history of painful diabetic neuropathy varies and its clinical course unpredictable. In some patients, the pain may improve after months or years, while in others it persists and gets worse. Treatment. Due the great number of causal and contributing factors in the pathogenesis of diabetic neuropathy, there is no single satisfactory treatment. The maintenance of a glycosylated haemoglobin between 6.5 and 7.5% can slow down and even prevent the progression of neuropathy. Treatment. The current treatment recommendations for painful diabetic neuropathy can be seen in table 5 and figure 1 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Soler Pedrola, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Homs Riera, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Samper Bernal, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monerris Tabasco, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Etiología. La neuropatía diabética dolorosa afecta aproximadamente al 25% de los pacientes diabéticos, aquellos tratados con insulina y/o hipoglucemiantes orales, y se caracteriza por presentarse como una neuropatía distal simétrica asociada a dolor crónico. Fisiopatología. Generalmente es de causa vascular, que provoca lesión de los nervios sensitivos primarios por hipoxia neuronal y déficit de nutrientes. Síntomas. El inicio suele ser bilateral en dedos y pies. En los casos de origen asimétrico, la progresión es hacia la bilateralidad. Puede progresar gradualmente a pantorrillas y rodillas, en cuyo caso los pacientes pueden notar síntomas álgicos y/o parestesias de forma conjunta en manos y pies (patrón de «guante-calcetín»). Síntomas. El dolor lo describen con diversos términos: urente, eléctrico, profundo. La alodinia y la hiperalgesia son menos comunes. La intensidad del dolor suele empeorar por la noche. Síntomas. Otros síntomas: claudicación vascular, signos disautonómicos (color de la piel y temperatura anormal, sudoración), depresión y ansiedad, trastornos del sueño. Hallazgos físicos. Es característico el déficit sensitivo en «guante-calcetín» y la pérdida o disminución del reflejo aquíleo, aunque algunos pacientes que solo tienen afectación de fibras nerviosas pequeñas pueden tener preservados los reflejos y la sensibilidad vibratoria. Diagnóstico. Es clínico. No hay necesidad de realizar estudios electrofisiológicos cuando la historia y los hallazgos físicos son consistentes con el diagnóstico de neuropatía diabética dolorosa. Historia natural. La historia natural de la neuropatía diabética dolorosa es variable y su curso clínico, impredecible. En algunos pacientes, el dolor puede mejorar después de meses o años, mientras que en otros persiste y empeora. Tratamiento. Debido a la gran variedad de factores causales y contribuyentes en la patogenia de la neuropatía diabética, no existe un tratamiento único satisfactorio. El mantenimiento de una hemoglobina glicosilada entre 6,5 y 7,5% puede enlentecer e incluso prevenir la progresión de la neuropatía. Tratamiento. En la actualidad las recomendaciones de tratamiento de la neuropatía diabética dolorosa se pueden observar en la tabla 5 y figura 1 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;17(6): 286-296, ago.-sept. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81869</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Etiología y manejo de la neuropatía diabética dolorosa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4648^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d936^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8188^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3952^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7109^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3952^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7109^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7109^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
