<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167090</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Utility of a simple lighting device to improve chest compressions learning</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The recommendations on cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR) emphasize the quality of the manoeuvres, especially chest compressions (CC). Audiovisual feedback devices could improve the quality of the CC during CPR. The aim of this study was to evaluate the usefulness of a simple lighting device as a visual aid during CPR on a mannequin. Material and methods. Twenty-two paediatricians who attended an accredited paediatric CPR course performed, in random order, 2min of CPR on a mannequin without and with the help of a simple lighting device, which flashes at a frequency of 100 cycles per minute. The following CC variables were analyzed using a validated compression quality meter (CPRmeter®): depth, decompression, rate, CPR time and percentage of compressions. Results. With the lighting device, participants increased average quality (60.23±54.50 vs. 79.24±9.80%; P=.005), percentage in target depth (48.86±42.67 vs. 72.95±20.25%; P=.036) and rate (35.82±37.54 vs. 67.09±31.95%; P=.024). Conclusions. A simple light device that flashes at the recommended frequency improves the quality of CC performed by paediatric residents on a mannequin. The usefulness of this CPR aid system should be assessed in real patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moure-González, JD</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abelairas-Gómez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Núñez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barcala-Furelos, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Calvete, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las recomendaciones sobre la reanimación cardiopulmonar (RCP) enfatizan la calidad de las maniobras, en especial las compresiones torácicas (CT). Los dispositivos de retroalimentación podrían mejorar la calidad de las CT durante la RCP. El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar la utilidad de un dispositivo lumínico simple como ayuda visual durante la RCP en un maniquí. Material y métodos. Veintidós mujeres pediatras que asistieron a un curso acreditado de RCP pediátrica realizaron, siguiendo un orden aleatorio, 2min de RCP en un maniquí sin y con la ayuda de un dispositivo luminoso simple, que emite destellos con una frecuencia de 100 ciclos por minuto. Se analizaron mediante un medidor validado de la calidad de las compresiones (CPRmeter®) las siguientes variables de las CT: profundidad, descompresiones, frecuencia, tiempo de RCP y porcentaje de compresiones. Resultados. Con el dispositivo luminoso, las participantes aumentaron la calidad media (60,23±54,50 vs. 79,24±9,80%; p=0,005), la profundidad (48,86±42,67 vs. 72,95±20,25%; p=0,036) y la frecuencia del masaje (35,82±37,54 vs. 67,09±31,95%; p=0,024). Conclusiones. Un dispositivo luminoso simple que parpadea a la frecuencia recomendada mejora la calidad de las CT realizadas por residentes de pediatría en un maniquí. Se debería evaluar la utilidad de este sistema de ayuda de la RCP en pacientes reales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;64(9): 506-512, nov. 2017. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167090</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de un dispositivo luminoso simple para mejorar el aprendizaje del masaje cardiaco</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2349^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30213^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6489^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28072^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6489^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2349^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
