<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139813</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recurrent meningitis due to anatomical defects: The bacteria indicates its origin</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Recurrent meningitis is a rare disease. Anatomical abnormalities and immunodeficiency states are predisposing factors. Four cases, in which immunodeficiency was excluded, are presented. The causal microorganism led to the detection of the anatomical defect responsible for the recurrences. Patients and methods: Retrospective review of 4 cases with clinical diagnosis of recurrent bacterial meningitis. Results: Case 1: a thirty month-old boy with unilateral hearing loss, diagnosed with Mondini abnormality by magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) after 2 episodes of Haemophilus influenzae meningitis. Surgical repair after third recurrence. Case 2: fourteen year-old girl diagnosed by MRI with cribriform plate defect after 3 episodes of meningitis due toStreptococcus pneumoniae. Ventriculoperitoneal shunt was placed. Case 3: girl with meningitis due to Staphylococcus aureus at 2 and 7 months. MRI shows occipital dermal sinus requiring excision. Complication with cerebellar abscesses because of a coexisting dermoid cyst. Case 4: child with meningitis due to Streptococcus bovis at 9 days andEnterococcus faecium, Klebsiella pneumoniae and Escherichia coli at 7 months, with positive cultures to Citrobacter freundii and E. faecium later on. Spinal MRI led to the diagnosis of Currarino syndrome with CSF fistula, which was surgically repaired. The 4 patients had undergone image studies reported as normal during the first episodes. Conclusions: In patients with recurrent meningitis the possibility of an anatomical defect should be considered. The isolated microorganism should help to locate it. It is essential to know the normal flora of the different anatomical sites. The definitive treatment is usually surgical (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morgenstern Isaak, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soler-Palacín, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bach Faig, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pumarola Segura, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Nalda, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Méndez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La meningitis recurrente es una patología infrecuente. Los factores predisponentes son alteraciones anatómicas o situaciones de inmunodeficiencia. Presentamos 4 casos en los que, excluida una inmunodeficiencia, el microorganismo responsable orientó al defecto anatómico causante de las recurrencias. Pacientes y métodos: Revisión retrospectiva de 4 casos clínicos con diagnóstico de meningitis bacteriana recurrente. Resultados: Caso 1: niño de 30 meses con hipoacusia unilateral, diagnosticado por resonancia magnética (RM) de malformación de Mondini tras 2 episodios de meningitis por Haemophilus influenzae. Reparación quirúrgica tras tercera recurrencia. Caso 2: niña de 14 años diagnosticada por RM de defecto de lámina cribiforme posterior a 3 episodios de meningitis por Streptococcus pneumoniae. Se coloca válvula de derivación ventrículo-peritoneal. Caso 3: niña con meningitis por Staphylococcus aureus a los 2 y 7 meses. La RM muestra seno dérmico occipital que requiere exéresis. Complicación con abscesos cerebelosos por coexistencia de quiste dermoide. Caso 4: niño con meningitis por Streptococcus bovis a los 9 días y porEnterococcus faecium, Klebsiella pneumoniae y Escherichia coli a los 7 meses, con crecimiento de Citrobacter freundii y E. faecium posteriormente. RM compatible con síndrome de Currarino. Incluye fístula rectal de LCR, que se repara quirúrgicamente. A los 4 pacientes se les habían realizado pruebas de imagen durante los primeros episodios de meningitis, informadas como normales. Conclusiones: En los pacientes con meningitis recurrentes se debe valorar la posibilidad de un defecto anatómico; el microorganismo aislado debe ayudar a localizarlo. Es imprescindible conocer la flora normal de los potenciales focos. El tratamiento definitivo es habitualmente quirúrgico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);82(6): 388-396, jun. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139813</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Meningitis recurrente por defectos anatómicos: la bacteria indica su origen</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29527^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29527^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29527^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29989^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29527^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29989^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29989^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29989^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
