<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95966</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Philosophy and science of the nursing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To promote the development of the nursing discipline it is not only necessary to acquire the body of nursing knowledge but it is also necessary to be aware of the importance of increasing professional self-esteem and to adequately value the care actions of individuals to make progress towards a more humanised care and the endowing social recognition. This recognition must be generated from with in, from the very core of the discipline.This paper depicts a brief reflexion on the nature of the philosophy of nursing. Firstly, the concept of &#147;Philosophy of Nursing&#148; is defined and the different approaches are analysed. Next, the essence and the values inherent to nursing are described. Lastly, a look into the knowledge and development of the nursing discipline is taken in order to explain that not only epistemological issues should be valued regarding knowledge but also ontological questions concerning the meaning, the being, and reality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Calatayud, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Para impulsar el desarrollo de la disciplina enfermera no solo es necesario estudiar el cuerpo de conocimientos de la Enfermería, sino también ser conscientes de la importancia de aumentar la autoestima profesional y valorar las acciones cuidadoras propias para avanzar hacia la humanización de la asistencia y el reconocimiento social merecido y estereconocimiento se debe generar desde dentro, desde el seno de la disciplina.En el presente artículo se presenta una breve reflexión acerca de la naturaleza de la filosofía de la Enfermería. En primer lugar se define el concepto de &#147;filosofía de la Enfermería&#148; y se analizan sus distintos enfoques. A continuación se describen la esencia y los valores de la Enfermería y, por último, se aborda el conocimiento y el desarrollo de la disciplina enfermera para explicar que no solo se deben valorar las cuestiones epistemológicas sobre el conocimiento sino también las preguntas ontológicas sobre el significado, el ser y la realidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;14(8): 67-70, oct. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95966</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Filosofía y ciencia de la disciplina enfermera</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10881</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4723^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23591^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
