<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127195</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of sleep disorders and associated factors in inpatient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the prevalence of insomnia in inpatient in an Internal Medicine Department and to identify risk factors of sleep disorders. Method: A cross-sectional observational study was designed. Inpatients over eighteen years old hospitalized for acute medical conditions were recruited. Insomnia was assessed by the Athens insomnia scale. A nurse administered a questionnaire on risk factors including sociodemographic factors, reason for admission, comorbidities, current medications, functional status, nocturnal symptoms, and environmental factors. Results: A total of 299 patients were recruited with a mean age of 73.7 years (SD 14.2). Overall prevalence of insomnia was 42.1%, slightly higher in women (48.2%) than in men (37.0%)(P = .052). In those less than 65 years the prevalence was 33.8%, and in patients aged 65 or over it was 44.9% (P = .093). The main factors associated with insomnia were a history of anxiety, depression and stroke, heartburn, pain, fear, and poor functional capacity at admission. Environmental factors such as noise, the sensation of cold or heat, and changing habits involved in hospitalization did not reach statistical significance. In patients 65 years or older, the use of beta-blockers was associated with insomnia. The multivariate analysis showed stroke, heartburn, and pain as independent risk factors for insomnia. Conclusions: Insomnia is highly prevalent among inpatient, and is associated with some treatable or modifiable factors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vico-Romero, Judit</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palomera-Faneges, Elisabet</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabré-Roure, Mateu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monteis-Cahis, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serra-Prat, Mateu</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Conocer la prevalencia de insomnio durante el ingreso en los pacientes hospitalizados en un servicio de medicina interna e identificar los factores asociados a la alteración del descanso nocturno. Método Estudio observacional y transversal de una muestra de pacientes hospitalizados por afecciones médicas, mayores de 18 años. El insomnio se valoró con la escala Atenas. Una enfermera administró un cuestionario de factores de riesgo que incluía factores sociodemográficos, motivo de ingreso, comorbilidades, medicamentos actuales, estado funcional, síntomas nocturnos y factores ambientales. Resultados Se reclutaron 299 pacientes, con una edad media de 73,7 años (DT 14,2). Se observó una prevalencia de insomnio global del 42,1%, algo superior en las mujeres (48,2%) que en los hombres (37,0%) (p = 0,052). En los menores de 65 años la prevalencia fue del 33,8% y en los pacientes de 65 años o más fue del 44,9% (p = 0,093). Los principales factores asociados al insomnio fueron los antecedentes de ansiedad, depresión y AVC, la pirosis, el dolor, el miedo y la pobre capacidad funcional durante el ingreso. Factores del entorno como el ruido, la sensación de frío o calor y los cambios de hábitos que comporta la hospitalización no alcanzaron la significación estadística. En los pacientes de 65 años o más el consumo de bloqueadores beta se asoció al insomnio. El análisis multivariado mostró como factores de riesgo independientes el AVC, la pirosis y el dolor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);24(5): 276-282, sept.-oct. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127195</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de trastornos del sueño y factores asociados en pacientes hospitalizados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32436^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
