<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111042</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bacterial skin infections requiring hospitalization</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Epidemiological analysis of bacterial skin infections requiring hospitalization in our area. The factors studied were diagnoses, etiology, association with other diseases, rate of hospitalization and clinical and analytical parameters. Methods. Retrospective analysis of patients admitted to the Department of Pediatrics of &#147;Principe de Asturias&#148; University Hospital from January 1993 to December 2000. Diagnoses reviewed included cellulitis, impetigo, erysipleas and necrotizing fasciitis. Results. Eighty-one percent of the 128 patients reviewed had cellulitis, 17% impetigo and 2% erysipelas. Fifty-nine percent of the patients were under five years age. None of the blood cultures were positive, and Staphylococcus aureus was isolated from the skin lesion in 45.5% of cases. Cellulitis and varicella constituted the most frequent association. Two patients developed necrotizing fasciitis, associated with varicella in both cases. Fifty percent of the patients presented fever at the time of admission. The main site of the infection was the lower extremities. Leukocytosis (WBC count &gt;15 x 103/µL) was found in 29,5% of the patients. The mean value for C-reactive protein was 108 mg/dl (normal value &lt;5). We observed an increasing trend in hospitalization due to bacterial skin infections. Conclusions. Bacterial skin infections occur primarily in boys under  five years of age and in the lower extremities. Blood culture was not useful for diagnosis in any patient. The WBC count and the C-reactive protein level can be of help in the diagnosis and follow-up. Varicella is the most frequently associated disease. To prevent complications, parenteral antibiotic therapy and hospitalization are recommended in those cases associated with varicella (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lassaletta Atienza, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torrijos Román, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Cristobo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García López, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García de Frías, J. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martino Alba, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Análisis epidemiológico de las infecciones bacterianas cutáneas que requirieron hospitalización  en nuestra área; se valoraron: diagnósticos, etiología, asociación con otras enfermedades, tasa de hospitalización, y parámetros clínicos y analíticos. Métodos: Análisis retrospectivo de los casos hospitalizados en el servicio de Pediatría del Hospital Universitario &#147;Príncipe de Asturias&#148; desde enero de 1993 a diciembre de 2000. Diagnósticos revisados: celulitis, impétigo, erisipela y fascitis necrotizante. Resultados: Se hallaron 128 casos; 81% celulitis, 17% impétigo y 2% erisipela. El 59,5% de los niños eran menores de 5 años. Ningún hemocultivo fue positivo y en el 45,5% de los casos en que se cultivaron exudados se aisló Staphylococcus aureus. La asociación más frecuente fue con celulitis y varicela. Dos casos evolucionaron a fascitis necrotizante, ambos asociados a varicela. El 50% presentó fiebre al ingreso. La principal localización fue en extremidades inferiores. En el 29,9% de los casos se observó leucocitosis (leucocitos &gt;15 x 103/µL); el valor medio de la proteína C reactiva (PCR) fue 108 mg/dL (normal &lt;5). Se evidenció una tendencia creciente en la hospitalización por infecciones cutáneas bacterianas. Conclusiones: Las infecciones cutáneas bacterianas son más frecuentes en niños del sexo masculino, menores de 5 años y en extremidades inferiores. El hemocultivo no ayudó a esclarecer el diagnóstico en ningún caso. La leucocitosis y la PCR pueden ayudar al diagnóstico y seguimiento. La varicela es la enfermedad más frecuentemente asociada. Es recomendable la antibioticoterapia parenteral y la hospitalización  en infecciones cutáneas bacterianas asociadas con varicela, ante la posibilidad de complicaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;61(4): 183-186, abr. 2003. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111042</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hospitalización por infecciones bacterianas cutáneas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2515^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1447^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2515^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2515^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1447^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
