<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143529</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Stress and protective factors in individuals at ultra-high risk for psychosis, first episode psychosis and healthy controls</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Stress-vulnerability models of schizophrenia regard psychosocial stress as an important factor in the onset and aggravation of psychotic symptoms, but such research in the early phases of psychosis is limited. Protective factors against the effects of stress might be the key to understanding some inconclusive findings and to the development of optimal psychosocial interventions. The present study compared self-reported levels of stress, self-esteem, social support and active coping in 32 patients with a first episode of psychosis (FEP), 30 individuals at ultra-high risk for psychosis (UHR) and 30 healthy controls. Associations with symptoms of psychosis were assessed in both patient groups. Individuals at UHR reported significantly higher stress levels compared to FEP patients. Both patient groups showed lower self-esteem compared to controls, and the UHR group reported lower social support and active coping than controls. These group differences could not be explained by age and dose of antipsychotic medication in the FEP group. In the UHR group, higher stress levels and lower self-esteem were associated with more severe positive and depressive symptoms on the Brief Psychiatric Rating Scale. Multiple regression analyses revealed that stress was the only significant predictor for both symptom measures and that the relationship was not moderated by self-esteem. Our findings show that individuals at UHR for psychosis experience high levels of psychosocial stress and marked deficits in protective factors. The results suggest that psychosocial interventions targeted at reducing stress levels and improving resilience in this population may be beneficial in improving outcomes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Iyer, Srividya N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Faridi, Kia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Joober, Ridha</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Malla, Ashok K</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pruessner, Marita</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los modelos de esquizofrenia de vulnerabilidad al estrés consideran que el estrés psicosocial es un importante factor en el inicio y la agravación de los síntomas psicóticos, pero en los estadios iniciales de la psicosis dicha investigación es limitada. Los factores protectores frente a los efectos del estrés podrían ser la clave para entender algunos hallazgos poco concluyentes y para el establecimiento de intervenciones psicosociales óptimas. En el presente estudio se compararon los niveles de estrés autorreferido, la autoestima, el apoyo social y el afrontamiento activo en 32 pacientes con un primer episodio de psicosis (PEP), en 30 individuos en riesgo ultra-alto (RUA) de psicosis y en 30 individuos de control sanos. En ambos grupos de pacientes se evaluaron las asociaciones con los síntomas de psicosis. Los individuos en RUA refirieron niveles de estrés significativamente mayores, comparados con los pacientes PEP. En ambos grupos de pacientes fue evidente una menor autoestima comparado con los individuos de control, y el grupo RUA mencionó un menor apoyo social y afrontamiento activo que los individuos de control. En el grupo de pacientes PEP estas diferencias de grupo no pudieron explicarse por la edad ni por la dosis de medicación antipsicótica. En el grupo RUA, los mayores niveles de estrés y la menor autoestima se asociaron a síntomas positivos y depresivos más graves en la escala breve de valoración psiquiátrica (Brief Psychiatric Rating Scale). En los análisis de regresión múltiple se puso de manifiesto que el estrés fue la única variable predictora significativa de la valoración de ambos síntomas y que la autoestima no moderó la relación. Los hallazgos del presente estudio ponen de relieve que los individuos en RUA de psicosis experimentan niveles elevados de estrés psicosocial y deficiencias destacadas en los factores de protección. Los resultados sugieren que las intervenciones psicosociales destinadas a reducir los niveles de estrés y a mejorar la resistencia y la capacidad de recuperación en esta población podrían ser beneficiosas para mejorar los desenlaces (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);19(supl.1): 6-14, dic. 2012. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143529</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrés y factores protectores en individuos en riesgo ultra-alto de psicosis, pacientes con un primer episodio de psicosis e individuos de control sanos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
