<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148766</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The language area of the brain: a functional reassessment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. During the late 19th and early 20th century, a &#145;brain language area&#146; was proposed corresponding to the periSylvian region of the left hemisphere as concluded by clinical observations. This point of view has continued up today. Aim. Departing from contemporary neuroimaging studies, to re-analyze the location and extension the brain language area with regard to the different Brodmann areas. Materials and methods. Using the method known as metaanalytic connectivity modeling seven meta-analytic studies of fMRI activity during the performance of different language tasks are analyzed. Results. It was observed that two major brain systems can be distinguished: lexical/semantic, related with the Wernicke&#146;s area, that includes a core Wernicke&#146;s area (recognition of words) and an extended Wernicke&#146;s area (word associations); and grammatical system (language production and grammar) corresponding to the Broca&#146;s complex in the frontal lobe, and extending subcortically It is proposed that the insula plays a coordinating role in interconnecting these two brain language systems. Conclusions. Contemporary neuroimaging studies suggest that the brain language are is notoriously more extended than it was assumed one century ago based on clinical observations. As it was assumed during the 19th century, the insula seemingly plays a critical role in language  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ardilla, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roselli, Monica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernal, Byron</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Hacia finales del siglo xix y comienzos del siglo xx, y basándose en observaciones clínicas, se propuso que existe un &#145;área del lenguaje&#146; en el cerebro que corresponde, en general, a la región perisilviana del hemisferio izquierdo. Tal idea ha continuado existiendo desde entonces. Objetivo. Partiendo de los estudios contemporáneos de imágenes cerebrales, reanalizar la localización y extensión del área del lenguaje con relación a las diferentes áreas de Brodmann. Materiales y métodos. Utilizando la metodología conocida como metaanalytic connectivity modeling, se revisan varios estudios metaanalíticos en los cuales se analizan las imágenes de resonancia magnética funcional durante la realización de tareas lingüísticas. Resultados. Se encontró que existen dos sistemas lingüísticos diferentes en el cerebro: un sistema léxico/semántico, relacionado con el área de Wernicke, y que incluye un área de Wernicke central (reconocimiento de palabras) y un área de Wernicke extendida (asociaciones lingüísticas); y un sistema gramatical, dependiente del complejo de Broca (producción del lenguaje y gramática), en el lóbulo frontal, y que se extiende subcorticalmente. Se propone también que la ínsula desempeña un papel de coordinación de estos dos sistemas lingüísticos cerebrales. Conclusión. Los estudios contemporáneos de neuroimagen sugieren que el área del lenguaje en el cerebro es notoriamente más amplia de lo que se supuso hace un siglo basándose en observaciones clínicas. Tal como se consideraba durante el siglo xix, la ínsula parece desempeñar un papel crítico en el lenguaje (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;62(3): 97-106, 1 feb., 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148766</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Área cerebral del lenguaje: una reconsideración funcional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54668^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55521^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7980</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55525^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30967</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8212^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55525^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55521^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8212^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54668^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55525^s22071</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55521^s22071</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7981^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55525^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7981^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52519^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55521^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7981^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52519^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
