<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157492</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-2841</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">During the period from April to June 2016 there was an infectious outbreak by an enterovirus of the A71 serotype with neurological complications of the rhombencephalitis type among the pediatric population of Catalonia. EV infections are frequent and benign during infancy, with a wide and polymorphic clinical spectrum, from a mild cutaneous affectation, as an exanthema, to an affectation of the nervous system, with a predomination of the meningitis before the more serious and less frequent encephalitic conditions. The EV serotypes are divided in four species, named A, B, C and D, a classification which replaces the former, four group one: poliovirus, Coxsackievirus A and B and Echovirus, since they would be later labeled with consecutive numbers, starting with EV68. The enterovirus are widely spread across the globe, with an endemic and epidemic behavior. The EV71 has led to hand-foot-and-mouth disease outbreaks with grave neurological complications. The affectation of the hindbrain has been common in patients affected by the outbreak in Catalonia, where more than the 90% of these patients have shown a favorable clinical evolution. The main measures to avoid transmission of the viral infection are the main method of prevention (hand hygiene). The EV71 outbreaks in some countries, with serious complications and fatal outcomes, has led to the research of preventive vaccines. Two of these vaccines against the most frequent subgenotype occurring in China have been authorized in this country in 2016, but its peculiar nature limits its use to controlling outbreaks in specific geographic areas and with a single subgenotype (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moraga-Llop, Fernando A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Durante el periodo de abril a junio de 2016 se ha producido entre la población pediátrica de Cataluña un brote de infección por enterovirus (EV) del serotipo A71 con complicaciones neurológicas del tipo de la rombencefalitis. Las infecciones por EV son frecuentes y benignas en la infancia, con un espectro clínico amplio y polimorfo, desde una afectación leve cutánea, como enfermedad exantemática, hasta la del sistema nervioso con predominio de la meningitis frente a las graves e infrecuentes formas encefalíticas. Los serotipos de EV se dividen en cuatro especies, denominadas A, B, C y D; clasificación que ha sustituido a la original de cuatro grupos: poliovirus, Coxsackievirus A y B, y Echovirus, ya que después empezaron a designarse con números consecutivos desde el EV68. Las enterovirosis tienen una amplia distribución mundial, con un comportamiento endémico y epidémico. El EV-A71 ha dado lugar a brotes de enfermedad boca-mano-pie con complicaciones neurológicas graves. La afectación del rombencéfalo ha sido la característica de los enfermos del brote de Cataluña, en el que más del 90% de los pacientes han presentado una buena evolución clínica. Las medidas para evitar la transmisión de la infección son el principal método preventivo (higiene de manos). Los brotes por EV-A71 de algunos países, con complicaciones graves y con letalidad, ha llevado a que se investiguen vacunas preventivas. Dos de estas vacunas frente al subgenotipo más circulante en China se han autorizado en este país en 2016, pero sus peculiaridades limitan su uso al control de brotes en determinadas áreas geográficas y solo por un subgenotipo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. prev;22(3): 5-12, 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157492</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Brote de enfermedad neurológica aguda por enterovirus en niños en Cataluña, 2016</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8746^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8746^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2727^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36381^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36381^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35627^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27817^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27817^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35625^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35627^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35627^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35627^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19338^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35625^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19338^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
