<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148682</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-654X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Numb chin syndrome as a manifestation of jaw metastasis diagnosed in a bone scan</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In many cases, numb chin syndrome (NCS) may represent a banal pathology. However, as it can be associated with malignant processes, its presence should alert the clinician of a possible occult disease. In patients already diagnosed with cancer, it often represents an ominous sign that indicates poor prognosis, due to the rapid progress of the disease. The case is presented of a 62-year-old man diagnosed with synchronous lung and bladder cancer, who suddenly complained of numbness in the chin. The bone scan confirmed the suspicion of metastastic bone disease, and the patient died two months after the appearance of this sign (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sabaté-Llobera, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Rubio, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Noriega, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benítez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, GA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome del mentón entumecido (numb chin syndrome [NCS]) en muchos casos puede representar una patología banal, pero al poder asociarse con procesos malignos, su presencia debe alertar al clínico como posible manifestación de una enfermedad maligna oculta. En pacientes previamente diagnosticados de una neoplasia, representa a menudo un signo ominoso que indica mal pronóstico por el rápido progreso de la enfermedad. Se presenta el caso de un paciente de 62 años diagnosticado de cáncer de pulmón y de vejiga que aqueja sensación de «acorchamiento» en zona mentoniana. La gammagrafía ósea confirma la sospecha de enfermedad metastásica ósea falleciendo a los 2 meses de manifestarse este signo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. med. nucl. imagen mol. (Ed. impr.);35(1): 34-37, ene.-feb. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148682</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hipoestesia mentoniana como manifestación de metástasis mandibular diagnosticada en la gammagrafía ósea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24895^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7165^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24338^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24895^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24235^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29338^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29338^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7165^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24235^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9871^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
