<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110867</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The majority of healthcare associated infections are endemic, but outbreaks or epidemic infections also occur. The most frequent nosocomial endemic infections are catheter associated bacteremia, ventilator-associated pneumonia, surgical site infections and urinary catheter associated infections. These are conditions with a significant healthcare burden. Infection control measures are the mainstay for reducing their frequency and health impact. Other nosocomial infections occur in epidemic outbreaks, with potential and various negative consequences. A well conducted outbreak investigation can achieve good control at an early stage of the development of an outbreak. This research is divided into several stages that facilitate monitoring the development of the work in an orderly and efficiently manner. It also includes some guidelines for writing reports and scientific papers concerning outbreaks (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Horcajada, Juan Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padilla, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La mayoría de las infecciones que ocurren en el ámbito sanitario son endémicas, pero también se producen brotes o infecciones epidémicas. Las infecciones nosocomiales endémicas más frecuentes son la bacteriemia relacionada con catéter, la neumonía asociada a ventilación mecánica, la infección de la herida quirúrgica y la infección urinaria asociada a catéter vesical. Son procesos con un gran peso asistencial. Las medidas de control de infecciones son fundamentales para reducir su frecuencia e impacto sanitario. Otras infecciones nosocomiales se producen en forma de brotes epidémicos, con potenciales y diversas consecuencias negativas. Una investigación de brotes bien realizada puede lograr controlar de forma precoz el desarrollo de un brote. Esta investigación se divide en diversas etapas, cuyo seguimiento facilita la consecución del trabajo de manera ordenada y eficaz. Así mismo, existen guías orientativas para la redacción de informes y artículos científicos relativos a brotes epidémicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;31(3): 181-186, mar. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110867</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Endemia y epidemia. Investigación de un brote epidémico nosocomial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54398^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53052^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28589^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33154^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
