<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132196</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Motivational factors related to aggression within martial arts context</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study was aimed at testing a meditational model in which goal orientation, self-determined motivation, and sportspersonship were predictive factors of aggressiveness. Italian martial artists (N = 366; Mage = 29.53, SD = 9.107; Men = 325, Female = 41) were asked to fill in a questionnaire assessing sport orientation, sport motivation, sportspersonship, and aggressiveness. The path analysis supported the hypothesized model: self-determined motivation mediates the relationship between motivational orientations and sportspersonhip, which in turn mediates the relationship between motivation and aggressiveness. The results suggest considering these motivational factors in order to plan interventions to prevent aggressiveness among athletes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palo, Valeria de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monacis, Lucia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sinatra, Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La finalidad del trabajo fue analizar un modelo de mediación en donde la orientación motivacional, la motivación autodeterminada y la deportividad eran factores predictivos de la agresividad. Practicantes de artes marciales italianos (N = 366; Medad = 29.53 años, DE = 9.107; Hombres = 325, Mujeres = 41) completaron un cuestionario para medir la orientación motivacional, la motivación autodeterminada, la deportividad y la agresividad. El path analysis confirmó el modelo hipotetizado: la motivación autodeterminada media la relación entre la orientación motivacional y deportivad y esta última media la relación entre la motivación y la agresividad. Los resultados sugieren que se debería intervenir sobre los factores motivacionales para prevenir la agresividad entre los atletas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;24(1): 163-169, 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132196</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores motivacionales relacionados con la agresividad en las artes marciales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29036^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29036^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29036^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29036^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
