<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-63166</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: Vesicoureteral reflux is a pathologic entity with different forms of therapeutic management, one of which is endoscopic injection of various materials. We show some histological changes produced by these materials in the bladder wall. Methods: We study three samples of intravesical ureter from three children suffering vesicoureteral reflux. The ureters were obtained during ureteral reimplantation surgery. Results: We show the changes found with various materials under study (polytetrafluorethylene , polydimethylsiloxane, hyaluronic acid and dextranomer copolimer) observing less conjunctive tissue with the two latter and with the more encapsulated hyaluronic acid - dextranomer copolimer. Conclusions: Migrations and granulomas are described with various materials and we ascertained the presence of foreign body reaction and fibrosis within the bladder wall. More studies in human beings are required to determine the best product for endoscopic injection (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Díaz, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Vázquez, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aransay Bramtot, Adolfo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Fraile, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabezalí Barbancho, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejedor Sánchez, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El reflujo vesicoureteral es una patología con diferentes formas de manejo terapéutico, una de las cuales es la inyección vía endoscópica de diferentes materiales. Mostramos algunos cambios histológicos que producen estos materiales en la pared vesical. Métodos: Estudiamos 3 muestras de uréter intravesical en 3 niños afectos de reflujo vesicoureteral. Las muestras se obtuvieron durante la reimplantación de los uréteres, extirpando la porción más distal de los uréteres. Resultados: Mostramos los cambios encontrados con los diferentes materiales estudiados (politetrafluoroetileno, polidimetilsiloxano, copolímero de dextranómero y ácido hialurónico) observando una menor formación de tejido conjuntivo con los 2 últimos. Conclusiones: Se describen migraciones y granulomas con diferentes materiales y se constata la reacción de cuerpo extraño y fibrosis en la pared vesical. Son necesarios más estudios en humanos para determinar el mejor producto de inyección endoscópica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;61(2): 112-116, mar. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-63166</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d15123^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3258^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15123^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14912^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11578^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12149^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14912^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15123^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14912^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6972^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
