<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89191</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">HPV Vaccines, up to date</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">HPV-16 and HPV-18 are responsible for approximately 54% and 17% of invasive cervical cancer cases worldwide, respectively, a major cause of cancer death among women. These types are divided into high-risk types and low-risk types. Although most women clear the infection within a few months, persistent oncogenic HPV infection has been confirmed as one key determinant in the development of premalignant lesions and cervical cancer. Two prophylactic human papillomavirus vaccines have been licenced. Both are highly immunogenic, produced outstanding  long-term efficacy and have showed evidence of cross-protection against other important oncogenic HPV. These vaccines are generally well tolerated and injection-site reactions have been the most common vaccine-related adverse event reported (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Sicilia López, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los papilomavirus humanos 16 y 18 se asocian con cerca del 54% y 17%, respectivamente, de cánceres invasores de cérvix en todo el mundo, una de las principales causas de muerte por cáncer en mujeres. Se diferencian tipos de alto y bajo riesgo oncogénico. Aunque la mayoría de las mujeres aclaran la infección en unos meses, cuando persiste es causa obligada para el desarrollo de lesiones premalignas y cáncer de cuello uterino.  Se han autorizado dos vacunas: Gardasil® (Sanofi Pasteur MSD) y Cervarix® (GlaxoSmithKline), preventivas de la infección. Ambas son muy inmunógenas, eficaces a largo plazo y han demostrado protección cruzada frente a otros tipos oncogénicos principales. Son vacunas bien toleradas y su reactogenicidad es fundamentalmente local, en el sitio de inyección (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;19(1): 12-24, feb. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89191</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actualización en vacunas VPH</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35997^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24326^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2623^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10403^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
