<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-67965</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1473</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The application of neuro-modulation techniques in general is currently gaining acceptance in various aspects of medicine. Neuro-modulation is defined as: &#147;Terapeutical interventions using implantable devices to modify the functioning of central, peripheral and and autonomic nervosus sysmtems&#148;. Following lumbar discsurgery, or lumbar spine surgery in general, several chronic pain syndromes can result, either in the lumbar region and/or in the lower limbs. The current status is for the application of surgery to the degenerative spine(degenerative disc disease and lumbar stenosis) for the relief of chronic pain. A review of the methodology of evidence based medicine, show that the instrumented and fusion techniques are not the answerd despite 20years of the use of these techniques following failure of surgery for the relief of back pain syndrome. Neuromodulation techniques represent a step in the right direction for the management of these chronic painsyndromes. Frecuently they enable the resolution of chronic pain following spine surgery without having to resort to repeat surgery. We describe here the different neuro-modulation techniques (spinal cord stimulation, spinal drug infusions) which can be used in the case of back surgery failure, and we describe technical aspects and &#147;tricks of the trade&#148; for the correct implantation of the devices used in techniques. Neuro-modulation techniques are applied to the management of chronic pain following disc surgery and represent a valid alternative to repeat surgery and/or arthrodesis (instrumented or not). Neurosurgeons are again called to play active roles in the field of neuro-modulation for the treatment of pain as well as in the field of neuro-modulation of abnormal movements disorders, for psychosurgery and the revovery of neurological functions</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Robaina Padrón, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La aplicación de las técnicas de neuromodulación avanza rápidamente en los distintos aspectos de la medicina actual. La neuromodulación se define como: &#147;la realización de intervenciones terapéuticas mediante aparatos implantables para modificar la función del sistema nervioso central, periférico o autonómico&#148;. Tras la cirugía discal y vertebral en general, se pueden generar síndromes dolorosos persistentes tanto a nivel axial como distal en las extremidades inferiores. La situación actual de la cirugía de la columna vertebral degenerativa en relación al alivio del dolor lumbar crónico, por enfermedad degenerativa discal y estenosis de canal, empleando los métodos de la medicina basada en la evidencia, concluyen, que la vía instrumentista y fijadora no es precisamente la ideal después de 20años de utilización de las mismas. Las técnicas de neuromodulación representan un escalón superior en el algoritmo de manejo de estos síndromes dolorosos, ya que permiten con mayor frecuencia solventar muchos casos de dolor persistente tras la cirugía sin la necesidad de realizar otra nueva cirugía. Se describen las técnicas de neuromodulación (estimulación medular e infusión espinal de medicamentos) aplicables al síndrome postlaminectomía lumbar y se detallan los aspectos técnicos para la realización de las mismas. Las técnicas de neuromodulación aplicadas al manejo del dolor postcirugía discal representan una alternativa válida en comparación con la nueva cirugía o la artrodesis. Los neurocirujanos estamos llamados de nuevo a participar activamente en el campo de la neuromodulación para el alivio del dolor crónico, el de los movimientos anormales, la psicocirugía y el restablecimiento de las funciones neurológicas perdidas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurocirugia (Astur);19(1): 35-44, ene.-feb. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-67965</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19209^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32115^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13499^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7974^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4630^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4639^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200802</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
