<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124553</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Exposure pathways to pesticides in schoolchildren in the Province of Talca, Chile</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To describe pesticide concentrations in distinct environmental matrices at two time points (low and high seasons in local agricultural production) and to estimate the association between the presence of pesticide residues in matrices and the use of pesticides in the home with the sociodemographic variables of schoolchildren in the Province of Talca, Chile. Methods A cross-sectional study was conducted in 190 schoolchildren. Families were surveyed about their children's vegetable consumption in school and at home, the use of pesticides in the home, and other sociodemographic variables. Additionally, we measured pesticide residues in vegetables and water consumed by the schoolchildren and in the soil of 14 schools. Results At both time points, the vegetable matrix had the highest pesticide concentration, both in urban and rural schoolchildren. The most common pesticide residues in vegetables were chlorpyrifos, diphenylamine, pyrimethanil, and thiabendazole. In the home, pyrethroid and organophosphate pesticides were mainly used in summer. Dangerous pesticide residues such as azinphos methyl and dimethoate were found in vegetables consumed by the children in schools and households, and organochlorines were found in the soil in some schools. Conclusions Pesticide exposure should be limited and the health effects related to pesticide exposure should be assessed in the school population (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lucero, Boris</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pía Muñoz, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Quezada, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Describir la concentración de plaguicidas en diferentes matrices ambientales en dos períodos de tiempo (baja y alta producción agrícola local) y estimar la asociación entre la presencia de residuos de plaguicidas en las matrices y su uso en el hogar con variables sociodemográficas de escolares de la Provincia de Talca. Métodos Estudio de diseño transversal en 190 escolares. Se encuestó a las familias para conocer el consumo de vegetales de los escolares en la escuela y en el hogar, el uso de plaguicidas en el hogar y otras variables sociodemográficas. También se midieron los residuos de plaguicidas en vegetales y agua consumidos por los escolares y en el suelo de 14 escuelas. Resultados La matriz vegetal presenta la mayor concentración de residuos en ambos períodos de tiempo, tanto en escolares urbanos como rurales. Los residuos de plaguicidas más frecuentes en los vegetales fueron clorpirifos, difenilamina, pirimetanil y tiabendazol. En los hogares se usan principalmente piretroides y organofosforados en la época de verano. Se encontraron residuos de plaguicidas peligrosos, como azinfos metil y dimetoato, en vegetales consumidos por los escolares en las escuelas y hogares, y de organoclorados en el suelo de algunas escuelas. Conclusiones Se sugiere elaborar propuestas de prevención y control de la exposición a plaguicidas en la población escolar, y evaluar los efectos en la salud de los escolares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;28(3): 190-195, mayo-jun. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124553</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vías de exposición a plaguicidas en escolares de la Provincia de Talca, Chile</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5795^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12159^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2722</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51635^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10121^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4862^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32531</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10764^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
