<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042701</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Suspiction of metastases in laryngeal carcinomas</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To look for models predicting metastasis    in laryngeal/hypopharyngeal carcinomas. Design: Prospective    study. Patients: Sixty patients bearing laryngeal    squamous cell carcinoma who were treated with curative    purposes were followed prospectively with at least 10-year    follow-up. Parameters: Clínical (Staging, site, age, alcohol    and smoking intake, surgery on the primary tumor, neck    surgery) and pathological (size, number of metastatic    lymph nodes, T and N staging, degree of differentiation,    Jakobsson's and Glanz's scoríng of malignancy, both scores    in biopsies and surgical specimens) parameters were recorded    in each case. Methods: A multivariate analysis was performed    to find out those parameters independently related    to presence of metastases. Results: The prospective study    rendered tumor burden and Glanz's scoring from biopsies    to be independently related with the presence of metastases.    Conclusions: Malignancy grading systems must be included    in laryngeal carcinoma patients' planning of neck    treatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-Pérez, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Moles, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado-Rodríguez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esteban, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benaixa, JP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Ávila, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solano, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Investigar la existencia de modelos de    predicción de la existencia de metástasis cervicales en el    cáncer de laringe e hipofaringe. Diseño: Estudio prospectivo.    Pacientes: 60 pacientes afectos de carcinoma epidermoide de    laringe intervenidos con finalidad curativa, seguidos de forma    prospectiva con un seguimiento mínimo de 10 años. Parámetros:    En todos los casos se registraron diversos parámetros    clínicos (localización del tumor, estadios T, N, edad del    paciente, ingesta de alcohol y tabaco, tipo de intervención    sobre tumor primitivo y sobre cuello) y anatomopatológicos    (tamaño del tumor, número de metástasis, estadios T y N    patológicos, grado de malignidad según la OMS, puntuaciones    según los sistemas de Jakobsson y Glanz) tanto en la    biopsia como en la pieza definitiva. Métodos: Estudio estadístico    multivariable para detectar aquéllas que de forma    independiente se encontraban relacionadas con la presencia    de metástasis ganglionares. Resultados: El diámetro máximo    del tumor y la puntuación de la malignidad según el sistema    de Glanz en biopsias mostraron ser factores independientes    relacionados con la existencia de metástasis. Conclusiones:    La graduación histopatológica de la malignidad    debería incluirse en la planificación del tratamiento cervical    del paciente afecto de cáncer de laringe</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;56(10): 477-481, dic. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042701</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Predicción de la capacidad metastásica del cáncer de laringe: implicaciones clínicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28150^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2337^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28150^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2337^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
