<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128101</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The value of genetic and neuroimaging studies in the differential diagosis of parkinson´s disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Parkinson&#146;s disease (PD) is usually diagnosed on the basis of clinical criteria. Today there are genetic and neuroimaging tests that can make a valuable contribution to the study of this disease. Aims. To review the recent advances in genetic studies and in neuroimaging techniques applied to PD, as well as looking at their shortcomings, and to analyse the reasons for conducting such tests and to discuss their importance in everyday clinical practice, including a series of reflections on ethical issues. Development. The list of genetic disorders associated with PD is continually being extended and reviewed, and pathological alterations have been defined in at least 10 genes. The most frequent mutations in our setting are to be found in the parkin gene (PARK2) and in the LRKK2 gene (PARK8). These mutations have a penetrance that is not very high and their clinical expression is variable. Images obtained by nuclear resonance, single-photon emission tomography, positron emission tomography or by cranial sonography provide data that can help in the diagnosis of PD and to differentiate it from other diseases. None of the techniques is wholly specific, however, and there are clinico-radiological disagreements. Conclusions. The detection of mutations does not allow a clear prognostic differentiation or a distinct therapeutic attitude to be established. The value of neuroimaging techniques in very early phases and in dubious cases is still not altogether clear. Whether establishing a diagnosis in very early phases currently offers the patient any benefits is subject to debate. It would be advisable to attempt to distinguish between tests that are carried out for clinical reasons and those which are conducted for research purposes so as to be able to proceed in the most suitable manner (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rojo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cobella, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El diagnóstico de la enfermedad de Parkinson (EP) se realiza habitualmente sobre la base de criterios clínicos. Actualmente existen pruebas genéticas y de neuroimagen que pueden contribuir al estudio de esta enfermedad. Objetivos. Revisar los avances recientes en estudios genéticos y en técnicas de neuroimagen aplicadas en EP, así como sus limitaciones, analizar los motivos de realización de dichas pruebas y discutir su trascendencia en la práctica clínica habitual, incluyendo una serie de reflexiones éticas. Desarrollo. El listado de alteraciones genéticas asociadas a EP se encuentra en ampliación y revisión continua, y se han definido ya al menos alteraciones patogénicas en 10 genes. Las mutaciones más frecuentes en nuestro medio se encuentran en el gen parkina (PARK2) y en el gen LRKK2 (PARK8). Son mutaciones con penetrancia no elevada y de expresión clínica variable. Imágenes obtenidas por resonancia magnética, tomografía computarizada por emisión de fotón simple, tomografía por emisión de positrones o mediante ecografía craneal aportan datos que pueden ayudar al diagnóstico de la EP y a la  diferenciación de otras enfermedades, pero ninguna técnica es totalmente específica y existen discordancias clinicorradiológicas. Conclusiones. La detección de mutaciones no permite establecer una clara diferenciación pronóstica ni una distinta actitud terapéutica. Aún no esta claramente establecido el valor de las técnicas de neuroimagen en fases muy precoces y en casos dudosos. Se debate el hecho de que establecer un diagnóstico en fases muy precoces consiga en la actualidad algún beneficio para el paciente. Convendría intentar diferenciar qué pruebas se realizan con propósito clínico y cuáles con fines investigadores para poder proceder de la manera más adecuada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;48(9): 482-488, mayo 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128101</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de los estudios genéticos y de neuroimagen en el diagnóstico diferencial de la enfermedad de Parkinson</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28087^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24895^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54668^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200905</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
