<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59672</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adaptation of complex physiotherapy in a congenital lymphedema of the lower limb in an infant. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The existence of any lymphatic failure regardless of its etiology leads to a defective resorption of protein macromolecules. Lymphedema is defined as the accumulation of high-protein fluid in the interstitial spaces due to the above-mentioned failure. It is found in both the supraaponeurotic and subcutaneous tissue.Lymphedema is generally divided into two types: primary and secondary. Primary lymphedema is a congenital condition related to hypoplasia or hypogenesis in the lymphatic system. Scarceness or even absence and/or dysfunction of the lymphatic system explain this condition.Several cases of lymphedema in infants have been seen in our Department in a short period of time. Because of the lack of literature concerning this issue, we have considered the development of a treatment protocol because maneuvers and compression garments need to be modified due to the special characteristics of these patients.This article aims to share our experience concerning the treatment of congenital lymphedema in infants(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Latorre González, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez De Obanos Frieros, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elcuaz Barasoain, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Belinchón Heras, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La insuficiencia linfática, cualquiera sea su etiología, conduce a un defecto de la reabsorción de las macromoléculas proteínicas tisulares. El linfedema es una acumulación de líquido rico en proteínas en los espacios intersticiales como resultado de dicha insuficiencia. Está presente en el tejido subcutáneo y supraaponeurótico.Los lifedemas se clasifican en primarios y secundarios. El linfedema primario es una enfermedad congénita relacionada con hipogenesia o hipoplasia del sistema linfático. La escasez o ausencia de vasos linfáticos y/o su mal funcionamiento explican esta enfermedad.En poco tiempo han llegado a nuestro servicio varios casos de linfedema en lactantes y ante la aparente ausencia de bibliografía con que nos hemos encontrado, nos parece interesante elaborar un protocolo de tratamiento, ya que las características especiales del paciente hacen que tanto las maniobras como el vendaje compresivo deban ser modificados.El objetivo de este artículo es transmitir nuestra experiencia en el tratamiento del linfedema congénito de extremidad inferior en lactantes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);31(1): 36-39, ene.-feb. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59672</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación de la terapia física compleja en un linfedema congénito de extremidad inferior en un lactante. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27990^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1480^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8386^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27990^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8386^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8386^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36319^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
