<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93273</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Resuscitation in shock. Volume replacement in shock</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Shock represents a multifactorial syndrome (secondary to an evident condition), which is life threatening both through inadequateO2 supply at tissular, cellular and subcellular level and through the response it induces in the patient. It is characterised by a constellation of symptoms and signs derived from inadequate O2 transport and from the generated tissue ischaemia. The causes of shock may be classed into vasodilatory, hypovolaemic and cardiogenic ones. Volume replacement during shock will depend on the cause responsible for the situation, and thus an adequate diagnostic approach is required. The liquids to be infused may be divided into the following groups: isotonic crystalloid solutions, hypertonic solutions, colloid solutions (mainly gelatins, dextranes and starches, as synthetic colloids, and albumin as a naturalone), haemoderivates, and alternative synthetic haemoglobin solutions. Volume replacement in shock is, with the exception of cardiogenic shock with increased filling pressures, the first and most effective measure for improving microcirculation and oxygen transport. In septic and anaphylactic shock with a marked vasodilation component volume replacement should be generous, with assessment of the extravascular and interstitial compartment expansion with colloids/crystalloids. In haemorrhagicshock, before the bleeding is brought under control, volume replacement should be limited and the patient should be stratified. In the pre-hospital environment and in the early phases, hypertonic saline solution might be a good alternative. The optimum fluid to be used has not been determined yet, but in the near/immediate future haemoglobin substitutes will doubtlessly play a fundamental role (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alted López, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toral Vázquez, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Martínez, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El shock representa un síndrome multifactorial (secundario a una patología evidente) que compromete la vida del paciente por inadecuado aporte de O2 a nivel tisular, celular y subcelular, así como por la respuesta que genera en el huésped. Se caracteriza por un conjunto de signos y síntomas propios del inadecuado transporte deO2 y de la hipoxia tisular generada. Las causas del shock se pueden clasificar en vasodilatadoras, hipovolémias y cardiogénicas. La reposición de volumen durante el estado de shock va a depender de la causa responsable del mismo, motivo por el que es necesario una adecuada aproximación diagnóstica. Los líquidos a infundir se pueden resumir en los siguientes grupos: Soluciones cristaloides isotónicas, soluciones hipertónicas, soluciones coloides, fundamentalmente gelatinas, dextranos y almidones, como coloides sintéticos, y albúmina como coloide natural, hemoderivados y soluciones alternativas de hemoglobinassintéticas. La reposición de volumen en el shock es, salvo en el shock cardiogénico con presiones de llenado elevadas, la primeramedida y más eficaz para mejorar la micro circulación y el transporte de oxígeno. En el shock séptico y anafiláctico con importante componente de vasodilatación debe ser generoso en su utilización, valorándola expansión del espacio intravascular e intersticial con coloides/cristaloides. En el shock hemorrágico y antes de controlar el sangrado se debe limitar el volumen y estratificar el paciente. En el medio prehospitalario y en fases iniciales puede ser una buena alternativa el salino hipertónico. El líquido óptimo no está determinado, pero en un futuro inmediato los sustitutos de la hemoglobina tendrán un papel fundamental (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);16(3): s20-s27, jun. 2004. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93273</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resucitación en pacientes con shock. Reposición de volumen en el shock</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d721^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13147^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13149^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13150^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12569^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5574^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13148^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3133^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
