<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88356</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Benefits of capillary glucose monitoring in patients with type 1 and type 2 diabetes treated with insulin</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The introduction of self-monitoring of blood glucose (SMBG) revolutionizeddiabetes therapy at the end of 70s. SMBG provides additional information tothat supplied by HbA1c for the management of patients with diabetes. Further,in those patients treated with insulin, either with type 1 or type 2 diabetes, it isconsidered an essential part of the treatment. Frequent SMBG is correlatedwith an improvement of metabolic control. However, the optimal number ofmeasurements of SMBG is not defined and it has been pointed out even potentialdisadvantages associated with frequent SMBG. In the present article wereview the existing scientific evidences and we propose an algorithm for SMBGin patients with type 1 and type 2 diabetes treated with insulin(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Blanco, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Pérez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La introducción de la monitorización de la glucemia capilar por el propio pacienterevolucionó el tratamiento de la diabetes mellitus (DM) a finales de losaños setenta. Aporta información complementaria a la de la hemoglobina glucosiladapara el manejo de los pacientes diabéticos y, en los pacientes tratadoscon insulina, tanto con DM tipo 1 (DM1) como tipo 2 (DM2), se considerauna parte esencial del tratamiento. La monitorización frecuente de laglucemia se correlaciona con una mejora del control metabólico. Sin embargo,el número óptimo de determinaciones de automonitorización no está bien definido,y hasta se han señalado potenciales desventajas asociadas a esta actuación.En el presente artículo revisamos las evidencias científicas existentesy proponemos un esquema para la automonitorización de la glucemia capilaren los pacientes con DM1 y DM2 tratados con insulina(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;26(supl.1): s5-s8, abr. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88356</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Beneficios de la monitorización de la glucemia en pacientes con diabetes mellitus tipo 1 y tipo 2 en tratamiento con insulina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22523^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
