<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159879</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The activity of rheumatology nurses in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Describe and analyze nursing activity in rheumatology. Material and methods. A cross-sectional study was performed in Spanish rheumatology departments. Results were based on surveys administered to rheumatology nurses. We included variables on socio-demographics, the setting and available resources, and the activities they carried out. Each activity was compared in terms of workplace, available resources and dedication exclusively to one field. Results. Sixty-seven surveys were collected from 57 hospitals in 17 Spanish autonomous communities. 97% of the nurses were women, with an average age of 48.9 years and an average nursing experience of 6 years. 56% of the professionals had gained their experience in outpatient clinics, 35% in day hospitals and 9% in inpatient and primary care. As for the availability of resources, 59% had their own office, 77.3% had a phone listing and 60% scheduled and conducted patient visits. Of the 19 activities included, those performed by the highest number of nurses were managing, monitoring and coordinating the use of biological drugs (90.9%), therapy monitoring (89.4%) and training patients in self-medication (89.4%). The activity in which nurses most frequently collaborated with physicians was the administration of local injections (51.5%). Other activities were teaching (50%) and research (78.8%) in their departments and studies in the nursing field (51.5%). Work in outpatient clinics versus day hospitals showed statistically significant differences for health education, nutrition, splinting and bandaging, and collaboration in ultrasound studies. Conclusion. These professionals performed a greater number of activities when they worked in outpatient clinics, had their own office and worked exclusively in rheumatology (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Paytubí Garí, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moragues Pastora, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Sánchez, Susan P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rusiñol Badals, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laiz Alonso, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padró Blanch, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer y analizar la actividad de la enfermería de reumatología en nuestro medio. Material y métodos. Se realizó un estudio transversal en servicios de reumatología de todo el país. Se utilizaron encuestas dirigidas a enfermería que incluyeron variables sociodemográficas, de medios estructurales y de actividad realizada por enfermería. Cada actividad fue comparada en función del lugar de trabajo, disponibilidad de medios y exclusividad laboral. Resultados. Se analizaron 67 encuestas, de 57 hospitales y 17 comunidades autónomas. Participaron un 97% de mujeres con una edad y experiencia laboral media de 48,9 y 6 años, respectivamente. El 56% trabajaron en consultas externas, el 35% en hospitales de día y el 9% en hospitalización y atención primaria. En cuanto a los medios: el 59% tenía despacho, el 77,3% agenda telefónica y el 60% agenda propia. Respecto a las actividades, el mayor número de profesionales realizó: monitorización de biológicos el 90,9%, seguimiento de terapias el 89,4% y entrenamiento en la autoadministración el 89,4%. La actividad en colaboración más frecuente fueron las infiltraciones, el 51,5%. Las actividades en docencia fueron el 50% y las de investigación dentro del servicio o con estudios en el área de enfermería el 78,8 y 51,5% respectivamente. Trabajar en consultas externas respecto a hospital de día, disponer al menos de despacho propio y realizar la jornada laboral con exclusividad en reumatología mostró diferencias significativas en distintas actividades. Conclusiones. El número de actividades realizadas por estos profesionales demostró ser mayor cuando el trabajo se realizó en la consulta externa, con despacho propio y exclusividad en reumatología (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);13(1): 4-9, ene.-feb. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159879</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actividad de la enfermera de reumatología en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28302^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22668^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22668^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36313^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12630^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12630^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28302^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
