<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-168130</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-0740</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of maternal stress during pregnancy on cognitive development of children: a review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the relationship between exposure to high levels of stress during pregnancy and impaired cognitive development of future children. Methodology: A review was made; in the databases Scopus, PubMed and Web of Science we introduced the terms 'pregnancy', 'cortisol', 'stress', 'infant', 'child', and 'cognitive development'. Methodological quality was assessed through the methodological checklist of the Scottish Intercollegiate Guidelines Network. Results: A total of 766 items, of which 53 were adequate to meet our goal, was obtained; this way, the final selection was reduced to 25 papers. Within the four age groups assessed (ranging from 7 months to 17 years), we find studies that found correlation between stress and/or anxiety with lower scores on tests of cognitive development, although the period in which this correlation is more evident is from 13 months to 9 years; any kind of stress (whether or not specifically related to pregnancy), at any time during pregnancy can have undesirable cognitive effects at language, working memory, psychomotor development, perceptual reasoning and processing speed, among other possible consequences. Conclusions: An excess of maternal stress during pregnancy can lead to undesirable consequences at cognitive level for the future child. We recommend that midwives become an active part in the diagnosis of stress in pregnancy, as well as taking action in women with high stress levels in order to prevent fetal impairment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santiago-Vasco, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Béjar-Poveda, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Identificar la relación existente entre la exposición a niveles elevados de estrés durante el embarazo y la alteración del desarrollo cognitivo de los futuros hijos. Metodología: Se realizó una revisión de las bases de datos Scopus, PubMed y Web of Science, introduciendo los términos «pregnancy», «cortisol», «stress», «infant», «child» y «cognitive development». Se valoró la calidad metodológica de los artículos a través de la lista de revisión metodológica del Scottish Intercollegiate Guidelines Network. Resultados: Se obtuvo un total de 766 artículos, de los que 53 cumplían el objetivo de estudio, quedando reducidos finalmente a 25. En los cuatro grupos de edad analizados (que abarcaron desde los 7 meses hasta los 17 años) se hallaron estudios que presentaban una correlación positiva entre el estrés y/o la ansiedad con los resultados más bajos en el test de valoración del desarrollo cognitivo (aunque el periodo de edad en que esta correlación era más evidente fue el de los 13 meses a los 9 años), cualquier tipo de estrés (estuviera o no relacionado específicamente con el embarazo) y que en cualquier momento de la gestación podrían aparecer en los futuros hijos efectos perjudiciales en el lenguaje, la memoria de trabajo, el desarrollo psicomotor, el razonamiento perceptivo y la velocidad de procesamiento, entre otras posibles consecuencias. Conclusiones: Un exceso de estrés materno durante el embarazo puede tener consecuencias cognitivas negativas para el futuro hijo. Recomendamos que la matrona tome parte activa en el diagnóstico de estrés durante el embarazo, así como en la adopción de medidas para las mujeres con elevados niveles de estrés, con el fin de prevenir la afectación fetal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Matronas prof;18(3): 115-122, 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-168130</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia del estrés materno durante el embarazo en el desarrollo cognitivo del niño: una revisión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2717</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
