<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102577</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8799</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Current concepts of the tendon injury. Therapeutic criteria</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The injury of the tendon is frequent when practicing sports; it produces damages in the tendon´s structure sometimes the treatment becoming defective in this one, producing a tendinopathy. Not yet known exactly tendon biology and treatment of his injuries remains controversial. Current knowledge suggests that the tendon is a dynamic structure that is in continuous process of regeneration/ degradation. Damaging agents, alter this balance causing the injury. In this paper, some harmful agents, level of activity and its mechanism of action. Their knowledge is essential to settle the therapeutic approach to aplied appropriate treatment to each tendon injury (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guillén Vicente, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillén García, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Jiménez, Ascensión</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padrón, Mario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Jaen, Tomás F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La lesión del tendón es frecuente en la practica deportiva, produce daño en la estructura del tendón cuya reparación en algunos casos es defectuosa, produciéndose una tendinopatía. Todavía no se conoce con exactitud la biología del tendón y el tratamiento de sus lesiones sigue siendo controvertido. Los conocimientos actuales hacen pensar que el tendón es una estructura dinámica que está en un proceso continuo de regeneración/ degradación. Los agentes lesivos, alteran este equilibrio produciendo la lesión .En este trabajo exponemos algunos agentes lesivos, nivel de actuación y su mecanismo de acción. Su conocimiento se hace imprescindible para asentar el criterio terapeútico afín de aplicar el tratamiento adecuado a cada lesión tendinosa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. med. deporte;27(140): 477-489, nov.-dic. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102577</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conceptos actuales de la lesión tendinosa. Criterios terapéuticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d906^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14086^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1273^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38811^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14086^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
