<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109623</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Identification of clinical features and laboratory abnormalities associated with the development of vertebral fractures in women with postmenopausal osteoporosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Vertebral fractures (VF) are a major risk factor for the development of furtherfractures. Therefore, it is important to identify clinical risk factors and laboratory abnormalities relatedto VF. We aimed to analyse clinical and biochemical alterations related to the presence of radiological VFin postmenopausal women with osteoporosis. Patients and methods: Two-hundred and four postmenopausal women with osteoporosis (aged 64,9 [10]years) who were referred to an outpatient Rheumatology Unit were prospectively included. Bonemineral density (BMD), spine X-ray, and laboratory tests were performed in all participants beforet reatment. Results: Twenty-eight per cent of patients had VF. Comparing women with and without VF, those with fractures were older (71.9 [10] vs 61.8 [8,6], P &lt; .001), had lower stature (152 [7.2] vs 155 [6.2], P = .01), lower total hip T-score values (-2.2 [0,9] vs -1.9 [0.8], P = .041), higher prevalence of non-VF (38 vs 30%,P = .04) and a higher prevalence of low serum 25(OH)D levels (69 vs 53%, P &lt; .05). In logistic regression analysis, age and BMD at the total hip were independent predictors of VF. Patients over 65 presented ahigher frequency of VF (47 vs 12%, P &lt; .0001). In addition, a T-score lower than -2,5 at the total hip was associated with an increased risk of VF (OR 2.5; 95% CI 1.2-4.9).Conclusions: Over the age of 65 nearly half of the postmenopausal women with osteoporosis have VF and a higher prevalence of low 25(OH)D serum measurements. Spinal X-ray and 25(OH)D serum measurements are especially indicated in this group of women since it in&amp;#64258;uences the therapeutic approach (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Surís, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guañabens, Núria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albaladejo, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monegal, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cerdà, Dacia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peris, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Las fracturas vertebrales (FV) son un factor de riesgo mayor para desarrollar nuevas fracturas. Es importante identificar las características clínicas y las alteraciones en las pruebas de laboratorio relacionadas con su desarrollo. El objetivo de este estudio fue analizar las características clínicas y alteraciones analíticas relacionadas con la presencia de FV radiológicas en mujeres posmenopáusicas con osteoporosis. Pacientes y método. En 204 mujeres (edad media [DE] de 64,9 [10] años) referidas a una consulta de Reumatología se determinaron pruebas bioquímicas y hormonales del metabolismo mineral, densidad mineral ósea (DMO) y radiografías de columna dorso lumbar. Resultados: Un 28% tenían FV. Al comparar las mujeres con y sin FV, aquellas con FV eran de mayor edad (media de 71,9 [10] frente a 61,8 [6,8] años, p&lt;0,001), menor estatura (media de 152 [2,7] frente a 155 [2,6] cm, p=0,01), menor DMO en fémur total (media de puntuación en la escala T de -2,2 [0,91] frente a -1,9 [0,8], p=0,041), mayor prevalencia de fracturas no vertebrales (38 frente a 30%, p=0,04) y de valores bajos de 25-hidroxivitamina D (25-OH-D) (69 frente a 53%, p&lt;0,05). En el análisis de regresión logística, la edad y la DMO en fémur total fueron factores predictores independientes para FV. Las pacientes mayores de 65 años presentaron una mayor frecuencia de FV (47 frente a 12%, p&lt;0,0001). Además, una puntuación en la escala T menor de -2,5 en fémur total se asoció con un incremento de riesgo de FV (odds ratio 2,5; intervalo de confianza del 95% 1,2-4,9). Conclusiones: A partir de los 65 años casi la mitad de las mujeres posmenopáusicas con osteoporosis referidas a una consulta especializada tienen FV y la mayoría de ellas presentan un déficit de vitamina D. En este grupo de pacientes es aconsejable realizar una radiografía de columna y determinar los valores séricos de 25-OH-D, ya que van a determinar la actitud terapéutica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);139(14): 626-630, dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109623</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Identificación de las características clínicas y alteraciones analíticas asociadas a la fractura vertebral en mujeres con osteoporosis posmenopáusica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29128^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15210^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54019^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
