<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130125</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">English words and expressions that can mislead or be difficult to translate in clinical research,biostatistics, and evidence-based medicine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This bilingual glossary incorporates some 100 English words and expressions that can mislead or present difficulties on translation in clinical research, biostatistics, and evidence-based medicine. The authors propose reasoned translations and offer critical comments on terms commonly used among doctors, the essential Spanish orthographic rules that apply, and the recommendations for standard nomenclatures issued by official bodies and the main international organizations. They also discuss the need for precision and clarity that should be the hallmarks of all scientific language (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González de Dios, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, F. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta un glosario bilingüe con más de un centenar de palabras y expresiones inglesas de traducción difícil o engañosa en el ámbito de la investigación clínica, labio estadística y la «medicina basada en la evidencia». Las propuestas razonadas de traducción que ofrecen los autores van en cada caso acompañadas de comentarios críticos sobre el uso habitual entre los médicos, las normas ortográficas básicas en castellano, las recomendaciones oficiales de las nomenclaturas normalizadas y los principales organismos internacionales, así como la necesidad de precisión y claridad que debe caracterizar a todo lenguaje científico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);26(5): 375-392, oct. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130125</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Palabras y expresiones inglesas de traducción difícil o engañosa en investigación clínica, bioestadística y medicina basada en la evidencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14567</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12077^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8546</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15354^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54358^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8212^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
