<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77465</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Monitoring skill acquisition in obstetric epidural puncture at a university hospital using the cumulative sum method</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE: Skill acquisition inanesthesiology is subject to a great deal ofinterindividual variability. Our aim was to developand test an individualized tool for monitoringacquisition of technical skills based on the cumulativesum (CUSUM) approach. This system objectivelyassesses whether an individual has acquired aminimum skill level and identifies the moment whenthe skill has been learned.MATERIAL AND METHODS: Nine third-year residentsin anesthesiology and postoperative recovery careparticipated. The residents anonymously recordedtheir first 100 obstetric epidural analgesiaprocedures in a database. The data were thenanalyzed with the CUSUM method. We consideredacceptable skill acquisition to be reflected by a firstattemptsuccess rate of 80% and a rate of successwith help of 20%.RESULTS: A total of 765 epidural blocks wereanalyzed, giving a mean (SD) of 84.7 (2.8) proceduresper resident (range, 47-100 procedures per resident).Seven residents became competent with the skill after23 procedures and 2 residents were not successful inlearning the skill. At the end of the study, 3 residentshad required help with more than 20% of theprocedures. Data collection from the trainees seemed tovary, leading to possible under- or overestimation offailures and/or need for help. Accidental dural punctureoccurred 6 times (0.78%) and blood vessel puncture 40times (5.2%).CONCLUSIONS: Although some third-year residentsreach the targeted rate of success quickly, we believethat close supervision is useful to control progress alongthe learning curve for individuals who need more help(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gilsanz, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guasch, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">INTRODUCCIÓN: El aprendizaje de las habilidades enanestesia muestra una amplia variabilidad interindividual.Nuestro objetivo fue establecer y probar unaherramienta individualizada de monitorización de lacapacitación técnica (CUSUM), que permitiera establecerde forma objetiva si un individuo alcanzaba un nivelmínimo y cuándo ocurría esto.MATERIAL Y MÉTODOS: Participaron 9 médicos residentesde Anestesiología y Reanimación en su tercer añode residencia, para que recogiesen sus 100 primeros procedimientosde analgesia epidural obstétrica, anónimamenteen una base de datos. Estos datos, fueron analizadoscon el método CUSUM. Se tomó como una tasa deéxito aceptable 80% al primer intento y una necesidadde ayuda del 20%.RESULTADOS: Se analizaron 765 bloqueos, 84,7±22,8por residente, rango 47-100. Tres de los residentes nocompletaron los 100 bloqueos. Siete de ellos alcanzaronla destreza con 23 bloqueos y 2 residentes no alcanzaronla destreza. En tres residentes, la supervisión fue necesariaen más del 20% de casos al final del periodo de estudio.La recogida de datos, parece variable entre los residentes,infra o sobreestimando los fallos y/o la necesidadde ayuda. La punción dural accidental se dio en 6 casos(0,78%) y la hemática en 40 (5,2%).DISCUSIÓN: Aunque la tasa de éxito es alcanzada rápidamentepor algunos residentes de tercer año, creemosque el elevado grado de supervision es útil para controlarel progreso de la curva de aprendizaje en casos individualesque precisen más control(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;57(1): 11-15, ene. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77465</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Metodología CUSUM en la curva de aprendizaje de la punción epidural obstétrica en un hospital universitario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d784^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d784^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d778^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d778^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d774^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11813^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11813^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d784^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d787^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201001</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
