<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121848</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Latent tuberculosis infection in healthcare personnel at a primary level general hospital in Catalonia, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim was to analyze the prevalence of latent tuberculosis infection and associated risk factors in healthcare personnel at the Hospital de Tortosa Verge de la Cinta (Tarragona, Spain). This was a cross-sectional study of 398 workers at this hospital who underwent tuberculin skin testing for latent tuberculosis infection (LTBI) between 2001 and 2012.We also analyzed the relationship between LTBI and age, sex, job and work area according to their risk of exposure to tuberculosis(high, low, uncertain). The total prevalence of LTBI in our sample was 11.1% (95%CI 8.3%-14.5%). LBTI was associated with age and work area. Multivariate analysis showed that the risk of LTBI increased by 6.4% per 1 year increase in age. The prevalence of LTBI in this population approximates that of the general population in Spain (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Catalán Gómez, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sol Vidiella, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lejeune, Marylène</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Callau Casanova, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del trabajo ha sido evaluar la presencia de infección tuberculosa latente en el personal sanitario del Hospital de Tortosa Verge de la Cinta (HTVC). Para ello se analizaron las historias clínicas laborales de 398 trabajadores de dicho hospital a los que se había realizado la prueba de tuberculina durante el periodo 2001-2012. La presencia de infección tuberculosa latente (ITL) se analizó en relación a las variables edad, sexo, categoría profesional, personal de áreas de trabajo de alto y bajo riesgo de exposición a la tuberculosis y personal de riesgo no definido. La prevalencia total de ITL en el grupo estudiado fue del 11,1% (IC 95%: 8,3%-14,5%), estando dicha prevalencia asociada a la edad y al área de trabajo. El análisis multivariable mostró que el riesgo de sufrir ITL se incrementa un 6,4% por cada año de edad. La prevalencia de ITL en el centro de estudio era similar a la de la población profesionalmente no expuesta de España (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. prev. riesgos labor. (Ed. impr.);17(2): 97-101, abr.-jun. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121848</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infección tuberculosa latente en trabajadores sanitarios de un hospital general básico en Cataluña</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22069</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9362^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53483^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10749^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
