<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162331</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cognitive behavioral group intervention in the adjustment disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The goal at this research is to study the effectiveness of a cognitive behavioral group therapy program in patients with adjustment disorder. The sample is made up of 102 patients from two Mental Health units and a Primary Care Center in Valencia (Spain). The treatment was a cognitive behavioral group intervention of one hour and a half session per week during eight weeks. Patients were evaluated at the beginning and end of the program. Monitoring was performed at three months. The resources used were: the Symptom Checklist-90-Revised (SCL-90-R), the Suicide Risk Scale (RS) and the SF-36 Health Survey (SF-36). The results show significant differences between previous and following treatment measures on key dimensions of the applied scales, maintaining these results at 3 months follow-up. The results suggest that cognitive-behavioral group therapy could be used as a first level of attention to adjustment disorder because of its effectiveness and efficiency (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuquerella, Miguel Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carbajo, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Isabel M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blasco, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jorda, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de esta investigación es estudiar la eficacia de un programa de tratamiento cognitivo conductual grupal en pacientes con diagnóstico de trastorno adaptativo. La muestra está compuesta por 102 pacientes de dos Unidades de Salud Mental y un centro de Atención Primaria de Valencia (España). El tratamiento consistió en una terapia grupal cognitivo conductual de ocho sesiones de una hora y media de duración, con una frecuencia semanal. Se realizaron mediciones pre y postratamiento y un seguimiento a los tres meses. Los instrumentos que se utilizaron fueron: el &lt;Listado de síntomas revisado&gt; (SCL-90-R), la «Escala de riesgo suicida» (RS) y el «Cuestionario de salud SF-36» (SF-36). Los resultados obtenidos muestran diferencias significativas entre las medidas previas al tratamiento y al finalizarlo en las principales dimensiones de las escalas aplicadas, manteniéndose estos resultados en el seguimiento a los tres meses. Los resultados sugieren que la terapia cognitivo conductual grupal, debido a su eficacia y eficiencia, podría ser utilizada como un primer nivel de atención al trastorno adaptativo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;24(3): 389-403, 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162331</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervención grupal cognitivo conductual en el trastorno adaptativo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12051^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55694^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54296</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d282^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
