<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87240</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Towards an understanding of the molecular mechanisms underlying the pharmacological treatments of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Methylphenidate and the amphetamines are the most frequently used medications for treating attentiondeficit/ hyperactivity disorder (ADHD). These medications modulate both norepinephrine as well as dopamine. Methyl phenidate is a pure blocker of the norepinephrine and dopamine transporters. The amphetamines also block reuptake  of both catecholamines, but they also release all three monoamines, norepinephrine, dopamine, and serotonin, from presynaptic vesicles. Amphetamines are the most robust agents in increasing synaptic dopamine levels, since they do so regardless of the endogenous level of the relevant neurons. Stimulant-evoked synaptic increases of dopamine have been demonstrated in the striatum in humans, but pharmacologic effects are likely relevant to therapeutic action in  other regions, particularly the prefrontal cortex. Blockade of noradrenergic reuptake in the prefrontal cortex may also indirectly increase prefrontal dopamine levels, but there is also evidence that noradrenergic effects are mediated by alpha-2a noradrenergic receptors. A recent study in non-human primates found that methylphenidate and atomoxetine  both increased the efficiency of prefrontal pyramidal neurons, but via distinct mechanisms. Methylphenidate decreased non-specific signals, i.e., neuronal noise, via D1 receptors. By contrast, atomoxetine increased the strength of specific signals via activation of alpha-2 receptors. These findings, although in non-human primates, suggest that combinations of  agents working on these complementary systems (D1 and alpha-2a) may be worth considering and evaluating rigorously in patients with ADHD with sub-optimal responses to monotherapy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Xavier Castellanos, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acosta, M Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El metilfenidato y las anfetaminas son los fármacos más utilizados para el tratamiento del trastorno por déficit de atención/hiperactividad (TDAH). Estos fármacos modulan la noradrenalina tanto como la dopamina. El metilfenidato funciona únicamente como bloqueador de los transportadores de noradrenalina y dopamina. Las anfetaminas tienen este mismo efecto, pero, además, producen la liberación de noradrenalina, dopamina y serotonina desde las vesículas neuronales presinápticas. Las anfetaminas son más eficientes en aumentar los niveles sinápticos de dopamina, al no  requerir que las neuronas estén activadas para producir la liberación de neurotransmisores. Los aumentos de dopamina producidos por estos fármacos se han identificado en el estriato en seres humanos; sin embargo, es probable que los efectos de los fármacos sean también importantes en otros circuitos cerebrales, particularmente en la corteza prefrontal.  El bloqueo del transportador de noradrenalina en circuitos de la corteza prefrontal también aumenta los niveles de dopamina. Adicionalmente, se considera que algunos efectos importantes noradrenérgicos son mediados por receptores del subtipo alfa-2a. Un estudio recientemente hecho en primates mostró que el metilfenidato y la atomoxetina aumentaron la eficiencia de las neuronas piramidales, pero a través de diferentes mecanismos. El metilfenidato disminuye señales  no específicas a través de receptores dopaminérgicos del tipo D1. En contraste, la atomoxetina incrementa la amplitud de las señales específicamente relacionadas con la función de la neurona particular, a través de receptores alfa-2a. Este hallazgo, aunque en primates, implica que el uso de combinaciones de agentes actuando de manera complementaria en  los receptores D1 y alfa-2a debería considerarse y evaluarse de manera rigurosa en pacientes con TDAH que no responden suficientemente bien a tratamiento con un solo fármaco (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;52(supl.1): 155-160, mar. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87240</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hacia un entendimiento de los mecanismos moleculares de los tratamientos farmacológicos del trastorno por déficit de atención/hiperactividad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28972^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d677^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4400</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31150^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8961^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
