<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81367</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Histopathology of the More Common Viral Skin Infections</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We describe the histopathological characteristics of viral skin infections. Herpes simplex virus and varicella-zoster virus produce an intraepidermal vesicle with variable degrees of epithelial necrosis. Typical findings include keratinocytes with ballooned nuclei with a ground-glass appearance and giant multinucleated keratinocytes. In the endothelial cells of the dermal blood vessels, cytomegalovirus produces large eosinophilic nuclear inclusions surrounded by a clear halo. Human herpes virus 8 is etiologically associated with Kaposi sarcoma. In its early stages, this tumor contains blood vessels with a fine endothelium passing through the dermal collagen bundles. In the plaque and nodular stages, the vessel lumens are more clearly visible and there is a progressive increase in the number of neoplastic spindle cells with a low degree of pleomorphism and atypia, and occasional mitoses. The infiltrate is made up of lymphocytes and plasma cells. Contagious ecthyma and milker's nodule give rise to an acanthotic epidermis with ballooned keratinocytes containing eosinophilic cytoplasmic viral inclusions. Molluscum contagiosum shows lobules of epithelium that open onto the epidermal surface and characteristic inclusion bodies. Acanthosis, papillomatosis, and hyperkeratosis are observed in common warts, with confluence of the epidermal ridges in the centre of the lesion and koilocytes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Requena, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Requena, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este trabajo describimos las características histopatológicas de las infecciones víricas cutáneas. El herpes simple y el virus varicela-zóster producen una vesícula intraepidérmica con grados variables de necrosis epitelial. Son característicos los queratinocitos con núcleos balonizados con aspecto de vidrio esmerilado y los queratinocitos gigantes multinucleados. El citomegalovirus produce grandes inclusiones nucleares eosinófilas rodeadas de un halo claro en los endotelios de los vasos dérmicos. El herpes virus tipo 8 se relaciona etiológicamente con el sarcoma de Kaposi, que en sus fases iniciales muestra luces vasculares de endotelios finos disecando los haces de colágeno dérmicos. En las fases en placa y nodular las luces vasculares son más visibles, aumenta progresivamente el número de células fusiformes tumorales con discreto grado de atipia y pleomorfismo y algunas mitosis. El infiltrado se compone de linfocitos y células plasmáticas. El orf y el nódulo de los ordeñadores inducen una epidermis acantósica con queratinocitos balonizados que contienen inclusiones víricas citoplasmáticas eosinófilas. El molusco contagioso muestra lóbulos de epitelio abiertos a la superficie epidérmica con característicos cuerpos de inclusión. En las verrugas vulgares aparece acantosis, papilomatosis e hiperqueratosis, con confluencia de las crestas epidérmicas hacia el centro de la lesión y coilocitos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;101(3): 201-216, abr. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81367</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Histopatología de las infecciones víricas cutáneas más frecuentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22721^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29179^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30504^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3605^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31212^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10403^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6723^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
