<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73117</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: asthma is the more prevalent infantile chronic disease in Spain and in therest of developed countries. According to the findings of ISAAC Phase Three, its prevalence inValladolid is 7.2-9.2%. Coinciding with the implementation of asthmatic children health careprogramme in Castilla y León, we present a comparative study based on the findings obtainedby this programme between a rural and periurban population in Valladolid. Subjects and methods: a cross-sectional, observational study of children 0 to14 years ofage who satisfied inclusion criteria to the infantile asthma programme. Demographic data,allergic tests, severity classification, seasonal distribution and treatment have been collected.Results: sex differences have been detected between both areas (70% for male in the periurbanarea), age differences (43.7% in periurban area vs. 30% in the rural one), in allergictests (46.2% positives for less than 2 years of age in periurban area and 26% in the rural one)seasonal distribution differences (winter prevalence in periurban area and spring prevalence inthe rural area for children less than 2 years of age) and treatment differences (use of oral salbutamol,mucolytics and antibiotics in crisis in rural area). The rest of the analysed data are similarbetween them and confirm the data of other studies.Conclusions: the findings of the comparison between the two areas of study are differencesdue to environmental factors (day care attendance, infections, environmental pollution&#133;)and similarities due to the fact that they are diseases with an important genetic base, not forgettingsome foreign factors to the process such as the lack of universalization of pediatric assistancein the rural area(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nido Alonso, M del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Clavero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aníbarro Pérez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: el asma es la enfermedad crónica infantil más prevalente en España y en elresto de países desarrollados. En Valladolid la prevalencia según los datos de la fase III del estudioISAAC es de 7,2-9,2%. Coincidiendo con la implantación del programa de atención al niñoasmático en Castilla y León, presentamos un estudio comparativo de los resultados de dichoprograma entre una población rural y otra periurbana en Valladolid.Pacientes y métodos: estudio observacional transversal en niños de 0-14 años que cumplíancriterios de inclusión en el programa de asma infantil. Se recogieron datos demográficos,pruebas alérgicas, clasificación de la gravedad, distribución estacional y tratamiento.Resultados: las diferencias entre ambas zonas se hallaron respecto a la prevalencia (mayoren zona periurbana), sexo (70% de varones en la zona periurbana), edad (43,7% en la zona periurbanafrente al 30% en la rural), en pruebas alérgicas (46,2% positivas en menores de 2 añosen la zona periurbana y 26% en la rural), distribución estacional (predominio invernal en la zonaperiurbana y primaveral en la rural en menores de 2 años) y tratamiento (en la zona rural usode salbutamol oral, mucolíticos y antibióticos en las crisis). El resto de datos analizados son similaresentre ellos y concordantes con otros estudios.Conclusiones: al comparar las dos zonas se observan diferencias atribuibles a factores ambientales(asistencia a guarderías, infecciones, contaminación ambiental, etc.) y similitudes enuna enfermedad que tiene una importante base genética, sin olvidar factores ajenos al proceso,como es la no universalización de la asistencia por pediatras a los niños de la zona rural(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;11(42): 241-249, abr.-jun. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73117</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Programa del asma en Atención Primaria: estudio comparativo entre dos centros de salud de Valladolid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12797^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d488^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7145^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7145^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d488^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28064^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13610^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
