<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75345</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nursing assessment: detection of loneliness and social isolation in old people in risk</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: Identify the valuation instruments that can beuseful in the nursing profession to detect loneliness and socialisolation in the elderly at risk. Methodology: The reviewof multidisciplinary instruments that value the lonelinessand social isolation from databases and search manualdiagnostic and scales to determine the loneliness and socialisolation in the NANDA Taxonomy and Taxonomy NursingOutcomes Classification (NOC). Results: Of the eleveninstruments analyzed, seven of them feel the lonelinessof both subjective and objective manner. However, differencesexist in the form of valuation. Conclusions: The scalesof social value and loneliness are a useful element in the detectionof elderly at risk of perceiving and suffer loneliness.The results confirm that nursing professionals have adequateinstruments to detect the risk factors of loneliness and socialisolation(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lluch Canut, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puig Llobet, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Ávila, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Identificar los instrumentos de valoración quepueden ser de utilidad en la profesión enfermera paradetectar la soledad y el aislamiento social en los ancianosde riesgo. Metodología. Se ha realizado una revisiónde los instrumentos multidisciplinares que valoran la soledady el aislamiento social, a partir de bases de datos ybúsqueda manual de diagnósticos y escalas que determinenla soledad y el aislamiento social en la TaxonomíaNANDA y la Taxonomía Nursing Outcomes Classification(NOC). Resultados. De los once instrumentos analizados,siete de ellos estiman la soledad tanto de formasubjetiva como objetiva. Sin embargo, existen diferenciasen la forma de valoración. Conclusiones. Las escalasde valoración social y de soledad son un elementoútil en la detección de ancianos con riesgo de percibir ysufrir la soledad. Los resultados corroboran que los profesionalesde enfermería tienen herramientas adecuadasen la detección de los factores de riesgo de la soledad ydel aislamiento social(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);20(1): 9-14, ene.-mar. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75345</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración de enfermería: detección de la soledad y del aislamiento social en los ancianos de riesgo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28940</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11757</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19270</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13316</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28470</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9926</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8308</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
