<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134969</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cardiovascular risk and metabolic syndrome at the Toledo area study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To know the anthropometric and clinical characteristics of a children population sample, to study the prevalence and concurrence of cardiovascular risk factors in that sample, and to define the prevalence of metabolic syndrome in that population considering the blood pressure, HDL cholesterol, and fasting glycemia values, as well as the anthropometrical measurements. Setting: The health care area of Toledo. Subjects: Children aged 4 years included in the Toledo Area Study. Interventions: A prospective study is performed on the metabolic syndrome-related cardiovascular risk factors in a sample of 58 children from the Toledo Area Study. Data on anthropometrical and lipoprotein profile at birth were obtained. The anthropometrical, lipoprotein, and biochemical data were compared with those from other populations; we also looked for possible differences between boys and girls. At the same time, we analyzed the association between several cardiovascular risk factors in that population (logistic regression model) and we set up the cut-off levels to define in the children population possible candidates to metabolic syndrome. These levels are in agreement with those from similar adolescent populations. Results: Among the risk factors, higher systolic and diastolic pressure values stand up in girls (93.93 -boys- vs 98.41 -girls- p = 0.058; 52.32 -boys- vs 57.27 -girls- p = 0.026, respectively), as well as the concurrence of high blood pressure and hypercholesterolemia in boys (almost 7%). The whole prevalence of candidates to MS was 10.9% (5 girls -9.1%- and 1 boy -1.8%-). A high percentage of boys (&lt; 50%) presented a wrong diet from the perspective of dietary cardiovascular risk markers. The only statistically significant variable at 10% (p &lt; 0.10) in the regression model was Apo AI. Conclusions: It is relevant that the presence of MS is higher in girls and in those infants with a dyslipemic nonhypercholesterolemic profile at birth, which emphasizes the usefulness of cardiovascular risk factors prospection from early ages (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Muniz, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Sesmero, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bastida, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Conocer las características antropométricas y clínicas de una muestra de población infantil, estudiar la prevalencia y concurrencia de factores de riesgo cardiovascular en dicha muestra de niños y definir la prevalencia de síndrome metabólico en esta población teniendo en cuenta los valores de presión arterial, colesterol HDL, glucemia en ayunas y medidas antropométricas. Ámbito: Área Sanitaria de Toledo. Sujetos: Niños de 4 años incluidos en el estudio Área de Toledo. Intervenciones: Se realiza un estudio prospectivo de factores de riesgo cardiovascular, relacionados con el síndrome metabólico, en una muestra de 58 niños del estudio Área de Toledo. De estos niños se tenían datos tanto antropométricos como del perfil lipoproteico al nacimiento. Los datos antropométricos, lipoproteicos y bioquímicos se comparan con los de otras poblaciones; así como se buscan las posibles diferencias entre niños y niñas. A su vez se analiza la asociación de varios factores de riesgo cardiovascular en dicha población (modelo de regresión logística), y se marcan niveles de corte para definir en la población infantil posibles candidatos a síndrome metabólico. Estos límites son adaptados de otras publicaciones similares realizadas en poblaciones de adolescentes. Resultados: Entre los factores de riesgo destaca la mayor presión arterial sistólica y diastólica en las niñas (93,93 - niños-vs 98,41 -niñas- p = 0,058; 52,32 -niños- vs 57,27 -niñas- p = 0,026, respectivamente), así como la concurrencia de tensión arterial e hipercolesterolemia en los niños (casi un 7%). La prevalencia global de candidatos para SM fue del 10,9% (5 niñas -9,1%- y 1 niño -1,8%-). Un porcentaje elevado de niños (&lt; 50%) presentó una dieta incorrecta bajo el punto de vista de marcadores de dietéticos de riesgo cardiovascular. La única variable estadísticamente significativa al 10% (p &lt; 0,10) en el modelo de regresión es la Apo AI. Conclusiones: Es relevante que la prevalencia de SM sea mayor en niñas y en aquellos infantes que tuvieron un perfil dislipémico no hipercolesterolémico al nacimiento, lo que da énfasis a la utilidad de la prospección de factores de riesgo cardiovascular en edades muy tempranas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;24(2): 167-175, mar.-abr. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134969</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Riesgo cardiovascular y síndrome metabólico en el Estudio Área de Toledo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3998^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13706^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
