<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154481</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Kinantropometry characteristic of elite baseball players</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Anthropometric characteristics is one of the methods that they have been used in sport talent detection. However, few studies have analyzed the morphological profile of elite baseball player. Objective: To analyze the anthropometric profile of elite Spanish baseball players, classified by playing positions and globally. Material and methods: Two hundred and seventeen male baseball players (age: 23.87 ± 5.32 years) from Spanish Honor Division participated in this study. Athletes were classified based on their playing position. Anthropometric variables were measured and somatotype, body composition, body mass index (BMI) and six skinfolds sum were calculated. Results: Players did not show significant differences based on their playing position in stretch stature; body mass; triceps, subscapular, biceps, supraspinale, abdominal and medial calf skinfolds; six skinfold sum; and wrist (bi-styloid) bone breadth. There were significant differences in front thigh skinfold, arm flexed and tensed and calf girths, humerus (biepicondylar) and femur (biepicondylar) bone breadths; BMI, body composition and somatotype. Endomorphy showed a high value, mesomorphy a high or medium-high values and ectomorphya low value. Generally, athletes showed a mesomorphic endomorph and mesomorph-endomorph somatotype, depends on the playing position. Conclusion: Baseball players of all the playing positions showed a high homogeneity in the anthropometric profi le. There were only few differences in some anthropometric variables such as girths and bone breaths (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Miñarro, Pedro A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero-Cristóbal, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Clavijo-Redondo, Arturo R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esparza-Ros, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: a pesar de que las características antropométricas es uno de los métodos utilizados dentro de la selección de talentos deportivos, son pocos los estudios que han analizado el perfil morfológico del jugador de béisbol de élite. Objetivo: analizar el perfil antropométrico de los jugadores de béisbol de élite nacional de forma global y según el puesto ocupado. Material y métodos: Doscientos diecisiete jugadores de béisbol masculino (edad: 23,87 ± 5,32 años) de la División de Honor española participaron en el presente estudio. A todos ellos se les clasificó según su posición de juego y se les realizó una valoración antropométrica. Posteriormente se calculó su somatotipo, composición corporal, índice de masa corporal (IMC) y sumatorio de seis pliegues. Resultados: los jugadores no mostraron diferencias significativas en función de su posición en el campo en la talla, el peso, los pliegues tríceps, subescapular, bíceps, supraespinal, abdominal y pierna, ni en el sumatorio de seis pliegues o el diámetro biestiloideo. Sí que se encontraron diferencias significativas en el pliegue del muslo, perímetros del brazo contraído y pierna y diámetros biepicondíleo del húmero y fémur. Tampoco se hallaron diferencias significativas en el IMC, la composición corporal o el somatotipo. Los valores de endomorfia fueron altos, los de mesomorfia altos o medio-altos y los de ectomorfia bajos, siendo la clasificación del somatotipo mesoendomorfo o endomorfo-mesomorfo según la posición de juego. Conclusión: existe una gran homogeneidad en el perfil antropométrico de los jugadores de béisbol según su posición de juego, diferenciándose únicamente en algunas variables antropométricas como perímetros y diámetros (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;33(3): 629-636, mayo-jun. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154481</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características cineantropométricas de los jugadores de béisbol de élite</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1506^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
