<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145158</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidemiological analysis of mandibular fractures treated in Sao Paulo, Brazil</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To analyze the results of an epidemiological study of mandibular fractures treated in a population of the city of Sao Paulo, Brazil. Materials and Methods. The population included patients treated by a Department of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery and Traumatology from January 2008 to September 2010, diagnosed with mandibular fractures. The variables analyzed for the study were gender, age, etiology, clinical signs and symptoms, type of treatment, and postoperative condition. Results. A total of 171 patients and a total of 269 mandible fractures were diagnosed, with the majority being the males (84.8%), between the 2nd and 3rd decade of life. The mandibular condyle was the most affected region (32.04%), followed by the mandibular angle (23.38%). The postoperative edema was the most evident clinical sign, and the treatment of choice was the reduction and internal fixation with titanium mini-plates in all cases. Conclusion. The treatment of mandibular fractures should be aimed at restoring the occlusion and mastication function, with surgery being the most indicated treatment, using reduction and internal fixation with the use of a plates and screws system based on the experience of the authors. Knowledge of surgical techniques and methods of reduction and fixation of fractures, and periodic monitoring allow these patients to receive the appropriate treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Piva, Fabio Henrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gonzalez, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lobo Leandro, Luiz Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Guevara, Henry Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rocha, Bárbara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marinho, Kelly</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Objetivo. Analizar los resultados de un estudio epidemiológico de las fracturas mandibulares tratadas en una población de la ciudad de Sao Paulo, Brasil. Materiales y Métodos. La población incluyó a pacientes tratados por un Departamento de Cirugía Oral y Maxilofacial y Traumatología desde enero 2008 hasta septiembre 2010, con diagnóstico de fracturas mandibulares. Las variables analizadas para el estudio fueron: sexo, edad, etiología, signos clínicos y síntomas, el tipo de tratamiento y la condición post-operatoria. Resultados. Un total de 171 pacientes fueron diagnosticados de fracturas mandibulares y un total de 269 fracturas, siendo los varones, el género más afectado (84,8%), entre la segunda y tercera década de la vida, el cóndilo mandibular fue la región más afectada (32,04%), seguido por el ángulo de la mandíbula (23,38%). El edema postoperatorio fue el signo clínico más evidente y el tratamiento de elección fue la reducción y fijación interna con miniplacas de titanio en todos los casos. Conclusión. El tratamiento de fracturas mandibulares debe estar dirigida para restaurar la función de la oclusión y la masticación, siendo la cirugía el tratamiento más indicado, a través de la reducción y fijación interna con el uso de placas y tornillos de sistema basados en la experiencia de los autores Conocimiento de las técnicas quirúrgicas y los métodos de reducción y fijación de fracturas y el seguimiento periódico de los pacientes permiten un tratamiento adecuado para estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;37(4): 175-181, oct.-dic. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145158</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis epidemiológico de fracturas mandibulares tratados en Sao Paulo Brasil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8509^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5727^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5727^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8509^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14414^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8507^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
