<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044305</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of factors related to smoking initiation and continued smoking in young adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyse the determining of the acquisition and later consolidation of the tobacco consumption in young adolescents. Material and method: Longitudinal study of three years of duration (2000-2002). Subjects were students of secondary education between 13 and 14 years old at the beginning of the study. The research was performed in Gran Canaria Island with a final sample of 745 subjects. Models of conditional binary election were considered for longitudinal data where the dependent variable reflects decisions of the adolescents through time, with regard to the probability of beginning to smoke, «beginning model», and the probability of being occasional or habitual smoker, «experimentation model». Results: In the last year, 57% of the young teenagers surveyed use tobacco, a 25% more than in the first year, some of them, 9% on a daily basis. In the «beginning model» the determining of the tobacco consumption are interest in studies (odds ratio [OR] = 0.27; 95% confidence interval (CI), 0.08-0.87 and OR = 0.14; 95% CI, 0.03-0.58 for the students having enough and much interest in studies, respectively), to have a smoker as the best friend (OR = 7.44; 95% CI, 2.59-21.4), the alcohol consumption (OR = 11.82; 95% CI, 4.96-28.2 and OR=15.42; 95% CI, 4.68-50.7 for youngs who drink alcohol occasionally or frequently) and having more pocket money (euros per week) (OR = 1.13; 95% CI, 1.07-1.19). For the «experimentation model», to have a smoker as the best friend (OR = 7.01; 95% CI, 2.96-16.5), the alcohol consumption (OR = 5.71; 95% CI, 1.98-16.4 and OR = 5.22; 95% CI, the 1.56-17.5 for youngs who drink alcohol occasionally or frequently) and the number of years since the student started smoking (OR = 1.44; 95% IC, 1.11-1.86). Conclusions: Our study emphasizes, peer group effect, drinking alcoholic beverages and lack of interest in studies as factors associated to the tobacco consumption</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinilla, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barber, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero-Hidalgo, Araceli</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar los factores que determinan la adquisición y posterior consolidación del consumo de tabaco en los jóvenes adolescentes. Material y método: Estudio longitudinal de 3 años de duración (2000-2002) sobre jóvenes estudiantes de enseñanza obligatoria, con una edad al inicio del estudio de 13-14 años. Los datos fueron recogidos mediante encuesta individual, cuyo ámbito de estudio era la isla de Gran Canaria, con una muestra final de 745 individuos. Se estimaron modelos de elección binaria condicional de efectos fijos para datos longitudinales, para determinar la probabilidad de probar por primera vez el tabaco («modelo de inicio»), así como sobre la probabilidad de ser fumador ocasional o habitual («modelo de experimentación»).Resultados: En el último año, el 57% de los adolescentes encuestados ha tenido contacto con el tabaco alguna vez, un 25% más que en el primer año, algunos de ellos (el 9%) de forma diaria. En el «modelo de inicio» los determinantes del consumo de tabaco son el interés por el colegio (odds ratio [OR] = 0,27; intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 0,08-0,87, y OR = 0,14; IC del 95%, 0,03-0,58 para los que manifestaron bastante y mucho interés por el colegio, respectivamente), el consumo de tabaco por parte del mejor amigo (OR = 7,44; IC del 95%, 2,59-21,4), el consumo de alcohol (OR = 11,82; IC del 95%, 4,96-28,2, y OR = 15,42; IC del 95%, 4,68-50,7 para los que beben alcohol de manera ocasional o frecuente, respectivamente), y el dinero disponible (euros semanales) (OR = 1,13; IC del 95%, 1,07-1,19). Para el «modelo de experimentación», el consumo de tabaco por parte del mejor amigo (OR = 7,01; IC del 95%, 2,96-16,5), el consumo de alcohol (OR = 5,71; IC del 95%, 1,98-16,4, y OR = 5,22; IC del 95%, 1,56-17,5 para los que beben alcohol de manera ocasional o frecuente, respectivamente) y los años que lleva como fumador (OR = 1,44; IC del 95%, 1,11-1,86). Conclusiones: El estudio destaca, principalmente, los efectos del grupo de amigos, el consumo de bebidas alcohólicas y el poco interés por los estudios como factores asociados al consumo de tabaco</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;19(6): 440-447, nov. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044305</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores predictores del inicio y consolidación del consumo de tabaco en adolescentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
