<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-168663</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Heart failure in patients with kidney disease and iron deficiency; the role of iron therapy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Chronic kidney disease and anaemia are common in heart failure (HF) and are associated with a worse prognosis in these patients. Iron deficiency is also common in patients with HF and increases the risk of morbidity and mortality, regardless of the presence or absence of anaemia. While the treatment of anaemia with erythropoiesis-stimulating agents in patients with HF have failed to show a benefit in terms of morbidity and mortality, treatment with IV iron in patients with HF and reduced ejection fraction and iron deficiency is associated with clinical improvement. In a posthoc analysis of a clinical trial, iron therapy improved kidney function in patients with HF and iron deficiency. In fact, the European Society of Cardiology's recent clinical guidelines on HF suggest that in symptomatic patients with reduced ejection fraction and iron deficiency, treatment with IV ferric carboxymaltose should be considered to improve symptoms, the ability to exercise and quality of life. Iron plays a key role in oxygen storage (myoglobin) and in energy metabolism, and there are pathophysiological bases that explain the beneficial effect of IV iron therapy in patients with HF. All these aspects are reviewed in this article (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ojeda López, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cases Amenós, Aleix</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Portolés Pérez, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad renal crónica y la anemia son frecuentes en la insuficiencia cardíaca (IC) y su presencia se asocia con un peor pronóstico en estos pacientes. La ferropenia es frecuente en pacientes con IC y aumenta el riesgo de morbimortalidad, independientemente de la presencia o no de anemia. Mientras el tratamiento de la anemia con agentes estimuladores de la eritropoyesis en pacientes con IC no ha demostrado un beneficio sobre la morbimortalidad, el tratamiento con hierro intravenoso (iv) en pacientes con IC y fracción de eyección disminuida y déficit de hierro se asocia con una mejoría clínica. Además, en un análisis post hoc de un ensayo clínico, la ferroterapia mejoró la función renal en pacientes con IC y ferropenia. De hecho, las recientes guías clínicas sobre IC de la Sociedad Europea de Cardiología señalan que se debe considerar el tratamiento con hierro carboximaltosa iv en pacientes sintomáticos con fracción de eyección disminuida y déficit de hierro a fin de mejorar los síntomas, la capacidad de ejercicio y la calidad de vida. El hierro juega un papel importante en el almacenamiento de oxígeno (mioglobina) y en el metabolismo energético, y existen bases fisiopatológicas que explican el efecto beneficioso de la ferroterapia iv en pacientes con IC. Todo ello es revisado en el presente artículo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;37(6): 587-591, nov.-dic. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-168663</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Insuficiencia cardíaca en la enfermedad renal y déficit de hierro: importancia de la ferroterapia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7668^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55027^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7668^s22015</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
