<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111400</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hypersensitivity Pneumonitis Due to Isocyanates: Lung Function, Clinical and Radiological Characteristics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of this present study was to describe the clinical-radiological and lung function characteristics of hypersensitivity pneumonitis due to exposure to isocyanates (HPI). Included for study were all those patients diagnosed with HPI (n=5) from 1995 to 2010. In all cases, chest CT and complete lung function studies were done. The diagnosis was made with positive specific bronchial provocation tests (BPT). A predominance of males and pattern variability in the radiological alterations were observed. The BPT was positive due to a decline in FVC or DLCO in all cases except in one patient in whom the diagnosis was established with clinical criteria. Positive IgG to isocyanates was confirmed in only one patient. The radiological presentation of HPI may be different from the more common HP in our setting and run their course with less clinical affectation on the BPT(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Uranga, Ane</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morell, Ferran</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Ortiz, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz, María Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente trabajo fue describir las características clínico-radiológicas y de función pulmonar de la neumonitis por hipersensibilidad por exposición a isocianatos (NHI). Se estudiaron todos los pacientes con diagnóstico de NHI (n=5) durante los años 1995-2010. En todos ellos se realizó TC torácica y estudio de función pulmonar completo. El diagnóstico se realizó mediante prueba de provocación bronquial específica (PPBE) positiva. Se observó un predominio de varones y una variabilidad de patrones en las alteraciones radiológicas. La PPBE fue positiva por descenso de la FVC o de la DLCO en todos los casos excepto en un paciente, en que se estableció por criterios clínicos. Tan solo en un paciente se constató una IgG positiva a isocianatos. La presentación radiológica de la NHI puede ser distinta de las NH más frecuentes en nuestro medio y cursan con menor afectación clínica en la PPBE(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;49(4): 169-172, abr. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111400</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neumonitis por hipersensibilidad a isocianatos. Características clínico-radiológicas y de función pulmonar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9158</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d543^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d543^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31380^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2015^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d543^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2015^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2015^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2015^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
