<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144204</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-7615</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Substance consumption when driving vehicles: reflections and approaches</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Although accident and road death figures in this country have dropped a great deal over the last few years, making Spain the fifth best country in the world in road safety results, we cannot ignore that to continue reducing this figure we have to apply increasingly specific policies and measures. The consumption of alcohol and drugs when driving vehicles is still a difficult problem to tackle in the framework of road safety, as these are involved in over 40% of the accidents taking place in this country. The present legislative and intervention measures would seem to be starting to involve certain limitations since a priori they are not providing an effective response to certain profiles of drivers committing substance abuse. Knowing these profiles, analysing and evaluating the present measures, as well as proposing measures that are not only legislative or technological, but also for direct intervention with the driver, will help to continue reducing these accident and road death figures (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lijarcio Cárcel, José Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Aunque las cifras de accidentalidad y mortalidad vial en nuestro país han conseguido un gran descenso en los últimos años, posicionando a España en el quinto país mejor del mundo en resultados de seguridad vial, no podemos obviar que para continuar reduciendo esta cifra debemos aplicar políticas y medidas cada vez más específicas. El consumo de alcohol y drogas en la conducción de vehículos continúa siendo un problema de difícil aproximación en el marco de la seguridad vial ya que están presentes en más del 40% de los accidentes que se producen en nuestro país. Las actuales medidas legislativas y de intervención parece que comienzan a presentar ciertas limitaciones ya que a priori no están dando una respuesta efectiva a ciertos perfiles de conductores que abusan de sustancias. Conocer estos perfiles, analizar y evaluar las medidas actuales, así como proponer medidas no solo legislativas o tecnológicas, sino también de intervención directa con el conductor, ayudará a continuar reduciendo esta cifra de siniestralidad y mortalidad vial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. drogodepend;40(3): 5-11, 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144204</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El consumo de sustancias en la conducción de vehículos, reflexiones y aproximaciones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29633</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12055^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1340^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3070^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1340^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
