<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131611</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A psychometric analysis of the Approaches to Teaching Inventory (ATI) and a proposal for a Spanish version (S-ATI-20)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Recent educational research has explored how university teachers approach their teaching. One of the most widely used instruments is Trig well and Prosser´s (2004) Approaches to Teaching Inventory(ATI). There is, however, scarce research on the Spanish version of this questionnaire. This paper aimed: 1) to analyse the reliability and structural validity of two existing versions of ATI in Spanish language, and 2) to present a proposal for a new Spanish version of ATI, and to measure its reliability and validity. Method: The samples comprised university and trainee teachers from two Spanish universities. Results: Reliability coefficients, factor structures, and item loadings of the two existing Spanish versions of ATI were evaluated. Some coincidental outcomes suggested that a revisedATI in Spanish was required, thus a new version (S-ATI-20) was presented and tested on a new sample. Conclusions: The results suggest questionnaires should be suitably translated and item wording carefully adapted. Factor analyses moderately support a two-scale model, but a lack of correlation between approaches suggests alternative approaches to teaching models might be worth considering. This paper presents preliminary results which should be taken with caution, but S-ATI-20 may serve as a tool for self-reflection in faculty development (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Monroy, Fuensanta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Pina, Fuensanta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Geraldo, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La investigación educativa de los últimos años ha explorado los enfoques de enseñanza de los profesores universitarios. Uno de los instrumentos más empleados para medir dichos enfoques es el Approaches to Teaching Inventory (ATI) (Trigwell y Prosser, 2004). Los objetivos de esta investigación fueron: a) analizar la fiabilidad y validez de dos versiones en castellano del ATI aplicadas en dos estudios independientes, y b) presentar una propuesta de cuestionario y analizar su consistencia interna y validez. Método: Las muestras estuvieron constituidas por docentes y profesores en formación de dos universidades españolas. Resultados: Se detectaron coincidencias en los resultados de sendas versiones en castellano del ATI en cuanto a la fiabilidad, estructura factorial, y cargas de ítems, lo que apuntó a la necesidad de desarrollar una nueva versión (S-ATI-20). Conclusiones: Los resultados destacan la importancia de traducir los cuestionarios adecuadamente y adaptarlos al contexto. La estructura factorial apoya el modelo de dos escalas del ATI, pero la falta de correlación entre escalas apunta a la posibilidad de considerar otros modelos para explicar los enfoques de enseñanza. Los resultados aquí presentados son preliminares, pero el S-ATI-20 podría emplearse para la auto-reflexión y auto-evaluación del profesorado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;31(1): 172-183, ene. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131611</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis psicométrico del cuestionario Approaches to Teaching Inventory (ATI) y propuesta en castellano (S-ATI-20)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
