<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131292</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Motivation and burnout in physical education teachers: incidence of thwarting of the basic psychological needs</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This work aims to assess the importance of the basic psychological needs to explain and predict the type of motivation and levels of burnout in physical education teachers. To achieve this purpose, the sample was formed by 357 male and female teachers, belonged to different public and private schools from Spain. A regression analysis by each dependent variable was conducted, which showed that thwarting of the needs of competence positively predicted a motivation, emotional burnout and effrontery, and negatively predicted intrinsic motivation and professional efficacy; thwarting of the need of autonomy positively predicted emotional burnout and negatively predicted professional efficacy. These results are consistent with Self-Determination Theory (Deci y Ryan, 2000; Ryan y Deci, 2000),emphasizing the importance of satisfaction of autonomy, competence and relatedness to optimize motivation and welfare in physical education teachers (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cuevas Campos, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Oliva, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pulido González, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Miguel, Pedro Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Chamorro, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A través del presente trabajo se pretende valorar la importancia de las necesidades psicológicas básicas para explicar y predecir el tipo de motivación y los niveles de burnout en profesores de educación física. Para ello, la muestra estuvo formada por 357 docentes de género masculino y femenino, pertenecientes a diferentes centros educativos públicos y privados de España. Se realizó un análisis de regresión lineal por cada variable dependiente, que indicaron cómo la frustración de la necesidad de competencia predecía positivamente la desmotivación, el agotamiento emocional y el cinismo, y negativamente la motivación intrínseca y la eficacia profesional; la frustración de autonomía predecía positivamente el agotamientos emocional y negativamente la eficacia profesional; y la frustración de relaciones sociales predecía positivamente la eficacia profesional. Estos resultados están en la línea de la Teoría de la Autodeterminación (Deci y Ryan,2000; Ryan y Deci, 2000), destacando la importancia que adquieren la satisfacción de autonomía, competencia y relaciones sociales para optimizarla motivación y el bienestar de los profesores de educación física (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;14(3): 75-82, sept.-dic. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131292</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Motivación y burnout en profesores de educación física: incidencia de la frustración de las necesidades psicológicas básicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5775</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
