<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039816</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4466</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The goal of this paper consists in the revision of argentinean pronatalist ideas of the period 190-1983 and so doing, in the evaluating the influences that they received from Nicola Pende´s Biotypology. This subject, derived from Francis Galton´s Eugenics, was usefull to autoritarian systems so it was very well accepted for the eugenic orthodoxic of Mussolini´s Italy, Franco´s Spain and the Argentina of those years. Around it, politics and demographers articulated a thomist speech with prominent emphasis in the promotion of a "selected natality"</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miranda, Marisa A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo central del presente trabajo consiste en revisar las propuestas pronatalistas argentinas del período 1930-1983 y evaluar las influencias que recibieran de la Biotipología de Nicola Pende. Esta disciplina, derivada de la Eugenesia de Francis Galton y funcional a regímenes autoritarios, tuvo gran aceptación en la ortodoxia eugénica de la Italia de Mussolini, la España de Franco y la Argentina de aquellos años. En torno a ella se articuló un discurso demográfico de claro sesgo tomista en el cual el fomento de la "natalidad seleccionada" fue, como veremos, uno de sus aspectos más destacados</dc:description>
<dc:source>Asclepio;57(1): 189-218, 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039816</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La biotipología en el pronatalismo argentino (1930-1983)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1121^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26146</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6976^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5149^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5149^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5149^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6976^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6825</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5964^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11594</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13391^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
