<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-66251</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Focal glandular atypia in needle prostatic biopsies consists of scarce glands with architectural and cytological features suggestive but not conclusive of malignancy. Although this is a relatively frequent finding, the advantage of carrying out additional sections has not been extensively explored. The objective of this review is to define the usefulness of performing multiple additional sections in needle biopsies showing areas with focal glandular atypia. Methods: Thirty-eight patients in whom prostate needle biopsies were performed and showed focal glandular atypia in routine sections were selected for this study. In all biopsies there were atypia only in one isolated microscopic field. Each case originally had three cuts of three microns each per slide. In all cases three additional slides were made with three additional cuts. Thus, each case wound up with a total of 12 cuts (the original 3, and additional 9). Results: The average age of the patients was 65 years old, and the average specific prostate antigen was 8.4 ng/ml. The additional sections made it possible to establish a definitive diagnosis of malignancy in nine (22.5%) of the 38 cases, because they made more apparent the architectural and cytological features of prostatic carcinoma. In the other 29 biopsies the area with glandular atypia was less apparent or disappeared altogether. Conclusions: The additional sections are useful for the diagnosis of adenocarcinoma in one of every four or five needle biopsies with focal glandular atypia. Making additional cuts in these biopsies is a quick and low-cost method that could be practiced routinely, especially if immunohistochemical studies are not available (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Benítez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Mijangos, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arista-Nasr, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La atipia glandular focal en biopsias por punción, esta constituida por escasas glándulas que muestran criterios arquitecturales y citológicos sugestivos, pero no diagnósticos, de malignidad. Aunque éste es un problema relativamente frecuente, la ventaja de realizar niveles adicionales múltiples en estas biopsias ha sido poco estudiada. El objetivo de la presente revisión es definir cual es la utilidad de practicar cortes adicionales múltiples en biopsias por punción que muestran áreas con atipia glandular focal. Metodos: Se seleccionaron 38 pacientes en los que se practicó biopsias por punción de la próstata que mostraron atipia glandular focal en cortes rutinarios. Todas las biopsias mostraron atipia glandular en un campo microscópico aislado. Cada caso contó originalmente con tres cortes de tres micras por laminilla. En todos los casos se practicaron tres niveles adicionales con tres cortes histológicos cada uno. Así, cada caso contó con un total de 12 cortes (3 originales y 9adicionales). Resultados: El promedio de edad fue de 65 años y el promedio del antígeno prostático específico de 8,4 ng/ml. Los niveles adicionales permitieron establecer el diagnóstico concluyente de malignidad en nueve (22,5%) de los 38 casos, ya que hicieron mas aparentes los criterios arquitecturales y citológicos de carcinoma prostático. En las otras 29 biopsias el área con atipia glandular se hizo menos aparente o desapareció. Conclusiones: Los niveles adicionales son útiles para el diagnóstico de malignidad en una de cada cuatro o cinco biopsias con atipia glandular focal. Practicar cortes adicionales en estas biopsias representa un método rápido y a bajo costo que podría practicarse rutinariamente, en particular si no se cuenta con estudios inmunohistoquímicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;32(6): 594-598, jun. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-66251</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1732</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11913^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
