<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039014</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recurrent tolosa-hunt syndrome with normal neuroimaging. A report of three cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Tolosa-Hunt syndrome is caused by an unspecific inflammation in the cavernous sinus or superiororbital fissure. Recurrence occurs in 40% of cases. Magnetic resonance (MR) of the head and orbital phlebography can revealcharacteristic data, although diagnosis is reached by exclusion according to International Headache Society criteria.Corticoids are the preferred treatment, since their use gives rise to the disappearance of the clinical condition in a few days.Case report. We describe the cases of three patients with recurrent Tolosa-Hunt syndrome and MR images of the head withnormal contrast. Case 1: a 52-year-old male with paralysis of the oculomotor nerve with recurrence on the contralateral side.Case 2: a 42-year-old female with recurrent paralysis of the abducent nerve. Case 3: a 34-year-old male with involvement ofthe oculomotor nerve, optic nerve and the first branch of the trigeminal nerve with recurrence of the ophthalmoplegia. In allcases the clinical symptoms disappeared with the use of corticoid therapy. Conclusions. The oculomotor disorder is producedby nerve infiltration and not by compression. The time for recurrence varies largely, and the clinical condition in therecurrence is usually milder owing to the fact that diagnosis is reached and treatment is started earlier. The absence ofalterations in the MR of the head does not rule out the existence of Tolosa-Hunt syndrome, even in cases of recurrence, andthese disorders therefore should not be included in the diagnostic criteria</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Caballero, P. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Florensa, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marsal-Alonso, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Tejerina, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El síndrome de Tolosa-Hunt está causadopor una inflamación inespecífica en el seno cavernoso o fisura orbitariasuperior. La recidiva ocurre en un 40% de los casos. Laresonancia magnética (RM) cerebral y la flebografía orbitaria puedenmostrar datos característicos, aunque el diagnóstico es deexclusión, según los criterios de la International Headache Society.Los corticoides son el tratamiento de elección, ya que producen ladesaparición de la clínica en pocos días. Casos clínicos. Se describentres casos de pacientes con síndrome de Tolosa-Hunt de repeticióny RM cerebral con contraste normal. Caso 1: varón de 52 añoscon parálisis del III par con recurrencia en el lado contralateral.Caso 2: mujer de 42 años con parálisis del VI par de repetición.Caso 3: varón de 34 años con afectación del III par, nervio óptico yprimera rama del trigémino con recurrencia de oftalmoplejía. Entodos los casos la clínica desapareció tras la instauración de corticoides.Conclusiones. La afectación oculomotora se produce porinfiltración nerviosa y no por compresión. El tiempo para la recurrenciaes muy variable y la clínica en la recurrencia suele ser másleve, debido al diagnóstico y a la instauración de tratamiento mástemprana. La ausencia de alteraciones en la RM cerebral no descartala existencia de un síndrome de Tolosa-Hunt, incluso en casosde recurrencia, por lo que no se deberían incluir estas alteracionesen los criterios diagnósticos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;41(1): 30-33, jul. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039014</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Tolosa-Hunt de repetición con neuroimagen normal. Descripción de tres casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34304^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34304^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34304^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34304^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3407^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
