<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158015</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Training degree assessment of staff producing parenteral nutrition in Pharmacy Services</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the level of expertise of Pharmacy personnel in the manufacturing of total parenteral nutrition. Material and methods: An on-line survey including 17 questions concerning key aspects of TPN manufacturing was designed. Survey monkey software was used to create the survey and to analize its results. Results: 135 answers were received. 95% of the participant Pharmacy services had written standard manufacturing procedures. 67% answered that phosphate salts should be the first electrolite to be additioned into the total parenteral nutrition and 34% affirmed that validation of the aseptic manufacturing technique was not performed. As far as personnel training was concerned, 19% of respondents had not received any specific training, although 99% considered it would be necessary to receive it. Conclusions: The polled personell has an acceptable level of expertise but adequate training courses are still necessary and should be promoted from Pharmacy services (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romero Jiménez, Rosa M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Pons, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Rodicio, Sonsoles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ripa Ciaurriz, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejada, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cervera, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piñeiro, Guadalupe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gimeno Ballester, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo, M Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gomis Muñoz, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar el grado de formación del personal que elabora nutrición parenteral en los Servicios de Farmacia. Material y métodos: Se diseñó una encuesta on-line con 17 preguntas en la que se incluyeron los puntos más importantes en la elaboración de nutriciones parenterales. Para el diseño de la encuesta y el análisis posterior se utilizó la aplicación informática Survey monkey®. Resultados: Se obtuvieron un total de 135 respuestas. En el 95% de los Servicios de Farmacia existían normas escritas de elaboración. El 67% contestó que el fosfato se debía añadir cuando se empiezan a añadir los electrolitos y el 34% que no se realizaba la validación de la técnica aséptica de elaboración. En cuanto a la formación, el 19% no la había recibido, considerando necesario recibirla el 99%. Conclusiones: El personal encuestado presenta un grado de formación aceptable, pero son necesarios los cursos de formación que se deben fomentar desde los Servicios de Farmacia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;40(6): 486-490, nov.-dic. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158015</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación del grado de formación del personal que elabora las nutriciones parenterales en los Servicios de Farmacia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10797^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30401^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50249^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2672^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54124^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7492^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
