<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79130</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Granulosa cell tumor with a diffuse sarcomatoid growth pattern: a case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Granulosa-cell tumors are rare malignant neoplasms characterized by a long natural history and a tendency to recur years after the initial diagnosis.We report a case of granulosa-cell tumor with a diffuse sarcomatoid growth pattern in a postmenopausal woman and discuss the differential diagnosis and treatment of this entity.Granulosa-cell tumors are rare neoplasms. The treatment of choice is surgery with prolonged post-therapeutic follow-up due to the risk of late recurrences. Granulosa-cell tumors with a diffuse sarcomatoid pattern can be mistaken for sarcomas and benign lesions such as thecoma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Velasco Serrano, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jurado Escámez, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Porras Hidalgo, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lara Bohórquez, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los tumores ováricos de células de la granulosa son neoplasias poco frecuentes, que se caracterizan por un curso clínico indolente con tendencia a presentar recurrencias tardías.Describimos un caso de tumor de células de la granulosa de patrón difuso sarcomatoide en una paciente posmenopáusica y se discuten su diagnóstico diferencial y tratamiento.Los tumores de células de la granulosa son neoplasias poco frecuentes, cuyo tratamiento de elección es quirúrgico con seguimiento prolongado debido al riesgo de recurrencias tardías. El patrón difuso sarcomatoide puede plantear dificultades diagnósticas con sarcomas y lesiones benignas como el tecoma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);53(4): 152-155, abr. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79130</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumor de células de la granulosa de patrón difuso sarcomatoide. Presentación de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14176^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4794^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14176^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4794^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6257^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12888^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6257^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12888^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
