<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84831</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Retrospective study of FibroScan®, APRI, FIB-4 and FORNS indexes compared with liver biopsy in the evaluation of liver fibrosis in patients with chronic hepatitis C monoinfection and HIV coinfection</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveTo assess the ability of FibroScan® (FS) and the APRI, FIB-4 and FORNS indexes to predict liver fibrosis (LF), using liver biopsy as the gold standard.MethodsLF stage was determined in 154 patients with chronic hepatitis C virus infection using the METAVIR system. Fibroscan® measurements and blood samples were taken simultaneously with biopsy. The tests were evaluated using ROC curves and the concordance, sensitivity, specificity and predictive values and likelihood ratios.ResultsSignificantly higher LF stages were found in older patients and in those with HIV coinfection. FS and FIB-4 were able to predict significant LF&amp;#8805;1 and more than 94% of patients with FS&gt;6.7 kPas or FIB-4&gt;1.3 had LF&amp;#8805;1 in liver biopsy, with low sensitivities (63% FS; 56% Fib-4). For the detection of LF&amp;#8805;2, all the tests had significant predictive capacity and between 77% and 86% of the patients with FS&gt;6.8kPas, APRI&gt;0.6, FIB-4&gt;1.4 and FORNS&gt;5.6 had LF&amp;#8805;2, with low sensitivities (70%FS; 54%APRI; 59%FIB-4; 54%FORNS). All tests had high negative predictive values (91&#150;92%) and specificities (86&#150;92%) in the detection of advanced fibrosis (FH=4).ConclusionAll tests were acceptable in predicting the presence or absence of mild fibrosis (LF&amp;#8805;2) and the absence of advanced fibrosis (LF=2). However, the low or moderate agreement with liver biopsy and low sensitivities in the detection of mild fibrosis indicate that liver biopsy continues to be required when the results of other methods are discordant or indeterminate(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hinojosa Mena-Bernal,  Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Guilabert, Maria Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pozo Pérez,  Miguel Angel del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pozo González,  Jorge del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoEvaluación de la capacidad predictiva de fibrosis hepática (FH) del FibroScan® y APRI, FIB-4 y FORNS, con la biopsia hepática como prueba de referencia.MétodosEl grado de fibrosis hepática (FH) se determinó en 154 pacientes con hepatitis crónica C usando el sistema METAVIR. Se tomaron medidas de FibroScan® (FS) y muestras sanguíneas simultáneamente a la biopsia. Las pruebas se evaluaron usando curvas COR y los valores de concordancia, sensibilidad, especificidad, razones de verosimilitud y valores predictivos.ResultadosLos pacientes de mayor edad y los coinfectados con VIH tenían significativamente mayores grados de fibrosis. El FS y el FIB-4 tuvieron una capacidad predictiva de FH&amp;#8805;1 significativa, y más de 94% de los pacientes con FS&gt;6,7kPas o FIB-4&gt;1,3 tenían FH&amp;#8805;1 en BH, con sensibilidades bajas (63%FS; 56%Fib-4). Para la detección de FH&amp;#8805;2, todas las pruebas tuvieron una capacidad predictiva significativa, y entre 77&#150;86% de los pacientes con FS&gt;6,8kPas, APRI&gt;0,6, FIB-4&gt;1,4 y FORNS&gt;5,6 tenían FH&amp;#8805;2, con sensibilidades bajas (70%FS; 54%APRI; 59%FIB-4; 54%FORNS). Todas las pruebas tuvieron valores predictivos negativos (91&#150;92%), y especificidades (86&#150;92%) altos para la detección de fibrosis avanzada (FH=4).ConclusiónTodas las pruebas tuvieron una capacidad aceptable de predicción de la presencia/ausencia de fibrosis leve (FH&amp;#8805;2) y de ausencia de fibrosis avanzada (FH=2). Sin embargo, grados de concordancia con la BH bajos a moderados y valores bajos de sensibilidad para la detección de fibrosis leve indican que la BH sigue siendo necesaria en caso de discordancia o resultados indeterminados usando estos métodos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;33(6): 425-432, Jun. -Jul. 2010. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84831</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio retrospectivo de la capacidad de evaluación de fibrosis hepática del FibroScan®, APRI, FIB-4 y FORNS con referencia a la biopsia hepática de pacientes con hepatitis crónica C, mono y coinfectados con VIH</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28614</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5862^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2834^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33344^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33344^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11406</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d413^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8272^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1226^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33344^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201007</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
