<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-33298</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-1285</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Control of the collagen network collapse: collagen remoral</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Resin penetration into and its reaction with the components of conditioned, mineralised dental tissues is known to be the fundamental micromechanical mechanism by which restorative materials can be successfully bonded to teeth. Monomers penetrated into conditioned dentin and concentrated in a superficial region of resin-reinforced dentin contributing significantly to the bond. The reinforcement, known as hybridization, involved impregnation, co-mingling and envelopment of collagen bundles and encapsulation of hydroxyapatite crystallites. A doubt raised concerning the quantitative contribution which the collagen network made to interfacial bond strength. lncreasing the thickness of the collagen network did not influence the assembly strength, and removal of the collagen with 5% sodium hypochlorite provided similar values to those recorded when the network was present (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ediciones Avances, S.L.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La penetración de la resina y su reacción con los componentes de los tejidos dentales desmineralizados es el mecanismo micromecánico con el cual los materiales restauradores de resina se unen al diente. Los monómeros penetran en la dentina acondicionada y se concentran en la región superficial contribuyendo a la unión. El refuerzo de esta zona con resina se conoce como hibridación, e implica la impregnación de la red de colágeno y el encapsulamiento de los cristales de hidroxiapatita. Han surgido dudas en cuanto a la contribución de la red de colágeno en el ensamblaje de la unión y en la fuerza interfacial, ya que el aumento del grosor de la red de colágeno no aumenta dicha fuerza y la remoción del colágeno con hipoclorito sódico al 5 por ciento en solución acuosa da valores similares de fuerza a los que se obtienen cuando la red de colágeno está presente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av Odontoestomatol;20(3): 123-130, mayo-jun. 2004. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Control del colapso del colágeno: desproteinización</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Osorio Ruiz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-33298</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33084^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29217^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29774</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
