<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163549</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1582</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Giant phyllodes tumour - Case report, oncoplastic treatment and literature controversies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Phyllodes tumour corresponds to 1% of breast primary tumours. Its primary treatment is presently surgical and, for several reasons, it usually requires breast reconstruction. First of all, an important breast volume is often removed, not only because it can easily achieve great dimensions, thanks to it fast growing potential, but also because wide excision is recommended to avoid its frequent but unpredictable local recurrence (meaning that ideal tumour resection margins are unknown). Second, it frequently affects young woman with more aesthetic concerns. We present a case of phyllodes tumour recurrence where oncoplastic surgery was necessary at both episodes and discuss the literature controversies on this subject, mainly related to treatment and prognosis prediction factors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gonzàlez-Farré, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Câmara, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vargas-Moniz, Joao</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tumor phyllodes representa el 1% de los tumores primarios de mama. Actualmente, su tratamiento primario es la cirugía y, por muchas razones, requiere normalmente reconstrucción de mama. Primeramente, porque a menudo es extirpado un importante volumen de mama, no sólo porque el tumor puede adquirir grandes dimensiones gracias a su alto potencial de crecimiento, sino también porque es recomendado una amplia excisión para evitar su frecuente pero impredecible recidiva local (los márgenes quirúrgicos ideales no son conocidos). Segundo, porque afecta frecuentemente a mujeres jóvenes con más preocupaciones estéticas. Presentamos un caso de recidiva de tumor phyllodes donde la cirugía oncoplástica fue necesaria en ambos episodios y discutimos las controversias en la literatura sobre este tema, principalmente dirigidos al tratamiento y a los factores pronósticos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. senol. patol. mamar. (Ed. impr.);30(2): 79-84, abr.-jun. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163549</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumor phyllodes gigante - Caso clínico, cirurgía oncoplástica y controversias en la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29995^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9572^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32722^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31817^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31817^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6010^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31817^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
