<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102507</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Healthcare and economic impact of vaccination against cervical cancer and precursor lesions in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To evaluate the healthcare and economic impact of vaccination against cervical cancer with the HPV 16/18 AS04-adjuvanted vaccine (Cervarix®) in Spain from the perspective of the national health system. Material and methods. A health economics model was adapted to the Spanish environment. The model simulated the impact of current vaccination programs on the burden of precancerous lesions and cervical cancer. National epidemiological data and the vaccine efficacy shown in clinical trials were used. Results. Considering the average vaccination coverage in Spain, the model estimated that vaccination with Cervarix® would prevent 45,060 cases of atypical squamous cells of undetermined significance (ASCUS), 35,166 cases of low-grade squamous intraepithelial lesions (LSIL), 29,549 cases of high-grade squamous intraepithelial lesions (HSIL) and 1,053 cases of cervical cancer. Thus, vaccination would save 89,271,085 &#128; in direct medical costs. Conclusions. Vaccination with Cervarix® in Spain would significantly reduce the number of cases of cervical cancer and precancerous lesions and the associated medical costs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castellsagué, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morano, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torné, Aureli</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Analizar el impacto sanitario y económico de la vacunación frente al cáncer de cérvix en España con la vacuna VPH 16/18 adyuvada AS04 (Cervarix®) desde la perspectiva del Sistema Nacional de Salud. Material y métodos. Adaptación al entorno español de un modelo farmacoeconómico que simula el impacto que podría esperarse de los actuales programas de vacunación infantil sobre la carga de las lesiones precursoras y cáncer de cérvix. El modelo emplea datos epidemiológicos nacionales y la eficacia demostrada por la vacuna en ensayos clínicos. Resultados. Considerando la cobertura vacunal media en España, el modelo estima que actualmente la vacunación con Cervarix® podría evitar anualmente 45.060 ASCUS, 35.166 lesiones CIN1, 29.549 lesiones CIN2/3 y 1.053 casos de cáncer de cérvix, lo que supondría evitar unos costes sanitarios totales de 89.271.085 euros. Conclusiones. La vacunación con Cervarix® en España disminuiría los casos de cáncer de cérvix y lesiones precursoras y los consecuentes costes sanitarios asociados a su tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);55(7): 299-303, ago.-sept. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102507</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto sanitario y económico de la vacunación frente al cáncer de cérvix y lesiones precursoras en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2617^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10399^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2623^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2624^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14811^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50090</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2623^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29592^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29592^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2623^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
