<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-15547</identifier>
<setSpec>1136-4890</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Detection of macroglial cells in the fish optic nerve by intracellular injection in fixed tissue</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this study we made intracellular injections of Lucifer Yellow fluorochrome into macroglial cells, astrocytes and oligodendrocytes of the fixed optic nerve of tench (Tinca tinca). From their three-dimensional morphology, we identified oligodendrocytes and at least four different types of astrocytes, both in the central zones of the nerve and in that forming part of the glia limitans. Moreover, we have identified and described groups of associated astrocytes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sociedad Anatómica Española</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este estudio realizamos inyecciones intracelulares del fluorocromo Amarillo Lucifer en las células macrogliales, astrocitos y oligodendrocitos del nervio óptico fijado de la tenca (Tinca tinca). En base a su morfología tridimensional, pudimos identificar oligodendrocitos y al menos cuatro tipos distintos de astrocitos, tanto en las zonas centrales del nervio como en la zona que forma parte de la glia limitans. Adicionalmente, identificamos y describimos grupos de astrositos asociados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Eur. j. anat;5(2): 89-95, sept. 2001. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Detección de células macrogliales en el nervio óptico de peces mediante inyección intracelular en tejido fijado</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Lara, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lillo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Weruaga, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aijón, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velasco, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cid, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jimeno, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-15547</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10080^s22071</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5588</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5535</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28186^s22071</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
