<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129608</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Substance-related abuse in health personnel: treatment programs</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Health personnel have some unique characteristics related with workload, stress, work shifts and long work hours. All these factors, as well as the easy access to drugs in their job, make them candidates for possible substance-related abuse. These addictions are also a risk for the health of a third group: the patients. There are diverse treatment programs with a single objective: to obtain the reincorporation of these professionals. Objectives: To know the current situation of substance related abuse, the treatment programs and their results with the health personnel. Methods: Structured bibliographical searches were made in the following databases: MEDLINE (PUBMED), Scopus, Web of Knowledge (WOK), IBECS, LILACS, SCIELO and grey literature. Results: A total of nine scientific articles from different sources were included. The evidence levels were low. There are treatment and reincorporation programs which achieve promising results (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Caballero Aranda, Inma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sevilla Lerena, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El colectivo sanitario tiene unas especiales características de carga de trabajo, estrés, turnicidad y jornada prolongada. Esto unido al fácil acceso a fármacos en su medio laboral, les hace susceptibles a posibles adicciones farmacológicas. Estas adicciones también suponen un riesgo para la salud de terceros. Existen diferentes programas de rehabilitación para conseguir la reincorporación de estos profesionales. Objetivos. Conocer la situación actual de las adicciones a fármacos, los programas de rehabilitación y sus resultados en el personal sanitario. Materiales y métodos: Se realizaron búsquedas bibliográficas en: MEDLINE (PUBMED), Scopus, Web of Knowledge (WOK), IBECS, LILACS, SCIELO y literatura gris. Resultados: Se incluyeron un total de nueve artículos científicos de diversa procedencia. Los niveles de evidencia encontrados fueron bajos. Existen programas de rehabilitación y reinserción con resultados prometedores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;60(235): 434-454, abr.-jun. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129608</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abuso de fármacos en medio sanitario: programas de tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31825</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4422^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24887^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
