<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163592</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Beneficial properties of mangosteen for health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The mangosteen (Garcinia mangostana L.) is a fruit of Asian origin, belonging to the family of Gutifferae and considered in Thailand as the «queen of fruits». Its effects on health benefit are attributed to xanthones, phenolic compounds present in the pericarp. Several researchers, with in vitro and in vivo studies, have proved their biological properties, among which we can highlight an important activity to combat reactive species of oxygen/nitrogen (ROS/RNS), anti-inflammatory activity, anticancer effects on various cancer cell lines (prostate, breast, leukemia, colon, etc.), antimicrobial activity, control of neuropsychiatric and cognitive symptoms and improvement parameters associated with obesity. In Spain, the mangosteen is starting to be used as a dietary supplement but we must be cautious, as we need more clinical trials in human beings to clarify the mechanisms of absorption, metabolism and elimination within the organism (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Periago, María Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro-González, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Codina Día, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El mangostán (Garcinia mangostana L.) es un fruto de origen asiático, perteneciente a la familia de las Gutíferas y considerado en Tailandia como «la reina de las frutas». Sus efectos en beneficio de la salud se atribuyen a las xantonas, compuestos de naturaleza fenólica presentes en la corteza. Varios investigadores, en estudios in vitro e in vivo, han demostrado sus propiedades biológicas, entre las que podemos destacar una importante actividad para combatir especies reactivas de oxígeno/nitrógeno (ROS/RNS), actividad antiinflamatoria, efectos anticancerígenos sobre varias líneas celulares de cáncer (próstata, mama, leucemia, colon, etc.), actividad antimicrobiana, control de síntomas neuropsiquiátricos y cognitivos y mejora de parámetros relacionados con la obesidad. En España, el mangostán está empezando a utilizarse como complemento alimenticio aunque debemos ser cautos, pues son necesarios más ensayos clínicos en humanos para aclarar sus mecanismos de absorción, metabolismo y eliminación en el organismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;21(3): 29-37, jul.-sept. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163592</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Propiedades beneficiosas para la salud del Mangostán</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1701^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35956</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8686^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d979^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51507</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d906^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
