<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158716</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fibrous cortical defect, please do not touch it</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The fibrous cortical defect is a common entity in children and the typical radiological image enables diagnosis. As these lesions are self-limited, no treatment is required. However, this lesion is not well known by pediatricians, which leads to an increased use of complementary tests and generates stress on patients and families. We present the case of a child with fibrous cortical defect recently diagnosed in our center (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Goikoetxea, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Ganuza, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Zallo, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Blanco, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andueza Sola, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El defecto fibroso cortical es una entidad común en la población infantil y su morfología radiológica típica permite el diagnóstico; dado su carácter involutivo no requiere tratamiento. Sin embargo, el desconocimiento de esta patología por parte de los pediatras conlleva un aumento de la demanda de exámenes complementarios y es generador de situaciones de estrés en pacientes y familiares. Se presenta el caso de un niño con defecto fibroso cortical recientemente diagnosticado en nuestro centro (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;18(72): 363-364, oct.-dic. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158716</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Defecto fibroso cortical, por favor no tocar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31268^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52593^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52593^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36500^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31268^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31268^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36500^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31268^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
