<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140624</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reasons for undergoing abortions among Cuban adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to identify the main reasons which lead to undergoing an abortion among Cuban adolescents. Method: a transversal descriptive study, in patients who had an abortion performed at the Curettage Department of the Hospital Universitario Mártires de Mayarí (Cuba), during the period from January to December, 2013. The study universe included 651 patients who attended the Abortion Department; the sample was finally made up of225 cases with subjects between 10 and 18 years of age, Results: a 55.3% of patients were included in the 14-to-16-year-oldage group. The predominance of psychogenic causes was confirmed; and within these, the most frequent ones were family violence (64%),followed by divorce and family conflict, with 21% and 18.4%,respectively.Conclusions: the reasons analyzed suggest that the active involvement by the Nursing Staff on the psychogenic causes for abortion can be very effective, and become an active part of treatment for improving the reproductive and sexual health of adolescents (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Sánchez, Yamicela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Gutiérrez, Raiza Mirtha</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bárcenas González, Mirsa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz Carballosa, Yosvanis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora Ramírez, Norma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maceo Seoanes, Edit</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: identificar los principales motivos que llevaron a la realización de un aborto en adolescentes cubanas. Método: estudio descriptivo transversal, en pacientes con aborto, asistido en el Servicio de Legrado del Hospital Universitario Mártires de Mayarí (Cuba), durante el periodo comprendido de enero a diciembre de 2013. El universo ascendió a 651 pacientes que acudieron al servicio de aborto; la muestra quedó conformada por 225 casos en edades comprendidas entre 10 y 18 años. Resultados: el 55,3% de las pacientes se encontró en el grupo de edad de 14 a 16 años. Se constató predominio de las causas psicogénicas y, dentro de ellas, las más frecuentes fueron la violencia familiar 64%, seguido de divorcio y conflicto familiar con 21% y 18,4%, respectivamente. Conclusiones: los motivos analizados sugieren que la participación activa del personal de Enfermería sobre las causas de aborto psicogénicas puede ser muy eficaz y formar parte activa en el tratamiento para mejorar la salud reproductiva y sexual de las adolescentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;18(4): 50-53, mayo 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140624</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Motivos de realización de un aborto en adolescentes cubanas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50242</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13116^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11695</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3482^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
