<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136549</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychosocial features of inflammatory bowel disease in the pediatric age group: acceptance of and adaptation to the disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Diagnosis of a chronic disease in children implies a series of major changes in their daily lives and in the family dynamics. Due to the symptoms, treatment and limitations imposed by IBD, the particular features of this disease may negatively affect the psychosocial development of pediatric patients at a time when their personalities are being formed, as well as the development of autonomy and the beginning of affective relationships. In the last few years, several studies have paid special attention to quality of life and mental health both in affected children and in their close family environment. The comprehensive care of pediatric patients with IBD should include the child&#146;s psychosocial domain and should also provide the resources necessary for satisfactory acceptance of and adaptation to the disease in children and their families (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín de Carpi, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El diagnóstico de enfermedad crónica en un niño implica una serie de cambios importantes en su vida diaria así como en toda la dinámica familiar. La enfermedad infl amatoria intestinal (EII) tiene unas peculiaridades (por su clínica, tratamiento y limitaciones) que pueden repercutir negativamente en el desarrollo psicosocial del paciente pediátrico durante fases importantes en la conformación de su propia personalidad, en la adquisición de autonomía y en el inicio de las relaciones afectivas. En los últimos años, diferentes estudios han prestado especial atención a la calidad de vida y a la salud mental, tanto del niño enfermo como de su entorno familiar más próximo. Una atención global del paciente pediátrico con EII deberá contemplar la esfera psicosocial del niño enfermo, así como ofrecer las armas necesarias para una correcta y satisfactoria aceptación y adaptación a ésta por parte del paciente y de su familia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;32(supl.2): 25-30, sept. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136549</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aspectos psicosociales de la enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
