<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157419</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The cohabitation of academia and industry: what position do the medical journals take regarding opinion articles?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Should medical journals publish editorials and educational articles written by authors who have financial conflicts of interest with pharmaceutical and biotechnology industries on whose products (or their competitors) they discuss? In the last 18 months, a controversy was sparked between The New England Journal of Medicine and BMJ, who took 2 opposite positions: the former stated that the negative bias against authors with conflicts of interest with industry is excessive and therefore accept articles from any expert, ensuring that they have the minimum possible bias. BMJ, in contrast, prohibits the publication of these types of article by authors who have financial conflicts of interest with industry. This article discusses the approaches of the 2 journals (and those of others) and reflects on this type of conflict in the medical profession (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dal-Ré, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carné, X</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">¿Deben las revistas médicas publicar editoriales y artículos de carácter educativo escritos por autores que presentan conflictos de intereses financieros con las industrias farmacéutica y biotecnológica de cuyos productos (o sus competidores) opinan? En los últimos 18 meses se ha desatado una polémica entre The New England Journal of Medicine y BMJ, que plantean 2 posturas opuestas: la primera entiende que el prejuicio negativo contra autores con conflicto de intereses con la industria es excesivo y, por tanto, acepta artículos de cualquier experto procurando que presenten el mínimo sesgo posible. BMJ, por el contrario, prohíbe publicar ese tipo de artículos por autores que tienen conflicto de intereses financieros con la industria. En este artículo se desarrollan las actitudes de ambas (y otras) revistas y se reflexiona sobre este tipo de conflicto en la profesión médica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;216(8): 423-426, nov. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157419</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La cohabitación de la academia y la industria: ¿qué postura toman las revistas médicas en relación con los artículos de opinión?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19089^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37728</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1894^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4407^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4407^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1894^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4407^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
