<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-37972</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality of life of obese patients submitted to bariatric surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The quality of life (QOL) of patients with morbid obesity (MO) is reduced given the restrictions it imposes. Bariatric surgery is considered an efficient treatment for MO as it leads to marked and progressive weight reduction. Weight loss, appropriate nutritional advice and follow up may induce significant improvement in QOL.  Aim: To evaluate the degree of QOL in patients with MO before and after bariatric, surgery (Fobi-Capella reducing gastroplasty).  Cases. Material and Methods: 95 morbidly obese(BMI &gt; 40 kg/m2) or moderately obese (BNI 35 - 39 kg/m2) patients with co-morbidities were seen, followed up and given advice by the Nutrition, Psychology, Endocrinology and Surgery staff at the Federal University of Bahia Hospital. Group I included 66 subjects at the pre-surgical stage and Group II was composed of 29 other patients in a late postsurgical phase. Group II patients were seen at 6, 12 and more months after bariatric surgery. The medical outcomes study Short-Form Health Survey (SF-36) was the instrument used to evaluate QOL in this study. Data were analyzed using the Mann-Whitney non-parametric method and the SPSS program.  Results: A statistically significant improvement in QOL was detected in the aspects of general health, functional ability and vitality. A progressive improvement in physical conditioning was particularly observed in the patients who had had bariatric surgery less than 6 months before, between 6 and 12 months and more than 12 months before. Small changes in subjective features were seen. An improvement in social aspects was observed after a post surgical fall. This explains why do not changes appear when pre and post surgical patients are compared.  Conclusions: Fobi-Capella bariatric surgery for our patients with MO or with co-morbidities associated moderate obesity resulted in QOL improvement, and gradual but marked improvements in physical condition over time (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Grupo Aula Médica, S.A.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La calidad de vida (QOL) de los pacientes con obesidad mórbida (OM) se ve reducida dadas las restricciones que esta situación impone. Se considera que la cirugía bariátrica es un tratamiento eficaz para la OM puesto que conduce a una reducción notable y progresiva del peso. Perder peso, el consejo dietético adecuado y el seguimiento pueden favorecer una mejoría notable en la QOL. Objetivo: Evaluar el grado de QOL en pacientes con OM, antes y después de la cirugía bariátrica (gastroplastia reductora de Fobi-Capella).Casos, material y métodos: Noventa y cinco pacientes obesos mórbidos (IMC &gt; 40 kg/m2), o moderados (IMC 35 -39 kg/m2) con comorbilidades, fueron vistos, seguidos y recibieron consejo por parte del personal de Nutrición, Psicología, Endocrinología y Cirugía del Federal University Bahia Hospital. El grupo I incluía individuos en la etapa prequirúrgica y el grupo II se componía de 29 pacientes distintos en una etapa posquirúrgica avanzada. A los pacientes del grupo II se les vio a los 6, 12 y más meses después de la cirugía bariátrica. Se utilizó el estudio de resultados médicos Short Form Health Survey (SF-36) para evaluar la QOL en este estudio. Se analizaron los datos utilizando el método no paramétrico de Mann-Whitney y el programa SPSS. Resultados: Se detectó una mejoría estadísticamente significativa en la QOL, en los aspectos de salud general, capacidad funcional y vitalidad. Se vio una mejoría progresiva en la forma física, particularmente en los pacientes que habían sido sometidos a cirugía bariátrica en los últimos 12 meses, entre los 6 y 12 meses, y hacía más de 6 meses. Se vieron pequeños cambios en los puntos subjetivos. Se observó un cambio en los aspectos sociales tras una caída posquirúrgica. Esto explica por qué los cambios no se ven cuando se comparan pacientes pre y posquirúrgicos. Conclusiones: La cirugía bariátrica de Fobi-Capella en nuestros pacientes con obesidad mórbida o con obesidad moderada y comorbilidades asociadas supuso una mejoría en la QOL, y una mejoría gradual, pero notable, en la situación física a lo largo del tiempo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;19(6): 367-371, nov. 2004. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida en pacientes obesos sometidos a cirugía bariátrica</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Lima Curvello, K</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Eduarda Paneili, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seal, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barreto Villela, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Braghrolli Neto, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-37972</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d9951</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28626</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23642</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23862</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200411</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
