<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156607</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Frey´s syndrome or auriculotemporal syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Frey´s syndrome or auriculotemporal syndrome is a rare disorder which is little known in Paediatrics, resulting often in a undiagnosed pathology or confuse it as a food allergy. We report the case case of a six-month-old breastfed baby with no relevant medical history, whose parents brought her to hospital due to a repeated bright erythema around the temples within seconds to minutes of ingesting fruit puree. The erythema resolves spontaneously within a few minutes, the baby does not reject the food and she does not show any other symptoms. We believe this is an important disorder to take into account since it generates additional tests and unnecessary visits to specialized departments, while it could be easily managed in a Primary Care center (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peinado Adiego, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arcauz Eguren, MP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olloqui Escalona, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de Frey o síndrome auriculotemporal es una entidad clínica poco conocida en Pediatría, lo que hace que muchas veces sea infradiagnosticada o confundida con una alergia. Presentamos el caso de una lactante de seis meses de edad, sin antecedentes de interés, cuyos padres acuden a la consulta de Pediatría por la aparición, de manera repetida y a los pocos minutos de comenzar la ingesta de papilla de frutas, de un eritema de color rojo tenue en ambas sienes. Este desaparece al cabo de unos minutos sin que el lactante muestre rechazo ni otra sintomatología. Creemos importante conocer esta entidad debido a que genera pruebas complementarias y derivaciones a consultas de atención de especializada innecesarias, siendo posible su manejo desde Atención Primaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;18(71): e93-e96, jul.-sept. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156607</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Frey o síndrome auriculotemporal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4977^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4977^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56121^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13928^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13928^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
