<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96448</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sexual adjustment and body image of mastectomized women due to breast cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of the present study is to analyze the effects that a mastectomy, due to breast cancer, has on the psychosexual adjustment and body image of women. On the one hand, sixty mastectomized women were assessed (thirty of them had been operated on less than one year ago, and the other thirty women had been operated on more than one year ago); on the other hand, thirty healthy women were assessed as a control group. The following measuring instruments were used: The Sexual Arousal and Satisfaction Scales of S.A.I.-Expanded, the Subscale of Physical Self-concept of the Self concept Scale of Tennessee and a structured interview created by us. In the results we did not find any statistically significant differences among the groups as regards sexual arousal and satisfaction, nor in the frequency of sexual encounters or orgasms, or in physical self concept. Nevertheless, about fifty per cent of women expressed that after the mastectomy they were worried about the resumption of their sexual encounters, they were afraid of being rejected by their partners and they had noticed a decrease in sexual interest. Likewise there is a significantly greater major number in both groups of mastectomized women who do not receive any caresses from their partners in the area of their breasts, who have more problems related to their own nakedness, and have a more negative assessment of their physical attractiveness. We concluded that the mastectomized women have alterations in sexuality and body image that remain after the first year after mastectomy, when there is no psychological intervention (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Ortiz, Jerónima</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antequera, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente estudio es analizar las repercusiones que tiene la mastectomía por cáncer de mama sobre la adaptación psicosexual y la imagen corporal de las mujeres. Se evalúan a 60 mujeres mastectomizadas (30 llevaban operadas menos de un año y otras 30 más de un año); de otro lado, se evaluaron 30 mujeres sanas como grupo control. Se utilizaron como instrumentos de medida: las Escalas de Excitación y Satisfacción del S.A.I.-Expanded, la Subescala de Auto concepto Físico de la Escala de Autoconcepto de Tennessee y una entrevista estructurada creada para esta investigación. Entre los resultados destacamos la inexistencia de diferencias entre los tres grupos en cuanto a excitación y satisfacción sexuales, ni en frecuencia de relaciones sexuales o de orgasmos, ni en auto concepto físico. No obstante, porcentajes cercanos al 50% de mujeres expresaron que tras la mastectomía estuvieron preocupadas por la reanudación de las relaciones sexuales, que tuvieron miedo al rechazo de la pareja y que habían notado una disminución de su interés sexual. Asimismo, hay un número significativamente mayor en ambos grupos de mujeres mastectomizadas que no reciben caricias en la zona del pecho por parte de sus parejas, manifiestan más problemas relacionados con la propia desnudez y tienen una valoración más negativa de su atractivo físico. Concluimos que las mujeres mastectomizadas presentan alteraciones en la sexualidad y en la imagen corporal que perduran transcurrido el primer año desde la mastectomía cuando no hay intervención psicológica (AU)P</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);7(2/3): 433-451, dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96448</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ajuste sexual e imagen corporal en mujeres mastectomizadas por cáncer de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33534^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8580^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
