<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152371</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of social skills in adults with intellectual disability: calibration of the SPSS-R Scale with Rasch model</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The study aims at calibrating the Social Performance Schedule Scale Revised (SPSS-R) in a sample of 181 adults with intellectual disability using the Rasch Andrich Rating Scale Model with the purpose of elucidating its structure, dimensionality and psychometric properties. In order to obtain a version with a clear factorial structure and coherent with the analysed construct (social skills), it was necessary to proceed with a drastic reduction of the scale. The resulting scale, composed of 24 items, showed the emergence of two distinct dimensions. Its psychometric properties (reliability and validity) turned out to be adequate, and it showed correct items and individuals fit to the Rasch model. According to their difficulty, the items concentrated in the mean zone of the analysed dimensions, which makes it advisable to include, in future studies, items in the high and low range of the latent variable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez, Laura E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva, Noemí</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias, Víctor B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias, Benito</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Henar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente estudio ha sido la calibración de la Escala de actuación social revisada (Social Performance Schedule Scale Revided, SPSS-R, en una muestra de 181 personas adultas con discapacidad intelectual, mediante el modelo de escalas de clasificación de Rasch-Andrich, a fin de clarificar su estructura, dimensionalidad y propiedades psicométricas. Fue necesaria una reducción drástica de la escala, a fin de obtener una versión con una estructura factorial clara y consistente con el constructo evaluado (habilidades sociales). La escala resultante, de 24 ítems, se configuró en dos dimensiones bien definidas. Sus propiedades psicométricas (fiabilidad y validez) resultaron adecuadas y presentó un correcto ajuste de ítems y personas al modelo de Rasch. Conforme a su dificultad, los ítems se concentraron en al zona media de las dimensiones evaluadas, lo que aconseja en futuras revisiones incluir ítems en rangos altos y bajos de la variable latente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;22(3): 479-500, 2014. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152371</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de las habilidades sociales en adultos con discapacidad intelectual: calibración de la escala SPSS-R mediante el modelo de Rasch</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55704</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2171^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8779^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
