<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91060</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Extracellular phospholipase activity of Malassezia strains isolated from individuals with and without dermatological disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. The Malassezia genus includes mainly lipophilic yeasts belonging to the cutaneous microbiota of man and other mammals. Some Malassezia species have been associated with various dermatological diseases. The factors permitting the transformation of yeasts of the Malassezia genus from a commensal organism to a pathogenic agent are still little known but the production of various enzymes such as lipase, phospholipase and lipoxygenase could contribute to the pathogenic activity of these yeasts. Aims. Here we have determined and compared the extracellular phospholipase activity of sixty human isolates of Malassezia so as to relate this feature to the species of Malassezia and to the origin (from dermatological diseases or not) of the strains examined. Methods. Phospholipase production was determined using the semi-quantitative egg-yolk plate method. Results and conclusions. Malassezia obtusa, Malassezia slooffiae, Malassezia globosa, Malassezia restricta had difficulty developing in the chosen culture medium so that it was not possible to measure phospholipasic activity. Malassezia pachydermatis showed the highest phospholipase activity. Twenty-nine Malassezia sympodialis strains produced phospholipase; the isolates from patients with pityriasis versicolor had significantly higher phospholipasic activity than those isolated from healthy individuals. This observation suggests that the phospholipasic activity of Malassezia may play a role in the onset of skin lesions, especially in the case of pityriasis versicolor(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pini, Gabriell</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Faggi, Elisabett</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. El género Malassezia incluye numerosas levaduras lipofílicas que pertenecen a la microbiota cutánea del hombre y de otros mamíferos. Algunas especies se han asociado con diversas dermatosis. Apenas se conocen los factores que permiten la transformación de las levaduras del género Malassezia de un microorganismo comensal a uno patógeno, pero la producción de diversas enzimas, como lipasas, fosfolipasas y lipooxigenasa, podría contribuir a la actividad patogénica de estas levaduras. Objetivos. En la presente investigación hemos determinado y comparado la actividad de la fosfolipasa extracelular a partir de 60 aislamientos de Malassezia en seres humanos para relacionar esta característica con las especies del género y con el origen (dermatosis o no) de las cepas examinadas. Métodos. La producción de fosfolipasa se determinó utilizando el método semicuantitativo de la placa de yema de huevo. Resultados y conclusiones. Malassezia obtusa, Malassezia slooffiae, Malassezia globosa y Malassezia restricta crecieron mal en el medio de cultivo seleccionado, por lo que no fue posible determinar la actividad fosfolipasa. Malassezia pachydermatis mostró la mayor actividad enzimática. Produjeron fosfolipasa 29 cepas de Malassezia sympodialis; los aislamientos de pacientes con pitiriasis versicolor se caracterizaron por una actividad fosfolipasa significativamente mayor que los aislamientos de individuos sanos. Esta observación sugiere que la actividad fosfolipasa de Malassezia podría desempeñar un papel en el inicio de las lesiones cutáneas, en particular en el caso de la mencionada micosis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;28(4): 179-182, oct.-dic. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91060</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actividad fosfolipasa extracelular de aislamientos de Malassezia de individuos con y sin dermatosis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8464^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8464^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8464^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4600^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4600^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4600^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10934^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
