<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120398</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Maternal fat mass may predict overweight/obesity in non-instituzionalized women with intellectual disability</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Previous studies have found a significant correlation between parents and offspring regarding overweight and obesity in general population at early life stages. However this issue has received no attention in people with intellectual disability (ID). Therefore, the present study was designed to find out potential correlations in overweight/obesity between young adult women with ID living in the family and their parents. Material and methods: In the present observational cross-sectional study, a total of thirty-four women with Down syndrome (n = 34; 22.6 ± 2.1 years; 29.6 ± 3.3 km/m2) were recruited through different community support groups for people with intellectual disabilities. Furthermore, biological mothers (n = 34; 59.6 ± 4.9 years; 28.5 ± 3.2 km/m2) and fathers (n = 34; 61.5 ± 5.3 years; 26.2 ± 2.7 km/m2) volunteered for this study. They all underwent an anthropometric assessment to determine body mass index (BMI). This protocol was approved by an Institutional Ethics Committee. Results: In the studied population, a total of 26 (76.5%) women with ID were overweight/obese. Furthermore, there were 22 (66.6%) overweight/obese mothers and 16(53.3%) fathers. Results also showed significant correlations between participants BMI and their father (r = 0.327; p = 0.0116) and mother BMI (r = 0.412; p &lt; 0.001). Lastly, overweight/obese women presented a stronger correlation with overweight/obese mothers (odds ratio 4.3; 95%CI 2.9-7.3) than fathers (odds ratio 3.1; 95%CI 1.6-4.4). Conclusion: Parental overweight/obesity, especially maternal one, was strongly associated to overweight/obesity in young adult women with DS. Accordingly, there is an urgent necessity of incorporating parents in the intervention programs designed to the prevention and treatment of overweight and obesity in people with ID (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Camacho-Molina, Alejandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordonez, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz, Antonio J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosety, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fornieles, Gabriel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosety, Miguel A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosety, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosety-Rodríguez, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alvero-Cruz, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Recientes estudios han encontrado en la población general una correlación entre la incidencia de sobrepeso/obesidad de padres e hijos, especialmente a edades tempranas. Sin embargo, este asunto no ha recibido atención en el caso de hijos adultos con discapacidad intelectual no institucionalizados. El presente estudio pretende determinar una posible correlación entre el sobrepeso/obesidad de padres respecto a sus hijas adultas con discapacidad intelectual que viven en el domicilio. Material y método: Se diseñó un estudio de tipo transversal observacional en el que participaron 34 mujeres adultas con síndrome de Down (22,6 ± 2,1 años; 29,6 ± 3,3 km/m2). Asimismo 34 madres (59,6 ± 4,9 años; 28,5 ± 3,2 km/m2) y 34 padres (61,5 ± 5,3 años; 26,2 ± 2,7 km/m2) biológicos participaron voluntariamente. Todos los participante se sometieron a un estudio cinenatropométrico en el que se obtuvo el índice de masa corporal (IMC). Este protocolo fue aprobado por un Comité de Ética Institucional. Resultados: El 76,5% de las mujeres con discapacidad intelectual estudiadas presentaba sobrepeso/obesidad. En cuanto a los progenitores, el 66,6% de las madres y el 53.3 de los padres también presentó sobrepeso/obesidad. El IMC de las participantes se correlacionó significativamente con el de sus madres (r = 0,412; p &lt; 0,001) y padres (r = 0,327; p = 0,0116). Por último, las participantes con sobrepeso/obesidad presentaron una fuerte correlación con sus progenitores con sobrepeso/obesidad, especialmente las madres (odds ratio 4,3; 95%CI 2,9-7,3) y en menor medida sus padres (odds ratio 3,1;95%CI 1,6-4,4). Conclusión: La masa grasa de los padres, especialmente la materna, podría recomendarse como predictor de sobrepeso/obesidad de hijas adultas con discapacidad intelectual no institucionalizadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;28(6): 1918-1921, nov.-dic. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120398</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La masa grasa materna como predictor de sobrepeso/obesidad en mujeres con discapacidad intelectual no institucionalizadas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9227^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d280^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
