<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141791</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-1342</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">An examination of the hypothesis that intraocular pressure elevation episodes can have prognostic significance in glaucoma suspects</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The efficacy of intraocular pressure reduction in retarding the progression of glaucoma has been demonstrated. This review examines the potential for prognostic advantage for glaucoma suspects in reducing their optic nerve head exposure to elevated intraocular pressure associated with activities which have been shown to elevate intraocular pressure. In this observational study, patients examined at the Centre for Eye Health (University of New South Wales) with a diagnosis of glaucoma suspect were surveyed to determine their histories for participation in activities which are known to elevate intraocular pressure. The evidence regarding the pathological significance of these sources of elevation in susceptible patients was examined. Apart from the universality of sleep-related intraocular pressure elevations, the histories from 183 confirmed glaucoma suspects indicate a wide range and variation in frequency of participation in other intraocular pressure elevating activities. A reduction in exposure to elevated intraocular pressure may improve the prognosis for glaucoma suspects. Additional patient specific assessment of the results of this screening could provide an indication of the degree (frequency, intensity level and duration) of exposure to elevated intraocular pressure. Such information may provide the basis for improving a patient's prognosis by helping them to identify opportunities to reduce such exposure to elevated intraocular pressure. Any benefit of reduction of such exposure appears likely to be greater if activities which elevate intraocular pressure are of long duration, occur frequently, occur over a long period of time, and/or involve high levels of intraocular pressure elevation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>McMonnies, Charles</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se ha demostrado la eficacia de la reducción de la presión intraocular para retardar la progresión del glaucoma. Esta revisión examina la posible ventaja de reducir la exposición de la cabeza del nervio óptico a la presión intraocular elevada asociada a las actividades que han demostrado que elevan dicha presión intraocular, en pacientes con sospecha de glaucoma. En este estudio observacional, se evaluó a los pacientes examinados en el Centro de Salud Ocular (University of New South Wales) con un diagnóstico de sospecha de glaucoma, para determinar sus antecedentes de participación en actividades, de las que se sabe que incrementan la presión intraocular. Se examinó la evidencia relativa a la significación patológica de estas fuentes de elevación en pacientes susceptibles. Aparte de la las bien conocidas elevaciones de la presión ocular relacionadas con el sueño, las historias de 183 sospechas de glaucoma confirmadas indican un amplio rango de variación de la frecuencia de participación en otras actividades que elevan la presión intraocular. La reducción de la exposición a la presión intraocular elevada puede mejorar el pronóstico de sospecha de glaucoma. La evaluación adicional y específica del paciente, de los resultados de esta revisión, podría aportar una indicación del grado (frecuencia, nivel de intensidad y duración) de la exposición a la presión intraocular elevada. Dicha información puede proporcionar la base de mejora del pronóstico del paciente, ayudándole a identificar las oportunidades para reducir dicha exposición a una presión intraocular elevada. Es probable que cualquier beneficio de reducción a tales exposiciones pueda ser superior si las actividades que elevan la presión intraocular se prolongan en el tiempo, y/o se producen con frecuencia y/o se producen durante un periodo prolongado y/o implican altos niveles de elevación de la presión intraocular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>J. optom. (Internet);8(4): 223-231, oct.-dic. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141791</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Examen de la hipótesis de que los episodios de elevación de la presión intraocular pueden tener una significación en el pronóstico de pacientes con sospecha de glaucoma</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28204^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10078^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28053^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
