<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047823</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intrauterine growth in a selected group of Peruvian neonates</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Subjects and methods: We performed a descriptive, cross sectional study with prospective enrollment of consecutive live newborns. The neonates were weighed and gestational age was determined by the last menstrual period. Exclusion criteria were maternal and fetal disease, maternal smoking and malnutrition. The Perinatal Computer System of the Latin-American Center for Perinatology and Human Development of the Panamerican Health Organization/World Health Organization and statistical tests were used.         Results: A total of 8,735 live newborns were selected (1995-2000). Week 40 of gestation was the most representative (36.7%). The mean weight was 3,514 g ± 403 g (10th, 50th and 90th percentiles were 2,983, 3,503 and 4,062 g, respectively). Comparison of Peruvian and Lubchenco curves according to weight revealed a visible graphic difference with significant differences in mean weight from weeks 37 to 42 of gestational age (p &lt; 0.001).         Conclusions: Growth curves according to weight, height, head circumference and ponderal index in a selected group of Peruvians newborn infants differed from Lubchenco's growth curves</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ticona Rendón, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Huanco Apaza, Diana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Obtener curvas de crecimiento intrauterino propia y representativa de un grupo seleccionado de recién nacidos peruanos y compararlo con las curvas de Lubchenco.         Sujetos y métodos: Estudio descriptivo, transversal y prospectivo de recién nacidos vivos sucesivos, técnica de pesaje, diagnóstico de edad gestacional por fecha de última menstruación; exclusión de patología materna y fetal; descarte de tabaquismo y desnutrición materna. Se usó el Sistema Informático Perinatal (CLAP-OPS/OMS) y pruebas estadísticas adecuadas.         Resultados: Un total de 8.735 recién nacidos vivos fueron seleccionados (1995-2000). La semana 40 de gestación fue la más representativa (36,7%), con un promedio de peso de 3.514 ± 403 g (los percentiles 10, 50 y 90 fueron: 2.983, 3.503 y 4.062 g, respectivamente). Comparando la curva peruana y de Lubchenco según el peso, se halló una diferencia gráfica y unos promedios de peso significativos desde la semana 37 a la 42 (p &lt; 0,001).         Conclusiones: Las curvas de crecimiento intrauterino según el peso, la talla, el perímetro cefálico y el índice ponderal en un grupo seleccionado de recién nacidos peruanos mostraron diferencias con la curva de crecimiento de Lubchenco</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);49(6): 298-304, jun. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047823</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Crecimiento intrauterino en un grupo seleccionado de recién nacidos peruanos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10757</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5443</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5428^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6278^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29399</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
