<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87578</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Thematic analysis of the discipline of physiotherapy in the Web of Science</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In spite of its youth, the area of physiotherapy has been developing all of its potential in recent years. This study has aimed to analyze those subjects of research that are being developed in this discipline according to the Web of Science database. A retrospective, longitudinal, descriptive and bibliometric study was done including the years 1945 to 2005. A thematic analysis was done through subject co-word analysis. There are 15 principal subjects in this area, the main ones being: Quality of life, Exercise, Low back pain, Mortality. The structure of the area is consistent and has good dynamics, although future project are needed to extend the study using other database and search engines in the interest of optimizing the discussion and the results (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Ríos, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Lorenzo,  C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Baños, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, Bailón</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La disciplina Fisioterapia, pese a su juventud, viene desarrollando todo su potencial de investigación en los últimos años. El objetivo de este estudio es analizar los temas de investigación que se están desarrollando en esta disciplina según la base de datos «Web of Science». Se realiza un estudio de corte bibliométrico descriptivo longitudinal retrospectivo desde 1945 hasta el 2005, realizando un análisis temático por el análisis de coocurrencia de las palabras. Existen 15 temas principales en esta disciplina, siendo los principales calidad de vida, ejercicio, lumbalgia y mortalidad. La estructura de la disciplina es homogénea y tiene una buena dinámica, si bien en futuros proyectos sería necesario ampliar el estudio mediante otras bases de datos y sistemas de búsqueda en aras de mejorar la discusión y la objetivación de los resultados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);32(4): 159-164, Abr. -Ago. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87578</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis temático de la disciplina Fisioterapia en la Web of Science</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28904</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36319^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
