<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102492</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Second renal biopsy in lupus nephritis: histopathological changes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Although lupus nephritis is a disease with frequent class switches, the usefulness of repeat renal biopsies is questionable in some cases. In order to assess the clinical utility of repeat biopsies, a retrospective study was made of our lupus nephritis patients who had undergone a second renal biopsy. Methods. Fourteen patients (28 biopsies) were included in the study. All biopsies were revised and classified according to ISN/RPS classification and activity and chronicity indexes were assessed. Class switches and necessity of treatment changes, based on histopathology, were determined. Acute and chronic changes between biopsies were also analyzed. Results. Main reasons for the second biopsy were proteinuria (recurrent, increased or de novo) in 10 cases (71.4%) and some degree of renal insufficiency in 4 (28.6%). In 6 patients (42.9%), there was no shift in nephritis class on repeat biopsies. All the cases with proliferative lesions in the first biopsy (6 cases) also showed proliferative lesions (100%) on the second biopsy, whereas 6 of 8 cases with non-proliferative lesions on the reference biopsy switched to proliferative lesions on the repeat biopsy (75%). Therefore, clinically significant class switches were more frequent in patients with non-proliferative lesions (P=.010). Chronicity index was significantly higher in the second biopsy (P=.003), while activity index was not statistically different (P=.306). Conclusion. These results show that therapeutically relevant switches from proliferative to non-proliferative lesions are a rare event and a second biopsy during a lupus nephritis flare could prove unnecessary in many cases. In the cases of a non-proliferative lesion in the reference biopsy, class switches are frequently found and repeat biopsies are advisable(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gil, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, Carlos Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias, Luis F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La nefritis lúpica es histológicamente cambiante, pero no está clara la utilidad de biopsias renales repetidas. Con el objetivo de conocer más sobre la utilidad de una segunda biopsia renal estudiamos retrospectivamente nuestros casos de pacientes con 2 biopsias renales. Métodos. Catorce pacientes (28 biopsias) fueron incluidos en este trabajo. Revisamos las biopsias y registramos la clase de nefritis e índices de actividad y cronicidad. Determinamos la necesidad de cambios terapéuticos basados en hallazgos histológicos y analizamos la evolución de lesiones agudas y crónicas. Resultados. Las razones para re-biopsiar fueron: proteinuria (recurrente, incrementada o de novo) en 10 casos (71,4%) o algún grado de insuficiencia renal en 4 casos (28,6%). En 6 pacientes (42,9%) no hubo cambio en la clase de nefritis. En 6 casos de lesiones proliferativas en la primera biopsia, la segunda mostró también lesiones proliferativas (100%), mientras que en 6 de 8 pacientes con lesiones no proliferativas hubo cambio a lesiones proliferativas (75%); por lo tanto, los cambios clínicamente importantes fueron más frecuentes en pacientes con lesiones no proliferativas (p=0,010). El índice de cronicidad fue significativamente mayor en la segunda biopsia (p=0,003). El índice de actividad no fue estadísticamente diferente (p=0,306). Conclusión. En recaídas o exacerbaciones de la enfermedad es infrecuente el viraje de lesiones proliferativas a no proliferativas, y una segunda biopsia podría no ser necesaria en muchos casos. En pacientes con lesiones no proliferativas en la biopsia inicial es frecuente el cambio a lesiones proliferativas, por lo que sería recomendable una segunda biopsia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;45(3): 157-162, jul.-sept.2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102492</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Segunda biopsia renal en nefritis lúpica: cambios histopatológicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11946^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7853^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11946^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7853^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19233^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19233^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
