<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165347</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Incidence of high body mass index in critically ill cancer patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The aims of this study were to describe the incidence of obesity and overweight in critically ill cancer patients, and to evaluate the clinical characteristics and Intensive Care Unit (ICU) outcomes of critically ill cancer patients with obesity and overweight. Methods: An observational cohort study. There were no interventions. Results: During the study period, 483 critically ill cancer patients were admitted to ICU, and 59.2% of them (258 patients) had high body mass index (BMI). Comparing the groups of patients with BMI &lt; 25 kg/m2 and &amp;#8805; 25 kg/m2, we observed that those with BMI &amp;#8805; 25 kg/m2 were older at the time of admission to the ICU. The global mortality in ICU was of 22.4%. ICU mortality was similar between patients with BMI &lt; 25 kg/m2 and &amp;#8805; 25 kg/m2 (21.3% versus 23.0%, p = 0.649). Univariate analysis indicated that the following fi ve factors were associated with ICU death in patients with BMI &amp;#8805; 25 kg/m2 as the outcome variable of interest: age, sepsis, invasive mechanical ventilation, type 2 diabetes, &amp;#8805; two organ failures. Multivariate analysis identified &amp;#8805; two organ failures as independent prognostic factor of ICU death. Conclusion: Critically ill cancer patients have a high incidence of high BMI; approximately six of every ten patients admitted to the ICU with a serious condition are overweight or show several degrees of obesity. The ICU mortality of the patients with a body mass index &lt; 25 kg/m2 and &amp;#8805; 25 kg/m2 was similar. The independent prognostic factor of ICU death in critically ill patients with a BMI &amp;#8805; 25 kg/m2 was the number of organ dysfunctions, especially when two or more organs were affected (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Guillén, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meneses-García, Abelardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arredondo-Armenta, Juan M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bautista-Ocampo, Andoreni R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera-Gómez, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ñamendys-Silva, Silvio A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Córdova-Sánchez, Bertha M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barragán-Dessavre, Mireya</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guevara-García, Humberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir la incidencia de obesidad y sobrepeso en pacientes graves con cáncer y evaluar las características clínicas y el pronóstico de los pacientes oncológicos gravemente enfermos con sobrepeso y obesidad. Métodos: Estudio observacional y descriptivo. No se realizó ninguna intervención. Resultados: Durante el periodo de estudio, 483 pacientes graves con cáncer fueron ingresados a la unidad de cuidados intensivos (UCI); el 59.2% (258 pacientes) tuvo índice de masa corporal (IMC) elevado. Al comparar los pacientes con IMC &lt; 25 kg/m2 y con IMC &amp;#8805; 25 kg/m2, se observó que los pacientes con IMC &amp;#8805; 25 kg/m2 eran de mayor edad al momento de ingresar en la UCI. La mortalidad en la UCI fue del 22.4%. La mortalidad fue similar en los grupos con IMC &lt; 25 kg/m2 y &amp;#8805; 25 kg/m2 (21.3% versus 23.0%, p = 0.649). El análisis multivariado determinó que las siguientes variables fueron asociadas con muerte en la UCI en el grupo de pacientes con IMC &amp;#8805; 25 kg/m2: edad, sepsis, ventilación mecánica invasiva, diabetes mellitus tipo 2 y cursar con dos o más fallas orgánicas. El análisis multivariado identificó como factor pronóstico independiente para muerte en la UCI cursar con dos o más fallas orgánicas. Conclusión: los pacientes graves con cáncer tienen una alta incidencia de IMC elevado; aproximadamente seis de cada diez pacientes ingresados en la UCI con una condición que pone en peligro la vida tienen sobrepeso o son obesos. La mortalidad fue similar en los grupos con IMC &lt; 25 kg/m2 y &amp;#8805; 25 kg/m2. En el grupo de pacientes con IMC &amp;#8805; 25 kg/m2 se identificó como factor pronóstico independiente para muerte en UCI el número de fallas orgánicas especialmente cuando dos o más órganos están afectados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;34(4): 856-862, jul.-ago. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165347</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incidencia de índice de masa corporal elevado en pacientes con cáncer críticamente enfermos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
