<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106843</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Elephantiasis nostras verrucosa in a patient with major depressive disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Elephantiasis nostras verrucosa is a rare condition characterised by papules, verrucous lesions, fibrosis and deformity of the affected area. It is caused by chronic lymphedema that could be congenital or produced by a non-associated infection (such as tuberculosis, mycotic infection, syphilis), surgery, radiotherapy, trauma, neoplastic obstruction, obesity, portal hypertension, or congestive heart failure. There is no standard treatment for this rare skin disorder. Depending on the cause and the severity, the treatment can be medical or surgical. We report the case of a man seen in our hospital with a major depression and elephantiasis nostras verrucosa skin lesions on both legs, who was successfully treated with surgical debridement and conservative measures (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Simón Llanes, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Niubó de Castro, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tamarit Francés, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coll Vilar, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La elefantiasis verrucosa nostras es una entidad poco frecuente que se caracteriza por pápulas, lesiones verrugosas, fibrosis y deformidad de la región afectada. Se debe a un linfedema obstructivo crónico que puede ser congénito o secundario a una infección no filariásica (tuberculosis, micosis, sífilis), cirugía, radioterapia, traumatismo, obstrucción neoplásica, obesidad, hipertensión portal o insuficiencia cardíaca congestiva. No hay un tratamiento estándar para estas raras manifestaciones cutáneas. Dependiendo de la causa y la severidad, el tratamiento puede ser médico o quirúrgico. Presentamos el caso de un varón que acudió a nuestro hospital con una depresión mayor y lesiones en la piel de ambas piernas compatibles con elefantiasis verrucosa nostras, que se trató con éxito con desbridamiento quirúrgico y medidas conservadoras (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);38(8): 526-529, nov.-dic. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106843</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Elefantiasis verrucosa nostras en paciente afectado de trastorno depresivo mayor</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1593^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4677^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4677^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4677^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4677^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4677^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4677^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
