<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122913</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Benefits of deep encoding in Alzheimer Disease. Analysis of performance on a memory task using the Item Specific Deficit approach</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: the aim of this study is to test the encoding deficit hypothesis in Alzheimer disease (AD) using a recent method for correcting memory tests. To this end, a Spanish-language adaptation of the Free and Cued Selective Reminding Test was interpreted using the Item Specific Deficit Approach (ISDA), which provides three indices: Encoding Deficit Index, Consolidation Deficit Index, and Retrieval Deficit Index. Methods: We compared the performances of 15 patients with AD and 20 healthy control subjects and analysed results using either the task instructions or the ISDA approach. Results: patients with AD displayed deficient encoding of more than half the information, but items that were encoded properly could be retrieved later with the help of the same semantic  clues provided individually during encoding. Virtually all the information retained over thelong-term was retrieved by using semantic clues. Encoding was shown to be the most impaired process, followed by retrieval and consolidation. Discriminant function analyses showed that ISDA indices are more sensitive and specific for detecting memory impairments in AD than are raw scores.  Conclusions: These results indicate that patients with AD present impaired information encoding, but they benefit from semantic hints that help them recover previously learned information. This should be taken into account for intervention techniques focusing on memory impairments in AD (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oltra Cucarella, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Duque, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Elvira, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El presente trabajo tiene como objetivo comprobar la hipótesis del déficit de codificación en la enfermedad de Alzheimer (EA)mediante el uso de una reciente metodología de corrección de test de memoria. Para ello, una adaptación espa&#152;nola del Free and Cued  Selective Reminder Test fue interpretada mediante el Item Specific Deficit Approach (ISDA), el cual proporciona 3 índices: Índice de déficit de codificación, Índice de déficit de consolidación e Índice de déficit de recuperación. Métodos Se comparó el rendimiento de 15 pacientes con EA y 20 sujetos sanos, y los resultados se analizaron mediante las instrucciones originales de la prueba y mediante el enfoque ISDA. Resultados: Los participantes con EA codificaron de manera deficitaria más de la mitad de la información, pero aquella bien codificada fue recordada posteriormente utilizando las claves semánticas proporcionadas individualmente durante la codificación. Prácticamente la totalidad de la información recordada a largo plazo fue la recuperada con claves semánticas. La codificación fue el proceso más alterado, seguido de la recuperación de la información y del almacenamiento. Los análisis discriminantes mostraron que los índices ISDA son más sensibles y específicos que las puntuaciones brutas para la detección de alteraciones mnésicas en la EA. Conclusiones: Los resultados indican que las personas con EA presentan alteraciones en la codificación de la información, pero se benefician de ayudas semánticas para la recuperación a largo plazo de la información previamente aprendida, lo que debería ser utilizado en las intervenciones centradas en las alteraciones de memoria en la EA (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;29(5): 286-293, jun. 2014. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122913</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Beneficios de la codificación profunda en la enfermedad de Alzheimer. Análisis del rendimiento en una tarea de memoria mediante el Item Specific Deficit Approach</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12374</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2990</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8776</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
