<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165256</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">«I am a complete woman»: Dragon boat and breast cancer survival</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Being diagnosed with breast cancer is like receiving a death sentence. While some surrender to their fate with diminished meaning of life, others manage to accept the challenges of their condition and move on with greater appreciation of life. This qualitative study examined the experiences of breast cancer survivors whose engagement with dragon boat enhanced their quality of life despite the traumatic discovery, treatment and long-term effects resulting from the illness. A focus group discussion (FGD) was conducted with three Filipina survivors of breast cancer who were actively engaged in dragon boat paddling. The in-depth discussion among the participants provided rich data on their survival of breast cancer and how dragon boat provided them physical and psychosocial benefits. Thematic analysis of the transcription data from the FGD yielded the following themes: (1) family as source of strength, (2) acceptance of breast cancer, (3) mutually supporting relationships, (4) increased personal strengths, (5) greater appreciation of life and (5) I Am a Complete Woman. Results were discussed within the framework of the Post-Traumatic Growth model (Schaefer and Moos, 1998) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Orsolino Zavala, Margarita Asunción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guinto-Adviento, Maria Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Recibir el diagnóstico de cáncer de mama es como recibir una sentencia de muerte. Mientras algunas personas se rinden a su destino con el sentido de vida disminuido, otras logran aceptar los desafíos de su condición y seguir adelante con una mayor apreciación de la vida. Este estudio cualitativo examinó las experiencias de supervivientes de cáncer de mama cuyo compromiso con el barco dragón mejoró su calidad de vida a pesar del descubrimiento traumático, el tratamiento y los efectos a largo plazo derivados de la enfermedad. Se llevó a cabo una discusión de grupo de enfoque con tres supervivientes de cáncer de mama filipinos que participaron activamente en el remo de barco dragón. La discusión en profundidad entre los participantes proporcionó datos enriquecedores sobre su supervivencia al cáncer de mama y cómo el barco dragón les proporcionó beneficios físicos y psicosociales. El análisis temático de los datos de transcritos de la discusión de grupo de enfoque produjo los siguientes temas: (1) la familia como fuente de fuerza, (2) la aceptación del cáncer de mama, (3) las relaciones de apoyo mutuo, (4) fortalezas personales aumentadas, (5) mayor apreciación de la vida y (5) soy una mujer completa. Los resultados se discutieron en el marco del modelo de crecimiento post-traumático (Schaefer y Moos, 1998) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;26(supl.3): 12-16, 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165256</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">«Soy una mujer completa»: El bote dragón y la supervivencia del cáncer de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31019^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8580^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30727^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10873</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
