<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84490</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-6585</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Salivary pH alterations in smoker patients with periodontal disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Several studies have found smoking a significant risk factor for periodontitis. Smoking alters salivary pH in order to improve nicotine absorption. Resting salivary pH estimate a range of 5.5 to 7.9, with the higher pH exhibited upon increased salivary flow. Imbalance of pH might constitute a local factor for periodontal disease activation. Objective: The purpose of this study was to determine the association of salivary pH with periodontal disease status in smokers and non-smokers. Materials and methods: 20 individuals were included in the study. 10 smokers and 10 non-smoker. Periodontal status was assed and the whole mouth unstimulated saliva was collected, measured and pH estimated extra orally. Means of pH were compared statically using SPSS 11.5.Results and conclusions: The difference between mean pH of smokers and non-smokers was statistically significant. Different levels of periodontal disease were found on both groups. The results of this study suggest that pH alteration may contribute to periodontal disease in smoker patients however it is not the main aspect of the pathogenesis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bascones Martínez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villarroel-Dorrego, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Osorio González, AY</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El tabaquismo es un factor de riesgo muy importante en la enfermedad periodontal. Para que la nicotina sea absorbida efectivamente el pH de la saliva pareciera sufrir cambios en sus propiedades. Se estima que el pH en la saliva no estimulada oscila entre 5,5 a 7,9, aumentando a medida que aumenta el flujo salival. Alteraciones del pH pudieran ser una de las causa de la activación de la enfermedad periodontal en fumadores. Objetivo: El propósito de este trabajo fue determinar la asociación entre el pH salival y la enfermedad periodontal en pacientes fumadores. Materiales y métodos: 20 individuos fueron incluidos en el estudio posterior a evaluación periodontal.10 conformaron el grupo de fumadores y 10 no fumadores. La saliva no estimulada de cada individuo fue recolectada y el pH determinado. Las medias de pH se compararon estadísticamente usando el software SPSS 11.5.Resultados y conclusiones: La diferencia entre el pH de ambos grupos no fue estadísticamente significativa, sin embargo si se observaron diferencias en relación al estatus periodontal de cada uno .Pareciera que el pH salival pudiera contribuir en la enfermedad periodontal de pacientes fumadores sin embargo no el factor fundamental en dicha patogénesis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. periodoncia implantol. oral;21(2): 71-75, ago. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84490</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alteración del pH salival en pacientes fumadores con enfermedad periodontal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10709^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7014^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12838^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
