<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041859</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sciaticblockade at the level of the popliteal fossa. Comparison between two approaches</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives:To assess the benefits and drawbacks, both for thephysician and for the patient, of the blockade of the sciaticnerve at the level of the popliteal fossa comparing the rearand the lateral approach.Material and methods:A prospective study was performed on 66 patients ASAI-II that were candidates for orthopedic foot surgery. Patientswere randomized to two groups: group A (33 patients)in which the rear approach would be used andgroup B (33 patients) in which the lateral approach wouldbe used. The local anesthetic used was mepivacaine 1.5%(20 ml). All the patients received prior medication with midazolam2 mg, i.v.The following parameters were determined: age,weight, height, gender, difficulty for the anesthesiologist tofind the anatomical references of the entrance point (high,medium, low), number of needle punctures before locatingthe nerve, time elapsed till the puncture to the location ofthe nerve, discomfort of the patient during the puncture(rated in a visual analogical scale from 0 to 10), toleranceof the patient to prone and supine position, global patientsatisfaction (poor, regular, good, very good, excellent) andcomplications associated to the technique.Results:No significant differences were found between the twogroups in terms of demographic characteristics, anatomicaldifficulty and global patient satisfaction. Blockade performedthrough the lateral approach results in a greaternumber of punctures, a longer procedure, greater discomfortfor the patient and a higher risk of arterial puncture.Only two of the patients studied had some difficulty withthe prone and supine position.Conclusions:The rear route is preferable for this procedure, althoughthe lateral route is an alternative that has to be consideredin some patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rufino, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego, R. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Jiménez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palacios, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santiago, F. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Banqueri, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos:Valorar las ventajas e inconvenientes, tanto desde elpunto de vista médico como del paciente, del bloqueo delnervio ciático a nivel del hueco poplíteo comparando la víaposterior y la lateral.Material y métodos:Se realizó un estudio prospectivo en 66 pacientes ASAI-II, propuestos para cirugía ortopédica del pie. Los pacientesfueron distribuidos de forma aleatoria en dos grupos,grupo A (33 pacientes): abordaje posterior y grupo B (33pacientes): abordaje lateral. El anestésico local utilizado fuemepivacaína 1,5% (20 ml). Todos los pacientes fueron premedicadoscon midazolan 2 mg, i.v. Se estudiaron los siguientes parámetros: edad, peso, altura,sexo, dificultad por parte del anestesiólogo para encontrarlas referencias anatómicas del punto de entrada (alta,media, baja), número de pases de la aguja hastaencontrar el nervio, tiempo desde el momento de la punciónhasta la localización del nervio, disconfort del pacientedurante la punción (en una escala visual analógica de 0 a10), tolerancia del paciente al decúbito prono, satisfacciónglobal del paciente (mala, regular, buena, muy buena, excelente)y complicaciones derivadas de la técnica.Resultados:No se encontraron diferencias significativas entre losdos grupos en cuanto a las características demográficas, dificultadanatómica y satisfacción global del paciente. El bloqueopor vía lateral presenta mayor número de pases,tiempo de ejecución, disconfort del paciente y un riesgomayor de punción arterial. Sólo dos de los pacientes estudiadospresentaron algún grado de dificultad para posicionarseen decúbito prono.Conclusiones:La vía posterior es de elección en este bloqueo y la víalateral es una alternativa a tener en cuenta en ciertos pacientes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;12(5): 264-268, jun.-jul. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041859</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bloqueo ciático a nivel de la fosa poplítea. Comparación entre dos abordajes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1348^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12965^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19248^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8791^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9600^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
