<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053181</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recent developments in metabolic syndrome, population aging, and the clinical interpretation of new atrial fibrillation guidelines</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article reviews the main developments reported during the last year concerning metabolic syndrome, population aging, and new atrial fibrillation guidelines. The principal aim was to provide the clinical cardiologist with an overview of recent 2006 publications and conference reports on these topics, which have been selected for their broad clinical implications</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Borrás, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escobar, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrios, Vivencio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedreira, Milagros</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo es una revisión de las principales novedades que se han publicado en el último año sobre el síndrome metabólico, el envejecimiento de la población y las nuevas guías de fibrilacion auricular. Nuestro objetivo ha sido ofrecer al cardiologo clínico una revisión sobre las últimas conferencias y publicaciones de 2006 relacionadas con estos temas que hemos seleccionado como de gran utilidad para todos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;60(supl.1): 101-110, 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053181</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Novedades en el síndrome metabólico, envejecimiento poblacional y visión del clínico de las nuevas guías en fibrilación auricular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6501^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6501^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27760</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
