<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92062</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Home hospitalization directly from emergency department: an efficient alternative to standard inpatient hospitalization</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: To compare technical quality, patient health outcomes, and satisfaction degree of patients admitted to hospital at home (HAH) from the emergency department (ED) with those with standard hospitalization (SH). Patients and methods: Comparative prospective study. Medical records of patients admitted to the HAH were reviewed and then they were also called and surveyed. The following variables were recorded: demographic and clinical aspects, patient health status at the time of phone survey, technical and perceived quality. Results: Patients included: 111 (65 from the ED and 46 from the SH). Phone survey was performed to 76 patients and 57 carers. Length of stay was significantly shorter in patients from the ED compared with those from SH (1.02±0.44 vs 2.23±0.94 days, P&lt;.0005). No other differences were observed in patients&#146; demographics, clinical aspects and health status, in technical quality, and in perceived quality between both groups.Conclusion: When HAH is an option, these results seem to indicate that patient hospital stay can be shortened if HAH admittance is obvious, after a period of patient treatment and stabilization, from the ED instead from HAH (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Coll-Vinent, Blanca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguiló, Sira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miró, Oscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antolín, Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, Sònia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Comparar la calidad técnica, los resultados de salud y el grado de satisfacción de los pacientes ingresados en una Unidad de Hospitalización a Domicilio (UHDOM) desde urgencias de los que lo hicieron desde una sala de hospitalización convencional. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio comparativo y descriptivo, con recogida de datos efectuada mediante revisión del informe de alta de los pacientes ingresados en la UHDOM y entrevista telefónica posterior. Se analizaron aspectos clínicos y de comorbilidad, resultados de salud, indicadores de calidad técnica y calidad percibida por pacientes y cuidadores.Resultados: Se incluyeron 111 pacientes (65 de urgencias y 46 de salas convencionales). Se realizó entrevista telefónica a 76 pacientes y 57 cuidadores. No se observaron diferencias en relación a los resultados de salud, indicadores de calidad técnica o calidad percibida de los pacientes. El tiempo de estancia hospitalaria fue inferior en los pacientes procedentes de urgencias (media [DE] de 1,02 [0,44] frente a 2,23 [0,94] días, p&lt;0,0005).Conclusiones: Podría obviarse el período de hospitalización convencional y todos los pacientes candidatos, tras un período de observación en urgencias, podrían ingresar directamente en hospitalización domiciliaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);137(13): 587-590, nov. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92062</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hospitalización a domicilio directamente desde urgencias: una alternativa eficiente a la hospitalización convencional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32196^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201111</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
