<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99499</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Results from the application of a quality management system in the community pharmacy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION: Protein intake in andalusian population presents values near 200% recommended intake 1, can affect kidney and liver function. In this situation, levels of specific biomarkers of the function of these organs will be altered and can cause irreversible damage sometimes.                                  OBJECTIVES: This study analyzed the frequency of protein intake and parameters related to protein metabolism in a sample of young people from the province of Granada.               METHODOLOGY: The study was conducted with 71 healthy students (15 men and 56 women) from the University of Granada, aged between 18 and 31 years. We proceeded to the extraction of blood samples to obtain serum and the subsequent determination of biochemical parameters of protein nutritional status. We determined anthropometric parameters, such as size, weight and body mass index. We made a survey of frequency of consumption of high protein foods.        RESULTST: he results show a frequency of consumption higher than recommended in birds of 20.3%, for1% beef and pork in 6%. Interestingly we found a significant positive correlation between pulse and intake of beef. With respect to the results in levels of creatinine, urea and uric acid was observed that 13% of the population showed urea levels higher than reference. Determinations made on urine remains normal in 100% of cases. Equally significant negative correlation was obtained between the levels of creatinine and uric acid with positive size and between the levels of urea and age.                                  CONCLUSIONS: Our results confirm the expected data and reported by other authors 2, since high protein intake can alter the values found for reference in the renal damage biomarkers such as urea, uricacid and creatinine. It would therefore be advisable to improve preventive training the population on the recommendations of the intake of protein foods, trying to change traditional habits common in Spanish population(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Planells, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lisbona, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Felices, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mata-Soto, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallardo-Escudero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Aliaga, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alférez, M. J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">CONCLUSIÓN: nuestros resultados confirman los datos esperados y referidos por otros autores 2, ya que las ingestas proteicas altas encontradas pueden alterar los valores de referencia en los biomarcadores de daño renal tales como la urea, el ácido úrico y la creatinina. Por tanto seria aconsejable mejorar la formación preventiva de la población sobre las recomendaciones de la ingesta de alimentos proteicos, intentando cambiar hábitos de consumo clásicos frecuentes en la población española(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;51(supl.3): 401-406, jul. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99499</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio del metabolismo proteico en una población de jóvenes sanos: factores asociados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52841^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3421^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3421^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52841^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14926^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14926^s22065</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23923^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23923^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23923^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201007</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
