<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162085</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of childhood sexual abuse on the sexual and affective relationships of adult women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyse perceived sexual satisfaction, sexual dysfunction, satisfaction with affective relationships and confidence and communication in existing relationships, related to a past history of childhood sexual abuse (CSA) and type suffered, among women treated as part of the Catalonian Sexual and Reproductive Health Care Programme (PASSIR). Method: Multicentric, descriptive, cross-sectional study. A total of 1,013 women over the age of 18 years, who underwent psychological therapy at any of the 24 PASSIR centres, were enrolled. A structured, anonymised, self-administered Sex History Questionnaire adapted from Wyatt (1985) &amp; Dubé et al. (2005), and the Female Sexual Function Index (Rosen, 2000), were used. Statistical analysis was descriptive, bivariate and multivariate. Results: Women who suffered childhood sexual abuse had a significantly higher prevalence of sexual dysfunction, with lower perceived sexual satisfaction. CSA with penetration or attempted penetration was associated with greater arousal difficulties and greater rejection. Women who experienced CSA were less confident and experienced greater communication difficulties with their partner. Conclusions: It is necessary to identify potential childhood sexual abuse among women who seek therapy due to relationship problems. It is also necessary to continue research into protective factors and therapeutic interventions to alleviate the consequences of CSA in adult life (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cobo, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Faro, Concepció</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lopetegui, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monteagudo, Mònica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pujol Ribera, Enriqueta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, Sílvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández,  María Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar la satisfacción sexual percibida, las disfunciones sexuales, la satisfacción con las relaciones afectivas, la confianza y la comunicación con la pareja actual, en función del antecedente de abuso sexual en la infancia y la adolescencia, y el tipo padecido, en mujeres atendidas dentro del Programa de Atención a la Salud Sexual y Reproductiva de Catalunya (PASSIR). Método: Estudio multicéntrico, descriptivo y transversal. Participaron 1013 mujeres mayores de 18 años, atendidas en visita psicológica en los 24 Centros del PASSIR. Se utilizó un cuestionario estructurado autoadministrado y anónimo adaptado del Cuestionario de abuso sexual en la infancia y adolescencia de Wyatt (1985) y Dubé et al. (2005), y el Female Sexual Function Index de Rosen (2000). Análisis estadístico descriptivo, bivariado y multivariado. Resultados: Todas las disfunciones sexuales resultaron significativamente más frecuentes en las mujeres que padecieron abuso sexual en la infancia y la adolescencia, y la satisfacción sexual percibida fue menor. Las situaciones de abuso sexual con intento de penetración o penetración se asociaron a más dificultades de excitación y mayor rechazo. Las mujeres que sufrieron abuso sexual en la infancia y la adolescencia manifestaron menos confianza y más dificultades de comunicación con la pareja. Conclusiones: Es necesario identificar un posible abuso sexual en la infancia y la adolescencia en las mujeres que consultan por problemas con sus parejas, y continuar investigando sobre factores protectores e intervenciones terapéuticas tendentes a paliar las consecuencias de dicho abuso al llegar a la vida adulta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;31(3): 210-219, mayo-jun. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162085</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto del abuso sexual durante la infancia-adolescencia en las relaciones sexuales y afectivas de mujeres adultas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33534^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23027^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52949^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19101^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
