<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146169</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Short bowel syndrome and nutritional enteral</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The particularity of this case is the nutritional management that has managed to avoid the use of prolonged parenteral nutrition and possible complications by placing jejunal tube at the distal end in patients with short bowel. It is a 34-year-old colecistectomizado complicated with postoperative peritonitis and dehiscence; two years he studied with small bowel obstruction, he was made de-volvulus and was complicated with two leak at different times after the second escape took place jejunostomy side double barreled shotgun level dehiscence, presented high debits by afferent loop of the terminal jejunostomy; during admission, polyurethane probe enteral feeding was inserted by the efferent loop jejunostomy. He received jejunal tube feeding laundry in the efferent loop terminal with decreased weight gain and subsequent reconstruction of intestinal transit debit proximal jejunostomy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ariadel Cobo, Diana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereira Cunill, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Socas Macías, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Liébana, Eulalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Conde, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Luna, Pedro Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Aguayo, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Lo más característico del presente caso es el manejo nutricional del paciente, que ha logrado evitar la utilización de nutrición parenteral total de forma prolongada y sus posibles complicaciones, mediante la administración de una nutrición enteral a través de una sonda yeyunal en el extremo distal de una ileostomía en un paciente con intestino corto severo. Se trata de un hombre de 34 años de edad, con antecedentes de colecistectomía complicada con peritonitis postquirúrgica y dehiscencia, que a los dos años desarrolló un cuadro de obstrucción de intestino delgado, por lo que se realizó devolvulación de intestino delgado que se complicó con dos fugas intestinales en diferentes tiempos; tras la segunda fuga se realizó yeyunostomía lateral en doble cañón de escopeta a nivel de la dehiscencia; presentó altos débitos por el asa aferente de la yeyunostomía terminal; durante el ingreso se insertó una sonda de poliuretano para alimentación enteral por asa eferente de la yeyunostomía. Recibió nutrición enteral por sonda yeyunal colada en el asa eferente con disminución del débito de yeyunostomía proximal terminal y ganancia de peso con posterior reconstrucción del tránsito intestinal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(6): 2958-2960, dic. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146169</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nutrición enteral en síndrome de intestino corto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22926^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30324^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38344^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13158^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
