<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130638</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7113</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The history of the Spanish Association of Toxicology. It is showed the creation and establishment of the Spanish Association of Toxicology. It is described each of the activities and its constituent element: information, sections, Board, Journal of Toxicology, congresses, Spanish Register of Toxicologists, Spanish Committee of Toxicology CeTox, toxicological glossary. Furthermore, it is concluded the aim of promoting the development and the promotion of training in Toxicology in both Spain and Iberoamerica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peña de Torres, E. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se detalla la creación y constitución de la Asociación Española de Toxicología y una descripcion pormenorizada de cada una de las actividades y elementos que la constituyen: Información, Secciones, Junta Directiva, Revista de Toxicología, Congresos, Registro Español de Toxicólogos, Comité Español de Toxicología CeTox, Glosario toxicológico; se concluye con la vocación de la AETOX de promover el desarrollo y formación de la Toxicología tanto en España como en Iberoamérica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. toxicol;31(1): 1-8, ene.-jun. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130638</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Historia de la Asociación Española de Toxicología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32415^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3250^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3250^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14509^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14509^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14509^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14509^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14509^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201401</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
