<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050760</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Non-progressive congenital ataxias</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Non-progressive congenital ataxias (NPCA) constitute a heterogeneous group of processes linked todiverse aetiological factors that can be either environmentally or genetically determined. The signs of cerebellar compromise,which are preceded by unspecific signs such as early hypotonia, difficulty in sucking or chewing or retarded motor acquisition,become apparent with development or may remain absent when the disorder is very severe. Development. NPCA can beaccompanied by a number of pathologies and their diagnosis can be made easier by the concurrence of symptoms or signs ofextra-cerebellar involvement, such as dysmorphic features or abnormalities affecting the skin, heart, bones, blood, eyes orother areas of the central or peripheral nervous system. Neuroimaging usually reveals vermian hypoplasia and/or hypoplasiaof the cerebellar hemispheres, but can be normal in certain situations. The article includes a review of the NPCA following theclassification proposed by Steinlin in 1998. Conclusions. The difficulties inherent in diagnosing these processes makes it necessaryto deploy a wide range of complementary examinations, especially metabolic tests, before a generic diagnosis of NPCA can beestablished. Although the progress made in molecular genetics has made it possible to categorise NPCA better, both theircausation and their hereditary or sporadic nature remain unknown in about 50% of cases</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castro-Gago, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Eirís-Puñal, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Lado, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las ataxias congénitas no progresivas(ACNP) conforman un grupo heterogéneo de procesos ligados afactores etiológicos diversos, bien ambientales o genéticamentedeterminados. Precedidos por signos inespecíficos como hipotoníaprecoz, dificultades para la succión o masticación o retraso en adquisicionesmotrices, los signos de afectación cerebelosa se ponende manifiesto con el desarrollo o pueden estar ausentes cuando laafectación es muy grave. Desarrollo. Son múltiples las entidadesque cursan con ACNP y su diagnóstico puede verse facilitado porla concurrencia de síntomas o signos de afectación extracerebelosacomo rasgos dismórficos, anomalías cutáneas, cardiológicas,óseas, hematológicas, oculares o en otras localizaciones del sistemanervioso central o periférico. La neuroimagen muestra habitualmentehipoplasia vermiana y/o de hemisferios cerebelosos, peropuede ser normal en situaciones determinadas. Se aporta una revisiónde las ACNP siguiendo la clasificación que propuso Steinlinen 1998. Conclusiones. Las dificultades diagnósticas inherentes aestos procesos obligan a un despliegue amplio de exploracionescomplementarias, en especial metabólicas, antes de establecer eldiagnóstico genérico de ACNP. Los avances en genética molecularpermiten una mejor categorización de las ACNP, a pesar de lo cualen alrededor del 50% de los casos siguen siendo desconocidos tantosu etiología como su carácter hereditario o esporádico</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;43(10): 621-629, nov. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050760</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ataxias congénitas no progresivas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1267^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1267^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13957</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
