<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89160</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Non-invasive coronariography with 64 detector-row multislice ct scan in ocupational medicine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cardiovascular diseases constitute the first cause of mortality in the inddustrialised countires; among them, and in Spain, the first one (30% of the total caridovascular mortality) is myocardial Iscaemi secondary to coronary artery atherosclerosis. Coronary heart disease may manifest in a number of ways, and it is important to identify and assess the symptoms in any given patient so as to be able to prevent the development of an acute corronary syndrome. A recent addition to the many cardiovascular risk factosr tables in use have been the non-invasive imaging techniques; among these, one of the those evidencing the greast potential is that multislice CT scan. The present paper reviews the technique, the requirements, the disadvantages and the clinical applications of non-invasive coronariography with 64 detector row multislice CT scan in the field of Occupational Medicine (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zamorano, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álares, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliete, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herráix, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Wert, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las enfermedades cardiovasculares representan la primera causa de mortalidad en los países industrializados; entre ellas, en España, la primera causa de mortalidad (30% del total por enfermedad cardiovascualar) es la esquemia miocárdica secuendaria a ateroclerosis coronaria. La caridopatía coronaria puede manifestarse de múltiples maneras y es importante identificar y valorar los síntomas que un paciente presenta para poder prevenir la aparición de un síndrome coronario agudo. A las tablas de factores de riego cardiovascular se han unido, más recientemente, una serie de exploraciones de imagen no invasivas; una de las que hoy manifiestan un mayor potencial es la de la TAC multicorete. Se exponen en el presente artículo la técnica, los requisitos, los inconvenientes y las aplicaciones clínicas de la coronariografía no invesiva mediante TAC multicorte con 64 detectores en Medicina del Trabajo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;16(1): 21-29, feb. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89160</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Coronariografía no invasiva meidante tac multicorte de 64 detectores en medicina del trabajo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22878^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30178^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19139^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23484^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
