<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036249</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Root development sulcus as a cause for endodontic treatment failure: a case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The radicular growth groove is an embriologic dental anomaly that affects the 8,5 % of the population. It is located in the palatal face of the maxillary lateral incisors. This groove begins in the central fossa, runs through the cingulum and arrives to the apex, having a variable length. The microorganisms can penetrate to the ligament periodontal through the groove, causing local bone destruction. These teeth can be asymptomatic, can present periodontal patology, pulpitis or pulp necrosis due to the secondary affectation of the pulp. We present the case of a patient that came to our clinic to do the periapical surgery of the right maxillary lateral incisor. We detected and explored the groove in the physic exam. We observed that the endodontic treatment was correct too and it didn't exist periapical patology. We decided to do an exploratory surgery where we saw the radicular growth groove. The final treatment was the extraction of the tooth. The prognosis of these teeth is uncertain and it depends on the depth and length of the radicular growth groove and on the oral hygiene of the patient. Some authors have attempted the treatment removing the inflamatory tissue, doing an odontoplasty and applying citric acid, sealing the groove with amalgam or using hidroxiapatite and guided tissular regeneration technics, but in most of the cases the extraction of the tooth is the election treatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arnabat, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gay Escoda, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pumarola, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguel, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berini, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El surco de desarrollo radicular es una anomalía dentaria de origen embriológico presente en el 8,5% de la población que se localiza principalmente en la cara palatina de los incisivos laterales superiores. Este surco se origina en la fosa central y atravesando el cíngulo se dirige hacia el ápice, siendo su longitud variable. A través de él, los microorganismos penetran en el ligamento periodontal, causando una destrucción ósea localizada. Clínicamente los dientes afectados por esta anomalía pueden ser asintomáticos o bien presentar patología periodontal, pulpitis o necrosis pulpar por afectación secundaria de la pulpa. Presentamos el caso de una paciente que acudió a nuestro Servicio para realizarse la cirugía periapical del 1.2. En el examen físico se detectó y se exploró el surco. Asimismo, también se observó que el tratamiento de conductos era correcto y no existía patología a nivel periapical. Se decidió efectuar una cirugía exploratoria donde se comprobó la presencia de un surco de desarrollo radicular. El tratamiento final efectuado fue la exodoncia. El pronóstico de estos dientes es incierto, dependiendo de la profundidad y de la extensión apical del surco radicular, así como de la higiene bucal del paciente. Diversos autores han intentado el tratamiento mediante la eliminación del tejido de granulación, odontoplastia y la aplicación de ácido cítrico, el sellado del surco con amalgama, o el uso de hidroxiapatita y técnicas de regeneración tisular guiada pero en la mayoría de los casos el tratamiento de elección continúa siendo la exodoncia</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);23(1): 7-13, ene.-mar. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036249</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El surco de desarrollo radicular como causa de fracaso endodóncico: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10090^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32866^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12107^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12107^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12107^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32866^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3801^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3819^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3819^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10673^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3801^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3801^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32866^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
