<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94155</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">BRAF T1799. A mutation in the primary tumor as a marker of risk, recurrence, or persistence of papillary thyroid carcinoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective. The BRAFT1799A mutation is reported to be associated to aggressive, persistent, and recurrent tumor in papillary thyroid carcinoma (PTC) patients. Association of the BRAFT1799A mutation in the primary tumor with the clinicopathological characteristics of PTC patients was analyzed. Patients, material and methods. Ninety-seven PTC patients were followed up for a median of 64.1 months. The BRAFT1799A mutation was analyzed in DNA from initial thyroidectomy biopsies by PCR amplification and restriction fragment length polymorphism using TspRI enzyme. Positive cases were confirmed by DNA sequencing. Statistical association between BRAFT1799A mutation and clinicopathological characteristics was analyzed by the relevant hypothesis tests and logistic regression. Results. 46.4% of patients were positive for the BRAFT1799A mutation. Bivariate and multivariate analysis showed the BRAFT1799A mutation to be only associated to age over 60 years (odds ratio [OR] = 5.5; 95% confidence interval [CI],1.4-21.9; p=0.019) and to tumor size of 1cm or greater (OR=3.6, 95% CI, 1.2-10.3; p=0.016). The BRAFT1799A mutation was not associated to histological subtype, metastasis, recurrence, more aggressive treatments (ablative I131 therapy or surgery), or PTC persistence at the end of follow-up. Conclusions. The BRAFT1799A mutation is associated to age over 60 and a tumor size of 1cm or greater, but not to other clinicopathological characteristics, tumor recurrence or PTC persistence  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Nevot, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vílchez Joya, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montes Ramírez, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Pérez, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Becerra Massare, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llamas Elvira, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López de la Torre Casares, Martín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villar Del Moral, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañadas Garre, Marisa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes y objetivo. La mutación BRAFT1799A se ha relacionado con características tumorales de más agresividad, recidiva tumoral y persistencia de carcinoma papilar de tiroides (CPT), aunque no todos los estudios apoyan esta asociación. En éste, se analiza la asociación entre la presencia de la mutación BRAFT1799A en el tumor primario de pacientes con CPT y las características clinicopatológicas de riesgo, recidiva y persistencia tumoral. Pacientes, material y método. Hemos seguido a 97 pacientes intervenidos de CPT durante una mediana de 64,1 meses. La mutación BRAFT1799A se determinó en ácido desoxirribonucleico procedente de muestras de la tiroidectomía inicial mediante amplificación por PCR del exón 15 del gen braf y análisis de los fragmentos de restricción con la enzima TspRI. Los casos positivos fueron confirmados por secuenciación. La asociación estadística entre la mutación BRAFT1799A y las diferentes variables se estudió mediante los correspondientes tests de contraste de hipótesis más regresión logística. Resultados. El 46,4% de los pacientes eran positivos para la mutación BRAFT1799A. Tras análisis bivariante y multivariante, la mutación BRAFT1799A sólo se asociaba con edad superior a 60 años (odds ratio [OR] = 5,5; intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 1,4-21,9; p=0,019) y tamaño de 1cm o superior (OR=3,6; IC del 95%, 1,2-10,3; p=0,016). No se asociaba con subtipos histológicos, metástasis, recidiva, necesidad de nuevos tratamientos ablativos con I131 o de otras intervenciones quirúrgicas debidas a la aparición de metástasis o persistencia de enfermedad al final del seguimiento. Conclusiones. La mutación BRAFT1799A está asociada a edad superior a 60 años y tamaño tumoral de 1cm o mayor, pero no con otras características clinicopatológicas, recidiva tumoral o persistencia de enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;58(4): 175-184, abr. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94155</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Presencia de la mutación BRAF T1799A en el tumor primario como indicador de riesgo, recidiva o persistencia de carcinoma papilar de tiroides</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9346</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34449^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2334^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22696^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30589^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9557^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
