<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124214</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Follow-up of newborns with hypoxic-ischaemic encephalopathy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hypothermia treatment for newborn infants with hypoxic-ischemic encephalopathy reduces the number of neonates who die or have permanent neurological deficits. Although this therapy is now standard of care, neonatal hypoxic-ischaemic encephalopathy still has a significant impact on the child&#146;s neurodevelopment and quality of life. Infants with hypoxic-ischaemic encephalopathy should be enrolled in multidisciplinary follow-up programsin order to detect impairments, to initiate early intervention, and to provide counselling and support for families. This article describes the main neurodevelopmental outcomes after term neonatal hypoxic ischaemic encephalopathy. We offer recommendations for follow-up based on the infant&#146;s clinical condition and other prognostic indicators, mainly neonatal neuroimaging. Other aspects, such as palliative care and medico-legal issues, are also briefly discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Alix, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Biarge, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salas, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La introducción del tratamiento con hipotermia para la encefalopatía hipóxicoisquémica neonatal ha conseguido reducir el número de niños con esta enfermedad que fallecen o que sobreviven con secuelas neurológicas. A pesar de la generalización de esta terapia, la encefalopatía hipóxico-isquémica continúa siendo una causa importante de mortalidad y de discapacidad neurológica. Las consecuencias de esta enfermedad sobre el neurodesarrollo y la calidad de vida del recién nacido justifican que estos pacientes sean incluidos en programas de seguimiento específicos con el fin de identificar y tratar precozmente los problemas que puedan surgir, así como de ofrecer orientación y apoyo a las familias. En este artículo se describen las complicaciones más importantes que presentan los niños con encefalopatía hipóxico-isquémica después del alta hospitalaria y se propone un programa de seguimiento basado en el pronóstico neurológico, establecido este a partir del estado clínico del recién nacido y de otros indicadores pronósticos, principalmente los estudios de neuroimagen. Se exponen también brevemente algunos aspectos sociales de importancia durante el seguimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);81(1): 52-52[e1-e14], jul. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124214</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguimiento de los recién nacidos con encefalopatía hipóxico-isquémica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7216^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7405^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28397</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2587^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33528^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34255^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201407</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
