<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039148</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Artificial nutrition in acute renal failure</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Nutritional support in critically ill patients that present with acute renal failure has been a matter of change in recent years. This is due to the increasing and earlier use of extrarenal depuration techniques. Modifications in nutritional and metabolic support regimen aimed at preventing renal failure progression, classically recommended, would not have an indication in these situations but in cases not treated with one of these depurative techniques. Thus, protein intake should be appropriate to the clinical situation, and formulations compounded exclusively by essential amino acids are no longer recommended. Glucose administration should not be different from that recommended in other conditions. Lipids infusion should have a maximum limit of 1 g/kg/day.  Thus, the use of standard diets is not problematic in patients treated with depurative techniques. However, the relationship between substrates flow through dialysis membranes and its effect on nutrients demands has not been fully established yet. It is likely that an increase in nutrients intake may be necessary to counteract the obliged loss by depurative techniques. The other way around, the role of these techniques as an appropriate way for nutritional support in critically ill patients remains to be studied (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanchez-Izquierdo Riera, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lopez Martinez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Jiménez, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El soporte nutricional en los pacientes críticos que presentan insuficiencia renal aguda ha sido motivo de cambio en los últimos años. Ello es debido al empleo cada vez más frecuente y precoz de las técnicas de depuración extrarenal. Las modificaciones en la pauta de soporte nutricional y metabólico destinadas a evitar la progresión del fracaso renal, recomendadas clásicamente, no tendrían indicación en estas situaciones salvo en los casos no tratados con alguna de las técnicas depurativas. El aporte proteico, por lo tanto, deberá ser adecuado a la situación clínica, no recomendándose ya el empleo de las formulaciones de aminoácidos compuestas exclusivamente por aminoácidos esenciales. La administración de glucosa no sería diferente a la recomendada en otras situaciones. La infusión de lípidos tendría un límite máximo de 1 gr/Kg/día.  El empleo de dietas estándar, por tanto, no plantea problemas si los pacientes están siendo tratados con técnicas de depuración. No obstante, la relación entre el flujo de substratos a través de las membranas de diálisis y su efecto sobre la demanda de nutrientes está aún sin establecer de manera clara. Es probable que se requiera un incremento del aporte de nutrientes con el fin de contrarrestar la pérdida obligada por las técnicas de depuración. A la inversa, queda también por estudiar el papel de dichas técnicas como vía adecuada para el soporte nutricional en los pacientes críticos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;20(supl.2): 18-21, jun. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039148</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nutrición artificial en la insuficiencia renal aguda</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32108^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32108^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53982^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
