<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160379</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Topical imiquimod 5% as an alternative therapy in periocular basal cell carcinoma in two patients with surgical contraindication</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Clinical cases: The cases are presented of two patients with periocular basal cell carcinoma of the eyelid who received topical imiquimod 5%, with a good response. Both had a functional state that contraindicated surgical treatment. Conclusion: Imiquimod cream 5% was shown to be an effective alternative to surgical treatment of periocular basal cell carcinoma, especially in those cases where surgery is not possible (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Coronado, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rozas Reyes, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Costales Álvarez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Vega, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Rodríguez, CM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Casos clínicos: Presentamos los casos de dos pacientes con carcinoma basocelular periocular palpebral, que recibieron imiquimod tópico al 5%, con buena respuesta. Ambos presentaban un estado funcional que desaconsejaba el tratamiento quirúrgico. Conclusión: La crema de imiquimod al 5% ha demostrado ser una alternativa eficaz al tratamiento quirúrgico de tumores basocelulares perioculares, especialmente en aquellos casos en los que la cirugía no es posible (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;92(2): 93-96, feb. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160379</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Imiquimod 5% tópico como terapia alternativa en carcinoma basocelular periocular en 2 pacientes con contraindicación quirúrgica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5243^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5243^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d287</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30862^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2323^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2323^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7336^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
