<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128700</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Differential effects of diabetes education programs by levels of HbA1c and the presence of chronic complications in patients with type 1 diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Diabetes Education Programs (DEP) that improve metabolic control are applied to a wide variety of patient types. The aim is to test whether DEPs work differently depending on the patient profile. Materials and Methods: Thirty-six type 1 diabetics participated. They were divided into four groups according to their haemoglobin levels (range: 7-13 %) and into two groups according to the presence or absence of complications. The ECODI scale for assessing diabetes knowledge and the Frequency of Self-Care scale were completed by all patients. Results: The results showed that HbA1c decreased after the DEP, with some areas of self-care also improving. There were no changes, however, to diet or exercise. Conclusions: DEP appear to work better in patients with worse control and with complications, suggesting that they have a certain role to play in prevention. Their lack of impact on diet or exercise, would suggest that the DEPs require improvement to include psychological strategies that motivate lasting lifestyle changes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Morales, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-González, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Alcántara, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guardia-Archilla, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casares, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos-Roig, M. de los</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: Los programas de Educación Diabetológica (PED) mejoran el control metabólico pero son aplicados a pacientes de muy diversa índole. El objetivo es comprobar si un PED funciona de manera diferente según el perfil del paciente. Material y Métodos: Participaron en el estudio 36 pacientes diagnosticados de diabetes tipo 1. Fueron segmentados en cuatro grupos según niveles de hemoglobina (rango de 7-13%) y en dos, según la presencia o no de complicaciones. Todos cumplimentaron la Escala ECODI y la de Frecuencia de Auto-Cuidado. Resultados: Se comprueba cómo tras el PED existe una disminución de la Hb1Ac y algunas áreas del auto-cuidado también mejoran, pero no hay cambios en dieta ni en el ejercicio. Conclusiones: El PED parece funcionar mejor en los pacientes con peor control y con complicaciones, y se discute, por tanto, su papel preventivo. Se concluye sobre la necesidad de mejorar la intervención, ya que no hay cambios en aspectos relativos a los factores de riesgo cardiovascular, incluyendo estrategias psicológicas que motiven un cambio real en el estilo de vida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;37(2): 235-240, mayo-ago. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128700</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos diferenciales de los programas de educación en diabetes según los niveles de HbA1c y la presencia de complicaciones crónicas en el paciente tipo 1</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22190^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
