<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72330</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Advances in heart failure</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article reports on the most significant developments in the field of heart failure in the past year. Principal innovations in the management of chronic heart failure are explained, including the most important features of new management models for patients with chronic heart failure and the main advances in drug therapy and in the use of and indications for cardiac devices in these patients. In addition, recent progress in the treatment of advanced heart failure, with particular emphasis on acute heart failure, is reviewed. Novel approaches to the surgical management of patients with heart failure, including new contributions in the field of the circulatory support, are also highlighted in this update (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Delgado Jiménez, Juan F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Aguilera, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Comín Colet, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuenca Castillo, José J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente artículo se presentan los avances más destacados en el campo de la insuficiencia cardiaca en el último año. Se exponen las principales novedades en el manejo de la insuficiencia cardiaca crónica tanto en los aspectos más relevantes de los nuevos modelos de gestión del paciente con insuficiencia cardiaca crónica como en los avances farmacológicos y en el uso y la indicación de dispositivos en estos pacientes. También se revisan los nuevos adelantos en el abordaje de la insuficiencia cardiaca en su fase más avanzada, con especial énfasis en la fase aguda. Los nuevos enfoques del manejo quirúrgico de la insuficiencia cardiaca, incluyendo en este apartado las nuevas aportaciones en el campo delas asistencias circulatorias, merecen un papel destacado en esta actualización (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;62(supl.1): 92-100, 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72330</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Temas de actualidad en insuficiencia cardiaca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6500^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28561^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2358^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1251^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1251^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200900</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
