<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037829</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A comparative study of intimal repair of the aorta in young and old atheromatous animals</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The purpose of this research work was to evaluate the effects exerted by    an atherogenic risk factor &#150;high fat diets&#150; on the development of atheromatous lesions induced    by traumatic endothelial injury in young and adult animals. Materials and methods. The study    involved a sample of 72 Spanish giant-New Zealand rabbits divided into two groups, one    consisting of young rabbits (750 g) and the other made up of adult rabbits (3,500 g), in all of    which endothelial injury was induced. These groups were divided into two; one was fed on a    normal diet and the other received an atherogenic diet. Finally, subgroups of six animals per    group were formed, which were then sacrificed at 7, 15 and 30 days after the endothelial    damage. A control group made up of six animals that did not receive any kind of treatment or    damaging manoeuvre was then added, as well as a reference group of six animals in which    atherogenesis was induced without endothelial injury. It was expected that the alterations    produced in the endothelial layer could be detected histologically and that a morphometric    study would allow them to be quantified. Results. The group of adult rabbits fed on an atherogenic    diet showed more alterations, both in the clinical evaluation and from a morphological    and morphometric point of view. Conclusions. Lesions induced by intimal damage and an    atherogenic diet were not suitable for repair, and these injuries have been observed with    greater intensity in adult rabbits than in younger animals</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-González, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero-Puerta, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diago-Santamaría, M. V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen. Introducción. La finalidad de este    trabajo de investigación ha sido valorar los    efectos que tiene un factor de riesgo aterogénico,    dietas hiperlipídicas, sobre el desarrollo    de la lesión ateromatosa inducida por    traumatismo endotelial en animales jóvenes    y adultos. Materiales y métodos. Se utilizaron    72 conejos neozelandés-gigante español, divididos    en dos grupos, uno de conejos jóvenes    (750 g) y otro de conejos adultos (3.500 g), a    los que se les provocó lesión endotelial. Estos    grupos se dividieron en dos; se alimentó    uno con dieta normal y otro con dieta aterogénica.    Finalmente, se hicieron subgrupos de    seis animales cada uno, que se sacrificaron a    los 7, 15 y 30 días tras el daño endotelial. Se    añadió un grupo control de seis animales a    los que no se realizó tratamiento ni maniobra    lesional, y un grupo testigo de seis animales    a los que se indujo aterogénesis sin lesión    endotelial. Se consideró que las alteraciones    producidas en la capa endotelial se podían    detectar desde un punto de vista histológico    y cuantificarlas mediante un estudio morfométrico.    Resultados. El grupo de conejos    adultos alimentado con dieta aterogénica    presentó más alteraciones, tanto en la valoración    clínica como desde el punto de vista    morfológico y morfométrico. Conclusiones.    Las lesiones provocadas por daño intimal y    dieta aterogénica no han presentado disposición    a la reparación, y estas lesiones se han    mostrado con mayor intensidad en los conejos    adultos que en los jóvenes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;57(1): 47-60, ene.-feb. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037829</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio comparativo de la reparación intimal de la aorta de animales jóvenes y viejos ateromatosos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1016^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15055^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7144^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1164^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1016^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15055^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15055^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
