<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052572</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Orientation of mental retardation from neurometabolic diseases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and development. Isolated mental retardation is rarely caused by metabolic factors. The applicationof a standardised protocol offers low diagnostic performance. There is no international agreement about what type ofmetabolic examination must be applied in patients with unspecific mental retardation. Nevertheless, and although they areinfrequent, there are a number of inborn errors of metabolism that can present in this way. Urea cycle disorders, differentforms of homocystinuria, creatine transport deficiency, 4-hydroxybutyric aciduria, Sanfilippo disease, adenylosuccinate lyasedeficit and certain extraordinarily rare congenital disorders of the glycosylation of proteins are some examples of them. It isimportant first to consider those for which treatment is available and that could be diagnosed genetically for possible familycounselling. Conclusions. Rather than applying a standardised study protocol it is essential is to perform a thorough appraisal ofthe signs and symptoms associated with the mental retardation (psychiatric disorders, autistic traits, predominant compromiseof language, signs of cerebellar dysfunction, epilepsy, dysmorphic traits), since in most disorders it is necessary to applyspecific analyses, which are not included in conventional metabolic studies and are only available in certain reference centres</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Campistol, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Artuch, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Cazorla, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Dueñas, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilaseca, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pineda, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y desarrollo. El retraso mental aislado raramentees de origen metabólico. La aplicación de un protocoloestandarizado ofrece un rendimiento diagnóstico bajo. No existe unconsenso internacional sobre qué tipo de exámenes metabólicos sehan de aplicar en pacientes con retraso mental inespecífico. Apesar de ello, y aunque es infrecuente, existen algunos errores congénitosdel metabolismo que pueden presentarse de este modo. Lostrastornos del ciclo de la urea, diferentes formas de homocistinuria,el déficit del transportador de creatina, la aciduria 4-hidroxibutírica,la enfermedad de Sanfilippo, el déficit de adenilosuccinatoliasa y algunas formas extraordinariamente infrecuentes deerrores congénitos de la glucosilación de las proteínas están entreellos. Es importante considerar en primer lugar aquellos que tienentratamiento y posibilidades de diagnóstico genético para unposible consejo familiar. Conclusiones. Más que la aplicación de unprotocolo de estudio estandarizado es imprescindible valorar meticulosamentela sintomatología asociada al retraso mental (trastornospsiquiátricos, rasgos autistas, afectación predominante del lenguaje,signos de disfunción cerebelosa, epilepsia, rasgos dismórficos),ya que en la mayoría de los trastornos se han de aplicar análisisespecíficos, no incluidos en los estudios metabólicos convencionalesy solamente disponibles en algunos centros de referencia</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;43(supl.1): s187-s192, oct. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052572</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Orientación del retraso mental desde las enfermedades neurometabólicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8836^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
