<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054921</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Air pollutant exposure during pregnancy and fetal and early childhood development. Research protocol of the INMA [Childhood and Environment Project]</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The INMA (INfancia y Medio Ambiente [Spanish for Environment and Childhood]) project is a cooperative research network. This project aims to study the effects of environment and diet on fetal and early childhood development. This article aims to present the air pollutant exposure protocol during pregnancy and fetal and early childhood development of the INMA project.         Methods: The information to assess air pollutant exposure during pregnancy is based on outdoor measurement of air pollutants (nitrogen dioxide [NO2], volatile organic compounds [VOC], ozone, particulate matter [PM10, PM2,5 ] and of their composition [polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons]); measurement of indoor and personal exposure (VOC and NO2); urinary measurement of a biological marker of hydrocarbon exposure (1-hydroxypyrene); and data gathered by questionnaires and geographic information systems. These data allow individual air pollutant exposure indexes to be developed, which can then be used to analyze the possible effects of exposure on fetal development and child health.         Conclusion: This protocol and the type of study allow an approximation to individual air pollutant exposure to be obtained. Finally, the large number of participants (N = 4,000), as well as their geographic and social diversity, increases the study's potential</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sunyer, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iñíguez, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Dos Santos, Saúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballestero, Ferrán</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Marieta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lacasaña, Marina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torrent, Maties</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tardón, Adonina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esplugues, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilera, Inma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Patier, Rosalía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rebagliato, Marisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribas-Fitó, Núria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sala, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estarlich, Marisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguirre Alfaro, Amelia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grimalt, Joan O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El proyecto INMA (Infancia y Medio Ambiente) es una red de investigación cooperativa que tiene como objetivos estudiar los efectos del medio ambiente y la dieta en el desarrollo fetal e infantil. El objetivo de este artículo es presentar el protocolo de exposición a contaminantes atmosféricos durante el embarazo y desarrollo prenatal y neonatal en el proyecto INMA.         Métodos: La información para la evaluación de la exposición a contaminación atmosférica durante el embarazo se basa en mediciones de contaminantes atmosféricos en el exterior (dióxido de nitrógeno [NO2], compuestos orgánicos volátiles [COV], ozono, partículas [PM10, PM2,5] y su composición [hidrocarburos aromáticos policíclicos]), medición de contaminantes de exposición individual (en el interior de la vivienda y captadores personales [COV y NO2]), determinación de un marcador biológico de exposición a hidrocarburos (1-hidroxipireno), en información recogida mediante cuestionarios y en la utilización de sistemas de información geográfica. Esta información permite elaborar índices de exposición individual a contaminación atmosférica con los que analizar su posible relación con el desarrollo fetal y la salud del recién nacido.         Discusión: El protocolo que se presenta y el tipo de estudio permiten obtener una aproximación a la exposición individual a contaminantes atmosféricos. Por último, el elevado número de participantes (n = 4.000), así como la heterogeneidad de las características ambientales y sociodemográficas, acrecienta el potencial del estudio</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;21(2): 162-171, mar.2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054921</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Exposición a contaminantes atmosféricos durante el embarazo y desarrollo prenatal y neonatal: protocolo de investigación en el proyecto INMA (Infancia y Medio Ambiente)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5425^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5425^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4862^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d400^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32153^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4865^s22050</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
