<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80431</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Procedure of taken care of in shaved surgery craneal withour in HUB</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The procedure of hygiene pre and post surgical of the patient of neurosurgery in the University Hospital of Bellvitge, initiated in 1995, guarantees the correct preparation of the surgical zone, the frequency and accomplishment of the therapeutic washing reduces the risk of infection of the wound and maintains the integrity of the hairy leather. It diminishes the presurgical anguish of the patient and improves the adaptation to the corporal changes by surgery(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Masó Serra, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Aguilar, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El procedimiento de higiene pre y post quirúrgica del paciente de neurocirugía en el Hospital Universitario de Bellvitge, iniciado en el año 1995, garantiza la correcta preparación de la zona quirúrgica. La frecuencia y realización del lavado terapéutico reduce el riesgo de infección de la herida y mantiene la integridad del cuero cabelludo. Minimiza la angustia prequirúrgica del paciente y mejora la adaptación a los cambios corporales por cirugía(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;30(11): 751-754, nov. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80431</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Procedimiento de cuidados en cirugía craneal sin rasurado en el Hospitla Universitaio de Bellvitge</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9682^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13912^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20180^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6357^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13908^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
