<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85953</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1582</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The importance of determining HER2 status lays on the fact that breast cancer patients with HER2 amplification are more reluctant to conventional chemotherapy and hormonal treatments. Thus the HER2 analysis is an essential requisite to determine which patients are eligible to be treated with trastuzumab. The aim of this article is reviewing the effectiveness and clinical utility of HER 2 diagnostic test with fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH), chromogenic in situ hybridization (CISH) and silver chromogenic in situ hybridization (SISH) to correctly select breast cancer patients who are candidates to be treated with trastuzumab(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Maestro, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rafael-Fernández, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidaurreta, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Román, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sua-Villegas, L. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Veganzones de Castro, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La importancia en la detección de la amplificación del gen HER2 es esencial en el cáncer de mama puesto que estas pacientes no responden a los tratamientos de quimioterapia y hormonales convencionales. La determinación del HER2 tiene un papel crucial como diana terapéutica del trastuzumab. A continuación discutiremos la efectividad y utilidad clínica de la técnica hibridación in situ fluorescente (FISH), la hibridación in situ cromogénica (CISH) y la hibridación in situ cromogénica con plata (SISH), como métodos usados para el estudio del gen HER2 en la selección correcta de las pacientes con cáncer de mama, que son candidatas a recibir trastuzumab(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. senol. patol. mamar. (Ed. impr.);23(4): 168-172, ago.-oct. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85953</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hibridación in situ fluorescente (FISH), hibridación in situ cromogénica (CISH) e hibridacion in situ cromogénica con plata (SISH): su uso para la detección de la amplificación del gen HER2 en cáncer de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5588</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32226^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3600^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32062^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32062^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30685^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30685^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34542^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30685^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
