<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83350</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of topic administration of nitric oxide donor gel in the clitoridian blood flow, assessed by Doppler ultra-sound</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: This study aims to evaluate of the impact of NO molecules in Pluronic F-127 gel, applied topically in the clitoris, on the clitoridian blood flow of healthy volunteer women, using the Doppler ultra-sound. Method: A total of 20 healthy women over 18 years old and sexually active with no sexual hormones alteration were enrolled. The Doppler ultra-sound procedure was performed on the artery of the clitoris in patients without the NO donor gel, and then after fifteen minutes of its application the same procedure was done again, to compare the values. Results: The hemodynamic results showed, that this formulation was responsible for the increase of the systolic and diastolic speeds in about 2,5 times after 15min of the administration of the gel. The initial resistance index was increased in 1.2 due to the local venous congestion in only 15min after the administration of gel. Indicating that this product can be used to promote the dilatation of the artery of the clitoris to treat women with sexual dysfunction. Conclusion: The use of topic hidrogel as a donor drug in the clitoris of women resulting in a local vasodilatation, without systemic effects. These findings suggest that this preparation may be useful in the management of selected cases of female sexual dysfunction(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palma, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riccetto, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seabra, A. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Souto, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliveira, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Capmartin, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palma, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar el impacto de las moléculas del donante de óxido nítrico (NO) en el gel F-127 plurónico, aplicado tópicamente en el clítoris, sobre el flujo sanguíneo clitoridiano de mujeres jóvenes voluntarias, usando eco-Doppler. Método: Veinte mujeres sanas mayores de edad, sexualmente activas y sin alteraciones sexuales en su historia clínica fueron enroladas para la medición mediante eco-Doppler de la velocidad del pico sistólico, velocidad diastólica y tasa de resistencia en las arterias clitoridianas previo a la aplicación del donante del NO en gel, a fin de observar los valores basales del flujo en ellas y comparar los valores pre y post. Resultados: Las velocidades sistólica, diastólica y resistencia de base, y 15min posterior a la aplicación del gel, fueron significativamente diferentes (p=0,002, p=0,043, p=0,005, respectivamente). Los resultados muestran el aumento de las velocidades sistólicas y diastólicas a nivel de las arterias clitoridianas en casi 2,5 veces después de 15min de la administración del gel, lo que traduce un aumento en el flujo sanguíneo clitoridiano. Conclusión: El uso del donante de NO en gel S-nitrosoglutation aumenta, significativamente, el flujo sanguíneo del clítoris. Esto podría ser usado terapéuticamente en algunos casos de disfunción sexual(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;34(8): 708-712, sept. 2010. graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83350</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto en la administración de un donante de óxido nítrico en gel en el flujo sanguíneo clitoridiano, medido por eco-Doppler</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3011^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9753^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13115^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12461^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
