<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144952</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1473</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Isocitrate dehydrogenase type I mutation as a prognostic factor in glioblastoma and a literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Treatment response and prognosis in glioblastoma (GBM) tumours can differ among patients, highlighting the growing relevance of genetic biomarkers to differentiate glioblastoma sub-types. The biomarker isocitrate dehydrogenase (IDH1) is currently receiving considerable attention. The objective of this work was to analyse the clinical and prognostic differences between glioblastomas with and without the IDH1 mutation. Methods. A retrospective study was performed on patients with GBM who underwent surgery between 2007 and 2012. The inclusion criteria were: patient age between 18-85 years who underwent surgery for the first time with complete macroscopic resection, complete adjuvant treatment with chemotherapy and radiotherapy, and a Karnofsky performance score &gt; 70. Results. A total of 61 patients (36 males/25 famales) were included and with a mean age of 62.3 years. An IDH1mutation was found in 14 patients (23%). Median survival in patients with the IDH1 mutation (IDH1-m)was 23.6 months compared with 11.9 months in those with the wild type IDH1 (IDH1-wt) (P=.028). Disease onset in IDH1-m patients tended to be at a younger age, 58.7 vs. 63.4 years, but this difference was not statistically significant. Conclusion. Glioblastomas with IDH1-m should be considered a different entity from the IDH1-wt, as their natural history and prognosis differ. In the near future we should be classified glioblastomas based on the presence of the IDH1 mutation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molet-Teixidó, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintana-Schmidt, Cristian de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nomdedeu-Guinot, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salgado-Lopez, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alvarez-Holzapfel, María Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego-Rubio, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leidinger, Andreas</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bague-Rosell, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. La respuesta al tratamiento y el pronóstico de los glioblastomas multiformes (GBM) puede ser distinta entre diferentes individuos. Este hecho está haciendo que cada vez estén cobrando más importancia los biomarcadores genéticos para intentar diferenciar distintos subtipos de GBM. Uno de los que está adquiriendo más importancia es la isocitrato deshidrogenasa (IDH1). El objetivo del trabajo es analizar la diferencias tanto clínicas como pronósticas de los GBM con y sin mutación de la IDH1. Materiales y método. Estudio retrospectivo de pacientes con GBM intervenidos entre los años 2007 y 2012. Los criterios de inclusión fueron: pacientes entre 18-85 años, sometidos por primera vez a cirugía, resección macroscópicamente completa, tratamiento coadyuvante con quimioterapia y radioterapia y Karnofsky status&gt;70. Resultados. N=61 pacientes (36 varones/25 mujeres). Edad media de 62,3 años. En 14 pacientes (23%) se encontró la IDH1 mutada. La supervivencia media de los pacientes con mutación de la IDH1 (IDH1-m) fue de 23,6 meses respecto a los 11,9 meses que presentaban los de la IDH1 en estado natural (IDH1-wt) (p=0,028). Existió una tendencia en los pacientes con IDH1-m a presentar la enfermedad en edades más tempranas 58,7 vs. 63,4 años, pero estas diferencias no fueron significativas. Conclusiones. Se deberían considerar los GBM con IDH1-m como una entidad distinta a los IDH1-wt. Se trata de dos subtipos de GBM con una historia natural y un pronóstico totalmente distinto por lo que se deberían clasificar en un futuro en función de la presencia de la mutación de la IDH1 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurocirugia (Astur);26(6): 276-283, nov.-dic. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144952</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Importancia de la mutación de la isocitrato deshidrogenasa tipo I como factor pronóstico en pacientes con glioblastomas y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7688^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13440^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13915</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6053^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31846^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6053^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6053^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31846^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31846^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31846^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9346</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7688</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6053^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6053^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7688^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31846^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
