<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116412</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-3334</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Antisocial behavior: Connection with positive emotions and predictor variables</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The study had two goals: 1) To explore the relations between antisocial behavior (self-assessed and parent-assessed) and variables such as empathy, emotional intelligence, self-esteem, and personality dimensions (neuroticism, extraversion, openness, agreeableness, responsibility); and 2) To identify variables that predict antisocial behavior. The sample is made up of 3,026 participants aged between 12 and 18 years. Using a descriptive and correlational design, 6 assessment instruments were administered. The results showed that adolescents young people of both sexes, with high scores in antisocial behavior had significantly: 1) less capacity for empathy (take on the other&#146;s viewpoint); 2) less capacity for emotional regulation (control of moods); 3) lower level of agreeableness (cordiality, altruism); 4) lower level of responsibility (will to achieve academic goals); 5) higher level of neuroticism (emotional instability, negative feelings); and 6) higher level of extraversion (sociability, assertiveness, excitement). The relations between antisocial behavior and self-esteem were inconclusive. Low levels of empathy, agreeableness, and responsibility, and high levels of neuroticism, extraversion, and being older predicted antisocial behavior. The discussion emphasizes the importance of implementing programs that promote socio-emotional development (communication, empathy, emotions, prosocialbehavior&#133;) to prevent antisocial behavior (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garaigordobil Landazabal, Maite</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aliri Lazcano, Jone</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernaras Iturrioz, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Valderrey, Vanesa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jaureguizar Alboniga-Mayor, Joana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maganto Mateo, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El estudio tuvo dos objetivos: 1) Explorar las relaciones que existen entre la conducta antisocial (autoevaluada y evaluada por los padres) y variables como empatía, inteligencia emocional, autoestima, y dimensiones de personalidad (neuroticismo, extraversión, apertura, amabilidad, responsabilidad), e 2) Identificar variables que predicen la conducta antisocial. La muestra fue de 3.026 participantes de 12 a 18 años. Con un diseño descriptivo y correlacional se administraron 6 instrumentos de evaluación. Los resultados mostraron que los adolescentes y jóvenes de ambos sexos, con altas puntuaciones en conducta antisocial tenían significativamente: 1) menor capacidad de empatía (para ponerse en el punto de vista de otro); 2) menor capacidad de regulación emocional (control de estados emocionales); 3) menor nivel de amabilidad (cordialidad, altruismo); 4) menor nivel de responsabilidad (voluntad para lograr objetivos académicos); 5) mayor nivel de neuroticismo (inestabilidad emocional, sentimientos negativos); y 6) mayor nivel de extraversión (sociabilidad, asertividad, excitación). Las relaciones entre conducta antisocial y autoestima no fueron concluyentes. Bajo nivel de empatía, de amabilidad, de responsabilidad, alto nivel de neuroticismo, de extraversión, y mayor edad predijeron la conducta antisocial. La discusión enfatiza la importancia de implementar programas que fomenten el desarrollo socioemocional (comunicación, empatía, emociones, conducta prosocial&#133;) para prevenir la conducta antisocial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apuntes psicol;31(2): 123-133, mayo-ago. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116412</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conducta antisocial: conexión con emociones positivas y variables predictoras</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53742</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d991^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4721</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
