<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135559</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The number processing and calculation system: Evidence from cognitive neuropsychology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Cognitive neuropsychology focuses on the concepts of dissociation and double dissociation. The performance of number processing and calculation tasks by patients with acquired brain injury can be used to characterise the way in which the healthy cognitive system manipulates number symbols and quantities. The objective of this study is to determine the components of the numerical processing and calculation system. Methods: Participants consisted of 6 patients with acquired brain injuries in different cerebral localisations. We used Batería de evaluación del procesamiento numérico y el cálculo, a battery assessing number processing and calculation. Data was analysed using the difference in proportions test. Results: Quantitative numerical knowledge is independent from number transcoding, qualitative numerical knowledge, and calculation. Recodification is independent from qualitative numerical knowledge and calculation. Quantitative numerical knowledge and calculation are also independent functions. Conclusions: The number processing and calculation system comprises at least 4 components that operate independently: quantitative numerical knowledge, number transcoding, qualitative numerical knowledge, and calculation. Therefore, each one may be damaged selectively without affecting the functioning of another. According to the main models of number processing and calculation, each component has different characteristics and cerebral localisations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alameda-Bailén, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salguero-Alcañiz, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La neuropsicología cognitiva se centra en los conceptos de disociación y doble disociación. Mediante la descripción de las ejecuciones de pacientes con daño cerebral adquirido en tareas de procesamiento numérico y cálculo podemos caracterizar cómo el sistema cognitivo sano manipula los símbolos numéricos y/o las cantidades. Así, el objetivo de este trabajo es conocer y caracterizar los distintos componentes que forman el sistema de procesamiento numérico y cálculo. Métodos: Los participantes en este trabajo son 6 pacientes con daño cerebral adquirido en diferentes localizaciones cerebrales. Como instrumento se ha empleado la Batería de Evaluación del Procesamiento Numérico y el Cálculo. Para el análisis de los datos se ha realizado una diferencia de proporciones. Resultados: El conocimiento numérico cuantitativo es independiente de la recodificación numérica, el conocimiento numérico cualitativo y el cálculo. La recodificación es independiente del conocimiento numérico cualitativo y del cálculo. El conocimiento numérico cualitativo y el cálculo funcionan de manera independiente. Conclusiones: El sistema de procesamiento numérico y cálculo parece estar formado por al menos 4 componentes que funcionarían de manera independiente, y estos son: conocimiento numérico cuantitativo, recodificación numérica, conocimiento numérico cualitativo y cálculo. De ahí que cada uno de ellos pueda dañarse de forma selectiva sin afectar al funcionamiento de los otros. Según los principales modelos de procesamiento numérico y cálculo, cada uno de ellos tiene características y localizaciones cerebrales diferentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;30(3): 169-175, abr. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135559</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sistema de procesamiento numérico y cálculo: evidencias desde la neuropsicología cognitiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8601^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8601^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8601^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8601^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1951^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
