<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050924</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Social and health characteristics of elderly patients with chronic and/or terminal diseases (PALET profile) attended in a short stay medical unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to describe the clinical, functional, health and social characteristics of the elderly population with chronic and/or terminal diseases (PALET profile) in a short-stay medical unit (SSMU) attached to an emergency department in relation to the remaining patients. Material and methods: a descriptive study of all patients admitted to the SSMU during a 1-year period was performed. Data on age, sex, length of hospital stay, patient profile (PALET or oncological), functional status (Barthel index), cognitive status (Pfeiffer), nutritional status (MNA), depression (Yesavage), living arrangements, and destination after discharge were gathered. The statistical analysis consisted of descriptive study and bivariate analysis (Student's t-test, chi-square test) with a significance level of p &lt; 0.05 (95% confidence interval [CI]). Results: there were 1,028 patients (51.0% men), with a mean age of 71.6 years [15-104] (median 77 years). There were 264 PALET patients (25.7%), 94 oncological patients (9.1%), and 770 patients with other diagnoses (65.2%). No significant differences were found between the groups in the mean length of stay. Overall mortality in the SSMU: 39 patients (76.9% PALET patients). PALET patients were older (OR = 8.16 [95% CI: 4.18-14.16], p &lt; 0.001), had poorer functional and mental status (p &lt; 0.001) and showed higher mortality (OR = 10.76 [95% CI: 5.03-22.98], p &lt; 0.001) than the remaining patients. PALET patients required a higher proportion of domiciliary resources and were more likely to be referred to medium- or long-stay facilities at discharge (p &lt; 0.001). Conclusions: our SSMU attends a substantial proportion of elderly patients with chronic and/or terminal diseases (PALET). Because of the functional, mental, and nutritional status of these patients, as well as the presence of comorbidities and the high mortality rate, domiciliary, health and social resources should be developed to improve the quality of care provided to these patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marín-Tena, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Colomer-Rubio, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peiró Gómez, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferran Ballester, Ferran</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andreu-Ballester, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almela-Quilis, Amadeo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: descripción de las características clínicas, funcionales y sociosanitarias de la población anciana con enfermedad crónica y/o terminal (perfil PALET) atendida en la Unidad Médica de Corta Estancia (UMCE) adscrita a un servicio de urgencias, en relación con el resto de pacientes. Material y métodos: estudio descriptivo de todos los pacientes admitidos en la UMCE durante un período de un año. Se recogen edad, sexo, estancia, tipología, situación funcional (índice de Barthel), cognitiva (Pfeiffer), nutricional (Mini Nutritional Assessment), depresión (Yesavage), situación de convivencia y destino de paciente. Se realizó un estudio descriptivo y análisis bivariante (t de Student, &amp;#967;2), con nivel de significación p &lt; 0,05 (intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%). Resultados: el número total de pacientes fue de 1.028, (51,0% varones), edad media 71,6 [15-104], mediana 77 años. Perfil PALET 264 (25,7%), pacientes oncológicos 94 (9,1%), otros 770 (65,2%). Estancia media sin diferencias significativas entre grupos. Mortalidad global en UMCE 39 casos (76,9% casos perfil PALET). Los pacientes PALET son mayores, odds ratio [OR] = 8,16 (IC del 95%, 4,18-14,16), p &lt; 0,001; presentan peor situación funcional y mental (p &lt; 0,001) y mayor mortalidad, OR = 10,76 (IC del 95%, 5,03-22,98), p &lt; 0,001, que el resto. Asimismo, necesitan mayor proporción de recursos de tipo domiciliario y de media o larga estancia al alta (p &lt; 0,001). Conclusiones: nuestra UMCE atiende a una proporción importante de ancianos con enfermedad crónica y/o terminal (PALET), cuya situación funcional, mental y nutricional, así como su comorbilidad y elevada tasa de mortalidad, obligan a desarrollar recursos domiciliarios, sociosanitarios y hospitales de apoyo que permitan mejorar la calidad de su atención</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);41(6): 327-333, nov. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050924</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio sociosanitario del paciente anciano con perfil de larga estancia y terminal atendido en una unidad médica de corta estancia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6913^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24693^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6913^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33200^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1527^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
