<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74213</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Benign Primary Cystic Lesions of Mediastinum in Adult: the Clinical Spectrum and Surgical Treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectiveThe mediastinal cysts form a group of heterogeneous and uncommon benign lesions of neoplastic, congenital, or inflammatory conditions. The forgoing controversy is how to manage them; surgical removal or observation. We reviewed our experience including some rare conditions, emphasizing the clinical spectrum and surgical treatment.Patientes and methodsThis is a retrospective review between 2000 and 2007 included 34 cases of primary mediastinal cystic lesions. Clinical features, imaging techniques, surgical operation, morbidity, mortality and follow-up were analyzed.ResultsThere were 18 females (53%) and 16 males (47%), with a mean age±standard deviation of 45.3±14.1 years (range: 22&#150;74). Most of cysts were congenital (94%), except patients with hydatid disease (6%). 24% of cysts (n=8) were detected in anterior mediastinum. Rest of them (n=26) were located in visceral mediastinum. Patients usually were symptomatic (61%). Chest pain and discomfort was most common symptom, others were dyspnea, cough and hemoptysis, respectively. Cysts excision was performed in all cases with an uneventful recovery and with no recurrence in long term follow up.ConclusionsAsymptomatic mediastinal cysts are not rare. Surgery is a reliable method of treatment of mediastinal cysts with acceptable mortality and morbidity(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ozturk, Ata</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gürsoy, Soner</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Erbaycu, Ahmet Emin</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ucvet, Ahmet</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">IntroducciónLos quistes mediastínicos forman un grupo de lesiones benignas heterogéneas y poco comunes de naturaleza neoplásica, congénita e inflamatoria. Continúa la controversia sobre cómo tratarlos, ya sea mediante extracción quirúrgica u observación. Examinamos nuestra experiencia en este campo, que incluye algunas situaciones infrecuentes, haciendo hincapié en el espectro clínico y el tratamiento quirúrgico.Pacientes y métodosSe ha realizado un estudio retrospectivo de 34 pacientes atendidos entre 2000 y 2007 por lesiones quísticas primarias del mediastino. Se analizaron las características clínicas, las técnicas de imagen empleadas, el tipo de cirugía, la morbilidad, la mortalidad y el seguimiento.ResultadosEl grupo estuvo constituido por 18 mujeres (53%) y 16 varones (47%), con una media de edad (±desviación estándar) de 45,3±14,1 años (rango: 22&#150;74). La mayoría de los quistes eran congénitos (94%), excepto en los pacientes con enfermedad hidatídica (6%). El 24% de los quistes (n=8) se detectó en el mediastino anterior y el resto (n=26) se localizó en el mediastino visceral. La mayoría de los pacientes (61%) presentaba síntomas. El dolor y las molestias torácicos fueron los síntomas más frecuentes, seguidos de la disnea, la tos y la hemoptisis. En todos los casos se procedió a la escisión del quiste, con la recuperación sin incidentes de los pacientes y sin recurrencias en el seguimiento a largo plazo.ConclusionesLos quistes mediastínicos asintomáticos no son infrecuentes. La cirugía es un tratamiento seguro para los quistes mediastínicos, con una mortalidad y morbilidad aceptables(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;45(8): 371-375, ago. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74213</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lesiones quísticas primarias y benignas del mediastino en el adulto: espectro clínico y tratamiento quirúrgico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23806^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23806^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23806^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
