<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154988</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reflection on the pharmaceutical service in nursing homes; understanding reality to cover needs</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The increasing concern regarding chronic care, which is a consequence of the current demographic progression, and the need to decrease the costs associated with its care, places a focus on social care homes caring for highly dependent patients. Simultaneously, the residential facilities are progressing in order to care for fragile patients with increasingly complexity, even though, with some exceptions, it is in parallel with the healthcare system. Within this reality, pharmaceutical care is developing very differently in all the autonomic regions, and has become a reason for controversy. In this sense, diverse factors related with the patient care setting, but also linked to different pharmaceutical levels, make it difficult to implement a patient care model. Faced with this scenario, it seems reasonable to analyze the situation from the perspective of the healthcare requirements of the institutionalized persons in these facilities, and in terms of the patient care that we can and should provide; subsequently, and based on this, we should be able to propose the basic guidelines for developing an efficient model of pharmaceutical care integrated within this patient care setting (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peris-Martí, Juan F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Villalba, Elia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáez-Lleó, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Mina Freire, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bravo-José, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La creciente preocupación por la atención a la cronicidad, consecuencia de la progresión demográfica actual, y la necesidad de disminuir los costes asociados a su cuidado, sitúa uno de sus focos en los centros de asistencia social que atienden a personas de alta dependencia. A su vez, el ámbito sociosanitario está evolucionando para atender a un paciente frágil cada vez más complejo aunque, salvo excepciones, lo hace de forma paralela al sistema de salud. Dentro de esta realidad, la prestación farmacéutica se está desarrollando de forma muy heterogénea entre las comunidades autónomas y es motivo de controversia. En este sentido, diversos factores relacionados con el ámbito asistencial, pero también con los distintos estamentos farmacéuticos, dificultan el establecimiento de un modelo asistencial. Ante esta situación, parece razonable realizar un análisis de la situación desde la perspectiva de las necesidades sanitarias de las personas institucionalizadas en estos centros y de la atención que podemos y debemos prestar para, posteriormente, ser capaces de proponer las líneas básicas sobre las que desarrollar un modelo de atención farmacéutica eficiente e integrado para este ámbito asistencial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;40(4): 302-315, jul.-ago. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154988</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reflexión sobre la prestación farmacéutica en centros sociosanitarios; entendiendo la realidad para cubrir las necesidades</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9919^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50249^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3182^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33105</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4421^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28940^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
