<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114561</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of the LightCycler ® SeptiFast test in newborns and infants with clinical suspicion of sepsis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction Neonatal sepsis is a significant cause of morbidity and mortality. Early diagnosis and prompt antimicrobial therapy are crucial for a favorable outcome of the newborn child. Blood culture, the current &#147;gold standard&#148; method for diagnosing bloodstream infections, has a low sensitivity in newborns. We evaluated the multiplex real-time PCR LightCycler® SeptiFast (LC-SF) for detection of bloodstream infections in newborns, compared with conventional blood culture. Methods A total of 42 blood samples were obtained from 35 subjects presenting with a febrile episode and hospitalized in neonatal intensive care unit at Hospital Universitario Virgen de las Nieves. Two samples were collected during each febrile episode in order to carry out LC-SF assay and blood culture, respectively. Results Sensitivity and specificity of 79% and 87%, respectively, compared with clinical diagnosis, were obtained for LC-SF. Contamination rate of blood cultures was 16.7%, mainly due to coagulase-negative staphylococci (CoNS) and viridans groups of streptococci. Contamination rate of LC-SF by CoNS was 2.4%. Concordance between LC-SF and blood culture was moderate (kappa index: 0.369). LC-SF demonstrated a higher concordance (kappa index: 0.729) with the final clinical diagnosis than blood culture (kappa index: 0.238). Conclusion LC-SF assay could be a useful diagnostic tool, along with a conventional blood culture, in newborn, for confirming or ruling out those cases that blood culture could not determine, shortening the time to result to 7 hours (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peña-Caballero, Manuela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedrosa-Corral , Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro-Marí , José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Valera, María Manuela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Ruiz, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Ramírez , María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres-Martos, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción La sepsis neonatal es una importante causa de morbimortalidad. Un diagnóstico precoz y el inicio rápido del tratamiento son fundamentales en la evolución del recién nacido. El hemocultivo, considerado técnica de referencia para el diagnóstico de sepsis, presenta una baja sensibilidad en este grupo de pacientes. Se planteó evaluar la utilidad de la PCR múltiple LightCycler® SeptiFast (LC-SF) en el diagnóstico de la sepsis neonatal, comparándola con el hemocultivo tradicional. Métodos Se recogieron 42 muestras de sangre correspondientes a 35 recién nacidos con episodios febriles ingresados en la unidad de cuidados intensivos neonatal del Hospital Universitario Virgen de las Nieves. Por cada episodio febril se procesaron 2 muestras de sangre venosa periférica para la realización del ensayo LC-SF y del hemocultivo, respectivamente. Resultados La sensibilidad y la especificidad de LC-SF, comparada con el diagnóstico clínico de sepsis, fueron del 79 y del 87%, respectivamente. La tasa de hemocultivos contaminados fue del 16,7%, detectándose Staphylococcus coagulasa negativa (SCN) y Streptococcus grupo viridans. En LC-SF la tasa de SCN contaminantes fue del 2,4%. La concordancia entre las 2 técnicas diagnósticas fue moderada (índice kappa: 0,369). La técnica LC-SF demostró una mayor concordancia con el diagnóstico clínico final (índice kappa: 0,729) que el hemocultivo (índice kappa: 0,238). Conclusión LC-SF podría ser una herramienta útil, empleada en paralelo con el hemocultivo en recién nacidos, al confirmar o descartar los casos que el hemocultivo no resuelve, además de disminuir el tiempo de obtención de resultado a 7 h( AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;31(6): 375-379, jun.-jul. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114561</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la técnica LightCycler ® SeptiFast en recién nacidos y lactantes con sospecha de sepsis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29181^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7405^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
