<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107450</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quaternary prevention in the elderly</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Quaternary prevention is a group of measures taken to prevent, decrease and/or alleviate the harm caused by health activities. Health activities not only generally produce benefits, but also harm. That is to say, although medical intervention is mainly favourable, there is a dynamic balance that requires continuous assessment of the clinical situation as naturally only those health activities that achieve more benefit than harm at the end are justified. Quaternary prevention is the avoidance of unnecessary medical activity, such as &#147;check-ups&#148;. In another example, quaternary prevention is the recommendation of preventive measures of proven efficacy. As regards diagnosis, quaternary prevention is, for example, the avoidance of screening without foundation, such as in prostate cancer. The appropriate use of antibiotics in upper respiratory tract infections serves as an example of quaternary prevention in the field of treatment. Another example is the application of the correct rehabilitation techniques in non-specific low back pain, such as swimming and maintaining an active life as much as possible. Not to forget other important &#147;non-classic&#148; aspects in the elderly, such as to limit the harm that can be caused by physical movement restriction devices. These and other examples in daily practice are considered in this article to encourage the continual assessment of quaternary prevention, the classic primum non nocere &#147;first, do no harm&#148;(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gérvas, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Prevención cuaternaria es el conjunto de medidas que se toman para evitar, disminuir y/o paliar el daño producido por las actividades sanitarias. Las actividades sanitarias producen en general beneficio, pero también daños. Es decir, aunque la situación de partida sea favorable a la intervención médica, existe un balance dinámico que exige la valoración continua de la situación clínica, pues solo se justifican, naturalmente, las actividades sanitarias que logran al final más los beneficios que los daños. Prevención cuaternaria es evitar las actividades médicas innecesarias, como los «chequeos». En otro ejemplo, es la recomendación de pautas preventivas de probada eficacia. Respecto al diagnóstico, prevención cuaternaria es por ejemplo evitar el cribado (screening) sin fundamento, como en el cáncer de próstata. Sirve de ejemplo en el campo del tratamiento el uso apropiado de los antibióticos en las infecciones de las vías respiratorias altas. Y en rehabilitación, la aplicación de técnicas correctas en las lumbalgias inespecíficas, como natación y mantenimiento de una vida activa en lo posible. A no olvidar otros aspectos no «clásicos», importantes en los ancianos; por ejemplo, limitar el daño que puedan producir los sistemas de restricción física de movimientos. En este texto se consideran estos y otros ejemplos del trabajo cotidiano, para promover la consideración continua de la prevención cuaternaria, del clásico primum non nocere(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);47(6): 266-269, nov.-dic.2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107450</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevención cuaternaria en ancianos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11750^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11750^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28470</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50219</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11750^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
