<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151830</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vulvar cancer in young women not associated with human papilloma virus infection: A propos of a case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Vulvar cancer encompasses 5% of all gynecologic cancers. It is the fourth most common cause of female genital tract malignancy after cancer of the endometrium, cervix and ovary. Ninety percent of vulvar cancers are squamous. In general, their etiology is unknown, but there are tests that indicate that human papilloma virus (HPV) is a causal factor in carcinomas of the genital tract. Other implicated factors are smoking, immunosuppressive therapy, prior cancer of the cervix, and vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia (VIN). We present a case of vulvar cancer in a 35-year-old woman not associated with HPV (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bas Esteve, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peiró Marqués, FM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Caneja Planell, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cáncer de vulva supone el 5% de todos los cánceres ginecológicos. Es la 4.ª causa de neoplasia del tracto genital femenino más frecuente tras la de endometrio, cérvix y ovario. El 90% de los cánceres vulvares son escamosos. Su etiología, en general, se desconoce, pero existen pruebas que categorizan por preferencia el virus del papiloma humano (VPH) como un factor causal de los carcinomas del tracto genital. Otros factores implicados son el tabaco, los tratamientos inmunosupresores, haber padecido cáncer de cervix y las neoplasias vulvares intraepiteliales (VIN). A continuación presentamos el caso de un cáncer clínico de vulva en una mujer de 35 años no asociado a VPH (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);43(2): 89-91, abr.-jun. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151830</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cáncer de vulva en la mujer joven no asociado a infección por virus del papiloma humano: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2337^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35997^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10403</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15247^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5969^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
