<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165875</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparison of clinical features and diagnosis between the A and B subgroups of respiratory syncytial virus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Lower respiratory tract infection by respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) is the most frequent cause of admission in children under 2 years old. The RSV subgroups A and B may circulate simultaneously. We aimed to determine whether clinical differences exist between RSV subgroups A and B. Additionally, we tested the sensitivity of the rapid antigen detection test (RADT) based on immunochromatography in diagnosing subgroups A and B, taking the polymerase chain reaction assay (RT-PCR) as reference. Methods. A retrospective observational study was performed in a tertiary hospital from October 2013 to March 2014. Clinical records and analytical variables of all children under 5 admitted with lower respiratory tract infection and RT-PCR positive for RSV in nasal lavage were consulted. Previously, the RADT for RSV had been performed from the same sample. Results. A total of 198 children under 5 were diagnosed with RSV by RT-PCR: 55 (28%) were RSV-A, 132 (67%) RSVB and 11 (5%) were positive for both subgroups. No differences were observed between subgroups in medical history, symptoms, radiological and analytical findings, and severity. The sensitivity of RADT for RSV was 52%, higher for RSV-A (69%) than for RSV-B (44%, p=0.001). Conclusions. The two RSV subgroups were indistinguishable in symptoms and prognosis. The sensitivity of RADT compared to RT-PCR was low and limits its usefulness for clinical decision-making (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bernaola, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castilla, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navascués, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Benavides, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ezpeleta, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendizabal, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viguria, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Galarraga, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. La infección del tracto respiratorio inferior por virus respiratorio sincitial (VRS) es la causa más frecuente de ingreso en menores de 2 años. Los subgrupos de VRS A y B pueden circular indistintamente. Nuestro objetivo fue determinar si existían diferencias clínicas entre los VRS subgrupo A y B, y si la sensibilidad del test de detección rápida de antígeno del VRS por inmunocromatografía difiere de la técnica de referencia (RT-PCR). Material y métodos. Estudio retrospectivo, observacional realizado en el hospital terciario desde octubre de 2013 a marzo de 2014. Se consultó la historia clínica y las analíticas de los niños menores de 5 años ingresados en por infección respiratoria de vías bajas con RT-PCR positivo a VRS en una muestra de lavado nasal. De la misma muestra previamente se había realizado el test de detección rápida de antígeno de VRS. Resultados. Se confirmaron 198 niños menores de 5 años para VRS mediante RT-PCR: 55 (28%) fueron VRS-A, 132 (67%) VRS-B y 11 (5%) fueron positivos para ambos subgrupos. No encontramos diferencias entre subgrupos en antecedentes, clínica, radiología, analítica y gravedad. La sensibilidad del test de detección rápida fue 52%, mayor para VRS-A (69%) que para VRS-B (44%, p=0,001). Conclusiones. Los dos subgrupos de VRS fueron indistinguibles por su presentación clínica y pronóstico. La sensibilidad del test rápido en comparación con la RT-PCR fue baja, lo que limita su utilidad en la toma de decisiones clínicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;40(2): 259-267, mayo-ago. 2017. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165875</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de las características clínicas y diagnósticas de los subgrupos A y B del virus respiratorio sincitial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31083^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31083^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31081^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31081^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33872^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54716^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33872^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
