<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167643</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cardiovascular safety of noninsulin antidiabetic drugs: facts and promises</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Non insulin antidiabetic drugs are widely used in patients with type 2 diabetes. However, the drugs' effect in terms of reducing cardiovascular risk has been the subject of controversy. In 2008, based on the evidence of cardiovascular risk resulting from the use of a number of non insulin antidiabetic drugs, the US Food and Drug Administration published directives on the need to perform cardiovascular safety studies. These directives have helped obtain more evidence, such that at present there are 2 families of drugs that can reduce cardiovascular risk. These recent data have helped us add the reduction of cardiovascular morbidity and mortality to the objective of controlling blood glucose. Nevertheless, research continues with the development of new long-term studies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santiago-Nocito, AM de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abajo, FJ de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Lledó, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los antidiabéticos no insulínicos son fármacos de uso muy extendido en los pacientes con diabetes tipo 2, cuyo efecto sobre la reducción del riesgo cardiovascular ha sido objeto de controversia. En el año 2008, ante la evidencia del riesgo cardiovascular derivado del uso de algunos de ellos, la Food and Drug Administration norteamericana publicó una directriz sobre la necesidad de realizar estudios de seguridad cardiovascular. Ello ha contribuido a disponer de más evidencia, de manera que en el momento actual existen dos familias de fármacos que podrían reducir el riesgo cardiovascular. Estos datos recientes nos permiten añadir, al objetivo de controlar la glucemia, el de reducir la morbimortalidad cardiovascular. No obstante, la investigación continúa con el desarrollo de nuevos estudios a largo plazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;217(8): 473-477, nov. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167643</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguridad cardiovascular de los antidiabéticos no insulínicos: hechos y promesas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2360^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
