<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132198</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reduced version on the athlete burnout questionnaire (ABQ): preliminary psychometric properties</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to present a reduced model of the Spanish version of the Athlete Burnout Questionnaire (ABQ). A reduced version enables answering with shorter times of application, which decreases the adverse effects of longer questionnaires, such as fatigue, lack of motivation, etc. The original version of ABQ is composed of 15 items that measure three dimensions of burnout: physical/emotional exhaustion, (E), reduced sense of accomplishment (RSA) and devaluation of sport (D). The Spanish version was applied to 1101 athletes of both sexes aged between 13 and 37 years (M = 19.35; SD = 4.52). A cross validation study evaluated the internal validity of the questionnaire, using exploratory and confirming analyses. Analysis of items and internal consistency of the factors were also carried out. Two reduced versions appear: one of 12 items (four items per factor) and another one of 9 items (three items per factor). The results show good validity values for the original version and also the two reduced versions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>De Francisco Palacios, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio es presentar un modelo reducido de la versión española del Athlete Burnout Questionnaire (ABQ). Una versión reducida permite tiempos de aplicación menores, lo cual reduce efectos nocivos de cuestionarios más largos, como la fatiga, la falta de motivación, etc. El ABQ original se compone de 15 ítems que miden tres dimensiones de burnout: agotamiento físico/emocional (AFE), reducida sensación de logro (RSL) y devaluación del deporte (D). La versión española fue aplicada a 1101 deportistas de ambos sexos con edades entre 13 y 37 años (M = 19.35; DE = 4.52). Se analizó la validez interna del cuestionario a través de una validación cruzada, usando análisis exploratorios y confirmatorios. También se realizó análisis de ítems y de consistencia interna de los factores. Se ofrecen dos versiones reducidas: una de 12 ítems (cuatro ítems por factor) y otro de 9 ítems (tres ítems por factor). Los resultados muestran buenos indicadores de validez, tanto de la versión original, como de las dos versiones reducidas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;24(1): 177-183, 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132198</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Versión reducida del Athlete Burnout Questionnaire (ABQ): propiedades psicométricas preliminares</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23802^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23802^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23802^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
