<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81580</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bleeding from gastric varices as the initial manifestation of primary pancreatic lymphoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In patients with pancreatic cancer, the most frequent symptoms are abdominal pain, weight loss and jaundice. Upper gastrointestinal bleeding produced by gastric varices is a rare entity in these patients and requires the presence of splenic vein thrombosis (SVT) to be excluded. We describe the case of a young man who presented to the emergency department with hematemesis. Diagnostic tests revealed primary pancreatic lymphoma (PPL), which provoked splenic vein thrombosis, collateral circulation and the formation of isolated bleeding gastric varices. To date, we have found no reports in the literature of PPL with this form of presentation. Finally, we review the literature, with emphasis on the importance of excluding splenic vein thrombosis in patients with isolated gastric varices, and discuss certain features of the diagnosis and treatment of PPL (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vida Pérez, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Galilea, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fraga Rivas, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los síntomas que con mayor frecuencia aparecen en el cáncer de páncreas son el dolor abdominal, la pérdida de peso o la ictericia. La hemorragia digestiva alta por rotura de varices gástricas es una entidad mucho menos prevalente en estos pacientes. Este hallazgo requiere descartar siempre la presencia de trombosis de la vena esplénica. Presentamos el caso de un varón joven que acude a urgencias por hematemesis en el que las pruebas diagnósticas acabaron dilucidando un linfoma pancreático primario (LPP) que provocó trombosis de la vena esplénica, circulación colateral y varices gástricas aisladas sangrantes. Hasta hoy no hemos encontrado en la literatura médica ningún LPP que se exprese inicialmente de este modo. Finalmente realizamos una revisión de la literatura médica e incidimos en la importancia de descartar la trombosis de la vena esplénica en pacientes con varices gástricas aisladas y unas nociones acerca del diagnóstico y tratamiento del LPP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;33(3): 165-170, mar. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81580</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hemorragia por varices gástricas como manifestación inicial de linfoma pancreático primario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8375^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23995^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31325</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31325^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6623^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31325^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28168^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13545</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28066^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10378^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
