<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038539</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Role of nephrectomy in metastatic renal cell carcinoma. Experience of the department of urology Juan Canalejo Hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: We expose our experience in nephrectomy in metastatic renal cell carcinoma, and also show complications, evolution and survival of these patients. Material and methods: We performe a retrospective review of renal cell carcinomaes treated at our service in the period between January 1st 1991 and December 31st 2002. We only studied those which presented in a metastatic pattern (31), and divide these in two groups: the ones which were nephrectomized and those which were not. We try to show the diferences between the two groups in order of status performance (E.C.O.G.), associated morbidity and median survival. In the first group we also study complications of surgery and treatment that patients underwent. Results: we performed nephrectomy in 19 cases, all of them E.C.O.G. 0-1. Median postoperative stay was 12 days, and complication rate was 11.5%. Of these patients, 45% underwent some tipe of systemic treatment, and median survival was 31 months. We didn´t performed nephrectomy in 12 patients, of which 9 were E.C.O.G. 2-3. Asociated comorbidity was higher in this group. Only in three patients any treatment was offerted always with paliative reason. Median survival was 3.8 months. Conclusions: In those patients with good performance status this aproach does not represent more morbility or mortality than in non- metastatic patients, and that is a cornerstone in their management. We also make a literature review in wich we see the last pathways in the management e of these patients, and that show the needing for a conbined approach both quirurgical and inmunotherapical. We have review with special interest the studie&#146;s conclusions of SWOG and EORTC groups (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Gómez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Novás Castro, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruibal Moldes, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Veiga, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Castelo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez Pascual, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Martín, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barbagelata López, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Rosado, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ponce Díaz-Reixa, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Díez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Presentar nuestra experiencia en la realización de nefrectomía en tumores renales que se presentan con metástasis al diagnóstico, y observar las complicaciones, evolución y supervivencia de estos pacientes. Material y métodos: Realizamos una revisión retrospectiva de los adenocarcinomas renales en el período entre 1-1-1991 y 31-12-2002. Estudiamos solamente los que se presentaron con metástasis (31). Se estudian aquellos pacientes a los que se les practicó nefrectomía y aquellos a los que no se les ofreció tratamiento quirúrgico. Buscamos mostrar las diferencias en los dos grupos en cuanto a status vital (Tabla E.C.O.G.), patología concomitante y supervivencia media. En el grupo de los pacientes nefrectomizados estudiamos las complicaciones derivadas de la intervención y el tratamiento posterior. Resultados: Realizamos nefrectomía en 19 casos. Todos ellos E.C.O.G. 0-1. La estancia post operatoria media fue de12 días, y la tasa de complicaciones 11,5%. El 45% de estos pacientes siguieron algún tipo de tratamiento posterior, y la supervivencia media fue de 31 meses. No se realizó nefrectomía en 12 casos, de los cuales 9 eran E.C.O. G 2-3. La patología asociada que presentaban estos pacientes era más importante que en el primer grupo. Sólo en 3 casos se administró tratamiento con fines paliativos y la supervivencia media fue de 3,8 meses. Conclusiones: En pacientes con buen estado vital la nefrectomía no representa más morbilidad ni mortalidad que en los pacientes sin metástasis, y nos parece una opción fundamental en su manejo. Realizamos una revisión bibliográfica en la que recogemos las últimas tendencias en el tratamiento de estos pacientes, que ponen de manifiesto la necesidad del abordaje combinado quirúrgico e inmunoterápico. Nos parecen de interés fundamental las conclusiones de los estudios del SWOG y del EORTC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;29(2): 190-197, feb. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038539</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papel de la nefrectomía en el adenocarcinoma renal metastático: experiencia del Servicio de Urología del Hospital Juan Canalejo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24890</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6913^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6940^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28604</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9585^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7855^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7855^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2335^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2335^s22064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
