<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72665</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mortality risk in spanish adults with diagnosed diabetes, undiagnosed diabetes or pre-diabetes. The Asturias Study 1998&#150;2004</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and Objectives. Although type-2 diabetes is a well-known cause of death, the mortality associated with undiagnosed diabetes and early-stage dysglycemia has not been clearly determined. Methods. This study included 1015 individuals aged 30-75 years who took part in the first phase of the Asturias study (1998-1999). Participants completed a questionnaire and underwent a physical examination and an oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT). All deaths that occurred in the cohort within 6 years of follow-up (ie December 1998 to December 2004) were recorded. Results. Participants were divided into four groups according to the condition indicated by their OGTT result in the first phase of the study: normoglycemia, pre-diabetes, undiagnosed diabetes, or diagnosed diabetes (World Health Organization 1999 criteria). A total of 42 deaths were recorded during follow-up. With normoglycemic individuals acting as a control group, multivariate analysis showed that the relative risk of mortality was 2.5 (95% CI, 1-6.3) in the group with diagnosed diabetes, 2.7 (95% CI, 1.1-6.7) in the group with undiagnosed diabetes, and 1.6 (95% CI, 0.7-4) in the group with pre-diabetes. Conclusions. Both individuals with diagnosed diabetes and those with undiagnosed diabetes had a risk of mortality around 2.5-3 times greater than individuals with normoglycemia. Those with pre-diabetes also had increased mortality relative to the control group, though the difference was not significant. multivariate analysis showed that the relative risk of mortality was 2.5 (95% CI, 1-6.3) in the group with diagnosed diabetes, 2.7 (95% CI, 1.1-6.7) in the group with undiagnosed diabetes and 1.6 (95% CI, 0.7-4) in the group with pre-diabetes. Conclusions. Both individuals with diagnosed diabetes and those with undiagnosed diabetes had a risk of mortality around 2.5-3 times greater than individuals with normoglycemia. Those with pre-diabetes also had increased mortality relative to the control group, though the difference was not significant (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Delgado, Elías</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Botas, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valdés, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Cadórniga, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Aunque la diabetes mellitus DM tipo 2 es una causa establecida de mortalidad, el riesgo de mortalidad asociado a DM no diagnosticada y a estadios previos de disglucemia no está claramente definido. Métodos. El estudio incluyó a 1.015 individuos de 30-75 años de edad que participaron en la primera fase del Estudio Asturias (1998-1999), realizando encuesta, exploración física y SOG. Se registraron los fallecimientos en la cohorte durante 6 años de seguimiento (diciembre de 1998 a diciembre de 2004). Resultados. Se clasificó a los sujetos en cuatro grupos según el resultado de la SOG en la primera fase del estudio: normoglucemia, prediabetes, DM ignorada y DM conocida (criterios de la OMS 1999). Se registraron 42 muertes durante el seguimiento. Respecto al grupo control con normoglucemia, el riesgo relativo (RR) de mortalidad en el modelo multivariable fue 2,5 (intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 1-6,3) en el grupo con DM conocida, RR = 2,7 (IC del 95%, 1,1-6,7) en el grupo con DM ignorada y RR = 1,6 (IC del 95%, 0,7-4) en el grupo con prediabetes. Conclusiones. Tanto los individuos con DM conocida como los que tenían DM no diagnosticada presentaron un riesgo de mortalidad alrededor de 2,5-3 veces superior al de los individuos con normoglucemia. En individuos con prediabetes también se encontró un incremento de mortalidad frente al grupo control, aunque no estadísticamente significativo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;62(5): 528-534, mayo 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72665</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Riesgo de mortalidad en diabetes diagnosticada, diabetes no diagnosticada y prediabetes en población adulta española. Estudio Asturias 1998-2004</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28567</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11671^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11671^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11671^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200905</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
