<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149987</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Development of two Spanish versions of the Verbal Selective Reminding Test</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Selective Reminding procedure has become a widely used test for evaluating verbal learning and memory. However, since this test was mainly devised for use in English speaking individuals, disadvantages could appear when translations of the test are applied to Spanish speaking patients. To overcome these difficulties, two Spanish versions of the Verbal Selective Reminding Test were devised and administered to 48 healthy individuals, 19-31 years in age, in two separate sessions. We found that performances on the two forms were comparable, except for one measure. All the variables on both forms yielded significant positive correlations. We also examined test-retest reliability separately for both possible orders, with Order 2 (Form 2 administered first) being more reliable than Order 1 (Form 1 administered first) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morales, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juan-Malpartida, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Test de Recuerdo Verbal Selectivo (TRVS) es una de las pruebas más extensamente utilizadas para la evaluación del aprendizaje y la memoria verbales. Sin embargo, este test ha sido construido principalmente para evaluar a pacientes de habla inglesa, no existiendo todavía ninguna versión española que pueda ser utilizada para evaluar a pacientes de habla hispana. Para solventar este problema, se construyeron dos versiones españolas del Test de Recuerdo Verbal Selectivo administrándose a 48 sujetos sanos, 19-31 años, en dos sesiones separadas. Encontramos que las respuestas de los sujetos a las dos versiones fueron comparables, excepto para un índice. Todas las variables sobre ambas formas presentaron correlaciones positivas significativas. También se estudió la fiabilidad test-retest para cada orden, encontrándose que el orden 2 (en el que la forma 2 se administró primero) fue más fiable que el orden 1 (donde la forma 1 se administró primero) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);12(supl.2): 108-110, 2000. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149987</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Versiones españolas del test de Recuerdo Verbal Selectivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12374</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12479</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15111</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
