<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042234</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-0599</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gender and age-differences in depressive symptomatology in adult development</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Our study has as objective to define the differences in the framework of the depressive disorders according to the sex, through the adult development.    Method: A self elaboration inventary about depressive Symptomatology has been applied to a sample composed by the general population's of the Region of Murcia 507 mature people. Later on, we have carried out different factorial analysis, for the study of the framework of these symptoms, keeping in mind the variable age and sexo    Results: Different configurations of the depressive Symptomathology have been obtained in both sexes and in the different age groups.    Conclusion: This results show the necessity to continue carrying out studies of this type, in order to obtain a more precise knowledge of the relationship among these variables. These works, could show the influences of cultural and cohort, factors as elements that can impact directly the validity and utility of the data obtained in this type of studies</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Navas, A. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riquelme Marín, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Díaz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Nuestro estudio tiene como objetivo delimitar tanto la sintomatología depresiva en ambos sexos como delimitar dicha sintomatología en distintos grupos de edad según el género.    Método: Se han realizado 8 análisis factoriales, en total, para un inventario de 57 síntomas depresivos. Se han aplicado para cada uno de los sexos y para cada grupo de edad según el género. La muestra está formada por 507 sujetos tomados de la población general de la Región de Murcia.    Resultados: Se han obtenido distintas configuraciones en la sintomatología depresiva en ambos sexos y en los distintos grupos de edad.    Conclusión: Faltan más estudios para poder delimitar la sintomatología depresiva en función del género a lo largo del desarrollo adulto, y así poder prevenir y tratar dichos problemas depresivos actuando sobre los síntomas concretos en cada caso</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psiquiatr;21(7): 312-323, dic. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042234</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características diferenciales de la depresión entre hombre y mujeres a través del desarrollo adulto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37627^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
