<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110544</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-7823</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Although elder abuse and neglect is not an unknown situation in research and intervention programs, current perspectives indicate that when highlighting age as a factor for this kind of violence, the gender perspective in the understanding of violence towards the elderly has been overlooked. This review attempts to shed light on this gender perspective when we look at what kind of abuse older people, and especially older women, are suffering. Three issues concerning the mistreatment of older women will be reviewed: the characteristics of intimate partner violence against older women, health and quality of life consequences of this kind of abuse, and intervention programs implemented in this group. The aim of this paper is to provide a framework to start national studies and interventions regarding intimate partner violence against older women, an issue barely studied in our country (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Celdrán, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A pesar de que el maltrato y la negligencia hacia las personas mayores no es una temática desconocida ni a nivel científico ni del intervención práctica, perspectivas actuales señalan que al resaltar la edad como factor explicativo de la violencia hacia este colectivo, se ha olvidado la perspectiva de género como forma de entender y actuar sobre la violencia hacia las personas mayores. Esta revisión bibliográfica se centra en esta cuestión de género a la hora de detectar e intervenir en la violencia dirigida hacia la mujer mayor. En concreto se analizarán tres ámbitos estudiados a nivel internacional: características del maltrato hacia la mujer mayor, consecuencias de dicho maltrato a nivel de salud y calidad de vida y propuestas de intervención hacia este colectivo. El artículo quiere servir de marco para iniciar estudios a nivel nacional sobre la problemática de las mujeres mayores que sufren violencia de pareja, tema todavía inédito en nuestro entorno (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pap. psicol;34(1): 57-64, ene.-abr. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110544</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La violencia hacia la mujer mayor: Revisión bibliográfica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33920</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13564^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50239</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32346^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
