<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122899</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Study and characterization of the atropine-oxime autoinjector DEF. Design of new autoinjectors for NBC Defense and other emergency drugs</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Autoinjectors (AI) are devices for parenteral administration (im) of emergency medications for self or buddy aid. They have NBC Defence military interest for the administration of antidotes against nerve agents and other emergency medications. It is needed five new AI that can be manufactured by the Spanish Pharmaceutical Services, in addition to the one currently made. Objectives: AJP Autoinjector (AI-AJP) presentation and its military medication Autoinjector of atropine-oxime DEF  (AI-AOD), as an I+D process result about AI carry out by the Military Pharmaceutical Services, and its characterization. The results are applied to the design of five new AI for NBC Defense. Methods: In the absence of formal testing and evaluation criteria for these devices, the scientific publications and the experience gained from two decades of development and manufacture of AI-AJP have been reviewed, to set characterization procedures, and to evaluate the pharmaceutical quality and the functional properties under normal conditions and in static and dynamic stress. By mean of ACAD and pharmaceutical development programs, five new AI have been designed. Results: AI-AJP availability, and its presentation AI-AOD. Components, operation, and results presentation from the analysis of design, process and control variables: usability, portability, dynamic operation, involved forces, injectability, contents, sterility, particles, pyrogens, stability, and physical resistance. The new five AI designs and characteristics are exposed, to which the results obtained in this study are applicable. Conclusion: The AJP Autoinyector meets the requirements demanded by the current science state, is safe in operation, and robust under static and dynamic stress. It is stable and the injection is consistent. Five new AI have been designed (Atropine, Diazepam, Multi-components, Morphine, and Epinephrine) needed to NBC Defense and Emergencies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Ramos, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: Los autoinyectables (AI) son dispositivos para administración de medicamentos de urgencia por vía parenteral (i.m.) por el afectado o un compañero. Tienen interés militar en Defensa NBQ para la administración de antídotos contra agentes nerviosos y otros medicamentos de urgencia. Se estiman necesarios cinco nuevos AI que pueden ser fabricados por los Servicios Farmacéuticos de la Defensa, además del que se fabrica en la actualidad. Objetivos: Presentación del Autoinyectable AJP (AI-AJP) y su preparado Autoinyectable  de atropina-oxima DEF (AI-AOD), resultantes de la I+D sobre AI en el CEMILFARDEF, y su caracterización. Aplicación de resultados al diseño de cinco nuevos AI de interés en Defensa NBQ. Métodos: Ante la falta de ensayos y criterios de valoración oficiales para AI, se realiza una revisión bibliográfica y un estudio retrospectivo sobre la investigación básica llevada a cabo durante dos décadas en el desarrollo y fabricación del AI-AJP, estableciendo procedimientos de caracterización y evaluación de la calidad farmacéutica y propiedades funcionales en condiciones normales y de estrés. Mediante programas ACAD y ensayos galénicos se diseñan cinco nuevos AI. Resultados: Obtención del AI-AJP y su presentación AI-AOD. Presentación de sus componentes, funcionamiento y resultados del análisis de las variables implicadas en su diseño, producción y control: usabilidad, portabilidad, funcionamiento, fuerzas, inyectabilidad, contenidos, esterilidad, partículas, pirógenos, estabilidad, y resistencia. Se expone el diseño de cinco nuevos AI, a los que son aplicables los resultados  obtenidos en este estudio. Conclusión: El Autoinyectable AJP cumple los requisitos exigidos por el estado actual de la ciencia, es seguro enfuncionamiento, y robusto en resistencia al estrés estático y dinámico. Es estable y la inyección consistente. Se han diseñado cinco nuevos  AI (Atropina, Diazepam, Multicomponentes, Morfina y Epinefrina) necesarios en Defensa NBQ y situaciones de urgencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;70(1): 7-9, ene.-mar. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122899</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio y caracterización del Autoinyectable de atropinaoxima DEF. Diseño de nuevos Autoinyectables para Defensa NBQ y otros medicamentos de urgencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10270^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22668^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d555</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1291^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51708</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d938^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9077</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
