<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116391</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of an Intensive Intervention Program in Suicidal Behaviour</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Suicide is a public health problem. Consumed suicides reach 1 million cases per year worldwide and it is estimated that the number of suicide attempts is 10 to 20 times higher. The aim of this study was to evaluate the effectiveness in reducing repeat suicide attempts in a program for the prevention of suicidal behavior: Intensive Intervention Program (IIP). Methods: We performed a study that compared a cohort of patients exposed to IIP intervention with another cohort of patients exposed to conventional therapy. The sample was made up of 191 patients, 89 in the treatment group and 102 patients in conventional treatment group, with a 12-month follow-up. Results: Relapse occurred in 20.6% of patients receiving conventional treatment relapse compared with 10% in the treatment group (p=0.047). Patients treated in the program had a 2.88 times lower risk of relapse (p=0.015), this being independent of the number of previous attempts, age, gender, need for admission after the index attempt and aggregated diagnosis. Conclusions: The results show that subjects who are treated in the IIP relapse less, need fewer admissions and the time elapsed between the treatment and the first repeat suicide attempt is greater (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferrer, Ernesto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias, Fernanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reijas, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El suicidio es un problema de salud pública. El suicidio consumado asciende a 1 millón de casos al año en el mundo y se estima que el número de intentos de suicidio es 10 o 20 veces superior. El objetivo del presente trabajo es la evaluación de la efectividad en la reducción de reintentos de suicidio en un Programa de prevención de conducta suicida: el Programa de Intervención Intensiva (PII). Metodología: Se realiza un estudio en el que se compara una cohorte de pacientes expuestos a la intervención en PII con otra cohorte de pacientes expuestos a terapia convencional. La muestra está formada por un total de 191 pacientes, 89 del grupo de tratamiento en PII y 102 pacientes del grupo de tratamiento convencional. Con un seguimiento de 12 meses. Resultados: un 20,6% de los pacientes que recibe tratamiento convencional recaen frente al 10% del grupo de tratamiento en PII (p=0,047). Los pacientes atendidos en el programa presentaron un riesgo menor 2,88 veces de recaída (p=0,015), esto es independiente del número de intentos previos, edad, sexo, necesidad de ingreso tras el intento índice y diagnóstico agregado. Conclusiones: Los resultados muestran que los sujetos que reciben tratamiento en el PII tiene menos reintentos, necesitan ingresar menos, y el tiempo trascurrido desde el inicio del tratamiento y el primer reintento es mayor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;41(5): 279-286, sept.-oct. 2013. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116391</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de un Programa de Intervención Intensiva en Conducta Suicida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54296</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13792^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
