<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058415</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-1285</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Peripheral giant cell granuloma: immunohistochemical analysis of different markers. Study of three cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Peripheral giant cell granuloma (PGCG) is a non-neoplastic lesion representing a local hyperplastic reaction to injury or inflammation. It is known to be a reactive soft tissue lesion that develops only within the oral cavity, with a slightly predilection for female sex. The usual localization for PGCG is the premolar region and the crest of the edentulous ridge. This study presents three cases of PGCG, including 2 male and 1 female, with an age comprised between 25 and 35 years. All patients were treated with resection biopsy and no one relapsed. With the aim of determine the probable origin of stromal mononuclear cells and multinuclear giant cells, each case was then studied by immunohistochemistry to evaluate the expression of endothelial and monocyte/macrophage lineage. Immunohistochemical results showed a strong diffuse positivity for CD-68 in round mononuclear stromal cells and in multinucleate giant cells. These latter were immunonegative for CD-34 and only focally positive for &amp;#945;-1 antitrypsin. These results suggest that multinucleated giant cell shows an osteoclast phenotype and that probably derive from monocyte/macrophage lineage and that do not derive from the endothelial cells of the capillary. In second instance, we underlined the importance of an exhaustive dia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ciavarella, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lo Muzio, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mazzanti, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Turco, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escudero, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bascones, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Falaschini, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Di Cosola, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El granuloma periférico de células gigantes (GPCG) es una lesión de tejido blando no neoplásica ocasionada por una reacción hiperplásica a consecuencia de un traumatismo o inflamación. Es una lesión reactiva del tejido blando que se desarrolla exclusivamente en la cavidad oral y con una ligera predilección en el sexo femenino. La localización habitual de GPCG es en la región de los premolares y la mucosa de la cresta alveolar edéntula. Se presentan tres casos con GPCG (dos hombres y una mujer) con una edad comprendida entre los 25 y 35años. Todos los pacientes se trataron con resección quirúrgica y ninguno sufrió recidivas. Con el propósito de determinar el posible origen de las células estromales mononucleares y de las células gigantes multinucleares, las muestras de cada caso se estudiaron mediante inmunohistoquímica (marcadores CD-68, CD-34 y &amp;#945;-1antitripsina) con el fin de evaluar la expresión del linaje endotelial y del linaje monocito/macrófago. Los resultados inmunohistoquímicos mostraron una marcada positividad difusa de CD-68 en las células estromales mononucleares y en las células gigantes multinucleadas. Estas últimas resultaron ser inmunonegativas para CD-34 y sólo puntualmente positivas para &amp;#945;-1 antitripsina. Estos resultados sugieren que las células gigantes multinucleares poseen un fenotipo osteoclástico, proviniendo del linaje monocito/macrófago, y que no derivan del linaje de las células endoteliales de los capilares. Se establece la importancia de un exhaustivo diagnóstico y de una exéresis quirúrgica completa de la lesión (curetaje óseo) con el propósito de evitar la reabsorción del diente y hueso adyacente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av Odontoestomatol;23(4): 181-188, jul.-ago. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058415</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Granuloma periférico de células gigantes: análisis inmunohistoquímico de la población celular en tres casos clínicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6024^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24199^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6024^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24199^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37266^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10674^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10675^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37266^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
