<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126937</identifier>
<setSpec>2254-2884</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acure renal failure caused by multiple myeloma: care in the hemodialysis unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Multiple myeloma (MM) is a hematologic malignancy with abnormal proliferation of immunoglobulins and its chains in blood. Renal insufficiency is a frequent and serious complication that can lead to a renal failure in 20 % of cases and may require renal replacement therapy. As it starts with non-specific symptoms, it&#146;s important an early treatment to prevent renal damage in order to avoid complications and improve survival conditions. The extracorporeal blood purification techniques using high pore filters or high cut- off (HCO) are very effective because they remove 60-90% of the chains and recover renal function in 50-80% of thecases. Due to the long time sessions characteristics and the treatment complexity, nurses are required an exclusive dedication during the entire process. Methods: 9 patients diagnosed of MM with figures over 500mg/dL light chains treated with HCO filters for at least 6 consecutive sessions of 6 hours. Results: A total of 107 sessions were performed and renal function was recovered in 7 cases. Complications: 18 flow problems, 12 circuit coagulation episodes, 13 fever episodes, 14 hypotension, 13 transfusions, 5 anxiolytic treatment and 7 catheter changes. Conclusions: The long term with haemodialysis HCO filters are effective in removing the light chains and recovering the renal function. The role of nursing is important including a complex technique and giving a human response to the debut of this severe disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vecino Soler, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcén Letosa, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cantín Lahoz, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aznar Buil, Blanca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paula Rojo Zulaica, Elisa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El mieloma múltiple (MM) es una neoplasia hematológica con proliferación anormal de inmunoglobulinas y sus cadenas en sangre. La insuficiencia renal es una complicación grave y frecuente que puede derivar en fracaso renal en el 20% de los casos y puede requerir de terapia renal sustitutiva. Al debutar con una clínica tan inespecífica es importante un diagnóstico y tratamiento precoz para evitar el daño renal ya que agrava las complicaciones y condiciona la supervivencia. La depuración sanguínea mediante técnicas extracorpóreas con filtros de alto poro o high cut-off (HCO) son muy eficaces eliminando el 60-90% de las cadenas y recuperando la función renal en 50-80% de los casos. Debido a las características de estas sesiones prolongadas y la complejidad del tratamiento se requiere dedicación exclusiva por parte de enfermería durante todo el proceso. Métodos: 9 pacientes diagnosticados de MM con cifras de más de 500mg/dl de cadenas ligeras tratados con filtros HCO durante al menos 6 sesiones consecutivas de 6 horas de duración. Resultados: Se realizaron 107 sesiones y se recuperó la función renal en 7. Complicaciones: 18 problemas de flujo, 12 episodios de coagulación del circuito, 13 fiebre, 14 hipotensiones, 13 transfusiones, 5 tratamientos con ansiolítico y 7 recambios de catéter. Conclusiones: Las hemodiálisis de larga duración con filtros HCO son eficaces para eliminar las cadenas ligeras y recuperar la función renal. El papel de la enfermería es importante englobando una técnica compleja y dando una respuesta humana al debut de una enfermedad tan grave (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. nefrol;17(2): 135-143, abr.-jun. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126937</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El fracaso renal agudo por mieloma múltiple: cuidados de los pacientes en una unidad de hemodiálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9920^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9920^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9293^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9293^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6587^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9293^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
