<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147652</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Detection of cognitive decline in patients over 65 years of age who visit the pharmacy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Alzheimer&#146;s disease (AD) is the most prevalent form of dementia, and the number of sufferers increases with the rising life expectancy and the general aging of the population. Thus, this condition will potentially be the most overwhelming health problem of this century. Although AD is an illness that currently has no cure, it is treatable. An early diagnosis is essential in order to initiate treatment that can slow down the progression of the disease and maintain the patient autonomous for a longer period of time. The objective of this study is to carry out a selection of patients over 65 years of age who come to the pharmacy regularly to acquire their medication and who agree to participate in the study. During the interview, the cognitive ability of the patient is evaluated using the Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE) and their medication is studied for the purpose of identifying those drugs that can cause cognition to deteriorate. In a total of 124 participants, the MMSE has detected a possible cognitive deterioration of 23.4%, as opposed to the 11.7% reported by Pfeiffer. The study of the medication of patients who have undergone the MMSE has revealed a significantly more marked deterioration in those taking benzodiazepines than in those consuming other drugs. The pharmacist, as a member of the medical team, is in a privileged position to detect slight cognitive decline and refer the patient to a general practitioner to be examined and diagnosed and, if necessary, referred to a specialist (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torres, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilaplana, AM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad de Alzheimer (EA) es la demencia más prevalente en todas las edades. El número de pacientes con esta enfermedad aumenta con el incremento de la esperanza de vida y el envejecimiento de la población, y será potencialmente el problema de salud pública más arrollador de este siglo. Aunque la EA es, hoy por hoy, incurable, se puede establecer un tratamiento. El diagnóstico precoz de los pacientes es fundamental para iniciar los tratamientos que puedan ralentizar la progresión de la enfermedad y dotar de autonomía durante más tiempo a los pacientes. Este trabajo pretende realizar un cribado entre los pacientes mayores de 65 años que acuden a la oficina de farmacia a retirar su medicación habitual y que accedan a participar en el estudio. Durante la entrevista se valora la función cognitiva del paciente mediante la utilización del Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE) y se estudia la medicación de los pacientes en busca de posibles fármacos que puedan empeorar la cognición. Entre un total de 124 participantes, mediante el MMSE se ha detectado un 23,4% de casos de posible deterioro cognitivo, frente al 11,7% hallado mediante el test de Pfeiffer. Al estudiar la medicación del paciente, se han constatado diferencias significativas en el consumo de benzodiazepinas y el deterioro detectado con el test MMSE. El farmacéutico, como parte integrante del equipo de atención primaria, se encuentra en una situación privilegiada para detectar los posibles deterioros cognitivos leves y remitir a estas personas al médico de atención primaria para su valoración y diagnóstico, y/o remisión a un especialista (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;9(3): 109-116, oct. 2007. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147652</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Detección de deterioro cognitivo en pacientes mayores de 65 años que acuden a la oficina de farmacia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11016^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50249</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
