<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133807</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Health-Related Quality of Life as an Explanatory Variable of Primary Care Consultations: Sex Differences</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: It is well known the inverse relationship between health-related quality of life (HRQoL) and the use of consultations. However, most studies deal sex as a confounding variable rather than to explicitly investi¬gate sex differences. The study aims to know the influence of HRQoL of the elderly on the use of Primary Care consultations in a sex analysis. Methods: Throughout 2013, 191 women and 155 men aged 65 years or older were enrolled in the study and assessed with interviews and analysis of medical records. We used the EuroQol-5D to assess the HRQoL and several demographic, clinical and social support variables were also analyzed. Two multiple linear regression models were developed. Results: HRQoL showed a negative correlation with the use of con-sultations (Spearman´s rho=-0,22; p=0,0001) and a crude OR value of 1,85 (95% CI:1,2&#150;2,9). The association remained significant after adjus¬ting for demographic [OR=1,99 (95% CI: 1,2&#150;3,2)], clinical [OR=1,79 (95% CI: 1,1&#150;2,9)] or social support covariates [OR=1,83 (95% CI: 1,1&#150;2,9)]. In regression analysis, the values of standardized coefficient (&amp;#946;) related to HRQoL were 0,22 (95% CI:-36,7&#150; -6,9) in females and 0,03 (95% CI:-15,6&#150;23,1) in males. Conclusions: In women &amp;#8805;65 years, HRQoL shows the greatest explana¬tory power of use of consultations, after adjusting for demographic, clinical and social support covariates. By contrast, its influence on men is negligible (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Molleda, Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojo Cárdenas, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pariente Rodrigo, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gálvez Castillo, Encarnación</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Expósito, Josefina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López León, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Garrido, Ana Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alessia Sgaramella, Giusi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: Es conocida la asociación inversa que existe entre la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud (CVRS) y el consumo de consultas. Sin embargo, el sexo es considerado habitualmente como variable de confusión, y son escasos los estudios que han analizado explícitamente las diferencias de sexo en esta cuestión. El objetivo fue conocer la influencia de la CVRS sobre el uso de consultas de Atención Primaria en las personas &gt;65 años, en un análisis diferenciado por sexo. Métodos: La selección de participantes se realizó a lo largo de 2013, 191 mujeres y 155 varones de &amp;#8805;65 años fueron estudiados mediante entre¬vista y análisis de historias clínicas. Se utilizó el Cuestionario EuroQol-5D y fueron analizadas variables demográficas, clínicas y de apoyo social. Se elaboraron 2 modelos de regresión múltiple, uno dirigido a las mujeres y otro a los varones.  Resultados: La CVRS se correlacionó de forma negativa con el con¬sumo de consultas (Rho-Spearman=-0,22; p=0,0001), con una OR cruda de 1,85 (IC95%: 1,2-2,9). La asociación se mantuvo significativa al ajustar tanto por variables demográficas [OR=1,99 (IC95%: 1,2&#150;3,2)], como por variables clínicas [OR=1,79 (IC95%: 1,1-2,9)] o de apoyo social [OR=1,83 (IC95%: 1,1&#150;2,9)]. En el análisis de regresión, los valores del coeficiente estandarizado (&amp;#946;) asociado a la CVRS fueron 0,22 (IC95%: -36,7&#150; -6,9) en las mujeres, y 0,03 (-15,6&#150;23,1) en los varones. Conclusiones: En las mujeres de &amp;#8805;65 años la CVRS es la variable con mayor capacidad explicativa de consumo de consultas, tras ajustar por va¬riables demográficas, clínicas y de apoyo social. Por el contrario, en los varones su influencia es prácticamente nula (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;89(1): 61-73, ene.-feb. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133807</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida relacionada con la salud como variable explicativa del consumo de consultas en atención primaria: un análisis por sexo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55170</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
