<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75151</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-6045</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Determination of the postural disorders in students from the Stomatology Clinics of the Benemerita Autonomous University of Puebla, Mexico</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To determine the main postural alterations in the students from the Stomatology Clinical of the Benemerita Autonomous University of Puebla (BUAP), in order to prevent future injuries associated with the clinical practice. Materials and methods A descriptive, observational, cross-sectional study based on the assessment of 100 students from the BUAP with at least one year of clinical practice. The students were examined in their underwear and barefoot, using a grid. Nine items were analyzed using the lateral view, 7 with the posterior view and 5 with the anterior view. The posture of the student was then classified comprehensively as: posture without deviation, mild deviation, moderate deviation and severe deviation. Descriptive statistics was calculated for all variables. Results We included 72 (72%) females and 28 (28%) males, with an average of 21.4±1.8 years of age, 61.7±12.7kg, 1.63±09m of height and BMI of 22.5±3.3. In the lateral view, 39.5% had moderate deviation, in the posterior view 81.4% mild deviation, and in anterior view, 48.1% mild deviation. The total alignment revealed that 73.6% had mild deviation and 26.4% moderate deviation. Conclusion The entire sample had some postural alterations. Two out of every ten students had moderate postural deviation and the remaining eight showed mild postural alterations(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Huixtlaca-Rojo, C. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rebollo-Vázquez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santiago-Álvarez, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espinosa-De Santillana, I. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Jiménez, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Determinar las principales alteraciones posturales de los estudiantes de la Clínica de Estomatología de la Benemérita Universidad Autónoma de Puebla (BUAP) con el fin de prevenir futuras lesiones relacionadas con la práctica clínica. Materiales y métodos Estudio observacional descriptivo, transversal, unicéntrico, basado en la evaluación de cien alumnos de la Facultad de Estomatología de la BUAP con un mínimo de un año de práctica clínica. Los alumnos fueron explorados en ropa interior y descalzos, con uso de una cuadrícula. Se analizaron 9 reactivos en vista lateral, 7 en vista posterior y 5 en vista anterior para posteriormente calificar la postura del alumno en forma global como: postura sin desviación, desviación ligera, desviación moderada y desviación severa. Se calculó estadística descriptiva de todas las variables. Resultados Se incluyeron 72 (72%) mujeres y 28 (28%) hombres, con un promedio de 21,4±1,8 años de edad, 61,7±12,7kg de peso, 1,63±0,09m de talla y 22,5±3,3 kg/m2 de IMC. En la vista lateral el 39,5% presentó desviación moderada, en vista posterior el 81,4% presentó desviación leve y en vista anterior el 48,1% presentó desviación leve. La alineación total reveló que el 73,6% tuvo desviación leve y el 26,4% desviación moderada. Conclusión La totalidad de la muestra presentó alguna alteración postural, 2 de cada diez alumnos presentaron desviación postural moderada y los ocho restantes presentaron alteraciones posturales leves(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. iberoam. fisioter. kinesiol. (Ed. impr.);12(2): 60-66, jul.-dic. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75151</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Determinación de las alteraciones posturales en alumnos de las clínicas de la Facultad de Estomatología de la Benemérita Universidad Autónoma de Puebla, México</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13722^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13722^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9331^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30392^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11625^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3812^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9331^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
