<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161963</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Integration of the Community Pharmacist in a Domiciliary Care Team: cost review of a pilot experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To estimate the economic burden that suppose the patients subscribed to the primary domiciliary care service and the cost that would suppose the inclusion of a pharmacist in this team. Methods: It was carried out a descriptive and prospective study that was focused on the evaluation of the domiciliary care program&#146;s economic burden. Location: CAP Montnegre of an urban Basic Area of Health (BAH) in Barcelona city. Participants: Patients included in the domiciliary care service that were attended between January and June 2014 by the case manager&#146;s nurse of the center. Pharmacists reviewed patients&#146; medication to identify problems related to medication and propose interventions to the domiciliary care team. Main measurements: Patients&#146; medical records were reviewed to collect the primary and specialized health care, the emergencies, the hospitalizations and medical examinations costs during six months. It was considered necessary a pharmacist visit every six months to evaluate the action plan. The average costs for each level were calculated. Results: 50 patients participated in the study: they generated a total average cost of 3174.5&#128; in 6 months. From this total amount, 29% was its origin in primary health care and 66% in secondary care. The pharmaceutical intervention average cost per patient was 116,4&#128;, which would suppose an increase of 3,7% of the costs generated by these patients. Conclusion: The study shows that the cost generated by patients in domiciliary care is high and that the inclusion of a pharmacist in the team would suppose a relatively low cost. It will be necessary to carry out cost-effectiveness&#146; studies of multidisciplinary interventions with a pharmacist to evaluate the clinical impact and the effectiveness of these interventions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lumbreras Garuz, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Travé Mercadé, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio Valera, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>March Pujol, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerra-Barrero, MB</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Via Sosa, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estimar la carga económica que suponen los pacientes adscritos al servicio de atención domiciliaria de atención primaria y el coste que supondría incluir un farmacéutico en este equipo. Método: Estudio descriptivo prospectivo de evaluación de la carga económica del programa de atención domiciliaria. Emplazamiento: CAP Montnegre de una ABS urbana de la ciudad de Barcelona. Participantes: Pacientes adscritos al servicio de atención domiciliaria que fueron atendidos entre enero y junio de 2014 por la enfermera gestora de casos del centro. Las farmacéuticas revisaron la medicación de los pacientes para identificar problemas relacionados con la medicación y proponer intervenciones al equipo de atención domiciliaria. Mediciones principales: Revisando los historiales clínicos de los pacientes, se recogieron los costes en atención primaria, especializada, urgencias, ingresos y pruebas en 6 meses. Se estimó necesaria una visita del farmacéutico cada 6 meses para evaluar el plan de actuación. Se calcularon los costes medios para cada nivel asistencial. Resultados: Participaron 50 pacientes que generaron un coste medio total en 6 meses de 3174,5&#128;, siendo el 29% la atención primaria y el 66% la atención secundaria. El coste medio por paciente de la intervención farmacéutica fue de 116,4&#128; (lo que supondría un incremento del 3,7% de los costes generados por estos pacientes). Conclusión: El estudio muestra que el coste generado por los pacientes en atención domiciliaria es elevado y que la inclusión de un farmacéutico en el equipo supondría un coste relativamente bajo. Será necesario realizar estudios de coste-efectividad de intervenciones multidisciplinares con farmacéutico para evaluar el impacto clínico y la eficiencia de estas intervenciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;19(2): 80-82, 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161963</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Integración del farmacéutico comunitario en un equipo de Atención Domiciliaria: estudio de costes de una experiencia piloto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50249^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30152^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50249^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30313^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50249^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6856^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
