<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158112</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-3334</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study analyzes the relationship between demotivation among teachers and sociodemographic (sex, age and marital status), work-related (area of expertise, teaching status and years spent teaching) and personality variables (trait anxiety and coping strategies). Participants were 66 lecturers at the University of the Basque Country and the Public University of Navarra (mean age = 40.48, SD = 9.02; 73% women, 27% men). The «Demotivation» subscale of the Teacher Stress Scale ED-6 was used, along with the Trait Anxiety Questionnaire, an adaptation of the Responses to Stress Questionnaire and some measures created ad hoc. The analyses revealed significant differences in sex, age and marital status; differences were also found in the work-related and personality variables. The profile of a demotivated teacher is a young, single woman from the social field, with no stable position and a tendency to suffer from anxiety, who uses adequate coping strategies such as emotional regulation, although scores highly also in denial. These and other questions which affect teacher demotivation should be taken into consideration during the training of university teaching staff (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Conejero López, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual Jimeno, Aitziber</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio analiza la relación de varias variables sociodemográficas (sexo, edad y estado civil), varias variables laborales (ámbito de conocimiento, categoría docente y años de ejercicio docente) y de personalidad (ansiedad rasgo y estrategias de afrontamiento) con la desmotivación docente. Participaron 66 profesores/as de la Universidad del País Vasco y de la Universidad Pública de Navarra (edad media = 40,48; DT = 9,02; 73% mujeres, 27% varones). Se utilizó la subescala «Desmotivación» de la Escala de Estrés Docente ED-6, el Cuestionario de Ansiedad Rasgo, el Responses to Stress Questionnaire adaptado y algunas medidas creadas ad hoc. Los análisis arrojaron diferencias significativas en sexo, edad y estado civil; también se hallaron diferencias en las variables laborales y de personalidad. El perfil de profesor desmotivado es una mujer joven, soltera, del ámbito de social, sin puesto estable, tendente a experimentar ansiedad y que emplea formas de afrontamiento adecuadas como la regulación emocional pero también la negación. Éstas y otras cuestiones que afectan a la desmotivación docente deberían ser tomadas en cuenta en la formación del profesorado universitario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apuntes psicol;33(1): 5-16, 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158112</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La desmotivación del profesorado universitario y su relación con variables sociodemográficas, laborales y de personalidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13228^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d231^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d231^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56173^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56173^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13228^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56173^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56173^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35223</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
