<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167079</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Disaster mortality in Spain: An analysis of the period 1950-2012</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To estimate the impact on mortality due to disasters in Spain since1950 to 2012 and its epidemiological trends. Methods: Retrospective observational study with trend analysis by regression analysis and exponential smoothing. Results: We studied 284 events during the period. 57% were technological disasters (81% transport accidents), 39% were natural disasters (64% biological disasters) and 4% deliberated events. We found a significant (p&lt;0,05) increasing trend in the total number of disasters, as well in natural and technological disaster groups, and also in the biological, climatological and transport accident subgroups. Technological disasters show highest average mortality per episode. Decreasing mortality trend was found significant (p&lt;0,05). Conclusions: Spain showed a mixed pattern of disaster type although technological ones are the most frequent. There is an upward trend of disaster frequency, especially in biological, climatological and transport accident subgroups. Mortality is determined by high-impact events (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castro Delgado, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arcos González, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrero Fernández, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Berrocal Alonso, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo principal: Estimar el impacto en mortalidad de los desastres en España y sus tendencias epidemiológicas entre 1950 y 2012. Metodología: Estudio observacional retrospectivo con análisis de tendencias mediante análisis de regresión y suavizado exponencial. Resultados principales: Se estudiaron 284 desastres ocurridos en España entre 1950 y 2012. 57% fueron desastres tecnológicos, 39% desastres naturales (64% biológicos) y 4% deliberados (atentados terroristas). Aumentaron significativamente (p&lt;0,05) la frecuencia total de desastres, los naturales, los tecnológicos y los subgrupos de desastres biológicos, climatológicos y de transporte. Disminuyó significativamente (p&lt;0,05) la mortalidad total por desastres y la más alta por episodio fue por tecnológicos. Conclusión principal: España tiene un patrón mixto de desastres, con predominio de los tecnológicos. Aumentaron la frecuencia de episodios, específicamente biológicos, climatológicos y de transporte. La mortalidad está condicionada por los eventos de alto impacto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;26(1/2): 113-117, ene.-jun. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167079</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La mortalidad por desastres en España: Un análisis del periodo 1950-2012</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24425^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35148^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28403^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51293</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
