<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86148</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Extrahepatic vessels depending on the hepatic artery. Identification and management</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Patients with malignant liver tumors, whether primary tumors or metastases, that are not candidates for surgical treatment can benefit from different endovascular treatments with proven efficacy in local control of the disease. Correct treatment requires a careful angiographic technique and precise knowledge about the vascular anatomy afferent to the lesion. Occasionally, lesions considered relapse are actually areas that were untreated because the afferent pedicle was not adequately detected. On the other hand, some of the complications of endovascular treatments are related with material passing into non-hepatic vessels. Knowing the hepatic vascular anatomy and correctly identifying all the extrahepatic vessels will make it possible to perform safer, more efficacious treatments. In this article, we present different representative examples of extrahepatic vessels that originate in the hepatic artery(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Martín, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bilbao, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinheiro da Silva, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias Fernández, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los pacientes con tumores hepáticos malignos, tanto primarios como metastásicos no susceptibles de tratamiento quirúrgico, pueden beneficiarse de distintos tipos de tratamientos endovasculares que han demostrado ser eficaces en el control local de la enfermedad. Para realizar un correcto tratamiento, además de una técnica angiográfica cuidadosa, es necesario conocer con precisión la anatomía vascular aferente a la lesión. En ocasiones, las recidivas son realmente áreas no tratadas que se originan por no detectar adecuadamente el pedículo aferente. Por otro lado, algunas de las complicaciones de los tratamientos endovasculares están relacionadas con el paso de material a vasos no hepáticos. El conocimiento de la anatomía vascular hepática y una identificación correcta de todos los vasos extrahepáticos permitirá realizar tratamientos más seguros y eficaces. En este artículo se presentan diferentes ejemplos representativos de vasos extrahepáticos con origen en la arteria hepática(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);53(1): 18-26, ene.-feb. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86148</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vasos extrahepáticos dependientes de la arteria hepática. Identificación y manejo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8281^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8287^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31620^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30194^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1164^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8287^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30194^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8287^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31620^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
