<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85826</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Semen quality and aging: a 9.168 sample study in Cordoba. Argentina</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: Concomitantly with the actual trend towards later fathering, more detailed studies are necessary to establish the relationship between male age and seminal features.The objective of the present paper was to evaluate the relationship of men age with semen quality and with the seminal levels of epididymal and accessory gland markers.METHODS: The study was conducted as a retrospective study of 9168 cases obtained from the Andrology and Reproduction Laboratory in Cordoba, Argentina for 10 years (1995-2004) (men ages 20 to 77). An important number of factors such as abstinence time, toxic habits, work conditions and drugs consumption has been statistically considered. The parameters measured were: seminal volume, sperm concentration, total sperm count, sperm motility, morphology and viability. Seminal levels of alpha-glucosidase, fructose and citric acid were also evaluated.RESULTS: We detected a significant decrease in seminal volume, sperm count, motility, viability and normal morphology, and a reduction in alpha-glucosidase and fructose levels in relation to age.CONCLUSIONS: Since semen quality is a tool for fertility prognosis estimation, the weight of evidence indicates that men may become progressively less fertile as they get older. Couples who decide to delay childbearing should be warned about this matter(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martini, Ana Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, Rubén Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olmedo, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tissera, Andrea</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Senestrari, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina, Rosa Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fiol de Cuneo, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: En coincidencia con la actual tendencia hacia la paternidad tardía, son necesarios más estudios para establecer la relación entre la edad del varón y las características seminales.El objetivo del presente trabajo fue evaluar la relación de la edad con la calidad espermática y con los niveles seminales de marcadores funcionales del epidídimo y de glándulas anexas.MÉTODOS: este estudio retrospectivo fue realizado sobre 9168 casos obtenidos de hombres miembros de parejas con problemas de fertilidad que se presentaron en el Laboratorio de Andrología y Reproducción, en Córdoba, Argentina durante 10 años (1995-2004) (en pacientes entre 20 y 77 años). Se controló estadísticamente un importante número de posibles factores de confusión tales como tiempo de abstinencia sexual, hábitos tóxicos, condiciones laborales y consumo de medicamentos. Los parámetros evaluados fueron: volumen seminal, concentración espermática, número total de espermatozoides, motilidad, morfología y vitalidad espermática. Se cuantificaron además las concentraciones seminales de alfa-glucosidasa, fructosa y ácido cítrico.RESULTADOS: en el presente estudio detectamos un descenso significativo en el volumen seminal, el recuento espermático, la motilidad, la vitalidad y el porcentaje de espermatozoides morfológicamente normales, así como una reducción en los niveles de alfa-glucosidasa y fructosa seminales en relación con la edad.CONCLUSIONES: dado que la calidad seminal constituye un factor de pronóstico para la fertilidad masculina, las evidencias indican que los hombres podrían disminuir su fertilidad a medida que envejecen. Aquellas parejas que decidan postergar su paternidad deben ser advertidas acerca de este hecho(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;63(3): 214-222, abr. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85826</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Envejecimiento y calidad seminal: un análisis en 9.168 casos en Córdoba. Argentina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13126^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7425^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13043^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52117^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d520^s22015</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d520^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32979^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31670</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
