<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88407</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidemiology of Contact Dermatitis in Spain. Results of the Spanish Surveillance System on Contact Allergies for the year 2008</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The epidemiology of contact dermatitis can be analyzed using clinical data from skin allergy units .Objectives: The aims of this study were to define the profile of patients attending a skin allergy unit and to determine the prevalence of the most common sensitizations in this population. Material and methods: Throughout 2008, a retrospective observational study was carried out in the 5 hospitals of the Spanish Surveillance System on Contact Allergies. All patients underwent skin patch tests with the Spanish standard series. The frequencies of sensitization were normalized for age and gender. Results: Data were gathered on 1161 patients. The 5 allergens that gave the most frequent positive reactions were nickel sulfate (25.88%), potassium dichromate (5.31%), cobalt chloride (5.10%), fragrance blends (4.64%), and balsam of Peru (4.44%). The least frequently detected reactions were to quinolone&#150;clioquinol mix and sesquiterpene lactone mix. There was a 35% prevalence of sensitization to nickel among women. Conclusions: The profile of sensitizations in Spain is similar to that of other Southern European countries. Nickel sulfate continues to be the most prevalent allergen, particularly in women. The low prevalence of sensitization to quinolone&#150;clioquinol mix and sesquiterpene lactone mix supports their exclusion of the Spanish series (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Uter, W</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armario-Hita, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Redondo, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silvestre, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Gavín, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Pérez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giménez-Arnau, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Vozmediano, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: el estudio epidemiológico del eczema de contacto puede realizarse mediante el análisis de los datos obtenidos a partir de la experiencia clínica de las unidades de alergia cutánea. Objetivo: determinar el perfil de los pacientes que acuden a una unidad de alergia cutánea y determinar la prevalencia de sensibilizaciones más frecuente en esta población. Material y métodos: estudio observacional retrospectivo de los 5 hospitales pertenecientes a la Red Española de Vigilancia de Alergia de Contacto (REVAC) durante el año 2008. Todos los pacientes fueron estudiados mediante pruebas epicutáneas con la serie estándar española. Las frecuencias de sensibilización se han estandarizado por sexo y edad. Resultados: se recogieron datos de 1.161 pacientes. Los 5 alérgenos que presentaron positividades más frecuentemente fueron sulfato de níquel (25,88%), dicromato potásico (5,31%), cloruro de cobalto (5,10%), mezcla de fragancias (4,64%) y bálsamo del Perú (4,44%). Los alérgenos menos frecuentes fueron la mezcla de quinoleínas/clioquinol y la mezcla de lactonas sesquiterpénicas. En las mujeres la prevalencia de sensibilización al níquel fue del 35%. Conclusiones: el perfil de sensibilizaciones de España es el esperado para un país del Sur de Europa. El sulfato de níquel sigue siendo el alérgeno más prevalente, siendo especialmente importante en mujeres. La mezcla de quinoleínas/clioquinol y la mezcla de lactonas sesquiterpénicas no han mostrado rentabilidad suficiente para su permanencia en la serie española (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;102(2): 98-105, mar. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88407</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Epidemiología del eczema de contacto en España. Resultados de la Red Española de Vigilancia en Alergia de Contacto (REVAC) durante el año 2008</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4553^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22604^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23089^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28402</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3894^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30757^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4862^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
