<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99612</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Short-lived disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Over the years, most of the mental disorders that are dealt with in everyday clinical practice have changed not only their names but also their conceptualisation. Furthermore, as some disorders disappear or are forgotten, others come into being. Seen from a historical perspective and unlike many of the diseases included within classical medicine, it can be stated that one of the basic characteristics of mental disorders is their short-lived presence in the scientific literature. In this study we analyse the causes underlying the transitory nature of mental disorders. The disappearance  of a disorder or the modification of how it is conceptualised may be linked to several different motives. Sometimes they may be due to an evolution of the construct, as a result of new findings. On other occasions the disorder falls into disuse owing to the weakness of the theoretical construct or the clinical research upholding it. Lastly, because the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders and the International Classification of Diseases require updates that incorporate new contributions and correct faults in the current model, they give rise to new denominations and definitions in mental disorders. This article analyses these three situations and offers an illustrative example in each case (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arigas Pallarés, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La mayor parte de los trastornos mentales que se manejan en la práctica clínica han cambiado a lo largo del tiempo no sólo en su denominación, sino también en su conceptualización. Además, mientras unos trastornos desaparecen o caen en el olvido, otros nacen. Considerados desde una perspectiva histórica, se puede afirmar que una de las características básicas de los trastornos mentales es, a diferencia de muchas enfermedades ubicadas en la medicina clásica, el carácter efímero de su presencia en la literatura científica. En este trabajo se analizan las causas que subyacen bajo el carácter transitorio de los trastornos mentales. La desaparición de un trastorno, o su modificación conceptual, pueden estar vinculadas a distintos motivos. Unas veces pueden obedecer a una evolución del constructo, acorde con nuevos hallazgos. Otras veces, el trastorno cae en desuso por la endeblez en el constructo teórico o en la investigación clínica que lo sustenta. Por último, las clasificaciones del Manual diagnóstico y estadístico de los trastornos mentales y la Clasificación  Internacional de Enfermedades, al requerir actualizaciones que incorporen nuevas aportaciones y corrijan los defectos del modelo vigente, generan nuevas denominaciones y definiciones en los trastornos mentales. En este artículo se analizan estas tres situaciones, aportando un ejemplo ilustrativo de cada una de ellas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;54(supl.1): s11-s20, feb. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99612</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos efímeros</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34570^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8037^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28405^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
