<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138323</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of the variability of the movement of elite soccer players during a competitive season of a generalized linear mixed model</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study aims at describing the variability in the traveled distance for professional soccer players through a season. Average traveled distances have been analyzed in different ranks of intensity for players of a same team in the Spanish second division (Liga Adelante) during the 2013-2014 season. The total distance traveled (DT) and meters per minute (m·min-1) were recorded using the computerized system TRACAB® system by ChyronHego at 25 frames per second, dinstinguishing between five kinds of intensity: still-moving (0-1 Km·h-1), marching (21 Km·h-1), trotting (21 Km·h-1), running (&lt;21 Km·h-1) and sprinting (&gt;21 Km·h-1). After an initial descriptive analysis, a linear mixed generalized one was applied to the data. The results showed that traveled distances in ranks of intensity over 7 Km·h- 1 and under 21 Km·h-1 varied more than the others during the season. This variability could be due to situational variables such as: place, rivals&#146; level and final score. The results of this analysis could have a double application. On one hand, the physical performance of the competition doesn&#146;t seem to be the best way to learn about the team&#146;s form, due to the contextual variability of the competition; in any case, the highest ranks of intensity or the global indicators of physical performance (DT and m·min-1) are the most adequate to enhance it. On the other hand, monitoring physical performance can be interesting if considered to improve intervention strategies during the training process with the objective to optimize the players&#146; physical performance applied to particular contexts of the matches (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castellano, Julen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco-Villaseñor, Angel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio pretende describir la variabilidad en la distancia recorrida por futbolistas de élite a lo largo de una temporada. Se han analizado las distancias medias recorridas en diferentes rangos de intensidad por los jugadores de un mismo equipo de la segunda división española (Liga Adelante) durante la temporada 2013-14. La distancia total (DT) y metros por minuto (m·min-1) recorrida por los futbolistas fueron registrados utilizando el sistema computerizado TRACAB® system by ChyronHego a 25 frames por segundo, distinguiéndose cinco tipos de intensidades: paradoandando (0-1 Km·h-1), marcha (21 Km·h-1) trote(21 Km·h-1), carrera (&lt;21 Km·h-1) and sprint (&gt;21 Km·h-1). Después de un primer análisis descriptivo, a los datos se les aplicó un análisis lineal mixto generalizado (Linear Mixed). Los resultados mostraron que las distancias recorridas en los rangos de intensidad por encima de 7 Km·h-1 y por debajo de 21 Km·h-1 variaron más que el resto durante la temporada. Esta variabilidad pudo deberse a variables situacionales como: lugar, nivel de los rivales y marcador final. Los resultados de estos análisis podrían tener una doble aplicación. Por un lado, el rendimiento físico de competición no parece ser la mejor manera de conocer el estado de forma del equipo, debido a la variabilidad contextual propia de la competición; siendo, en todo caso, los rangos de intensidad más elevados o los indicadores globales de rendimiento físico (DT y m·min-1) los más adecuados para valorarlo. Por otro, el seguimiento del rendimiento físico puede ser interesante considerarlo para adecuar estrategias de intervención en el proceso de entrenamiento con el objetivo de optimizar el rendimiento físico de los jugadores aplicado a contextos particulares de los partidos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;15(1): 161-168, ene.-jun. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138323</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la variabilidad del desplazamiento de futbolistas de élite durante una temporada competitiva a partir de un modelo lineal mixto generalizado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50295^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3194</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
