<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61436</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Paraneoplastic opsoclonus myoclonus ataxia syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Opsoclonus myoclonus ataxia syndrome (OMAS)is a very infrequent paraneoplastic or postinfectiousmovement disorder, which may occur at any age, mostcommonly between 6 and 36 months of age.In four days, a previously healthy 30-month-oldgirl progressively developed gait instability, intentiontremor, dysarthric speech, irritability and altered sleep.Physical and neurological examination did not revealadditional deficits. She had had a transient exanthemawithout fever three weeks before. Basic blood analysis,serologies, cultures, urine toxin detection, EEG and cerebralCT were normal. Lumbar puncture showed minimallymphocytosis. On the fifth day following the onsetof symptoms, the ataxia worsened, precluding sitting,and the tremor was aggravated by intentional myoclonus.Chaotic saccadic, large amplitude multidirectionalbut conjugated eye movements appeared. An opsoclonuswas suspected and a chest X-ray and CT revealeda paravertebral thoracic mass. Surgery confirmed alocalized ganglioneuroblastoma. Blood neuron-specificenolase and urine catecholamine levels were normal.Opsoclonus disappeared with high doses of prednisoneand following surgery. Ataxia improved but the patientstill required low daily doses of steroids for one year(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aguilera, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bosque, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Botella, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montiano, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salado, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ocio, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome opsoclono-mioclono-atáxico (SOMA)es un trastorno del movimiento muy infrecuente, de origenautoinmune y de aparición a cualquier edad, másprobable entre los 6-36 meses.Se presenta el caso de una niña de 30 meses, previamentesana, que desarrolló progresivamente en cuatrodías marcha inestable, temblor intencional, habla escandida,irritabilidad y trastorno del sueño. El resto de laexploración física y neurológica era normal. Presentóexantema leve tres semanas antes. Al ingreso, la analíticageneral, cultivos, tóxicos en orina, serologías, electroencefalogramay tomografía cerebral (TC) fueron normales.La punción lumbar mostró linforraquia leve. Al quintodía desde el inicio, la ataxia impedía la sedestación y eltemblor era generalizado agravado probablemente pormioclonias intencionales. Aparecieron entonces movimientosoculares rápidos, sacádicos, multidireccionales,aunque conjugados. Ante el diagnóstico de opsoclono,se solicitó radiografía de tórax observando una masa torácicaparavertebral, corroborada en la TC torácica. Lacirugía confirmó un ganglioneuroblastoma localizado. Laenolasa neuronal específica en sangre y catecolaminasen orina fueron normales. El opsoclono desapareció conprednisona oral a altas dosis y tras cirugía. Un año despuésprecisaba dosis mínima de corticoide por apariciónde leve inestabilidad de la marcha e irritabilidad al suspenderla medicación(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;32(1): 91-95, ene.-abr. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61436</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome opsoclono-mioclono-atáxico paraneoplásico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52097^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22622^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52097^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31453^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31453^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
