<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164221</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-3334</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Emotional recognition is a component of the emotional understanding, which is strongly influenced by the experiences of social interaction. Early adversity is often linked to deficits in interpersonal situations, which could affect the emotional development. This research explores the emotional recognition in three groups of children: international adoptees, institutionalized, and a comparison group. Furthermore, it is analyzed the influences of the type of emotion to identify (positive, negative, and ambiguous), as well as the relationship between emotional recognition and attachment, and the cognitive developmental these groups of children. The results show differences between the three groups, as well as more difficulties in the identification of ambiguous emotions in adoptees and foster children. In addition, relationships between emotional recognition and cognitive development were found in all groups; however, the relationship with attachment was less clear (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Román, Maite</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paniagua, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palacios, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivera, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El reconocimiento de emociones es un componente de la comprensión de emociones que se encuentra fuertemente influenciado por las experiencias de interacción social. La adversidad temprana en menores suele estar ligada a déficits en las interacciones interpersonales, lo que puede afectar al desarrollo emocional. En este trabajo se explora el reconocimiento de emociones en tres grupos de niñas y niños: un grupo de adoptados internacionalmente, otro que vive en acogimiento residencial y un grupo de comparación. Además, se analiza la influencia del tipo de emoción a identificar (positivas, negativas y ambiguas), así como la relación del reconocimiento de emociones con el apego y la inteligencia de dichos menores. Los resultados muestran diferencias entre los tres grupos, así como más dificultades en la identificación de las emociones ambiguas entre los menores adoptados y en en acogimiento residencial. Además, se encontraron relaciones significativas entre el reconocimiento de emociones y el desarrollo cognitivo para todos los grupos, mientras que la relación con el apego fue menos evidente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apuntes psicol;34(2/3): 321-330, 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164221</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reconocimiento de emociones en menores con adversidad familiar temprana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9954</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3102</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23894^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52882^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
