<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105035</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bladder rehabilitation in a patient affected with a brain lesion</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Patients affected by brain damage or by a cerebro vascular accident(CVA) or head trauma, present regularly urinary incontinence, which may affect between 40-60% of patients admitted for stroke and usually 25%have this problem at the time of discharge and 15% are still incontinent after one year. This is a problem that requires a multidisciplinary approach due to the complexity of this type of patient. This article discusses how bladder rehabilitation is performed in these patients from the nursing discipline, whose goal is the acquisition of voluntary voiding (sphincter continence). Action protocols and care plans are based on the taxonomy NANDA-NIC-NOC. Rehabilitation requires the participation of the patient and / or family and success will largely depend on the patient's cognitive status (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Devilleneuve, Emilien Amar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguayo Álvarez, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los pacientes afectados por una lesión cerebral, sea por un accidente cerebro vascular(ACV) o traumatismo craneoencefálico, presentan de forma habitual incontinencia urinaria, que puede afectar a entre un 40-60% de los pacientes que ingresan por ACV y que por lo general, el 25% presenta este problema en el momento del alta y el 15% sigue con incontinencia después de un año. Éste es un problema que requiere de un abordaje multidisciplinar por la complejidad que supone el tipo de paciente. En este artículo se aborda cómo se realiza la rehabilitación vesical en estos pacientes desde la disciplina enfermera y cuyo objetivo es la realización de micción voluntaria (continencia de esfínteres). Los protocolos de actuación y planes de cuidados están basados en la taxonomía NANDA-NIC-NOC. La rehabilitación requiere de la participación del propio paciente y/o familia y en gran medida el éxito dependerá del estado cognitivo del mismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;15(6): 54-57, jul. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105035</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rehabilitación vesical en el paciente afectado de lesión cerebral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6410^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201207</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
