<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054829</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vitamin intake in the adult population of the Andalusian Autonomous Community</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The aim of this study was to know the intake        of vitamin A of the Andalusian population and its        distribution by gender and age.        Study setting: The sample size was 3680 healthy individuals,        from both genders, residents and registered at        census of the Autonomous Community of Andalusia,        with a multi-step, stratified and probabilistic study.        Subjects: Men and women with ages between 25-60        years, both included.        Interventions: By means of a personal interview, health        habits of the individuals interviewed were gathered,        and a dietary questionnaire was undertaken, which consisted,        in the first place, of a 48-hour remembering        analyzing dietary intake of each selected individual determining        not only the type and quantity of foods consumed        but also the way of cooking them and other ingredients,        and distributing them according to the different        daily meals.        Results: Mean Vitamin A intake in Andalusia is        800,63 mg/day. Men have greater intake than women,        although the values for both genders are under the recommended        (RI) ones. Vitamin A intake decreases        with age in men, whereas in women the age group 50-        69 years is the one having the lowest intake. 8,84% of        women and 15,22% of men have intakes lower than 1/3        of de RI, which may be considered a high risk factor.        The percentages of individuals having a likely risk of        inadequate vitamin A ingestion (values lower than 2/3        of RI) are considerably high among the Andalusian population. Conclusions: Mean global intake of vitamin A in Andalusia        is acceptable although about 40% of the population may be at risk of inappropriate ingestion, this condition        being more pronounced for men</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ochoa Herrera, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Alcover, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Frías, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mataix Verdú, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: El objetivo de este estudio es conocer la        ingesta de vitamina A en la población andaluza y su distribución        por sexo y edad.        Ámbito del estudio: El tamaño muestral fue de 3.680        individuos sanos de ambos sexos, residentes y censados        en la Comunidad Autónoma Andaluza, realizándose un        estudio probabilístico, estratificado y polietápico.        Sujetos: Hombres y mujeres con edades comprendidas        entre los 25 y los 60 años ambos inclusive.        Intervenciones: Mediante una entrevista personal, se        recogieron los hábitos de salud de los individuos encuestados        y se realizó una encuesta de alimentación consistente        en primer lugar en un Recordatorio de 48 horas, en        el cual se analizó la ingesta alimentaria de cada individuo        seleccionado y se ha determinado no sólo el tipo de        alimentos y la cantidad consumida, sino también la forma        de preparación y sus ingredientes, distribuyéndolos        en las distintas comidas diarias.        Resultados: La ingesta media de vitamina A en Andalucía        es de 800,63 &amp;#956;g/día. En los hombres la ingesta de vitamina        A es superior a las mujeres, aunque dichos valores        se encuentran por debajo de las IR para ambos        sexos. La ingesta de vitamina A en los hombres disminuye        con la edad, mientras que para las mujeres el grupo        de 50-59 años es el que tiene una ingesta menor. El        8,84% de las mujeres y el 15,22% de los hombres presentan        ingestas inferiores a 1/3 de las IR, lo que podría        considerarse de alto riesgo. El porcentaje de individuos        que presenta un posible riesgo de ingesta inadecuada para        esta vitamina (valores inferiores a los 2/3 de las IR) es        bastante elevado en la población andaluza. Conclusiones: En Andalucía la vitamina A presenta un        consumo medio global aceptable, aunque alrededor de        un 40% de la población puede presentar riesgo de ingesta        inadecuada, siendo en el caso de los hombres esta situación        más acentuada</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;22(1): 108-111, ene.-feb. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054829</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ingesta de vitamina A en la población adulta de la Comunidad Autónoma Andaluza</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15217^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15202^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
