<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111871</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-6581</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of adapting to high intensity training by cyclists using different strategies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Regenerative training is very important for trainers and athletes as it could avoid problems of overreaching or overtraining, as well as improve performance. Thus, the aim of this study was to evaluate the effect of a high intensity training protocol combined with recovery sessions on biochemical and performance parameters in amateur cyclists. A total of 15 male cyclists with a mean age of 36.18±5.30 years were assigned to one of three groups: regenerative-plus (RP): high intensity training (EII) with low intensity training (50% VO2max) and antioxidant supplements; regenerative (R): EII with low intensity training to 50% VO2max; control (C): rest. They performed an EII combined with low intensity recovery sessions for 20 days. Several biochemical parameters (bicarbonate [HCO3], lactate [La], pH and partial pressure of carbon dioxide [PCO2]) and performance parameters (maximum power [Pmax], aerobic capacity [RA] and maximum uptake oxygen [VO2max]) were measured before and after applying the protocol. Significant increases were observed in the maximum power with no differences between the different situations. No significant changes were seen in the endurance or VO2max in either group. As regards metabolic state, a lower lactate concentration (not significant) was observed after application of protocol in group RP. It may be concluded that this protocol with or without antioxidant supplements could be an option to assimilate particular training loads(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vaz Pardal, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordoñez Muñoz, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosety Rodríguez, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arroyo García, Pelayo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El entrenamiento regenerativo está siendo de gran interés tanto para entrenadores como para atletas, ya que puede evitar situaciones de sobrecarga o sobreentrenamiento y mejorar el rendimiento. Así, el objetivo de este estudio preliminar fue evaluar la adaptación de un mismo protocolo de entrenamiento de alta intensidad unido a diferentes estrategias de recuperación sobre variables bioquímicas y de rendimiento en ciclistas amateurs. Quince ciclistas hombres con una edad media de 36,18±5,30 años fueron asignados de forma dirigida a tres diferentes grupos: regenerativo-plus (RP, n=6): entrenamiento interválico intensivo (EII) combinado con sesiones de baja intensidad (50% VO2max) más la suplementación de antioxidantes; regenerativo (R, n=5): EII combinado con sesiones de baja intensidad al 50% VO2max; control (C, n=4): descanso. Realizaron un EII combinado con sesiones de baja intensidad durante 20 días. Antes y después de la aplicación del protocolo se midieron parámetros bioquímicos (bicarbonato [HCO3], lactato [La], pH y presión parcial del dióxido de carbono [PCO2]) y parámetros de rendimiento (potencia máxima [Pmax], resistencia aeróbica [RA] y consumo máximo de oxígeno [VO2max]). Se observó un aumento significativo en la potencia máxima aplicada, sin diferencias en las diversas situaciones estudiadas. En cuanto a la resistencia aeróbica y VO2max, no se observaron mejoras significativas en ninguno de los grupos. Respecto al estado metabólico, solo se observó una menor concentración de lactato (no significativa) tras la aplicación del protocolo en el grupo RP. Los resultados sugieren que este protocolo unido o no a la suplementación de antioxidantes podría ser una estrategia adecuada para asimilar determinadas cargas de entrenamiento(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apunts, Med. esport (Internet);48(177): 17-25, ene.-mar. 2013. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111871</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la adaptación a un entrenamiento de alta intensidad con diferentes estrategias de intervención en ciclistas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d979^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12034^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5180^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15211^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1667^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1667^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1667^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
