<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-8096</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Radiotherapy in glottic T1 carcinoma. Local control and survival</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Between January 1980 and April 1995, 57 treatment-naive patients diagnosed as glottic epidermoid T1 carcinoma were treated in the ear, nose and throat department of Juan Canalejo Hospital of La Coruña, Spain. Seventy-nine percent (79%) (45/57) had T1a lesions and 21% (12/57) had T1b. All patients were treated by the radiotherapy department of the Regional Oncological Center with Co60 at doses ranging from 50 Gy to 70 Gy. Local control was achieved in 74.5% (43/57). Cause-specific survival was 96% at 3, 5, and 10 years. The larynx was preserved in 96.5% (55/57). The local recurrence rate was significantly lower for T1a (16.8%) than for T1b (57.8%) (p &lt; 0.05). No significant differences were found in local control or survival with different dosing regimens (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sanidad y Ediciones (SANED, S.L.)</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Entre Enero de 1980 y Abril de 1995, se trataron mediante radioterapia 57 pacientes diagnosticados de carcinoma epidermoide TI glótico, en el Servicio de Otorrinolaringología del Hospital Juan Canalejo de La Coruña. El 79 por ciento (45/57) correspondían a lesiones T1 y 21 por ciento (12/57) T1b. Todos los pacientes fueron tratados en el Servicio de Radioterapia del Centro Oncológico Regional mediante Co60, con dosis que oscilaron entre los 5.000 y los 7.000 cGy. El control local fue del 74,5 por ciento (43/57). La supervivencia causa-específica fue de 96 por ciento a los 3,5 y 10 años. El índice de preservación de la laringe fue del 96,5 por ciento (55/57). El índice de recidiva local fue significativamente inferior en los T1a (16,8 por ciento) frente a los T1b (57,8 por ciento) (p &lt; 0,5). No se encontraron diferencias significativas ni en el control local ni en la supervivencia en función de la dosis empleada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;51(1): 57-61, ene. 2000. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Radioterapia en el carcinoma T1 glótico. Control local y supervivencia</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Martínez Vidal, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Veiras, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herranz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vazquez Barro, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarandeses García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernandez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-8096</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28604</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9557</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2337</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6075^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28150^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28150^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28150^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200001</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
