<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055195</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Medical and physical condition evaluation before beginning of exercise</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Physical exercise is important for maintaining a good health status.        However, not all the physical activities and sports are appropriate for        people with diabetes. Activities requiring bursts of maximum effort        that result in the activation of the glycolytic system are not recommended        for type 1 diabetic patients because they induce hyperglycemia        and increase blood pressure. On the other hand, prolonged        activity can cause hypoglycemia if no preventive measures, such as        food ingestion, are taken just before and during exercise. The type of        exercise and its duration should also be taken into account. The capillary        blood glucose level should be tested prior to exercise in type 1        diabetic patients because this factor is determinant to ascertain the        effort and load they can withstand. In conclusion, a long session (&gt;1        hour) of aerobic exercise and strength and resistance exercise with        loads less than or equal to 60% and an established maximal repetition        are recommended</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ballester Esteve, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La práctica de ejercicio físico es importante para gozar de una buena        salud. Sin embargo, no todas las actividades físicas y deportes        son adecuados para los pacientes con diabetes. Las actividades con        cargas de fuerza máxima que provocan la activación de la glucólisis,        no se aconsejan en los pacientes con diabetes por inducir hiperglucemia        y aumento de la presión arterial. Por el contrario, las actividades        de larga duración pueden causar hipoglucemias si no se toman        precauciones, como la ingestión de alimentos antes y durante el        ejercicio. También debe tenerse en cuenta el tipo de actividad física        y su duración. Además, es importante valorar el nivel de glucemia        del paciente antes del ejercicio, dado que este factor es determinante        para evaluar el esfuerzo y la carga soportable por aquél. En        conclusión, se aconsejan ejercicios aeróbicos de larga duración        (&gt;1 hora) y ejercicios de fuerza-resistencia con cargas menores o        iguales al 60% sobre una repetición máxima</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;23(1): 28-32, ene.-feb. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055195</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación médico-deportiva antes del inicio del ejercicio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5179^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6161^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37656</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
