<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145766</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Superior vena cava thrombosis in a patient on hemodialysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present a patient with end-stage renal disease on maintenace hemodialysis through a permanent catheter (Permcath®) on the right subclavian vein. One month after the catheter placement the patient exhibited a superior vena cava syndrome due to a pericatheter thrombosis. The patient was initially managed with anticoagulation with early clinical improvement. Nevertheless, the reappearance of the symptoms forced the removal of the catheter and percutaneous angioplasty of the superior vena cava. After those measures and anticoagulation with coumarin the patient remains stable with complete clinical resolution and angiographical improvement (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Burrel, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saval, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cases, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Pedret, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pou, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos el caso de un paciente con insuficiencia renal crónica terminal en programa de hemodiálisis crónica a través de un catéter Permcath® subclavio derecho, que presentó un síndrome de la vena cava superior (VCS) a consecuencia de una trombosis pericatéter que se trató inicialmente de manera conservadora mediante anticoagulación con mejoría inicial. Por reaparición de la clínica debió finalmente procederse a la retirada del Permcath®, angioplastia de la VCS y continuar la anticoagulación con dicumarínicos, con resolución clínica del cuadro y mejoría radiológica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;24(supl.3): 35-38, 2004. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145766</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trombosis de la vena cava superior en un paciente en hemodiálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30956</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23279^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13738</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7851^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19562^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19562^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2446^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19562^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22859^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1752^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
