<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163966</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Results of short term radiotherapy followed by radical surgery for rectal cancer: A long-term unicenter observational study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Short-term radiotherapy (STR) for rectal cancer (RC) has rarely been used in Spain. The aim of the present study is to describe oncological results after RTC and surgery for RC. Methods: This is a retrospective analysis of a consecutive series of patients treated with STR and surgery for RC (1999-2012). Epidemiological data, staging, complications of STR, STR-surgery interval, surgical approach, rate of anastomotic/perineal wound dehiscence, and pathological data (regression degree and staging) were collected. Global survival, disease free survival, local recurrence rate and incidence of toxicity, response and complications of combined treatment are reported. Results: Of 1229 patients treated, 209 patients received STR and surgery. The median follow-up was 6.2 years. Mean age was 68 years and 66% of the patients were men. A total of 88% were cT3-4 and 44% cN+17 (8.1%) patients had resectable synchronous metastases. Acute and chronic toxicity due to STR was &lt;5%. In 75% of the cases the STR-surgery interval was &lt;15 days, and in 9%&gt; 4 weeks. Seven patients (3.3%) presented complete response. Nine (4.3%) patients presented an local recurrence rate. Global survival at 5, 10 and 15 years was 67.8, 49.2 and 37.5%, respectively. Disease free survival at 5, 10 and 15 years was 66.1, 47.1 and 33%, respectively. Conclusions: The results compare favorably with multicentric historical series. STR offers certain advantages that could be increased by increasing the STR-surgery interval and/or interspersed with sequential chemotherapy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Elorza, Garazi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saralegui, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Enríquez-Navascués, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lacasta, Adelaida</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Osorio, Mikel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Placer, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ciria, Juan Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garmendia, Maddi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La radioterapia preoperatoria corta (RTC) para el tratamiento del cáncer de recto (CR) ha sido poco utilizada en España. El objetivo del presente trabajo es describir los resultados oncológicos tras tratamiento con RTC y cirugía por CR. Métodos: Estudio retrospectivo que incluye una serie consecutiva de pacientes tratados por CR (1999-2012). Se recogieron datos epidemiológicos, estadificación, complicaciones de la RTC, intervalo RTC-cirugía, abordaje quirúrgico, tasa de dehiscencia de anastomosis o herida perineal e histológicos (grado de regresión y estadificación). Se analizan la supervivencia global, supervivencia libre de enfermedad, tasa de recurrencia local e incidencia de toxicidad, respuesta y complicaciones del tratamiento combinado con RTC y cirugía. Resultados: De 1.229 pacientes tratados, 209 pacientes recibieron RTC y cirugía. La mediana de seguimiento fue de 6,2 años. La edad media fue de 68 años y el 66% fueron hombres. El 88% eran cT3-4 y el 44% cN+. Un total de 17 pacientes (8,1%) tenían metástasis síncronas resecables. La toxicidad aguda y crónica por RTC fue inferior al 5%. En el 75% de los pacientes el intervalo RTC-cirugía fue inferior a 15 días y en el 9%, superior a 4 semanas. Fueron 7 los pacientes (3,3%) que presentaron respuesta completa. La mediana de supervivencia fue de casi 10 años. Nueve (4,3%) pacientes presentaron una recurrencia local. La supervivencia global a 5, 10 y 15 años fue del 67,8, 49,2 y 37,5%, respectivamente. La supervivencia libre de enfermedad a 5, 10 y 15 años fue del 66,1; 47,1 y 33%, respectivamente. Conclusiones: Los resultados se comparan favorablemente con las series históricas multicéntricas. La RTC ofrece ciertas ventajas que pueden ampliarse incrementando el intervalo RTC-cirugía o si se intercala con quimioterapia secuencial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);95(5): 268-275, 1 mayo, 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163966</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados de la radioterapia de ciclo corto seguida de cirugía radical en el cáncer de recto: estudio unicéntrico y observacional a largo plazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12424^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24373^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9557^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20180^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51716^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13886^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12314^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
