<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109169</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bronchiectasis in a young patient: presentation of a case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bronchiectasis is an abnormal and irreversible dilation of the bronchial wall. It is the result of different diseases, some of which include primary ciliary dyskinesia, a genetic disorder associated with abnormal ciliary structure and function resulting in changes in mucociliary transport. Common clinical signs and symptoms include recurrent upper and lower respiratory tract infections since childhood, and infertility. About 50% of cases are a Kartagener¿s syndrome, associated to situs inversus, chronic sinusitis and bronchiectasis. It is recommended to evaluate the aetiology, clinical manifestations, bronchial colonization and infection, respiratory function and structural damage, in order to determine the prognosis and the best treatment to improve the quality of life of these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ochoa-Linares, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las bronquiectasias son dilataciones anormales e irreversibles de la pared de los bronquios con alteraciones del epitelio ciliar. Son el resultado de distintas enfermedades, entre ellas las discinesias ciliares primarias (DCP), trastornos genéticos asociados con la alteración de la estructura y función ciliar que provocan un déficit en la aclaración mucociliar. Se manifiestan por infecciones recurrentes de las vías aéreas desde la infancia e infertilidad. El 50% de las DCP corresponden al síndrome de Kartagener, caracterizado por sinusitis, situs inversus y bronquiectasias. Se recomienda evaluar la etiología, las manifestaciones clínicas, la colonización y la infección bronquial, la función respiratoria y el daño estructural para determinar el pronóstico y el tratamiento más adecuado y mejorar la calidad de vida de estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);39(1): 48-51, ene.-feb. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109169</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bronquiectasias en paciente joven: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34315^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13238^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3935^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28293^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13233^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13233^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2017^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13238^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2017^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3935^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2017^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28293^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2017^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34315^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
