<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057003</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-5981</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Knee prosthesis infection</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Two-step replacement surgery is recommended for treating        infected knee prostheses. The extraction-free survival of        implants secondary to reinfection following this technique        is 93.5% after 5 years, and 85% after 10 years. In addition,        the initial healing rates are maintained over time. The        risk of infection relapse is unrelated to the type of microorganism,        the type of prosthetic fixation used in the second        step, or the patient demographic characteristics. The        extraction-free survival of implants secondary to any cause        is 90% after 5 years, and 77.3% after 10 years</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Cardero, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Merchán, E. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El recambio en dos tiempos es la recomendación para el        tratamiento de las infecciones protésicas de rodilla. La        supervivencia libre de extracción del implante por re-infección        tras dicha técnica es del 93,5% a los 5 años y del        85% a los 10 años. Además, las cifras de curación iniciales        se mantienen con el paso del tiempo. El riesgo de        recidiva de la infección no está relacionado con el tipo de        germen, ni con el tipo de fijación protésica en el segundo        tiempo, ni con los datos demográficos de los pacientes.        La supervivencia libre de retirada del implante por cualquier        motivo es del 90% a los 5 años y del 77,3% a los        10 años</dc:description>
<dc:source>Patol. apar. locomot. Fund. Mapfre Med;5(supl.1): 47-57, 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057003</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infección protésica de rodilla</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33578^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27990^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29867^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33578^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33759^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3664^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
