<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88670</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Faculty of Pharmacy of the University of Seville: 4 years of pilot plan - EHEA. Teaching activities for a better quality in the education and students repercussion</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Before entering into the Degree of Pharmacy (EHEA), the Faculty of Pharmacy of the University ofSeville has worked in a Pilot Plan for the implementation of the EHEA. This has helped teachers andstudents to the process of adaptation. The analysis of (i) statistical data and (ii) innovation teachingactivities developed in the several subjects have pointed out the positive impact of this Pilot Plan over thequality of the teaching procedures. More dynamic classes, more assistance to the exams and moresuccessful results have been produced. The Pilot Plan have helped to achieve a more quality learning.Moreover, this experience have allowed to develop several generic skills of great interest for our students.The processed data obtained during this 4 years has allowed us to evaluate the impact of Pilot Plan for theimplementation of the ECTS system, as well as to highlight the effectiveness of the process. It have beenidentified improvement points before the full incorporation of our Faculty of Pharmacy into the EHEA(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Delgado Quintana, M. O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Márquez, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Arévalo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega Pérez, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García López, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saborido Ceballos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Debido a la entrada en vigor del nuevo modelo de aprendizaje propio del EEES, la Facultad de Farmaciade la US vio necesaria la adaptación del sistema actual a estos nuevos paradigmas, participando en un PlanPiloto que facilitara tanto a Profesores como a Alumnos y a PAS este proceso de cambio. Después deestudiar los datos estadísticos recopilados por los becarios designados por la Universidad de Sevilla paraapoyo a este proceso, así como del análisis de las distintas actividades recogidas en las guías docentes decada asignatura, se comprobó que la realización de estas actividades beneficiaba positivamente la calidadde la enseñanza. Se hizo patente el aumento del dinamismo en las clases, viéndose mejorada con laparticipación del alumnado. Como resultado se obtuvo un aumento de asistencia a los exámenes y unmayor índice de aprobados. Con ello, se ha comprobado cómo este sistema ayuda a fomentar unaprendizaje de calidad, y lo que es más importante, proporciona al alumno las cualidades necesarias yespecíficas que demanda el mundo laboral, propias de competencias transversales, como son liderazgo,iniciativa, trabajo en grupo, conocimiento de nuevas tecnologías, así como conocimientos generales yespecíficos de nuestra rama. Con los datos procesados, se puede evaluar la mejora en la calidad de laenseñanza, y poner de manifiesto la efectividad de la experiencia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;51(supl.2): 471-478, mayo 2010. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88670</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Facultad de Farmacia de la Universidad de Sevilla: 4 Años de plan piloto para la adaptación al EEES. Actividades docentes realizadas para una mejora en la calidad de enseñanza y su repercusión en el alumnado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14043^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33921^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32065^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27771</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50069</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12961^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12961^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
