<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057668</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vegetarian diets; effect on health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Vegetarian diets are those diets mainly based on the consumption of vegetable product, but that also permit consumption of eggs and milk. The American Dietetic Association made a declaration on these vegetarian diets in which they stated that «a well-planned vegetarian diet is healthy, nutritionally adequate and provides health benefits in the prevention and treatment of certain diseases». Some studies have shown beneficial results in obesity, cancer, Parkinson disease, hypertension, type 2 diabetes mellitus and urinary stones, compared with the omnivorous. The possible theoretical benefits in some diseases has been seen in the medical practice (diabetes mellitus, obesity, cardiovascular risk). However more studies are needed in the case of Parkinson's disease and rheumatoid arthritis</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Luis Román, D. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castaño, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aller, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las dietas vegetarianas son aquellos regímenes alimenticios basados principalmente en el consumo de productos vegetales, pero que admite el uso de productos del animal vivo, como los huevos y la leche. La Asociación Dietética Americana adoptó una declaración sobre las dietas vegetarianas en la que se afirma que «las dietas vegetarianas convenientemente planificadas son saludables, nutricionalmente adecuadas y aportan beneficios de salud en la prevención y tratamiento de algunas enfermedades». Algunos estudios han mostrado los beneficios de las dietas vegetarianas sobre la obesidad, cáncer, Parkinson, hipertensión arterial, diabetes mellitus tipo 2 y los cálculos renales, comparados con los omnívoros. En algunas patologías los posibles beneficios teóricos se han podido constatar en la práctica (diabetes mellitus, obesidad, riesgo cardiovascular), sin embargo, en el caso de la enfermedad de Parkinson y de la artritis reumatoide son necesarios más estudios</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;207(3): 141-143, mar.2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057668</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dietas vegetarianas; repercusión sobre la salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15077</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
