<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160845</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Criteria for training and accreditation in Interventional Neuroradiology-Neurointervention, approved by the Spanish Group of Interventional Neuroradiology (GENI), the Spanish Society of Neuroradiology (SENR), the Spanish Group of Cerebrovascular Diseases (GEECV), the Spanish Society of Neurology (SEN), and the vascular disease specialists in the Spanish Society of Neurosurgery (SENEC). Requirements for accreditation in Interventional Neuroradiology-Neurointervention for institutions and specialists</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. The development of endovascular techniques has put Interventional Neuroradiology (INR) as the first-option treatment in the majority of vascular diseases of the central nervous system. Scientific societies in developed countries have created standard procedures for training and accreditation for a safe practice in these procedures. Discussion. In Spain, we are waiting for the development of the legislation on the accreditation for specialists which will establish the official formative model to achieve an accreditation in INR. Until this moment comes, it is necessary to establish standards that define desirable minimums for the formative period in INR. Radiology specialists as well as neurologists and neurosurgeons will have access to INR accreditation. Specific requirements for the hospitals that wish to offer this technique and training should also be defined. Conclusion. The Spanish Group of Interventional Neuroradiology (GENI), the Spanish Society of Neuroradiology (SENR), the Spanish Group of Cerebrovascular Diseases (GEECV), the Spanish Society of Neurology (SEN) and the Spanish Society of Neurosurgery (SENEC) have approved the content of this document and will create a committee in order to put into practice the accreditation of formative centres and INR specialists (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Alen, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arenillas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rovira, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fortea, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gállego, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arikán-Abello, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Masjuan, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El desarrollo de las técnicas endovasculares ha colocado a la Neurorradiología Intervencionista-Neurointervencionismo (NRI-NI) como una alternativa de primera elección para el tratamiento de gran parte de las enfermedades vasculares del sistema nervioso central. Al no disponer de programas formativos en NRI-NI normalizados, las sociedades científicas de los países desarrollados han creado estándares de formación y acreditación para la práctica segura de estos procedimientos. Desarrollo. En España, estamos a la espera del desarrollo legislativo de las Áreas de Capacitación Específicas que establecerán el modelo formativo oficial para los especialistas que deseen formarse en NRI-NI. Hasta que llegue ese momento, se hace pertinente disponer de unos estándares que definan los mínimos deseables para el periodo formativo en NRI-NI al que puedan acceder especialistas no solo de la Radiología, sino también de la Neurocirugía, y la Neurología, así como los requisitos exigibles a los hospitales que realizan esta actividad y quieran impartir dicha formación. Conclusiones. Para poner en práctica la acreditación de centros formativos y la acreditación de los centros formadores y especialistas formados en NRI-NI, el Grupo Español de Neurorradiología Intervencionista (GENI), la Sociedad Española de Neurorradiología (SENR), el Grupo de Estudio de Enfermedades Cerebrovasculares (GEECV) de la Sociedad Española de Neurología (SEN) y el grupo experto en enfermedades vasculares de la Sociedad Española de Neurocirugía (SENEC), han aprobado el contenido de este documento de consenso y crearán un comité acreditador (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;32(2): 106-112, mar. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160845</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Criterios para la formación y capacitación en Neurorradiología Intervencionista-Neurointervencionismo, acordados por el Grupo Español de Neurorradiología Intervencionista (GENI), la Sociedad Española de Neurorradiología (SENR), el Grupo de Estudio de Enfermedades Cerebrovasculares (GEECV) de la Sociedad Española de Neurología (SEN) y el grupo experto en enfermedades vasculares de la Sociedad Española de Neurocirugía (SENEC). Bases para la obtención de una Acreditación de Centros y Especialistas en Neurorradiología Intervencionista-Neurointervencionismo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24850^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d72^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9682^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d72^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24850^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d72^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24850^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24848^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24850^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9682^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54238^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
