<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115117</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dabigatran versus Acenocumarol for the prevention of stroke in atrial fibrillation. Budget impact analysis in one health department in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: To Estimate, in the context of a Health Department of the Valencia Health Agency, the budgetary impact of the widespread use of dabigatran at doses of 110 and 150 mg in patients with non-valvular atrial fibrillation (AF), regarding the current scenario with acenocoumarol therapy. Methods: Budget impact analysis of three scenarios of oral anticoagulation use in AF: a) current treatment with acenocoumarol, b) widespread replacement of acenocoumarol for Dabigatran 110 mg and, c) idem at doses of 150 mg. The analysis was conducted from the perspective of the Valencia Health Agency with a time horizon of one year (2009). The effectiveness and adverse effects were extrapolated from the RE-LY study, while prevalence and cost data correspond to the Health Department estimates in 2009. Results: We included 5889 patients (2.4% of the population &gt; 18 years) diagnosed with AF, of which 3726 (63.2%) were treated with acenocoumarol. The total costs of each scenario were &#128; 1,119,412 (&#128; 300 patient/year) for acenocoumarol, &#128; 4,985,095 (&#128; 1,337 patient/year) for dabigatran 110 and &#128; 4,981,226 (&#128; 1,336 patient/year) for dabigatran 150, with a budget impact of 1,037 euros/year per patient shifted from acenocumarol to dabigatran-150. Conclusions: The high budgetary impact of moving to a scenario of widespread substitution of warfarin for Dabigatran supports the restriction of this therapeutic strategy to subgroups of patients at high risk or difficult control(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gosalbes Sóler, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peiró, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Cubells, Blanca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Pérez, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonet Pla, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ridao-López, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: La aparición de nuevas opciones terapéuticas con diferentes efectividad y costes requiere la revaluación del papel de los actuales programas de anticoagulación oral (AO) para informar la toma de decisiones. El objetivo del trabajo es estimar el impacto presupuestario de la utilización generalizada de Dabigatrán a dosis de 110mg y 150 mg en pacientes con fibrilación atrial (FA) respecto al escenario actual de tratamiento con acenocumarol. Métodos: Cálculo del impacto presupuestario en 3 escenarios diferentes de anticoagulación oral: a) tratamiento con acenocumarol, b) sustitución generalizada de acenocumarol por Dabigatrán a dosis de 110 mg y c) sustitución generalizada de acenocumarol por Dabigatrán a dosis de de 150 mg. El análisis se realizó desde la perspectiva de la Agencia Valenciana de Salud y con un horizonte temporal de 1 año (2009). La efectividad y los efectos adversos se extrapolaron del estudio RE-LY, mientras que los datos de prevalencia y costes procedieron de las estimaciones en el Departamento Sanitario. Resultados: Se incluyó a 5.889 pacientes (2,4% de la población &gt;18 años) diagnosticados de FA de origen no valvular, de los que 3.726 (63,2%) recibían tratamiento con acenocumarol. Los costes totales de los respectivos escenarios fueron de 1.119.412 &#128; (300 &#128; paciente/año) para acenocumarol, 4.985.095&#128; (1.337&#128; paciente/año) para dabigatrán 110mg y 4.981.226&#128; (1.336&#128; paciente/año) para dabigatrán 150mg, con un impacto económico de 1.037 euros por paciente que cambiara de acenocumarol a dabigatrán 150. Conclusiones: El elevado impacto presupuestario de pasar a un escenario de sustitución generalizada de dicumarínicos a Dabigatrán apoya la restricción de esta estrategia terapéutica a subgrupos de pacientes de alto riesgo o de difícil control(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;87(4): 331-342, jul.-ago. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115117</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dabigatran versus acenocumarol para la prevención del ictus ene la fibrilación atrial. Análisis de impacto presupuestario en un departamento sanitario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d78^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
