<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139742</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-1285</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of dental caries and periodontal disease on women&#146;s Sexuality</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The development of sexuality is essential to achieve an integral health state in the individual. The stomatognathic system is actively involved in the full and harmonious development of the person, so diseases such as dental caries and periodontal disease and subsequent tooth loss affect the physical, psychological and social aspect of the patient. The purpose of this research was to determine whether dental caries, periodontal disease or tooth loss affect the emotional, creative and communicative traits of female sexuality. The sample consisted of 86 women between 18 and 40 who had dental caries, periodontal disease or tooth loss, who underwent oral examination to confirm the diagnosis. A survey of 15 questions developed for this study was applied to the whole group. It was observed that the presence of signs and symptoms such as halitosis, missing teeth and cosmetic alterations influence the sexuality of women, increasing with the progression of the severity of these pathologies. Given the design and the conditions of this study, the results indicate that dental caries and periodontal disease and its consequences, are related to changes in female sexuality, so it would be very important to consider these pathologies to create oral health programs and to focus on the overall health of women (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fuentes Fernández, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soto, PC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oporto, VGH</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanhueza, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cantín, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva,  MA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El desarrollo de la sexualidad es imprescindible para lograr un estado de salud integral en un individuo. El sistema estomatognático participa activamente en el desarrollo pleno y armónico de ésta, por lo que patologías como la caries dental y enfermedad periodontal, y la consecuente pérdida de dientes afectan el aspecto físico, psicológico y social de quien las padece. El propósito de esta investigación fue determinar si la caries dental, la enfermedad periodontal o pérdida de dientes afectan los rasgos afectivo, creativo y comunicacional en la sexualidad femenina.  La muestra se constituyó por 86 mujeres de entre 18 y 40 años, quienes presentaban caries dental, enfermedad periodontal o pérdida de dientes, a quienes se les realizó el examen oral confirmando el diagnóstico. A todo el grupo se aplicó una encuesta de 15 preguntas desarrolladas para este estudio. Se observó que la presencia de signos y síntomas como halitosis, falta de dientes y alteraciones en la estética influyen en la sexualidad de la mujer, afecciones que aumentan al progresar la severidad de estas patologías. Dado el diseño y las condiciones del presente estudio, los resultados indican que la caries dental y enfermedad periodontal, así como sus consecuencias, tienen relación con las alteraciones en la sexualidad femenina, por lo que sería de gran importancia considerar estas patologías al momento de crear programas de salud bucal enfocándose en la salud integral de la mujer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av Odontoestomatol;31(4): 273-281, jul.-ago. 2015. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139742</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de la caries dental y enfermedad periodontal sobre la sexualidad de la mujer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6362^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3745^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10701^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29135^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
