<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74239</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish validation of the Epidemiology of Prolapse and Incontinence Questionnaire-EPIQ</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: One out of three women suffers from pelvic floor disorders. Thus, an instrument to evaluate this pathology in common clinical practice would be very useful. In this study the psychometric characteristics of the Spanish version of the US questionnaire &#147;Epidemiology of Prolapse and Incontinence Questionnaire-EPIQ&#148; have been evaluated, in order to test its equivalence to the original and allow for its use in Spain. Material and Methods: 60 women with pelvic floor pathology and 60 control women filled in the Spanish version of the EPIQ. The questionnaire was validated following the statistical procedure used in the validation of the original form. Results: Factibility: 113 women filled in all questionnaire items and 7 leaved some of them blank. Validity: 7 dimensions were indentified: quality of life (QoL), overactive bladder (OAB), anal incontinence (AI), micturition difficulty/pain (MD/P),functional defecation disorders (FDD), stress urinary incontinence (SUI), and pelvic organ prolapse (POP). The validity of contents was proved comparing the mean scores for each dimension in patients and control (T-student test). Positive and negative predictive values were POP=92,3% and 82,52%; SUI= 54,34% and 84,93%; OAB=60,6% and 84,52% and AI=24,32% and 92,68%. Reliability: Global Cronbach´s-alfa was 0,94 and for the different dimensions: 0,96 (QoL); 0,91(OAB); 0,63 (AI); 0,72 (MD/P); 0,75 (FDD) y 0,61 (SUI).Discussion: The Spanish version of the EPIQ questionnaire presents adequate factibility, validity and reliability to evaluate pelvic floor pathology in clinical practice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rebollo Álvarez, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto Soto, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espuña Pons, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual Amorós, María A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fillol Crespo, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La patología de suelo pélvico afecta a un tercio de la población femenina adulta, por lo que un instrumento para su cribado en práctica clínica habitual sería de gran utilidad. En este estudio se evaluaron las propiedades psicométricas de la versión española del cuestionario estadounidense &#147;Epidemiology of Prolapse and Incontinence Questionnaire-EPIQ&#148; para comprobar su equivalencia al original y poder recomendar su uso en España. Material y métodos: En el estudio se incluyeron 60 mujeres con problemas de suelo pélvico y 60 pacientes control que respondieron a la versión española del EPIQ. Para validar formalmente el cuestionario se replicó el análisis estadístico utilizado en la validación del original. Resultados: Factibilidad: 113 mujeres respondieron a todos los ítems del cuestionario y 7 dejaron algún ítem sin contestar. Validez: las dimensiones identificadas fueron: calidad de vida (CV), vejiga hiperactiva (VH), incontinencia anal (IA), dolor y dificultad de vaciado (DDV), disfunción defecatoria (DD), incontinencia urinaria de esfuerzo (IUE) y prolapso pélvico (POP).Se comprobó la validez de contenido comparando las puntuaciones medias de las siete dimensiones entre el grupo de pacientes y el control (prueba T de Student). Los valores predictivos positivos y negativos del cuestionario fueron: POP=92,3% y 82,52%; IUE= 54,34% y 84,93%; VH=60,6% y 84,52% y IA=24,32% y 92,68%. Fiabilidad: el coeficiente alfa de Cronbach global fue 0,94 y para las distintas dimensiones: 0,96 (CV); 0,91 (VH); 0,63 (IA); 0,72 (DDV); 0,75 (DD) y 0,61(IUE). Discusión: La versión española del cuestionario EPIQ muestra adecuadas factibilidad, validez y fiabilidad para ser utilizado en la práctica clínica como instrumento de cribado de la patología de suelo pélvico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;33(6): 646-653, jun. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74239</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación de la versión en español del cuestionario &#147;Epidemiology of Prolapse and Incontinence Questionnaire-EPIQ&#148;</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11824</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28085</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14950</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31203^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52871</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
