<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051667</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9168</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cytokine induction by the effect of electronegative LDL on monocytes and lymphocytes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objective. Electronegative low-density lipoprotein (LDL(­)) is a minor modified LDL fraction present in plasma with atherogenic and inflammatory properties. In cultured endothelial cells, LDL(­) has been reported to induce production of several mediators of inflammation, as well as apoptosis and/or cytotoxicity. However, the effect of LDL(­) on other cell types, such as white blood cells ­with which its interaction is more feasible during plasma circulation­ has not previously been evaluated. Therefore, the objective of this study was to analyze the cytokines, growth factors and other proinflammatory molecules involved in the atherosclerotic process that are induced by LDL(­) in monocytes and lymphocytes isolated from peripheral blood. Material and methods. Total LDL was isolated by ultracentrifugation and electropositive (LDL(+) or native LDL) and electronegative fractions were separated by anion-exchange chromatography. Monocytes and lymphocytes isolated from normolipemic volunteers were incubated with LDLs for 20 h; lipopolysaccharide was used as positive control. The production of 42 inflammatory mediators related to atherosclerosis was determined in cell supernatants by protein array. Induced proteins were quantified by ELISA assays. The question of whether induction was transcriptional was determined by real time-polymerase chain reaction. Results and conclusion. LDL(­) induced greater release and expression of interleukin (IL)-6, IL-8, IL-10, MCP-1, GROß and GRO* than did LDL(+) in monocytes and lymphocytes. Therefore, in mononuclear cells, LDL(­) is able to induce production of several factors involved in the inflammatory process that act on different stages of the atherosclerotic lesion (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ordóñez-Llanos, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bancells, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benítez, Sónia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Quesada, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo. La lipoproteína de baja densidad (LDL) electronegativa (LDL[­]) es una fracción minoritaria modificada de la LDL presente en circulación plasmática con propiedades aterogénicas e inflamatorias. Se ha descrito que la LDL(­) induce, en cultivos de células endoteliales, la producción de diversos mediadores de la inflamación, así como apoptosis y/o citotoxicidad. Sin embargo, no se ha evaluado previamente su efecto sobre otros tipos celulares, como células en circulación, sobre las que es más posible su interacción durante la circulación plasmática. Por ello, el objetivo fue analizar las citocinas, los factores de crecimiento y otras moléculas proinflamatorias implicadas en el proceso arteriosclerótico que son inducidos por la LDL(­) en monocitos y linfocitos aislados de sangre periférica. Material y métodos. La LDL total fue aislada mediante ultracentrifugación y se separaron las fracciones electropositiva (LDL[+] o LDL nativa) y electronegativa por cromatografía de intercambio aniónico. Se incubaron monocitos y linfocitos aislados de voluntarios normolipémicos con las LDL durante 20 h; se utilizó lipopolisacárido (LPS) como control positivo. Se valoró en los sobrenadantes celulares la producción de 42 mediadores inflamatorios relacionados con la arteriosclerosis mediante un array de proteínas. Se cuantificó por ELISA las proteínas inducidas y mediante PCR a tiempo real se evaluó si su inducción era transcripcional. Resultados y conclusión. La LDL(­) indujo una mayor liberación y expresión, comparada con la LDL(+), de interleucina (IL) 6, IL-8, IL-10, MCP-1, growth-related oncogene (GRO) (GROß y GRO*, tanto en monocitos como en linfocitos. Así pues, la LDL(­) es capaz de inducir en células mononucleares la producción de factores implicados en el proceso inflamatorio que actúan en diferentes estadios de la lesión arteriosclerótica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. arterioscler. (Ed. impr.);19(1): 13-21, ene. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051667</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inducción de citocinas por efecto de la LDL electronegativa en monocitos y linfocitos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23303^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28224</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28903^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23396^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8251^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4869</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2901</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
