<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-SMB-14152</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Paraneoplastic Pemphigus. A Life-Threatening Autoimmune Blistering Disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Paraneoplastic pemphigus (PNP), a subset of pemphigus, is a unique autoimmune blistering condition that can affect multiple organs other than the skin. It is a life-threatening disease associated with an underlying malignancy, most commonly of lymphoproliferative origin. The clinical picture may resemble pemphigus, pemphigoid, erythema multiforme, graft-versus-host disease, or lichen planus. The earliest and most consistent finding is a painful, severe, chronic and often recalcitrant stomatitis. Treatment of PNP is difficult. Immunosuppressive agents are required to decrease blistering, and treating the underlying tumor may control autoantibody production. In this review, we included essential diagnostic aspects of PNP and the most useful treatment options in the dermatologist practice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tirado-Sánchez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonifaz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El pénfigo paraneoplásico (PNP), una variedad de pénfigo, es una enfermedad ampollosa autoinmune que puede afectar a múltiples órganos distintos de la piel. Es una enfermedad grave asociada con una malignidad subyacente, comúnmente de origen linfoproliferativo. Las lesiones clínicas pueden parecerse al pénfigo, penfigoide, eritema multiforme, enfermedad de injerto contra huésped o liquen plano. El hallazgo más temprano y más consistente es una estomatitis dolorosa, grave, crónica y, a menudo, recalcitrante. El tratamiento del PNP es difícil. Se requieren agentes inmunosupresores para disminuir la formación de ampollas y el tratamiento del tumor subyacente puede controlar la producción de autoanticuerpos. En esta revisión se incluyeron los aspectos diagnósticos más esenciales del PNP y las opciones de tratamiento más útiles en la práctica dermatológica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;108(10): 902-910, dic. 2017. graf, tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-SMB-14152</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pénfigo paraneoplásico. Una enfermedad ampollosa autoinmune grave</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
