<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131998</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-0740</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevention of early neonatal infection by group B streptococcus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Group B streptococcus (GBS) is the leading cause of neonatal morbimortality and maternal morbidity during pregnancy and postpartum.GBS colonizes the gastrointestinal and genitourinary apparatus in 10-30% of pregnant women, having a vertical transmission rate of 50%.1-2% of the colonized newborns develop early severe sepsis. A literature review has been performed in order to find the strategies for prevention of neonatal GBS infection. The results show that recommendations for prevention consist on universal prenatal screening for GBS colonization by vaginal and rectal culture at 35-37 weeks, and the administration of intrapartum antibiotic prophylaxis to all pregnant carriers (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Paulí Cabezas, Àngels</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tortosa Moreno, Avelina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Francés Ribera, Lidia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León Ortega, Montserrat César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viñas Llebot, Helena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Güevasa, Villanueva</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El estreptococo del grupo B (EGB) constituye la principal causa de morbimortalidad neonatal y de morbilidad materna durante el embarazo y el posparto. Coloniza el aparato digestivo y el genitourinario en un 10-30% de las gestantes, con una tasa de transmisión vertical del 50%. De entre los recién nacidos colonizados, un 1-2% desarrollará una sepsis grave precoz. Se ha realizado una revisión bibliográfica con el objetivo de conocer las estrategias de prevención de la infección neonatal por EGB. Los resultados ponen de manifiesto que las recomendaciones para su prevención consisten en el cribado universal prenatal de colonización por EGB mediante cultivo vaginorrectal a las 35-37 semanas, y la administración de profilaxis antibiótica intraparto a todas las embarazadas portadoras (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Matronas prof;15(4): 132-136, oct.-dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131998</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevención de la infección neonatal precoz por estreptococo del grupo B</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32282^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13677^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13679^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
