<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90958</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sensitivity of transvaginal ultrasound in the diagnosis of first-trimester hydatiform moles</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To assess the accuracy of first trimester ultrasound to diagnose complete or partial hydatidiform moles. Patients and methods. All cases of sonographically suspected and/or histologically proven complete or partial hydatidiform mole diagnosed in our center from January 1998 to December 2010 were analyzed. The sensitivity and positive predictive value of ultrasound in the detection of molar pregnancies were calculated. Results. The study group included 59 patients. Of these, 49 were suspected of having hydatidiform mole by ultrasound, 39 of which were histologically confirmed (27 partial and 12 complete). In the remaining 10 cases, the histological diagnosis was pregnancy loss. During the same period, histopathology demonstrated molar pregnancy in a further 10 patients (nine partial and one complete) previously diagnosed as pregnancy loss by ultrasound. Therefore, the study included a total of 49 cases with a final diagnosis of hydatidiform mole (36 partial, 13 complete). The sensitivity and positive predictive value of ultrasound in first-trimester hydatidiform mole was 79.6% (39/49) and 79.6% (39/49) respectively. Of the 49 molar pregnancies, 10 (20.4%) were not identified correctly. The detection rate for complete mole (12/13, 92.3%) was slightly better than that for partial mole (27/36, 75%) but this difference was not significant (p=0.18). Conclusion. The accuracy of first-trimester ultrasound in the diagnosis of hydatidiform mole is high. No significant differences were found between the diagnosis of partial and complete hydatidiform mole. In view of the significant number of molar pregnancies not diagnosed by ultrasound, we recommend histopathological evaluation of all cases of pregnancy loss (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palau Capdevila, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canto Rivera, M a José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Girvent Vilarmau, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano Bachs, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ojeda Pérez, Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar la efectividad de la ecografía del primer trimestre en el diagnóstico de mola hidatiforme completa o parcial. Pacientes y métodos. Se evaluaron todos los casos de sospecha ecográfica de mola hidatiforme y/o diagnóstico histológico confirmado de nuestro centro desde enero 1998 hasta diciembre 2010. Se calcula la sensibilidad y el valor predictivo positivo de la ecografía en la detección de la gestación molar. Resultados. El grupo de estudio incluyó 59 pacientes. En 49 se sospechó ecográficamente mola hidatiforme, 39 de los cuales fueron confirmados histológicamente (27 parciales y 12 completas). En los 10 casos restantes el diagnóstico histológico fue de aborto. Durante el mismo período, la histopatología demostró una gestación molar en otras 10 pacientes (9 parciales y 1 completa) previamente diagnosticadas de aborto por ecografía. Por tanto, el estudio incluyó un total de 49 casos de diagnóstico final de mola hidatiforme (36 parciales y 13 completas). La sensibilidad y valor predictivo positivo de la ecografía en el diagnóstico de mola hidatiforme fue de 79.6% (39/49) y 79.6% (39/49) respectivamente, y 10/49 (20.4%) gestaciones molares no fueron correctamente identificadas. Aunque la tasa de detección ecográfica para la mola hidatiforme completa (12/13, 92.3%) fue discretamente superior a la de mola parcial (27/36, 75%), la diferencia no fue significativa (p=0.18). Conclusión. La efectividad de la ecografía del primer trimestre para diagnosticar mola hidatiforme es elevada. No hallamos diferencias significativas entre el diagnóstico de mola hidatiforme parcial y completa. Ante la existencia de un número no despreciable de molas no detectables por ecografía, recomendamos realizar estudio histológico en todos los casos de aborto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);54(10): 501-505, oct. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90958</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sensibilidad de la ecografía transvaginal en el diagnóstico de la mola hidatiforme de primer trimestre</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8986^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31993^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24209^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24209^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
