<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60880</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Preterm premature rupture of membranes and neonatal outcome prior to 28 weeks of gestation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe the characteristics and outcomes after conservative management of pregnancies with preterm premature rupture of membranes (PPROM). Material and methods: We performed a descriptive, observational study of 65 cases of PPROM at less than 28 weeks of pregnancy between 1995 and 2005. Results: The main characteristics were twin pregnancies, positive culture for group B Streptococcus agalactiae (14,85%) and previous PPROM (16%). The median number of days with broken membranes, when the Bishop score was &lt; 7, was 14 for pregnancies with PROM &lt; 24 weeks and 5 for pregnancies with PPROM &amp;#8805; 24 weeks (P=.01). Conservative management does not increase morbidity or mortality, unless there is moderatesevere oligohydramnios: 100% of chorioamnionitis and 69% of perinatal mortality occurred in pregnancies with oligohydramnios. Conclusions: Pregnancies with RPMP &lt; 24 weeks and a Bishop¿s score of &lt; 7 have a longer latency period and maternal-fetal morbidity and mortality are not increased if the amniotic fluid index is normal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Armada Maresca, M. Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Granados, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herráiz Martínez, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Echevarría, Leyre</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo Méndez, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidart Aragón, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir las características y el pronóstico del manejo conservador en gestantes con rotura prematura de membranas pretérmino (RPMP). Material y métodos: Estudio observacional descriptivo de 65 casos de RPMP &lt; 28 semanas, entre 1995 y 2005. Resultados: Características principales: gestación múltiple (29,3%), exudado positivo para Estreptococcus agalactiae (Streptococcus del grupo B) (14,85%) y RPMP anterior (16%). La mediana de días de bolsa rota (BR), cuando el índice de Bishop es &lt; 7 es de 14 para gestantes con RPMP &lt; 24 semanas y de 5 para gestantes con RPMP &amp;#8805; 24 semanas (p = 0,01). El manejo conservador no aumenta la morbimortalidad, salvo que presenten oligoamnios moderado-severo: el 100% de las corioamnionitis y el 69% de la mortalidad perinatal ocurrieron en gestantes con oligoamnios. Conclusiones: Las gestantes con RPMP &lt; 24 semanas e índice de Bishop &lt; 7 presentan mayores períodos de latencia, pero la morbimortalidad maternofetal no aumenta si el índice de líquido amniótico es normal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);52(3): 151-159, mar. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60880</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rotura prematura de membranas antes de la semana 28 de gestación y resultados neonatales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11705</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22968</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21031^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
