<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89885</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Medical Nutritional therapy and therapeutic patient education in diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article includes an introduction to the current approach to dietary treatment of diabetes. Are provided the nutritional reccomendations to primary, secondary and tertiary prevention of diabetes, as recommended by the American Diabetes Association (ADA) adapted to different types of diabetes, treatments and special situations. Secondly, it introduces the concept of Therapeutic Education, especially education and nutritional diet for persons with diabetes and their families, the educational objectives in food according to type of diabetes type 1 or type 2 in different treatment modalities and educational strategies recommended by the Diabetes Education Study Group (wear) of the European Association for the Study of Diabetes (EASD) to facilitate better adherence to dietary treatment(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jansá, Margarida</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mercè Vidal, Mercé</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murillo, Serafin</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo incluye en primer lugar una introducción sobre el enfoque actual del tratamiento dietético de la diabetes. Se aportan las características nutricionales de la alimentación en la prevención primaria, secundaria y terciaria de la diabetes, según las recomendaciones de la American Diabetes Association (ADA) adaptadas a los distintos tipos de diabetes, tratamientos y situaciones especiales. En segundo lugar se introduce el concepto de Educación Terapéutica, y en especial la educación dietético nutricional dirigida a las personas con diabetes y sus familiares, los objetivos educativos en alimentación según sea diabetes tipo 1 o tipo 2 en sus diferentes modalidades de tratamiento, así como las estrategias educativas que recomienda la Diabetes Education Study Group (DESG) de la European Association for Study of Diabetes (EASD) para facilitar una mejor adherencia al taratmiento dietético(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;34(5): 16-23, mayo 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89885</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Terapia médico-nuticional y educación terapéutica en la diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4080^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4080^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3950^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3950^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53393^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53394^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201105</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
