<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155734</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Is there an overprescription of proton pump inhibitors in oncohematologic patients undergoing ambulatory oncospecific treatment?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The aim of this study is to evaluate the prevalence of proton pump inhibitors (PPIs) prescription, and the level of adequacy of the indication of these drugs in oncohematologic patients under ambulatory oncoespecific treatment. Method: An observational descriptive study in oncohematologic patients under ambulatory oncoespecific treatment. A protocol for the rational use of PPI targeted to oncohematologic patients based on the PPI protocol of our hospital was designed. Patients under active treatment with PPIs were quantified and the appropriateness of their indications evaluated. Results: 111 patients (71 oncologic and 40 hematologic) were included. 56% of all oncologic patients and 63% of all hematologic patients were under active treatment with PPIs. After reviewing the indications for PPI in all patients, 72% of oncologic and 12% of hematologic patients did not present evidence justifying treatment with these drugs. Conclusion: It is important the pharmacist to detect unappropriated prescriptions of PPIs, especially among oncologic patients, and to promote a deprescription of these drugs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pujal Herranz,  Meritxell</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo de este estudio es analizar la prevalencia de inhibidores de la bomba de protones (IBP) en el paciente oncohematológico de dispensación ambulatoria y el grado de adecuación de su indicación. Método: Estudio observacional descriptivo en pacientes oncohematológicos en tratamiento oncoespecífico de dispensación ambulatoria. Se elaboró un protocolo dirigido al paciente oncohematológico a partir del protocolo de uso racional de IBP de nuestro hospital. Se cuantificaron los pacientes en tratamiento activo con IBP y se analizó la idoneidad de su indicación. Resultados: Se incluyeron 111 pacientes (71 oncológicos, 40 hematológicos). El 56% de los pacientes oncológicos y el 63% de los hematológicos estaban en tratamiento activo con IBP. Tras revisar las indicaciones de los pacientes con IBP, el 72% de los oncológicos y el 12% de los hematológicos no presentaron una indicación que justificara el tratamiento. Conclusiones: Es importante que el farmacéutico detecte las prescripciones inadecuadas de IBP especialmente entre la población oncológica y sugiera una deprescripción del mismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;40(5): 436-446, sept.-oct. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155734</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Existe una sobreprescripción de inhibidores de la bomba de protones en el paciente oncohematológico en tratamiento oncoespecífico ambulatorio?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52844^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11742^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d555^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54219^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32936^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
