<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78363</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gene polymorphisms and pharmacogenetics in rheumatoid arthritis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Rheumatoid arthritis (RA)is a systemic, chronic and inflammatory disease of unknown a etiology with a genetic predisposition. The advent of new biological agents, as well as the more traditional disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs, has resulted in highly efficient therapies for reducing the symptoms and signs of RA; however, not all patients show the same level of response regarding disease progression to these therapies. These variations suggest that RA patients may have different genetic regulatory mechanisms. The extensive polymorphisms revealedin non-coding gene-regulatory regions in the immune system, as well as genetic variations in drug-metabolizing enzymes, suggest that this type of variation is of functional and evolutionary importance and may provide clues for developing new therapeutic strategies. Pharmacogenetics is a rapidly advancing area of research that holds the promise that therapies will soon be tailored to an individual patient&#146;s genetic profile (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carreira-García, Vanessa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rego-Pérez, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Moreno, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La artritis reumatoide (AR) es una enfermedad inflamatoria, sistémica y crónica de etiología desconocida y con predisposición genética. La llegada de los nuevos agentes biológicos, así como los ya conocidos fármacos antirreumáticos modificadores de la enfermedad, condujeron a una eficacia elevada en los tratamientos de la AR. Sin embargo, no todos los sujetos muestran el mismo grado de progresión de la enfermedad como respuesta a estos tratamientos. Estas variaciones demuestran que los sujetos con AR deben tener diferentes mecanismos de regulación génica. Los polimorfismos detectados en las regiones reguladoras no codificantes del sistema inmune y las variaciones genéticas de las enzimas que metabolizan los fármacos demuestran que este tipo de variaciones tiene una importancia funcional y evolutiva elevada, lo que proporciona nuevas pistas para el desarrollo de nuevas estrategias terapéuticas. La farmacogenética es un campo que avanza rápidamente y promete el desarrollo de tratamientos adaptados al perfil genético del sujeto en un futuro cercano (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);5(6): 268-279, nov.-dic. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78363</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Polimorfismos genéticos y farmacogenética en la artritis reumatoide</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11547</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10788^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29487^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24725^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1178^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38737^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28903^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
