<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129681</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8799</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of maximal oxygen uptake and maximum strength of the upper body of university students in the ability to perform quality cardiopulmonary resuscitation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: It has been hypothesized that fitness and body mass index of the rescuers are predictors of the adequate of external chest compressions. The aims of this study were to: 1) analyze by sex the percentage of maximum heart rate (%EMHR) reached in 5 minutes of cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR); 2) examine the influence of both body mass index and fitness on predicting adequate chest compressions; and 3) estimate the optimal levels of them in 5 minutes of cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR). Methods: Quasi-experimental study involving sixty three subjects were recruited from University of Castilla-La Mancha, Spain. We determined weight, height, cardiorespiratory (maximal oxygen uptake -VO2max) and muscular fitness (handgrip-test). After previous training, participants performed cardiopulmonary resuscitation on a mannequin during 5 minutes. Results: The %EMHR achieved was 64.2 in men and 76.9 in women. The mean percentage of adequate chest compressions was higher on the participants with normal weight/overweight (p&lt;0.001), and on those who had a low level of cardiorespiratory (p=0.004) and muscular fitness (p=0.011). Body mass index, cardiorespiratory and muscular fitness are predictors of correct compression depth and chest compression when controlling for age and sex. The best cut-off points for predicting successful chest compressions were 44.45 ml/kg/min for VO2max, and 30.22 kg for muscular fitness. Conclusions: Anthropometric and physical fitness conditions may influence the external chest compressions performance. Our data suggest that rescuers should improve their fitness in order to increase their capacity to provide cardiopulmonary resuscitation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Vizcaíno, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López  González, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez López, Mairena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rovira Gil, Elias</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer López, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: 1) analizar por sexo el porcentaje medio de la frecuencia cardiaca máxima (PFCM) alcanzado en 5 minutos de reanimación cardiopulmonar (RCP); 2) examinar la asociación del índice de masa corporal (IMC) y la forma física con la proporción de compresiones torácicas externas (CTE) correctas; y 3) establecer los puntos de corte óptimos de consumo máximo de oxígeno (VO2max), y fuerza muscular en brazos (kg) para realizar CTE correctas durante 5 minutos. Métodos: Estudio cuasi-experimental que incluyo 63 estudiantes universitarios. Se determinaron IMC, capacidad cardiorrespiratoria y fuerza muscular manual. Tras formación previa, realizaron Reanimación Cardiopulmonar en maniqui durante 5 minutos. Resultados: El PFCM alcanzado fue 64,2 en hombres y 76,9 en mujeres (p = &lt;0,001). El porcentaje medio de CTE correctas fue mayor en participantes con normo peso/sobrepeso, alto nivel de VO2max y fuerza manual. IMC, VO2max y fuerza manual fueron predictores de adecuada profundidad de compresiones en modelos de regresión lineal múltiple controlando por edad y sexo. En curva característica de operación del receptor (ROC), el área bajo la curva normal para predecir CTE correctas fue 0,862 para VO2max, y 0,872 para la fuerza manual (puntos de corte de 44,5 ml/Kg/min y de 30,22 Kg respectivamente). Conclusiones: Las características antropométricas y la forma física influyen en la realización de CTE correctas en una RCP. Nuestros datos sugieren que una adecuada forma física aumentara la capacidad de los reanimadores para realizar RCP-Básica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. med. deporte;31(162): 238-244, jul.-ago. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129681</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia del consumo máximo de oxígeno y de la fuerza del tren superior en la calidad de la reanimación cardiopulmonar realizada por universitarios jóvenes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30213^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8520</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28453</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
