<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155827</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Meaning, relevance and gender elements associated with care. Metasynthesis qualitative</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of the research was Interpret the meaning, relevance and gender loads assigned to care. It consisted of a meta-synthesis, in which the searching questions guided the collection of information. It was held in the database Library System Documentation and Information of the University of Costa Rica, obtaining a total of 95 relevant and 20 sample items. Through Atlas 6.0 you information is organized in nominal variables categories and codes. They raised a total of 4 variables: dynamic and interactive process, beyond the disease, based on the human essence and feminine tradition. In general, the variables compiled definitions of care in which the dynamics between individuals played a key role, sustained beyond treatment morbidity. It is emphasized that care within interpersonal sensitivity must meet physical and emotional needs. Finally there is a historical tradition of assigning partner care to women workers. We conclude that the true essence of care is their linkage and human interaction and therefore technical or procedural aspects overshadow the social relevance of care and reduce disciplinary autonomy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Elizondo, Noé</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de la investigación fue Interpretar el significado, relevancia y cargas de género que se le asignan al cuidado. Consistió en una metasíntesis, en la que las preguntas de búsqueda guiaron la recolección de la información. Se realizó en la base de datos del Sistema de Bibliotecas Documentación e Información de la Universidad de Costa Rica, obteniendo un total de 95 artículos pertinentes y 20 de muestra. Por medio del Atlas ti 6.0 se organizó la información en códigos nominales, categorías y variables. Surgió un total de 4 variables: proceso dinámico e interactivo, más allá de la enfermedad, partiendo de la esencia humana y tradición femenina. En general, las variables compilaron definiciones de cuidado en las que la dinámica entre individuos cumplía un papel fundamental, sustentada más allá que el tratamiento de la morbidez. Se hace énfasis que dentro del cuidado la sensibilidad interpersonal debe responder a necesidades físicas y emocionales. Por último hay una tradición socio histórica de asignar el cuidado al colectivo femenino. Se concluye que la verdadera esencia del cuidado radica en el vínculo e interacción humana y por ende, los aspectos técnicos o procedimentales opacan la relevancia social del cuidado y reducen la autonomía disciplinar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;25(1/2): 33-37, ene.-jun. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155827</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Significado, relevancia y elementos de género asociados al cuidado. Metasíntesis cualitativa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13321</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29871</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5924</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36312</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9907</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
