<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115578</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of an animal model for the quantitative analysis of articular degeneration</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate joint degeneration on four surgically induced models of Osteoarthritis in the Ovine´s stifle in order to establish a model of early joint degeneration using different magnetic resonance imaging semi quantitative scales. Material and methods: Twenty, 3-year old merino female sheep were randomly assigned to one of four open procedures: Group 1 anterior cruciate ligament transection, Group 2 total medial meniscectomy, Group 3 anterior cruciate ligament transection combined with total medial meniscectomy and Group 4 mid-body transection of the medial meniscus. All sheep were euthanized at 8 weeks post-surgery, when the magnetic resonance imagings were performed. The assessment of joint degeneration was performed using the WORMS, BLOCK and MOAKs scales. Results: Group 3 (anterior cruciate ligament transection combined with total medial meniscectomy) obtained the highest values of joint degeneration followed by Group 4 (mid-body transection of the medial meniscus). Groups 1 (anterior cruciate ligament transaction) and 2 (total medial meniscectomy) showed similar values. Conclusion: Induced anterior cruciate ligament transection combined with total medial meniscectomy in the Ovine´s stifle induced a higher degree of joint degeneration than the rest of models described in the literature (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moya Angeler, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Altónaga, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Forriol, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Valorar la afectación del cartílago de la rodilla de la oveja mediante RMN, con cuatro modelos experimentales diferentes, para establecer un modelo animal de cambios articulares a corto plazo y analizar dichos cambios con las escalas más utilizadas en la literatura. Material y método: Utilizamos veinte ovejas hembra, de raza merino, de 3 años de edad, con un peso entre 35 y 45 kg. Se lesionó alguna estructura articular para provocar la degeneración articular: grupo 1 (n=5) sección completa del ligamento cruzado anterior (LCA); grupo 2 (n=5) resección del menisco interno; grupo 3 (n=5) sección completa del LCA y resección completa del menisco interno, y grupo 4 (n=5) producción de una lesión en asa de cubo en el menisco interno. Las RM fueron analizadas con las escalas WORMS, BLOCK y MOAK. Resultados: El grupo 3 (lesión completa del LCA y resección completa del menisco interno) presentó mayor grado de degeneración articular, seguido por el grupo 4 (lesión en asa de cubo del menisco interno) y los grupos 1 (sección del LCA) y 2 (resección del menisco interno) que presentaron valores similares. Conclusión: La lesión que produce un mayor grado de degeneración articular en la rodilla de la oveja por RMN es la lesión completa del LCA y resección completa del menisco interno (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);24(3): 167-174, jul.-sept. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115578</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración de un modelo experimental para el análisis cuantitativo de la degeneración articular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33759^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33759^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33759^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2402^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2401^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2402^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2401^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2402^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13651^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13651^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
