<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87889</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Transphenoidal endoscopic approaches for pituitary adenomas: a critical review of our experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The surgical approach to the pituitary fossae has evolved from transcranial to sublabial and transseptal microscopic ones, up to the current transsphenoidal endoscopic approach. Objectives: To present our experience in the transnasal transsphenoidal approach for pituitary adenomas and the modifications introduced to improve tumoral resection and to lower iatrogenia. Material and methods: Over nine years, we operated on 37 patients with pituitary adenomas using the transsphenoidal endoscopic approach. We utilised optical lens of 0° (approach) and 30° (adenoma resection), optic navigator, surgical instruments for nasal endoscopic and pituitary surgery. During the neurosurgical step, the endoscope was fixed by an articulated arm. We acceded to the pituitary fossae by a bilateral sphenoidotomy. Results: Sphenoid pneumatisation was sufficient in all the patients. The more common postoperative complications were diabetes insipidus and endocrinology deficiencies. Postoperative rhinoliquorrhea affected only one patient. No alterations of nasal fossae were observed. Mean patient hospitalisation was five days. Conclusions: Transsphenoidal endoscopic approach guided by navigator gives significant advantages: Shorter operating time and fewer complications, greater safety and preservation of the nasal passages. Resecting the sphenoidal rostrum and a fragment of adjacent nasal septum improves surgical instrument management into the pituitary fossae and therefore adenoma resection. Endoscope fixation stabilises the vision and allows the second surgeon to help more effectively (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barcia, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armengot, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barcia, Juan Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Basterra, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El abordaje quirúrgico de la región hipofisaria ha evolucionado desde las vías transcraneales, a las sublabiales y transseptales microscópicas hasta los abordajes endoscópicos actuales. Objetivos: El objetivo de este trabajo es exponer y reflexionar sobre nuestra experiencia en el abordaje transnasal transesfenoidal endoscópico de los tumores hipofisarios, con las modificaciones que hemos introducido para mejorar la exéresis del tumor y disminuir la iatrogenia. Material y métodos: A lo largo de 9 años hemos intervenido a 37 pacientes afectos de adenomas hipofisarios mediante abordaje transesfenoidal endoscópico. Utilizamos lentes de 0 y 30 grados, navegador óptico, instrumental habitual de endoscopia nasal y brazo articulado para fijación de la óptica en el tiempo neuroquirúrgico. Se accede a la celda hipofisaria mediante esfenoidotomía bilateral. Resultados: La neumatización esfenoidal ha sido suficiente en todos los pacientes. Las complicaciones postperatorias más frecuentes han sido la diabetes insípida y los transtornos endocrinológicos. Rinolicuorrea postoperatoria en un paciente. Secuela nasal definitiva ninguna. Tiempo medio de estancia hospitalaria 5 días. Conclusiones: El abordaje endoscópico guiado con el navegador aporta grandes ventajas: rapidez, seguridad, disminución de la iatrogenia, preservación de la vía aérea nasal. La resección de un fragmento de tabique nasal adyacente al rostrum mejora la manejabilidad de los instrumentos hacia los márgenes tumorales. La fijación del endoscopio estabiliza la visión y permite al segundo cirujano ayudar con más eficacia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;62(1): 25-30, ene.-feb. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87889</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abordajes transesfenoidales endoscópicos de los adenomas hipofisarios: una revisión crítica de nuestra experiencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7197^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9495^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7197^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d244^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3941^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11344^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
