<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148260</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Genes and kidney disease. Candidate genes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Molecular biology techniques have provided important advances in the search for causal relationships in complex diseases supporting traditional epidemiologic studies. Genetic epidemiology allows us to detect genetic variants that could be related to the onset and progression of different diseases. In cardiovascular and renal diseases, this approach linking traditional risk factors to new described ones and those allelic variants, which contribute to the development of these manifestations permits a better understanding of individual disease suceptibility. This is usually afforded through case-control studies evaluating allelic variants of candidate genes previously associated with the disease. Even in this candidate gene search, association-based methods are more powerful than linkage studies in complex traits if we assume that some of the typed polymorphisms are causative although with subtle phenotypic effects. Some brief examples may illustrate the progress in the understanding of renal and cardiovascular diseases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Pérez, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Perera, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Esparragón, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La biología molecular ha aportado importantes avances en el conocimiento del origen de enfermedades complejas, deducidas de lo aportado por los estudios epidemiológicos. La epidemiología genética nos permite detectar variantes genéticas relacionadas con la progresión de las enfermedades. En las enfermedades cardiovasculares y renales ésta relación de los factores de riesgo clásicos con los nuevos y las variantes alélicas de aquellos genes candidatos nos va a permitir igualmente identificar la susceptibilidad de cada individuo a una determinada enfermedad. Esto normalmente se realiza a través de estudios casos-controles. Damos más valor a los estudios de asociación que a los estudios de desequilibrio de ligamiento. Se presenta en este trabajo las técnicas más básicas de biología molecular y ejemplos de enfermedades renales monogénicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;22(supl.1): 80-88, feb. 2002. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148260</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Genes y enfermedad renal. Generalidades. Genes candidatos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7849^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9587^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22275^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22152^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29177</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31926^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200200</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
