<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95470</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Type 2 diabetes in Mexican workers exposed to a potential source ofdioxins in the cement industry determined by a job exposure matrix</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To identify association between type 2 diabetes (DM2) with occupational exposure to potential dioxins source in Mexican cement industry workers. Materials and Methods: 56 medical files of cement industry workers with diagnosis of DM2 were included; 56 medical files of workers from the same industry without DM2 were the controls. The daily dose of exposure (DDE) to the potential dioxins source per work years was estimated by a job exposure matrix and categorized as low, moderate, and high. Logistic regression model that correlated high exposure to potential source of dioxins (cement clinker confinement) per work years and presence of DM2 was adjusted by work seniority, patient age at which DM2 diagnosis was established and DM2 familiar background. Results: the OR for the presence of DM2 in workers with moderate and high exposure to potential source of dioxins in the cement industry was 3.25 (1.10&#150;9.57), p= 0.03, adjusted by work seniority, workerage at which DM2 diagnosis was established, and DM2 familiar background.Conclusions: In according with the data explored in the medical files of cement industry workers,there is an association between high exposure to the industrial confinement of the cement clinker as apotential source of dioxins and presence of DM2 in a modest dose-response gradient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Juárez-Pérez, Cuauhtémoc Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Lucio, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Navarro, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Haro-García, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar-Madrid, Guadalupe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Escalante, Vanessa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Propósito: Identificar asociación entre diabetes tipo 2 (DM2) en trabajadores Mexicanos con la exposición ocupacional a una fuente potencial de dioxinas de la industria cementera.Material y métodos: Se incluyeron 56 expedientes clínicos de trabajadores de la industria cementera con diagnóstico de DM2; los controles lo constituyeron 56 expedientes clínicos de trabajadores de la misma industria pero sin DM2. La dosis diaria de exposición (DDE) a la fuente potencial de dioxinas por años trabajados se estimó a través de una matriz de exposición ocupacional y fue categorizada como baja,moderada y alta. El modelo de regresión logística que correlacionó la alta exposición a la fuente potencial de dioxinas (confinamiento de la escoria o clinker de cemento) por años trabajados y presencia de DM2 fue ajustada por antigüedad en el trabajo, la edad del paciente en la que se estableció el diagnóstico de DM2 y antecedente familiar de DM2.Resultados: la razón de momios para la presencia de DM2 en trabajadores con exposición moderada y alta a la fuente potencial de dioxinas en la industria cementera fue de 3.25 (1.10&#150;9.57), p= 0.03, ajustada por antigüedad en el trabajo, edad del trabajador en la que se estableció el diagnóstico de DM2, y el antecedente familiar de DM2.Conclusiones: De acuerdo con los datos explorados en los expedientes clínicos de trabajadores de la industria cementera, existe asociación entre la alta exposición al confinamiento industrial de la escoria oclinker de cemento, como fuente potencial a dioxinas, y la presencia de DM2 con un modesto gradiente de dosis-respuesta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;56(219): 114-123, abr.-jun. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95470</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diabetes tipo 2 en trabajadores Mexicanos expuestos a una fuente potencial de dioxinas en la industria del cemento determinado a través de una matriz de exposición ocupacional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29063^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25305</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4203^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
