<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120590</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence and determinants of the dual burden of malnutrition at the household level in Puna and Quebrada of Humahuaca, Jujuy, Argentina</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The objective of the present study was to identify households in which overweight and underweight coexisted (dual burden of malnutrition) and explore the factors that could be contributing to the dual burden of malnutrition at the household level in this population.Study design: Cross-sectional nutritional survey. Methods: After applying the exclusion criteria, 136households were included. Mothers were classified as normal weight or overweight/obese based on body mass index (BMI) cut-off points and children and adolescents were classified as stunted or not based on height-for-agez-score. Households with an obese mother and a stunted children or adolescent were categorized as dual burdenhouse holds. Results: The prevalence of dual burden household was12%. Compared with other households, dual burden households tended to have more people living in the house, and the educational level of the head of household was lower. Individuals living in dual burden households showed overall lower energy intakes and were more likely to have inadequate intakes of calcium and iron. Conclusions: The nutrition transition in this community might be one of the leading causes of the observed dual burden of malnutrition. The results presented here indicate the need to consider whether programs that focus on only one type of nutritional problem come might actually exacerbate the other (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bassete, MN</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romaguera, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giménez, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Samman, NC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lobo, MO</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente estudio fue identificar los hogares en los que coexisten el sobrepeso y bajo peso(doble carga de malnutrición) y explorar los factores que podrían contribuir a la doble carga de malnutrición en los hogares de esta población. Después de aplicar los criterios de exclusión, se incluyeron 136 hogares. Las madres fueron clasificadas como de peso normal o con sobrepeso/obesidad basado en puntos de corte del índice de masa corporal (IMC), los niños y adolescentes fueron clasificados según z&#150;score de la talla para la edad, si tenían o no retraso en el crecimiento (Stunted). Los hogares con una madre obesa y niños o adolescentes con retraso en el crecimiento fueron clasificados como hogares de doble carga. La prevalencia de hogares con doble carga fue del12 %. En comparación con los otros hogares, en los hogares con doble carga de malnutrición habitan un mayor número de personas en la casa, y el nivel de educación del jefe de familia fue menor. Las personas que viven en hogares de doble carga mostraron ingestas de energía global más bajas y eran más propensos a tener una ingesta insuficiente de calcio y hierro. Una de las principales causas de la doble carga de malnutrición observada en esta comunidad podría ser la transición nutricional. Los resultados presentados aquí indican la necesidad de considerar a los programas que se centran en un solo tipo de problema nutricional y que en realidad podrían exacerbar el otro (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;29(2): 322-330, 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120590</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia y determinantes de la doble carga de malnutrición en hogares en La Puna y Quebrada de Humahuaca, Jujuy, Argentina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1121^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16508</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9227^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50319</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16595</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6280^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50331</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
