<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129507</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Electrophysiological tests in the assessment of visual disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Some electrophysiological tests are helpful in the assessment of visual disorders. The physiological basis, technical aspects and general indications of those available at most neurophysiology services are reviewed. The Full-Field electroretinogram reflects photoreceptor and outer retinal function. The Pattern electroretinogram assesses retinal ganglion cell function and can identify macular dysfunction mimicking optic nerve disease. The electro-oculogram is a test of function of the outer retina and retinal pigment epithelium; it differentiates Best´s disease from all other bestrophinopathies. Visual evoked potentials evaluate the visual pathway and are especially helpful in the evaluation of the optic nerve (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Iragui-Madoz, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los tests electrofisiológicos ayudan al estudio de la función visual. El objetivo de este trabajo es presentar las bases fisiológicas, aspectos técnicos e indicaciones generales de los tests que se practican de forma habitual en nuestro medio. El electorretinograma-flash refleja la función de los fotorreceptores y de capas más externas de la retina. El electrorretinograma-patrón informa de las células ganglionares retinianas y puede identificar alteraciones maculares que simulan neuropatías ópticas. El electrooculograma valora la función del epitelio pigmentario y capas externas de la retina y diferencia la enfermedad de Best de otras bestrofinopatías. Los potenciales evocados visuales informan de las vías ópticas y son, sobre todo, útiles en la valoración del nervio óptico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;32(supl.3): 93-103, sept.-dic. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129507</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tests electrofisiológicos en el estudio de la patología visual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4667^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4667^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4667^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4667^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31066^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4667^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5168^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
