<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142465</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The increase of dairy intake is the main dietary factor associated with reduction of body weight in overweight adults after lifestyle change program</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study evaluated which was the main nutritional change associated with weight reduction of overweight adult participants of a lifestyle change program. It was hypothesized that increases in dairy intake could be an important nutrition intervention in a lifestyle change program. 117 individuals, male (19.5%) and female (80.5%), with a minimum age of 36 years (54.2±10.4). All study participants were enrolled in a lifestyle change program consisting of nutritional counseling and physical activity during 20 weeks. All participants were grouped in three groups according to Body Mass Index (BMI) delta median (-0.87 kg/m2 ) of individuals that showed weight loss: G1 &#150; lost more than 0.87 kg/m2 of BMI (n=38); G2 &#150; lost 0 to 0.87 kg/m2 of BMI (n=36); and G3 &#150; increased BMI (n=43). G1 increased dairy, fruit and vegetables intake and after forward stepwise multiple regression analysis, it was noted that an increase in dairy product intake of 0.40 servings per day had an impact of 9.6% on the loss of one kg/m2 of BMI. In conclusion, an increase in dairy product intake was the main dietary factor associated with reductions in body weight in overweight adults after 20 weeks of lifestyle change program (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carlos Burini, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Portero McLellan, Kátia Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliveira, Erick Prado de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mourão Diegoli, Ana Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corrente, José Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio evaluó cuál era el cambio nutricional principal asociado con la reducción de peso de los participantes adultos con sobrepeso de un programa de cambio de estilo de vida. La hipótesis era que el aumento de la ingesta de lácteos podría ser una importante intervención nutricional en un programa de cambio de estilo de vida. 117 personas, de sexo masculino (19,5%) y mujeres (80,5%), con una edad mínima de 36 años (54,2±10,4). Todos los participantes en el estudio fueron incluidos en un programa de cambio de estilo de vida que consiste en el asesoramiento nutricional y la actividad física durante 20 semanas. Todos los participantes fueron agrupados en tres grupos de acuerdo con el Índice de Masa Corporal (IMC) medio delta (-0,87 kg/m2 ): G1 &#150; perdieron más de 0,87 kg/m2 (n=38); G2 &#150; perdió 0-0,87 kg/m2 (n=36); y G3 &#150; aumentó el IMC (n=43). El G1 aumentó lácteos, frutas y verduras y después de un análisis de regresión múltiple por pasos hacia adelante se observó un aumento en la ingesta de productos lácteos de 0,40 porciones por día que tuvo un impacto del 9,6% en la pérdida de un kg/ m2 de IMC. En conclusión, el aumento en la ingesta de productos lácteos fue el principal factor dietético asociado con reducciones en el peso corporal en adultos con sobrepeso después de 20 semanas de programa de cambio de estilo de vida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(3): 1042-1049, sept. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142465</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El aumento de la ingesta de lácteos es el principal factor dietético asociado con la reducción del peso corporal en adultos con sobrepeso después de un programa de cambio de estilo de vida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4071^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37738^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23862</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
