<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118454</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-1959</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Report: Control of tobacco consumption and environmental exposure to tobacco smoke in the Community of Madrid in 2012. Results of the Global Tobacco Surveillance System</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Regional Ministry of Health of Madrid has a comprehensive system for the surveillance of the tobacco epidemic (Tobacco Epidemic Comprehensive Surveillance System). This system is comprised of several information systems that have been developed by the Department of Epidemiology since 1995. The aim of this system is to provide the information needed to fight an epidemic that causes more than 5,000 deaths in the Community of Madrid every year and more than 53.000 per year in Spain. This report describes the epidemic until 2012, the most recent year available. Between 1995 and 2012 the prevalence of tobacco consumption within the adult population decreased 33.7%. Among adolescents, the prevalence of daily smokers decreased 63.5% from 1996/1997 to 2011/2012. Additionally, the prevalence of involuntary exposure to tobacco smoke dropped dramatically to less than 5% in all public places that have been firmly regulated by the Spanish comprehensive public health smoke-free laws (National Law 28/2005 and National Law 42/2012), among which are bars, pubs, restaurants and other leisure facilities (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díez-Gañán, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Consejería de Sanidad de la Comunidad de Madrid dispone de un Sistema para la Vigilancia Integral del Tabaquismo (VITa) integrado por diversos sistemas de información que se han ido desarrollando en el Servicio de Epidemiología desde 1995. Su objetivo es proporcionar la información necesaria para combatir una epidemia que causa anualmente más de 5.000 muertes en la región de Madrid y más de 53.000 en España. En este informe se describe la situación de la epidemia hasta 2012, último año disponible. Entre 1995 y 2012 la prevalencia de consumo de tabaco en adultos disminuyó globalmente un 33,7%. En la población juvenil, la prevalencia de fumadores diarios disminuyó globalmente un 63,5% entre 1996/1997 y 2011/2012. Por otro lado, la prevalencia de exposición pasiva al humo de tabaco en espacios públicos descendió drásticamente hasta niveles inferiores al 5% en todos los espacios que han sido regulados de manera taxativa por las normativas sanitarias de prevención y control del tabaquismo (en concreto, las leyes de medidas sanitarias frente al tabaquismo en España 28/2005 y 42/2012), entre ellos, los bares, pubs, restaurantes y otros lugares de ocio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prev. tab;15(4): 162-169, oct.-dic. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118454</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Informe: Vigilancia del consumo de tabaco y de la exposición ambiental al humo de tabaco en la Comunidad de Madrid en 2012. Resultados del sistema de Vigilancia Integral del Tabaquismo (VITa)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51528</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51529</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
