<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120608</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usual dietary glycemic load is associated with cardiometabolic risk factors in physically active Brazilian middle-aged men</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The effects of dietary glycemic load (GL) on cardiometabolic risk factors in physically active subjects are not completely known. Objective: This cross-sectional study assessed the association of habitual dietary GL with cardiometabolic risk factors in physically active Brazilian middle-aged men. Methods: One-hundred seventy-six subjects (Age: 50.6 ± 5.0 years, BMI: 25.5 ± 3.6 kg/m2) were evaluated. Anthropometry, lifestyle features, insulin resistance, oxidative stress biomarkers (8-iso-prostaglandin F2&amp;#945;; 8-iso-PGF2&amp;#945; and 8-hydroxydeoxyguanosine; 8-OHdG) and lipid profile were assessed. Dietary intake was estimated through a quantitative food frequency questionnaire. Results: The dietary GL was positively associated with free fatty acid concentrations (&amp;#946; = 0.311, r2 = 0.13, P-value = 0.034) and triglycerides/HDL cholesterol ratio (&amp;#946; = 0.598, r2 = 0.19, P-value = 0.028) regardless of confounding factors (central obesity, red meat consumption, age and energy intake). The oxidative stress biomarker, 8-OHdG, wasassociated with habitual dietary GL (&amp;#946; = 0.432, r2 = 0.11, P-value = 0.004), regardless of previous confounding factors plus excessive alcohol consumption, iron intake and current smoking status. Conclusions: The dietary GL was positively associated with lipid profile (free fatty acid concentrations and triglycerides/HDL cholesterol ratio) and oxidative stress biomarker (8-OHdG). These results indicate potential harmfulness of diet with higher GL to cardiometabolic risk factors in middle-aged men, even in physically active individuals (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cocate, Paula G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Buthers, Jéssica M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliveira, Alessandro de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Longo, Giana Z</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peluzio, Maria do Carmo G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alfenas, Rita de Cássia G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hermsdorff, Helen Hermana M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliveira, Leandro L de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Natali, Antônio J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, Eliziária C dos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los efectos de la carga glucémica (CG) de la dieta sobre los factores de riesgo cardiometabólico en sujetos físicamente activos no están establecidos por completo. Objetivo: Este estudio transversal evaluó la asociación entre la CG de la dieta habitual y los factores de riesgo cardiometabólico en hombres brasileños de mediana edad físicamente activos. Métodos: Ciento setenta y seis sujetos (índice de masa corporal: 25,5 ± 3,6 kg/m2; edad: 50,6 ± 5,0 años) fueron evaluados. Antropometría, características del estilo de vida, la resistencia a la insulina, biomarcadores del estrés oxidativo (8-iso-prostaglandina F2&amp;#945;, 8-iso-PGF2&amp;#945; y 8 hidroxideoxiguanosina, 8-OHdG) y el perfil lipídico fueron evaluados. La ingesta dietética se estimó por medio de un cuestionario cuantitativo de frecuencia de consumo. Resultados: La CG de la dieta se asoció positivamente con las concentraciones de ácidos grasos libres (&amp;#946; = 0,311, r2 = 0,13, P = 0,034) y la razón triglicéridos/colesterol HDL (&amp;#946; = 0,598, r2 = 0,19, P = 0,028), independientemente de los factores de confusión (obesidad central, consumo de carne roja, edad e ingesta calórica). El biomarcador del estrés oxidativo, 8-OHdG, también se asoció con CG de la dieta habitual (&amp;#946; = 0,432, r2 = 0,11, P = 0,004), independientemente de los factores de confusión anteriores más el consumo excesivo de alcohol, la ingesta de hierro y tabaquismo actual. Conclusiones: La CG de la dieta se asoció positivamente con el perfil lipídico (concentraciones de ácidos grasos libres y razón triglicéridos/HDL colesterol) y el biomarcador de estrés oxidativo 8-OHdG. Estos resultados indican el potencial de nocividad de una dieta con mayor CG respecto a los factores de riesgo cardiometabólico en hombres de mediana edad, incluso en aquellos físicamente activos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;29(2): 444-451, 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120608</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La carga glucémica dietética habitual se asocia con factores de riesgo cardiometabólico en hombres brasileños de mediana edad físicamente activos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8249^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23100^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14679^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32101</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
