<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78439</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Update of the Clinical Guidelines of the European Association of Urology on muscle-invasive and metastatic bladder carcinoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Context: New data regarding diagnosis and treatment of muscle-invasive and metastatic bladder cancer (MiM-BC) has emerged and led to an update of the European Association of Urology (EAU) guidelines for MiM-BC. Objective: To review the new EAU guidelines for MiM-BC. Evidence acquisition: A comprehensive workup of the literature obtained from Medline, the Cochrane central register of systematic reviews, and reference lists in publications and review articles was developed and screened by a group of urologists, oncologists, and radiologist appointed by the EAU Guideline Committee. Previous recommendations based on the older literature on this subject were taken into account. Levels of evidence and grade of guideline recommendations were added, modified from the Oxford Centre for Evidence-based Medicine Levels of Evidence. Evidence synthesis: The diagnosis of muscle-invasive bladder cancer (BCa) is made by transurethral resection (TUR) and following histopathologic evaluation. Patients with confirmed muscle-invasive BCa should be staged by computed tomography (CT) scans of the chest, abdomen, and pelvis, if available. Adjuvant chemotherapy is currently only advised within clinical trials. Radical cystectomy (RC) is the treatment of choice for both sexes, and lymph node dissection should be an integral part of cystectomy. An orthotopic bladder substitute should be offered to both male and female patients lacking any contraindications, such as no tumour at the level of urethral dissection. Multimodality bladder-preserving treatment in localised disease is currently regarded only as an alternative in selected, well-informed, and compliant patients for whom cystectomy is not considered for clinical or personal reasons. An appropriate schedule for disease monitoring should be based on: a) natural timing of recurrence; b) probability of disease recurrence; c) functional deterioration at particular sites; and d) consideration of treatment of a recurrence. In metastatic disease, the first-line treatment for patients fit enough to sustain cisplatin is cisplatin-containing combination chemotherapy. Presently, there is no standard second-line chemotherapy. Conclusions: These EAUguidelines are a short, comprehensive overview of the updated guidelines of (MiM-BC) as recently published in the EAU guidelines and also available in the National Guideline Clearinghouse(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jakse, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kuczyk, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sherif, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cowan, N. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santis, M. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merseburger, A. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribal, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Witjes, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Stenzl, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Contexto: la aparición de nuevos datos relacionados con el diagnóstico y tratamiento de cáncer vesical músculo-invasivo y metastásico (CaV-MiM) ha obligado a una actualización de las Guías sobre el CaV-MiM de la Asociación Europea de Urología (EAU). Objetivo: revisión de las nuevas guías de la EAU para el CAV-MiM. Evidencia adquirida: un grupo de urólogos, oncólogos y radiólogos designados por el Comité de Guías Clínicas de la EAU ha realizado un exhaustivo trabajo de revisión de la literatura procedente de Medline, el registro central Cochrane de revisiones sistemáticas y las citas bibliográficas de publicaciones y artículos de revisión. Se han tenido en cuenta las recomendaciones basadas en la literatura previa disponible sobre este aspecto. Además, han sido añadidos niveles de evidencia y grados de recomendación, según las modificaciones del Oxford Centre for Evidence-based Medicine. Evidencia sintetizada: el diagnóstico de cáncer vesical músculo-invasivo (CaVMI) se realiza mediante la resección transuretral y el consiguiente estudio histopatológico. Una vez confirmada la existencia de CaVMI es preciso realizar el estadiaje mediante tomografía computarizada toraco-abdómino-pélvica, si se dispone de ella. Actualmente, la quimioterapia adyuvante solamente se recomienda en el contexto de ensayos clínicos. La cistectomía radical es el tratamiento de elección en ambos sexos, y la linfadenectomía debe constituir una parte integral de la misma. Tanto a hombres como a mujeres se les debe ofrecer la sustitución vesical ortotópica siempre que no existan contraindicaciones, tales como la existencia de tumor en el margen uretral. En la actualidad, los tratamientos multimodales para la conservación vesical en casos de enfermedad localizada constituyen un alternativa terapéutica solamente en pacientes seleccionados, adecuadamente informados, y en aquellos en los que se desestima la cistectomía por motivos clínicos o personales. Los protocolos de seguimiento deben diseñarse sobre la base de: a) historia natural de la recurrencia; b) probabilidades de recurrencia; c) deterioro funcional en localizaciones específicas; y d) consideraciones sobre el tratamiento de la recurrencia. En la enfermedad metastásica el tratamiento de primera línea para los pacientes con un estado general adecuado para tolerar el cisplatino es la quimioterapia combinada basada en este fármaco. Actualmente no existe una quimioterapia estandarizada de segunda línea. Conclusiones: estas guías de la EAU constituyen un resumen de la exhaustiva visión de conjunto de las guías recientemente actualizadas del CaV-MiM, publicadas en las guías clínicas de la EAU, también disponibles en la National Guideline Clearinghouse(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;34(1): 51-62, ene. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78439</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actualización de las Guías Clínicas de la Asociación Europea de Urología sobre el carcinoma vesical músculo-invasivo y metastásico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24595^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29636</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33861^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14947^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24595^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14947^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201001</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
