<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134374</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">School failure and pediatric epilepsy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. School failure, learning and behavioral problems are more common in children with epilepsy than the general population. The aim of this study is to examine the different factors which can affect the school performance of children with epilepsy. Development. Various psychosocial, medication-related, and epilepsy-related factors may be associated with learning disorders in epilepsy. The age of onset of epilepsy, the type of syndrome, its aetiology, and the response to treatment aresome of the most important epilepsy-related factors. All of the established antiepileptic drugs can produce cognitive side effects, which are increased with polypharmacy and with increasing dosage and anticonvulsant blood levels. Conclusions. Judicious management of all related factors is essential for an optimal outcome. Recent onset of educational  problems in a child with epilepsy deserves immediate and exhaustive evaluation and management (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Peñas, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El fracaso escolar, los trastornos de aprendizaje y las alteraciones de conducta son más frecuentes en el niño epiléptico que en la población general. El objetivo de este trabajo es estudiar los diversos factores que pueden afectar al rendimiento escolar del niño con epilepsia. Desarrollo. Los aspectos que condicionan el fracaso escolar y las alteraciones de aprendizaje en el niño epiléptico son muy heterogéneos, e incluyen factores propios de la epilepsia, factores de índole psicosocial y factores derivados del tratamiento  antiepiléptico. La edad de comienzo de la epilepsia, el tipo de síndrome epiléptico, la etiología de la epilepsia y la respuesta al tratamiento antiepiléptico son algunos de los factores más importantes. Todos los fármacos antiepilépticos disponibles pueden producir efectos adversos cognitivos, que son más frecuentes en politerapia, con dosis totales altas y niveles séricos elevados. Conclusiones. Una buena valoración de cada uno de los posibles factores implicados es fundamental para garantizar un mejor pronóstico. El desarrollo de alteraciones en el rendimiento escolar en un niño con epilepsia debe conducir a una inmediata y exhaustiva evaluación diagnóstica y terapéutica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;60(supl.1): s63-s68, mar. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134374</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fracaso escolar y epilepsia infantil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1953^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1953^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1953^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14876</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1953^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
