<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142955</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fiber in the treatment of obesity and its co-morbidities</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A considerable part of the health-care significance of obesity lies in its co-morbidity. Obesity is associated with high blood pressure, type 2 diabetes mellitus and dyslipidaemia, representing both individually and when taken together risk factors for cardiovascular disease, the main cause of death in industrialized countries. The influence of fibre consumption on body weight, the risk of type 2 diabetes and cardiovascular disease has been shown in important epidemiological surveys, but the mechanisms whereby fibre exercises this protective effect have not been definitively clarified. For the most part, the ability of fibre to slow down the process of absorption of nutrients by modifying the metabolic response to intake, its ability to increase the excretion of biliary acid and the metabolic effects of the short-chain fatty acids produced in the bacterial fermentation of fibre have all focussed the attention of the working hypotheses analyzed in the studies published in the last few years. This review is intended to identify the importance of fibre for the prevention and treatment of obesity and its comorbidities on the basis of the available evidence at present (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Trallero Casañas, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Una parte importante de la trascendencia sanitaria de la obesidad radica en su comorbilidad. La hipertensión, la diabetes tipo II y la dislipemia se asocian a la obesidad, representando individualmente y en conjunto factores de riesgo para la enfermedad cardiovascular, principal causa de muerte de los países industrializados. La influencia del consumo de fibra sobre el peso corporal, el riesgo de diabetes tipo II, y de enfermedad cardiovascular ha sido mostrada en importantes estudios epidemiológicos, pero los mecanismos a través de los cuales la fibra ejerce este efecto protector no están definitivamente aclarados. La capacidad de la fibra para ralentizar los procesos de absorción de nutrientes modificando la respuesta metabólica a la ingesta, la capacidad para aumentar la excreción de ácidos biliares y los efectos metabólicos de los ácidos grasos de cadena corta producidos en la fermentación bacteriana de la fibra, centran mayoritariamente las hipótesis de trabajo de los estudios publicados en los últimos años. Esta revisión pretende situar la importancia de la fibra en la prevención y el tratamiento de la obesidad y sus comorbilidades sobre la base de las evidencias disponibles hasta el momento actual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;17(supl.1): 17-22, 2002.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142955</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La fibra en el tratamiento de la obesidad y sus comorbilidades</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1860^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23102^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23102^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23102^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25401^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23102^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200200</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
