<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119767</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-6221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Late diagnosis of congenital syphilis. Tirad hutchinson that go unn oticed</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The Hutchinson´s Triad, typical of the congenital syphilis, consists of the appearance of the same patient of interstitial keratitis, deafness and dental alterations. The above mentioned manifestations, appear when the contagion takes place in the channel of the childbirth, from an infected or inadequately treated pregnant woman. Clinical case. 59-year-old patient male who comes for decrease of visual acuity in both eyes for years, hiperemia and irritation. The best  corrected visual acuity (BCVA) right eye (OD) is 0,1 and of 0,6 in left eye (OI).In the OD, is observed a paracentral lesion by slimming stromal sublesional without infectious active aspect, estimating vessels withoutperfusion confluent to the leucoma. Areas of atrophy of retina appear in the right eye. There is realized a physical general exploration,  which does not reveal any information of interest except the use of headphone in the auditory right pavilion for deafness of unknown reason and certain dental alterations as the malformation of the incisor teeth. A possible Hutchinson´s Triad is suspected so we request analytical confirmation for syphilis obtaining positive values in treponemic test. The patient suffers a congenital not treated syphilis, for what it stems to the Service of infectiously to get treatment with high doses of intravenous Penicillin G (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lavid, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torregrosa, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domingo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vinuesa, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La Triada de Hutchinson, típica de la sífilis congénita, consiste en la aparición en un mismo paciente de queratitis intersticial, sordera y alteraciones dentarias. Dichas manifestaciones, aparecen cuando el contagio se produce en el canal del parto, a partir de una embarazada infectada o inadecuadamente tratada. Caso clínico. Paciente varón de 59 años que acude por disminución de agudeza visual en ambos ojos desde hace años, hiperemia y picor. La mejor agudeza visual corregida (MAVC) del ojo derecho (OD) es 0,1 y de 0,6 en ojo izquierdo (OI). En el OD, se observa lesión leucomatosa paracentral con adelgazamiento estromal sublesional sin aspecto infeccioso activo, apreciando vasos sanguíneos no perfundidos confluentes al leucoma. En retina OD, aparecen áreas de atrofia coriorretiniana peripapilares y periféricas. Se realiza una exploración fisica general, que no revela ningún dato de interés salvo el uso de audífono en el pabellón auditivo derecho por sordera de causa desconocida y ciertas alteraciones dentarias como la malformación de los incisivos. Ante una supuesta Triada de Hutchinson no diagnosticada, solicitamos confirmación serológica para Lues, obteniendo valores positivos en las pruebas treponémicas y no treponémicas. El paciente sufre una sífilis congénita no tratada, por lo que se deriva al Servicio de infeccioso para recibir tratamiento con altas dosis de Penicilina G por vía intravenosa. Conclusiones. Para el diagnóstico de sífilis, es necesario un alto nivel  de sospecha. Se trata de una enfermedad infecciosa prevalente e incidente que puede simular otras alteraciones oculares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. oftalmol;4(1): 26-28, ene.-mar. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119767</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico tardío de sífilis congenita. Triada de Hutchinson que pasó desapercibida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13972^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7803^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10592^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14604^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53672</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
