<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149196</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Complexity of social and healthcare coordination in addictions and the role of the nurse</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present article discusses the psychosocial impact of basic and advanced concepts, such as social support and prevention, as well as to establish a link between theoretical models related to the social sphere on one side, and the health aspects on the other. This work is based on the context of the influence on health shared by community psychology and social psychology. Starting from the historical background of current approaches, a review is presented of those first actions focused on the care plan and they are framed in a reaction model to the drug problem, which progressed to the current healthcare network model, through the creation of Spanish National Action Plan on Drugs. The complexity of the problem is then broken down into the following key elements: Multifactorial Model of Drugs and Addictions, importance of prevention, and social support. Subsequently, a description is presented on the different levels of the healthcare network, with their different resources. This is also illustrated using a coordination protocol. Finally, it features the nursing approach to drugs, with its contributions, particularly as regards the coordination of resources, and aspects that must be developed for improvement in this area (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montero Bancalero, Francisco José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Riera, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Salgado, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina Fernández, Antonio Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente artículo entronca con conceptos psicosociales básicos y avanzados, tales como apoyo social y prevención, al tiempo que se establece una conexión entre modelos teóricos relativos al ámbito social por un lado, y al de la salud, por otro. Este trabajo se contextualiza en la influencia compartida por la psicología comunitaria y la psicología social de la salud. Partiendo de los antecedentes históricos de los planteamientos actuales, se efectúa un recorrido desde aquellas primeras acciones enfocadas hacia el plano asistencial y enmarcadas en un modelo de reacción ante el problema del consumo de drogas, que evolucionan hasta configurarse en el modelo de red atencional de nuestros días, pasando por la creación del Plan Nacional Sobre Drogas. A continuación se desglosan elementos clave sobre la complejidad del problema: Modelo Multifactorial de Drogodependencias y Adicciones, importancia de la prevención y el apoyo social. Posteriormente, se describe el entramado atencional en sus diferentes niveles y con sus distintos recursos, además de ilustrar con un protocolo de coordinación. Finalmente, se desarrolla el papel de los profesionales de enfermería ante las drogas, con su especial contribución a la coordinación de casos y recursos y las áreas de mejora en este ámbito (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);26(1): 68-75, ene.-feb. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149196</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La complejidad de la coordinación social y sanitaria en las adicciones y el papel de la enfermera</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29655</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3222</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30236^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
