<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-27593</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Numerical and calculation processing: evidence for a case from cognitive neuropsychology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. This paper, which deals with cognitive Neuropsychology, attempts to contribute to the understanding of normal cognitive processing by examining and analysing the deficits acquired by individuals who have suffered brain damage. Aims. Our aim was to analyse the different cognitive processes involved in numerical processing (NP) and in calculation, together with the relations between them. Patients and methods. A quadriplegic patient with sequelae that include motor aphasia and deep dysgraphia as the residual pathologies of a traumatic brain injury, with a history of over four years; language comprehension is preserved (both oral and written) and there is no verbal expression whatsoever. Expression is achieved functionally by means of a specially adapted laser pointer. Assessment of NP and calculation was performed. Results. Alterations were observed in the calculation system, one in the recognition of arithmetical signs and the other in the execution of arithmetical operations. Conclusions. 1. Calculation skills are independent of those required to perform numerical recoding and of lexical or encyclopaedic numerical knowledge. 2. Recognition of arithmetical signs is independent of, and therefore dissociated from, data retrieval and the execution of calculation procedures. 3. Data retrieval processes and those required for the execution of calculations are independent. Therefore, the calculation system consists of different elements that are independent from one another (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Este artículo se enmarca dentro de la Neuropsicología cognitiva y, por tanto, pretende contribuir a la comprensión del procesamiento cognitivo normal, a partir del estudio y análisis de los déficit adquiridos por sujetos que han sufrido un daño cerebral. Objetivo. Analizar los distintos procesos cognitivos implicados en el procesamiento numérico (PN) y en el cálculo, así como las relaciones entre ellos. Pacientes y métodos. Paciente tetrapléjica con secuelas de afasia motora y disgrafía profunda como patología residual aun traumatismo craneoencefálico, de más de cuatro años de evolución; la comprensión del lenguaje se conserva (oral y escrita), pero la expresión verbal es nula. Su expresión es funcional, mediante un puntero láser adaptado. Se realiza una evaluación del PN y el cálculo. Resultados. Se observan alteraciones en el sistema de cálculo, una en el reconocimiento de los signos aritméticos y otra en los procedimientos de ejecución de las operaciones aritméticas. Conclusiones. 1. Las habilidades del cálculo son independientes de las de recodificación numérica, así como del conocimiento numérico léxico o enciclopédico. 2. El reconocimiento de los signos aritméticos es independiente y, por tanto, se disocia de la recuperación de datos y de la ejecución de los procedimientos de cálculo. 3. Los procesos de recuperación de datos y los de ejecución de los procedimientos de cálculo son independientes. Por tanto, el sistema de cálculo se compone de distintos elementos independientes entre sí (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;36(9): 817-820, mayo 2003. tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Procesamiento numérico y cálculo: evidencia de un caso desde la Neuropsicología cognitiva</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Alameda Bailén, JR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorca Marín, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salguero Alcañiz, MP</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-27593</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d1956</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13733</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8601</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200305</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
