<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052372</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cost-effectiveness analysis comparing methotrexate with PUVA therapy for moderate-severe psoriasis in the sanitary area of Badajoz</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To perform a cost-effectiveness analysis, by using a decision tree model, comparing methotrexate with PUVA therapy for moderate to severe chronic plaque psoriasis in the sanitary area of Badajoz (south-western Spain) over a one-year period.                 Material and methods. The following variables and data sources were included: efficacy (a 50 % reduction in the PASI) and safety (adverse reactions). Data were retrieved from the dermatologic medical literature, mainly general reviews, systematic reviews and randomized clinical trials. Therapy schedules followed current guidelines from work task teams and consensus documents.                 Direct costs included unitary costs of medical consults, costs of laboratory tests, pharmacy, phototherapy sessions and costs derived from adverse reactions.                 Indirect costs included travel expenses and costs of lost productive work time.                 Results. Unitary cost of methotrexate therapy would be 952.79 euros per treatment (direct cost: 796.48; indirect cost: 156.31). Unitary cost of PUVA therapy would be 899.70 euros per treatment (direct cost: 383.36; indirect cost: 516.34). Total cost of a one-year treatment with methotrexate would be 255,202.73 euros. Total cost of a one-year treatment with PUVA would be 266,406.88 euros. The average cost-effectiveness ratios per case effectively treated would be 1,519.06 euros for methotrexate therapy, and 1,085.18 euros for PUVA therapy. The incremental cost-effectiveness ratio of PUVA/methotrexate would be 150.65 euros for each additional case effectively treated.                 Conclusions. One-year treatment for moderate to severe psoriasis in the sanitary area of Badajoz would be more expensive but also more cost-effective with PUVA than with methotrexate. However, indirect costs (borne by patients), are higher for PUVA therapy, a fact that raises an issue of equity. The results should be interpreted taking into account the methodological limitations of a modelling study</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Nevado, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Argila, D de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chaves, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Realizar un análisis de coste-efectividad modelizado, usando un árbol decisión, comparando metotrexato y fototerapia tipo PUVA para la psoriasis crónica en placas moderadas-severas en el Área de Salud (AS) de Badajoz, durante el periodo de un año, desde la perspectiva societaria.                 Material y métodos. Se consideraron las variables eficacia (PASI50 [descenso del 50 % del PASI basal]) y seguridad (reacciones adversas). Se valoró como eficaz la mejoría del PASI50. Se tomaron datos de la literatura médica dermatológica, fundamentalmente revisiones generales, revisiones sistemáticas y ensayos clínicos aleatorizados. Los regímenes de tratamiento se obtuvieron de las recomendaciones de grupos de trabajo y documentos de consenso, recogidos en publicaciones médicas.                 Como costes directos se consideraron los costes unitarios por consulta, los de las pruebas de monitorización, los de la medicación y las sesiones de fototerapia y los de las reacciones adversas.                 En los costes indirectos se valoraron los costes por desplazamiento, y los de productividad debidos a la pérdida de horas de trabajo de la jornada laboral.                 Resultados. El coste unitario por tratamiento con metotrexato sería de 952,79 euros (directos: 796,48; indirectos: 156,31). El coste unitario por tratamiento con PUVA sería 899,70 euros (directos: 383,36; indirectos: 516,34). El coste total del tratamiento durante un año con metotrexato sería 255.202,73 euros, y con PUVA 266.406,88 euros. Las ratios medias de coste-efectividad serían, para cada uno de los tratamientos: metotrexato 1.519,06 euros, y PUVA 1.085,18 euros por caso tratado eficazmente. La ratio incremental PUVA/metotrexato sería: 150,65 euros por cada caso añadido eficazmente tratado.                 Conclusiones. El tratamiento de la psoriasis durante un año en el AS de Badajoz con PUVA sería más caro, pero también más coste-efectivo que el tratamiento con metotrexato. Sin embargo, los costes indirectos (soportados por el paciente) del tratamiento con PUVA son más altos, lo que plantea un problema de equidad. Estos resultados deben considerarse a la luz de las limitaciones metodológicas de un estudio modelizado</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;98(1): 35-41, ene. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052372</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de coste-efectividad modelizado comparando metotrexato con fototerapia tipo PUVA para la psoriasis moderada-severa en el Área de Salud de Badajoz</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12335^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12002^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12002^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12137^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30313^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12137^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12002^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28169^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12137^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32388</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10987^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5629^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3380^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
