<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61111</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Omega-3 and cardiovascular disease: beyond the risk factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cardiovascular diseases are the leading cause of dea thin Europe, representing 49% of all deaths and 30%of deaths before 65s. At present, the prevalence of cardiovascular disease goes away from diminishing,continues to rise, linked to the progressive increase ofthe population&#146;s age. Diet plays a role in promotion andprevention of cardiovascular disease. Thus, the specifictype of fat will determine, in part, the final effect on thedevelopment or prevention of this disease. An exampleof the importance of the type of fat on cardiovascularhealth is the omega-3.At present, a large number of scientific evidenceshows that consumption of omega-3 fatty acids producesa decrease of cardiovascular risk. This has led tomajor scientific societies like the AHA, the AmericanSociety of Cardiology and the European Society ofCardiology recommend their consumption and thus theomega-3 fatty acids have been included in their actionguidelines, albeit with varying degrees evidence. Thusfor people who do not have cardiovascular disease, therecommendation of fish consumption, preferably blue,at least twice a week, as well as foods rich in ALA. Forits part, in cases where there is obvious disease shouldensure the provision of 1 g daily of a mixture of EPAand DHA. Taking into account that the contribution ofomega-3 in the diet of many Western countries is farbelow the figures recommended by scientific societies,is a clear need to increase their consumption.It has been demonstrated in various clinical trials thatsupplementation of omega-3 fatty acids can reduce cardiovascularevents, in addition to a reduction in the atherosclerosisprogression. However, additional studies areneeded to replicate the benefits on health from thesesupplements, both in primary and secondary prevention (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Antonio, García-Ríos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pablo, Pérez-Martínez</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Francisco, Pérez-Jiménez</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>María Eugenia, Meneses</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las enfermedades cardiovasculares son la principal causa de muerte en Europa, representando el 49% detodas las muertes y el 30% de las muertes antes de los65 años. En la actualidad, la prevalencia de enfermedadcardiovascular lejos de ir disminuyendo, continúacreciendo, vinculada al aumento progresivo en la edadde la población. En la promoción y prevención de la enfermedadcardiovascular, la dieta juega un papel predominante.Así, específicamente el tipo de grasa que lacompone merece especial atención porque determinará,en parte, el efecto final sobre el desarrollo o prevenciónde esta patología. Un ejemplo de la importanciadel tipo de grasa en la salud cardiovascular, loconstituyen los omega-3.En la actualidad, gran número de evidencias científicasdemuestran que el consumo de ácidos grasos omega-3 produce una disminución en el riesgo cardiovascular.Esto ha llevado a que las grandes sociedadescientíficas como la AHA, la Sociedad Americana deCardiología y la Sociedad Europea de Cardiología recomiendensu consumo y por tanto, los ácidos grasosomega-3 han sido incluidos en sus guías de actuación,aunque con distinto nivel de evidencia. De este modo,para las personas que no tienen enfermedad cardiovascular,se recomienda el consumo de pescado preferentementeazul, al menos dos veces a la semana, asícomo alimentos ricos en ALA. Por su parte, en los casosen que hay enfermedad evidente se debería garantizarel aporte de 1 gramo diario de una mezcla de EPAo DHA. Teniendo en cuenta que el aporte de omega-3de la dieta habitual de muchos países occidentales estámuy por debajo de las cifras recomendadas por las sociedadescientíficas. (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;29(1): 4-16, ene.-abr. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61111</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Omega-3 y enfermedad cardiovascular: más allá de los factores de riesgo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24651^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
