<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81266</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-2399</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Development of an attention guideline for the critical patient's family</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">IntroductionWithin the context of participatory action research (PAR) at an Intensive Care Unit (ICU), 4 proposals for change were agreed by consensus to improve the attention given to families of critical patients. One proposal was the creation of a guideline for attending to family members, inspired by the participants&#146; desire to improve the attention given to this group of users.Objectives1) To design a guide that would meet the needs of professionals and users. 2) To reach an agreement on the minimum requirements for attention given to families of critical patients.Materials and methodsQualitative methodology, based on PAR. For each of the initiatives, a working group was created, composed mainly of professionals from the ICU coordinated by a researcher. In the case of the guide, an online community was also created as a working tool to speed up communications among the participants, reducing the number of face-to-face sessions. Participation was voluntary. To draft the guideline, a Clinical Practice Guideline for support the family was made available, which had been translated into Spanish, together with an up-to-date bibliography.ResultsTwenty four professionals were involved. We developed a guide that contained the following sections: introduction, objectives, the experiences and needs of families of patients in the ICU, strategies for action, specific procedures, and hospital resources. We designed strategies for the diffusion and implementation of the guide.ConclusionsThe guide is a useful tool that offers the professionals greater assurances and unifying criteria for action. During subsequent stages of the PAR project, an assessment will be made of the impact on professionals and users(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Balaguer Albarracín, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zaforteza Lallemand, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Roldán, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Gascue,  M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lastra Cubel, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Calvín, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durán Torres, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez Alcalde, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amorós Cerdá, S. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Mozo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">IntroducciónEn el contexto de un proyecto de investigación-acción participativa (IAP) en una unidad de cuidados intensivos (UCI), se consensuaron 4 propuestas de cambio para mejorar los cuidados a los familiares del paciente crítico. Una de ellas fue la elaboración de una guía de cuidados a los familiares, derivada de la voluntad de los participantes de mejorar la atención a este grupo de usuarios.Objetivos1) Diseñar una guía de atención adaptada a las necesidades de profesionales y usuarios. 2) Establecer un acuerdo de mínimos en la atención a los familiares.Material y métodosMetodología cualitativa, diseño IAP. Para cada una de las iniciativas se creó un grupo de trabajo integrado mayoritariamente por profesionales de la UCI y coordinado por un investigador. En el caso de la guía se creó, además, una comunidad virtual como herramienta de trabajo para agilizar la comunicación entre los participantes, disminuyendo las reuniones presenciales. La participación fue voluntaria. Para su elaboración se dispuso de una guía de práctica clínica traducida al castellano y una revisión bibliográfica actualizada.ResultadosSe han implicado 24 profesionales. Desarrollamos una guía con los siguientes apartados: introducción, objetivos, experiencias y necesidades de los familiares en UCI, estrategias de actuación, procedimientos específicos y recursos del hospital. Diseñamos las estrategias para su difusión e implantación.ConclusionesLa guía es una herramienta útil para dar seguridad al profesional y unificar criterios de actuación. Las siguientes fases del proyecto de IAP evaluarán el impacto en profesionales y usuarios(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Intensiva;21(1): 20-27, ene. -marz. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81266</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desarrollo de una guía de atención a los familiares del paciente crítico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23905</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30602</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
