<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120610</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Short bowel syndrome cause of hypomagnesaemia importance of its diagnosis and treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The short bowel syndrome (SIC) is a complex entity characterized by a malabsorptive state usually secondary to extensive intestinal resection originating a clinical, metabolic and/or nutritional disorder due to the reduction of the effective intestinal absorptive surface. The diagnosis is essentially clinical and, due to the patients malabsorptive process, it requires nutritional support to maintain their basic requirements, as the case reported. The clinical features of SIC patients depend on the grade of the alteration of function of the the small intestine or the impairment secondary to the surgical resection. We know that electrolytes are absorbed predominantly in the proximal gut. The regulation of ion/mineral levels depend on both the intestinal absorption and the renal excretion. We present an unusual case of SIC with only low absortion of magnesium. We discuss the most outstanding aspects of the case and review the literatura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calañas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Botella-Carretero, JI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arrieta, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zamarron, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, FB</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanchez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de intestino corto (SIC) es una entidad compleja caracterizada, por un estado malabsortivo secundario normalmente a una resección intestinal extensa que ocasiona alteraciones clínico, metabólicas y/o nutricionales debidas a la reducción de la superficie absortiva intestinal efectiva. El diagnóstico es fundamentalmente clínico y el paciente, por el proceso malabsortivo, requiere un soporte nutricional para mantener sus requerimientos básicos, como en el caso que presentamos. La clínica asociada al SIC también está en función de la zona de intestino delgado afectada por la resección o la alteración funcional. Sabemos que los electrolitos son absorbidos predominantemente en el intestino delgado. La regulación de los niveles de iones/minerales se basa tanto en la absorción intestinal como en la excreción renal. Consideramos de interés la publicación del caso, dado lo excepcional de la pérdida aislada de magnesio secundaria al SIC. Comentamos los aspectos más destacables del mismo y revisamos la literatura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;29(2): 456-459, 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120610</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de intestino corto causa de hipomagnesemia; importância de su diagnostico y tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8449^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13158^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8459^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
