<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79945</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Is the 6-min walk test useful in primary care?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction Given the frequency and importance of COPD, we need to know the functional performance of our patients. Therefore we have sought to evaluate their exercise capacity using the 6-min walk test (6MWT), evaluating its utility and safety. Material and methods An evaluation study of a functional test in Primary Care with 94 COPD patients (mean, 72.34 years; 77.77%, men) who performed the 6MWT. Results Our patients walked a mean of 360.39 meters. The distance significantly correlated with the FEV1 in liters (r=0.423), with the 10-year likelihood of survival (r=0.403), with height (r=0.236), with O2 saturation (r=0.226) and with FEV1% (r=0.214). Significant inverse correlations were observed with age (r=&amp;#8722;0.458), adapted Charlson index (r=&amp;#8722;0.290), and with their disease stage (r=&amp;#8722;0.215). Heart rate, that went from 78.26 to 85.70bpm, and oxygen saturation (94.07% to 95.84%), systolic blood pressure (146.82mmHg to 158.77), diastolic blood pressure (80.79mmHg to 83.78) and the sensation of dyspnea (from 0.72 to 2.83) and tiredness (0.69 to 2.36) measured with the Borg scale significantly increased during the test (p&lt;0.0001). There were no complications and all the patients, except for one, correctly completed the test. Conclusion The older patients with other conditions and with an advanced COPD stage were able to walk significantly shorter distances. The 6MWT was a useful test to evaluate the severity of the disease, and was also easy and safe (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garcés Asemany, C. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabedo García, V. R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción  La enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica (EPOC) constituye una importante causa de muerte y discapacidad y un frecuente motivo de consulta en Atención Primaria. Pretendemos estudiar la utilidad y seguridad de la prueba de la marcha durante 6 min (PM6M) para valorar el estado funcional de los pacientes. Material y métodos Estudio de valoración de una prueba funcional en atención primaria con 94 pacientes (media: 72,34 años; el 77,77% eran hombres) con EPOC que realizaron la PM6M. Resultados Nuestros pacientes caminaron una media de 360,39m, la distancia correlacionó significativamente con el volumen espiratorio forzado en un segundo en litros (r=0,423), la probabilidad de supervivencia a los 10 años (r=0,403), con la talla (r=0,236), la saturación de oxígeno (r=0,226) y el porcentaje del volumen espiratorio forzado en un segundo (r=0,214); observamos correlaciones inversas significativas con la edad (r=&amp;#8722;0,458), el índice de Charlson ajustado (r=&amp;#8722;0,290) y el estadio de su enfermedad (r=&amp;#8722;0,215). Tanto la frecuencia cardiaca que pasó de 78,26 a 85,70ppm como la saturación de oxígeno (del 94,07 al 95,84%), la presión arterial sistólica (de 146,82 a 158,77mmHg), la presión arterial diastólica (80,79 a 83,78mmHg), así como la sensación de disnea (de 0,72 a 2,83) y el cansancio (0,69&#150;2,36) medidas con la escala de Borg aumentaron de forma muy significativa en el transcurso de la prueba (p&lt;0,0001). No hubo complicaciones y todos los pacientes, menos uno, finalizaron correctamente el test. Conclusión Los pacientes más mayores con otras patologías y en un estadio avanzado de EPOC conseguían caminar distancias significativamente menores; la PM6M resultó una prueba útil para valorar la gravedad de la enfermedad, resultando además ser sencilla y segura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);36(5): 259-265, mayo 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79945</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Es útil la prueba de la marcha durante 6 min en Atención Primaria?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5178^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5823^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
