<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94519</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Myofascial release therapy in attention deficit hyperactivity disorder: a case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder is a childhood neuropsychiatric disorder onset that clinically impairs social, academic and personal functioning, with childhood onset. In a high proportion of cases, it persists beyond adolescence. Even though the variability of its clinical signs, symptoms and comorbidities requires a multidisciplinary therapeutic approach, there are few publications existing on the contribution of physiotherapy intervention for the treatment of this condition. Results obtained on a patient treated with two myofascial release techniques (ligamentum nuchae and suboccipital inhibition release) are presented, that point out some improvement on the patient's clinical manifestations. Controlled large scale studies would be desirable to elucidate the true role of such therapy in patients with this disorder (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz-Bustillo, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El trastorno por déficit de atención e hiperactividad se caracteriza por un cuadro clínico neuropsiquiátrico que conlleva retraso y dificultades en el funcionamiento personal, académico y social, de inicio en la infancia y que, en un elevado porcentaje de los casos, persiste más allá de la adolescencia. A pesar de que la variabilidad de sus manifestaciones clínicas y comorbilidades requieren un abordaje terapéutico multidisciplinar, en el campo de la fisioterapia existen pocos estudios relativos al tratamiento de esta patología. Se presentan los resultados obtenidos en una paciente tras la aplicación de dos técnicas de terapia de inducción miofascial, la técnica de liberación del gran ligamento nucal y la técnica de inducción suboccipital, que permiten apuntar cierta mejoría de las características del cuadro clínico de la paciente. Sería deseable realizar estudios controlados a mayor escala a fin de esclarecer el verdadero papel de esta terapia en este tipo de pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);33(5): 227-230, sep. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94519</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Terapia de inducción miofascial en el trastorno por déficit de atención e hiperactividad: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11245^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
