<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036807</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-1637</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of the mixed dentition methods to predict unerupted teeth</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The estimation of the size of unerupted    permanent teeth, canines and premolars, in mixed dentition    has always been considered an essential aspect in    orthodontics.    The aim of the present study is to show all the methods    that have been developed to make these predictions    and their advantages and disadvantages.    Four main methods have been used to estimate the    mesiodistal crown widths of unerupted canines and    premolars: calculations from prediction equations and    tables, direct measurements on radiographs, combination    of radiographic measurements and prediction tables    and other independent method.    Methods with a regression equation that relate the    widths of unerupted teeth to the widths of erupted teeth    are easy and fast to use but not very reliable, methods    of measuring unerupted teeth on radiographs depend    on the quality of the x-ray films available for use    and methods that combine regression equations and    radiographs present great accuracy but are time consuming    and difficult to use.    Finally, we present a new digital computerized-aid    method to predict the size of unerupted teeth in mixed    dentition using several reference teeth already erupted    and mesiodistal teeth tables</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gandia Franco, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cibrian Ortiz de Anda, R. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paredes Gallardo, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde siempre, conocer el tamaño de los    dientes no erupcionados, caninos y premolares, en dentición    mixta, ha sido un claro reto en ortodoncia.    El objetivo del presente trabajo es mostrar todos los    métodos existentes en la bibliografía para realizar la    predicción del tamaño de estos dientes, así como sus    ventajas e inconvenientes.    Estos métodos pueden clasificarse en 4 grandes grupos:    los basados en ecuaciones de regresión; los basados    en mediciones directas en radiografías; los que    combinan elementos de los 2 anteriores, y otro método    no clasificable en ninguno de los anteriores.    Los métodos basados en ecuaciones de regresión    son rápidos de realizar pero presentan coeficientes de    correlación bajos y de poca fiabilidad; los que usan mediciones    directas sobre radiografías periapicales presentan    el problema de obtener imágenes distorsionadas    en ocasiones, lo cual limita la exactitud de estas técnicas;    los métodos combinados son los más fiables, aunque    son los que más tiempo consumen y son más complejos    de realizar.    Por último, se presenta un método digital de gran    fiabilidad y sencillo y rápido de realizar, no clasificable    en ninguno de los grupos anteriores. Se trata de un método    basado en la interpolación de tamaños de los dientes    utilizando listas de tamaños dentarios y dientes de    referencia ya erupcionados</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ortod. esp. (Ed. impr.);45(1): 1-8, ene. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036807</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración de los métodos de predicción de tamaños dentarios en dentición mixta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1666^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1666^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8483^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3501^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8483^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3833</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9997^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8506^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10148^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8506^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15363</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
