<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137826</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Morbidity observed in a health area: Impact on professionals and funding</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze morbidity, in the context of a health area, and broken down by health centre, of patients who made contact with healthcare services, in order to propose an adjustment to finance the payment per capita. Design: A descriptive study of morbidity observed in citizens assigned a health area during year 2010. Site: Health Area 9. Autonomous Community of Madrid. Formed by the municipalities of Fuenlabrada, Humanes, and Moraleja de Enmedio. All levels of health care included. Participants: All citizens with health card assigned to a health center in the area who has maintained contact with the public health service's own area. Measurements: Coded contact of patients are grouped using the Population Grouping Clinical Risk 3M TM Software (CRG). Each patient is included in a homogeneous and exclusive group with a numerical morbidity and clinical sense. Through the health card is known primary care centre, physician, age and sex. Results: The distribution of morbidity is obtained by primary care centre, primary care physician, age and sex analyzing differences and combinations. Conclusions: It was found that the average values of the population morbidity are different in each primary care centre. In order to maintain the principle of equity in health care, it is suggested that an adjustment is made to the per capita payment based on the morbidity rate of the population (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vicente, María Auxiliadora de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivas, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguel, Pablo de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manera, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar, en el contexto de un área sanitaria, la morbilidad desagregada por centro de salud de los pacientes que entran en contacto con los servicios asistenciales para proponer un ajuste a la financiación en el pago per cápita. Diseño: Estudio descriptivo, retrospectivo, de la morbilidad observada en los ciudadanos asignados a un área de salud durante el año 2010. Emplazamiento: Área 9 de salud de la Comunidad Autónoma de Madrid, que comprende los municipios de Fuenlabrada, Humanes y Moraleja de Enmedio. Incluyendo todos los niveles de atención sanitaria. Participantes: La totalidad de ciudadanos con tarjeta sanitaria asignada a un centro de salud del área que haya mantenido contacto con los servicios públicos de salud del propio área. Mediciones: Se obtienen y agrupan los contactos codificados de los pacientes mediante el agrupador poblacional 3MTM Clinical Risk Grouping Software (CRG) cada paciente resulta incluido en un grupo homogéneo y excluyente con una morbilidad numérica y sentido clínico. A través de la tarjeta sanitaria se conoce centro de salud, médico de atención primaria, edad y sexo. Resultados: Se estratifica la morbilidad por centro de salud, médico de atención primaria, edad y sexo y analizando las diferencias entre cada una de ellas y sus diferentes combinaciones. Conclusiones: Se comprueba cómo los valores promedio de morbilidad de la población presentan valores distintos en cada zona básica de salud. Para mantener el principio de equidad sería necesario ajustar pago per cápita y número de tarjetas asignadas en función de la morbilidad observada de la población (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;47(5): 301-307, mayo 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137826</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Morbilidad observada en un área sanitaria: variabilidad e impacto en profesionales y en financiación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28631^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32415^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32415^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32415^s22082</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23662^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32415^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23662^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23662^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23662^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
