<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-30887</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Lamotrigine in refractory epilepsy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Lamotrigine (LTG) is a new antiepileptic drug indicated in all kinds of partial and generalised clonic-tonic seizures, both in monotherapy and polytherapy. Between 20 and 30% of epileptic patients have poor control over their seizures despite adequate treatment. Aims. We report on our experience regarding the long-term efficacy and tolerability of LTG in refractory seizures. Patients and methods. We conducted a consecutive 10-year study of patients who began LTG therapy following poor control of their seizures, in spite of being treated with two or more antiepileptic drugs in monotherapy or in combination. Both their epidemiological and clinical data were collected for study. We studied the efficacy of the treatment, differentiating between remission (absence of seizures), improvement (reduction &gt; 50% of the seizures), inefficacy (reduction &lt; 50%), exacerbation (increase in seizures) and its tolerability (side effects and dropout). Results. In all, data was collected from 39 patients, 18 males (46.2%), mean age 30.9 ± 13.7 years; mean follow-up time: 27.6 ± 23.4 months. 43.7% presented cryptogenic epilepsy, in 28.5% it was symptomatic and in the remaining 28.5% it was idiopathic. EEG readings and neuroimaging scans were pathological in 53.8% and 43.6%, respectively. After beginning therapy with LTG, 33% remained free of seizures, 43.6% improved, in 18.3% it was seen to be ineffective and 5.1% got worse. Dropout rate was 56.4%: 23.1% due to insufficient control over the seizures, 17.9% owing to side effects and 15.4% because of non-compliance. Conclusion. Treatment with LTG offers a high degree of efficacy in the control of seizures in patients with refractory epilepsy, although it is limited by a high dropout rate (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La lamotrigina (LTG) es un nuevo antiepiléptico indicado para todo tipo de crisis parciales y tonicoclónicas generalizadas, tanto en monoterapia como politerapia. El 20-30 por ciento de los pacientes epilépticos tienen un mal control de las crisis, pese a un tratamiento adecuado. Objetivo. Presentamos nuestra experiencia en cuanto a eficacia y tolerabilidad a largo plazo de la LTG en crisis refractarias. Pacientes y métodos. Estudiamos consecutivamente durante 10 años a los pacientes que iniciaron tratamiento con LTG tras un mal control de sus crisis, pese al tratamiento con dos o más fármacos antiepilépticos en monoterapia o en combinación. Recogimos sus datos epidemiológicos y clínicos. Estudiamos la eficacia del tratamiento, diferenciando entre remisión (ausencia de crisis), mejoría (reducción mayor o igual al 50 por ciento de las crisis), ineficacia (reducción menor del 50 por ciento), agravamiento (aumento de las crisis), y su tolerabilidad (efectos secundarios y abandono del tratamiento).Resultados. Se recogieron 39 pacientes -18 hombres (46,2 por ciento), edad media de 30,9 ñ 13,7 años-; el seguimiento medio fue de 27,6 ñ 23,4 meses. El 43,7 por ciento presentaba epilepsia criptogénica, el 28,5 por ciento, sintomática, y el 28,5 por ciento, idiopática. El EEG fue patológico en el 53,8 por ciento de los pacientes y la neuroimagen, en el 43,6 por ciento. Tras la introducción de la LTG, el 33 por ciento de los pacientes quedó libre de crisis, el 43,6 por ciento mejoró, en el 18,3 por ciento de ellos fue ineficaz y el 5,1 por ciento empeoró. El 56,4 por ciento abandonó el tratamiento: el 23,1 por ciento por control insuficiente de las crisis, el 17,9 por ciento por efectos secundarios y el 15,4 por ciento por incumplimiento terapéutico. Conclusión. El tratamiento con LTG logra una alta eficacia en el control de las crisis en los pacientes con epilepsia refractaria, si bien está limitado por una elevada tasa de abandonos terapéuticos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;38(4): 301-303, feb. 2004. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lamotrigina en epilepsia refractaria</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Palao Sánchez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliver Navarrete, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Asensio Asensio, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moltó Jordá, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-30887</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d7980</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4419</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
