<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151393</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Subfoveal choroidal thickness in eyes with diabetic macular oedema using swept source optical coherence tomography</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To compare subfoveal choroidal thickness (GCSF) in patients with diabetic macular oedema (DMO) and healthy subjects using swept source optical coherence tomography (SS-OCT). Method: Cross-sectional study including 50 eyes of 36 patients with DMO, and 47 eyes of 34 patients as a control group. GCSF was measured in both groups, analysing between the eyes with DMO according to the type of oedema (predominantly cystic or diffuse). Results: The study groups were homogeneous in terms of mean age (63.4 years for DMO and 62.65 years for controls; P=.36) and the mean axial length (23.21 mm for DME and 23.53 mm for controls; P=.06). A statistically significant reduction in the eye with DME GCSF compared to controls (P=.041, 222.9 vs. 192.82 &amp;#956;m) was observed. No statistically significant differences were observed in the eyes with DMO with a predominantly cystic pattern and diffuse oedema (P=.13, 178.68 vs. 205.7 &amp;#956;m). Conclusion: The GCSF in patients with DMO could be reduced. Future studies are needed to confirm these preliminary results (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gallego Pinazo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cisneros Lanuza, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Freytas, A de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Propósito: Comparar el grosor coroideo subfoveal (GCSF) entre pacientes con edema macular diabético (EMD) y sujetos sanos mediante tomografía de coherencia óptica swept source (SS-OCT). Método: Estudio transversal con 50 ojos de 36 pacientes con EMD y 47 ojos de 34 pacientes como grupo control. Fue evaluado el GCSF en ambos grupos, realizándose además un análisis entre los ojos con EMD en función del tipo de edema (predominantemente quístico o difuso). Resultados: Los grupos de estudio fueron homogéneos en cuanto a la edad media (63,4 años para EMD y 62,65 años para controles; p = 0,36) y la longitud axial media (23,21 mm para EMD y 23,53 mm para controles; p = 0,06). Se objetivó una reducción estadísticamente significativa en el grosor coroideo entre los ojos con EMD respecto al grupo control (192,82 vs. 222,9 &amp;#956;m; p = 0,041). No se evidenciaron diferencias estadísticamente significativas en los ojos con EMD en función del patrón de edema predominantemente quístico y difuso (205,7 vs. 178,68 &amp;#956;m; p = 0,13). Conclusión: El GCSF en pacientes con EMD podría encontrarse reducido, sin que el patrón de engrosamiento macular tomográfico se asocie a diferencias significativas en este sentido. Son necesarios futuros estudios para confirmar estos resultados preliminares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;91(5): 228-231, mayo 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151393</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Grosor coroideo subfoveal medido con tomografía de coherencia óptica swept source en ojos con edema macular diabético</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3954^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3954^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28131^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28131^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2879^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2879^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28131^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3954^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
