<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110671</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Utilization of dermatology services among the immigrant population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the utilization rate of a dermatology service among the immigrant population and compare this rate with that among the autochthonous population. Methods: Over a 1-year period, data on all patients attended in the Dermatology Service of Health Department 19 in the autonomous community of Valencia were prospectively collected. Results: Of 39,160 consultations, 1,625 were made by immigrants (4.1%). Attendance for dermatologic emergencies was greater in immigrants than in the autochthonous population (7.7% vs 3.0%; p &lt; 0.001), while surgical activity was lower in immigrants than in Spanish-born patients (2.6% vs 5%; p &lt; 0.001). Demand for consultation in the immigrant population was 5.7 visits per 100 immigrants, lower than that in the autochthonous population (16.2). The standardized rate ratio was 0.34. North Africans (5.6 per 100 immigrants), East Europeans (4.8), sub-Saharan Africans (5.3) and Asians (4.2) consulted less than Latin Americans (8.5; p&lt;0.001). Conclusions: Demand was lower in the immigrant than in the autochthonous population, and the utilization patters differed according to country (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Betlloch Más, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Belinchón Romero, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albares Tendero, M. Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastor Tomás, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Botella Antón, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Rincón, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Conocer la demanda asistencial en dermatología de la población inmigrante (PI) y compararla con la de la población autóctona (PA). Métodos: Durante un año, se recogió prospectivamente el número de enfermedades atendidas en dermatología en el Departamento de Salud 19 de la Comunidad Valenciana. Resultados: De 39.160 episodios, 1.625 fueron en PI (4,1%). La asistencia por urgencias fue mayor en PI que en PA (el 7,7 frente al 3,0%; p &lt; 0,001) y la actividad quirúrgica en PI fue menor que en PA (el 2,6 frente al 5%; p &lt; 0,001). La demanda en la PI fue de 5,7 episodios por 100 inmigrantes, inferior a la PA (16,2). La razón de tasas estandarizada fue de 0,34. Los pacientes del norte de África (5,6 por 100 inmigrantes), Europa del Este (4,8), África subsahariana (5,3) y Asia (4,2) consultaron menos que los latinoamericanos (8,5; p &lt; 0,001). Conclusiones: La demanda en PI fue inferior a la PA y con un patrón de utilización diferente por países (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;22(2): 133-136, mar.-abr. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110671</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la demanda asistencial en dermatología de la población inmigrante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6453^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
