<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114836</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cultural adaptation and content validation of the «Pain level» outcome of the Nursing Outcomes Classification</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims To translate and culturally adapt the Pain Level outcome to the Spanish context to validate the contents of the Spanish version of the «Pain level» outcome. Method The original English version of the «Pain level» outcome was translated into Spanish (twice); then back-translated into English, and all the discrepancies were resolved after consulting with NOC authors. A panel consisting of 21 experts in pain care assessed this culturally adapted Spanish version, in order to score the content validity. In the first step, the experts scored the adequacy of each indicator to the concept «Pain level». In the second round, three new indicators were scored. The Statistical analysis included content validity index (CVI), probability of agreement by chance, and modified kappa statistic. Results A Spanish version was developed including label, definition, two groups of indicators, and two measurement scales. This version is fully adapted to the Spanish context and language. A set of 21 indicators (19 translated and two new) was selected, and 4 were deleted (three translated and one new). The CVI-average score was 0.83 and the CVI-universal agreement was 0.05. Conclusion The Spanish-version of the outcome «Pain level» is semantically and culturally to adapted to a Spanish context and preserves equivalency with the original. Content validation has identified indicators useful for practice. The clinimetric properties (validity and reliability) of the adapted version could be tested in a clinical study with people suffering from acute pain (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Torres, María del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Medina, Isabel María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pancorbo-Hidalgo, Pedro Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bellido-Vallejo , José Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos Traducir y adaptar culturalmente el resultado de la Clasificación de Resultados de Enfermería «Pain level» al español y validar el contenido de la versión española del resultado «Nivel del dolor». Método Doble traducción de la versión original en inglés del resultado «Pain Level» al español y retrotraducción al inglés. Se contrastan las discrepancias con las autoras originales y se somete la versión adaptada a un panel de 21 expertos en dolor para realizar la validación de contenido de los indicadores. En la primera fase, los expertos valoraron la adecuación de los indicadores al concepto «Nivel del dolor» y en la segunda, la adecuación de 3 nuevos indicadores. El análisis estadístico se realizó a través del índice de validez de contenido ( IVC ), probabilidad de acuerdo por azar y el coeficiente kappa modificado. Resultados Se elaboró una versión en español que incluye etiqueta, definición, 2 grupos de indicadores y 2 escalas de medición, con una redacción adaptada a la lengua y contexto español. Se han seleccionado 21 indicadores (19 traducidos y 2 nuevos) y se han eliminado 4 (3 traducidos y uno nuevo), obteniendo un IVC-promedio de 0,83 y un IVC-acuerdo universal de 0,05. Conclusiones La versión del resultado «Nivel del dolor», adaptada semántica y culturalmente al contexto español, preserva la equivalencia con el original. La validación de contenido ha permitido identificar los indicadores útiles para la práctica habitual. La versión adaptada podrá ser sometida a un estudio de campo para conocer sus propiedades clinimétricas (validez y fiabilidad) en personas con dolor agudo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);23(4): 154-159, jul.-agos. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114836</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación cultural y validación de contenido del resultado «Nivel del dolor» de la Clasificación de Resultados de Enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
