<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82973</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ultrasound diagnosis of fetal cardiac tumors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Primary fetal cardiac tumors are uncommon and are mostly benign. The prognosis depends on the location of the tumor and its histological aggressiveness. We present two cases of primary cardiac tumors diagnosed at the end of the second and third trimester of pregnancy by ultrasound scanning during intrauterine life. In the first case, the tumor was localized in the right atrium, requiring surgery in the neonatal period. The pathological diagnosis was capillary hemangioma. In the second case, the cardiac tumor was located in the interventricular septum and was considered unresectable. The neonate died at 44hours of life. The ultrasonographic images of both cases are presented (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Payo, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias Goy, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ángeles Martos Cano, M. de los</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los tumores cardiacos fetales primarios no son frecuentes, en su mayoría son benignos, y su pronóstico depende fundamentalmente de su localización y de su agresividad histológica. Se presentan dos casos de tumores primarios cardiacos, diagnosticados en el final del segundo y tercer trimestre de la gestación, mediante estudio ecográfico durante la vida intrauterina. En el primer caso, la tumoración estaba localizada a nivel de la aurícula derecha y precisó tratamiento quirúrgico en el periodo neonatal, siendo el resultado anatomopatológico de hemangioma capilar. En el segundo caso, la tumoración estaba localizada a nivel del septo interventricular, considerándose irresecable tras el nacimiento, y falleciendo el neonato a las 44 horas de vida. Se aportan las imágenes ecográficas prenatales de ambos casos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);53(12): 513-516, dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82973</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico ecográfico de las tumoraciones cardiacas fetales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6492^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31420^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9425^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9572^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d664^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29142^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31420^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6492^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29142^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6492^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6492^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
