<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60579</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Infections related to recreational waters</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Recreational waters are a source of infection by severalmicroorganisms causing acute gastrointestinal, cutaneousand respiratory illnesses. Cryptosporidium, noroviruses and enteropathogenic Escherichia coli strains are the mostimportant causes of diarrhea, while Pseudomonas andStaphylococcus aureus are the main causes of cutaneousinfections, and Legionella is the major cause of acutelower respiratory disease. Approximately 90% ofoutbreaks occur in treated recreational waters (swimmingpools, spas and recreational parks), while the remaining10% arise from natural waters used for leisure (bathing inrivers, beaches, etc). In spas, most infections are caused bythermophilic bacteria, such as Pseudomonas andLegionella, since overgrowth of these bacteria is facilitatedby the direct effect of temperature and, indirectly, by theevaporation of the disinfectant.Outbreaks related to recreational waters usually reflectdeficient control of the system: a low level of disinfectant,or the use of an inappropriate disinfectant, insufficientmaintenance and cleaning of the installation, higher thanrecommended usage, and failure of the disinfectantdosage system. The correct design, maintenance and useof these facilities drastically lower the risk of infectionsfrom recreational waters. Thus, other key actions tominimize this risk are the existence of, and compliancewith, regulatory rules, as well as educational campaignson good hygiene practices directed at users. Rapidetiologic diagnosis of affected patients, together with anepidemiological survey and detection of the pathogenimplicated in water samples are the keys to outbreakcontrol(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Berrocal, Clara I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olea, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Doménech-Sánchez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El uso recreativo del agua implica un riesgo de contagiopor parte de microorganismos responsables degastroenteritis, dermatitis y patología respiratoria.Cryptosporidium, norovirus y cepas de Escherichia colienteropatógenas son las causas más importantes debrotes de diarrea, mientras que Pseudomonas yStaphylococcus aureus son los principales agentes deinfecciones cutáneas, y Legionella de infecciónrespiratoria. Aproximadamente, el 90% de los brotes quese producen son en aguas de recreo tratadas (piscinas,balnearios, parques recreativos), frente a un 10% en aguasnaturales (ríos, playas, etc.). En los balnearios, lasinfecciones más frecuentes son debidas a bacteriastermófilas (Pseudomonas y Legionella), puesto que latemperatura y la consiguiente evaporación deldesinfectante contribuyen a facilitar su multiplicación.Los brotes siempre se deben a deficiencias en el controldel sistema: bajo nivel de desinfectante o utilización deuno inadecuado, mantenimiento y limpieza insuficientes,alto nivel de ocupación y averías en los equipos dedosificación. El diseño, mantenimiento y uso adecuado deestas instalaciones disminuyen este riesgo, y esfundamental la existencia de una normativa reguladora,así como campañas de concienciación a los usuarios paraque se cumplan las normas de higiene básicas. Eldiagnóstico etiológico del cuadro clínico, complementadocon la encuesta epidemiológica y la detección sanitaria enlas aguas, todos ellos realizados con rapidez, constituye laclave para el control de estos brotes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;26(supl.13): 32-37, nov. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60579</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infecciones relacionadas con las aguas de recreo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35604^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5016^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15280</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3475^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24946^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28582^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15275</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200811</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
