<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72987</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Congenital myotonic dystrophy. Clinical, electrophysiological and genetic findings of our casuistry</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Congenital myotonic dystrophyis an autosomal dominant inherited generally transmittedmultisystemic disease that is generally inherited through themother. It is characterized by the birth the newborn babywith hypotonia, respiratory and nutritional problems, and facialand general weakness.Objective. Descriptive study of our experience in congenitalmyotonic dystrophy.Patients and methods. Twelve patients with congenital myotonicdystrophy, belonging to 9 families in which the motherwas a carrier of the disease have been studied. The clinical,electromyographic and genetic characteristics of their familieswere analyzed.Results. Motor retardation as well as the intellectual retardation,dysarthria and nasal voice was clear in all the patients.The affected children had more than 1,500 repetitions of thecytosine-thymine-guanine (CTG) trinucleotide on chromosome19 determined by the Southern Blot technique. Myopathictype alterations were found in the electromyographsof all of the subjects. The muscular biopsy done in 8 patientsshowed atrophy and predominance of type 1 fibers with centralnuclei and type 2 fiber hypertrophy.Conclusion. Myotonic dystrophy should be suspected incases of newborn babies with hypotonia, in mothers with abackground of abortions or stillborn babies. After survivingthe first years of life, their development is similar to the myotonicdystrophy of the adult. It is fundamental to perform agenetic study in those who are affected by or carriers of thedisease(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ibarra-Lúzar, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estévez-Poy, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Zorrilla, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villelabeitia-Jaureguizar, K</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-García, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cutillas-Ruiz, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La distrofia miotónica congénitaes una enfermedad multisistémica de herencia autosómicadominante, heredada generalmente a través de la madre, yque se caracteriza porque al nacimiento, el recién nacido presentahipotonía, problemas respiratorios y alimenticios, debilidadfacial y general.Objetivos. Estudio descriptivo de nuestra experiencia en ladistrofia miotónica congénita.Pacientes y métodos. Se estudiaron 12 pacientes con distrofiamiotónica congénita, pertenecientes a 9 familias donde lasmadres eran portadoras de la enfermedad, y se analizaron lascaracterísticas clínicas, electromiográficas y genéticas.Resultados. El retraso motor era manifiesto en todos lospacientes, así como el retraso intelectual, la disartria y la voznasal. Los niños afectados presentaban más de 1.500 repeticionesdel trinucleótido citosina-timina-guanina del cromosoma19 determinadas por la técnica de Southern Blot. Lasalteraciones electromiográficas de tipo miopático estabanpresentes en todos ellos. La biopsia muscular realizada a8 pacientes mostraba atrofia y predominio de fibras tipo1 con núcleos centrales e hipertrofia de fibras tipo 2.Conclusión. Es necesario sospechar la distrofia miotónicaante casos de recién nacidos con hipotonía, en madres conhistoria de abortos o recién nacidos muertos. Una vez superadoslos primeros años de vida, su desarrollo es similar al dela distrofia miotónica del adulto. Es fundamental realizar elestudio genético a los afectados y portadores de esta enfermedad(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);43(4): 144-150, jul.-ago.2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72987</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Distrofia miotónica congénita. Hallazgos clínicos, electrofisiológicos y genéticos de nuestra casuística</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2587^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34194^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34194^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34194^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2587^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34196^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2587^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9414^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4667^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9414^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9414^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34196^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9414^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9414^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
