<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166046</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sister Mary Joseph's nodule and diffuse large B-cell lymphoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A 38-year-old patient presented with abdominal distention, anorexia and a weight loss of 7kg over the previous two months. Physical examination revealed a solid abdominal mass and a 3cm umbilical nodule. He had raised lactate dehydrogenase and beta-2 microglobulin levels, as well as hypogammaglobulinemia. An abdominal CT showed a solid retroperitoneal mass invading the left kidney and displacing the aorta, splenomegaly and an umbilical nodule. Histopathology revealed a diffuse large b cell lymphoma germinal center type. Umbilical metastases, also known as Sister Mary Joseph's nodule, are uncommon and usually associated with disseminated gastrointestinal and gynecological malignancies; indeed only a few cases of lymphomas with this presentation have been reported, most of which have a much better prognosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Hernández, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña-Montelongo, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Martínez, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Reimers, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Arnay, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se describe el caso de un varón de 38 años que consultó por distensión abdominal, saciedad precoz y pérdida de 7kg de peso de 2 meses de evolución. Presentaba una masa pétrea abdominal y una tumoración umbilical de 3cm que había aumentado de tamaño en las semanas previas. En la analítica destacaba elevación de lactato deshidrogenasa y beta-2 microglobulina, así como hipogammaglobulinemia. Se realizó una tomografía computarizada abdominal, en la cual se observó un gran tumor retroperitoneal que englobaba el riñón izquierdo y desplazaba la aorta, esplenomegalia, afectación peritoneal, adenopatías mesentéricas y un nódulo umbilical. El diagnóstico anatomopatológico fue de linfoma no Hodgkin de células grandes B inmunofenotipo centro germinal (según algoritmo de Hans). Las metástasis umbilicales, también denominadas «nódulo de la hermana María José», son infrecuentes, generalmente asociadas a neoplasias gastrointestinales y ginecológicas diseminadas. Solo se han descrito unos pocos casos en linfomas, asociados en general a mejor pronóstico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;50(4): 268-272, oct.-dic. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166046</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nódulo de la hermana María José y linfoma difuso de células grandes B</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29271^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14871^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10530^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19237^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12603^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19237^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53942^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29271^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29271^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38793^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
