<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80640</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adherence to Mediterranean Diet in restaurants in Gran Canaria: AMED Project in the Canary Islands</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To evaluate adherente to the Mediterranean diet on restaurant menus on the island of Gran Canaria (Spain) and observe the relationship between the various ingredients of the same in preparing dishes. Design: We conducted a survey of thirteen questions (the questionnaire AMED-Mediterranean Food), which contains the main ingredients that make up the Mediterranean Diet (olive oil, vegetables, fruits, etc.) in order to categorize the restaurant and monitoring the Mediterranean Diet. Setting: 101 restaurant from the island of Gran Canaria (mainly from Las Palmas de Gran Canaria, Telde and Southeastern Area) that offer a menu for working days composed at least by two first dishes, two main courses and dessert. Results: More than half of the restaurants are average followers of the Mediterranean diet, being good just 22% of them. There was a relationship between the use of olive oil for cooking the meals and the offer of whole grain products (bread, pasta or rice) in restaurants (p=0028), without a linear relationship between them. Conclusion: The restaurants of Gran Canaria (54%) are mostly average followers of the Mediterranean Diet, with a 22% of good supporters(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Sánchez, Rubén D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fulgencio González, Adexe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serra Majem, Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero Martel, Jonathan R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la adherencia a la dieta mediterránea en los menús de los restaurantes de la isla de Gran Canaria (España) y observar la relación entre los diferentes ingredientes de la misma en la elaboración de platos. Diseño: Se realizó un estudio descriptivo mediante una encuesta de trece preguntas (encuesta del grupo AMED -Alimentación Mediterránea-), donde se recogen los principales ingredientes que conforman la Dieta Mediterránea (aceite de oliva, verduras, hortalizas, etc.); con el fin de categorizar a los restaurantes según su seguimiento de dicha dieta, según el baremo diseñado. Muestra: 101 restaurantes de la isla de Gran Canaria (principalmente de Las Palmas de Gran Canaria, Telde y Mancomunidad del Sureste) que ofertan en días laborales menús consistentes en dos primeros platos, dos segundos platos y postre. Resultados: Más de la mitad de los restaurantes son regulares seguidores de la dieta mediterránea, siendo buenos apenas un 22% de los mismos. Existe relación entre el mayor empleo de aceite de oliva para cocinar las preparaciones culinarias y la mayor oferta de productos integrales (pan, pasta o arroz) en los restaurantes (p = 0,028) no encontrándose relación lineal entre las mismas. Conclusión: Los restaurantes de Gran Canaria son mayoritariamente (54%) regulares seguidores de la Dieta Mediterránea, existiendo un 22% de buenos seguidores(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;15(2): 89-96, abr.-jun.2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80640</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguimiento de la dieta mediterránea en los restaurantes de Gran Canaria: el Proyecto AMED en Canarias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32738</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12567</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37653</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
