<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043396</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Differences in variables representatives of cardiovascular disease or repercussion between subjects with high cardiovascular risk with and without any family history of early cardiovascular events</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction, bases and aims: Study the possible associations between any family history of early heart disease and variables expressive of heart disease, lesion or repercussion in subjects of high cardiovascular risk. Material and methods: Nationwide cross-sectional study with 2264 consecutive patients in the Outpatient Clinic of Internal Medicine 18 years of age or older and with high or extremely high cardiovascular risk taken from the CIFARC (Integral Control of High Risk Cardiovascular Factors) study run by the SEMI (Spanish Internal Medicine Association) cardiovascular Risk Group. We have studied the relationship between the presence or lack of same in family histories of early heart disease (AFP &#150; Family History of early heart disease, hereinafter FH) and different variables in the factors concerning cardiovascular risk and target organ lesion. The statistical treatment (Chi-2, ANOVA and Pearson&#146;s linear regression) was performed using the STATISTIX programme. Results and discussion: We observed a significative increase (p  250 mg/dl, HDL  130 mg/dl, LVH (left ventricular hypertrophy), creatinine 1.2-2mg/dl, retinopathy I-II, serious retinopathy, smoking, proteinuria &gt; 300 mg/dl, kidney insufficiency and peripheral vascular disease. This significative increase in the variables under study appeared in males of over 55 years of age and in females of over 65 years of age; nevertheless, this increase in the incidence rate is becoming more common as of age 50 in males, with a maximum in both sexes after the age of 70. No significative differences were noted with regard to sex, BMI (Body Mass Index), atheromatosis, ischemic cardiopathy and cerebrovascular disease. On the whole, subjects of both sexes of the FH group have come to the clinic 3 years earlier than those of the group without FH. Conclusions: Patients with FH show a greater incidence of certain factors concerning heart risk and target organ lesion</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fuentes Solsona, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Portoles Suso, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuende Melero, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ebrí Torné, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ebrí Verde, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Conesa, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción, fundamentos y objetivos: Estudiar las posibles asociaciones entre antecedentes familiares precoces (AFP) de enfermedad cardiovascular y variables expresivas de enfermedad, lesión o repercusión cardiovascular en los sujetos de alto riesgo cardiovascular. Material y métodos: Estudio transversal de ámbito nacional con 2.264 pacientes consecutivos de las Consultas Externas de Medicina Interna, mayores de 18 años y con riesgo cardiovascular alto o muy alto, procedentes del Estudio CIFARC del Grupo de Riesgo Vascular de la SEMI. Se estudia la relación entre la presencia o no de antecedentes familiares de enfermedad cardiovascular precoz (AFP) y distintas variables de factores de riesgo cardiovascular y lesión de órgano diana. El tratamiento estadístico (Chi cuadrado, ANOVA y regresión líneal de Pearson) se ha realizado mediante el programa STATISTIX. Resultados y discusión: Observamos un incremento significativo (p  250 mg/dl, HDL  130 mg/dl, HVI (hipertrofia ventricular izquierda), creatinina 1,2-2 mg/dl, retinopatía I-II, retinopatía grave, tabaquismo, proteinuria &gt; 300 mg/dl, Insuficiencia renal y enfermedad vascular periférica. Este incremento significativo de las variables estudiadas se produce en varones de más de 55 años y en mujeres de más de 65 años; no obstante comienza a observarse este aumento del porcentaje de incidencia a partir de los 50 años en varones, con un máximo en ambos sexos tras los setenta. No se observan diferencias significativas respecto a sexo, IMC (índice de masa corporal) ateromatosis, cardiopatía isquémica y enfermedad cerebrovascular. Existe en general en ambos sexos un adelanto de tres años en el grupo de AFP en acudir a la consulta médica respecto al grupo que no posee AFP. Conclusiones: Los pacientes con AFP presentan mayor incidencia de ciertos factores de riesgo cardiovascular y de lesión de órgano diana</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;23(1): 11-18, ene. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043396</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias en variables representativas de enfermedad o repercusión cardiovascular entre sujetos de alto riesgo cardiovascular con y sin antecedentes familiares de eventos cardiovasculares precoces</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
