<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143826</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">High prevalence of inactivity among young patients with type 1 diabetes in south Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To describe usual physical activity level and analyze its association with metabolic control and presence of microvascular complications in a cohort of patients with type 1 diabetes (DM-1) in south Spain. Methods: Observational, cross-sectional study that included one hundred thirty patients, aged 33.9 ± 11.5 years-old with disease duration of 16.5 ± 9.5 years that consecutively were recruited among patients attending the Endocrinology Service of Puerta del Mar University Hospital (Cádiz, Spain). Usual physical activity level was assessed using the «General Practice Physical Activity Questionnaire» (GPPAQ) together with clinical, anthropometric, metabolic parameters and microvascular complications. Results: DM-1 patients were grouped in four categories of physical activity level: inactive (n = 33; 25.3%), moderately inactive (n = 31; 23.8%), moderately active (n = 26; 20.0%) and active (n = 40; 30.9%). We observed no significant differences in glycated haemoglobin (HbA1c) level between the different physical activity groups analyzed. Patients classified as moderately active and active were more often men, significantly younger and presented lower plasmatic levels of triglycerides than patients classified as inactive or moderately inactive, with no differences in other clinical or anthropometric variables. In addition, active and moderately active patients had a lower prevalence of diabetic retinopathy and microvascular complications in general compared to inactive or moderately inactive patients. Conclusions: Half of patients with type 1 diabetes evaluated were classified as inactive and these patients had a higher prevalence of diabetic retinopathy than active patients. No difference in HbA1c levels was documented among different groups of physical activity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Carmona, Soledad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar Diosdado, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Manzanedo, José Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carral San Laureano, Florentino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayala Ortega, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Domínguez, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Describir el nivel de actividad física habitual y analizar su asociación con el control metabólico y la presencia de complicaciones microvasculares en una cohorte de pacientes con diabetes tipo 1 (DM-1) del sur de España. Métodos: Estudio transversal observacional que incluyó ciento treinta pacientes de 33,9 ± 11,5 años de edad y una duración de la enfermedad de 16,5 ± 9,5 años que fueron reclutados consecutivamente en el Servicio de Endocrinología del Hospital Universitario Puerta del Mar (Cádiz, España). El nivel de actividad física habitual fue evaluado utilizando el «General Practice Physical Activity Questionnaire» (GPPAQ) conjuntamente con diversos parámetros clínicos, antropométricos, metabólicos y de complicaciones microvasculares. Resultados: Los pacientes con DM-1 fueron agrupados en cuatro categorías de nivel de actividad física: inactivo (n = 33; 25,3%), moderadamente inactivo (n = 31; 23,8%), moderadamente activo (n = 26; 20,0%) y activo (n = 40; 30,9%). No observamos diferencias significativas en el nivel de hemoglobina glucosilada (HbA1c) entre los diferentes grupos de actividad física analizados. Los pacientes clasificados como moderadamente activos y activos fueron con mayor probabilidad hombres, más jóvenes y con menores niveles plasmáticos de triglicéridos que los pacientes clasificados como inactivos o moderadamente inactivos, sin encontrarse diferencias en otras variables clínicas o antropométricas. Adicionalmente, los pacientes activos y moderadamente activos tenían una menor prevalencia de retinopatía diabética y de complicaciones microvasculares en general comparados con los pacientes inactivos o moderadamente inactivos. Conclusiones: La mitad de los pacientes con DM-1 evaluados fueron clasificados como inactivos y estos pacientes tenían mayor prevalencia de retinopatía diabética que los pacientes activos. No fueron documentadas diferencias en los niveles de HbA1c entre los diferentes grupos de actividad física (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;29(4): 922-928, abr. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143826</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Elevada prevalencia de inactividad física en pacientes jóvenes con diabetes tipo 1 del sur de España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7124^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22190^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3954^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
