<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94321</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reading and writing in Fragile X Syndrome children: intervention strategies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Syndrome X fragile (SXF) is the most common cause of inherited intellectual disability. It&#146;s characterized by a very specific physical and behavioral phenotype. The SXF is caused by a mutation in the FMR1 gene located on chromosome X, locus Xq27.3. Gene mutation causes an abnormal number of repetitions of the triple CGG (cytosine-guanine-guanine). The SXF analysis represents a good model to determine the relationship between genes and behavior. The area of reading and writing in the fragile X population samples too many dark areas. The main problems of the SXF with reading and writing have their origin in disorders of language and motor difficulties and sensory integration. Our work aims to expand and systematize organically some aspects that we consider fundamental for improving educational practice and restore reading deficiencies. In this line of action we highlight both methodological strategies and programmed proposals which should be explored to learn about their educational value and practical effectiveness (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Puente-Ferreras, Aníbal</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Lozano, M. Paz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrando-Lucas, M. Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome X frágil (SXF) es la causa más frecuente de discapacidad intelectual hereditaria. Se caracteriza por un fenotipo físico y conductual muy específicos. El SXF está causado por una mutación del gen FMR1 situado en el cromosoma X, locus Xq27.3. La mutación del gen produce un número anómalo de repeticiones de la tripleta CGG (Citosina- Guanina- Guanina). El análisis del SXF representa un buen modelo para determinar las relaciones entre genes y conducta. El área de la lectura y la escritura en la población X frágil muestra demasiadas zonas oscuras. Los principales problemas de los SXF con la lectura y la escritura tienen su origen en alteraciones del lenguaje y en dificultades motoras y de integración sensorial. Nuestro trabajo pretende ampliar y sistematizar de manera orgánica algunos de los aspectos que consideramos fundamentales para mejorar la práctica educativa y la restauración de las deficiencias lectoras. En esta línea de actuación destacamos tanto estrategias metodológicas como propuestas programáticas que conviene explorar para conocer su valor pedagógico y su eficacia práctica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;27(3): 808-815, oct.-dic. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94321</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lectura y escritura en niños con síndrome x frágil: estrategias de intervención</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33552^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33552^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7986^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13448</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7984^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4589^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5735^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4473^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8037^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4589^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5735^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4473^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33552^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33552^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
