<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055136</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-7606</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Valoración médica de la sospecha de abuso. Medical evaluation of sexual abuse suspicion in children. Report of three cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The diagnostic, valuation and treatment of children    that could have been victims of any form of sexual abuse, is    an emergent health problem with important legal and social    implications. Because of the complexity and diversity of the    factors that can be related to this issue, its study has to be    done with the cooperation of a wide range of specialists,    professionals of different disciplines and also institutions    belonging to several sectors.    Through the revision of three different cases our aim    is to express the obstacles that can be created by the    diagnostic of sexual abuse in minors. Such a diagnostic is    established after a medical, psychological and social    process, always in a probabilistic rank, still this fact must    never create doubts about the diagnostic.    As a conclusion just to insist in the fact that not always    it is going to be possible to obtain certainty indicators, and    also that the medical impression will not always coincide    with the psychological or social one, as well as not always    it is necessary to have the permission of the Court to obtain    a response of the Public Administration</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Largo Blanco, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acosta Gordillo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Arrones, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ostos Serna, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero Trigo, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El diagnóstico, la valoración y el tratamiento de    menores que pueden haber sido víctimas de alguna forma    de abuso sexual, constituye un problema emergente de    salud que tiene implicaciones legales y sociales. Por la    complejidad y diversidad de los factores que intervienen,    su abordaje tiene que ser llevado a cabo con la colaboración    de diferentes especialistas, profesionales de distintas    disciplinas y por instituciones de varios sectores.    A través de la revisión de tres casos se pretende    expresar las dificultades que puede ofrecer el diagnóstico    de abuso sexual en personas menores de edad, que como    otros síndromes, se establece con un rango de probabilidad,    basado en un proceso de valoración médica, psicológica    y social; lo que no debe poner en cuestión el propio    diagnóstico del abuso.    Como conclusión fundamental se extrae que no    siempre es posible obtener indicadores de certeza, y que    no siempre coincidirán la valoración médica con la psicológica    o con la social, o que las actuaciones judiciales no    habrán de ser en todos los casos determinantes para que    la entidad pública pueda adoptar medidas de protección</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. med. forense;12(43/44): 57-74, ene.-abr. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055136</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">sexual en personas menores de edad. A propósito del estudio de tres casos. sexual en personas menores de edad. A propósito del estudio de tres casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12338^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8657^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11241^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24326^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19101^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2696^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2699^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
