<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044253</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Heterotopic ossification in critical patient. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The development of heterotopic ossification has been shown to be associated with musculoskeletal trauma, central nervous system injury and severe burns. Nevertheless, it is a very uncommon entity in patients who have suffered a critical illness. The severe functional impairment due to multiple heterotopic ossification demands in most of the cases surgical treatment to achieve an independent gait and activity. We report the case of a patient with heterotopic ossification in both hips and knees, which developed during a period of critical illness due to acute myeloid leukemia. We introduced physical therapy at a very early stage in order to avoid contracture flexions and ankylosis. This strategy not only has allowed the patient to avoid surgery but also to obtain independency for gait and daily activities</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Chinchetru, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales-Palacios, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valverde-Carrillo, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las osificaciones heterotópicas son complicaciones bien conocidas en pacientes que han sufrido traumatismos musculoesqueléticos, lesiones del sistema nervioso central y quemaduras severas. Sin embargo, constituyen una entidad poco frecuente en pacientes que han estado sometidos a una situación crítica. La importante afectación funcional que producen las osificaciones heterotópicas, habitualmente de localización múltiple en estos enfermos, hace necesario la mayoría de las veces un tratamiento quirúrgico para lograr una marcha y una actividad independientes. Presentamos el caso de una paciente sometida a situación crítica por leucemia mieloide aguda que desarrolló osificaciones heterotópicas en ambas caderas y rodillas. El diagnóstico y la instauración de un tratamiento rehabilitador precoz previno el desarrollo de rigideces y anquilosis. Esta actitud ha permitido evitar la cirugía y ha proporcionado a la paciente una marcha y una actividad independientes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);40(2): 107-110, mar. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044253</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Osificaciones heterotópicas en el paciente crítico: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29507</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30417^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30396^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23731^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30396^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30396^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27938^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28145^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
