<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135555</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical and neuroimaging characteristics of 14 patients with prionopathy: A descriptive study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Prionopathy is the cause of 62% of the rapidly progressive dementias (RPD) in which a definitive diagnosis is reached. The variability of symptoms and signs exhibited by the patients, as well as its different presentation, sometimes makes an early diagnosis difficult. Methods: Patients withdiagnosis of definite or probable prionopathy during the period 1999-2012 at our hospital were retrospectively reviewed.The clinical features and the results of the complementary tests (14-3-3 protein, EEG, MRI, FDG-PET, and genetic analysis) were evaluated in order to identify some factors that may enable an earlier diagnosis to be made. Results: A total of 14 patients are described: 6 with definite sporadic Creutzfeldt-Jakob (sCJD) disease, 3 with probable sCJD, 4 with fatal familial insomnia, and 1 with the new variant. The median age at diagnosis was 54 years old. The mean survival was 9.5 months. Mood disorder was the most common feature, followed by instability and cognitive impairment. 14-3-3 protein content in the cerebrospinal fluid was positive in 7 of 11 patients, and the EEG showed typical signs in 2 of 12 patients. Neuroimaging (FDG-PET, MRI) studies suggested the diagnosis in 13 of the 14 patients included. Conclusions: Most patients presenting with RPD suffer from a prion disease. In our series the most useful complementary tests were MRI and FDG-PET, being positive in 13 of the 14 patients studied (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Luquin, M. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arbizu, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega-Cubero, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastor, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gállego Pérez-Larraya, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Vila, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pagola, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Irimia, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro, P de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riverol, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viteri, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las prionopatías representan hasta el 62% de los casos de demencia rápidamente progresiva (DRP) en los que se alcanza un diagnóstico definitivo. La variabilidad de los síntomas y signos iniciales y las diferencias en su evolución dificultan el diagnóstico precoz. Métodos: Estudio retrospectivo en el que se incluye a pacientes con prionopatía probable o definitiva, que acudieron a la consulta de Neurología de nuestro centro durante el periodo 1999-2012. Se describen las características clínicas y los resultados de las exploraciones complementarias (proteína 14-3-3, EEG, RM, PET-FDG y análisis genético), con la finalidad de identificar qué marcadores permiten un diagnóstico precoz. Resultados: Se describe a 14 pacientes: 6 con enfermedad de Creutzfeldt-Jakob esporádica (ECJe) definitiva, 3 con ECJe probable, 4 con insomnio familiar fatal y uno con la nueva variante de la enfermedad de Creutzfeldt-Jakob. La mediana de edad al diagnóstico fue de 54 años y la mediana de supervivencia de 9,5 meses. El trastorno del ánimo fue el síntoma inicial más frecuente, seguido de inestabilidad de la marcha y deterioro cognitivo. La proteína 14-3-3 fue positiva en el líquido cefalorraquídeo en 7 de 11 pacientes y el EEG mostró signos típicos en 2 de 12 pacientes explorados. El estudio de neuroimagen mostró alteraciones en 13 de los 14 pacientes. Conclusiones: Además de la DRP, el trastorno conductual y de la marcha son síntomas iniciales frecuentes en las prionopatías. En nuestra serie, las pruebas complementarias más útiles para apoyar el diagnóstico fueron la RM y la PET-FDG (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;30(3): 144-152, abr. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135555</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Descripción de una serie de pacientes con diagnóstico de enfermedad priónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54668^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5865^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54668^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5865^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
