<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047332</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Family practice and diagnosis of cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To describe the types of cancer identified in primary health care, their clinical presentation, management until diagnosis and delay in diagnosis. Design. Descriptive study based on secondary information from medical records. Setting. Two urban health care centres in Mallorca, Spain. Participants. Patients over 14 years old diagnosed with cancer between 1994 and 1998. Measurements. Age, sex, location of tumour, symptoms, role of family doctor, specialist referral, care environment, time from first symptom to diagnosis, and stage of tumour. Results. We identified 408 cancers. Mean age at diagnosis was 66.5 years (95% CI, 65.3-67.7); 237 (58.1%) were male. The most frequent tumours were colorectal, lung, prostate, breast and bladder, and the most common symptom was pain (33.1%; 95% CI, 28-38.3). The family doctor was involved in 63% of diagnoses (95% CI, 58.2-67.8). Mean delay from first symptom until diagnosis was 90 days, of which 26 were attributed to the patient and 55 to primary health care services. For colorectal, lung and prostate cancers, delay was shorter. The tumour was less advanced at diagnosis when family doctors were involved. Conclusions. Family doctors are involved in the diagnosis of most cancers. In colorectal, lung and prostate cancers, their contribution could improve prognosis. More studies are needed to confirm these findings</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llobera-Cánaves, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos-Monserrat, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Torrejón, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Describir los tipos de cáncer identificados en atención primaria, su forma de presentación clínica, el proceso asistencial seguido hasta su diagnóstico y los tiempos de demora diagnóstica. Diseño. Estudio descriptivo basado en la recogida de información secundaria a partir de la historia clínica. Emplazamiento. Dos centros de salud urbanos de Mallorca. Participantes. Cánceres diagnosticados, entre 1994 y 1998, en usuarios mayores de 14 años. Mediciones. Edad, sexo, localización, desencadenantes, intervención del médico de familia, tipo de derivación, ámbito de actuación, intervalos de tiempo desde el inicio de síntomas hasta el diagnóstico y estadio. Resultados. Se identificaron 408 cánceres. La media de edad en el momento del diagnóstico fue de 66,5 años (intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 65,3-67,7), 237 (58,1%) en varones. Los más frecuentes fueron colorrectal, pulmón, próstata, mama y vejiga. El síntoma más frecuente fue el dolor, que se presenta en el 33,1% (IC del 95%, 28-38,3). El médico de familia intervino en el 63,0% (IC del 95%, 58,2-7,8). La demora total fue de 90 días de mediana, mientras que en atención primaria fue de 55 días y la debida al paciente de 26 días. En los casos en que intervino el médico de familia, la demora fue menor y se llegó al diagnóstico en estadios más precoces para el cáncer colorrectal, de pulmón y de próstata, pero no en el resto de las localizaciones. Conclusiones. El médico de AP interviene en el diagnóstico de la mayoría de los cánceres. Su intervención podría mejorar el pronóstico en el cáncer colorrectal, de pulmón y de próstata. Deben realizarse estudios que confirmen estos hallazgos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;37(1): 16-21, ene. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047332</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El médico de atención primaria y el diagnóstico de los pacientes con cáncer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
