<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058244</identifier>
<setSpec>0301-0546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hypersensitivity to Vespula and Polistes: can we tell the primary sensitization from the clinical history?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To study the relationship between theprimary sensitization to wasp venoms and the geographicaland seasonal circumstances of the anaphylaxis-induced sting.Methods: We performed a retrospective review of115 patients (age 10-80) who suffered a systemicreaction to a wasp sting. Season and type of locality(urban or rural) at the moment of the sting wererecorded. Serum specific IgE levels to venoms fromVespula and Polistes were measured, and a primarysensitization was determined to whichever genus ofwasp for which the highest class of specific IgE wasobserved. The primary sensitization in relation to thetype of locality and the season was assessed usingthe chi-square test.Results: Most reactions occurred in urban areas(67.8 %), and in the summer season (63.4 %). Mostpatients were sensitized to Vespula venom (94.8 %).Primary sensitization was to Vespula in 56.5 %, toPolistes in 10.4 %, and undetermined in 33 %. Thedistribution of geographical areas did not show significantdifferences in relation to primary sensitization(p &gt; 0.05). Most patients with primary sensitization toVespula suffered the anaphylaxis-induced sting afterthe spring season, with a statistically significant result(p &lt; 0.05).Conclusion: In our population, the probability ofVespula sting is higher than Polistes sting when thereaction occurs after spring. This finding can help usto identify the responsible vespid when the diagnostictests do not provide an accurate result</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Pimiento, AJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Cubero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto Lastra, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vásquez Bautista, AA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo Manuel, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Cabreros, MI</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">No disponible</dc:description>
<dc:source>Allergol Immunopathol (Madr);35(6): 225-227, nov. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058244</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hipersensibilidad a vespula y polistes: ¿se puede determinar la sensibilización predominante a partir de la historia clínica?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15264^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15264^s22025</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11472^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7145^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7145^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11472^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15264^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d721^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d488^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d721^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
