<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126711</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-8831</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Methemoglobinemia due to topical absorption of anilines</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Acquired methemoglobinemia, a rare cause of cyanosis in children, is due to the exposure of hemoglobin to oxidizing agents such as nitrites, which are found in some vegetables, local anesthetics, and other drugs. Methemoglobin is an oxidized form of hemoglobin with decreased affinity for oxygen, which leads to decreased delivery of oxygen to tissues and resulting hypoxia. Clinical case. We report the case of a 3-year old child with two episodes of methemoglobinemia secondary to topical absorption of anilines. Comments. Anilines are organic compounds that are used for making synthetic paints and industrial dyes. If consumed, inhaled, or absorbed through the skin, they are toxic and may cause methemoglobinemia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Àngel Solà, Judith</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias Constantí, Vanessa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luaces Cubells, Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido Romero, Roser</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Santanach, David</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La metahemoglobinemia adquirida es una causa de cianosis poco frecuente en la edad pediátrica, causada por la exposición de la hemoglobina a agentes oxidantes, como los nitritos resentes en algunas verduras, anestésicos tópicos y otros fármacos. La metahemoglobinemia produce una disminución de la cesión de oxigeno a los tejidos y, como consecuencia, síntomas derivados de la hipoxia tisular. Caso clínico. Se expone el caso clínico de una paciente de 3 años que presentó dos episodios de metahemoglobinemia secundaria a la absorción tópica de anilinas con las que se habían teñido sus zapatos. Comentarios. La anilina es un compuesto orgánico que se utiliza para fabricar pinturas sintéticas y colorantes industriales. La anilina puede ser tóxica si se ingiere, inhala o si se absorbe por vía cutánea, pudiendo provocar una metahemoglobinemia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. catalan;74(2): 82-84, abr.-jun. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126711</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Metahemoglobinemia secundaria a absoricón tópica de anilinas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3510^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d829^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29916^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35506</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3510^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8885^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d874</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8885^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8885^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8885^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
