<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106273</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Body composition related with health in veteran athletes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze the corporal composition of veteran athletes of resistance and his relation with the health and quality of life. Methodology: It is a question of a descriptive and transverse study with a sample of 91 males (44.1 ± 6.9 years) and 16 women (41.4 ± 5.5 years) healthy medical instructors of career of resistance. For the analysis of the corporal composition there has been used an eight-electrode impedance meter (Inbody 720). The health and quality of life was analyzed by means of the scale SF-36, Spanish version. There were registered the values of athletic practice as for number of weekly meetings and duration of the session. Results: The IMC, the abdominal fat and the percentage of fat place in healthy values, for below even of the normative values. Significant differences do not exist in any parameter of the corporal composition in relation with the number of weekly meetings of athletic practice. A negative correlation exists between the percentage of fat and the social function of the scale SF-36. The health and quality of life perceived of the veteran athletes presents superior values to the Spanish modals normative. Conclusion: The practice of four weekly meetings of 60 minutes of career of resistance allows to keep healthy parameters of composition corporal in spite of the age (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Latorre Román, PA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salas Sánchez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soto Hermoso, VM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar la composición corporal de atletas de resistencia veteranos y su relación con la salud y calidad de vida. Metodología: Se trata de un estudio descriptivo y transversal con una muestra de 91 varones (Edad: 44,1 ± 6,9 años) y 16 mujeres (Edad: 41,4 ± 5,5 años) sanos practicantes de carrera de resistencia. Para el análisis de la composición corporal se ha empleado un impedianciómetro táctil multifrecuencia de 8 electrodos (Inbody 720). La salud y calidad de vida se analizó mediante la escala Healthy Survey Short Form 36 (SF-36), versión española. Se registraron los valores de práctica atlètica en cuanto a número de sesiones semanales y duración de la sesión. Resultados: El IMC, la grasa abdominal y el porcentaje de grasa se sitúan en valores saludables, por debajo incluso de los valores normativos. No existen diferencias significativas en ningún parámetro de la composición corporal en relación con el número de sesiones semanales de práctica atlètica. Existe una correlación negativa entre el porcentaje de grasa y la función social de la escala SF-36. La salud y calidad de vida percibida de los atletas veteranos presenta valores superiores a los referentes normativos españoles. Conclusiones: La práctica de cuatro sesiones semanales de 60 minutos de carrera de resistencia permite mantener parámetros de composición corporal saludables pese a la edad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;27(4): 1236-1243, jul.-ago. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106273</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Composición corporal relacionada con la salud en atletas veteranos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
