<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106428</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sense of coherence of nurses and the SOC-13 questionnaire</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to validate the SOC-13 questionnaire (Sense of Coherence13) in nursing professionals of Primary Health Care. Materials and methods: descriptive and cross-sectional study in 83nursing professionals from the four basic of Gerona (Spain) conducted between 2009 and 2010. The SOC-13 questionnaire was administered, on which an exploratory factor analysis (EFA) was performed, as well as an analysis of internal consistency for the entire questionnaire and for each of the factors of the proposed model. Results: the final sample included 55 professionals, mean age 48,4 years(standard deviation-SD-: 9.8), 25,6 mean years in the profession, mostly married women. SOC mean score was 67,4 (SD 8,6). In the EFA, Kaiser-Meyer-Oklin statistics was &gt; 0,5, approaching a medium adjustment, and Bartlett's test of sphericity was significant (p &lt;,001). Factor analysis pointed to three theoretical domains that author defined and estimated acceptable factor loadings for the items. Conclusions: SOC score was high and moderately higher compared to other international studies conducted in the nursing profession. TheSOC-13 questionnaire is valid to measure the sense of coherence of Spanish nursing professionals (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Juvinyà Canal, Dolors</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Malagón Aguilera, M. Carmené</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bertran Nogué, Carme</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bosch Farré, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonmatí Tomàs, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suñer Soler, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Peña, Roser</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: validar el cuestionario SOC-13 (sense of coherence 13) en los profesionales de Enfermería de la Atención Primaria de Salud. Material y método: estudio descriptivo y transversal en 83 profesionales enfermeros de las cuatro áreas básicas de salud de Gerona (España) realizado entre 2009 y 2010. Se aplicó el cuestionario SOC-13, sobre el que se realizó un análisis factorial exploratorio (AFE), así como un análisis de consistencia interna, para el cuestionario total y para cada uno de los factores del modelo propuesto. Resultados: la muestra final incluyó 55 profesionales, edad media de48,4 años (desviación estándar -DE-: 9,8), media de años de profesión de 25,6, en su mayoría mujeres casadas. La puntuación media del SOC fue de 67,4 (DE: 8,6). En el AFE, el estadístico Kaiser-Meyer-Oklin fue&gt; 0,5, aproximándose a un ajuste medio; y la prueba de esferidad de Bartlett resultó significativa (p &lt; ,001). El análisis factorial apuntó hacia los tres dominios teóricos que el autor definió y estimó unas cargas factoriales aceptables para los ítems. Conclusiones: la puntuación de SOC ha sido moderadamente alta y más elevada respecto a otros estudios internacionales realizados en el colectivo enfermero. El cuestionario SOC-13 es válido para medir el sentido de la coherencia de los profesionales enfermeros españoles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;15(9): 27-31, nov. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106428</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sentido de coherencia de las enfermerasy validación del cuestionario SOC-13</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3183^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54741</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9912^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201211</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
