<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94555</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">How does collective violence shape the health status of its victims? Conceptual model and design of the ISAVIC study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: Epidemiologic research on collective violence (violence exerted by and within groups in pursuit of political, social or economic goals) is very scarce despite its growing recognition as a major publichealth issue. This paper describes the conceptual model and design of one of the first research studies conducted in Spain aiming to assess the impact of collective violence in the health status of its victims(study known as ISAVIC, based on its Spanish title Impacto en la SAlud de la VIolencia Colectiva).Methods: Starting with a comprehensive but non-systematic review of the literature, the authors describe the sequelae likely produced by collective violence and propose a conceptual model to explain the nature of the relationships between collective violence and health status. The conceptual model informed the ISAVIC study design and its measurement instruments.Results: The possible sequelae of collective violence, in the physical, emotional and social dimensions of health, are described. Also, the review distinguishes the likely impact in primary and secondary victims,as well as the interplay with the social environment. The mixed methodological design of the ISAVIC study supports the coherence of the conceptual model described. Conclusions: The ISAVIC study suggests that collective violence may affect the main dimensions of the health status of its victims, in intimate relation to the societal factors where it operates. It is necessary to validate these results with new studies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>equipo ISAVIC</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: La investigación epidemiológica de la violencia colectiva (con fines políticos, sociales o económicos)es muy incipiente a pesar de su creciente reconocimiento como un problema de salud pública.Este artículo describe el modelo conceptual y el diseño de una de las primeras investigaciones realizadas en España para medir el Impacto en la SAlud de la VIolencia Colectiva (estudio ISAVIC).Métodos: A partir de una amplia revisión no sistemática de la literatura se describe el alcance global de dicho impacto y se propone un marco teórico que describe la relación. La revisión identifica las posibles consecuencias de la violencia colectiva en las dimensiones física, emocional y social de la salud. El modelosirve de base para establecer el diseño del estudio y sus instrumentos de medida.Resultados: Se describe el conjunto de posibles secuelas producidas por la violencia colectiva y se propone un marco relacional y temporal. El modelo considera el efecto en víctimas primarias y secundarias, y surelación con el medio social. Se diseña un estudio empírico con una metodología mixta para estimar lamagnitud y la naturaleza de la posible afectación de la salud por la violencia colectiva. Conclusiones: El estudio ISAVIC señala la coherencia del modelo dise&#152;nado, apoyando que la violencia colectiva puede afectar a las principales dimensiones de la salud en relación con el marco social donde opera. Es necesario validar estos resultados con nuevos estudios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;25(3): 246-253, may. -jun. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94555</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Cómo influye la violencia colectiva en la salud?  Modelo conceptual y diseño del estudio ISAVIC</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10956^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8571</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
