<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046759</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Familiar case of granular dystrophy and oculocutaneous albinism</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Clinical case: A 35-year-old female patient with ;;blurred vision since childhood, for which no treatment ;;had been given, presented with poor visual ;;acuity. She had white skin and fair yellow hair. There ;;were several well circumscribed deposits in the ;;central and anterior corneal stroma, and iris transillumination ;;and foveal hypoplasia were evident. ;;The clinical diagnosis was oculo-cutaneous albinism ;;and granular corneal dystrophy. We found oculo- ;;cutaneous albinism in two brothers and granular ;;dystrophy in three brothers, the mother and a son. ;;Discussion: Corneal dystrophy is an autosomal ;;dominant disorder inherited independently of oculocutaneous ;;albinism, which is inherited as an autosomal ;;recessive condition. This is the first case ;;report of granular dystrophy concurrent with oculocutaneous ;;albinism</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Verduzco, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Niño-Pecina, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chin-Wong, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villanueva-Mendoza, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Valcárcel, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Paciente femenino de 35 años deedad con mala agudeza visual desde la infancia. Ala exploración se encontró baja agudeza visual, nistagmo,hipopigmentación de piel y cabello amarillento,córnea con depósitos blanquecinos en estromacentral y anterior, transiluminación de iris ehipoplasia foveal. Se diagnosticaron albinismo oculocutáneoy distrofia corneal granular. Se encontróalbinismo oculocutáneo en dos hermanos y distrofiagranular en tres hermanos, la madre y el hijo.Discusión: La distrofia corneal granular se transmitegenéticamente siguiendo un patrón autosómicodominante e independiente del albinismo oculocutáneo.Este es el primer caso publicado de presentaciónconcomitante de ambas entidades</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;81(5): 289-292, mayo 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046759</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asociación de albinismo oculocutáneo y distrofia granular en una familia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34303^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28243^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28852^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
