<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160426</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-7279</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Sexuality and its biological basis, human sexual response and its factors and phases, and sexual dysfunctions and their classification and assessment are reviewed. Sexual dysfunction related to substance abuse and especially to cannabis is described. An update on research about the use of cannabis and its effects on fertility and sexuality data is offered. The conclusions are threefold: cannabis has a number of adverse effects on male and female fertility and sexual arousal, pleasure and performance in both men and women, although it still lacks quality research in this area; there is a dichotomy between the subjectivity of the positive perception of the effects of this toxic in sexual function, and the reality that such effects are negative in empirical studies, ie, objective and physically demonstrable; and the latest experimental research suggests that cannabis use in adolescents may have long term effects on sexual behavior of adults and on sex related brain reactivity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romaguera Psiquiatra, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se revisan la sexualidad y sus bases biológicas, la respuesta sexual humana y sus factores y fases, y las disfunciones sexuales y su clasificación y evaluación, haciendo hincapié en las disfunciones sexuales relacionadas con las sustancias de abuso y especialmente con el cannabis. Se ofrecen datos actualizados sobre la investigación en torno al consumo de cannabis y sus efectos en la fertilidad y la sexualidad. Las conclusiones son tres: el consumo de cannabis tiene una serie de efectos adversos en la fertilidad masculina y femenina y en la excitación sexual, el placer y el rendimiento tanto en hombres como en mujeres, si bien aún se carece de investigación de calidad en esta área; existe una dicotomía entre la subjetividad de la percepción positiva de los efectos de este tóxico en la función sexual, y la realidad de que tales efectos resultan ser negativos en estudios empíricos, es decir, objetivos y físicamente demostrables; y la investigación experimental más reciente apunta a que el consumo de cannabis en adolescentes puede tener efectos a largo plazo en el comportamiento sexual de los adultos y en la reactividad cerebral relacionada con el sexo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Inf. psiquiátr;(226): 63-76, oct.-dic. 2016. graf, ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160426</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cannabis y sexualidad: mito y realidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13115^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5408^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
