<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86215</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-1375</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nursing knowledge as an instrument for the promotion of peritoneal dialysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Although it is proven that peritoneal dialysis, like haemodialysis, is an option for treating Terminal Chronic Renal Disease, it is used less. There has been considerable debate on the possible causes of its limited development in Spain, and it has been suggested that the lack of promotion of peritoneal dialysis may be due to the fact that both doctors and nurses have insufficient information or training on this treatment option. We set ourselves the aim of identifying the degree of knowledge that Nursing staff have of peritoneal dialysis, in order to take the necessary measures to promote this treatment and good practice. The sample was made up of a total of 66 nurses. To identify Nursing staff&#146;s degree of knowledge of peritoneal dialysis, a questionnaire was designed. As a result we found that only 57.6% knew how to change a bag and 30.3% recognized how to handle a cycler. More than 86.4% knew how to recognize the symptoms of infection at the insertion point and peritoneal infection, but 55% would not know how to act in response to the most frequent complications in peritoneal dialysis. We have found that the general degree of knowledge of peritoneal dialysis is limited. We think that this can influence the promotion of and good practice in peritoneal dialysis, although 69.2% think that the results of this type of treatment for a standard patient are equal to or better than with haemodialysis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cirera Segura, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jesús Lucas Martín Espejo, Jesús Lucas</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Si bien está probado que la diálisis peritoneal es una opción de tratamiento de la Enfermedad Renal Crónica Terminal al igual que la hemodiálisis, su uso es menor. Se ha debatido mucho sobre las posibles causas para su escaso desarrollo en España, apuntándose que la falta de impulso de la diálisis peritoneal puede deberse a que tanto médicos como Enfermería, no tengan la suficiente información o formación sobre esta opción de tratamiento. Como objetivo nos propusimos identificar el grado de conocimiento sobre la diálisis peritoneal que tiene el personal de Enfermería, con el fin de tomar las medidas necesarias para el fomento y la buena práctica de este tratamiento. La muestra estaba constituida por un total de 66 enfermeros. Para identificar el grado de conocimiento de Enfermería sobre la diálisis peritoneal, se diseñó un cuestionario. Como resultado obtuvimos que sólo el 57,6% sabía realizar un cambio de bolsa y un 30,3% reconocieron manejar una cicladora. Más del 86,4% sabían reconocer los síntomas de infección de la inserción y la infección peritoneal, pero un 55% no sabría actuar ante las complicaciones más frecuentes en diálisis peritoneal. Hemos podido comprobar que el grado de conocimiento general sobre la diálisis peritoneal es limitado. Pensamos que esto puede influir en el fomento y la buena práctica de la diálisis peritoneal, a pesar que el 69,2% piensan que los resultados de esta modalidad de tratamiento para un paciente estándar son iguales o mejores que con la hemodiálisis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Enferm. Nefrol;14(1): 7-13, ene.-mar. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86215</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los Conocimientos de Enfermería como Instrumento para el Fomento de la Diálisis Peritoneal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9926^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9926^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9926^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
