<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054738</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Heterogeneous topography of Foix-Chavany-Marie syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Bilateral facio-pharyngo-laryngo-glosso- masticatory palsy with automatic-voluntary dissociation is known as Foix-Chavany-Marie (FCM) syndrome. It is usually due to bilateral cortical lesions involving both anterior opercula (biopercular syndrome). We describe three patients with FCM syndrome associated with ischemic lesions in two atypical localizations: a) bilateral subcortical infarcts, and b) unilateral opercular infarct.    Cases report. Patient 1, a 66 year old male, was admitted for a sudden onset of anarthria and facial, lingual and masticatory paralysis. Neurological examination revealed automatic-voluntary dissociation of facial motility. MRI showed an acute left subcortical infarct and multiple bilateral subcortical ischemic lesions. Patient 2, a 61 year old male, also suffered a sudden onset of anarthria, with bilateral facial and lingual paralysis and automatic-voluntary dissociation together with sudden onset swallowing alteration. MRI showed a single ischemic lesion involving the left operculum. Patient 3, a 36 year old male, presented sudden onset of dysarthria, dysphagia and bilateral facial palsy with automatic-voluntary dissociation and loss of force in left upper limb. MRI showed an acute right opercular infarct and no contralateral lesions.        Conclusions. FCM syndrome is not only due to bilateral opercular lesions but can also be seen in bilateral subcortical and even unilateral opercular lesions</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cardona Portela, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moragas Garrido, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Yélamos, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio Borrego, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El síndrome de Foix-Chavany-Marie (FCM) fue descrito como una diplejía labio-facio-faringo-laringogloso- masticatoria con disociación automático-voluntaria del movimiento. Se correlaciona habitualmente con lesiones corticales bilaterales con afectación de ambos opérculos (síndrome biopercular). Describimos tres pacientes con síndrome de FCM asociado a lesiones isquémicas en dos topografías atípicas: a) subcortical bilateral, y b) opercular unilateral.    Casos clínicos. Paciente 1: varón de 66 años que consultó por paresia facial, lingual y faríngea bilaterales junto con anartria de inicio ictal. En la exploración destacaba la presencia de disociación automático-voluntaria de la motilidad facial. La resonancia magnética (RM) craneal mostró un infarto reciente subcortical izquierdo, así como múltiples lesiones isquémicas antiguas subcorticales contralaterales. Paciente 2: varón de 61 años, diabético, que consultó también por anartria y parálisis facial y lingual bilaterales con disociación automático-voluntaria junto con alteración de la deglución de inicio brusco. La RM craneal mostró la presencia de una única lesión isquémica opercular izquierda. Paciente 3: varón de 36 años que consultó por aparición brusca de disartria grave, disfagia, diplejía facial con disociación automático-voluntaria y pérdida de fuerza de la extremidad superior izquierda. La RM craneal mostró un infarto opercular derecho sin lesiones contralaterales.        Conclusiones. El síndrome de FCM no se asocia únicamente a lesiones operculares bilaterales, sino que además puede deberse a lesiones subcorticales bilaterales e incluso a lesiones corticales unilaterales</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;22(5): 333-336, jun. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054738</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Heterogeneidad topográfica del síndrome de Foix-Chavany-Marie</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27925^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2579^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5258^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2583^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2613^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
