<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102346</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1972</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Innovations in the flexible packing for sterilization</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Along this article a brief tour is done by the history of the packings of sterilization as well as a vision of what the imminent future promises. The appearance and the development of new materials like the polypropylene trilaminado open a new route for the attainment of the initial aim of any wrapper of sterilization: to be  a biological barrier, resistant to the break and compatiblly with all the available systems of sterilization (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Camón Álvarez, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A lo largo de este artículo se hace un breve recorrido por la historia de los envases de esterilización así como una visión de lo que el futuro inminente promete. La aparición y el desarrollo de nuevos materiales como el polipropileno trilaminado abren una nueva vía para la consecución del objetivo inicial de toda envoltura de esterilización: ser barrera biológica, resistente a la rotura y compatible con todos los sistemas de esterilización disponibles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Todo hosp;(269): 45-51, feb. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102346</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Novedades en el embalaje flexible para esterilización</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13904^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29758^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27987^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51538</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27840^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
