<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148298</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Are the new oral anticoagulants the same as vitamin K antagonists for acute lower limb ischaemia? A systematic review of the evidence</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: New oral anticoagulants (apixaban, dabigatran, and rivaroxaban) are alternatives to vitamin-K antagonist (VKA) for preventing embolic events in patients withauricular auricular fibrillation. So far, direct comparative studies between agents in prevention of acute limb ischaemia are unavailable. Material and methods: The present study shows the outcome from the 3 randomised clinical trials (RE-LY, ROCKET-AF, ARISTOTLE) regarding acute limb ischaemia risk prevention. Results: Novel oral anticoagulant therapies have shown a non-inferior efficacy compared with VKAs in lowering cerebrovascular ischaemic events and systemic embolism risk in several randomised clinical trials as well as in meta-analysis. Moreover, they have been shown to have a decreased complication rate in non-valvularauricular auricular fibrillation. Conclusions: There is no high quality evidence available on the effect of these treatments in preventing acute limb ischaemia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Varela, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bleda, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acin, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Haro, J de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañibano, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los nuevos anticoagulantes orales (dabigatran, ribaroxaban y apixaban) se presentan como alternativas a los antagonistas de la vitamina K (AVK) en la prevención de eventos embólicos en pacientes con fibrilación auricular (FA). No existen ensayos clínicos que comparen directamente estos fármacos para la prevención de la isquemia aguda (IA) de miembros inferiores. Material y métodos: Este estudio presenta los ensayos clínicos aleatorizados (RE-LY, ROCKET-AF, ARISTOTLE) que describen la capacidad de prevención de IA entre estos nuevos fármacos. Resultados: Los nuevos anticoagulantes orales han demostrado en diversos ensayos clínicos y metaanálisis una eficacia similar a los AVK en la prevención de accidente cerebrovascular y embolismo sistémico con un menor número de complicaciones en pacientes con FA no valvular. Conclusiones: Todavía no disponemos de evidencia de calidad sobre el efecto de estos fármacos para la prevención de la IA de miembros inferiores. Son necesarios futuros ensayos clínicos en esta dirección (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;68(2): 123-126, mar.-abr. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148298</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Son los nuevos anticoagulantes orales iguales a las antivitaminas K para la isquemia aguda de los miembros inferiores? Revisión sistemática de la evidencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7678^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15213^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15261^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36500^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15213^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
