<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104581</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Economic evaluation of hemodialysis. Analysis of cost components based on patient-specific data</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Hemodialysis (HD) cost analysis provides information about the economic impact of the disease on the community. Its knowledge is crucial to adequate and optimize health resources. Our aim was to study sanitary and non-sanitary direct costs of HD, based  on  patients  individual  data.  Furthermore,  the  effect  of sociocultural factors and comorbidity on costs will be evaluated. Material and methods:  Retrospective and observational study of prevalence costs produced during one year of HD therapy. All patients from North Health District of Tenerife province (Canary Islands,  Spain)  included  for  at  least  3  months  on  HD  were considered  for  the  study.  Sociodemographic  parameters  and comorbidity data were collected from a generic individual survey and reviewing database records. Direct sanitary and non-sanitary costs were organized in 6 categories: HD sesions, medicaction costs,  hospitalization  costs  (evaluated  by  Diagnosis-Related Groups   classification   system),   outpatient   care   (including consultation and complementary studies); sanitary material and patient  transportation.   Results: Finally,  161  patients  were included (63 ± 16 years, 63% males, 38% diabetics). Of note, the proportions  of  sociocultural  deprivation  was  high  among  this population (75-85% did not complete first school and had non- qualified jobs. Mean cost ot global therapy was 43,070 ± 13,932 &#128; . Proportional allocation of costs was as follow: HD sesion 51%, pharmacy  27%,  hospitalization  17%,  transportation  3% and  ambulatory  cares  2%.  It  was  not  association  between sociocultural profile, comorbidity and therapy cost.  Conclusions: This is the first study of HD costs, itemized by components of expenses, based in individual data and introducing GRD model for hospitalization cost. The highest expenses corresponded to HD sesions and medication (79%), both very homogeneous to this patient population. The saving in economic term should be, fundamentally, the prevention of CKD (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perestelo, l</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barroso, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nazco, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes:  El  conocimiento  del  coste  de  la  hemodiálisis (HD) proporciona información del impacto económico de la enfermedad sobre la comunidad. Dicho conocimiento es cru- cial para adecuar y optimizar la asignación de recursos. Nues- tro objetivo ha sido estudiar los costes sanitarios directos por- menorizados  de  la  HD.  Además,  analizamos  el  eventual impacto de los factores socioculturales y de comorbilidad so- bre los costes.  Material y métodos:  Estudio retrospectivo y ob- servacional durante un año de tratamiento con HD basado en datos  individuales  de  pacientes.  Se  incluyeron  todos  los  pa- cientes del Área Norte de Salud de la Provincia de Tenerife que durante el primer semestre de 2006 llevaran al menos 3 me- ses en HD. Se recogieron variables sociodemográficas y de co- morbilidad mediante una encuesta individual y revisión de ba- ses de datos. Los costes sanitarios fueron organizados en cinco categorías: sesiones de HD; consumo farmacéutico; hospitali- zaciones (evaluado por GRD, grupos relacionados por el diag- nóstico);  atención  ambulatoria  (incluyendo  exploraciones complementarias  y  uso  de  material  sanitario),  y  empleo  de transporte.  Resultados: La muestra final fue de 161 enfermos (63 ± 16 años, 63% hombres, 38% diabéticos). Destacó la ele- vada  deprivación  sociocultural  de  la  población:  75-85%  sin graduado escolar y/o trabajos no cualificados. El coste medio del tratamiento global fue de 43.234 ± 13.932  &#128; . La propor- ción  de  costes  fue:  sesiones  HD  51%,  gastos  farmacéuticos 27%, hospitalizaciones 17%, transporte 3% y atención ambu- latoria 2%. No se demostró una asociación relevante entre el perfil sociocultural o la comorbilidad y el coste del tratamien- to.  Conclusiones:  Es el primer estudio de coste de HD por com- ponentes de gasto, basado en datos individuales, e introdu- ciendo el modelo de GDR para los costes de hospitalización. La mayor partida de gastos correspondió a las sesiones de HD y medicación (78%), ambos factores son muy homogéneos en esta población, minimizando el impacto del perfil demográfi- co y de comorbilidad. El ahorro económico debe buscarse fun- damentalmente en la prevención (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;30(4): 403-412, jul.-ago. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104581</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación económica de la hemodiálisis. Análisis de los componentes del coste basado en datos individuales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30327^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7851^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6587^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30152^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
