<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111974</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Stress and Crohn&#146;s disease: differences among outbrake and quiescence patients and healthy persons</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Research has shown the relationship between stress and many diseases. The aim of this study is to investigate its effect on Crohn&#146;s disease. Using the Perceived Stress Scale we compared the stress levels of three different groups: 37 patients in the outbreak phase, 27 in quiescence, and 40 healthy controls. Results show that Crohn&#146;s sufferers in outbreak phase have higher stress levels than both quiescence patients and healthy persons. However, no significant differences were observed between those in quiescence and healthy persons.  The paper concludes by suggesting plausible explanations for these results, particularly that stress may be better understood as a consequence rather than a cause/precursor of Crohn&#146;s disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dios Duarte, María José de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias Astray, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Braschi, Diaferia, Lorenzo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrón López de Roda, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Distintas investigaciones han puesto de manifiesto la relación entre estrés y numerosas patologías. Este estudio pretende explorar su relación con la  enfermedad de Crohn. Se compararon los niveles de estrés, medidos mediante la escala de estrés percibido, de 37 pacientes en brote con 27 en fase de quiescencia y 40 personas sanas. De los resultados obtenidos parece derivarse que los enfermos de Crohn en fase de brote poseen mayores niveles de estrés que las personas sanas, además se constatan diferencias significativas en dicha variable entre enfermos de Crohn con brote y sin brote y enfermos de Crohn con brote y personas sanas. No se observan diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre enfermos de Crohn sin brote y personas sanas. El trabajo concluye planteando algunas explicaciones plausibles a dichos resultados y, en particular, que el estrés pueda entenderse más como una de las consecuencias que como uno de los antecedentes de la enfermedad de Crohn (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;18(2/3): 167-176, dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111974</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrés y enfermedad de Crohn: diferencias entre enfermos de Crohn con brote, sin brote y personas sanas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
