<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105222</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-9476</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">With the aim of knowing the environmental factors perceived as stressful by the patients in the operating theater of urology, a transversaldescriptive observable study was carried out in the patients surged from March to July 2010 that fulfill the criteria of inclusion. For theidentification of these factors the "Scale of Stressful Environments" of Ballard was used, and once the questionnaire was adapted to thisstudy, patients fill it in with Lickert scale in the immediate postsurgical period. The environmental factors perceived as more stressful,among others, were: having pain (53.84%), having the mobility limited by the surgical posture (35.89%) and to hear different noises(30.76%), and that&#146;s why to have a Welcoming Plan will allow us to eradicate behaviors perceived by patients as stressful, enabling a relaxingenvironment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blanco García, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varela Curto, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanjurjo Gómez, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varela López, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Con el objetivo de conocer los factores ambientales percibidos como estresantes por los pacientes en el quirófano de urología se realizóun estudio observacional descriptivo transversal en los pacientes operados de marzo a julio de 2010 que cumplían los criterios de inclusión.Para la identificación de estos factores se utilizó la «Escala de Estresores Ambientales» de Ballard, y una vez adaptado el cuestionario alpresente estudio, es cumplimentado a través de una escala Lickert por el paciente en el posoperatorio inmediato. Los factores ambientalespercibidos como más estresantes, entre otros, fueron: tener dolor (53,84%), tener limitada la movilidad por la postura quirúrgica (35,89%)y oír diferentes ruidos (30,76%), por lo que contar con un plan de acogida permitirá erradicar conductas percibidas como estresantespor el paciente, facilitando un entorno más relajado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>ENFURO: Rev. Asoc. Esp. A.T.S. Urol;(119): 9-12, jul.-sept. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105222</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores ambientales estresantes en el quirófanode urología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14970^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53693^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4858</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
