<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120414</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">ILSI Task Force on enteral nutrition; estimated composition and costs of blenderized diets</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Blenderized tube diets (BTD) are used in some parts of Brazil and few studies have analyzed their features in comparison with industrialized preparations. Among 14 randomly collected BTD recipes 9 were poorly described or failed to standardize foodstuffs and portions and, consequently, nutrient and energy composition was difficult to define. Only five BTD allowed theoretical estimation of their nutritional properties. Macronutrient content was highly variable, often conflicting with accepted daily recommendations. According to the literature there are further disadvantages with BTD use including diet high risk of contamination, physical and chemical instability, and high osmolarity and viscosity. Nominal cost of BTD was comparatively low in relation to industrialized formulas; however we did not compute labor and indirect expenses, probably rendering final value more expensive than with the industrialized alternative. It is likely that within such circumstances, hospital and home care malnutrition will not be adequately dealt with and related complications may occur. It is concluded that the continued use of blenderized tube feeding diets requires careful assessment, prioritizing correction of potencial nutritional deficits by means of safe, balanced, chemically complete and effective nutritional prescriptions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Araujo, Thalita Dutra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Souza, Telma Theodoro de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Linetzky Waitzberg, Dan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vieira, Roberta Ianni Airoldi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borghi, Roseli</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Dietas enterales artesanales (DEA) son utilizadas en algunas partes de Brasil y pocos estudios analizaron sus características en comparación con las preparaciones industrializadas. De un total de 14 DEA colectadas 9 estaban mal definidas o no establecían claramente los géneros alimenticios y porciones empleados, consecuentemente fue difícil calcular su composición en nutrientes y energia. Solo cinco DEA permitieron una estimativa teórica de sus propiedades nutricionales. El contenido de los macronutrientes era muy variable, y con frecuencia divergente de las recomendaciones diarias aceptas. De acuerdo con la literatura hay otros inconvenientes en el uso de DEA, o sea elevado riesgo de contaminación, inestabilidad físico-química, y alta osmolaridad y viscosidad de las DEA. El costo nominal de las dietas fue comparativamente bajo en relación a las formulaciones industrializadas, pero los gastos laborales y otros costos indirectos no fueron computados por nosotros, probablemente conduciendo a un valor total final superior al de la alternativa industrializada. Es esperado que en tales circunstancias la desnutrición no quedara bien tratada y complicaciones relacionadas podrán aparecer. La conclusión es que el empleo continuado de dietas artesanales requiere una evaluación criteriosa, con prioridad para la corrección de los déficits nutricionales utilizando prescripciones seguras, balanceadas quimicamente, completas y efectivas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;28(6): 2033-2038, nov.-dic. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120414</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Grupo de estudios ILSI sobre nutrición enteral; composición y costos estimados de dietas artesanales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5650^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24449^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30324^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24468</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5641^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
