<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-27867</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Generalized neonatal hypotonia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Generalized neonatal hypotonia implies a pathologically decreased postural tone involving at least the extremities, trunk and neck occurring during the first month of life. The gestational age of the neonate, the behavioral state of the neonate at the time of the examination, and the possibility of pseudoparalysis (due to generalized pain) should be considered when evaluation a neonate for the possibility of generalized hypotonia. The evaluation of neonates with hypotonia should guided by the characteristic of the muscular dynamic reflexes, primitive reflexes, the relation between the degree of hypotonia and weakness and findings during several maneuvers (traction, ventral and horizontal suspension, plantar response and response to forward displacement from a lying position). Possible sites of pathology in neonates with hypotonia include: (1) brain, (2) brain stem, (3) cervical spine, (4) cerebellum, (5) lower motor neurons in the brain stem and spine; (6) nerve, (7) myoneural junction, and (8) muscles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hipotonía generalizada del recién nacido se caracteriza por un tono postural patológicamente disminuido que afecta, como mínimo, a las extremidades, el tronco y el cuello durante el primer mes de vida. La edad gestacional del recién nacido, su estado conductual en el momento del examen y la posibilidad de una seudoparálisis (debido al dolor generalizado) son factores que deben tenerse en cuenta al evaluar la posible existencia de una hipotonía generalizada en el neonato. La evaluación de los recién nacidos con hipotonía debe guiarse por las características ofrecidas por los reflejos dinámicos musculares, los reflejos primitivos, la relación entre el grado de hipotonía y debilidad y los resultados de algunas maniobras (tracción, suspensión ventral y horizontal, respuesta plantar y respuesta a un desplazamiento hacia adelante con el paciente en decúbito supino). Algunas de las posibles localizaciones de la patología en los recién nacidos con hipotonía incluyen: 1) el cerebro, 2) el tronco encefálico, 3) la médula cervical, 4) el cerebelo, 5) las neuronas motores inferiores del tronco encefálico y la médula espinal, 6) el nervio, 7) la unión neuromuscular, y 8) los músculos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;37(3): 228-239, ago. 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hipotonía neonatal generalizada</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Papazian, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alfonso, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valencia, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-27867</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9239</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32124</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2525</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9661</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2614</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29399</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
