<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-33123</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The extracellular matrix of the central nervous system: chondroitin sulphate type proteoglycans and neural repair</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. In this paper we present a review of the main features of the extracellular matrix (ECM) of the central nervous system (CNS). Development. Proteoglycans (PG) are glycoproteins, a very common type of protein in the ECM. Among the PG, the most abundant type is the hyalectan or lectican family. The PG is formed by two main components; a protein and a sugar chain, which that is termed glycosaminoglycan (GAG). These GAGs are polymers of two simple sugars. The hyalectan family has GAGs of the Chondroitin sulphate type (CS), and for this reason they are termed PG-CS. PG-CS are linked to the hyaluronic acid (HA) and other molecules of the ECM in order to form a three-dimensional network. This network has several important roles in the maintenance of the homeostasis of the CNS. Conclusions. Several hypotheses have been proposed to elucidate the failure of the CNS regeneration after an injury or in several pathologies. It has been suggested that PG-CS, which expression is up-regulated after CNS injury, may play some role in this process of inhibition of the CNS regeneration. Furthermore, we present an approach to the therapeutic potential of the CNS regeneration after the inactivation of the PG-CS up-regulation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. En este artículo realizamos un estudio de las características de la matriz extracelular (MEC) del sistema nervioso central (SNC). Desarrollo. Los proteoglicanos (PG) son glicoproteínas, un tipo de molécula muy abundante en la MEC. Dentro de este grupo de PG destacan los hialectanos o lecticanos. Los hialectanos se caracterizan por poseer dos componentes: la proteína eje y la fracción glucídica, que está formada por los glucosaminoglicanos (GAG). Los GAG están formados por la polimerización de dímeros de azúcares sencillos. Los GAG de los hialectanos son del tipo condroitinsulfato (CS). Por esta razón, estos PG se denominan PG del tipo CS (PG-CS). Los PG-CS se unen al ácido hialurónico y a otras moléculas de la MEC para formar una red tridimensional de naturaleza proteica, que cumple funciones muy importantes en la homeostasis del tejido nervioso. Conclusiones. Diversas hipótesis se han planteado para tratar de explicar la falta de regeneración del SNC tras la lesión neural o en ciertas patologías. Se ha propuesto que los PG-CS, cuya expresión se incrementa tras las lesiones del SNC, pudieran desempeñar algún papel en este proceso de inhibición de la capacidad regenerativa neural. En este sentido, realizamos finalmente un análisis de las aproximaciones terapéuticas, experimentales, que se realizan para tratar de inducir la regeneración del SNC tras la actuación sobre los PG-CS de la MEC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;38(9): 843-851, mayo 2004. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La matriz extracelular del sistema nervioso central: los proteoglicanos del tipo condroitinsulfato y la reparación neural</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Crespo Santiago, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-33123</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d11949</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2859</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6862</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23765</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5208</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2525</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9609</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
