<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055802</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gene therapy: is possible a vaccine for prostate cancer?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: New approaches for prostate cancer are needed due to limitations of current therapies    for the treatment in advanced stages of the disease. In fact, there is no effective treatment for these    patients. Development in molecular biology research on prostate cancer has improved the knowledge    of common alterations encoded in DNA sequence, which may be useful as targets for prostate cancer    approach. In this review we give an overview of current gene therapy concepts, the most common gene    alterations in prostate cancer and the gene therapy treatment strategies</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Pérez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Cruz, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Oliva, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Andreu, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vera Donoso, C. D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Debido a las limitaciones existentes en el tratamiento del cáncer de próstata en estadios    avanzados, se precisan nuevas estrategias de tratamiento para estos pacientes. El desarrollo de la biología    molecular en el campo del cáncer de próstata, ha proporcionado un mayor conocimiento de las    alteraciones más comunes a nivel del ADN de las células cancerígenas, que podrían ser utilizadas    como dianas terapéuticas. En este artículo se han revisado los conceptos actuales en el campo de la    terapia génica, las alteraciones génicas más frecuentes en el cáncer de próstata y posibles estrategias    de tratamiento</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;31(7): 705-710, jul.-ago. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055802</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Terapia génica en el cáncer de próstata. ¿Es posible una vacuna?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5955^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23123^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
