<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108053</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical characterisation and course following therapeutic intervention for swallowing disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Swallowing disorders are common in hospitalised patients and are an added difficulty when it comes to  discharging them from hospital. Suitable characterisation performed by means of assessments conducted by a neurologist and a speech and language therapist allows for more accurate therapeutic decision-making.  Aim. To describe swallowing disorders from the speech and language therapy evaluation performed on admission until discharge in paediatric patients and their relation with the therapeutic intervention that was implemented. Patients and methods. We performed a retrospective analysis consisting in the examination of the medical records of 38 paediatric patients hospitalised between May 2007 and June 2008. Functional clinical evaluation was carried out in 100% of patients, and a video swallow study was conducted in 34%. Swallowing disorders were characterised as mild, moderate and severe, according to the stage that was altered and aspiratory risk to the airway. A speech therapist provided therapeutic intervention, and parents and caregivers were given special training. Results. Swallowing disorders were chiefly associated to prematurity. The most frequently used therapeutic techniques were: tactile stimulation, providing patterns and training of parents. In the speech and language therapy evaluation  performed on admission, 37% of disorders were severe, 21% were moderate and 42% were mild disorders. In most of the newborn infants, progress was favourable, as shown by a shift to normal swallowing in 48% and to mild in 8%. In the 17 preterm newborn infants, there was a change to normal swallowing in 65% and to mild in 12%. Conclusions. Swallowing disorders in this group of patients is mainly associated to prematurity. Systematic therapeutic intervention would help in the recovery from swallowing disorders, especially in preterm newborn infants (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salinas Valdebenito, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Milagros, Angeli</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nuñes Farias, Alicia C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escobar Heríquez, Raul G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los trastornos de la deglución son frecuentes en pacientes hospitalizados y determinan una dificultad adicional en el alta. Su adecuada caracterización a través de una evaluación neurológica y fonoaudiológica permite planificar estrategias terapéuticas más certeramente. Objetivo. Describir los trastornos de la deglución desde la evaluación fonoaudiológica de ingreso hasta el alta en pacientes pediátricos y su relación con la intervención terapéutica realizada. Pacientes y métodos. Es un análisis retrospectivo con revisión de fichas de 38 pacientes pediátricos hospitalizados desde mayo de 2007 a junio de 2008. El 100% tuvo evaluación clínica funcional, y en el 34% se hizo videodeglución. Se caracterizaron los trastornos de la deglución como leves, moderados y graves según la etapa alterada y el riesgo aspirativo a la  vía aérea. Se realizó intervención terapéutica por un fonoaudiólogo (logopeda) y entrenamiento a padres y cuidadores. Resultados. Los trastornos de la deglución se asociaron preferentemente a prematuridad. Las técnicas terapéuticas más utilizadas fueron: estimulación táctil, facilitación de patrones y entrenamiento a padres. En la evaluación fonoaudiológica de ingreso, hubo un 37% de trastornos graves, un 21% de trastornos moderados y un 42% de trastornos leves. En la mayoría de los recién nacidos, la evolución fue favorable, evidenciada por cambio a deglución normal en el 48% y a leve en el 8%. De los 17 recién nacidos de pretérmino, hubo cambio a deglución normal en el 65% y a leve en el 12%.  Conclusión. Los trastornos de la deglución en este grupo de pacientes se asocian principalmente a prematuridad. La intervención terapéutica sistemática contribuiría a la recuperación de los trastornos de la deglución, especialmente en recién nacidos prematuros (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;50(3): 139-144, feb. 2010. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108053</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Caracterización clínica y evolución tras la intervención terapéutica de trastornos de deglución en pacientes pediátricos hospitalizados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13455^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13777</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23977^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7410^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
