<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116677</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Survey About the Use of Lung Function Testing in Public Hospitals in Catalonia in 2009</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Underdiagnosis is one of the problems with the greatest impact on respiratory disease management and requires specific interventions. Access to quality spirometry is especially important and is an objective of the Master Plan for Respiratory Diseases of the Department of Health of the Generalitat de Catalunya. Objective: To determine the current use of spirometry at public hospitals in Catalonia, possible deficiencies and options for improvement. Methods: A cross-sectional survey of 65 public hospitals in Catalonia in 2009. Descriptive analyses were developed for each public health-care region. Results: A lack of uniformity was observed in the use of spirometry at the regional level (between 0.98 and 1.50 spirometries per 100 inhabitants). We identified two factors associated with a higher rate of spirometry: (i) the existence of a Respiratory Medicine Department at the hospital, and (ii) the existence of a set location to carry out spirometries. Several areas for improvement also were identified: quality control of the test itself, the inclusion of spirometry in electronic health-care records and continuing education programmes. Conclusions: The results of this study have identified areas for improvement in spirometry programmes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Burgos, Felip</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roger, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosas, Alba</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escarrabill, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tresserras, Ricard</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giner, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El infradiagnóstico es uno de los problemas de mayor impacto en las enfermedades respiratorias y requiere intervenciones específicas. Una de ellas es tener acceso a una espirometría de calidad. Este es uno de los objetivos del Plan Director de Enfermedades Respiratorias del Departament de Salut de la Generalitat de Catalunya. Objetivo: Conocer la utilización de la espirometría hospitalaria en Cataluña, y conocer los posibles déficits y las opciones de mejora. Método: Estudio transversal mediante una encuesta a los 65 hospitales públicos de Cataluña durante el año 2009. Se realizó un análisis descriptivo para cada región sanitaria. Resultados: Se observó una falta de homogeneidad en la utilización de la espirometría a nivel territorial (de 0,98 a 1,50 espirometrías por 100 habitantes). Se identificaron 2 factores que están asociados a una mayor tasa de espirometrías: la existencia de un servicio de neumología en el centro y disponer de una ubicación estable para realizar espirometrías. Como áreas de mejora se identificaron el control de calidad de la prueba, la inclusión en los sistemas hospitalarios de información y los programas de formación continuada. Conclusiones: Los resultados de este estudio han permitido identificar las áreas de mejora para un programa a desarrollar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;49(9): 371-377, sept. 2013. tab, mapa, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116677</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Encuesta de utilización de la función pulmonar en los hospitales públicos de Cataluña en 2009</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13530^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6935^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1969^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12542^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
