<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052392</identifier>
<setSpec>0303-8874</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Otorhinolaingology approach of the chronic cough. Clinical case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Chronic cough is defined as that which is persisting at least for trhee weeks without an evident cause. It is very common on the otorhinological practice to receive patients with chronic cough in order to rule out that their chronic cough is not produced because of an alteration in the high respiratory system. We show a clinical case with chronic cough and we make reference to the physical exploration, diagnostical method, and possibilities of medical and surgical treatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García de Hombre, Alin María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La tos crónica se define como aquella que persiste al menos tres semanas sin tener una causa evidente. En la práctica Otorrinolaringológica se hace muy habitual recibir enfermos con tos crónica para descartar que su causa no sea una alteración en el aparato respiratorio alto. Presentamos un caso clínico con tos crónica y hacemos referencia a la exploración física, metodología diagnóstica y posibilidades de tratamiento médico y quirúrgico</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Otorrinolaringol Ibero Am;34(1): 75-80, ene.-feb. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052392</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfoque otorrinolaringológico de la tos crónica. Caso clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27810^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d908^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27810^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1000^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24004^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24004^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9210^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27810^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1000^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24004^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3386^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d908^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
