<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050467</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Virus and systemic vasculitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The participation of genetic and environmental factors has always been invoked in the pathogenesis of the autoimmune systemic diseases, including the primary vasculitides. Among the environmental factors, infections, fundamentally those having a viral nature, have always been focused on, especially after the discovery of the close existing relationship between the polyarteritis nodosa and the hepatitis B virus, on the one hand, and mixed cryoglobulinemia and the hepatitis C virus, on the other. The present review summarizes data from the most recent literature related to associations between virus infections and primary vasculitides, following the Chapel-Hill vasculitis classification</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Callejas Rubio, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortego Centeno, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cervantes Bonet, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la patogenia de las enfermedades autoinmunes sistémicas, incluyendo las vasculitis, siempre se ha invocado la participación de factores genéticos y factores ambientales. Entre los ambientales, las infecciones, fundamentalmente de naturaleza vírica, han sido siempre un foco de atención, máxime tras el descubrimiento de la estrecha relación existente entre la poliarteritis nudosa y el virus de la hepatitis B, por una parte, y la crioglobulinemia mixta esencial y el virus de la hepatitis C, por otra. La presente revisión pretende actualizar los conocimientos recogidos en la literatura más reciente sobre el binomio virus y vasculitis sistémicas, siguiendo la clasificación de vasculitis de Chapel-Hill</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;206(10): 507-509, nov. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050467</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Virus y vasculitis sistémicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15059^s32386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
