<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114290</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Thematic áreas of study in Congresses of Asociación Española de Pediatría</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. The thematic áreas  (or subspecialties) in Pediatrics is a relaity in clinical practice in Spain. Bibliometric indicators are important tools used to determine the quality of scientific publications, but this type of study is infrequent in the analysis of free communications of congresses. The objective of this article is to analyze the dynamic of publication in the different thematic areas in the context of the congresses of pediatrics. Material and methods. A bibliometric study of all the free communications published in the congresses of Asociación Española de Pediatría (AEP) during four years (1996-1997 and 2000-01), was performed (n=2.677). The dependent variable was thematic area of study (25 subspecialties) and independent variables were the other bibliometric indicators classified in three groups: quantitative (productivity), qualitative (statistical accessibility) and scientific evidence. Results. The main thematic areas were Infectology (418 communications), Neonatology (252), Hemato-oncology (221), Neurology (195) and Endocrinology (176). Ninetyfive percent of communications were signed by hospitals, with a predominant role of the hospitals of Andalusia (hospital Virgen del Rocio, Carlos Haya, Virgen Macarena, Clínico de Granada, Torrecárdenas, etc) and Madrid (hospital Gregorio Marañón, Doce de octubre, Niño Jesús, La Paz, etc). The provinces more scientific productive were Madrid (710), Sevilla (288), Barcelona (227), Granada (126) and Valencia (108). Madrid is the most productive province in all thematic areas, except Genetic-Dysmorphology (Granada) and Reumatology (Valencia). We found positive bibliometric indicators in the areas of Metabolism-Nutrition, Endocrinoloy and Neonatology, and negative ones in Pediatric Surgery and Genetic-Dysmorpholgy. Conclusions. The bibliometric study of thematic areas in congresses of AEP is a good starting point for analyse the quality of their free communications, and discuss possible solutions for limited the negative aspects and favour the positive ones, by example more structured communications, more complex statistical accessibility, more analytical and/or experimental studies, and more use of epidemiological concepts in evidence-based medicine (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González de Dios, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paredes Cencillo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. Las áreas temáticas (o subespecialidades) en pediatría son una realidad en la práctica clínica en España. Los indicadores bibliométricos son herramientas importantes utilizadas para conocer la calidad de las publicaciones científicas, pero este tipo de estudio es infrecuente en el análisis de las comunicaciones a congresos. El objetivo de este artículo es analizar la dinámica de publicación de las diferentes áreas temáticas en el contexto de los congresos pediátricos. Material y métodos. Se ha realizado un estudio bibliométrico de todas las comunicaciones publicadas en los congresos de la Asociación Española de Pediatría (AEP) durante cuatro años (1996-97 y 2000-01) (n=2.677). La variable dependiente corresponde al área temática de estudio (25 subespecialidades) y las variables independientes son los restantes indicadores bibliométricos, clasificados en tres grupos: cuantitativos (productividad), cualitativos (accesibilidad estadística) y de evidencia científica. Resultados. Las principales áreas temáticas fueron infectología (418 comunicaciones), neonatología (252), hemato-oncología (221), neurología (195) y endocrinología (176). El 95% de las comunicaciones eran firmadas por hospitales, con un papel destacado de los hospitales de Andalucía (Hospital Virgen del Rocío, Carlos Haya, Virgen Macarena, Clínico de Granda, Torrecárdenas, etc) y Madrid (Hospital Gregorio Marañón, Doce de Octubre, Niño Jesús, La Paz, etc). Las provincias con mayor productividad científica son Madrid (710), Sevilla (288), Barcelona (227), Granada (126) y Valencia (108). Madrid es la provincia con mayor productividad en todas las áreas temáticas, salvo en genética-dismorfología (Granada) y reumatología (Valencia). Detectamos indicadores bibliométricos positivos en las áreas de metabolismo-nutrición, endocrinología y neonatología y negativos en las áreas de cirugía pediátrica y genética-dismorfología. Conclusiones. El estudio bibliométrico de las áreas temáticas en los congresos de la AEP es un buen punto de partida para analizar la calidad de las comunicaciones científicas y discutir las posible soluciones para limitar los aspectos negativos detectados y potencia los positivos como, por ejemplo, exigir la estructuración de las comunicaciones, mayor complejidad en la accesibilidad estadística, favorecer el uso de estudios analíticos y/o experimentales, así como el uso de conceptos metodológicos propios de la medicina basada en pruebas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;60(6): 430-444, nov.-dic. 2004. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114290</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Áreas temáticas de estudio en los congresos de la Asociación Española de Pediatría</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13421^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50088</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
