<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053056</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sociopoética: a bridge for to care and research in nursing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this work we justify a preposition of taking care - investigating based on the social poetics rudiments, having as centre the researcher group that meets approval in the Theory of Dialogical Action. The care of the group articulates to the act of the researching because the knwledges of the professionals and of the clients are questioned, being that each one learns with the other. There is coherence with the nursing because the care helps the group in the identification of its human potential of growing up becoming strong. So that, when we take care of the other, we foment his comprehension and his acceptance of the care, favorouring him to take care of himsel. We concluded that, considering physical and spiritual dimensions, the social poetics establishes a bridge even a political ecology of the spirit, consolidating the solidarity between the human beings and the plural self- administration</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santos, Iraci dos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este trabajo justificamos una propuesta de "Cuidar - Investigar" fundamentada en los principios sociopoéticos, centrándonos en el grupo investigador que encuentra un gran aporte en la "Teoría de la Acción Dialógica". El "cuidar" del grupo se articula con el acto de "investigar", porque los conocimientos de los profesionales y de los clientes se cuestionan siendo que cada cual aprende con el otro. Existe coherencia con la naturaleza de la enfermería en la que "cuidar" es una ayuda al grupo en la identificación de su potencial humano de crecer y fortalecerse como tal. Así al cuidar a otro, se promueve su comprensión y aceptación del cuidado, ayudándolo a cuidarse a sí mismo. Se concluye que al considerar las dimensiones físicas y espirituales en el "cuidar", la Sociopoética establece un puente hacia una ecología política del espíritu, consolidando la solidaridad entre los seres humanos y la pluralidad autogestionaria</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;14(50): 35-37, nov. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053056</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sociopoética: un puente para "cuidar - investigar" en enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10881</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
