<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-68772</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish normative data of the Zuckerman-Kuhlman Personality Questionnaire in a general population sample</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Zuckerman-Kuhlman Personality Questionnaire (ZKPQ), a tool designed to measure the alternative five-factor model of personality, was translated and adapted into the Spanish language. To date, there appears to be no normative data for the ZKPQ in general population samples in any culture. The aim of this study was to obtain Spanish normative data for the scales and subscales in a community sample of the general population. The questionnaire was administered to 1,678 participants of both genders (55.8 % females) with ages ranging from 18 to 93 years. The magnitude of the sample, as well as an adequate representativity of both genders and the wide age range being considered, provides a satisfactory description of each scale and subscale of this instrument. The normative data obtained showed a normal distribution of the scales. The norms (means and standard deviations) are presented by gender and five age ranges and are adjusted according to the level of education attained. Gender differences are in accordance with data obtained with instruments measuring similar personality traits. This is the first time the normative data of the ZKPQ is reported in a general community sample in any culture (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valero Ventura, Sergi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gomà-i-Freixanet, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Zuckerman-Kuhlman Personality Questionnaire (ZKPQ), un instrumento diseñado para la evaluación del modelo alternativo de los cinco factores de personalidad, ha sido traducido y adaptado a la lengua española. Hasta la fecha, no existen datos normativos en población general en ninguna cultura. El objetivo del presente estudio fue obtener datos normativos españoles de las escalas y subescalas en una muestra de la población general. El cuestionario fue administrado a 1.678 participantes de ambos géneros (55.8 % mujeres) con edades comprendidas entre los 18 y 93 años. La magnitud de la muestra, así como una adecuada representatividad de ambos géneros y el amplio rango de edad considerado, proporcionan una descripción satisfactoria de cada escala y subescala de dicho instrumento. Los datos normativos obtenidos mostraron una distribución normal de las escalas. Las medias y desviaciones estándar son presentadas por género y cinco rangos de edad, y ajustadas por el nivel de educación alcanzado. Las diferencias de género van en la misma dirección que las obtenidas con instrumentos que evalúan rasgos de personalidad similar. Esta es la primera vez que se refieren datos normativos del ZKPQ en una muestra de población general (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);20(2): 324-330, abr.-jun. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-68772</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Datos normativos españoles del Zuckerman-Kuhlman Personality Questionnaire en una muestra de población general</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10747</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10743^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31670</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
