<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104922</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-6585</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Biofilms like expression of quorum sensing mechanism: A revision</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In modern periodontics, we must check continuously many concepts that are driving some time, which does not allow the progress and development of many structures of thinking in solving problems such as periodontal disease in all its various forms presentation. The concept of biofilms is in progress so overwhelming that the ability of discussion is completely necessary and indispensable, so that you can update and change a plaque idea to a concept much more complex, dynamic, and that genetic exchange what has been established to date. Biofilms are a non-random, is a form of growth and sustainability quite advanced and structured to facilitate the survival of the pathogens included in these partnerships. This article is a narrative review, mechanisms such as quorum sensing, biofilms and the relationship of these with periodontal diseases that affect many people at all latitudes worldwide. It explores various concepts and research areas with potential application in biomedical experimentation level (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Puerta, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrales Salgado, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera Herrera, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ahumedo Monterrosa, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Caballero, AJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vivas Reyes, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arévalo  Tovar, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la periodoncia moderna, el concepto de biopelículas viene en un progreso tan abrumador quela capacidad de discusión se hace necesaria y completamente indispensable, de forma que se pueda actualizar y cambiar de una idea de placa bacteriana a un concepto mucho más complejo, dinámico y de intercambio génico que lo que se viene estableciendo. Las biopelículas muestran una organización no al azar, con una forma de crecimiento y de sostenibilidad muy avanzada y estructurada que facilita la supervivencia de los patógenos incluidos dentro de estas formas de asociación. El presente artículo es una revisión narrativa de los mecanismos de como el quórum sensing y las biopelículas se relacionan con las enfermedades periodontales que afectan a tantas personas en todas las latitudes a nivel mundial. Se exploran diversos conceptos y campos de investigación biomédicas con posibles aplicaciones a nivel experimental (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. periodoncia implantol. oral;23(3): 195-201, dic. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104922</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Biopelículas como expresión del mecanismo de quorum sensing: Una revisión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52467^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10709^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3788^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24666</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32342^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
