<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90541</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Who Funds Research by Spanish Dermatologists? Comparative Analysis of Articles Published in 2008</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: References have been made in the literature to the funding of clinical trials by the pharmaceutical industry. Other types of funding, however, have been less well studied. Objective: To describe the sources of funding for research by Spanish dermatology departments published in 2008. Material and methods: A bibliometric study was performed of the research articles published by Spanish, French, and British dermatology departments and by Spanish rheumatology departments in 2008 according to MEDLINE records. Results: Articles published by Spanish dermatology departments received funding in 36.4% of cases. This percentage is lower than that found for the other groups studied and remained low for all different types of funding. Statistically significant relationships were found between a higher percentage of funding and a higher level of evidence, as well as between a higher level of funding by the pharmaceutical industry and the publication of research into quality of life and pharmacological treatment. Inadequate declaration of funding was observed in 57.1% of articles from Spanish dermatology departments and the role of the sponsor was not declared in any article. Similar findings were obtained for the other groups studied. Conclusions: The proportion of research articles published by Spanish dermatology departments that receive external funding is low, and this is associated with a lower level of scientific evidence. In order to obtain more external funding, we must improve our competitiveness (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Doval, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Cruz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Batalla, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aranegui, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Existen referencias en la literatura acerca de la financiación de los ensayos clínicos por la industria farmacéutica. Otros tipos de financiación han sido menos evaluados. Objetivos: Describir la presencia de financiación y su tipo en la investigación realizada por los Servicios de Dermatología españoles en el año 2008. Material y métodos: Estudio bibliométrico de los artículos de investigación publicados por Servicios de Dermatología españoles, franceses y británicos y Servicios de Reumatología españoles en el año 2008, indexados en Medline. Resultados: El porcentaje de financiación de los artículos de investigación publicados por Servicios de Dermatología españoles fue del 36,4%, siendo este porcentaje menor en comparación con los restantes grupos estudiados, y manteniéndose bajo para los distintos tipos de financiación. Existen relaciones significativas entre un mayor porcentaje de financiación y un mayor nivel de evidencia, así como entre un mayor porcentaje de financiación por la industria y los temas de calidad de vida y de tratamiento farmacológico. En un 57,1% de los artículos de investigación dermatológica española no se declara la financiación de modo adecuado y en ninguno se indicó el papel del financiador. Estos últimos hallazgos fueron similares para los restantes grupos estudiados. Conclusión: El porcentaje de financiación externa en los artículos de investigación publicados por Servicios de Dermatología españoles es bajo, y se relaciona con menor nivel de evidencia científica que los restantes grupos estudiados. Se propone la necesidad de aumentar nuestra competitividad para obtener mayor financiación externa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;102(7): 517-526, sept. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90541</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Quién financia la investigación de los dermatólogos españoles? Análisis del año 2008 y comparación con otros grupos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50098</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12530</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50116</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4407^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
