<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60983</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Functional hemispherectomy in adult patients with catastrophic epilepsy: a new therapeutic indication?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Functional hemispherectomy was reported in 1983 for the treatmentof catastrophic refractory epilepsies in order to reduce thecomplications derived by the anatomical hemispherectomy. A seriesof variants of the functional hemisphectomy have been reported.They include peri-insular hemispherectomy, modified lateralhemispherectomy, vertical parasagital hemispherectomy. The functionalhemispherectomy has been used mainly in the treatment of catastrophic epilepsies in children, in which extensive hemisphericlesions are associated with pharmacoresistant epileptic seizuresand focal neurological deficit such as: Rasmussen&#146;s encephalitis,hemimegalencephaly, Sturge-Weber syndrome, and extensivehemispheric cortical dysplasias, etc.Recently, two series of adults patients with catastrophic epilepsieswith excellent control of the episodes (above 75 %) andwithout mortality have been reported. Thus, functional hemispherectomymay be an effective procedure in appropriately selectedadult patients, although more studies with larger series arestill needed to evaluate the long-term prognosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Medina, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kraemer, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solano, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hemisferectomía funcional fue descrita en 1983 para el tratamientode epilepsias refractarias catastróficas con el objetivo dereducir las complicaciones derivadas de la hemisferectomía anatómica.Se han logrado una serie de variantes de la hemisferectomíafuncional que incluyen: hemisferectomía periinsular, hemisferectomíamodificada lateral, hemisferectomía parasagital lateral, y otras.La hemisferectomía funcional ha sido utilizada principalmente en eltratamiento de epilepsias catastróficas de la niñez, en las que seasocian lesiones hemisféricas extensas con crisis epilépticas farmacorresistentesy déficits neurológicos focales como: encefalitis deRasmussen, hemimegalencefalia, síndrome de Sturge-Weber, displasiascorticales hemisféricas extensas.Recientemente se han descrito dos series de pacientes adultoscon epilepsias catastróficas con un excelente control de crisis (másdel 75 %) y sin mortalidad. Parece que la hemisferectomía funcionalpuede ser un procedimiento efectivo en pacientes adultos apropiadamenteseleccionados, aunque aún se requieren más estudios conseries más grandes para evaluar el pronóstico a largo plazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;24(1): 7-8, ene.-feb. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60983</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La hemisferectomía funcional en pacientes adultos con epilepsia catastrófica: ¿una nueva indicación terapéutica?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29633</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37569^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37569</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
