<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047262</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Oxidative stress and alzheimer&#146;s disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. According to the oxidative stress hypothesis, the pathogenesis of several diseases should be relatedwith an excessive production of prooxidant substances (free radicals, transition metals), the deficiency of antioxidantdefensive mechanisms, or both. Oxidative stress has been implicated in the pathogenesis of aging of the brain and severalneurological diseases, including Alzheimer&#146;s disease (AD). Development. In recent years there are many data suggesting apossible role of oxidative stress in the pathogenesis of AD. These include the demonstration of increased oxidation of lipids,proteins and deoxyribonucleic acid, alterations in mitochondrial function and the possible role of amyloid beta and itsprecursor protein in the oxidative reactions in experimental models (cortical neuronal cultures and transgenic animals).Conclusions. Many studies show increased oxidative stress in the brain of patients with AD, although its possible role con thepathogenesis of this disease are controversial</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Navarro, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayuso-Peralta, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jabbour-Wadih, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Jiménez, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Según la hipótesis del estrés oxidativo, lapatogenia de algunas enfermedades se relacionaría con el excesode producción de sustancias prooxidantes (radicales libres, metalesde transición), el déficit de mecanismos de defensa contra laoxidación, o ambos factores. El estrés oxidativo se ha implicado enla patogenia del envejecimiento cerebral y de algunas enfermedadesneurológicas, incluida la enfermedad de Alzheimer (EA). Desarrollo.En los últimos años se han presentado numerosos datos queparecen sugerir un posible papel del estrés oxidativo en la patogeniade la EA. Éstos incluyen la demostración de un aumento de losprocesos oxidativos de lípidos, proteínas y ácido desoxirribonucleico,alteraciones en las concentraciones de algunos factoresprooxidantes y antioxidantes en el cerebro y en otros tejidos, alteracionesde la función mitocondrial y del papel del amiloide y suproteína precursora en los procesos oxidativos en modelos experimentales(cultivos de neuronas corticales y animales transgénicos).Conclusiones. Existen muchos estudios que muestran un aumentodel estrés oxidativo en el cerebro de los pacientes con EA, sibien su posible papel en los procesos patogénicos de la misma escontrovertido</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;42(7): 419-427, abr. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047262</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrés oxidativo y enfermedad de Alzheimer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32101</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5744</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
