<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113954</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Suspected hirayama disease. Presentation of a case and a clinical review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hirayama's disease, or juvenile muscular atrophy of distal upper extremity, is a cervical myelopathy. It affects adolescent males, and is characterized by progressive muscle weakness and atrophy of the distal upper extremities, followed by slow paralysis. Although the cause remains unclear, radiological findings suggest neuropathic forward displacement of the posterior cervical dural sac during neck flexion, causing compression of the cervical cord, resulting in atrophic changes and ischemic disease of the medullar anterior horn. Since the bending of the neck was recognized as a cause of the disease, cervical orthosis, spinal fusion, and duraplasty combined with fusion, have been proposed as treatment. A solid understanding of Hirayama disease is critical as early recognition and effective treatment can stop the deterioration (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Monje, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Cordovés, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mirpuri-Mirpuri, P. G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad de Hirayama, o atrofia muscular juvenil distal de una extremidad superior, es una mielopatía cervical. Afecta principalmente a los adolescentes varones, caracterizándose por la debilidad muscular progresiva y atrofia distal de una extremidad superior, seguida de la parálisis de lenta evolución. Aunque la causa sigue siendo poco clara, hallazgos neuropáticos y radiológicos sugieren un desplazamiento hacia delante del saco dural posterior cervical durante la flexión del cuello, causando la compresión de la médula cervical, produciendo cambios atróficos y enfermedad isquémica del cuerno anterior. Desde que la flexión del cuello fue reconocida como causa de la enfermedad, han sido empleados como tratamientos: las ortesis cervicales, la fusión vertebral y la duraplastia asociada a fusión. Una buena comprensión de la enfermedad de Hirayama es fundamental porque el reconocimiento precoz y el tratamiento eficaz pueden detener el deterioro progresivo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);39(5): e1-e3, jul.-ago. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113954</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sospecha de enfermedad de Hirayama. A propósito de un caso en Atención Primaria. Revisión clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13501^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32676^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8657^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23397^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4648^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23397^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23397^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23397^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4648^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32676^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13501^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13501^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13501^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
