<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100538</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Análise da suspensão de cirurgias em um hospital de ensino</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the search for better quality indices, the suspensions of surgeries have been examined by and received attention from researchers in the field of health. High cancellation rates reveal an inadequate management that impacts negatively on the health team iself and the patient's life and and that of his or her family. This retrospective descriptive study aim to identify the rate of surgical suspension and the reasons for this procedure in a public teaching hospital. Data were collected from the Surgical Center Archive and Medical Archive Service Statistics. There was a rate of 14.14% surgical cancellations and in 1,402 (63.78%) occasions no records were found that justify the suspension of the surgeries. The results showed the following justifications for the suspensions of the surgery: 194 (8.82%) were non hospitalized patients; 182 (8.30%) for inadequate clinical conditions;, 179 (8.14%) due to administrative problems;, 94 (4.27%) for welfare issues;, 61 (2.77%) for structural issues; 40 (1.82%) for lack of patients and 46 (2.10%) for other reasons. These findings point to the need to adopt measures that will ensure patient safety and quality of service offered (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vieira de Andrade, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miranda Goulart, DM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mattia, AL de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barbosa, MH</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En busca de los índices de mejor calidad, la suspensión de las cirugías han sido examinadas por los servicios y recibido la atención de los investigadores en el campo de la salud. Las altas tasas de cancelación revelan un manejo inadecuado que tienen efectos negativos en el equipo de salud y en la vida del paciente y su familia. Este estúdio retrospectivo y descriptivo tuvo como objetivo identificar el tipo de suspensión quirúrgica y las razones de este procedimiento en un hospital público de enseñanza. Los datos fueron recolectados de los archivos del Archivo de la Unidad Quirúrgica y Servicio de Archivo Médico y Estadístico del referido hospital. Hubo una tasa de anulación quirúrgica de 14.14% y para 1402 (63,78%) cirugías canceladas no había constancia de la justificación de la suspensión. Las razones para la suspensión de las cirugías fueron: 194 (8,82%) por la no hospitalización de los pacientes, 182 (8,30%) por las condiciones clínicas inadecuadas, 179 (8,14%) debido a problemas administrativos, 94 (4,27%) por asuntos de asistencia para el cuidados de la salud, 61 (2,77%) por problemas estructurales, 40 (1,82%) por ausencia del pacientes y 46 (2.10%) por otras razones. Estos resultados señalan a la necesidad de adoptar medidas para garantizar la seguridad del paciente y la calidad del servicio ofrecido (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;11(26): 164-173, abr. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100538</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la suspensión de cirugía en un hospital docente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13883^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6939^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13913^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6939^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13883^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13885^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6939^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13913^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
