<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157116</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9427</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Twenty-five year old male with repeating ulcers on lower limbs of several years of evolution and moderate mental retardation. We detected alterations of the fibrinolysis in the complementary studies performed with an increase of PAI&#151;1 levels, C-functional protein increased and resistance to C-activate protein, the hormonal study showed an increase of FSH (24,57 u/l), LH (20, 78 u/l) and estradiol (59,2 pg/ml) with decrease of testosterone (1,73 nmol/l), DHEA-S (78,7 nmol/l), free testosterone (5,54) and GH (&lt;0, 05 ng/dl). The echography of the genital area showed a symmetrical reduction of the testicular size with a maximum diameter of 7,6 cm, signs of bilateral testicular atrophy and inflammatory left inguinal adenopathy. All these results, associated to the mental retardation of the patient, were within the context of a syndrome of Klinefelter, thus we performed a karyotype which confirmed the existence of a mosaic variable (48XXX Y/46XY) of this syndrome. We established a treatment with parenteral and oral anticoagulants associated to a hormonal substitute treatment with testosterone depot every 27 days and topical treatment with testosterone enanthate, this achieved the partial improvement of the lesion but we could not obtain the total cure of the ulcer. Chronic ulcers could be a cutaneous manifestation to be taken into account as a possible first sign for the diagnosis of this syndrome (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morillo Montañés, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armario Hita, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Gaviño, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Vozmediano, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Varón de 25 años de edad con úlceras de repetición en miembros inferiores de varios años de evolución y retraso mental moderado. En los estudios complementarios realizados se detectaron alteraciones de la fibrinólisis con aumento de los niveles de PAI-1, proteína C funcional aumentada y resistencia a proteína C activada, en el estudio hormonal se apreció aumento de FSH (24,57 u/l), LH (20, l8 u/l) y estradiol (59,2 pg/ml) con disminución de testosterona (7,73 nmol/l), DHEA-S (78,7 nmol/l), testosterona libre (5,54) y GH (&lt;0,05 ng/dl). En la ecografía del área genital se observó una disminución simétrica del tamaño testicular con un diámetro máximo de 7,6 cm, signos de atrofia testicular bilateral y adenopatías inguinales izquierdas de carácter inflamatorio. Todos estos resultados, asociados al retraso mental del paciente, estaban dentro del contexto de un síndrome de Klinefelter, por lo que se realizó un cariotipo en el que se confirmó la existencia de una variante mosaico (48XXXY/46X Y) de este síndrome. Se instauró tratamiento con anticoagulantes parenterales y orales asociados a tratamiento sustitutivo hormonal con testosterona depot cada 21 días y tratamiento tópico con enantato de testosterona, con lo que sólo se pudo conseguir la mejoría parcial de la lesión pero no se pudo lograr la curación total de la úlcera. Las úlceras crónicas pueden ser una manifestación cutánea a tener en cuenta como posible primer signo diagnóstico de este síndrome (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. int. dermatol. dermocosmét. clín;6(1): 42-45, feb. 2003. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157116</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Úlceras crónicas de piernas como manifestación primaria del síndrome de Klinefelter</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8049^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8049^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8049^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8049^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8049^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22124^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14118^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7889^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7889^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
