<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131074</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Preoperative aspects of information related to patient anxiety scheduled for surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Preoperative anxiety is a frequent event that depends on multiple factors. One is the prior information to the patient, which must be simple, understandable and reliable. The aim of this study is to establish the relationship between the degree of information of the surgical procedure and the level of preoperative anxiety in patients scheduled for surgery. Material and methods: Cross-sectional study of 99 randomly selected patients scheduled for surgery at the Hospital Royo Villanova (sector I at Zaragoza). APAIS and STAI-AE scales were used to assess the preoperative anxiety level and the degree of prior information. The statistical analysis was performed using SPSS v.21.0, with the Chi-square test, ANOVA test and the nonparametric Kruskal Wallis to study the association between the different questions and the degree of anxiety. To assess the association of the two scales Pearson correlation test was used. Results: The educational level, type of surgery, previous surgery, specialty and previous surgery variables do not show statistical significance (p &lt;0.05) compared to the anxiety level variable. It has been shown that there is an association between the degree of information and level of anxiety. Conclusions: The data shown in the present study support the hypothesis that patients who believe they need more knowledge about the surgical procedure have higher anxiety levels than patients who believe they need less (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Monge Sanz, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Serrano, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Litago Cortés, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Doñate Marín, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La ansiedad preoperatoria es un evento frecuente que depende de múltiples factores. Uno de ellos es la información previa que recibe el paciente, que debe de ser sencilla, inteligible y fidedigna. El objetivo de este estudio es establecer la relación entre el grado de información del procedimiento quirúrgico y el nivel de ansiedad preoperatoria en los pacientes programados para cirugía. Material y métodos: Estudio descriptivo transversal de 99 pacientes seleccionados aleatoriamente, programados para intervención quirúrgica en el Hospital Royo Villanova, del sector I de Zaragoza. Se valoró el nivel de ansiedad preoperatoria y el grado de información previa mediante la escala APAIS y se utilizó la escala STAI-AE en algunos de los pacientes, para comprobar la veracidad de la escala APAIS. El análisis estadístico se realizó mediante el programa SPSS v.21.0, aplicando la prueba de Chi-cuadrado, el test Anova y la prueba no paramétrica de Kruskal Wallis para estudiar la asociación entre las distintas preguntas y el grado de ansiedad. Para valorar la asociación de las dos escalas se empleó el test de Correlación de Pearson. Resultados: Las variables de: nivel educativo, tipo de cirugía, especialidad e intervención quirúrgica previa, no muestran una significación estadística (p&lt;0,05) respecto a la variable de nivel de ansiedad. Se ha evidenciado que existe asociación entre el grado de información y el nivel de ansiedad. Conclusiones: Los datos que muestra el presente estudio refuerzan la hipótesis de que los pacientes que creen necesitar más conocimientos sobre el procedimiento quirúrgico presentan niveles de ansiedad mayores que los pacientes que creen necesitar menos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;14(37): 170-180, ene. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131074</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aspectos de la información preoperatoria relacionada con la ansiedad del paciente programado para cirugía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5932^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20180^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20180^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
