<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113309</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Laryngeal MFH.  Two unusual cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Laryngeal presentation of Malignat Fibrous Histiocytoma (MFH) is uncommon. It is more prevalent in elderly males. The most frequent form of laryngeal presentation is as subepithelial nodules, and its clinical behaviour is variable and unpredictable. Microscopically, it is a tumour with two well differentiated components: histiocitic and fibroblastic, with several different structural patterns that can make histologic diagnosis a difficult one. We present two cases of MFH of the larynx, and a review of the literature (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Galera Ruiz, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Bish, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Borge, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mingo Fernández, EJ de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Clemente, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El fibrohisticitoma (FHM) es una tumoración infrecuente en cabeza y cuello, y todavía mas en la laringe. Es más prevalente en varones de mediana edad, pudiendo aparecer a cualquier edad. la presentación más habitual laringea es en forma de nódulos subepiteliales. el comportamiento clínico es variable e impredecible. Microscópicamente, es un tumor con dos componentes diferenciados: histiocítico y fibroblástico, con diferentes patrones estructurales que pueden dificultar el diagnostico histológico. Se presentan dos casos de FHM laríngeos y se revisa la bibliografía(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;55(8): 390-394, oct. 2004. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113309</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fibrohistiocitoma maligno laríngeo. A propósito de dos casos de localización infrecuente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28150^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50469^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
