<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119611</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1780</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects on School Conflicts of a Conflict Resolution Program in Tutorship</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to test an intervention program to improve school coexistence in Secondary Education. The intervention program consisted of ten units for the training of students in conflict resolution. It was applied to classroom groups of first cycle of Compulsory Secondary Education, second cycle of Compulsory Secondary Education and Baccalaureate of an IES by their teachers in tutoring schedule. The implementation of these units was accompanied by the use of this material by tutors to manage everyday school conflicts in a negotiated or mediated way. It was also accompanied by regular monitoring meetings.  The students&#146; perceived level of violence in the experimental classrooms was compared with the perceived level in the classrooms where intervention program was not applied. The results show that intervention was more effective in the first cycle of Compulsory Secondary Education and Baccalaureate than in second cycle of Compulsory Secondary Education. They also show a greater impact on violence committed by the students than on violence committed by teachers. The influence of experimental mortality on the results  is discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Pienda, Julio Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Castro, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Pérez, Celestino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Pérez, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez Pérez, José Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez García, David</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo fue poner a prueba un programa de intervención para la mejora de la convivencia. El programa de intervención consistió en un temario de diez unidades para la formación del alumnado en resolución de conflictos. Fue aplicado en un Instituto de Educación Secundaria, en aulas de primer ciclo de ESO, segundo ciclo de ESO y Bachillerato, por sus respectivos tutores en horario de tutoría. La aplicación de este temario fue acompañada del uso de este material por parte de los tutores para el afrontamiento negociado o mediado de ciertos conflictos en el centro y de reuniones periódicas de seguimiento. Mediante el Cuestionario de Violencia Escolar (CUVE), se comparó el  nivel de violencia escolar percibido por el alumnado de las aulas experimentales con el percibido por el alumnado de las aulas en las que no se introdujo el programa de intervención,antes y después de su aplicación. Los resultados muestran una mayor eficacia de la intervención en primer ciclo de ESO y en Bachillerato que en segundo ciclo de  SO. También muestran un mayor impacto en la violencia por parte del alumnado que en la cometida por el profesorado. Se debate la influencia de la mortalidad experimental sobre los resultados obtenidos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int. j. psychol. psychol. ther. (Ed. impr.);9(2): 189-204, jun. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119611</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos sobre la conflictividad escolar de un programa de educación en resolución de conflictos en tutoría</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3244</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11775</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d378^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
