<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041109</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-3568</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assited reproduction in an approved center for the gathering of sperm in, the stallion farm in Avila. Organization and results</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In Avila's stallion farm, there is an approved center to gather sperm which meets all the requirements established by the European administration (92/65/CE) in relation to the installations, stallions etc. In this center all the different reproductive biotechnologies can be applied, being the most frequently used Artificial Insemination either with cooled semen or frozen semen; the use of this technique requires an ecographic diagnostic of the proximity of ovulation and it should be carried out the strictest hygienical procedures. The pregnancy rates with cooled semen are similar to those obtained during the natural service</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Crespo Castejón, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el depósito de sementales de Ávila existe un centro homologado para la recogida de esperma que cumple todos los requisitos marcados por la Directiva 92/65/CE en lo referente a instalaciones, sementales etc. En este centro pueden ser aplicadas las diferentes biotecnologías reproductivas, siendo la de más frecuente uso la Inseminación Artificial ya sea con semen refrigerado o congelado; el empleo de esta técnica requiere un diagnostico ecográfico del momento óptimo de la inseminación y que sea aplicada con las suficientes garantías higiénicas. Los índices de preñez con semen refrigerado son similares a los obtenidos mediante el uso de la monta natural</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. mil;61(2): 82-88, feb. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041109</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Organización y puesta en práctica de la reproducción asistida, periodo 2004-2005: reproducción asistida en un centro homologado de recogida de esperma en el Depósito de Sementales de Ávila. Organización y resultados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6893</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29201^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d836^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24000^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13044^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22679^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23290^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
