<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139270</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Physical activity patterns in adolescents according to sex, chronological and biological age</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To verify the patterns of physical acti vity (PA) aligned chronological and biological age and analyze differences according to sex. Methods: 275 adolescents (153 males and 122 females) from a geographic area of Peru located at 2,320 meters above sea level (Arequipa) were studied. The age range was 11-17 years (X = 14.0 ± 2.1años). Weight, height, trunk-cephalic height, physical activity (questionnaire) was evaluated. Somatic maturation through the years of peak growth rate (PVC) was calculated. Results: PVC occurred in women 12.2 ± 0.5 years and boys at 15.6 ± 0.6 years. PA levels were maintained after the VCCT occur. Males showed higher levels of AF in relation to women, both chronological age and biological age (p&lt; 0.001). Conclusion: PA levels were stable after the PVC occurs in both sexes. Males showed higher levels of AF than women. The results suggest increasing levels of AF in women, especially after the somatic maturation occur (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Campos, Rossana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gatica, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viveros-Flores, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cossio-Bolaños, Marco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vargas-Vitoria, Rodrigo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo-Retamal, Marcelo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: verificar los patrones de actividad física (AF) alineados por edad cronológica y biológica, así como analizar las diferencias en función del sexo. Métodos: Se estudiaron a 275 adolescentes (153 varones y 122 mujeres) de una zona geográfica del Perú localizada a 2320 metros sobre el nivel del mar (Arequipa). El rango de edad fue de 11 a 17 años (X&amp;#773;=14.0±2.1 años). Se evaluó el peso, la estatura, la altura tronco-cefálica, la actividad física (por cuestionario). Se calculó la maduración somática por medio de los Años de Pico de Velocidad de Crecimiento (PVC). Resultados: El PVC se produjo en las mujeres a los 12,2±0,5 años y en los varones a los 15,6±0,6 años. Los niveles de AF se mantuvieron después de ocurrir los APVC. Los varones mostraron mayor nivel de AF en relación a las mujeres, tanto por edad cronológica y edad biológica (p&lt; 0,001). Conclusión: Los niveles de AF se mantuvieron estables después de ocurrir el PVC en ambos sexos. Los varones mostraron mayor nivel de AF que las mujeres. Los resultados sugieren incrementar los niveles de AF en las mujeres, en especial, luego de ocurrir la maduración somática (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;35(2): 41-47, 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139270</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patrones de actividad física en adolescentes en función del sexo, edad cronológica y biológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12436</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6278^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
