<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111466</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7113</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Possible treatment of macrocyclic lactone poisoning in pets with intravenous lipids</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Intravenous lipid emulsions (ILE), intended for parenteral nutrition, have been advocated for several years as therapy of humans poisoning by local anesthetics. Their use have been progressively extended to the therapy of other toxicoses, including poisoning of dogs by macrocyclics lactones, with anectodal reports cited in the literature. The Veterinary Pharmacovigilance Centre of Lyon advocated ILE on several occasions. ILE was used in 6 dogs intoxicated by macrocyclic lactones. Results seem sufficiently promising to encourage the systematic use in case of ivermectin or moxidectin toxicosis (accidental ingestion of oral paste or tablets for horses, or inadvertent overdose). It would be advisable in the future further evaluation on a large number of cases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hercberg-Rebelle, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pineau, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Buronfosse-Roque, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Queffélec, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-López, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las emulsiones lipídicas, utilizadas inicialmente en la alimentación parenteral, están siendo propuestas, desde hace algunos años, en el tratamiento de las intoxicaciones humanas por anestésicos locales. Poco a poco, se van citando algunos casos aislados en la literatura científica. El Centro de Fármaco-vigilancia Veterinaria de Lyon (Francia) ha propuesto esta terapéutica en varias tomas y ha analizado la evolución de 6 casos de intoxicación de perros tratados con la administración intravenosa de emulsión lipídica. Los resultados parecen suficientemente esperanzadores para que esta terapéutica sea sistemáticamente propuesta en el futuro tras una ingestión o tratamiento accidental con ivermectina o moxidectina. Sería aconsejable realizar en el futuro nuevas evaluaciones sobre un mayor número de casos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. toxicol;29(1): 40-44, ene.-jun. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111466</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Posible tratamiento con lípidos intravenosos de carnívoros domésticos intoxicados con lactonas macrocíclicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23743^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8230^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4732^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54726</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2376^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7960^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
