<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-66628</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Treatment options for large, compressive goiters are currently limited to surgery and radioiodine administration. Classically, the first-line option has been surgery, with radioiodine therapy being reserved as an lternative treatment in patients with highsurgical risk. We describe the case of an 81-year-old woman with a large, compressive multinodular goiter and hyperthyroidism, substernal extension and associated co-morbidity, contraindicating surgery. We review the efficacy of different treatment options for compressive multinodular goiter, as well as the potential secondary complication (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Iglesias Bolaños, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diaz Guardiola, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pavón de Paz, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guijarro de Armas, Guadalupe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Penín González, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elvira Peña, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Actualmente, las opciones terapéuticas del bocio compresivo se limitan a la cirugía o a la administración de radioyodo. Clásicamente, la cirugía suele plantearse como primera opción, y se reserva el radioyodo para lospacientes de elevado riesgo quirúrgico. Comentamos el caso de una paciente de 81 años, con bocio multinodular (BMN) hiperfuncionante, extensión intratorácica y sintomatología compresiva, en quien la cirugíaestaba contraindicada por enfermedades concomitantes. Revisamos las evidencias de eficacia de las alternativas de tratamiento del BMN compresivo y las posibles complicaciones secundarias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;55(6): 263-266, jun. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-66628</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d6191^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7621^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6191^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14348^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8890^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
