<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045466</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Language and cognitive impairment: a semiological study into visual naming</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The presence of anomia and/or paraphasias in patients with cognitive impairment suggests an associateddeterioration of their language. Visual naming makes it possible to examine these signs in a controlled manner as the targetword is already known. Aim. To conduct a semiological study of naming in normal aging, cognitive impairment and languageimpairment conditions. Subjects and methods. The study consisted in an analysis of nine types of signs (correct response,increased latencies, circumlocutions, absence of response, semantic verbal paraphasias, verbal paraphasias with a similarform, unrelated verbal paraphasias, phonemic paraphasias and neologisms) in a visual naming task (6 items), in two groupswith normal language &#150;controls &gt; 70 years and patients with Alzheimer&#146;s disease (AD) with onset of amnesia&#150; and two groupswith language impairment &#150;vascular aphasia and anomic AD&#150;. Results. Patients failed to perform naming correctly in 4.2% ofthe responses in controls, 10% in patients with amnesic AD, 30% in patients with vascular aphasia and 50% in patients withanomic AD. Semantic paraphasias were observed in the two groups with normal language abilities (controls and amnesic AD),although frequencies were low. Signs that suggest difficulties in accessing/retrieving lexical items were more frequent in patientswith AD and ran parallel to the degree of anomia. One notable finding was the absence of signs of phonological dysfunction inthe two groups with AD, regardless of the degree of anomia. Conclusions. Semiological quantification makes it possible todistinguish differences in the degree of anomia and in the pattern of errors both in controls and in patients with amnesic onsetAD and among patients with vascular aphasia and neurodegenerative anomia</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santos-Lasaosa, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Turrado, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Lázaro, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejero-Juste, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual-Millán, L. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mostacero-Miguel, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piñol-Ripoll, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La presencia de anomia y/o parafasias enpacientes con deterioro cognitivo sugiere un deterioro asociado dellenguaje. La denominación visual permite explorar estos signos deforma controlada al conocerse la palabra diana. Objetivo. Estudiosemiológico de la denominación en el envejecimiento normal, deteriorocognitivo y deterioro del lenguaje. Sujetos y métodos. Análisisde nueve tipos de signos (respuesta correcta, incremento de latencias,circunloquios, ausencia de respuesta, parafasias verbales semánticas,parafasias verbales con similitud formal, parafasias verbalesno relacionadas, parafasias fonémicas y neologismos), en unatarea de denominación visual (6 ítems), en dos grupos con lenguajenormal &#150;controles &gt; 70 años y pacientes con enfermedad de Alzheimer(EA) de inicio amnésico&#150; y dos grupos con deterioro del lenguaje&#150;afasia vascular y EA anómico&#150;. Resultados. La denominaciónfalló en el 4,2% de las respuestas en controles, el 10% en pacientescon EA amnésico, el 30% en pacientes con afasia vascular y el 50%en pacientes con EA anómico. En los dos grupos con lenguaje normal(controles y EA amnésico) se observaron parafasias semánticas,con frecuencias bajas. Los signos que sugieren dificultad en el acceso/recuperación léxica fueron más frecuentes en los pacientes conEA, de forma paralela al grado de anomia. Destaca la ausencia designos de disfunción fonológica en los dos grupos con EA, de formaindependiente del grado de anomia. Conclusión. La cuantificaciónsemiológica permite objetivar diferencias en el grado de anomia yen el perfil de errores, tanto entre controles y pacientes con EA deinicio amnésico, como entre los pacientes con afasia vascular y anomianeurodegenerativa</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;42(10): 578-583, mayo 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045466</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lenguaje y deterioro cognitivo: un estudio semiológico en denominación visual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10557</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7985</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7984^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7984^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1043^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d863^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
