<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96152</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of Fournier`s necrosis in a high complexity hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: To determine clinical characteristics of the population with Fournier`s necrosis at Hospital Universitario del Valle (HUV) in Cali during the period 2003-2008.METHODS: We performed a retrospective review of patients with the diagnosis of Fournier´s necrosis at HUV during the period 2003-2008. We collected information on age, personal history, duration of illness, hospitalization, surgeries performed, time to surgical treatment, isolated germs, and mortality. Univariate descriptive analysis was performed in STATA v 10.1.                                        RESULTS: 42 patients with mean age 51 years and 12 days mean disease duration. 26% had diabetes mellitus and 21.4% urethral trauma before admission. Average time to surgical debridement was 41.4 hours. 62% required suprapubic cystostomy, 14.3% derivative colostomy, 9.5% and 2.4% orchiectomy and penectomy respectively. The average hospital stay was 23 days and 12% required ICU care.Scrotal cultures were positive in 59.5%: 64% a single germ and 36% polymicrobial. Reported mortality was 17%.CONCLUSION: Fournier`s necrosis is a life-threatening clinical entity in patients with multiple comorbidities requiring multiple interventions. Broad-spectrum antimicrobial therapy, aggressive debridement of necrotic tissue and comprehensive management of these patients are the mainstays in the treatment of these severely ill patients(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Osorio, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Herney Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vargas, Andrés Humberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carbonell, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Determinar las características clínicas de la población con Necrosis de Fournier que consulto al Hospital Universitario del Valle (HUV) en Cali durante el período 2003-2008.MÉTODOS: Estudio descriptivo. Se realizo una revisión retrospectiva de los pacientes atendidos por Necrosis de Fournier en el H.U.V durante el período 2003-2008. Se recopilo información sobre la edad, antecedentes personales, tiempo de evolución de la enfermedad, estancia hospitalaria, cirugías realizadas, tiempo hasta el tratamiento quirúrgico, gérmenes aislados y mortalidad. Análisis descriptivo univariado en STATA v 10.1RESULTADOS: 42 pacientes con edad promedio de 51 anos y tiempo de evolución promedio de 12 días. 26% tenían antecedente de diabetes mellitus y 21.4% traumatismo uretral previo al ingreso. El tiempo promedio hasta el desbridamiento quirúrgico fue de 41.4 hrs. 62% requirieron cistotomía suprapúbica, 14.3% colostomía derivativa, 9.5% orquidectomía y 2.4% penectomia. El promedio de estancia hospitalaria fue de 23 días y 12% requirió manejo en UCI.59.5% de los pacientes se le aisló algún germen en escroto de los cuales 64% un único germen y 36% fueron polimicrobiano. La mortalidad reportada fue de 17%.CONCLUSIÓN: La necrosis de fournier es una entidad clínica que amenaza la vida en pacientes con múltiples comorbilidades y con requerimiento de múltiples intervenciones. El manejo antibiótico de amplio espectro, el debridamiento agresivo del tejido necrótico y el manejo integral de estos pacientes son los pilares fundamentales en el tratamiento de éstos pacientes severamente enfermos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;64(10): 948-952, dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96152</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la necrosis de Fournier en un hospital de alta complejidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32750^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32745^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3664^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10693</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
