<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056976</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5665</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Correlation between 6-minute walking test and transthoracic echocardiography for diagnosing chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To determine the diagnostic yield of the 6-minute walking        test (6MWT) to predict chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension        (CTPH) in a cohort of patients with acute pulmonary embolism        (PE).        Methods: The study population included consecutive patients with        confirmed diagnosis of acute symptomatic PE. All patients underwent        transthoracic echocardiography and 6MWT 4 weeks after diagnosis.        The correlation between the distance walked in the 6MWT        and the echocardiographic findings was analized.        Results: Of the 86 study patients, 19% had a diagnosis of pulmonary        hypertension, defined by a systolic pulmonary pressure equal or        greater than 30 mm Hg. With a predefined cut-off point of 300        hundred metres, the negative predictive value of the 6MWT for        CPTH was 93% (95% CI, 85-100). The negative likelihood ratio was        0.3 (95% CI, 0.1-1). There was a significant correlation between        the systolic pulmonary pressure measured by transthoracic echocardiography        and the distance walked in the 6MWT (r = 0.79; P &lt;        0.001).        Conclusions: There is a significant correlation between the systolic        pulmonary pressure measured by transthoracic echocardiography        and the distance walked in the 6MWT</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escobar, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sueiro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo de este estudio fue el evaluar la capacidad de        la prueba de la marcha de 6 minutos (6MWT) para predecir hipertensión        pulmonar tromboembólica crónica (HPTC) en una cohorte        de pacientes con diagnóstico confirmado de tromboembolia de pulmón        (TEP).        Material y metodos: Se incluyó prospectivamente en el estudio a        todos los pacientes diagnosticados de TEP aguda sintomática en un        hospital universitario terciario. Se realizó en todos ellos una ecocardiografía        transtorácica y una prueba de la marcha de 6 minutos a        las 4 semanas del diagnóstico de TEP. Se analizó la correlación entre        la distancia recorrida en el 6MWT y los hallazgos ecocardiográficos.        Resultados: Se estudiaron 86 pacientes con diagnóstico de TEP        aguda sintomática. Dieciséis pacientes (19%) presentaron HPTC        definida por una presión sistólica pulmonar (PSP) igual o mayor a        30 mm Hg. Con un punto de corte de 300 metros, el valor predictivo        negativo del 6MWT para predecir HPTC fue del 93% (IC 95%:        85-100), y el cociente de probabilidad negativo fue de 0.3 (IC 95%:        0.1-1). Existió una correlación estadísticamente significativa entre la        PSP determinada por ecocardiografía transtorácica y la distancia en        metros recorrida en el 6MWT (r = 0.79; P &lt; 0.001).        Conclusiones: Existe una correlación significativa entre la presión        sistólica pulmonar determinada por ecocardiografía transtorácica y        la distancia recorrida en la prueba de la marcha de 6 minutos</dc:description>
<dc:source>MAPFRE med;18(3): 154-158, jul.-sept. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056976</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Correlación entre la prueba de la marcha de 6 minutos y la ecocardiografía transtorácica en el diagnóstico de la hipertensión arterial pulmonar tromboembólica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23233^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5178^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7155^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12092^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
