<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105124</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-1813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Semi-presential university teaching. An experience in the use of SWAD virtual platform</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The new European Space of higher education demands innovation in the university teaching methodology. The use of the new information and communication technologies is a reality in our current society, especially among university students. The use of virtual platforms for teaching is more developed in post graduate lifelong learning than in university education. Materials and methods. This articles narrates an experience in the use of SWAD virtual platform, teaching aid, in the subject course Health and Environment, in the University of Granada. Results and conclusions. The students have a positive opinion about the use of this platform. Their satisfaction level is very high, although it means more dedication and effort than expected. This virtual platform offers academic possibilities that allows us to get close and adapt to the new student profiles. To professors, it means a change in their main activities: preparing and designing contents, virtual tutorials, and forums managing (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Celma-Vicente, Matilde</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-López, M. Ascensión</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Morales, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano-Caballero Gálvez, M. Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quero-Rufián, Aurora</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La innovación en la metodología docente universitaria es una exigencia del nuevo Espacio Europeo de Educación Superior. La utilización de las tecnologías de la información y la comunicación es una realidad de la sociedad actual, y especialmente del alumnado universitario. Materiales y métodos. Este artículo muestra la experiencia en el uso de la plataforma virtual de apoyo a la docencia, en la asignatura de Salud y Medio Ambiente en la Universidad de Granada. Resultados y conclusiones. La opinión de los alumnos es muy favorable hacia su uso. Su nivel de satisfacción es muy alto, aunque les supone una dedicación y esfuerzo mayores a los esperados. La plataforma virtual ofrece unas posibilidades académicas que permiten el acercamiento y adaptación a los nuevos perfiles de alumnado. Para el profesorado supone un cambio en sus principales actividades: la preparación y diseño de contenidos, las tutorías virtuales y la gestión de foros (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Educ. med. (Ed. impr.);14(4): 229-234, dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105124</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Docencia universitaria semipresencial. Experiencia en el uso de la plataforma virtual SWAD</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19371</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33919^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53806^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32065^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
