<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132308</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Concordance between self-reported weight and height for nutritional assessment in a adult aged between 25 and 50 years without higher education</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Overweight and obesity are metabolic disorders that have become a public health problem due to the current high prevalence; therefore, it is important to create simple monitoring systems to assess their trends. Objective: To determine the correlation between weight, height and body mass index reported by patients and the values measured directly in adults between 25 and 50 years old without higher education. Patients and methods: A cross-sectional descriptive study was conducted with participation of 207 adults between 25 and 50 years old. Each participant was asked weight and height; and body mass index was calculated with these data. Moreover, a qualified person determined the real value of these variables. The coefficient of intra-class correlation between self-reported and measurements was obtained. Results: The body mass index measured for men was 25,8±3,7 kg/m2 and for women 26,0±4,1 kg/m2. Intraclass correlation coefficients were for weight 0,962 (IC95%: 0,950-0,971), height 0,909 (IC95%: 0,882-0,930), and body mass index 0,929 (IC95% 0,907-0,945); the real prevalence of people with a body mass index greater than 25 kg/m2 was 52.1%, whereas the value obtained by self-reported data was 44%.  Conclusions: Self-reported weight and height data are useful for obesity assessment in adults aged between 25 and 50 years without higher education at the population level (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mariotta, Sharon</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, Yelixa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Torres, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lee Osomo, Belinda Inés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendoza, Leylis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Epiayu, Yandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, Nelly</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El sobrepeso y la obesidad son desordenes metabólicos que se han convertido en un problema de salud pública debido a la alta prevalencia que presentan actualmente, lo que hace importante crear sistemas de monitoreo sencillos para evaluar su comportamiento. Objetivo: Determinar la concordancia del peso, la talla, el índice de masa corporal auto-reportados versus los medidos directamente, en personas de 25 a 50 años sin educación superior. Pacientes y métodos: estudio descriptivo de corte transversal, en el que participaron 207 personas de ambos sexos entre 25 y 50 años. A cada participante se le preguntó el peso y la talla; y el índice de masa corporal fue calculado a partir de estos datos. Adicional a esto, una persona capacitada determinó el valor real de estas variables. Se  obtuvo el coeficiente de correlación intraclase entre el auto- reporte y las mediciones. Resultados: el valor del índice de masa corporal medido para los hombres fue de 25,8±3,7 kg/m2 y para las mujeres de 26,0±4,1 kg/m2. Los coeficientes de correlación intraclase fueron para el peso: 0,962 (IC95%:0,950-0,971); la estatura: 0,909 (IC95%: 0,882-0,930), y el índice de masa corporal: 0,929 (IC95% 0,907-0,945); la prevalencia real de personas con un índice de masa  corporal superior a 25 kg/m2 fue de 52,1%, mientras que la obtenida por medio de los datos auto-reportados fue de 44%. Conclusiones: Los datos auto-reportados de peso y talla, en personas de 25 a 50 años sin educación superior son útiles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;30(5): 1039-1043, nov. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132308</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Concordancia entre auto-reporte de peso y talla para valoración nutricional en población de 25 a 50 años sin educación superior</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4592</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23861^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1852</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9936^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23861^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9936^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1860</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54263</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201411</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
