<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053836</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Severe pelvic fractures, associated injuries and hemodynamic instability: incidence, management and outcome in our center</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The aim of this study was to review the incidence, treatment and outcome of severe pelvic fractures, as well as associated injuries, in our center.   Patients and method. We performed a retrospective study of patients included in our trauma registry between June 1993 and January 2005. Pelvic fractures were classified according to the system proposed by Tile. Clinical and demographic data such as age, gender, mechanism of injury, transfer time, hemodynamic status, and trauma scores were compared and analyzed statistically. Shock was defined as a systolic blood pressure of &amp;#8804; 90 mmHg during the primary assessment. Mortality and associated risk factors were analyzed, with emphasis on patients in shock on admission.    Results. Of 1274 patients with severe trauma admitted during the study period, 192 (15%) had pelvic fracture. Only 6.7% were isolated fractures and 6% were open fractures. Twenty percent of the patients were in shock on admission. The mean Injury Severity Score of the series was 28.5 ± 14 and that of patients in shock was 38 ± 16. The most frequently associated injuries were thoracic (70%), abdominal (55%), long bone fractures (52%), and head injuries (40%). Twenty-three percent of the patients had retroperitoneal hematoma. Arteriograms were performed in 16 patients, with four embolizations. Eight patients underwent external orthopedic fixation, and none posterior orthopedic fixation. Five patients underwent pelvic packing and two patients underwent ligation of hypogastric arteries. Overall mortality was 30% and mortality in patients in shock was 61%. Predictors of mortality were shock on admission, a Glasgow Coma Scale score of &amp;#8804; 8, ISS &gt; 25 and age &gt; 55 years.   Conclusions. Patients in shock with pelvic fractures have a poor prognosis in our center, frequently related to the severity of associated injuries, the relative rarity of these fractures, and the lack of a clearly defined management protocol. The main cause of death was massive hemorrhage (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Tocino, Juan María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Baena, Darío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Díaz, Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Turégano-Fuentes, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz-Sánchez, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zorrilla-Ortúzar, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lago-Oliver, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El objetivo de esta revisión ha sido conocer la incidencia, lesiones asociadas, tratamiento y resultados obtenidos en el manejo de los pacientes con fracturas graves de pelvis en nuestro centro.                 Pacientes y método. Estudio retrospectivo de los pacientes incluidos en nuestro registro de traumatizados graves entre junio de 1993 y enero de 2005. La clasificación de las fracturas pelvianas se ha realizado con los criterios de Tile. Se comparan y analizan estadísticamente aspectos demográficos y clínicos, incluidos la edad, el sexo, el mecanismo lesivo, tiempo de traslado, la situación hemodinámica al ingreso y las escalas de gravedad. Se ha definido el estado de shock como una presión arterial sistólica &amp;#8804; 90 mmHg durante la revisión primaria. Se analizan la mortalidad y los factores de riesgo asociados, con especial énfasis en el grupo de pacientes en shock.  Resultados. De los 1.274 politraumatizados graves atendidos en el período de estudio, 192 (15%) presentaban fractura pelviana. Muy pocas fracturas se han presentado como lesiones aisladas (6,7%), y el porcentaje de fracturas abiertas ha sido del 6%. El 20% de los pacientes presentaba shock al ingreso. El Injury Severity Score (ISS) medio de la serie fue de 28,5 ± 14, y el de los pacientes en shock fue de 38 ± 16. Las lesiones asociadas más frecuentes fueron las torácicas (70%), seguidas por las abdominales (55%), fracturas de huesos largos (52%) y craneoencefálicas (40%). El 23% de los pacientes presentaba hematoma retroperitoneal. Se realizaron 16 arteriografías y 4 embolizaciones pelvianas. Se colocaron 8 fijadores externos anteriores y ninguno posterior. Se realizaron 5 taponamientos pelvianos y 2 ligaduras de arterias hipogástricas. La mortalidad general fue del 30%, y del 61% en los pacientes en shock al ingreso. El shock a la llegada, una escala de coma de Glasgow &amp;#8804; 8, un ISS &gt; 25 y la edad &gt; 55 años se correlacionaron con la mortalidad. Conclusiones. El pronóstico de los pacientes en shock y con fracturas de pelvis graves en nuestro medio es sombrío y, con frecuencia, está condicionado por la gravedad de las lesiones asociadas, la relativa escasa incidencia de estas fracturas y la heterogeneidad de criterios de manejo de los equipos de guardia. La hemorragia masiva incontrolada ha sido la causa principal de muerte  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);81(6): 316-323, jun. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053836</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fracturas de pelvis graves, lesiones asociadas e inestabilidad hemodinámica: incidencia, manejo y pronóstico en nuestro medio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10577^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22947^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50518^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50518^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4695^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
