<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146119</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Thao-Child Health Programme: community based intervention for healthy lifestyles promotion to children and families: results of a cohort study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: childhood obesity is one of the main public health concerns. The multifactorial and multilevel causes require complex interventions such the community based interventions (CBI). Thao-Child Health Programme is a CBI implemented in Spain since 2007. Goal: show the Thao methodology and the latest cross-sectional and longitudinal results. Methods: longitudinal cohort study (4 years of follow-up) and cross sectional study. Results: the longitudinal study found an increase of 1% in the overweight prevalence after a follow-up of 4 years of Thao-Programme implementation in 10 municipalities with 6 697 children involved. The cross-sectional study carried out with 20 636 children from 22 municipalities found a childhood overweight prevalence of 26.6%. Discussion: currently a brake in the increase of childhood overweight prevalence is considered a success due to the high prevalence worldwide. More studies well methodologically performed are needed to know the efficacy of the CBI&#146;s in this field (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Beltrán de Miguel, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estévez Santiago, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuadrado Vives, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Santos, Santiago Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palacios Gil-Antuñano, Nieves</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas Esteve, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tojo Sierra, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leis Trabazo, María Rosaura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ávila Torres, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varela Moreiras, Gregorio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la obesidad infantil es una de las principales preocupaciones de salud pública. La etiología multifactorial y multinivel requiere de intervenciones complejas como las intervenciones de base comunitaria (CBI). El Programa Thao-Salud Infantil es una CBI implementada en España desde 2007. Objetivo: mostrar la metodología Thao y los últimos resultados transversales y longitudinales. Métodos: estudio de cohortes longitudinal (4 años de seguimiento) y estudio transversal. Resultados: el estudio longitudinal encontró un incremento del 1% en la prevalencia de exceso de peso tras 4 años de implementación del Programa Thao en 10 municipios con 6.697 niños y niñas involucrados. El estudio transversal llevado a cabo con 20.636 niños y niñas de 22 municipios encontró una prevalencia de exceso de peso infantil del 26,6%. Discusión: actualmente un freno en el incremento de la prevalencia de exceso de peso infantil es considerado como un éxito debido a la alta prevalencia a nivel mundial. Son necesarios más estudios metodológicamente bien realizados para conocer la eficacia de las CBI en este campo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(6): 2584-2587, dic. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146119</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Programa Thao-Salud Infantil: intervención de base comunitaria de promoción de estilos de vida saludables en la población infantil y las familias: resultados de un estudio de cohorte</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37738^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32738^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
