<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101856</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of patients&#146; age in the probabilistic models of mortality on admission in general Internal Medicine wards</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: The predictive models of in-hospital mortality in the departments of Internal Medicine have not reached a generalized use. Our hypothesis is that the very elderly patients interfere in the models currently in use. Patients and method:In this observational, prospective cohort study, 1,500 patients admitted consecutively in the department of Internal Medicine were analysed. A logistic regression analysis based on the REMS model was used for the whole series and after segmenting it according to if the age of patients was 85 years or less, or more than 85 years. Results: The global in-hospital mortality of the patients was 12%. Although the REMS model predicted a global mortality of 11.9%, sensitivity and specificity for an individual prediction were not satisfactory because the AUC was only 0.704. When the sample was split according to the age of patients, the model gained precision for the group &amp;#8804; 85 years (AUC 0.799), whereas it lost sensitivity and specificity for the group of patients &gt; 85 years (AUC 0.66). Conclusions: Age of patients interferes in the general models of prediction of mortality in departments of Internal Medicine. There may be important variables in advanced age not taken into account in the predictive models nowadays available. We think that specific predictive models of in-hospital mortality in Internal Medicine should be designed for patients of advanced age (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Francia, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casademont, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Los modelos predictivos de mortalidad intrahospitalaria en los servicios de Medicina Interna no han alcanzado un uso generalizado. Nuestra hipótesis es que la inclusión de pacientes de edad muy avanzada interfiere en los modelos descritos. Pacientes y método: Se trata de un estudio de cohortes prospectivo observacional en el que se incluyeron 1.500 pacientes ingresados consecutivamente en el servicio de Medicina Interna. Se utilizó un análisis de regresión logística basado en el modelo REMS y posteriormente se reprodujo el análisis segmentando la serie según si la edad de los pacientes era de 85 años o menos, o de más de 85 años. Resultados: La mortalidad global intrahospitalaria de los pacientes incluidos en el estudio fue del 12%. A pesar de que el modelo REMS predijo una mortalidad global del 11,9%, la sensibilidad y especificidad para una predicción individual fueron poco satisfactorias, pues el AUC (área bajo la curva) fue únicamente del 0,704. Cuando se segmentó la muestra según la edad de los pacientes, se observó que el modelo ganó precisión para el grupo &amp;#8804; 85 años (AUC 0,799), mientras que la perdió para el grupo de pacientes&gt;85 años (AUC 0,660). Conclusiones: La edad avanzada interfiere en los modelos generales de predicción de mortalidad intrahospitalaria. Posiblemente hay variables importantes en edades avanzadas que no se tienen en cuenta en estos modelos. Creemos que deberían diseñarse modelos predictivos de mortalidad intrahospitalaria específicos para los pacientes de edad avanzada ingresados en los servicios de Medicina Interna (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);139(5): 197-202, jul. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101856</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de la edad en los índices probabilísticos de mortalidad al ingreso en salas convencionales de Medicina Interna</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28633</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30047^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6913^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31670</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201207</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
