<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157178</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-9895</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To identify diagnostic, therapeutic and self-care practices in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) patients which are inadequate, of dubious effectiveness or non cost-effective, both in stable phase and during an exacerbation.  Material and Methods: The study was performed in 3 phases and designed to identify practices which do not add value or must be discouraged in the management of stable COPD and its exacerbations, and also in self-care carried out by the patients.  The first phase was carried out by the Metaplan technique in which the most frequent practices which had to be clearly discouraged were rated and selected . The second phase was made through the web by a consensus conference technique that allowed to evaluate and select hierarchically recommendations based on the frequency of occurrence and intensity of the practices which were found useless or harmful. In the third phase a technical file on each of the final recommendations was created. It includes the description of the practices which must be eradicated, evidence levels and recommendation degrees, as well as indicators of the measure achieved thanks to the change in practice.  Results: The results are shown in a table that summarizes &#145;do not do&#146; practices in COPD, the frequency with which the practice is discouraged and the intensity with which the practice is inadequate, both in stable and exacerbated COPD and in practices carried out by patients. In addition, there will be a technical file developed for each recommendation with denomination, justification and evidence level of the recommendation. Indicators, permitting to evaluate collected data and the improvements  reached by decreasing inadequate, ineffective or non cost-effective practices, will also be developed.  Conclusions: &#145;Do not do&#146; recommendations in COPD will improve the management of this patology by reducing inadequate or non cost-effective diagnostic, therapeutic or care practices (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno Zabaleta, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero Lozano, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Soler, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Torralba, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Lobato, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo Corbella, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernando Sanz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salgado Aranda, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez Palomo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villar Álvarez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mira Solves, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Simón Rodríguez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Identificar en pacientes con enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica (EPOC) prácticas diagnósticas, terapéuticas y de autocuidado que resultan inadecuadas, de dudosa efectividad o que no son coste-efectivas, tanto en fase estable como durante una agudización.  Material y método: El estudio se ha organizado en 3 fases y diseñado para identificar prácticas que no aportan valor o que deben desaconsejarse en el manejo de la EPOC estable y agudizada, y en los autocuidados llevados a cabo por estos pacientes.  La primera fase se realizó mediante la técnica Metaplan en la que se puntuaron y seleccionaron las prácticas que con más frecuencia claramente debían desaconsejarse. La segunda fase se hizo a través de la web mediante una técnica de conferencia de consenso que permitió la valoración y la selección jerarquizada de las recomendaciones en función de la frecuencia en que ocurren y la intensidad en el que esa práctica resultaba inútil o perjudicial. En la tercera fase se elaboró una ficha descriptiva de cada una de las recomendaciones finales, que incluye la descripción de la práctica a erradicar, el nivel de evidencia y grado de recomendación y los indicadores de la medida en que se ha logrado un cambio en la práctica.  Resultados: Los resultados se mostrarán en una tabla que recogerá las prácticas &#145;no hacer&#146; en la EPOC, con la frecuencia con que se produce la práctica que se desaconseja y la intensidad con que la práctica resulta inadecuada, tanto en la EPOC estable como en la EPOC agudizada y en las prácticas realizadas por los pacientes. Además, se desarrollará en una ficha técnica para cada recomendación en el que se expondrá la denominación, la justificación y el nivel de evidencia de la recomendación.  También se elaborarán indicadores que permitan evaluar los datos recogidos y que se haya logrado cambiar la práctica inadecuada, ineficaz o no coste-efectiva.  Conclusiones: Las recomendaciones &#145;Qué no hacer en la EPOC&#146; mejorarán el manejo de esta patología al reducir las prácticas diagnósticas, terapéuticas o de cuidados que sean inadecuadas o no coste-efectivas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. patol. respir;19(3): 76-82, jul.-sept. 2016. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157178</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Qué no hacer en la EPOC. Análisis metodológico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19291^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33121^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54219^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33125</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10221</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36300^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3979^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54376^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8675^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
