<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113546</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Association of multiseptated gall-bladder and cholelithiasis in a newborn with Down´s syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Multiseptate gallbladder is a rare congenital malformation of the gallbladder and its etiopathogenesis is unclear. Down syndrome or trisomy 21 may be associated with gastrointestinal abnormalities or malformations. Clinicians and radiologists should know that patients with multiseptate gallbladder and Down syndrome are at risk of development gallstones, for early diagnosis and appropriate management. We report an asymptomatic case, who was diagnosed incidentally on ultrasound and  review the literature (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Vega-Leal, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Flores, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez López, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La vesícula multiseptada es una malformación congénita rara de la vesícula biliar cuya etiopatogenia es incierta. En el síndrome de Down o trisomía 21 pueden encontrarse anomalías o malformaciones gastrointestinales asociadas. Clínicos y radiólogos debemos saber que los pacientes con vesícula multiseptada y/o síndrome de Down tienen aumentado el riesgo de desarrollar litiasis biliar, para realizar un diagnóstico precoz y un manejo adecuado. Presentamos una recién nacida asintomática con estas entidades, diagnosticada incidentalmente mediante ecografía y revisamos la literatura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;68(3): 223-225, mayo-jun. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113546</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asociación de vesicular multiseptada y colelitiasis en una recién nacida con síndrome de Down</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5843^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
