<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136830</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">GHB: an overview</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper gives an overview of the nature, effects and related harms of gamma-hydroxybutyrate (GHB), a drug with depressant effects upon the central nervous system. It also gives a summary of research conducted to date on those who use GHB for recreational purposes. The illicit use of GHB has increased in a number of developed countries over the past decade, largely among users of other illicit drugs. Those using illicit GHB seem to be users of other illicit drugs, who tend to use GHB in combination with other drugs, which may increase the harms associated with such use. Given numerous reports of overdose on GHB, and high rates of self-reported overdose on GHB, it would appear that the risk of overdose on this drug is high. The majority of overdoses reported are non-fatal, and many remit with full recovery, but deaths have been reported and there are a number of possible harms that may occur to users during unconsciousness. Dependence following regular use has been reported and appears to be common among heavy long-term users. Treatments for dependent GHB use remain to be developed, but treatment for withdrawal has been reported and seems important given the seriousness of withdrawal from GHB and related drugs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Degenhardt, Louisa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se revisa la naturaleza, efectos y daños asociados al GHB (gamma-hidroxibutirato), una droga con efectos depresores sobre el sistema nervioso central y se resumen las investigaciones realizadas para analizar los efectos sobre consumidores recreativos. El consumo ilegal de GHB se ha extendido, en la última década, en ciertos países desarrollados, especialmente entre consumidores de otras drogas ilegales. Las personas que utilizan GHB suelen consumir también otras drogas, ingiriendo ambas de una manera combinada, lo que puede incrementar los daños asociados. La existencia de un importante número de informes sobre casos de sobredosis de GHB y el elevado número de casos de sobredosis referidos por los propios consumidores, indican que el riesgo de sobredosis con esta droga es muy alto. La mayoría de las sobredosis no tienen consecuencias fatales y muchas finalizan con una total recuperación, pero también se han indicado algunas muertes, además de los posibles daños que pueden aparecer mientras los consumidores se encuentran inconscientes. El consumo regular de GHB genera dependencia y ésta es común en consumidores habituales de larga duración. El tratamiento de la dependencia generada por GHB se encuentra aún en fase de desarrollo, pero se han descrito tratamientos para el síndrome de abstinencia, lo que parece relevante dada la gravedad de dicho síndrome (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);15(supl.2): 167-177, 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136830</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">GHB: Un análisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54899^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d772^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13364^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50245</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200300</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
