<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-63351</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article summarizes the data reported to the 2006 registry of the Spanish Society of Cardiology Working Group on Cardiac Catheterization and Interventional Cardiology. Data were obtained from 135 centers. Of these, 125 performed catheterizations mainly in adults, while 10 carried out procedures in pediatric patients only. In 2006, 126,196 diagnostic catheterizations were carried out. Of these, 113,228 were coronary angiograms, 7.6% more than in 2005. The population-adjusted rate was 2560 coronary angiograms per million inhabitants. A total of 57,041 percutaneous coronary interventions were performed, which was 7.8% more than in the previous year and which corresponds to a rate of 1293 per million inhabitants. Stents were used in 96.1% of coronary interventions. Overall, 90,006 stents were implanted, of which 59.3% were drug-eluting stents. Moreover, 10,067 interventions were carried out for acute myocardial infarction, 20.6% more than in 2005 and accounting for 17.6% of all percutaneous coronary interventions. Non-coronary interventions were most frequently performed for adult congenital heart disease, with closure of an atrial septal defect being the most numerous, at 334 procedures. Percutaneous mitral valvuloplasties were performed in 431 cases, a similar figure to that recorded in the previous registry, and the success rate was 93.6%. Each year, radial access continues to be used more frequently for coronary procedures. Finally, it is important to emphasize that a high percentage of laboratories reported results, which ensures that the data presented here can serve as an international reference source for percutaneous cardiac interventions performed in Spain (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mauri, Josepa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baz, José A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albarrán, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinar, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presentan los resultados del Registro de Actividad de la Sección de Hemodinámica y Cardiología Intervencionista de la Sociedad Española de Cardiología del año 2006. Se recogen los datos de 135 hospitales, de los cuales 125 realizan su actividad predominante en adultos y 10 atienden exclusivamente a pacientes pediátricos. Se realizaron 126.196 estudios diagnósticos, con 113.228 coronariografías, lo que representa un aumento del 7,6% respecto al año 2005 y una tasa de 2.560 coronariografías/millón de habitantes. Se realizaron 57.041 procedimientos intervencionistas coronarios, con un incremento del 7,8% respecto al 2005 y una tasa de 1.293 intervenciones/millón de habitantes. Se implantaron 90.006 stents, de los cuales el 59,3% fueron farmacoactivos. Se llevaron a cabo 10.067 procedimientos de intervencionismo en el infarto agudo de miocardio, lo que supone un incremento del 20,6% respecto al año anterior y representa el 17,6% del total de las intervenciones coronarias percutáneas. El intervencionismo no coronario más frecuente se realiza en las cardiopatías congénitas del adulto, como el cierre de la comunicación interauricular, que es el de mayor número, 334 procedimientos. La valvuloplastia mitral, con 431 casos tratados, apenas presenta cambios respecto al anterior Registro, y su éxito está en el 93,6%. La vía de acceso radial se usa cada vez más y mantiene el aumento de años anteriores. Es de destacar el alto grado de participación de los diferentes centros en el actual Registro, que hace que sea un referente internacional de la actividad hemodinámica en nuestro país (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;60(12): 1273-1289, dic. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-63351</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d28402</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6484^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6590</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13884^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
