<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92811</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tako-tsubo syndrome. Transient left ventricular dyskinesia. Presentation of our casuistics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This syndrome was described in 1990. It is characterized by chest pain that simulatesan acute coronary syndrome (ACS), with alterations in the ECG, but with normal coronaryarteries. We present 16 patients admitted in our ICU, who met the criteria of transient leftventricular dysfunction syndrome (TLVDS). All but 1 patient were women, with age in generalhigher than 55 years. Chest pain was detected in the 75% of them. A total of 43% had emotionalstress as 56% had an elevation of the ST segment, essentially anterolateral. The increase of thebiomarkers was slight-to-moderate, with the exception of one patient in whom it was especiallyhigh. All of them had undergone a coronary arteriogram and ventriculography, and either septalor anterolateral dyskinesia had been detected, with normal ejection fraction. In 75% of the casesthe dyskinesia had disappeared between 4 days to 6 weeks (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blasco Navalpotro, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villar Molina, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Del Nogal Sáez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Abad, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meyer García-Sípido, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grande Ingelmo, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este síndrome fue descrito en 1990, y se caracteriza por dolor torácico que simula un síndrome coronario agudo (SCA), alteraciones en el ECG y coronarias sin lesiones. Presentamos 16 pacientes ingresados en nuestra UCI, con criterios de síndrome de discinesia transitoria del ventrículo izquierdo (SDTVI). Todos nuestros pacientes menos uno eran mujeres con edad, en general, mayor de 55 años. Se detectó dolor torácico en el 75% de los pacientes. Un 43% tuvo como desencadenante una situación estresante emocional. Un 56% tuvo elevación del ST. La elevación de biomarcadores fue ligera-moderada, salvo en un paciente que fue especialmente elevado. A todos se les realizó coronariografía y ventriculografía, detectándose una discinesia septal o anterolateral, con fracción de eyección normal en el 75% de los casos. La discinesia desapareció entre los 4 días y las 6 semanas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);35(5): 307-311, jun.-jul. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92811</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de tako-tsubo. Discinesia transitoria del ventrículo izquierdo. Presentación de nuestra casuística</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52615^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201107</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
