<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97725</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of CYP2C19 polymorphisms in platelet reactivity and prognosis in an unselected population of non ST elevation acute coronary syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. CYP2C19*2 and CYP2C19*17 alleles appear to contribute to heterogeneous clopidogrel metabolism. The aims of the present study were to assess the phenotype-genotype relationship of CYP2C19*2 and *17 allele carriage and to explore the clinical impact of those polymorphisms at 6-month follow-up of an acute event in an unselected population of non-ST elevation acute coronary syndrome. Methods. Recruitment for the first and second objectives was 40 stable acute coronary syndrome patients under dual antiplatelet therapy at 12 months after coronary stent placement and an unselected population of 493 consecutive patients with non-ST elevation acute coronary syndrome, respectively. Platelet reactivity was assessed by optical aggregometry induced by adenosine diphosphate and thrombin receptor activating peptide, and by vasodilator-stimulated phosphoprotein phosphorylation measurement using flow cytometry. Genotypes were determined with a TaqMan assay. Results. Only the vasodilator-stimulated phosphoprotein phosphorylation measurement detected significant differences in on-clopidogrel platelet reactivity between the wild-type subjects and the CYP2C19*2 (P=.020) and *17 allele carriers (P=.048). No significant difference was found between CYP2C19*2 ([HR (95%CI): 1 (0.94-1.55)], P=.984) or *17 ([HR (95%CI): 0.93 (0.61-1.43)], P=.753) allele carriage and the occurrence of adverse events at 6-month follow-up. Conclusions. Even though CYP2C19 genotype is associated with variable on-clopidogrel platelet reactivity, it has no significant clinical influence. Prognosis of acute coronary syndromes may be influenced by a myriad of variables (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lozano, María L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Vega, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastor, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valdés, Mariano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jover, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivera, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hurtado, José A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tello-Montoliu, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernal, Agustina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Los alelos CYP2C19*2 y *17 parecen relacionarse con la variabilidad en el metabolismo del clopidogrel. Los objetivos del presente estudio son valorar la relación fenotipo-genotipo asociada a los polimorfismos CYP2C19*2 y *17 y explorar el impacto clínico de estos polimorfismos durante 6 meses de seguimiento en una población no seleccionada con síndrome coronario agudo sin elevación del segmento ST. Métodos. Se reclutó a 40 pacientes estables doblemente antiagregados, 12 meses después del implante de stent coronario para el primer objetivo, y a 493 pacientes ingresados con síndrome coronario agudo sin elevación del segmento ST para el segundo. La reactividad plaquetaria se evaluó mediante agregometría óptica estimulando las plaquetas con adenosina difosfato o péptido activador del receptor de trombina, y valorando la fosfoproteína estimulada por vasodilatadores fosforilada mediante citometría de flujo. El genotipo para los polimorfismos CYP2C19*2 y *17 se analizó con sondas TaqMan. Resultados. Sólo el test de fosforilación de fosfoproteína estimulada por vasodilatadores mostró diferencias significativas en la reactividad plaquetaria entre los pacientes portadores y no portadores de los alelos CYP2C19*2 (p=0,020) y *17 (p=0,048). No se observó asociación con el pronóstico a 6 meses de los alelos CYP2C19*2 ([HR (IC95%): 1 (0,94-1,55)], p=0,984) y *17 ([HR (IC95%): 0,93 (0,61-1,43)], p=0,753). Conclusiones. Los polimorfismos de CYP2C19 *2 y *17 se relacionaron con la reactividad plaquetaria, pero no con el pronóstico a 6 meses, en el que multitud de variables deben influir (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;65(3): 219-226, mar. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97725</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de los polimorfismos de CYP2C19 en la reactividad plaquetaria y el pronóstico en una población no seleccionada de pacientes con síndrome coronario agudo sin elevación del ST</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11547^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11547^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22965^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d485</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35532</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
