<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94257</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Chronic bronchial infection: the problem of Pseudomonas aeruginosa</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pathogenic bronchopulmonary colonizations and the exacerbations produced are among the most importantcauses of reduced pulmonary function in patients with bronchiectasis. The most frequent pathogens in thesepatients are Haemophilus influenzae and Pseudomonas aeruginosa. Lesions are produced by the localinflammatory process and the vicious circle developed by antigen stimulation, the release of inflammatorymediators, the presence of neutrophils, the increase of bacterial inoculum and the release of bacterialexoproducts. P. aeruginosa has been demonstrated to affect the patients with bronchiectasis and poorestquality of life and to colonize those with the poorest pulmonary function and the highest number ofantimicrobial treatments. In bronchiectasis, as in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) or cysticfibrosis, P. aeruginosa is able to colonize the respiratory mucosa chronically. Due to the ecological nicheoccupied by P. aeruginosa and the multitude of cycles with antimicrobial agents to which these patients aresubjected, the development of antimicrobial resistance is highly likely, encouraged by the high proportion ofhypermutation variants in existence. Likewise, P. aeruginosa naturally grows in the form of biofilms on themucosal surface, greatly contributing to its persistence. Antimicrobial treatment in patients withbronchiectasis and P. aeruginosa colonization should be based on antimicrobial agents, alone or incombination, that do not lose activity when acting on biofilms(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cantón, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meseguer, María Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez G. de la Pedrosa, Elia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Olmos, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campo, Rosa del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La colonización patogénica broncopulmonar y las exacerbaciones que se derivan de ella constituyen las causasmás importantes del deterioro de la función pulmonar en los pacientes con bronquiectasias. Haemophilusinfluezae y Pseudomonas aeruginosa son los patógenos más frecuentes en estos pacientes. El efecto lesivo seproduce por el proceso de inflamación local y el círculo vicioso que se desarrolla por el estímulo antigénico, laliberación de mediadores de la inflamación, la presencia de neutrófilos, el aumento del inóculo bacteriano yla liberación de exoproductos bacterianos. Se ha demostrado que P. aeruginosa afecta a los pacientes con bronquiectasiascon peor calidad de vida, coloniza a los que tienen peor funcionalidad pulmonar y mayor númerode tratamientos antimicrobianos. En las bronquiectasias, al igual que en la enfermedad pulmonar obstructivacrónica (EPOC) o fibrosis quística, P. aeruginosa es capaz de colonizar crónicamente la mucosa respiratoria.Debido al nicho ecológico donde se sitúa P. aeruginosa y a la multitud de ciclos con antimicrobianos a los queson sometidos estos pacientes es fácil que se desarrollen resistencias a los antimicrobianos, favorecidas por laelevada proporción de variantes hipermutadoras que existen. Asimismo, hay que resaltar la forma natural decrecimiento en biopelículas de P. aeruginosa en la superficie mucosa y la contribución que ejerce para su persistencia.El tratamiento antimicrobiano en los pacientes con bronquiectasas con colonización por P.aeruginosa ha de basarse en antimicrobianos o asociaciones de éstos que no pierdan actividad al actuar sobrelas biopelículas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;47(supl.6): 8-13, jun. 2011. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94257</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infección bronquial crónica: el problema de Pseudomonas aeruginosa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11988^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22165^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2017^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2017^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2017^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11988^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11988^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11988^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
