<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127958</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1582</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cytological diagnosis in breast pathology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The diagnosis of breast lesions is multidisciplinary, with participation by clinicians, radiologists, and pathologists. Fine-needle aspiration cytology of the breast is a technically simple and inexpensive procedure and the results can be made available immediately. This procedure can improve the management of patients with breast disease. Since the introduction of mammographic screening, more breast lesions are being detected and aspirated at a premalignant or preinvasive stage. Cytological interpretation of the findings can be very difficult and requires further investigation such as core needle biopsy. Despite these limitations, breast cytology remains the technique of choice for the study of axillary lymph nodes, recurrences, and metastatic lesions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Combalia, Neusa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El diagnóstico de las lesiones mamarias se realiza de forma multidisciplinar entre clínicos, radiólogos y patólogos. La citología por punción-aspiración con aguja fina de la mama es un procedimiento técnicamente simple, barato, de resultados inmediatos, cuya efectividad ha sido probada en el manejo de pacientes con enfermedad mamaria. Desde la introducción del screening mamográfico, la mayoría de dichas lesiones se aspiran en estadios premalignos o preinvasivos. Su interpretación citológica puede ser muy difícil y requerir estudios posteriores, como la core-biopsia. A pesar de estas limitaciones, la citología mamaria sigue siendo la técnica de elección para el estudio de ganglios axilares, lesiones metastásicas y recidivas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. senol. patol. mamar. (Ed. impr.);27(4): 183-189, oct.-dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127958</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico citológico en patología mamaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1965^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1965^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1965^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29170^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29170^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29170^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3599^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3599^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29170^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3599^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3599^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3599^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1732^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
