<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120174</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-123X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Potentially malignant disorders. Clinical aspects</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In 2005 a committee of experts, coordinated by the WHO Collaborating Centre for Oral Cancer and Precancer, establishes the concept and classification of potentially malignant oral disorders. The most common in our country are: leukoplakia, erythroplakia, lichen planus, actinic keratosis and discoid lupus erythematosus. In this paper we describe the most common clinical manifestations of these disorders. Knowledge of the clinical features facilitates early diagnosis as a measure of oral cancer prevention (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blanco Carrión, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Otero Rey, E. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco-Carrión, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peñamaría-Mallón, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el año 2005 un Comité de Expertos, coordinado por el Centro Colaborador de la OMS para el Cáncer Oral y Precáncer, establece el concepto y clasificación de los trastornos orales potencialmente malignos. Los más frecuentes en nuestro medio son: la leucoplasia, eritroplasia, liquen plano, queilitis o queratosis actínica del labio y el lupus eritematoso discoide. En este trabajo se describen las manifestaciones clínicas más frecuentes de los dichos trastornos. El conocimiento de sus características clínicas facilita el diagnóstico precoz como medida de prevención del cáncer oral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>RCOE;18(2): 101-110, jun. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120174</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desórdenes orales potencialmente malignos. Manifestaciones clínicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11665^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22542^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5008^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2658^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22570^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22548^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53221^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31345^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
