<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100974</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Consensus document on the management after hospital discharge of patient with hyperglycaemia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present document intends to adapt the general recommendations set up in a consensus to elaborate the hospital discharge report in medical specialties to the specific needs of the hospitalized diabetic population. Diabetes is an illness with a very high health cost, being the global risk of death in people with diabetes almost double than in non-diabetes people, justifying the fact that diabetes constitutes one of the most frequent diagnoses in hospitalized patients and the growing interest upon hyperglycaemia management during hospitalization and at discharge. To set up an adequate treatment plan at discharge suitable for each patient, the most important elements to take into account are the etiology and prior hyperglycaemia treatment, the patient's clinical situation and the degree of glycaemia control. Due to instability of glycaemia control, it is also needed to anticipate the educational needs for each patient, as well as to set up the monitoring schedule and follow-up at discharge, and an adequate treatment plan at discharge (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mediavilla Bravo, José Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Guisasola, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Huelgas, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Menéndez Torre, Edelmiro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Pérez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Alegría, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente documento se pretende adaptar las recomendaciones generales establecidas en un consenso para la elaboración del informe de alta hospitalaria en especialidades médicas a las necesidades específicas de la población diabética hospitalizada. La diabetes es una enfermedad con un coste sanitario muy elevado, siendo el riesgo global de muerte entre personas con diabetes casi el doble que entre personas sin diabetes, lo que justifica que esta patología constituya uno de los diagnósticos más frecuentes en los pacientes hospitalizados y el creciente interés sobre el tratamiento de la hiperglucemia durante la hospitalización y al alta. Para establecer un plan de tratamiento al alta adecuado a cada paciente, los elementos más importantes a tener en cuenta son la etiología y el tratamiento previo de la hiperglucemia, la situación clínica del paciente y el grado de control glucémico. Debido a la inestabilidad del control glucémico también es necesario prever las necesidades educativas de cada paciente, así como establecer las pautas de monitorización y seguimiento al alta, y un adecuado plan de tratamiento al alta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);138(15): 666-666, mayo 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100974</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Documento de consenso sobre el tratamiento al alta hospitalaria del paciente con hiperglucemia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7124^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3285^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10545^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7124^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
