<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96144</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-6581</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Regular Pilates and fitness class participants vs non exercisers. A comparison of functional strength capacity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Pilates is a mind-body exercise program gaining in popularity and acceptanceby health and physical activity professionals, but there is a scarcity of scientific research.The aim of this study was to evaluate functional strength capacity between three groups:regular exercisers of Pilates Method, regular fitness class participants, and a non-exercisersgroup (regular exercise = at least 2 days per week for three consecutive months).Method: The total sample comprised 54 subjects, 14,5% men (n = 8) and 85,5% women (n = 47).The mean age of the sample was 41,11 (SD = 7.75) years. All volunteers completed the StrengthFunctional Capacity battery.Results: There were significant differences in squat test (F[2,51]=4.67, P &lt; .05) and back endurancetest (F[2,52]=4.54, P &lt; .05) among the three groups. Post-hoc analyses showed thatPilates Method participants scored higher vs non-exercisers in Squat test (Pilates [M = 41.67;SD = 9.52] vs non-exercisers [M = 30.65; SD = 14.24]) and back endurance test (Pilates [M = 158.52;SD = 56.92] vs non-exercisers [M = 115.04; SD = 34.58]).Conclusions: Pilates Method is associated with good scores in the functional strength capacitybattery(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Pastor, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aznar Laín, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laguna Nieto, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: El método Pilates es un sistema de ejercicio mente-cuerpo con cadavez más popularidad y reconocimiento en al ámbito de la actividad física encaminada a lamejora de la salud, pero las evidencias científicas, por el momento, son escasas. El objetivo deeste estudio fue valorar y comparar la capacidad de fuerza funcional en tres grupos diferentes:practicantes habituales de método Pilates, practicantes habituales de clases colectivas de fitness,y sedentarios (practicantes habituales = 2 días por semana durante los últimos tres mesesconsecutivos).Métodos: La muestra completa comprendía 54 sujetos, 14,5% hombres (n = 8) y 85,5% mujeres(n = 47), con una media de edad de 41,11±7,75 años. Todos los participantes completaron labatería de test Functional Strength Capacity Battery (Yeoman &amp; Liebeson, 1996).Resultados: Se encontraron diferencias significativas en el test de sentadillas (F[2,51]=4,67;p&lt;0,05) y en el test de fuerza de la espalda (F[2,52]=4,54; p &lt; 0,05) entre los tres grupos. Losanálisis post-hoc indicaron que el grupo que practicó Pilates tuvo un nivel significativamente másalto que el grupo sedentario en dos pruebas: sentadillas (Pilates [M = 41,67; SD = 9,52] vs sedentario[M = 30,65; SD = 14,24]) y fuerza-resistencia de espalda (Pilates [M = 158,52; SD = 56,92] vssedentario [M = 115,04; SD = 34,58]).Conclusiones: La práctica regular de método Pilates se asoció con mejores resultados en laspruebas de fuerza funcional(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apunts, Med. esport (Internet);46(172): 169-175, oct.-dic. 2011. îlus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96144</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de la capacidad de fuerza funcional entre tres grupos de ejercicio: participantes regulares de clases dirigidas de fitness, de método Pilates y sedentarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30732^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6324^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
