<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164694</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Rationale for cardio-oncology units</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">With the rapidly rising number of patients surviving cancer, often in the setting of new or pre-existing cardiovascular disease and risk factors, a need has arisen for a specialty within the realm of cardiovascular care that can evaluate and manage these patients along with our colleagues in oncology and hematology. By the same token, all health care providers involved in the care of cancer patients with heart disease must be fully aware of the impact of adverse cardiovascular effects on the survival of these patients. Collaboration is required to mitigate the effect of cardiovascular toxicity associated with these necessary life-saving cancer therapies. The cardio-oncologist plays a pivotal role in bridging the 2 specialties, by creating a comprehensive plan to address the comorbidities as well as to provide guidance on the optimal choice of therapy. In this 3-part review, we will outline: a) the significant impact of cancer therapies on the cardiovascular health of patients with cancer and cancer survivors, b) the advantage of a multidisciplinary team in addressing these cardiovascular complications, and c)the delivery of clinical care to patients with cancer and heart disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villarraga, Hector R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nhola, Lara F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Con el número cada vez mayor de supervivientes al cáncer, a menudo con enfermedades cardiovasculares o factores de riesgo preexistentes o nuevos, ha surgido la necesidad de una nueva especialidad en el ámbito de la atención cardiovascular que pueda evaluar y tratar a estos pacientes, conjuntamente con nuestros colegas de hematología y oncología. De la misma manera, todos los proveedores de atención médica que participan en el cuidado de pacientes con cáncer y enfermedad cardiaca deben ser plenamente conscientes del impacto adverso de la enfermedad cardiovascular en la supervivencia de estos pacientes. La colaboración es necesaria para mitigar el efecto de la toxicidad cardiovascular asociada con estas terapias anticancerosas que salvan vidas. Los cardio-oncólogos tienen un papel fundamental en la unión entre las dos especialidades creando un plan integral para abordar las comorbilidades y proporcionando orientación para la elección del tratamiento óptimo. En esta revisión de 3 partes se describen: a) el impacto significativo de las terapias anticancerosas en la salud cardiovascular de los pacientes con cáncer y los supervivientes a este; b) la ventaja de un equipo multidisciplinario para abordar estas complicaciones cardiovasculares, y c) la prestación de atención clínica a los pacientes con cáncer y enfermedad cardiaca (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;70(7): 583-589, jul. 2017. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164694</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fundamentos de las unidades de cardio-oncología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d55593^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d974^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10542^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30214^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53221</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29924^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201707</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
