<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104966</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Preoperative weight loss in bariatric surgery candidate patients. evidence-based recommendations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction Bariatric surgery is becoming increasingly more common in the treatment of morbid obesity in our hospitals. One of the measures being used to optimise the results of this surgery seems to be the standardising the preoperative weight loss. As there are no universal recommendations for carrying out this weight loss, a review of this topic is presented. Objectives To analyse whether sufficient scientific evidence exists to recommend preoperative weight loss in candidate patients for bariatric surgery. What would be the best options to carry out this weight loss is also analysed, as well as making some recommendations based on the scientific evidence. Results There is great heterogeneity in the designs of the different studies, with different guidelines for weight loss and various surgical techniques. However, preoperative weight loss leads to a decrease in the size of the liver and intra-abdominal fat, which improves the surgical field and intra-operative view, which in turn helps during the surgical act, both in open as well as laparoscopic surgery. There is no consensus on the effect of preoperative weight loss has in predicting the medium or long term results after bariatric surgery. Conclusion The current scientific evidence makes preoperative weight loss recommendable in candidate patients for bariatric surgery. However, there is no consensus on what is the best procedure to achieve this preoperative weight loss (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escrig-Sos, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Ramos, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvador-Sanchis, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción La cirugía bariátrica es cada vez más frecuente para el tratamiento de la obesidad mórbida en nuestros centros. Entre las medidas utilizadas para optimizar los resultados de esta cirugía parece estar generalizándose la pérdida de peso preoperatoria. No existen unas recomendaciones universales para realizar esta pérdida de peso preoperatoria, por lo que se plantea un trabajo de revisión al respecto. Objetivos Analizar si existe suficiente evidencia científica para recomendar la pérdida de peso preoperatoria en pacientes candidatos a cirugía bariátrica. Analizar cuáles serían las mejores opciones para realizar esta pérdida y hacer unas recomendaciones basadas en la evidencia científica. Resultados Existe una gran heterogeneidad en los diseños de los diferentes estudios, con diferentes pautas de pérdida de peso y diferentes técnicas quirúrgicas. No obstante, la pérdida de peso preoperatoria produce una disminución del tamaño hepático y de la grasa intraabodminal, lo que mejora los campos quirúrgicos, la visión intraoperatoria y, por tanto, facilita el acto quirúrgico, tanto en cirugía abierta como laparoscópica. No existe consenso sobre el efecto que la pérdida de peso preoperatoria tiene para predecir los resultados a medio y largo plazo tras cirugía bariátrica. Conclusión La evidencia científica actual hace recomendable la pérdida de peso preoperatoria en pacientes candidatos a cirugía bariátrica. Sin embargo, no existe consenso sobre cuál es el mejor procedimiento para obtener esta pérdida de peso preoperatoria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);90(3): 147-155, mar. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104966</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pérdida de peso preoperatoria en pacientes candidatos a cirugía bariátrica. Recomendaciones basadas en la evidencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51221^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38836^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53366^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23862</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4071^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
