<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111246</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Promoting routine human immunodeficiency virus testing in primary care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives To promote human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) testing in the primary care setting and to describe patients&#146; attitudes toward this practice. Methods A non-randomized intervention was conducted on five physicians of an urban primary care center attending patients aged 18-65 years old, who were scheduled to undergo blood tests for other reasons. The patients were systematically offered HIV blood testing if they reported having had sex without a condom with a person of unknown HIV status. Not being tested required active refusal. The intervention period was from October to December 2008 and the control period was from October to December 2007. The main variable was the difference in the number of HIV tests requested. The proportion of patients accepting the test was also analyzed. Results Demographic factors were similar in patients in the two periods. The number of HIV tests increased from 3.7% (22/599) to 27.2% (212/780), p &lt;0.001. A total of 209 patients were offered the HIV test. Their mean age was 45.6 years (SD 11.7), 141 were women (68%) and 11 were born outside Spain (5%). One hundred and ninety-five patients (93%) admitted the possibility of having been or being at risk. Of these patients, only three (1.5%), refused the HIV test. Conclusions Routine HIV testing in the primary care setting is feasible and few patients refuse to be tested (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Losa-García, Juan E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Cabo, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Moreno, Asunción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias-González, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias-Franco, Higinio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fajardo-Alcántara, Angélica</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos Promover la prueba diagnóstica frente al virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana (VIH) en atención primaria y describir su aceptación. Métodos Estudio de intervención no aleatorizado en un centro de salud urbano sobre cinco médicos de atención primaria que atendían pacientes de 18 a 65 años de edad a quienes se iba a realizar un análisis de sangre por otro motivo. Se ofreció sistemáticamente la realización de la prueba del VIH si reconocían haber mantenido una relación sexual sin usar preservativo con una persona de la que desconocían su estado serológico frente al VIH. No realizarse la prueba del VIH requería una negativa expresa. El periodo de intervención fue de octubre a diciembre de 2008, y el periodo control de octubre a diciembre de 2007. La variable principal del estudio fue la diferencia en el número de pruebas del VIH solicitadas. Se analizó también la aceptación de dicha prueba. Resultados No hubo diferencias en las características demográficas de los pacientes en los dos periodos. El número de pruebas del VIH se incrementó de un 3,7% (22/599) a un 27,2% (212/780) (p &lt;0,001). Se ofreció la prueba a 209 pacientes, cuya edad media fue de 45,6 años (desviación estándar: 11,7), 141 eran mujeres (68%) y 11 no habían nacido en España (5%). Ciento noventa y cinco pacientes (93%) reconocieron la posibilidad de haber estado o estar en situación de riesgo. Sin embargo, sólo tres de aquellos en posible riesgo (1,5%) rechazaron la prueba del VIH. Conclusiones Ofrecer sistemáticamente la prueba del VIH en atención primaria aumenta de manera significativa su realización, y en raras ocasiones es rechazada por la población (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;26(2): 116-122, mar.-abr. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111246</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Promoción de la detección del virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana en atención primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24719^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23555^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28379^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
