<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162607</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Atypical Guillain-Barré syndrome clustering: is it necessary to reconsider the diagnostic criteria and microbiological protocol?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Guillain-Barré syndrome is classically defined as a symmetrical ascending acute polyradiculoneuropathy, although there are atypical variants that make diagnosis difficult. CASE REPORTS. The medical data of six patients in our hospital area are collected during the first quarter of 2013. Lumbar punctures, imaging, neurophysiological studies, ganglioside antibodies and serologies have been proposed in all cases. We focus on the atypical features as late hyporeflexia, increased frequency of asymmetry and distal paresis and initial fever. From a neurophysiological point of view, all patients presented sensorimotor axonal forms. The most consistent datas in early studies is the F wave&#146;s alteration. A Miller Fisher variant associated with faciocervicobraquial paresis and cerebral reversible vasoconstriction syndrome has been detected. A bilateral brachial paresis and lumbar polyradiculopathy in the context of influenza A infection is other interesting case. The saltatory variant with cranial nerve involvement and lower limbs paresis has been demonstrated in one patient. Bands in cerebrospinal fluid are positive in three cases and anti-ganglioside antibodies in one patient. The syndrome of inappropriate secretion of antidiuretic hormone may explain some of the hyponatremias registered. The first line of treatment are inmunoglobulins in all patients. Plasmapheresis exchanges has been used as an additional therapy in four cases.  Conclusions. These clusters of six axonal cases with atypical clinical features justifies the need for knowledge of these variants in order to achieve an early treatment. Late hyporeflexia and brachialfaciocervico, saltatory and lumbar forms should be considered in the spectrum of Guillain-Barré syndrome. The etiological study should rule out a lots of pathogens as influenza  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Domínguez, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Eichau, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez-Mayoral, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quesada-García, María A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Menéndez-De León, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-López, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abril, Javier Abril</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro-Mascarell, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El síndrome de Guillain-Barré se define clásicamente como una polirradiculopatía aguda simétrica ascendente, si bien existen variantes atípicas que dificultan el diagnóstico. Casos clínicos. Se recogen las historias clínicas de seis pacientes de nuestra área hospitalaria durante el primer trimestre de 2013. Se han realizado punciones lumbares, electroneurograma-electromiograma y analíticas con autoinmunidad en todos los casos. El conjunto de la muestra destaca por la presencia de características atípicas, como hiporreflexia tardía, mayor frecuencia de asimetría y afectación distal, así como fiebre inicial. Desde el punto de vista neurofisiológico, todos los pacientes presentan formas axonales de tipo sensitivomotoras y las alteraciones de la onda F son el dato más precoz. Se identifica una variante de síndrome de Miller Fisher asociada a paresia faciocervicobraquial y síndrome de vasoconstricción cerebral reversible. Otro caso aúna las variantes de paresia braquial bilateral y polirradiculopatía lumbar en el contexto de infección aguda por influenza A. La variante saltatoria ha sido demostrada en otro paciente. Todos los pacientes han recibido tratamiento con inmunoglobulinas, y en dos de ellos se sumó la plasmaféresis como terapia adicional. Conclusiones. La agrupación de seis casos axonales con características clínicas atípicas justifica la necesidad del conocimiento de estas variantes para lograr un diagnóstico y un tratamiento precoz. La hiporreflexia tardía y las formas faciocervicobraquiales, saltatorias y lumbares deben considerarse dentro del espectro del síndrome de Guillain-Barré. El estudio etiológico debe incluir el cribado de numerosos patógenos, entre los que debe incluirse el virus influenza  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;64(9): 407-412, 1 mayo, 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162607</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Agrupación de casos de síndrome de Guillain-Barré atípico: ¿es necesario redefinir los criterios diagnósticos y los protocolos microbiológicos?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30327^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34211^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29181^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11565^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33353^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
