<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150384</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The patents game. Generic and biosimilar drugs</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The protection provided by patents on medicines has a limited duration. The expiry of patents expiration allows copies of the drugs to be released, competing with original. At first, they were identical to the original, known as generic drugs, but in recent years, due to the marketing of biological therapies and the expiry of many of their patents, biosimilar drugs have also emerged. These are not exact copies of the original, but, like generic drugs, biosimilar drugs have to demonstrate equivalence to the reference drugs in quality, safety and efficacy. Nevertheless, despite their importance and contribution to sustainability of health system, doctors are sometimes unaware of differences between them, and their impact in terms of clinical and economic effects. An attempt is made to review and clarify certain aspects often unknown by physicians, despite their involvement in their use (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Sala, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruano, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villamañán, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armada, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La protección mediante patentes a los medicamentos es limitada y, al expirar estos títulos de propiedad intelectual, entran en el mercado otros medicamentos copiados que compiten con los innovadores. Inicialmente estos fueron idénticos a los originales, los llamados medicamentos genéricos, pero, en los últimos años, a raíz de la irrupción de las terapias biológicas y la expiración de muchas de sus patentes han aparecido también los medicamentos biosimilares. Aunque no son copias exactas del original, al igual que los medicamentos genéricos, los medicamentos biosimilares tienen que demostrar equivalencia en calidad seguridad y eficacia respecto a los originales. A pesar de su importancia y su contribución a la sostenibilidad del sistema sanitario, a veces hay desconocimiento sobre las diferencias entre medicamentos genéricos y medicamentos biosimilares y qué implica su utilización en términos clínicos y económicos. Con esta revisión pretendemos aclarar aspectos que a menudo se desconocen a pesar del uso cada vez mayor de estos fármacos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;31(2): 99-105, mar.-abr. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150384</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Juego de patentes. Sobre medicamentos genéricos y biosimilares</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30150^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54726</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10523^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51470</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51460</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4398^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30150^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30149^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
