<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73661</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">William Cheselden (1688-1752) and Gerard van der Gucht (1695-1776). Surgical technique, the art of printed images and controversy in the urology book of the XVIII century</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We review the printed work of the English anatomist and surgeon William Cheselden, with special attention to the chalcographic engravings which illustrated it, mainly those by Gerard van der Gucht and the miniaturist Jacob Schijnvoet, vindicating the valuable collaboration of illustrators and printers and their essential figurative contribution to explain the texts and make them easier to understand for the reader. These images were as important as the texts and contributed considerable artistic value to the work.Likewise, we present the bitter controversy caused in the English medical-surgical society of the time, most especially in the lithotomist or &#147;urology&#148; community, by the publication of the work entitled &#147;The High Operation for the Stone&#148; by W. Cheselden. The publication coincided chronologically with the second edition of &#147;Lithotomia Douglassiana&#148; by John Douglas, and the scathing criticism hurled against Cheselden, one of the prime examples of which was the publication of the book entitled &#147;Lithotomus Castratus&#148;; in the book, both works were revised meticulously by its author, collated, analysed in detail and compared against each other, publically indicating that Cheselden plagiarised Douglas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómiz León, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se revisa la obra impresa del anatomista y cirujano inglés William Cheselden prestando atención preferente a los grabados calcográficos que la ilustran, mayoritariamente estos de autoría de Gerard van der Gucht y del miniaturista Jacob Schijnroet, reivindicándose el valioso concurso de dibujantes y estampadores y su imprescindible aportación figurativa para explicar y facilitar al lector la comprensión de los textos, resultando las imágenes a tal objeto de tanta importancia como aquellos, y aportando a la obra un sensible valor artístico.Así mismo, se expone la agria polémica que provocó en la sociedad médico-quirúrgica inglesa del tiempo, muy particularmente en la litotomista o &#147;urológica&#148;, la publicación de la obra intitulada &#147;The High Operation for the Stone&#148; de W. Cheselden, que coincidió cronológicamente con la segunda impresión de la &#147;Lithotomía Douglasiana&#148; de John Douglas, y las acervas críticas que se dispararon contra Cheselden, uno de cuyos máximos exponentes fue la publicación del libro titulado &#147;Lithotomus Castratus&#148;, en el cual, revisadas puntualmente por su autor ambas obras, cotejadas, detalladamente analizadas y confrontadas una y otra, señaló públicamente a Cheselden ser plagiario de Douglas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;62(9): 695-701, nov. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73661</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">William Cheselden (1688-1752) y Gerard van der Gucht (1695-1776). La técnica quirúrgica, el arte de la estampa y la controversia en el libro urológico del siglo XVIII</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d727^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6825</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14972^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200911</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
