<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-15566</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Social structure, social support and mental health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Previous research has revealed a persistent positive association between social support and mental health. However, most researchers have focused on the psychological and psychosocial aspects of social support. The present paper points out the need of including the social and structural basis of distress in our theoretical models. Starting from a general social and psychological model, our research considered the role of several social, environmental and structural variables (social position, social stressors, and social integration). The theoretical model was tested working on a sample of 401 subjects, which includes different social positions. The results obtained using structural equation modelling support our model, showing the relevant role played both by social support and social and structural factors. Implications for theory and intervention are discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barrón López de Roda, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Moreno, Esteban</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La investigación previa ha mostrado la existencia de una persistente asociación positiva entre apoyo social y salud mental. Sin embargo, la mayoría de los investigadores se ha centrado en los aspectos sociales y psicológicos del apoyo social. Este artículo señala la necesidad de incluir los fundamentos sociales y estructurales del deterioro psicológico en nuestros modelos teóricos. A partir de un modelo general, nuestra investigación consideró el papel de varios factores sociales y estructurales (posición e integración sociales). El modelo teórico fue empíricamente contrastado en una muestra de 401 personas, la cual incluía diferentes posiciones sociales. Los resultados obtenidos utilizando modelos de ecuaciones estructurales. Finalmente, se discuten algunas implicaciones teóricas y para la intervención. (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);13(1): 17-23, feb. 2001. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-15566</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estructura social y salud mental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13306^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
