<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055874</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Implications of quality of life in surgical decisions of lung cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Available evidence suggests that the patients with a forced expiratory volume in 1 second [FEV1] over 60% or in which a postoperative FEV1 is predicted over 45%, they do not develop severe disability after lung resection surgery; nevertheless, currently some groups are operating patients with EPOC and FEV1 less than 35%. In emphysema patients can occur that the function improve, as in the volume reduction lung surgery, but in the cases that it does not occur, they can remain with chronic shortness of breath until a 10%. At present, there are not any functional or effort test that be able to predict what patients will present satisfactory residual pulmonary function or chronic shortness of breath or important exercise limitations. It has been noticed that medical team opinion is not satisfactory to predict defi cit in postoperative quality of life. Nevertheless, long-term survivors (more than one year) inform relatively good quality of life, even in which they have pulmonary function reduced. In comparison with other chronic respiratory diseases, the survivors of lung cancer seem to be in better psychological state, the deficit in quality of life is caused mainly by depression, and not for physical limitation. Therefore, empirical evidence does not justify excluding undergoing surgery on basis of medical team suppositions about a postoperative poor Quality of life. In addition, studies about Quality of Life suggests patients who is undergo lung cancer surgery are willing to assume risks for their survival, although, they want to receive information about how surgery may affect them</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villar, Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puente-Maestu, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La evidencia disponible sugiere que los pacientes con un volumen espiratorio forzado en el primer segundo (FEV1) mayor de 60% o en los que se prevé un FEV1 postoratorio mayor de 45%, no desarrollan discapacidad severa tras la cirugía de resección pulmonar; sin embargo, en la actualidad algunos grupos están operando pacientes con EPOC y FEV1 menor de 35%. En pacientes con enfisema puede ocurrir que la función mejore, como en la cirugía de reducción de volumen, pero en los que no es así, hasta un 10% pueden quedar con insuficiencia espiratoria crónica. Hasta el momento, ninguna prueba funcional o de esfuerzo ha demostrado de forma clara poder predecir quiénes serán estos sujetos o quienes tendrán restricciones importantes en las actividades físicas. Se ha observado que la opinión del equipo médico tampoco es mejor para predecir una calidad de vida postoperatoria pobre. Los supervivientes a largo plazo (más de un año), sin embargo refi eren una calidad de vida razonablemente elevada, incluso en los que tienen la función pulmonar reducida. En comparación con otras enfermedades respiratorias crónicas, los supervivientes de cáncer de pulmón parecen estar en mejor situación mental, y en los que tienen una Calidad de vida más baja el origen parece ser principalmente la depresión, y no la limitación física. Por tanto, la evidencia disponible no permite descartar a los pacientes sometidos a cirugía en base a que el equipo suponga una pobre calidad de vida postoperatoria. Además, los estudios que han valorado la QOL sugieren que el paciente que se opera de cáncer de pulmón está dispuesto a asumir el riesgo con tal de vivir más tiempo, aunque si le gustaría saber cómo le va a afectar la cirugía</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);3(2/3): 393-406, dic. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055874</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implicaciones de la calidad de vida en las decisiones quirúrgicas del cáncer de pulmón</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1969^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11442^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
