<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121938</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of the Spanish version of the alcohol smoking and substance involvement screening test (ASSIST)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: To evaluate the psychometric properties of the Spanish version of the Alcohol, Smoking and Substance Involvement Screening Test (ASSIST) and its effectiveness as a screening tool for problematic alcohol, tobacco and other psychoactive substance use in groups of low, moderate, and high risk users. Methods: A test battery including the ASSIST and several standardized screening, assessment, and diagnostic instruments was administered to 485 patients recruited in different primary health-care facilities and specialized addiction treatment units from Health Area 11 in Madrid. Results: ASSIST cut-off scores show a good sensitivity and specificity for discrimination between substance use and abuse and between abuse and dependence. Concurrent validity was demonstrated by significant correlations between ASSIST scores and scores from the Mini-International Neuropsychiatric Interview (MINI-Plus), the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT), the Revised Fagerstrom Tolerance Questionnaire (RTQ) and the Severity of Dependence Scale (SDS). Conclusions: Psychometric properties of the Spanish version of the ASSIST indicate that is a valid screening test for identifying substance use disorders in various health-care settings (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rubio Valladolid, Gabriel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Gras, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zarco Montejo, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ponce Alfaro, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jurado Barba, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rigabert Sánchez-Junco, Alina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Raga, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz Bértolo, Javier de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: evaluar las propiedades psicométricas de la versión española del test de detección de uso de alcohol, tabaco y otras sustancias (ASSIST) y su efectividad como herramienta para la detección de un uso problemático en alcohol, tabaco y otras sustancias psicoactivas en grupos de bajo, moderado y alto riesgo de consumo. Método: una batería de test estandarizados, de evaluación y diagnóstico incluyendo el ASSIST fueron aplicados a una muestra de 485 pacientes reclutados en diferentes centros de atención primaria y centros de tratamiento por consumo drogas, del área 11 en Madrid. Resultados: los puntos de corte del ASSIST muestran buena sensibilidad y especificidad para discriminar entre el uso y el abuso de sustancias, y entre el abuso y la dependencia. La validez concurrente fue demostrada con correlaciones significativas entre las puntuaciones del ASSIST y las puntuaciones de la entrevista neuropsiquiátrica Mini-International (MINI-Plus), el test de identificación de desórdenes por el consumo de alcohol (AUDIT), Cuestionario revisado de tolerancia Fagerstrom (RTQ) y escala de gravedad de la dependencia (SDS). Conclusiones: las propiedades psicométricas de la versión española del ASSIST indican que es un test de detección válido para identificar los desórdenes por el consumo de sustancias en varios centros de atención primaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);26(2): 180-185, abr.-jun. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121938</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación de la versión española del Test de Detección de Uso de Alcohol, Tabaco y otras Sustancias (ASSIST)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24887^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24887^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24887^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24887^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24887^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24887^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
