<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057019</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-5981</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Indirect reduction and percutaneous pinning as treatment of distal radius fractures</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: Intraarticular fractures of        distal radius are associated with high energy mechanisms,        are severe and difficult to obtain a surgical reduction. The        aim of this study is to compare the clinical, radiographically        and activity results in workers treated with indirect reduction        and percutaneous pinning.        Material and methods: A prospective study was organized        in 24 heavy-labour workers with unstable fractures of        distal radius. The minimal follow-up was of one year. The        mean age were 40 years (22-65 years) and dominant        limb was involved in 40% of the cases. All patients were        surgically treated with indirect reduction and percutaneous        fixation with K-wires and cast immobilization.        Pain (visual analogue score), mobility and radiograhs were        evaluated and also strength (isokinetics), functionality        (DASH score) and, finally, the return to work at 3, 6 and        12 months.        Results: Fracture healing was obtained at 7 weeks but.        Pain score, at 12 months, were 2,9 points. The flexion -        extension mobility loss, in relation to the contralateral        wrist, was 11º. Radiographs corrections were non-anatomically        in 35% of the cases. The mean DASH score was        29 and the loss of grip strength related to contralateral        wrist was 23%. All the patients return to the same work        activity 14 weeks after surgery.        Conclusions: Indirect reduction with percutáneous pinning        with triangle fixation frame, allows excellents clinical, X-ray and laboral results, comparable with another        surgical techniques</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fuentes, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez de Albornoz, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abad, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado, P. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: Las fracturas intraarticulares        del radio distal se asocian a traumatismos de alta energía        y se caracterizan por su complejidad y la dificultad de obtener        una reducción estable, que precisa tratamiento quirúrgico.        El objetivo del trabajo es presentar los resultados        clínicos, radiológicos y laborales del tratamiento mediante        reducción indirecta, fijación percutánea e inmovilización        con yeso para este tipo de fracturas.        Material y métodos: Se realiza un estudio prospectivo de        24 pacientes con fracturas intraarticulares desplazadas de        la extremidad distal del radio tratados entre los años 2003 y        2005, con un seguimiento mínimo de 1 año. La edad media        era 40 años (22-65 años) y todos tenian trabajos de alta        demanda funcional. En el 40% se afectó la muñeca dominante.        Se trataron mediante reducción indirecta con        fijación percutánea con agujas de Kirschner en forma de        triangulo de fuerzas y se inmovilización con yeso por 4 semanas,        seguido de tratamiento rehabilitador. Se valora el        dolor (escala analógico visual), rango de movilidad, parámetros        radiológicos, fuerza (test isocinéticos), funcionalidad        (escala DASH) y resultados laborales a los 3, 6 y 12 meses.        Resultados: Se obtuvo la consolidación completa en todos        los casos a las 7 semanas. 2 pacientes precisaron una        reintervención. A los 12 meses los pacientes presentaron        una escala analógico visual del dolor (0-10) de 2,9, 11º de        pérdida de flexo-extensión con respecto a la muñeca contralateral        y el 35% presentaban resultados radiológicos no aceptables. La puntuación obtenida en el cuestionario        DASH fue de 29 puntos y presentaban un 23% de pérdida        de fuerza isométrica. Todos volvieron a trabajar con el mismo        nivel de actividad a las 14 semanas de media.        Conclusiones: El tratamiento quirúrgico de las fracturas        intraarticulares del radio distal mediante reducción indirecta        y fijación percutánea ofrece unos excelentes resultados        clínicos, radiológicos y laborales comparables a otras técnicas        quirúrgicas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Patol. apar. locomot. Fund. Mapfre Med;5(supl.2): 56-63, 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057019</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reducción indirecta y fijación percutánea en fracturas del radio distal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30724^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15352^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5727^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12319^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
