<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118061</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spinal anesthesia in ambulatory surgery? Are we near the optimal  anesthetic technique for ambulatory surgical procedures?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Ambulatory anesthesia is being increasingly used, and in more complex surgical procedures. The optimal anesthetic technique must comply with specific requirements: low onset time, fast recovery, reliability, and minimal side effects. Spinal anesthesia would fulfill these requirements, as long as its associated complications are adequately handled. The development of specific techniques such as unilateral and selective spinal anesthesia, or drugs as  2-chlorprocaine (preservative-free) could make spinal anesthesia the ideal technique for ambulatory surgical procedures (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Río Fernández, S. del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La cirugía mayor ambulatoria cada vez se utiliza más frecuentemente y en procedimientos más complejos. La técnica anestésica óptima para cirugía ambulatoria debe cumplir unos requisitos específicos: rápida instauración y recuperación, fiabilidad y mínimos efectos secundarios asociados. La anestesia espinal cumpliría estos requisitos si conseguimos evitar o minimizar sus posibles complicaciones asociadas. El desarrollo de técnicas específicas,  como la anestesia espinal unilateral y selectiva o fármacos como la 2-clorprocaína sin conservantes, podrían hacer de la anestesia espinal la técnica  ideal para cirugía ambulatoria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;18(4): 182-186, oct.-dic. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118061</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anestesia espinal en cirugía mayor ambulatoria: ¿estamos en el camino de la técnica anestésica ideal para procedimientos ambulatorios?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d775^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
