<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138897</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of a comprehensive stroke centre on the care of patients with acute ischaemic stroke due to cervical artery dissection</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Cervical artery dissection (CAD) is the cause of 2% to 3% of ischaemic strokes and 10% to  25% of the ischaemic strokes in young people. Our objective is to evaluate whether implementation of a comprehensive stroke centre (CSC) improves the diagnosis and modifies the prognosis of patients with acute stroke due to CAD. Patients and methods: Retrospective study of a registry of consecutive patients with acute stroke due to CAD. They were classified according to the period of care at our centre: pre-CSC (October 2004-March 2008, 42 months) or post-CSC (April 2008-June 2012, 51 months). We compared baseline characteristics, methods of diagnosis, treatment and outcome of these patients in both periods. Results: Nine patients were diagnosed with CAD in pre-CSC and 26 in post-CSC, representing 0.8% and 2.1% of all ischaemic strokes treated in each period, respectively. The diagnosis of CAD was made within the first 24 hours in 42.3% of the patients in post-CSC versus 0% in pre-CSC, by using urgent cerebral angiography as a diagnostic test in 46.2% of cases in the second period compared to 0% in the first. Both severity of stroke (median NIHSS score 11 vs. 3, P=.014) and time to neurological care (265 min vs 148,P=.056) were higher in the post-CSC period. Endovascular treatment was performed in 34.3%, and all treatments were post-CSC. The functional outcome was comparable for both periods. Conclusions: Implementation of a CSC increases the frequency of the diagnosis of CAD, as well as the treatment options for these patients in the acute phase of stroke (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Millán, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dorado, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Cancio, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Pérez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gomis, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hidalgo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dávalos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castaño, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Bermejo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domenech, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almendrote, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez de la Ossa, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prats, L. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La disección de arterias cervicales (DAC) es la causa del 2-3% de ictus isquémicos y del 10-25% en pacientes jóvenes. Nuestro objetivo es evaluar si la implementación de un centro terciario de ictus (CTI) facilita el diagnóstico y modifica el pronóstico de los pacientes con ictus agudo por DAC. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio retrospectivo de un registro de pacientes consecutivos con ictus agudo por DAC. Se clasificaron según el periodo de atención: pre-CTI (octubre 2004-marzo 2008, 42 meses) o post-CTI (abril 2008-junio 2012, 51 meses). Se compararon las características basales, el método diagnóstico, el tratamiento y la evolución de estos pacientes entre ambos periodos. Resultados: Se diagnosticó a 9 pacientes con DAC en el periodo pre-CTI y 26 en el post-CTI, representando el 0,8 y el 2,1% de los ictus isquémicos atendidos en cada periodo. El diagnóstico de DAC se realizó en las primeras 24 h en el 42,3% de pacientes en el periodo post-CTI frente al 0% en el pre-CTI, gracias al uso de la arteriografía cerebral urgente como prueba diagnóstica en el 46,2% de los casos en el segundo periodo frente al 0% en el primero. La gravedad del ictus (mediana puntuación escala NIHSS 11 vs. 3, p = 0,014) y el tiempo hasta la atención neurológica (265 minutos vs. 148, p = 0,056) fueron mayores en la fase post-CTI. Se realizó tratamiento endovascular en el 34,3%, todos en el periodo post-CTI. El pronóstico funcional fue comparable en ambos periodos. Conclusiones: La implementación de un CTI incrementa la frecuencia en el diagnóstico de DAC y aumenta las opciones terapéuticas en la fase aguda del ictus en estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;30(6): 331-338, jul.-ago. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138897</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de un centro terciario de ictus en la atención de pacientes con ictus isquémico agudo por disección de arterias cervicales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24892^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54238^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2586^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34254^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
