<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-27914</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nutritional value of the diet in healthy pregnant women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Goal: The purpose of the present paper is to describe the level of nutritional adequacy of the regular diet of pregnant women belonging to our health-care area.  Scope: Health-care area of Valme Hospital, Seville. Design: Randomized transversal descriptive study.  Subjects: Forty-nine pregnant women during their first trimester.  Interventions: The daily intake was assessed by means of a 24-hour reminder sheet and a weekly consumption survey. The data obtained were compared with the recommended daily intake of nutrients and with the recommended daily allowances for various foods. At the same time, an anthropometric and basic analysis were also carried out.  Results: The calorie intake was as recommended (2,208 ± 475 kcal/day). The diet contained excessive amounts of proteins (88 ± 21 g/day) and fat (97 ± 27 g/day), with a predominance of monounsaturated fats (46.9 ± 5.5%) over saturated (36.6 ± 7.2%) or polyunsaturated fats (15.1 ± 7%), (p &lt; 0.0005). Nonetheless, the diet was short on carbohydrates (44%), fibre (18 ± 4.9 g/day), calcium (948 ± 353 mg/day), iron (13.4 ± 3.1 mg/day) and vitamin B6 (1.1 ± 0.8 mg/day) (p &lt; 0.0005), and extremely short on folic acid (172 ± 101 µg/day), (p &lt; 0.0005). In the assessment of the diet in terms of daily allowances, this was sufficient in fruit (2.3 ± 1.8/day), but short on dairy products (1.9 ± 1.1/day) and extremely short on vegetables (1 ± 0.4/day), (p &lt; 0.0005). Only 2% of the subjects fulfilled with the recommended daily intake for key vitamins and minerals. The prevalence of obesity (BMI &gt; 30 kg/m2) was 18.4%.  Conclusions: The normal diet of pregnant women in our health-care area is short on calcium, iron, folic acid and dietary fibre, although with an excess of animal protein and fat (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Grupo Aula Médica, S.A.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo de este trabajo es describir el nivel de adecuación nutricional de la dieta habitual en gestantes pertenecientes a nuestra área sanitaria. Ámbito: Área Sanitaria Valme. Sevilla. Diseño: Estudio descriptivo aleatorio transversal. Sujetos: Cuarenta y nueve gestantes de primer trimestre. Intervenciones: Se valoró la ingesta diaria, por recordatorio de 24 horas y por encuesta de consumo semanal. Los datos obtenidos se comparan con las ingestas diarias recomendadas de nutrientes y con las raciones diarias recomendadas para determinados grupos de alimentos. Al mismo tiempo, se realizó una valoración antropométrica y analítica básica. Resultados: La ingesta calórica fue la recomendada (2.208 ñ 475 kcal/día). La dieta contenía un exceso de proteínas (88 ñ 21 g/día), de grasa (97 ñ 27 g/día), con predominio de grasas monoinsaturadas (46,9 ñ 5,5 por ciento) sobre las saturadas (36,6 ñ 7,2 por ciento) y poliinsaturadas (15,1 ñ 7 por ciento), (p 30 kg/m2) fue de un 18,4 por ciento. Conclusiones: La dieta habitual de las gestantes de nuestra área es deficitaria en calcio, hierro, ácido fólico, y fibra dietética, aunque excesiva en proteína animal y grasas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;18(5): 248-252, sept. 2003. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valor nutricional de la dieta en embarazadas sanas. Resultados de una encuesta dietética en gestantes</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Maetzu Aznar, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mingo Canal, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernal López, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Avilés Mejías, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benito de Valle Galindo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias Bravo, EM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moriones López, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Irles Rocamora, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-27914</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9936</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24300</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
