<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131966</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reccomendations of the Spanish Working Group on Crohn's Disease and Ulcerative Colitis (GETECCU) on the use of methotrexate in inflammatory bowel disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Methotrexate is an immunosuppressant that may be useful in several clinical scenarios in inflammatory bowel disease. In this article, we review the available evidence in Crohn's disease and ulcerative colitis and establish general recommendations for its use in clinical practice. Although the available data are limited, it is very likely that methotrexate is underused because its effectiveness is underestimated and its toxicity is overestimated. Both in induction therapy and in maintenance of remission, methotrexate is useful in Crohn's disease. When prescribed in combination with biologic agents, immunogenicity is less frequent and consequently long-term response could potentially be improved. There are few published studies, but several data suggest that methotrexate could also be useful in ulcerative colitis. Although myelotoxicity and liver toxicity are well known risks, methotrexate is a drug that is well tolerated in many patients, even in the long term (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Charro, Mara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domènech, Eugeni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gisbert, Javier P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-López, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gomollón, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio, Saioa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El metotrexato es un inmunosupresor que puede ser útil en diversos escenarios clínicos en las enfermedades inflamatorias intestinales. En este artículo se revisa la evidencia disponible en enfermedad de Crohn y colitis ulcerosa, estableciéndose unas recomendaciones generales para su uso en la práctica diaria. Aunque los datos son limitados, muy probablemente el metotrexato se infrautiliza en las enfermedades inflamatorias intestinales porque se infraestima su eficacia y se sobrestima su toxicidad. Tanto para la inducción de la remisión como para el mantenimiento de la misma, utilizado a la dosis adecuada, el metotrexato resulta útil en la enfermedad de Crohn. Coadministrado con los biológicos disminuye su inmunogenidad, con lo que potencialmente puede mejorar la respuesta a largo plazo. Aunque los estudios publicados son escasos, es muy posible que sea también un fármaco útil en la colitis ulcerosa. Aunque puede asociarse con mielotoxicidad, y toxicidad hepática, es un fármaco razonablemente tolerado incluso a largo plazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;38(1): 24-30, ene. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131966</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recomendaciones del Grupo Español de Trabajo de Enfermedad de Crohn y Colitis Ulcerosa (GETECCU) sobre el uso de metotrexato en la enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29431^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7344^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23971^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28169^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5629^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
