<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-69110</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-1375</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In recent years a number of studies have been published on patients with chronic renal insufficiency undergoing haemodialysis in which it is shown "paradoxically" that, contrary to what occurs in the population in general, obesity, measured through the body mass index, is related to better survival. Here we have studied the influence of obesity on survival after 5 years in patients with renal insufficiency in predialysis. The sample was made up of 160 patients, seen for the first time in the predialysis clinic between 1 September 1998 and 31 October 1999. The data required to calculate their BMI (weight (kg)/height2) was taken from the nursing case history on the first (basal) and last (final) predialysis visit. We considered patients with BMI=30 to be obese. Of the 157 patients whose evolution after 5 years is known to us: 85 (54%) were still alive: 19 were still in predialysis, 43 on dialysis and 23 with a functioning transplant. The patients with a BMI=30 had a lower survival in months than the non-obese patients (53±24 compared to 61±19 months p= 0.04), in other words, obesity defined as IMC=30 has a negative effect on survival after 5 years in our population of patients with advanced renal insufficiency treated in the predialysis clinic (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guerrero Riscos, María Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Ana Ruiz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soler Junco, Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montes Delgado, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barbosa Martín, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Espejo, Jesús Lucas</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galeano Macías, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos años se han publicado diversos estudios en pacientes con insuficiencia renal crónica en hemodiálisis en los que se demuestra "paradójicamente" que, al contrario que en la población general, la obesidad, medida a través del índice de masa corporal, se relaciona con mejor supervivencia. En este trabajo hemos estudiado la influencia de la obesidad en la supervivencia a los 5 años en pacientes con insuficiencia renal en Prediálisis. La muestra estaba formada por 160 pacientes, vistos por primera vez en la consulta de Prediálisis desde el 1 de septiembre de 1998 a 31 de octubre de 1999. Se recogieron de la Historia de Enfermería los datos para calcular el IMC (peso (Kg)/ altura2) en la primera (basal) y última (final) visita en Consulta Prediálisis. Consideramos obeso al paciente con IMC=30.De los 157 pacientes que conocimos la evolución a los 5 años: 85 (54%) permanecían vivos: 19 seguían en Prediálisis, 43 en diálisis y 23 con un trasplante funcionante; Los pacientes con un IMC=30 tenían una supervivencia en meses inferior a los no obesos (53=24 vs 61=19 meses p= 0,04), es decir, la obesidad, definida como IMC=30, influye negativamente en la supervivencia a los 5 años en nuestra población de pacientes con insuficiencia renal avanzada atendidos en la Consulta Prediálisis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Enferm. Nefrol;10(3): 234-238, jul.-sept. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-69110</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13915</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
