<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-28235</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Variability and tendencies in the consumption of methylphenidate in Spain. An estimation of the prevalence of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) is one of the most frequently occurring behavioural disorders in childhood; its prevalence in Spain is estimated to be around 3-6%. Methylphenidate (MPH) is the only medication available on the Spanish market. Material and methods. The prevalence of ADHD was estimated by calculating the daily doses of MPH defined per 1000 inhabitants per day (Therapeutic group N06B A04), over the period 1992-2001, for each of the provinces in Spain. Figures for the number of prescriptions made out were obtained from the Spanish Ministry of Health and Consumer Affairs. The odds ratio and the 95% confidence interval were calculated, as was the linear tendency c 2 . Results. A minimum prevalence of ADHD was estimated to be 0.63 per 1000 inhabitants per day for the overall Spanish population. Its use and consumption does, however, vary with a north-south slope, and higher prevalence in Catalonia than in Andalusia. Taken as a whole, the consumption of MPH has undergone a uniform 8% increase annually since 1992, with a rising variation in the OR from 0.19 up to the year 2001 (OR = 1), and every year it has been statistically significant (c 2 = 78.246; p &lt; 0.05). Conclusions. The consumption of MPH enables us to estimate the distribution of ADHD in Spain. The figures obtained do not yet allow us to offer an accurate estimate of the prevalence of the disease, despite the increase in consumption. Nevertheless, they do enable us to establish the variations that exist in medical practice regarding this disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El trastorno por déficit de atención con hiperactividad (TDAH) es uno de los trastornos conductuales más frecuentes de la infancia; su prevalencia en España se estima en un 3-6 por ciento. El metilfenidato (MPH) es el único fármaco disponible en el mercado español para tratarlo. Material y métodos. Se estima la prevalencia del TDAH mediante el cálculo de las dosis diarias definidas por 1.000 habitantes y día de MPH (grupo terapéutico N06B A04), durante los años 1992-2001, para cada una de las provincias españolas. Se ha dispuesto de los datos de las prescripciones indicadas por el Ministerio de Sanidad y Consumo. Se ha calculado el odds ratio y su intervalo de confianza del 95 por ciento, y calculado el X2 de tendencia lineal. Resultados. Se estima una prevalencia mínima de TDAH de 0,63 por 1.000 habitantes y día para el conjunto de la población española, y existe una variabilidad en el uso y consumo de MPH con un gradiente norte-sur, con una mayor prevalencia en Cataluña frente a Andalucía. En su conjunto, el consumo de MPH se ha incrementado un 8 por ciento anual, que ha sido uniforme desde 1992, con una variación ascendente del OR desde 0,19 hasta el año 2001 (OR = 1), y todos los años son estadísticamente significativos (X2= 78,246; p &lt; 0,05). Conclusiones. El consumo de MPH permite estimar la distribución del TDAH en España. Las cifras obtenidas no permiten todavía estimar con precisión la prevalencia de la enfermedad, pese al aumento en su consumo. Sí se puede establecer la variabilidad en la práctica médica frente a esta enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;37(9): 806-810, nov. 2003. tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variabilidad y tendencias en el consumo de metilfenidato en España. Estimación de la prevalencia del trastorno por déficit de atención con hiperactividad</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Romo-Barrientos, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Criado Álvarez, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-28235</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d8961</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4422</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24568</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d711</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200311</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
