<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89354</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fragile-X syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Fragile-X Syndrome is the most  frequente  hereditary from of mental retardation. It has a prevalence of 1 in 4.000 males and 1 in 8.000 females. The gene that causes the syndrome is FMR1, which is X-linked and presents a semi dominant segregation affecting both sexes. The molecular cause of FXS is the unstable mutation of a CGG repeat in the 5´untranslated end of the gene. This repeated sequence can one causes the absence of the protein FMRP, which is the cause of the disease. Clinical diagnosis of the syndrome is based on its characteristic physical findings, although when there is no family history, it may be difficult to recognize it before the onset of psychomotor delay or the behavioral problems (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Heine Suñet, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosell Andreo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome X frágil es la forma más frecuente de retraso mental hereditario con una prevalencia de 1 de cada 4.000 varones y 1 de cada 8.000 mujeres. El gen responsable es el FMR1 que presenta un mecanismo de trasmisión ligado al sexo semidominante, por lo que puede afectar a ambos sexos. La etiología del SXF es una mutación inestable de una secuencia repetitiva CGG en el extremo 5´ no codificante que puede encontrarse de forma normal, premutada o con mutación completa que es la que provoca la inactivación del gen y por tanto, la falta de proteína FMRP que es la causa del síndrome. El diagnóstico clínico del síndrome se basa en los hallazgos físicos característicos, sin embargo, si no existen antecedentes familiares, puede ser difícil reconocerlo antes de la aparición del retraso psicomotor o de los trastornos de conducta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;65(1): 37-41, ene.-feb. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89354</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome X frágil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5735^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9346</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51238^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34579</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12033^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
