<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043358</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prognosis for acute exacerbation of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease in mechanically ventilated patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine the variables associated with prognosis for acute exacerbation of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (AECOPD) in mechanically ventilated patients. Design. Prospective cohort study with retrospective analysis. Location. 361 Intensive Care Units (ICU) in 20 countries. Patients and methods. There were included in the study 522 patients who required mechanical ventilation for more than 12 hours due to an acute exacerbation of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (AECOPD). In order to determine those variables associated with mortality, there was performed a recursive partition analysis in which the following variables were included: demographics, arterial blood gas prior to intubation, complications arising during mechanical ventilation (barotrauma, acute respiratory distress syndrome, ventilator-associated pneumonia, sepsis), organ dysfunction (cardiovascular, renal, liver, coagulation) and duration of ventilatory support. Interventions. None. Variables of prime importance. ICU mortality. Results. ICU and hospital mortality rates were 22% and 30%, respectively. Variables associated with mortality were cardiovascular dysfunction, renal dysfunction and duration of ventilatory support &gt; 18 days. Median durations were as follows: mechanical ventilatory support, 4 days (P25: 2, P75: 6); weaning from ventilatory support, 2 days (P25: 1, P75: 5); stay in intensive care unit, 8 days (P25: 5, P75: 13); stay in hospital, 17 days (P25: 10, P75: 27). Conclusions. Mortality in the studied cohort of patients with AECOPD was associated with cardiovascular dysfunction, renal dysfunction and prolonged mechanical support</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Anzueto, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>David, C. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodrigo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frutos-Vivar, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soto, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esteban, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Apezteguia, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bugedo, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elizalde, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palizas, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>D`Empaire, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar las variables asociadas con el pronóstico de los enfermos con agudización de la enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica que requieren ventilación mecánica. Diseño. Estudio prospectivo de cohortes con análisis retrospectivo. Ámbito. Trescientas sesenta y una Unidades de Cuidados Intensivos (UCI) de 20 países. Pacientes y métodos. Se incluyeron en el estudio a 522 pacientes que precisan ventilación mecánica durante más de 12 horas debido a una agudización de la enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica. Para la estimación de las variables asociadas a la mortalidad se realizó un análisis de particiones recursivas, donde se incluyeron las siguientes variables: demográficas, gases arteriales previos a la intubación, complicaciones aparecidas durante la ventilación mecánica (barotrauma, síndrome de distrés respiratorio agudo, neumonía asociada a la ventilación mecánica, sepsis), disfunción de órganos (cardiovascular, renal, hepático, coagulación) y duración del soporte ventilatorio. Intervenciones. Ninguna. Variables de interés principales. Mortalidad en la UCI. Resultados. La mortalidad en la UCI fue de un 22% y en el hospital de un 30%. Las variables asociadas a la mortalidad fueron la disfunción cardiovascular, la disfunción renal y una duración del soporte ventilatorio de más de 18 días. La mediana de la duración de la ventilación mecánica fue de 4 días (P25: 2, P75: 6), de desconexión de la ventilación mecánica de 2 días (P25: 1, P75: 5), de estancia en la UCI de 8 días (P25: 5, P75: 13) y de estancia en el hospital de 17 días (P25: 10, P75: 27). Conclusiones. En nuestra cohorte de enfermos con enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica que requieren ventilación mecánica la mortalidad se asoció a disfunción cardiovascular, renal y necesidad de soporte ventilatorio prolongado</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);30(2): 52-61, mar. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043358</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pronóstico de los enfermos con enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica reagudizada que precisan ventilación mecánica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7603^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23042^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
