<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109781</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Synovial chondromatosis of the temporomandibular joint. a rare case with subcranial extension</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Synovial chondromatosis (SC) is a cartilaginous metaplasia of the mesenchymal remnants of the synovial tissue of joints. It is an uncommon disease of unknown origin. This benign synovial process involves the formation of cartilaginous nodules (loose bodies) in the synovium and within the articular space. SC mainly affects large synovial joints, and only very rarely affects the temporomandibular joint (TMJ). The main symptoms are pain, swelling, mouth opening limitation, crepitation, and lateral mandibular deviation. Diagnosis can be made by panoramic radiograph, computed tomography scan, magnetic resonance imaging, and arthroscopy of the TMJ. The main treatment includes complete removal of the loose bodies in conjunction with excision of the affected synovium. It can be performed by arthroscopy or by open surgery. In cases with TMJ involvement, the lesion is usually confined to the joint cavity. In this report, a rare case of SC of the TMJ with subcranial extension is presented(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Medina, Blas</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bailón Berrio, Luis Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Plaza, Adoración</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín Fernández, Ana Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez López, José Dario</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La condromatosis sinovial (CS) es una metaplasia cartilaginosa de los remanentes mesenquimales del tejido sinovial de las articulaciones. Es una enfermedad de etiología desconocida y poco frecuente. Puede definirse como un proceso benigno sinovial caracterizado por la formación de nódulos cartilaginosos (cuerpos libres). La CS afecta principalmente a grandes articulaciones sinoviales siendo poco común su aparición en la articulación temporomandibular. La sintomatología predominante es dolor, inflamación, limitación de los movimientos mandibulares, crepitación y laterodesviación mandibular. El diagnóstico se realiza mediante el estudio radiológico y artroscópico de la articulación. El tratamiento adecuado englobaría la extirpación completa de los cuerpos libres y de la sinovial afecta, bien mediante artroscopia o mediante cirugía abierta. Cuando está afectada la articulación temporomandibular las lesiones suelen estar localizadas en la cavidad articular, siendo rara su extensión extraarticular. En este artículo describimos un caso excepcional de condromatosis sinovial con extensión a la fosa craneal media(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;35(1): 31-35, ene.-mar. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109781</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Condromatosis sinovial de la articulación temporomandibular con extensión a la base de cráneo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1189^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1189^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8855^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24563^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24563^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14082^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24563^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24563^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8855^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14082^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8855^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
