<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82557</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Implementation of Response to Intervention (RtI) Model in Spain: an example of a collaboration between Canarian universities and the department of education of the Canary Islands</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this study was to examine the effectiveness of second tier intervention at-risk readers within the context of a Response to Intervention approach. The study was conducted in the Canary Islands (Spain), directed by research team «Dificultades de Aprendizaje, Psicolingüística y Nuevas Tecnologías » (DEA&amp;NT) from University of La Laguna, and supported by the Government of the Canary Islands. A sample of 1.123 Spanish children from fourteen schools districts were given the Spanish adaptation of The Hong Kong Specific Learning Difficulties Behavior Checklist and children who scored at or above the 75th percentile on the test were classified as «at risk» for early reading difficulties. Half of the students were randomly assigned to a project-based intervention condition where they received small group supplementary intervention for 30 minutes daily using the Prevención de las Dificultades Específicas de Aprendizaje (PREDEA) curriculum from mid to late December and continued until mid June. The other half received whatever remedial services were available at their schools. Results indicated that children who received the PREDEA curriculum had higher scores on the Early Grade Reading Assessment Test (EGRA) on initial sound identification, listening comprehension, letter sound knowledge and oral reading fluency compared to the control group (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, Juan E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alfonso, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, Desirée</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Artiles, Ceferino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio consistió en examinar la eficacia del segundo nivel de actuación del modelo de respuesta a la intervención. El estudio se llevó a cabo en las Islas Canarias (España), dirigido por el equipo de investigación «Dificultades de Aprendizaje, Psicolingüística y Nuevas Tecnologías» (DEA&amp;NT) de la Universidad de La Laguna, y apoyado por la Dirección General de Ordenación e Innovación Educativa de la Consejería de Educación del Gobierno de Canarias. Se administró inicialmente a una muestra de 1.123 niños españoles procedentes de un total de catorce colegios, la adaptación española del The Hong Kong Specific Learning Difficulties Behavior Checklist. Los niños que puntuaban igual o superior al percentil 75 en esta prueba de selección eran considerados niños en riesgo de padecer dificultades específicas de aprendizaje. La mitad de los niños se asignó al azar a una condición experimental donde recibieron una intervención en pequeño grupo con una duración diaria de 30 minutos a través del programa Prevención de las Dificultades Específicas de Aprendizaje (PREDEA). Esta intervención se inició a mediados del mes de diciembre y finalizó a mediados del mes de junio. La otra mitad recibía los servicios habituales de apoyo que tiene disponible la escuela. Los resultados mostraron que los niños que recibieron el programa curricular PREDEA alcanzaron puntuaciones superiores al grupo control en habilidades que mide el Early Grade Reading Assessment Test (EGRA), tales como la identificación del primer segmento fonológico en palabras, comprensión oral, conocimiento del sonido de las letras y fluidez en lectura oral de palabras en textos cortos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);22(4): 935-942, 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82557</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implementación del Modelo de Respuesta a la Intervención (RtI) en España: un ejemplo de colaboración entre las Universidades Canarias y la Consejería de Educación del Gobierno de Canarias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7980</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16735</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3320</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8037^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37623^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7985^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
