<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164231</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6709</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Life&#146;s unity and flexibility: the ecological link</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The small size, ubiquity, metabolic versatility and flexibility, and genetic plasticity (horizontal transfer) of microbes allow them to tolerate and quickly adapt to unfavorable and/or changing environmental conditions. Prokaryotes are endowed with sophisticated cellular envelopes that contain molecules not found elsewhere in the biological world. Although prokaryotic cells lack the organelles that characterize their eukaryotic counterparts, their interiors are surprisingly complex. Prokaryotes sense their environment and respond as individual cells to specific environmental challenges; but prokaryotes also act cooperatively, displaying communal activities. In many microbial ecosystems, the functionally active unit is not a single species or population (clonal descendence of the same bacterium) but a consortium of two or more types of cells living in close symbiotic association. Only recently have we become aware that microbes are the basis for the functioning of the biosphere. Thus, we are at a unique time in the history of science, in which the interaction of technological advances and the exponential growth in our knowledge of the present microbial diversity will lead to significant advances not only in microbiology but also in biology and other sciences in general (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guerrero, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berlanga, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los microbios son de pequeño tamaño, ubicuos, presentan versatilidad y flexibilidad metabólica, y plasticidad genética (transferencia horizontal) que les permite soportar y adaptarse rápidamente a las condiciones ambientales desfavorables y/o cambiantes. Los procariotas poseen sofisticadas envolturas que contienen moléculas que no se encuentran en ninguna otra parte del mundo biológico. Aunque la célula procariota carece de los orgánulos que caracterizan sus equivalentes eucariotas, su interior es asombrosamente complejo. Los procariotas sienten su ambiente y responden como células individuales a los desafíos ambientales específicos; pero también actúan de forma cooperativa, mostrando actividades comunitarias. En muchos ecosistemas microbianos, la unidad funcionalmente activa no es una sola especie o población (descendencia clónica de la misma bacteria), sino un consorcio de dos o más tipos de células que vive en estrecha asociación simbiótica. La comprensión de los microbios como la base del funcionamiento de la biosfera es algo muy reciente. Nos encontramos en un momento en que la interacción de avances tecnológicos y el conocimiento exponencial de la actual diversidad microbiana permitirán avances significativos no sólo en microbiología, sino en biología y en otras ciencias en general (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int Microbiol;9(3): 225-235, sept. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164231</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La unidad y flexibilidad de la vida: la conexión ecológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1443^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1443^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d230</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4531</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32348</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13954</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7487^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31494</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
