<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113477</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gender differences in the perception of professional achievement in family medicine, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The concept of achievement is important to study the professional development. Inmedicine there are gender inequalities in career. The purpose was to know and compare the professional achievement's perceptions and attributions of female and male primary care physicians inAndalusia. Method: Qualitative study with 12 focus groups (October 2009 to November 2010). Population: primary care physicians. Sample: intentionally segmented by age, sex and health care management. Were conducted by sex: two groups with young physicians, two groups with middle aged and two with health care management. Total: 32 female physician and 33 male physicians. Qualitative content analysis with Nuddist Vivo. Results: Female and male physicians agree to perceive internal achievements and to consider aspects inherent to the profession as external achievements. The most important difference is that female physician related professional achievement with affective bond and male physician with institutional merit. Internal attributions are more important for female physician who also highlight the importance of family, the organization of working time and work-family balance. Patients, continuing education, institutional resources and computer system are the most important attributions for male physician. Conclusions: There are similarities and differences between female and male physicians both in the understanding and the attributions of achievement. The differences are explained by the gender system. The perception of achievement of the female physicians questions the dominant professional culture and incorporates new values in defining achievement. The attributions reflect the unequal impact of family and organizational variables and suggest that the female physicians would be changing gender socialization(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Delgado, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Gómez, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saletti-Cuesta, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López- Fernández, Luis Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: El concepto de logro es clave para estudiar el desarrollo profesional. En medicina existen desigualdades de género en la carrera profesional. El objetivo fue conocer y comparar la percepción de resultados y atribuciones de logro en médicas y médicos de familia de Andalucía. Método: Estudio cualitativo con 12 grupos de discusión. Población: médicas y médicos de familia que trabajan en atención primaria. Muestra: intencional segmentada por edad, sexo y ocupación de la dirección del centro de salud. Realizamos por sexo: dos grupos de jóvenes, dos grupos de mayores y dos de directores/as; total 32 médicas y 33 médicos. Análisis de contenido. Resultados: Médicas y médicos perciben de igual modo los logros internos y coinciden en considerar como logros externos aspectos inherentes a la profesión. La diferencia más importante es que las médicas relacionan el logro con los vínculos afectivos y los médicos con méritos institucionales. Para las médicas las atribuciones internas son más importantes y destacan la importancia de la familia, la organización de la jornada laboral y el balance familia- trabajo. Para los médicos las atribuciones más importantes son sus pacientes, la formación continuada, los recursos disponibles y el sistema informático. Conclusiones: Existen similitudes y diferencias entre médicas y médicos en la percepción de logro. Las diferencias se explican por el sistema de género. La percepción de logro de las médicas cuestiona la cultura profesional e incorpora nuevos valores. Las atribuciones reflejan el impacto desigual de variables familiares y organizacionales y apunta a que las médicas estarían modificando rasgos de la socialización de género(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;87(3): 221-238, mayo-jun.2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113477</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias de género en la percepción del logro profesional en especialistas de medicina familiar y comunitaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11724</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11799^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11799^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11799^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5924</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11253^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d133</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5086^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11253^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
