<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90012</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Botulinum toxin and cervical myofascial pain: a pilot study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Myofascial pain is characterized by shortened muscles with increased tone that contain firm nodules in which pressure triggers intense local and distant pain. The aim of empirically used treatments has been to inactivate the painful points, however, the response has not been satisfactory. Recent studies have suggested the utility of botulinum toxin A (BTX-A) in persistent myofascial pain as it controls muscle spasm as well as having other possible effects in neurotransmission. Aim. To evaluate the duration of the analgesic effect of BTX-A in relationship to the dose applied. Material and methods. All the patients who came to Rehabilitation during a one-year period due to chronic moderate-severe (n=8) cervical myofascial pain were included. BTX-A (Dysport®) 100, 150 or 300 U was infiltrated on the trapezoid level and a follow-up was made regarding the analgesic effect for one year. In order to evaluate the effect, the patients were questioned about their degree of pain (mild-moderate-severe) and the presence of other coadjuvant analgesic treatments. Results. All but one of the cases remained asymptomatic for more than three months, and those who received a higher dose were even asymptomatic at one year. Conclusions. The application of BTX-A in a dose of 300 U (Dysport®) in patients with cervical myofascial refractory obtain better long term results than those with 100 U BTX-A (Dysport®)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oyarzabal Zulaica, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laparte Escorza, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El dolor miofascial está caracterizado por músculos acortados, con tono aumentado, que contienen nódulos firmes cuya presión desencadena dolor intenso localizado y a distancia. El objetivo de los tratamientos utilizados empíricamente ha sido la inactivación de los puntos dolorosos, pero la respuesta ha sido poco satisfactoria. Estudios recientes señalan la utilidad de la toxina botulínica A (BTX-A) en el dolor miofascial persistente, a través del control del espasmo muscular, además de otros posibles efectos en la neurotransmisión. Objetivo. Valorar la duración del efecto analgésico de la BTX-A en relación con la dosis aplicada. Material y métodos. Se incluyó a todos los pacientes que acudieron a consulta de rehabilitación durante 1 año, por dolor miofascial cervical crónico, moderado-intenso (n=8). Se procedió a infiltrar 100, 150 o 300 U de BTX-A (Dysport®) a nivel de los trapecios, y posteriormente se realizó un seguimiento del efecto analgésico durante 1 año. Para la valoración del efecto, se preguntó el grado de dolor (leve-moderado-intenso) y la presencia de otros tratamientos analgésicos coadyuvantes. Resultados. Todos, excepto uno de los casos, permanecieron asintomáticos durante más de 3 meses, llegando incluso a 1 año los que habían recibido mayor dosis. Conclusiones. La aplicación de 300 U de BTX-A (Dysport®) en pacientes con cervicalgia miofascial refractaria consigue mejores resultados a largo plazo que 100 U BTX-A (Dysport®)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);45(3): 217-221, jul.-sep.2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90012</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Toxina botulínica y dolor miofascial cervical crónico. Estudio piloto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9401^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3305^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33081^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9401^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27771</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3305^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
