<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107110</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Role of laboratory tests in managing acute poisonings: a survey of emergency physicians</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To survey physicians who treat acute poisoning cases to determine their attitudes toward laboratory testing in these cases and also toward certain tests for the management of common poisonings. Methods: A questionnaire was sent to physicians working in the emergency departments of 2 hospitals with toxicology units and to physicians attending toxicology training courses. Survey items asked about professional data; the degree of importance the physicians attached to laboratory testing at different stages in the care process; which 3 tests the respondents considered important in 17 different acute poisoning scenarios; and which laboratory test they considered highly important was unavailable at the hospitals where the physicians worked. Results: Eighty-eight valid questionnaires were returned; 69 of them (78%) were from physicians attending toxicology courses and 19 (22%) were from emergency room physicians. The respondents in both groups believed that laboratory tests were most important when cases of acute poisoning were being diagnosed; 62% of the emergency department physicians and 58% of the trainee physicians expressed that opinion. More emergency department physicians at(..)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castanyer Puig, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barceló Martín, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puiguriguer Ferrando, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nogué Xarau, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar mediante una encuesta la percepción que los facultativos que atienden a pacientes intoxicados agudos tienen sobre el papel del laboratorio y conocer la importancia subjetiva que otorgan a determinadas pruebas para realizar el manejo clínico de las intoxicaciones agudas frecuentes. Método: La encuesta se dirigió a urgenciólogos que trabajan en servicios de urgencias(SU) de dos hospitales con Unidades de Toxicología Clínica (UTC) y médicos asistentes a cursos de formación toxicológica. Se solicitaba: datos profesionales, grado de importancia atribuida a las pruebas del laboratorio para las diferentes etapas asistenciales, un máximo de tres pruebas fundamentales para el cuidado de 17 intoxicaciones agudas e indicar una determinación de analítica básica y que no se realizase en su laboratorio. Resultados: Ochenta y ocho encuestas se consideraron válidas, de las cuales 69 (78%)se recogieron en cursos y 19 (22%) en 2 SU. La etapa asistencial a la cual los facultativos encuestados otorgan una mayor importancia al laboratorio es la etapa diagnóstica, independientemente del grupo al que pertenecen (62% si pertenecen a SU y 58% si asistieron a cursos). El papel del laboratorio es más relevante (p &lt; 0,05) para aquellos médicos encuestados que trabajan en SU de los hospitales con UTC (52%) que para los (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);24(6): 447-453, dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107110</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Encuesta a urgenciólogos sobre el papel del laboratorio en el manejo de las intoxicaciones agudas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22929^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24419</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11471^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
