<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-37671</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Antibodies against cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Within the revolution of molecular biology in cancer, it should be pointed out the role of monoclonal antibodies clinically utilized as if they were "magic bullets". From the works of Kohler and Milstein in 1975 the evolution has been fast and its inclusion in daily clinical practice gradual. Among the more significant there is anti-CD20 that has revolutionized the treatment of lymphomas. Currently, antibodies conjugated with isotopes derived from anti-CD20 have been produced. Trastuzumab antibody against HER2/neu has opened new prospects in the treatment of breast cancer. Cetuximab antibody against EGFR has achieved good results in the treatment of chemotherapy-resistent colon cancer. Bevacizumab is perhaps the most promising antibody against solid tumors, having shown effectiveness as first line therapy in metastatic colon cancer in combination with chemotherapy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ediciones Doyma, S.L.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Dentro de la revolución que está suponiendo la biología molecular en el cáncer cabe destacar el papel de los anticuerpos monoclonales empleados en la clínica como si de "balas mágicas" se tratara. Desde los trabajos de Kholer y Milstein en 1975 la evolución ha sido rápida y su inclusión en la práctica clínica diaria paulatina. Entre los más destacados se encuentra el anti-CD20, que ha revolucionado el tratamiento de los linfomas. Actualmente se han realizado anticuerpos conjugados con isótopos derivados del anti-CD20. El trastuzumab anticuerpo frente al HER2/neu que ha abierto nuevas perspectivas en el tratamiento del cáncer de mama. El cetuximab anticuerpo frente al EGFR ha conseguido buenos resultados en el tratamiento del cáncer de colon quimiorresistente. El bevacizumab quizá sea el más prometedor de los anticuerpos frente a tumores sólidos, habiendo mostrado eficacia en primera línea de cáncer de colon metastásico en combinación con quimioterapia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;204(12): 649-654, dic. 2004.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anticuerpos contra el cáncer</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>González Barón, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-37671</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d7345^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d921^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d974^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d921^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
