<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045701</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Correlation of lipid profiles and anthropometric variables with serumlipoprotein(a) levels in childhood</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of the present study was to evaluate lipoprotein(a) distribution in children and to assess its association with lipid profile and anthropometric variables.                 We studied 98 children (44 girls and 54 boys) with ages ranging from 6 to 7 years, who were included in an epidemiological study on the prevalence of hypercholesterolemia in children in the province of Biscay. The following parameters were determined: weight and height, body mass index, lipoprotein(a), and lipid profile. Lipid profile included total cholesterol, high-density lipoprotein (HDL)-cholesterol, low-density lipoprotein (LDL)-cholesterol, triglycerides, apolipoprotein B, and apolipoprotein A1.                 The mean and median serum lipoprotein(a) levels were 13.07 and 5.56 mg/dl respectively and were 11.43 and 3.92 mg/dl for boys and 15.09 and 8.32 mg/dl for girls. Lipoprotein(a) concentrations &gt; 30 mg/dl were found in 7.4 % of the boys and in 11.4 % of the girls. The mean values and prevalences of lipoprotein(a) &gt; 30 mg/dl were lower in boys than in girls but these differences were not statistically significant. A positive correlation was found between lipid profile (LDL-cholesterol, apolipoprotein B and LDL-cholesterol/HDL-cholesterol index) and lipoprotein(a) levels. When evaluating anthropometric variables, we found a statistically significant inverse correlation between weight and lipoprotein(a).                 In view of the cumulative effect of cardiovascular risk factors and the results of this study, we believe that lipoprotein(a) determination should be considered in children with an unfavorable lipid profile</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Magro López, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Narváez Gofinondo, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vacas Rius, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iriarte Ezkurdia, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáez Meabe, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molinero de Miguel, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lafita Bernar, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáez de Lafuente Chivite, J. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sagastagoitia Gorostiza, J. D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del estudio ha sido determinar la distribución de lipoproteína(a) en niños y su relación con variables antropométricas y parámetros lipídicos.                 Se estudian 98 niños (44 niñas, 54 niños), con edades comprendidas entre los 6 y 7 años, procedentes de un estudio epidemiológico sobre prevalencia de hipercolesterolemia en niños de Vizcaya. Se les determinó peso y talla, se calculó el índice de masa corporal, la concentración de lipoproteína(a), así como un estudio lipídico que incluía colesterol total, colesterol HDL (c-HDL), triglicéridos, colesterol LDL (c-LDL), apolipoproteína B y apolipoproteína A1.                 La media y mediana de lipoproteína(a) fue de 13,07 y 5,56 mg/dl; para los niños era de 11,43 y 3,92 mg/dl y 15,09 y 8,32 mg/dl para las niñas. El 7,4 % de los niños y el 11,4 % de las niñas presentaban concentraciones de lipoproteína(a) superiores a 30 mg/dl. Los niños mostraron valores medios y prevalencias de lipoproteína(a) superiores 30 mg/dl inferiores a las niñas, pero sin ser estadísticamente significativas. Hay una correlación positiva entre el perfil lipídico (c-LDL, apolipoproteína B y el cociente c-LDL/c-HDL) y las concentraciones de lipoproteína(a). En cuanto a la evaluación de las variables antropométricas, encontramos una correlación estadísticamente significativa inversa entre el peso y la lipoproteína(a).                 Teniendo en cuenta el efecto aditivo de los factores de riesgo cardiovascular y observando los datos obtenidos, pensamos que debería considerarse la determinación de lipoproteína(a) en aquellos niños que presenten un perfil lipídico desfavorable</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);64(3): 235-238, mar. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045701</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Correlación de los perfiles lipoproteicos y variables antropométricas con concentraciones séricas de lipoproteína(a) en la infancia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30669^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8230^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
