<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163462</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-5887</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A bioethics approach to the Convention against trafficking in Human Organs</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The article analyzes the Convention against trafficking with Human Organs from the Council of Europe (2015) from a legal and bioethical perspective. It systematizes and considers the contributions of the Convention: commercialization with the human body as a violation of human rights and the delimitation of organ donations to free and informed consented acts. The Convention is significant for its contribution to the human rights and to the debate of the limits on the use and control over one&#146;s body. But it takes no position on certain highly controversial issues: donation by incompetent people and compensation for donation; giving a broad margin of appreciation to States parties may undermine its potential effectiveness (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Porxas Roig, Maria Àngels</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El artículo analiza jurídicamente desde una perspectiva bioética el Convenio sobre la lucha contra el tráfico de Órganos del Consejo de Europa (2015). Se sistematizan y se reflexiona sobre los valores y novedades que aporta el Convenio: la mercantilización del cuerpo humano como vulneración de los derechos humanos y la delimitación de las donaciones de órganos a los actos de gratuidad con consentimiento informado. El Convenio es significativo por su aporte a los derechos humanos y al debate sobre la libre disponibilidad del cuerpo. Pero no se posiciona sobre ciertas cuestiones altamente controvertidas: la donación por parte de personas incapaces de consentir y la compensación por donación; dando un amplio margen de apreciación a los Estados que puede mermar su potencial efectividad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. bioét. derecho;(40): 141-155, jul. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163462</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La Convención sobre la lucha contra el Tráfico de Órganos, una mirada desde la bioética</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3433^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55428^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55779^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33598</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55428^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201707</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
