<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120644</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Metabolism in fasting and injury. Its role in the development of disease-related malnutrition</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The healthy human body has adaptation mechanism allowing survival without having access to exogenous nutrients for prolonged periods of time. These mechanisms are sequential and are characterized by the onset of glucose producing systems followed by the generation of ketonicbodies, among others. These modifications are set up in the hormonal context of &#147;saving or hypometabolism&#148;, which is characterized by low anabolic hormones (insulin) levels without an excessive response of catabolic hormones. In any case, in the context of a patient suffering from an acute pathology, the situation dramatically changes and the response of &#147;excessive waste or catabolic / hypermetabolic &#148;response largely surpasses the hypometabolic response. During a stressful condition, several mechanisms are put in place such as contrarregulatory hormones, catabolic interleukins, mTOR, receptors blockade, the ubiquitin-proteasomeroute, etc., all of them aimed at providing energy and substrates to enhance healing. However, it generally is a redundant, excessive, and partially uncontrolled response in which the subject rapidly losses substrates and reserves, which increases the morbimortality. Therefore, in order to improve the efficiency, we should keep in mind an early therapeutic approach aimed at providing specialized nutritional support (or nutrimetabolic) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García de Lorenzo y Mateos, Abelardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Montes, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El organismo humano sano dispone de mecanismos de adaptación que le permiten subsistir sin acceso a nutrientes exógenos durante largos periodos de tiempo. Estos mecanismos son secuenciales y se caracterizan por puesta en marcha de sistemas de producción de glucosa continuados por generación de cuerpos cetónicos, entre otros. Estas modificaciones se plantean en un contexto hormonal &#147;de ahorro o hipometabolismo&#148; y caracterizado por bajos niveles de hormonas anabólicas (insulina) y sin una respuesta excesiva de las hormonas catabólicas. De cualquier forma, en el contexto de un paciente portador de patología aguda, la situación cambia de forma radical y la respuesta de &#147;gasto desmesurado o catabólica/hipermetabólica &#148;supera con creces a la respuesta hipometabólica. En el estrés nos encontramos con puesta en marcha de diversos mecanismos como las hormonas contra reguladoras, las interleucinas catabólicas, el bloqueo de los receptores, la vía de la ubiquitina-proteasoma, el mTOR&#133; todos ellos dirigidos a la consecución de energía y substratos para potenciar la curación. Ahora bien, suele ser una respuesta redundante, excesiva y parcialmente descontrolada en laque el individuo pierde substratos y reservas de forma rápida, lo que aumenta la morbimortalidad. Ello hace que en aras de una mejor eficiencia debemos tener en mente el abordaje terapéutico, precoz y dirigido a objetivos con soporte nutricional (o nutrometabólico) especializado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;6(supl.1): 1-9, mayo 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120644</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Metabolismo en el ayuno y la agresión. Su papel en el desarrollo de la desnutrición relacionada con la enfermedad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32108^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13700</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4813^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29390^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201305</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
