<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100956</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of endoscopic biopsy in Barrett's esophagus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objetive: Endoscopy with random biopsies is the standard technique for the diagnosis of Barrett's esophagus (BE). We studied the usefulness of endoscopic biopsies in the diagnosis and surveillance of patients with BE.Patients: We reviewed all patients with BE controlled at the Hospital Clínic from February 2002 to March 2010. Results: During the study period, 493 endoscopies were performed in 206 patients. We excluded 86 patients who had undergone one endoscopy only, hence the final sample consisted of 117 patients (mean age 61 [12] years, 73% men) with 407 endoscopies and a mean follow-up of 45 (38) months. Fifty-seven patients had a short-BE (49%), 28 a long-BE (24%) and 32 (27%) could not be inferred from the report. In 25 cases (21%), intestinal metaplasia (IM) was not detected at the endoscopic index. During follow-up, biopsies were negative for IM at some point in 45 patients (38.4%) and there was a change in the histologic grade in 100 cases (24.6%). The presence of a short-BE (43% in short-BE vs 7% in long-BE, P=.001) and few biopsies (3 [1.5] vs 6.2 [4.5]; P=.005) were associated with a higher frequency of negative biopsies for IM. Conclusion: Random endoscopic biopsies are not a good tool for diagnosis and surveillance of patients with BE (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Saperas, Esteve</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuatrecasas, Miriam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elizalde, J. Ignasi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-D&#146;Jesús, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Córdova, Henry</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Esparrach, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llach, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: La endoscopia con obtención de biopsias múltiples es la técnica estándar para el diagnóstico y seguimiento del esófago de Barrett (EB). El objetivo de este trabajo fue estudiar la utilidad de las biopsias endoscópicas en el diagnóstico y seguimiento de los pacientes con EB. Pacientes y método: Estudio retrospectivo de todos los pacientes con EB controlados en el Hospital Clínic desde febrero de 2002 hasta marzo de 2010. Resultados: En el período de estudio se realizaron 493 endoscopias a 206 pacientes. Se excluyeron 86 pacientes a los que se les había realizado solo una endoscopia, siendo la muestra final de 117 pacientes (edad media [DE] de 61 [12] años y 73% de varones) con 407 endoscopias y un tiempo medio de seguimiento de 45 (38) meses. Un total de 57 pacientes tenían un EB corto (49%), 28 un EB largo (24%) y en 32 (27%) no se pudo deducir del informe. En 25 casos (21%) no se detectó metaplasia intestinal (MI) en la endoscopia inicial. Durante el seguimiento, las biopsias fueron negativas para MI en algún momento en 45 pacientes (38,4%) y se produjo un cambio en el grado histológico en 100 ocasiones (24,6%). La presencia de un EB corto (43% en EB corto frente a 7% en EB largo; p=0,001) y un menor número de biopsias (media de 3 [1,5] frente a 6,2 [4,5], p=0,005) se asociaron a una mayor frecuencia de biopsias negativas para MI. Conclusión: Las biopsias endoscópicas múltiples no son una buena herramienta para el diagnóstico y seguimiento de los pacientes con EB (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);139(3): 103-106, jun. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100956</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de la biopsia endoscópica en el esófago de Barrett</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8855^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29389^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1493^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
