<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77889</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mesenchymal cells and fibrocytes in peripheral blood. Culture conditions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: The fibrocytes, the mesenchymal cells and the colony forming units are included in the concept fibroblast-like, peripheral-blood circulating stem cells The aim of this work was to establish the culture conditions. Material and method: Peripheral blood mononuclear cells were isolated from 25 samples collected from the cephalic vein. These were cultured in McCoy&#146;s 5A enriched with 20% of foetal bovine serum. The culture was read at 7, 14 and 21 days, evaluating the proliferation, confluence and the round cell/spindle cell ratio. Moreover the 21st day surface markers and phagocytic activity testing was carried out. Results: Growth was achieved in all the cases but only in two dishes were confluence areas retrieved. Spindle cells were 36 ± 3.71% (mean ± SD). All the cells showed intense signal against vimentin, CD34 marker and the NBT test were positives. Conclusions: Clear CD34 expression, positivity against a connective tissue marker such as vimentin and positivity in a phagocytic assay like the NBT-test, support that stem cells, monocytes and fibroblasts share common characteristics (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villarroya-Aparicio, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cativiela, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín-Redondo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Ochoa, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Lahoz, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: El término fibroblast-like, célula madre de sangre periférica, engloba a las unidades formadoras de colonias fibroblásticas, los fibrocitos y las células mesenquimales. El diseño de este trabajo intenta establecer las condiciones de cultivo. Material y método: En 25 muestras de sangre venosa se aislaron células mononucleares y se sembraron en medio de cultivo McCoy&#146;s 5A con suero bovino fetal al 20%. A los 7, 14 y 21 días se evaluó la proliferación, la confluencia y la relación células redondas/células alargadas. El día 21 se valoró la morfología, los marcadores de superficie y la actividad fagocítica. Resultados: En todos los cultivos se detectó crecimiento celular positivo para la vimentina, CD34 y NBT. La media ± desviación estándar del 36 ± 3,71% eran células alargadas (fibrocitos) y sólo en 2 casos se registraron áreas de confluencia. Conclusiones: Los métodos de cultivo descritos son adecuados para los seudofibroblastos de sangre periférica. La positividad de CD34, prueba NBT y vimentina demuestra que los seudofibroblastos tienen características comunes con la célula madre, los monocitos-macrófagos y los fibroblastos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);3(5): 200-203, sept.-oct. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77889</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Células mesenquimales y fibrocitos en sangre periférica. Condiciones de cultivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32815^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9764</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15150^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2512^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32848^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5482^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54432^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
