<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046970</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Visions from the perspective of disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There is an almost obsessive need to find some sense to suffering andthe feeling of loss. Finding some sort of answer significantly helps to livewith the disease and to overcome it. The experience of suffering a conditionmakes us come face to face with the most pristine traits of oursociety. In this paper I will try to analyse briefly some of those traits, as Ido not consider a therapeutic action involving care and rehabilitation,possible without taking such traits into account. This brings healthcareprofessionals and beloved ones face to face with the ill individual in thissearch for meaning. This specific activity is called &#147;accompaniment&#148;</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pont Barceló, Esteban</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Existe una necesidad casi obsesiva en encontrar algún sentido al sufrimientoy a las pérdidas, pues hallar alguna respuesta ayuda de formasignificativa a vivir con la enfermedad y tratar de superarla. La experienciade sufrir una enfermedad nos enfrenta a los rasgos más prístinos denuestra humanidad. En el presente artículo, trataré de analizar someramentealgunos de esos rasgos, pues no creo posible la acción terapéutica,de cuidados o rehabilitación, sin tenerlos en cuenta. Esto confrontaimperativamente a los profesionales y allegados a acompañar al enfermoen esta búsqueda de significados. Esta actividad concreta se denomina&#147;acompañamiento&#148;</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;9(5): 10-15, jun. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046970</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Visiones desde la enfermedad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5342^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54840^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12467^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8308^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28564^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23274</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23899</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13184</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
