<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133686</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of information technologies by the plastic surgeons of Uruguay. A national online survey</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Internet has become an essential tool in modern communication and has changed significantly and in a lasting way how people relate and communicate with other people in different aspects, including the professional one. Currently the vast majority of the information available to the physician in his training and in his professional life is on the Internet. To be able to access this information and to be able to take advantage of technology has key importance today. In 2010, at least 100 medical research studies in internationally indexed journals were based on survey data; among these, online surveys via emails or internet sites, because of its low costs and high accessibility, are becoming more common every day. Considering this fact, we developed an online survey about the use of information technology by the plastic surgeons in Uruguay, with the support of the Department of Plastic Surgery and the Plastic Surgery Society of Uruguay (SCPREU). The survey was conducted using an online survey service called Survey Methods® (Dallas, Texas, USA). We used the database of emails of the SCPREU, and sent by e-mail 142 surveys; we obtained 71 responses for a gross response rate of 50%. We sent out an initial invitation and 3 minder messages, 1 each week. The most relevant results of our survey showed that the respondents have at least one computer equipment allowing access to the Internet and 84,51 % access the network on a daily basis. Of all respondents, 95,77 % look for scientific information on the Internet and 98,57 % are interested on receiving scientific information by mail. We considerer that these data creates a window of opportunity for the development of online contents in our specialty (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castillo Arboleda, FE</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jacobo Bastreri, OM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Internet se ha convertido en una herramienta esencial en la comunicación moderna que ha cambiado de manera significativa y duradera la forma de relación y comunicación personal en sus diferentes aspectos, incluido el profesional. Actualmente, la gran mayoría de la información disponible para el médico tanto durante su formación como en su vida profesional está en Internet; el acceso a esta información y el tener la capacidad de sacar ventaja de la tecnología tienen por tanto una importancia clave. En 2010, al menos 100 investigaciones médicas en revistas indexadas internacionalmente se basaron en datos de encuestas; entre éstas, las encuestas en línea a través de correos electrónicos o sitios de Internet se están volviendo cada día más habituales por su bajo costo, su accesibilidad e inmediatez de contacto. Teniendo en cuenta todos estos aspectos, desarrollamos una encuesta en línea sobre el uso de la tecnología de la información por los cirujanos plásticos en Uruguay, con el apoyo de la Cátedra de Cirugía Plástica y la Sociedad de Cirugía Plástica, Reparadora y Estética del Uruguay (SCPREU). La encuesta se realizó mediante el servicio de encuesta en línea Survey Methods® (Dallas, Texas, EE.UU.). Usando la base de datos de correos electrónicos de afiliados a la SCPREU, enviamos por correo electrónico 142 encuestas y obtuvimos 71 respuestas para una tasa bruta de respuesta del 50 % . La encuesta se envió mediante una invitación inicial y 3 mensajes de recordatorio, 1 cada semana. Los resultados más relevantes de la encuesta mostraron que la mayoría de los que respondieron tiene más de un equipo que le permite acceder a Internet, y que el 84,51 % accede a la red con regularidad diaria. El 95,77 % de quienes respondieron a la encuesta, buscan información científica en Internet a la misma y el 98,57 % está interesado en recibir información científica por correo electrónico. Consideramos que estos datos constituyen una ventana de oportunidad para el desarrollo de contenidos en línea en el ámbito de nuestra especialidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;40(4): 429-435, oct.-dic. 2014. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133686</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso de las tecnologías de la información por los cirujanos plásticos del Uruguay. Encuesta nacional en línea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19081</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7432^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14985</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51868^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53738</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
