<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050812</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Industrial homework: the case of shoe workers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Industrial homework undertaken by a large number of women in the footwear industry is part of the        submerged economy with a long tradition in the Valencian region. The objective of this study is to identify and analyse        the working conditions of women who make shoes in Elche and the effects on their heath and their family.        Methods: The research combines quantitative methodology, cross-sectional descriptive study with qualitative        methodology, based on semi-structural individual interviews. Women were selected from those who attend the Health        Centre in Plá de Elche (Alicante), with the condition of having previously worked or are now working in industrial        homework in the footwear industry. Information was obtained from 30 women about socio-demographic characteristics,        working conditions and effects on health. The interviews were recorded and transcribed for the later analysis of 6        women.        Results: 96. 7% of the women who took part in the study did not use protective measures against the toxicity of the        adhesives. Accidents originating in the use of tools represents 80% and osteo-muscular complaints were evident in        67.7%. 26.7% had had abortions.        Conclusion: The productive work they carry out causes health problems . These women lack knowledge about        preventive and place more importance on having a job than on the unfavourable conditions of their work</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ronda Pérez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrillo, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nolasco, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El trabajo a domicilio que realizan un amplio número de mujeres en la industria del calzado es una actividad        económica sumergida de larga implantación en la Comunidad Valenciana. El objetivo de este estudio es describir las        condiciones laborales de estas mujeres que trabajan en Elche y los efectos en su salud y en la de su familia.        Métodos: Investigación que combina metodología cuantitativa, estudio descriptivo transversal, y cualitativa, basada en        entrevistas individuales semiestructuradas. Se seleccionaron mujeres que acudían al Centro de Salud el Plá de Elche        (Alicante), con el criterio de haber trabajado o que trabajen en la actualidad a domicilio en la rama industrial del        calzado. Para 30 mujeres. se obtuvo información sobre datos sociodemográficos, condiciones laborales, laborales y salud        percibida. Las entrevistas fueron grabadas y transcritas para el posterior análisis en 6 mujeres.        Resultados: De las 30 mujeres que participaron en el estudio, el 96,7% no utilizaban medidas protectoras frente a los        factores de riesgo. La siniestralidad originada por la utilización de herramientas supone un 80,0% y los problemas        osteomusculares se presentan en un 66,7%. El 26,7% ha tenido abortos.        Conclusión: El trabajo productivo que realizan afecta a su salud. Estas mujeres carecen de cultura preventiva y        anteponen el tener un contrato laboral a las condiciones desfavorables de su trabajo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. prev. riesgos labor. (Ed. impr.);8(4): 149-154, oct.-dic. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050812</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trabajo a domicilio: el caso de las aparadoras de calzado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7395^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13153</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
