<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130727</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychosocial factors and the type of volunteerism</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The first purpose of this study is to research the existence of differences between two types of volunteerism in certain variables. The second purpose is to identify the variables that increasing the prediction of sustained volunteerism. 290 volunteers completed a questionnaire and after two telephone follow-ups were carried out to determine whether volunteers remained in the NGO. The results show that environmental and socio-assistential volunteers are significantly different in several variables, and different variables and relationships according to the types of volunteerism allow increasing the prediction of sustained volunteerism (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Chacón Fuertes, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dávila de León, M Celeste</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El propósito de este trabajo es, en primer lugar, estudiar la existencia de diferencias entre diversos tipos de voluntariado en ciertas variables relevantes en la explicación de este fenómeno; y, en segundo lugar, identificar cuáles de estas variables pueden aumentar la predicción de la permanencia en función del tipo de voluntariado. Un total de 290 voluntarios completaron un cuestionario y posteriormente colaboraron en dos seguimientos telefónicos para evaluar su permanencia en la organización. Los resultados muestran que los voluntarios ecologistas y socioasistenciales difieren significativamente en diversas variables, y que no son las mismas variables, ni las mismas relaciones las que permiten  incrementar la predicción de la permanencia en cada tipo de voluntariado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);16(4): 639-645, oct.-dic. 2004. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130727</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores psicosociales y tipo de voluntariado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4531</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15240^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
