<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114777</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Low cost reproducible controlled negative pressure system for the treatment of problem wounds</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">As plastic surgeons we deal frequently with the management of problem wounds. The literature describes as a therapeutic option the use of negative pressure. As a technical instrument the system called Vacuum Assisted Closure-KCI® (San Antonio, Texas, USA) is the commercially available system. The cost of this therapy is not accessible to the patients of our institution. Therefore we designed a system of controlled negative pressure for the treatment of these wounds. The system is made of a negative pressure manometer installed to a two way valve, connected in one end to the hospital wall negative pressure system and in the other end to a sterile 1/4 inch diameter tube, connected to a drain that is put over sterile towels that are placed over the problem wound area to be treated, and sealed with a sterile adhesive. With this system we treated 14 patients with different types of problem wounds, achieving clinical improvement. We also used this system to improve the survival of skin grafts placed on problem wounds (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Serrano González-Rubio, A. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Zambrano, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Como cirujanos plásticos nos enfrentamos con el manejo de heridas problema. Está descrito como opción de tratamiento la terapia con presión negativa. Como instrumento técnico se reconoce en la literatura al sistema Vacuum Assisted Closure-KCI® (San Antonio, Texas, EE.UU.) como sistema comercialmente disponible. Su costo hace que no sea accesible para los pacientes de nuestra institución. Por esta razón diseñamos un sistema de presión negativa controlada para tratar estas lesiones. El sistema consiste en un manómetro de presión negativa instalado a una válvula bidireccional conectada en un extremo al sistema de presión negativa de pared del hospital y en el otro extremo a un tubo estéril de 1/4 de pulgada, conectado a su vez a un drenaje que se coloca sobre compresas estériles ubicadas sobre el área de la herida a tratar, que se sella con un adhesivo estéril. Tratamos con este sistema 14 pacientes con diversos tipos de heridas problemáticas logrando mejoría clínica de las mismas. Se utilizó también para mejorar la integración de los injertos de piel colocados sobre heridas problema (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;39(2): 173-179, abr.-jun. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114777</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sistema reproducible de presión negativa controlada de bajo costo, para curación de heridas problema</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54250^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6248</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15343</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
