<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110545</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-7823</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The paper revises the processes that take place in cyberbullying at the interpersonal, intrapersonal, group and contextual levels, analyzing the most significant components in the profiles of participants of cyberbullying. Moreover, these situations are related to the moral values that may arise. Thus, educational conditions that favour prevention and intervention tasks in cyberbullying by the educational community are highlighted. Lines of work to approach the necessary moral education issues needed by educational agents to eradicate these behaviours are also suggested (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Avilés Martínez, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el artículo se revisan los procesos que se dan en el ciberbullying en los planos interpersonal, intrapersonal, grupal y contextual, analizando los componentes más significativos en los perfiles de sus participantes. Por otra parte, se relacionan con los valores morales que ponen en juego. Por ello, se destacan las condiciones educativas que favorecen tareas de prevención e intervención en el ciberbullying por la comunidad educativa. Igualmente se sugieren líneas de trabajo para tratar los contenidos de la educación moral por parte de los agentes educativos para erradicar estas conductas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pap. psicol;34(1): 65-73, ene.-abr. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110545</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis psicosocial del ciberbullying:  Claves para una educación moral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9204</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50132</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33921</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34823</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
