<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93271</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Heat stroke</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Heat stroke is a medical emergency and a treatable cause of multiorganicfailure (MOF). It is caracterized by an increase in central bodytemperature (above 40oC) and alterations in the central nervous system where encephalopathy is predominate and comatous states are typical. An early diagnosis is vital and if the right initial measures are not taken the death rate tends to be very high (according to different series arround70%). It is habitually found in two types. Firstly in relation to exercise in hot atmospheres (which affects young healthy people fundamentally) and secondly the more classical situation (which affects young healthly people fundamentally)and secondly the more classical situation (which affects the elderly or people with weakening illnesses) during severe heat weaves. It can be classified within syndromes induced by the heat in the atmosphere and occurs as a consequence of a thermo regulating system failure. The treatment is based on an immediate cooling process and supportive measures view to recovering all organs from their state of insufficiency (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alemparte Pardavila, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez García, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piñeiro Sande, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Melgar, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El golpe de calor es una emergencia médica y causa tratable de fracaso multiorgánico (FMO). Se caracteriza por un incremento de la temperatura corporal central por encima de 40ºC y alteraciones del sistema nervioso central donde predomina la encefalopatía y es típico el coma. Es fundamental el diagnóstico precoz y, si no se toman las medidas iniciales oportunas, la tasa de mortalidad es muy alta (hasta el 70%). Las dos formas habituales de presentación son: 1ºen relación con el ejercicio en ambientes calurosos (que afecta fundamentalmente a individuos jóvenes sanos) y 2º la forma clásica (que afecta a ancianos o individuos con enfermedades debilitantes) durante intensas olas de calor. Puede clasificarse dentro de los síndromes inducidos por el calor ambiental y su presentación es consecuencia del fracaso del sistema termorregulador. El tratamiento se basa en el enfriamiento inmediato junto con el soporte de órganos y sistemas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);16(3): 116-125, jun. 2004. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93271</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Golpe de calor</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3159^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5444^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9294^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1947^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6509^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1858</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
