<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91759</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A trial on prevention/minimization of the disorganization of attachment in &#147;Paris and Suburbs&#148;</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Attachment is considered an essential component of social and emotional development in early life, and individual differences in the quality of attachment relationships are regarded as important early indicators for infant mental health. In this article we explore the relevance of the early prevention work as a strategic attachment intervention. The prevention program CAPEDP-Attachment, developed in &#147;Paris an suburbs&#148; is presented here. We conclude with a clinical discussion of a strange situation video of a disorganized attachment enfant, to illustrate the relevance of the video feedback therapy in the context of early home intervention  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tereno, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guedeney, Antoine</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sodjnou, Andrée</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guedeney, Nicole</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El apego está considerado como un componente esencial del desarrollo social y afectivo en la vida temprana y la calidad de las relaciones de apego se consideran como importantes indicadores tempranos de la salud mental del bebé. Este articulo analiza la relevancia del trabajo de prevención temprana como una estrategia de intervención del apego. Se presenta el programa de prevención CAPEDP-Apego, desarrollado en &#147;París y suburbios&#148;. Concluimos con una discusión clínica sobre un video de una situación extraña en un niño con apego desorganizado, para ilustrar la importancia de la terapia de video-feddback, en el contexto de la intervención temprana en el hogar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(17): 19-26, abr. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91759</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Un ensayo de prevención/disminución de la desorganización del vínculo en &#147;París y suburbios&#148;</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9954</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56095^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
