<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95913</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interhospital transport in Castile-Leon: analysis of consisteny in use of transport services</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To determine whether patient transfers from 2 secondary level hospitals (in Palencia and Zamora, Spain) to their respective tertiary care referral hospitals differ with respect to indications for transfer and medical conditions.Methods: Retrospective, observational study with consecutive patient inclusion comparing descriptive statistics for the 2 hospitals over a 3-year period. Hospital transfer orders and patient records were consulted to record patient characteristics, the reason for the transfer, and conditions to be treated. Data for the 2 provinces were then compared. Results: A total of 4467 transfers were analyzed (Palencia, 1861; Zamora, 2606); 58% were scheduled and 42% were emergencies. The mean (SD) age of patients was 60.9 (21.3) years and 67% were males. Scheduled cardiac catheterization accounted for 47.8% of the transfers. Of the emergency transfers, 26.5% were related to neurosurgery. We observed significant differences between the 2 provinces with respect to age, time of transfer, reason for transfer,department of destination, and patient return. Conclusions: Provinces with limited health care resources require interhospital ambulance services, due to the number and variety of transfers and the seriousness of patient conditions. However, there are significant differences between similar provinces, suggesting a need to regulate and standardize criteria for the use of such services (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cembellín del Ama, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez Barrio, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Investigar si existen diferencias en las indicaciones y patologías de los traslados realizados desde los complejos hospitalarios de dos hospitales de nivel II (Palencia y Zamora) a los hospitales de referencia de nivel III. Método: Estudio observacional, descriptivo, retrospectivo, con inclusión consecutiva y con comparación de grupos durante un periodo de tres años. Se recogieron datos de los informes de traslado y del historial clínico de los pacientes, que valoran las características demográficas, el carácter del traslado y las patologías a tratar, y se comparan los datos de ambas provincias. Resultados: Se han valorado 4.467 traslados (Palencia: 1.861; Zamora: 2.606), el 58% de ellos programados y el 42% urgentes. La edad media fue de 60,9 años (DT 21,3) yel 67% fueron hombres. En relación a los motivos de traslado, los cateterismos cardiacos programados suponen el 47,8%, mientras que dentro de los traslados urgentes destacan los subsidiarios de tratamiento neuroquirúrgico con un 26,5%. Se encontraron diferencias significativas entre ambas provincias en cuanto a la edad, el horario, el motivo, el servicio receptor y el retorno final del paciente. Conclusiones: El número de traslados realizados, la variedad y la gravedad de las patologías trasladadas hacen al transporte interhospitalario imprescindible en provincias con recursos sanitarios limitados, si bien existen discrepancias significativas en sus características entre provincias similares, lo que sugiere que es necesaria la regulación y unificación de los criterios en su utilización (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);22(5): 349-354, oct. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95913</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la homogeneidad en las indicaciones de transporte interhospitalario en Castilla-León</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28835^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28845^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
