<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130711</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychometric properties of the Spanish version of the Survey Work-Home Interaction Nijmegen (SWING)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this work was to analyze the psychometric properties of the Spanish version of the «Survey Work-Home Interaction Nijmegen» (SWING) developed by S. Geurts and colleagues to evaluate the relationships between work and family. Its psychometric properties were analyzed with data  from a sample of 283 emergency professionals. Results of confirmatory factor analyses indicated that the four-factor model, in which both kinds of positive and negative interactions were not correlated, provided the best fit to the data (GFI= 0.98, AGFI= 0.98, NFI= 0.97, RMR= 0.03). Thus, this version maintains the original structure of 22 items distributed in four factors: negative work-home interaction, negative home-work interaction, positive work-home interaction and positive home-work interaction. Reliability analysis showed good internal consistency for this Spanish version with Cronbach alpha coefficients for the factors ranging from .77 to .89. Significant correlations were found between the SWING and various scales related to work, family, and well-being, which provided evidence of convergent validity. Thus, this version shows adequate psychometric properties. Guidelines are also provided for the use of the Spanish version of the SWING in future investigations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz Vergel, Ana Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Muñoz, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Jiménez, Bernardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Geurts, Sabine</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente trabajo consistió en examinar las propiedades psicométricas de la versión española del «Survey Work-Home Interaction-Nijmegen» (SWING), desarrollado por S. Geurts y colaboradores para evaluar las relaciones entre el trabajo y la familia. Se estudiaron sus propiedades psicométricas con una muestra de 283 profesionales de emergencias. Los resultados del análisis factorial confirmatorio indican que el modelo de cuatro factores en el que no se correlacionan los componentes de interacción positiva y negativa es el que mejor se ajusta a los datos (GFI= 0,98, AGFI= 0,98, NFI= 0,97, RMR= 0,03). Se mantuvo la estructura original de la escala, que contiene 22 ítems distribuidos en cuatro subescalas: interacción negativa trabajo-familia, interacción negativa familia-trabajo, interacción positiva trabajo-familia, e interacción positiva familia-trabajo. El análisis de la fiabilidad de la escala señaló que esta versión española posee una buena consistencia interna, con valores que se situaron entre 0,77 y 0,89. Se encontraron correlaciones significativas entre el SWING y medidas relativas a aspectos laborales, familiares, así como de bienestar, lo que proporciona apoyo sobre su validez convergente. Se concluye que esta versión posee propiedades psicométricas adecuadas, y se sugieren pautas para el uso de la versión española de este cuestionario en futuras investigaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);21(2): 331-337, abr.-jun. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130711</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Propiedades psicométricas de la versión española del Cuestionario de Interacción Trabajo-Familia (SWING)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16629</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
