<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125242</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship between antihypertensive drug use and development of atrial fibrillation in hypertensive patients in a Primary Care center</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Although antihypertensive treatment can reduce the risk of cardiovascular morbimortality, studies aimed at evaluating the association between antihypertensive drug use and incidence of atrial fibrillation (AF) yield mixed results. This study aimed to determine the possible relationship between antihypertensive drug use and development of AF. Material and methods. Case control study. Cases: Hypertensive patients with AF diagnosed at least one year after the start of drug treatment for hypertension. Controls: Hypertensive patients without AF with pharmacological antihypertensive treatment for at least one year, matching by sex, age and duration of antihypertensive therapy at diagnosis of AF cases. The study included 136 cases and 132 controls. Variables: AF, antihypertensive drugs, control of hypertension, duration of treatment with antihypertensive drugs, number of antihypertensive drugs. Analysis: Crude OR were calculated, with logistic regression being used to calculate the adjusted odds ratios. Results. Overall, diuretics was close to statistical significance: OR 0.616 (95% CI 0.365 to 1.040), as a protective factor for development of AF. Calcium channel blockers behaved as a protective factor against development of AF at 75 years or older (OR 0.366; 95% CI 0.173 to 0.772), and within this age in women (OR 0.343; 95% CI 0.145-0.811). Conclusions. Calcium channel blockers in the group of 75 years or more, especially in women, worked statistically significant as a drug protecting against the appearance of AF. Diuretics may have a protective role in AF incidence in all hypertensive patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cubero-Gómez, C. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Alfonsín, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mena-Villalba, A. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monsalvo-Moro, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lendínez-de la Cruz, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Ruíz, R. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Aunque el tratamiento antihipertensivo puede reducir el riesgo de morbimortalidad cardiovascular, los estudios enfocados a evaluar la asociación entre fármacos antihipertensivos utilizados e incidencia de fibrilación auricular (FA) arrojan resultados dispares. Con este estudio se pretendía averiguar la posible relación entre fármaco antihipertensivo utilizado y aparición de FA. Material y métodos. Estudio de casos y controles. Casos: hipertensos con FA diagnosticada al menos un año después del inicio del tratamiento farmacológico para la hipertensión arterial. Controles: hipertensos sin FA con tratamiento antihipertensivo farmacológico durante al menos un año. Se emparejaron según sexo, edad y duración del tratamiento antihipertensivo al diagnóstico de la FA. Se estudiaron 136 casos y 132 controles. Variables: FA, fármacos antihipertensivos, control de la hipertensión arterial, tiempo de tratamiento con fármacos antihipertensivos, número de fármacos antihipertensivos. Análisis: se calcularon las OR brutas y ajustadas mediante regresión logística. Resultados. Globalmente los diuréticos estuvieron cerca de la significación estadística: OR 0,616 (IC 95% 0,365-1,040), como factor protector de aparición de FA. Los calcioantagonistas se comportaron como factor de protección de aparición de FA en el grupo de 75 años o mayores (OR 0,366; IC 95% 0,173-0,772). Conclusiones. Los calcioantagonistas en el grupo de 75 años o más se comportan como fármaco protector de la aparición de FA. Los diuréticos pudieran tener un papel protector de incidencia de FA en todos los hipertensos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);40(5): 247-253, jul.-ago. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125242</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre el fármaco antihipertensivo utilizado y la aparición de fibrilación auricular en los pacientes hipertensos de un centro de Atención Primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23177^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
