<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166681</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Incidence of cancer in outpatients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The relationship between chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) and the overall incidence of cancer is poorly understood. The aim of this study was to analyse the incidence of cancer (pulmonary or extrapulmonary) in patients with COPD during follow-up in a specialised outpatient unit, as well as to assess its relationship with the degree of airflow obstruction. Methodology. A prospective observational study was conducted with a cohort of 308 patients with COPD in pulmonology outpatient follow-up consultations from January 2012 to December 2015. The diagnosed malignancies during this period were divided into pulmonary and extrapulmonary. Results. The overall incidence rate of cancer, lung cancer and extrapulmonary cancer were 10.3, 3.4 and 7.3 cases per 1,000 patients with COPD per year, respectively. The most common cancers were lung cancer (31%), genitourinary tract cancer (29%) and gastrointestinal cancer (21%). Mild-moderate stages (gradeI-II of the 2009 GOLD classification) and the increase in the pack-year index (PYI) were related to an increase in the onset of malignancies, with an odds ratio (OR) of 2.16 (95% confidence interval [95% CI]: 1.087-4.309; P=.026) and 1.01 (95% CI: 1.002-1.031; P=.023), respectively. Conclusion. The incidence of extrapulmonary cancer in patients with COPD was twice that of lung cancer; stagesI-II of the 2009 GOLD classification and the PYI were significantly related to the onset of malignancies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Rodríguez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Negrín, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Pérez, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Talavera, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Figueira Gonçalves, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dorta Sánchez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Méndez, LI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guzmán Sáenz, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viña Manrique, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La relación entre la enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica (EPOC) y la incidencia global de cáncer es poco conocida. El objetivo del estudio fue analizar la incidencia de cáncer (tanto de localización pulmonar como extrapulmonar) en pacientes con EPOC en seguimiento en una consulta ambulatoria especializada, así como valorar su relación con el grado de obstrucción al flujo aéreo. Metodología. Estudio observacional prospectivo de una cohorte de 308 pacientes con EPOC en seguimiento en consultas ambulatorias de neumología durante el periodo comprendido entre enero de 2012 y diciembre de 2015. Las neoplasias diagnosticadas en este periodo se dividieron en pulmonares y extrapulmonares. Resultados. Las tasas de incidencia global de cáncer, de cáncer de pulmón (CP) y de cáncer extrapulmonar fueron de 10,3, 3,4 y 7,3 casos por 1.000 pacientes EPOC-año, respectivamente. Los tumores más frecuentes fueron el CP (31%), los del tracto genitourinario (29%) y digestivo (21%). Los estadios leve-moderado (gradosI-II de la GOLD 2009) y el incremento del índice paquetes-año (IPA) se relacionaron con un aumento en la aparición de neoplasias con un odds ratio (OR) de 2,16 (intervalo de confianza al 95% [IC95%]: 1,087-4,309; p=0,026) y 1,01 (IC95%:1,002-1,031; p=0,023), respectivamente. Conclusión. La incidencia de cáncer de localización extrapulmonar en pacientes con EPOC duplica a la de CP. Los estadiosI-II de la GOLD 2009 y el IPA se relacionan de forma significativa con la aparición de neoplasias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;217(7): 387-393, oct. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166681</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incidencia de cáncer en pacientes ambulatorios con enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d555^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24811</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
