<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131013</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The autistic disorder: a current perspective</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The paper describes the diagnosis, etiopathogenesis and treatment issues of the autistic disorder. This disorder is viewed as a set of symptoms and capacities which vary in every child. An indepth knowledge of such capacities - the resources and healthy aspects of the child- is of a crucial importance as these are the ones which will have to be enhanced throughout treatment. In dealing with the etiopathogenic issues, the author explores the psychological and psychodynamic aspects of the autistic disorder, along with various facets of possible biological factors. The basic principles of the treatment, together with clinical illustrations, are finally considered (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torras de Beà, Eulàlia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El artículo describe la cuestión del diagnóstico, la etiopatogenia y el tratamiento del trastorno autista. Este trastorno es visto como un conjunto de síntomas y capacidades que varían en cada niño. Conocer a fondo estas capacidades &#150;recursos y aspectos sanos del niño&#150; es definitivamente importante ya que son las que habrá que desarrollar en el tratamiento. En cuanto a la etiopatogenia, se explora los aspectos psicológicos y psicodinámicos del trastorno autista, así como las distintas vertientes de los posibles factores biológicos. Estudia los pilares básicos del tratamiento y presenta ilustraciones clínicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(8): 65-71, nov. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131013</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El trastorno autista: una perspectiva actual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2704^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
