<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85474</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Otoplasty in prominent ears: surgical alternative</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Prominent ear, is the most frequent congenital malformation of the auricular pavillion. In this pathology, the absence of the antihelix is notorious as well as the increase of the mastoid-conchal angle, considering that the dimensions of the area of the auricular pavillion are within the normal limits. Many techniques have been described, all of them trying to reduce the mastoid-conchal angle and to create a new antihelix. Each ear has its own characteristics within the normal anatomic context; so it is important to make a correct evaluation in order to apply the adequate surgical technique. The surgical steps to be followed are systematically described to simplify the procedure, and most of all, showing that with aminimum incision done with a 21G size angulated needle, over the anterior side of the auricular cartilage, we can perform relaxation cuts parallel to the vertical axe of the auricular pavillion, and obtain a natural curve of the neoantihelix (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dávalos Dávalos, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Rivera, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dávalos Dávalos, P. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las orejas prominentes o en asa son la deformidad congénita más frecuente del pabellón auricular. En estapatología es notoria la falta del antihélix y el aumento del ángulo mastoideoconchal, teniendo en cuenta que las dimensiones del área del pabellón auricular estén dentro de unos límites normales. Han sido descritas numerosas y diversas técnicas quirúrgicas para su corrección, buscando todas ellas cómo acortar el ángulo mastoideo conchal y crear un nuevo antihélix. Cada oreja tiene sus propias características en el contexto anatómico normal del paciente, por lo que es importante realizar una evaluación correcta para aplicarla técnica quirúrgica más adecuada a cada caso. En el presente trabajo describimos sistemáticamente los pasos quirúrgicos a seguir buscando la simplificación del procedimiento y sobre todo, demostrando que con una incisión mínima producida por una aguja calibre21G con punta angulada, mediante la que se realizan cortes de relajación en la superficie anterior del cartílago paralelos al eje vertical del pabellón auricular en el área que corresponde a la proyección del antihélix,  se puede obtener una curvatura natural del neoantihélix (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;35(2): 107-114, abr.-mayo 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85474</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Otoplastia en orejas prominentes: alternativa quirúrgica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52522^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4489^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52522^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
