<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-SMB-14254</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Low dose rate brachytherapy in low and middle risk prostate cancer: Results and impact on quality of life with 5 year follow up</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Low dose rate brachytherapy (LDR-Br) with radioactive isotopes is a curative treatment and has shown to be comparable for the management of localized prostate cancer (PCa) to more conventional treatments such as radical prostatectomy or external beam radiotherapy, but with fewer side effects. The aim of this study is to show the global, specific and biochemical recurrence-free survival in 193 patients undergoing low dose rate Brachytherapy with permanent implants with iodine 125 and analyze the quality of life impact. 193 patients with localized PCa were consecutively treated over a period of 10 years (2005-2015). All of them were followed up on levels of prostate specific  antigen (PSA) and 68 of them completed a quality of life survey. The average age was 62.8 years and the average PSA was 6.4 ng/dl at the time of Br. 29.5% of patients were classified as intermediate risk, with a Gleason score sum of 7 and/or a PSA between 10 and 20 ng/dl. Mean follow-up was 64.2 months; overall, specific and biochemical recurrence-free survival were 92.8%, 99.0% and 90.2% respectively. The most significant changes in the quality of life recorded were urinary incontinence, urinary and bowel irritative symptoms, in the first 6 months after brachytherapy. Sexual function shows significant changes but all with favorable response using phosphodiesterase inhibitors. This series of patients with PCa shows similar biochemical free survival rates BFSR in low risk patients to external beam radiotherapy and radical prostatectomy, but better BFSR in intermediate risk patients. The impact in the quality of life was significant in urinary incontinence, urinary irritate symptoms, and sexual function, but they were transitory with the exception of sexual function (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Balbontín, Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canals, Andrea</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alliende, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pizzi, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La braquiterapia LDR (low-doserate brachytherapy) (Br LDR) con isotopos radioactivos es un tratamiento curativo para el cáncer de próstata (CaP) localizado con resultados similares a tratamientos más convencionales como la prostatectomía radical o radioterapia externa, pero con menos efectos colaterales de acuerdo a lo publicado en algunas series. El objetivo de este trabajo es comunicar la sobrevida global, específica y libre de recidiva bioquímica en 193 pacientes que padecen de CaP localizado sometidos a Br de baja tasa de dosis con implantes permanentes de yodo 125. Como objetivo secundario analizar el impacto en la calidad de vida. El análisis se realizó en pacientes que padecen CaP localizado y que fueron tratados en un período de 10 años (2005-2015). A todos se les efectuó un seguimiento con niveles de antígeno prostático específico (PSA) y a 68 pacientes se les aplicó encuesta de calidad de vida. El promedio de edad fue de 62,8 años y el PSA promedio al momento del implante fue de 6,4 ng/dl. El 29,5% de los pacientes era de riesgo intermedio, con un puntaje Gleason 7 y/o un PSA entre 10 y 20 ng/dl. La media de seguimiento fue de 64,2 meses y la supervivencia global, específica y tasa libre de recidiva bioquímica (TLRB) fue de 92,8%, 99,0% y 90,2% respectivamente. Los cambios más significativos en la calidad de vida fueron en cuanto a incontinencia urinaria, síntomas de llenado/vaciado vesical e intestinales durante los primeros 6 meses desde la braquiterapia. En la función sexual se observaron cambios negativos significativos pero con respuesta favorable a distintas dosis de inhibidores de la fosfodiesterasa. Nuestra serie muestra TSLRB similares a los obtenidos en pacientes de bajo riesgo tratados con radioterapia externa o prostatectomía radical pero mejores TSLRP en pacientes de riesgo intermedio. El impacto en la calidad de vida fue significativo en los ítems de incontinencia de orina síntomas de llenado/vaciado vesical y función sexual, estos son transitorios a excepción de la función sexual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;70(10): 824-832, dic. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-SMB-14254</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Braquiterapia de baja tasa en cáncer de próstata de riesgo bajo e intermedio: resultados e impacto en la calidad de vida con un seguimiento de 5 años</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
