<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132819</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Multicentre prospective cohort study to assess the quality of life of patients undergoing surgery for subcapital femoral fracture</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe health-related quality of life (HRQoL) in patients with subcapital femur fracture. Patients and methods: Multicenter cohorts study within a randomized clinical trial, evaluating the efficacy of different hemostatic treatments in patients undergoing surgery for subcapital femur fracture. The primary endpoint was HRQoL after five days of surgery using the generic EQ-5D -5L and EQ-VAS questionnaire. One hundred one patients were included, who were, in average, 84 (8) years of age and of which 78.2% were women. Results: Prior to fracture, 67.9% and 65.5% of patients had some limitation in mobility and performance of everyday activities; the EQ-VAS was 66.6 (18.8). After fracture, HRQoL scores decreased significantly, especially in the dimensions of mobility, self-care, and performance of everyday activities; the EQ-VAS was 30.5 (16.0). The HRQoL of patients after surgery improved significantly (p &lt;0.001), although basal levels were not reached. The EQ-VAS was 42.6 (13.7) five days after surgery and 53.7 (14.7) thirty days after surgery, with no significant differences between intervention groups. Conclusion: Subcapital femoral fractures that require partial or total arthroplasty significantly alters the quality of life of patients. After surgery, patients&#146; HRQoL improve progressively, although in the short term they do not reach basal levels (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grupo TRANEXFER</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud (CVRS) en pacientes con fractura subcapital de fémur. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio de cohortes dentro de un ensayo clínico que evalúa la eficacia de diferentes tratamientos hemostáticos en pacientes sometidos a cirugía por fractura subcapital de fémur. Variable principal: CVRS a los cinco días postquirúrgicos medida con el cuestionario EQ-5D-5L y EQ-VAS. Se incluyeron 101 pacientes, con 84 (8) años y el 78,2% fueron mujeres. Resultados: Previo a la fractura, el 67,9% y el 65,5% de los pacientes presentaban alguna limitación en la movilidad y en la realización de las actividades cotidianas, respectivamente. El EQ-VAS fue de 66,6 (18,8). Con la fractura femoral las puntuaciones de la CVRS descendieron significativamente, especialmente en las dimensiones de movilidad, realización de actividades cotidianas y autocuidado. El EQ-VAS fue de 30,5 (16,0). La CVRS de los pacientes tras la cirugía mejoró significativamente (p&lt;0,001), aunque no se alcanzaron los niveles basales. El EQ-VAS fue de 42,6 ( 13,7) a los cinco días de la cirugía y de 53,7 (14,7) a los 30 días, sin diferencias significativas entre los grupos de intervención. Conclusión: La fractura subcapital de fémur que precisa una artroplastia total o parcial altera la calidad de vida de los pacientes. Tras la cirugía los pacientes mejoran progresivamente, aunque a corto plazo, no alcanzan los niveles previos a la fractura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);25(4): 188-195, oct.-dic. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132819</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio prospectivo multicéntrico de una cohorte para evaluar la calidad de vida de pacientes intervenidos de fractura subcapital de fémur</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5368^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23108^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6641</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29646</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6642^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14540^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22316^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1185^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5368^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1185^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
