<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136850</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Smoking and schizophrenia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Many studies across different countries demonstrate consistently an association between schizophrenia and current smoking. This association is relatively independent of sociocultural factors. Schizophrenia is found to be associated with high nicotine dependence when schizophrenic smokers are compared with smokers from the general population, but not when they are compared with smokers with other severe mental illnesses. The increased prevalence of ever smoking in schizophrenic patients and the higher rates of smoking initiation before schizophrenia starts suggest that people who are going to develop schizophrenia have some risk factors that make them more vulnerable to start smoking. The reinforcing nicotine properties may be associated with dopamine release, which may allow to make links with the dopamine hypothesis of schizophrenia. The polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in tobacco smoke are metabolic inducers of clozapine, olanzapine and typical antipsychotics. Limited and small studies suggest that typical antipsychotics may increase smoking and make it difficult to quit smoking, while clozapine treatment is associated with small smoking decreases. The selfmedication hypothesis in schizophrenia proposes that smoking would improve cognition, decrease depressive, anxious and positive symptoms, decrease antipsychotic side effects, and favor psychosocial interaction; but clinical studies do not appear to demonstrate these allegedly beneficial effects. Clinicians trying to help patients with schizophrenia quit smoking need to be flexible, so that if abstinence is not possible smoking reduction can be an appropriate goal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gurpegui, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Ortega, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leon, José de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Numerosos estudios en distintos países demuestran repetidamente una asociación significativa entre la esquizofrenia y el fumar tabaco, relativamente independiente de factores socioculturales. En comparación con los fumadores de la población general, los fumadores con esquizofrenia presentan más frecuentemente una alta dependencia nicotínica; pero en esto la esquizofrenia no se distingue de otras enfermedades mentales graves. La elevada prevalencia de &#147;alguna vez fumadores&#148; entre los pacientes con esquizofrenia y el predominio del inicio del fumar antes del diagnóstico sugieren que quienes van a presentar esquizofrenia tienen mayor vulnerabilidad para comenzar a fumar. El efecto reforzante de la nicotina podría ser explicado por la liberación de dopamina, lo que permite enlazar con la teoría dopaminérgica de la esquizofrenia. Los hidrocarburos aromáticos policíclicos del humo del tabaco aumentan el metabolismo de la clozapina, la olanzapina y los antipsicóticos típicos. Algunos estudios, con pequeñas muestras, sugieren que los antipsicóticos típicos se asocian a mayor intensidad en el fumar y a dificultad para dejar de fumar; y que la clozapina se asocia a modestas disminuciones en el fumar. La hipótesis de la automedicación en la esquizofrenia propone que el fumar podría tener efectos cognitivos beneficiosos y reducir síntomas depresivos, ansiosos y psicóticos, así como reducir los efectos secundarios de los antipsicóticos y favorecer la interacción social; pero los estudios clínicos no parecen demostrar esos supuestos efectos beneficiosos. Conviene que los clínicos tengan un planteamiento flexible, de modo que, si la abstinencia no es posible, el objetivo pueda ser la reducción del fumar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);16(supl.2): 177-190, 2004. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136850</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tabaco y esquizofrenia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29815^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
