<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81542</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Subperiosteal aneurysmal bone cyst located in the fifth metatarsal shaft in a 13 year-old girl</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. We present s a case of aneurysmal bone cyst, unusual and rare, both for its location and its initial clinical and radiographic presentation. Case report. A girl of 13 years consulting for atraumatic pain in the outer edge of right foot, with a normal initial X-ray and then one month later presented with a subperiosteal tumour lesion in the fifth metatarsal shaft, which was definitively diagnosed as an aneurysmal bone cyst, Campanacci type IV. Conclusions. There are few cases in the literature of aneurysmal bone cyst with these characteristics. Such lesions may pose significant diagnostic difficulties with other pathologies, such as tumours, stress fractures or infections, due to its unusual presentation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mínguez-Rey, M. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Faus-Alcañiz, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pino-Almero, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Se presenta un caso poco frecuente de quiste óseo aneurismático por su localización y por su forma de presentación clínica y radiográfica inicial. Caso clínico. Mujer de 13 años que consultó por dolor atraumático en el borde externo del pie derecho con radiografía inicial normal y presentación al cabo de un mes de una lesión tumoral subperióstica en la diáfisis del quinto metatarsiano, cuyo diagnóstico definitivo fue de quiste óseo aneurismático tipo iv de Campanacci. Conclusiones. Existen pocos casos en la literatura médica de quiste óseo aneurismático que presenten estas características. Por su localización poco frecuente, este tipo de lesiones pueden plantear dificultades diagnósticas con otro tipo de enfermedades, como tumores, fracturas de estrés o infecciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);54(5): 310-313, sept.-oct. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81542</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Quiste óseo aneurismático subperióstico localizado en el quinto metatarsiano en una niña de 13 años: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24403^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32289^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23375^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31613^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22943^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32289^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24403^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31613^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22943^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31613^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23375^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31613^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22943^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
