<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101242</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevention of type 2 diabetes. What can be done from Primary Care? The experience of DE-PLAN-CAT</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Type 2 diabetes is a real growing public health problem. Based on clinical trials, it is known that the development of diabetes can be prevented or delayed by intensive lifestyle intervention among the high-risk population. A public health strategy is needed when implementing clinical trials in primary care settings. These strategies have been shown to be effective, and even cost-effective. The challenge is extreme because it requires not only an organizational, but also a political commitment. National plans targeting diabetes prevention should be based on screening the population at risk and developing a reinforced preventive intervention. These were the principles of the DE-PLAN European project developed in Catalonia (DE-PLAN-CAT), which has demonstrated the feasibility, and subsequently the 4-years effectiveness of a real-life primary care strategy to prevent diabetes using existing public healthcare resources(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Costa, Bernardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La diabetes tipo 2 es un auténtico problema de salud pública en incremento continuo. Basándose en ensayos clínicos de eficacia, la diabetes se puede prevenir, o al menos demorar, mediante la intervención intensiva sobre el estilo de vida en individuos tan solo con riesgo de padecerla. Su traslación a la práctica clínica en atención primaria supone aplicar una estrategia a amplios sectores de la población que debería ser efectiva e, idealmente, coste-efectiva. La dificultad es extrema porque se requiere no solo organización sino también compromiso político. Un plan nacional de prevención de la diabetes habría de considerar primero el cribado y la selección de individuos con mayor riesgo y luego la ejecución de una intervención sólida con su refuerzo periódico. Estas fueron las bases del proyecto europeo DE-PLAN, desarrollado en Cataluña (DE-PLAN-CAT), que ha evidenciado la factibilidad y la efectividad a 4 años de una estrategia de prevención en atención primaria utilizando los recursos públicos existentes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;28(3): 59-63, mayo-jun. 2012. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101242</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevención de la diabetes de tipo 2. ¿Qué se puede hacer desde la atención primaria? La experiencia del DE-PLAN-CAT</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11671^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37738^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
