<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110665</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Childhood obesity: pediatricians' attitudes and opinions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To identify the Spanish pediatricians' opinions and attitudes towards obesity, in relation with its treatment, prevention, and care organization, barriers they find in its treatment, and to know the tools they consider more useful to have for the management of obese children. Methods: Mail survey posted to the primary care pediatricians of Castilla-León (Spain) exploring: willingness to act against obesity, utility of therapies and preventive strategies, barriers found in treating obese patients, most needed tools for treating obesity, autoefficacy, and support to an obese children management programme in primary care. Results: There was a broad consensus in seeing obesity as an important health problem that demands action from pediatricians. This willingness to action decreased when bigger personal barriers were found. The most frequently encountered barriers came from the social milieu: easy access and advertisement of certain foods and beverages, lack of implication of parents, lack of perception of a weight problem in children and parents. Training was the most trusted tool. Pediatricians considered themselves as some or low efficacious in treating obesity. The effectiveness of an obese children management program in primary care was surpassed by the work it would need. Conclusions: In spite of their high willingness to act against obesity, pediatricians feel themselves limited because they find barriers mainly from the social and cultural milieus. They ask for training to fight pediatric obesity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casares Alonso, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez García, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano Garcinuño, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Identificar las actitudes y opiniones de los pediatras respecto al tratamiento, la prevención y la organización asistencial de la obesidad, identificar las barreras que encuentran en el tratamiento de la obesidad y las herramientas que creen más útiles para prestar una atención más efectiva. Métodos: Encuesta postal a los pediatras de atención primaria de Castilla y León, explorando la necesidad de acción frente a la obesidad, la utilidad de medidas terapéuticas y estrategias preventivas, las barreras que obstaculizan el tratamiento, las herramientas útiles para el pediatra, la eficacia propia en el tratamiento de la obesidad y la utilidad de incorporar la obesidad a la cartera de servicios. Resultados: Se consideró la obesidad como un problema de salud importante que necesita una actuación por parte de los pediatras. Esta disposición a la acción era menor entre quienes manifestaron más barreras personales. Las barreras más frecuentes procedían del medio social: disponibilidad y publicidad de determinados alimentos y bebidas, dificultades en involucrar a los padres en el tratamiento, ausencia de percepción del problema por el niño y los padres. La herramienta mejor considerada fue la formación del personal sanitario. Los pediatras se consideraban algo o poco eficaces en el tratamiento de la obesidad. La efectividad de un servicio de atención a la obesidad en atención primaria pareció ligeramente superada por la carga de trabajo que requeriría. Conclusiones: Pese a su alta disposición a la acción frente a la obesidad, los pediatras se sienten limitados debido a las barreras que encuentran, sobre todo de tipo social o cultural, y demandan más formación como una herramienta frente a la epidemia de obesidad infantil (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;22(2): 98-104, mar.-abr. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110665</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Obesidad infantil: opiniones y actitudes de los pediatras</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33883</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23897</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
