<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77001</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Late-onset bipolar disorder following right thalamic injury</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bipolar disorder occurs in the elderly ages and is frequently associated to a brain injury &#150;cerebrovascular disease. Its diagnosis is based on the finding of an ischemic injury in specific regions of the brain. The case of a 63-year-old male with cardiovascular risk factors, who was admitted due to mani form picture during a two-year long bipolar affective syndrome is presented. The neuroimaging tests showed lacunar infarction in the right thalamus and diffuse foci of ischemia in subcortical white matter having right predominance. Due to the refractoriness to psycho drugs of an endogenomorphic depressive episode, electroconvulsive therapy was prescribed, with normalization of motor component, although without mood stabilization. The therapeutic strategies and the evolution of this form of bipolarity are discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Araúxo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Páramo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, J. D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El trastorno bipolar se presenta en edades avanzadas frecuentemente asociado a una lesión cerebral &#151;enfermedad cerebrovascular&#151;, y su diagnóstico se fundamenta en el hallazgo de un daño isquémico en regiones específicas del cerebro. Se presenta un varón de 63 años, con factores de riesgo cardiovascular, que ingresa por cuadro maniforme en el curso de un síndrome afectivo bipolar de 2 años de evolución. Las pruebas de neuroimagen mostraron infarto lacunar en tálamo derecho y focos difusos de isquemia en sustancia blanca subcortical de predominio derecho. La refractariedad a psicofármacos de un episodio depresivo endógenomorfo indicó terapia electroconvulsiva, con normalización del componente motor, aunque sin eutimización. Se discuten las estrategias terapéuticas y la evolución de esta forma de bipolaridad  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;37(4): 233-235, jul.-ago. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77001</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastorno bipolar de inicio tardío secundario a lesión talámica derecha</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4637^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24895</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4637</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34253</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14165</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
