<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78210</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Measurement of health-related quality of life and functional capacity in patients with chronic tophaceous gout</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: In gout there are few instruments validated for the evaluation of activity, functional capacity or quality of life. It is not known if generic instruments such as the MOS-20, or specific for other illnesses, such as the AIMS, can be applied to patients with Gout. Objective: To evaluate the clinimetric characteristic of the MOS-20 and AIMS questionnaires, and their correlation with HAQ-DI, as well as with clinical variables in patient with tophaceous gout (TG). Methods: 49 patients with TG were included. Demographic and clinical variables were obtained. The 3 questionnaires were applied at the basal evaluation. A second evaluation was applied to 20 patients, 8 weeks later. Results: All patients were male. The time of since onset of the illness was 14.9±8.3 years. The HAQ-DI was 0.43±0.56 with an alpha of Cronbach (&amp;#945;C) of 0.95 and the intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC) was 0.86. The MOS-20 had an &amp;#945;C of 0.68 to 1.0 and a ICC of 0.27 to 0.61 between the several components. The AIMS had an &amp;#945;C of 0.66 to 0.96, and a ICC of 0.11 to 0.79 between the several components. Reliability was better between the physical components in MOS-20 and AIMS. The MOS-20, AIMS and the HAQ-DI correlated with the presence of joints with functional limitation. There weren&#146;t any significant differences among the patients with inflamed joints, nor in those with tophi. The HAQ-DI was best correlated with the physical component than with the mental component of the AIMS and the MOS-20. Conclusion: The AIMS, the MOS-20 and the HAQ-DI are useful in measuring the functional capacity and the quality of life in patient with TG (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vázquez-Mellado, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Hernández, Everardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zamudio-Lerma, Jorge A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burgos-Martínez, Gabriela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pelaez-Ballestas, Ingris</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Etchegaray, Sandra E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Hay pocos instrumentos en el estudio de gota validados para evaluar la actividad, la capacidad funcional o la calidad de vida de los pacientes. Se desconoce si los instrumentos genéricos como el cuestionario MOS-20 (Medical Outcomes Study Short Form Health Survey &#145;Resultados médicos del formulario corto del estudio de la encuesta de salud&#146;) o los instrumentos específicos para otras enfermedades, como el cuestionario AIMS (Arthritis Impact Measurement Scales &#145;Escala de medición del impacto de la artritis&#146;) puedan aplicarse a pacientes con gota. Objetivo: Evaluar las características clinimétricas de los cuestionarios MOS-20 y AIMS y su correlación con el cuestionario HAQ-DI (Health Assessment Questionnaire &#145;Cuestionario de evaluación de salud&#146;) así como con variables clínicas en los pacientes con gota crónica tofácea (GCT). Pacientes y métodos: Se incluyeron 49 pacientes con GCT. Se obtuvieron las variables demográficas y clínicas. Se aplicaron los 3 cuestionarios en la valoración basal. En 20 pacientes se realizó una segunda evaluación después de 8 semanas. Resultados: Todos los pacientes fueron de sexo masculino. El tiempo de evolución de la enfermedad fue de 14,9±8,3 años. El HAQ-DI fue de 0,43±0,56 con un alfa de Cronbach (&amp;#945;C) de 0,95 y un coeficiente de correlación intraclase (CCI) de 0,86. El MOS-20 tuvo un &amp;#945;C de 0,68 a 1,0 y un CCI de 0,27 a 0,61 entre las diferentes dimensiones. El AIMS tuvo un &amp;#945;C de 0,66 a 0,96 y un CCI de 0,11 a 0,79 entre los diferentes componentes. La reproducibilidad fue mejor en los componentes físicos que en los componentes de salud mental tanto del MOS-20 como del AIMS. Los cuestionarios MOS-20, AIMS y HAQ-DI correlacionaron con la presencia de articulaciones con limitación funcional. No se encontraron diferencias significativas entre los pacientes con articulaciones inflamadas ni con tofos. El HAQ-DI se correlacionó mejor con las variables del componente físico que con las del componente mental de los cuestionarios AIMS y MOS-20. Conclusión: Los cuestionarios AIMS, MOS-20 y HAQ-DI son útiles para valorar la capacidad funcional y la calidad de vida en los pacientes con GCT (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);5(3): 103-108, mayo-jun. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78210</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Medición de la calidad de vida asociada a la salud y a la capacidad funcional en pacientes con gota crónica tofácea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6223^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
