<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81599</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-6157</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: A wide range of disinfection products with ultrasonicfor instruments is available, but prolonged use inevitably causessome degree of corrosion. The aim of this study was to evaluate thecorrosive effect of a free-aldehydes and phenols detergent on thesurface of stainless steel dental tools.Material and methods: Seven frequently-used dental instruments oftwo different qualities of stainless steel were selected. Distilled waterwas used as control. Corrosion was assessed with optical microscopyand a visual analogue scale (VAS) at 0, 200, 400, 600 and 800cycles of use with ultrasound.Results: Instruments of the control group and with a low stainlesssteel quality showed greater deterioration of the surface at the endof the study.Conclusion: The free-aldehydes and phenols detergent minimallydeteriorate the surface of dental stainless steel instruments at 800cycles. This product has demonstrated to be of choice for disinfectingdental instruments with ultrasonics (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mayoral, Juan R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tarrida, Lluís Giner</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vélez, Esmeralda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Violant, Deborah</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Existe una gran variedad de productos para la desinfecciónde instrumentos con ultrasonidos, pero inevitablemente suuso prolongado provoca cierto grado de corrosión. El objetivo deeste estudio fue evaluar el efecto corrosivo de un detergente librede aldehídos y fenoles sobre la superficie de acero inoxidable deinstrumentos de uso odontológico.Material y métodos: Se seleccionaron siete instrumentos de uso frecuenteen Odontología de dos calidades de acero inoxidable distintas.Como control de utilizó agua destilada. Mediante microscopía ópticay una escala visual analógica, se evaluó el estado de la superficie alos 0, 200, 400, 600 y 800 ciclos de uso con ultrasonidos.Resultados: Los instrumentos del grupo control y con una aleaciónde baja calidad mostraron mayor corrosión de la superficie al finaldel estudio.Conclusiones: El detergente libre de aldehídos y fenoles deterioramínimamente la superficie de instrumentos de acero inoxidable alcabo de 800 ciclos, mostrando ser un producto de elección parala desinfección de instrumentos odontológicos con ultrasonido (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Dentum (Barc.);9(2): 77-83, mar.-abr. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81599</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de un nuevo agente desinfectante libre de aldehídos sobre la superficie de instrumentos de acero inoxidable</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13579</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3776</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4263^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
