<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124768</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Genetic polymorphism linked to the probability of developing occupational asthma in workers exposed to isocyanates</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Technological development has led to the use of chemicals potentially damaging to workers' health. In particular, the use of isocyanates has resulted in a greater morbidity caused by respiratory pathology, especially asthma. Considering that not all the exposed workers develop the disease, a gene-environment interaction model has been proposed, which tries to explain the genetic predisposition that some individuals have and others have not to develop occupational asthma. Objective: To find out about the scientific evidence related to the genetic polymorphism and workers exposed to isocyanates' susceptibility to develop occupational asthma. Methods: We conducted a systematic review. Bibliographic electronic searches were conducted in PubMedline databases, as well as in Dialnet and ELSEVIER repositories. Papers related to this review's objective were retrieved, without applying temporary filters, using the following descriptors: MeSH Major Topic, MeSH Terms. Search period started on November 20th 2013 and ended on December 15th 2013. We established the level of evidence according to GRADE criteria. Results: Forty-two full-text papers were analyzed, scientific evidence being supported by eleven case-control studies. Given the complexity of the genetic polymorphism associated with disease phenotype, as a limitation from the studies, authors agree that the sample size is not large enough, yet the papers found obtained a GRADE B level of evidence after adjustment for confounding factors. Conclusion: Genetics has a significant influence on isocyanate-induced occupational asthma. The weight of genetic susceptibility and gene-environment interaction remains unclear. Understanding these relationships has implications for workers' health, given the influence that some workplace factors have on genetic risk, which can and must be modified (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hibsen Da Silva Sánchez, Tonny</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pepe Betancourt, Gaetano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Godoy Carus, Ivanio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El desarrollo tecnológico ha traído como consecuencia el uso de sustancias químicas potencialmente perjudiciales para la salud de los trabajadores. Particularmente el uso de isocianatos ha resultado en una mayor morbilidad de patología respiratoria, especialmente el asma. Considerando que no todos los trabajadores expuestos desarrollan la enfermedad se ha propuesto un modelo de interacción gen-medioambiental, el cual trata de explicar la predisposición genética que tienen algunos individuos a desarrollar asma ocupacional y otros no. Objetivo: Conocer la evidencia científica relacionada con el polimorfismo genético y la susceptibilidad que tienen los trabajadores expuestos a isocianatos a desarrollar asma ocupacional. Metodología: Se realizó una revisión sistemática mediante una búsqueda bibliográfica utilizando las bases de datos PubMedline, así como en los repositorios Dialnet y ELSEVIER. Se extrajeron los artículos relacionados al objetivo de esta revisión, no se aplicaron filtros de temporalidad, utilizándose los siguientes descriptores: MeSH Major Topic, MeSH Terms. El periodo de búsqueda fue desde el 20 de noviembre de 2013 y finalizó el 15 de diciembre de 2013. El nivel de evidencia se estableció de acuerdo a los criterios GRADE. Resultados: Se analizaron a texto completo 42 (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;60(234): 239-259, ene.-mar. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124768</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Polimorfismo genético relacionado con la probabilidad de desarrollar asma ocupacional en trabajadores expuestos a isocianatos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28087^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11547</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31380^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29063^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54493^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
