<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130997</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Medical and Surgical Management for Chronic Thromboembolic Pulmonary Hypertension: A Single Center Experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Pulmonary endarterectomy (PE) is the treatment of choice for chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension (CTEPH). The aim of this study was to analyze our experience in the medical and surgical management of CTEPH. Methods: We included 80 patients diagnosed with CTEPH between January 2000 and July 2012. Thirty two patients underwent PE and 48 received medical treatment (MT). We analyzed functional class (FC), sixminute walking distance (6MWD) and pulmonary hemodynamics. Mortality in both groups and periods were analyzed. Results: Patients who underwent PE were younger, mostly men, and had longer 6MWD. No differences were observed in pulmonary hemodynamics or FC at diagnosis. One year after treatment, all PE patients versus 41% in MT group were at FC I-II. At follow-up, the PE group showed greater increase in 6MWD, and greater reduction in mean pulmonary arterial pressure and pulmonary vascular resistance than the MT group (P &lt; .05). Overall survival in the MT group at 1 and 5 years was 83% and 69%, respectively. Conditional survival in patients alive 100 days post-PE at 1 and 5 years was 95% and 88%, respectively. Surgical mortality in operated patients in the first period (2000-2006) was 31,3%, and 6,3% in the second (2007-2012). Conclusions: PE provides good clinical results, and improves pulmonary hemodynamics in patients who successfully overcome the immediate postoperative period. After a learning period, the current operatory  mortality in our center is similar to international standards (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pozo, Roberto del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barberá, Joan Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amado, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coronel, María Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pomar, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Badia, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rovira, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matuta, Purificación</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chamorro, Núria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Argemí, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castellá, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La endarterectomía pulmonar (EP) es el tratamiento de elección para la hipertensión pulmonar tromboembólica crónica (HPTEC). El objetivo del estudio fue analizar nuestra experiencia en el tratamiento médico (TM) y quirúrgico de la HPTEC. Métodos: Se evaluaron 80 pacientes diagnosticados de HPTEC en el periodo enero 2000-julio 2012. En 32 casos se realizó EP, el resto recibió TM. Se analizaron: clase funcional (CF), distancia recorrida en seis minutos (PM6M) y hemodinámica pulmonar. Se analizó la mortalidad según el tratamiento y el periodo. Resultados: Los pacientes del grupo EP eran más jóvenes, mayoritariamente hombres y recorrieron mayor distancia en la PM6M. No hubo diferencias hemodinámicas ni de CF al diagnóstico. Al a&#152;no del tratamiento, el 100% del grupo EP y el 41% del grupo TM estaban en CF I-II. Al seguimiento, el grupo EP presentó mayor incremento en la PM6M y mayor reducción de la PAPm y la RVP que en el grupo TM (p &lt; 0,05). La supervivencia global del grupo TM a 1 y 5 a&#152;nos fue del 83% y del 69%, respectivamente. La supervivencia condicionada de los pacientes vivos 100 días post-EP a 1 y 5 a&#152;nos fue del 95 y del 88%, respectivamente. La mortalidad quirúrgica en los pacientes operados en el período 2000-2006 fue del 31,3%, y en el período 2007-2012, del 6,3%. Conclusiones: La EP proporciona buenos resultados clínicos, hemodinámicos y de supervivencia en los pacientes que superan satisfactoriamente el postoperatorio inmediato. Tras un periodo de aprendizaje, la mortalidad perioperatoria actual en nuestro centro es superponible a los estándares internacionales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;50(12): 521-527, dic. 2014. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130997</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento médico y quirúrgico de la hipertensión pulmonar tromboembólica crónica: experiencia en un único centro</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4772^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29148^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12092^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7155^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
