<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72577</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Behavioural profile of selective ligands for mGlu7 and mGlu8 glutamate receptors in agonistic encounters between mice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Evidence is accumulating for a role of glutamate transmission in aggression modulation. Recent studies indicate that glutamate metabotropic receptors (mGlu1 and mGlu5) are involved in the regulation of aggressive behaviour. However, to date, the possible role of mGlu7 and mGlu8 receptors has not been explored. In this work, we analyze the effect of acute administration of AMN082 (0.5-4mg/kg, ip) and (S)-3,4-DCPG (2.5-10 mg/kg, ip), selective ligands for the mGlu7 and mGlu8 receptors, respectively, on agonistic encounters between male mice. Individually housed mice were exposed to anosmic opponents 60 or 30 min after drug administration. Ten min of dyadic interactions were staged between a singly housed and an anosmic mouse in a neutral area. The encounters were videotaped and the accumulated time allocated by subjects to ten broad behavioural categories was estimated using anethologically based analysis. The highest dose of AMN082 (4 mg/kg) significantly reduced offensive behaviours (threat and attack), as compared with the control group, without depressing motility, whereas (S)-3,4-DCPG did not produce significant behavioural changes. Overall, these results suggest that mGlu7 receptors (but not mGlu8) may be implicated in the modulation of aggression (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Navarro, José Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro, Vanessa de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-López, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Existe una evidencia creciente de la implicación del glutamato en la modulación de la agresión. Estudios recientes indican que los receptores metabotrópicos de glutamato (mGlu1 y mGlu5) están involucrados en la regulación de la conducta agresiva. Sin embargo, el posible papel de los receptores mGlu7 y mGlu8 no ha sido aún examinado. En este trabajo analizamos el efecto de la administración aguda de AMN082 (0.5-4 mg/kg) y (S)-3,4-DCPG (2.5-10 mg/kg), ligandos selectivos para los receptores mGlu7 y mGlu8, respectivamente, sobre los encuentros agonísticos entre ratones machos. Se llevaron a cabo interacciones agonísticas de 10 minutos de duración entre un animal aislado y un oponente anósmico en un área neutral, tras 60 y 30 minutos de la administración de ambos fármacos. Dichos encuentros fueron grabados en vídeo para su análisis etológico mediante un programa de ordenador, estimándose el tiempo pasado por los ratones en cada una de diez categorías conductuales. AMN082 (4 mg/kg) redujo significativamente las conductas ofensivas, sin disminuirla motilidad, en comparación con el grupo control, mientras  que la administración de (S)-3,4-DCPG no produjo cambios conductuales significativos. Estos resultados sugieren que los receptores mGlu7(pero no los mGlu8) podrían estar implicados en la modulación de la agresión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);21(3): 475-479, jul.-sept. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72577</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfil conductual de ligandos selectivos para los receptores de glutamato mGlu7 y mGlu8 en encuentros agonísticos entre ratones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8994</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31115^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31115^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d378^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1540^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
