<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99581</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Molecular weight heparins and new treatments anticoaglants in the prevention and treatment of thromboembolic disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In recent years, the risk factors for thrombosis are being better understood. The difficulties inherent in treatment with oral anticoagulants are responsible for the low molecular weight heparins (LMWH) are becoming a therapeutic tool increasingly common. However, there are different types of LMWH which necessitates the existence of objective therapeutic guide. Other new anticoagulant drugs are appearing on the market with the aim of replacing both the oral anticoagulants such as LMWH. This paper will review the biochemistry and pharmacology of different LMWHs and other anticoagulants in prevention and treatment of thromboembolic disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Del Río Solá, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero Puerta, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos años, los factores de riesgo para la trombosis están siendo mejor entendidos. Las inherentes dificultades en el tratamiento con los anticoagulantes orales son responsables de que las heparinas de bajo peso molecular (HBPM) se estén convirtiendo en una herramienta terapéutica cada vez más frecuente. Sin embargo, existen diferentes tipos de HBPM lo cual hace necesario la existencia de una guía terapéutica objetiva. Otros nuevos fármacos anticoagulantes están apareciendo en  el mercado con el objetivo de sustituir tanto a los anticoagulantes orales como a las HBPM. Este trabajo revisará la bioquímica y la farmacología de diferentes HBPM y de otros fármacos anticoagulantes tanto en la prevención como en el tratamiento de la enfermedad tromboembólica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;14(4): 240-244, oct.-dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99581</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Heparinas de bajo peso molecular y nuevos tratamientos anticogualentes en la prevención y en el tratamiento de la enfermedad tromboembólica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14308^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31696^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23521^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
