<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114452</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper analyzes, from the point of view of the principles of Bioethics, the problems of embryonic selection with the purpose of serving as donors of future transplant for their brothers seriously ill. Analyzed the principles of Bioethics of no malice, charity, autonomy and justice in connection with the matter explained, the author defends its moral fairness and he explains the necessity of proceeding to a legal reform which permits to accommodate in the Spanish Legal Code to this kind of embryonic selection, since nowadays laws into effect prohibit this practice with the purpose discussed here (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Soutullo, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente artículo analiza, desde el punto de vista de los principios de la bioética, los problemas de la selección de embriones con el fin de que sirvan como donantes de un futuro trasplante para sus hermanos gravemente enfermos. Analizados los principios de no maleficencia, beneficiencia, autonomía y justicia en relación con la cuestión planteada, el autor defiende la licitud moral de la misma y plantea la necesidad de proceder a una reforma legal que permita dar cabida en el ordenamiento jurídico español a este tipo de selección embrionaria, ya que en la actualidad las leyes en vigor prohíben esta práctica con la finalidad aquí discutida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. derecho genoma hum;(21): 185-198, jul.-dic. 2004.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114452</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Selección de embriones y principios de la bioética</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37583^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33589^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37584^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33877^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36358</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
