<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95591</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The historical and dialectical nature of the globalization-glocalización processes and its incidence in culture care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study is to reflect on the historical and dialectical nature of globalization and glocalización terms and their relationship with the culture of health care. We have carried a literature review whose contributions have guided the analysis and critical thinking about these phenomena. The creation of new terms or neologisms (glocalización), on the one hand, you may need to adjust the language and communication to the dynamics of cultural and historical reality, but then can lead to excessive and unjustified verbal incontinence that artificial result in confusion (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Siles González, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del estudio consiste en reflexionar sobre la naturaleza histórica y dialéctica de los términos globalización y glocalización y su relación con la cultura de los cuidados de salud. Se ha realizado una revisión bibliográfica cuyas aportaciones han orientado el análisis y la reflexión crítica sobre estos fenómenos. La creación de nuevos términos o neologismos (glocalización), por un lado, puede ser necesario para ajustar el lenguaje y la comunicación a la dinámica de la realidad histórica y cultural, pero por otra parte puede conllevar un exceso de incontinencia verbal injustificada y artificiosa que produzca confusión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;19(2/3): 162-166, sept. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95591</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La naturaleza histórica y dialéctica de los procesos de Globalización-Glocalización y su incidencia en la cultura de los cuidados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52938</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6955</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
