<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054127</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevention and treatment of food allergy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There has been a great debate during recent year about the possibility of preventing food allergy in children, but it still exists controversy in this Tepic. Primary prevention could be planned during pregnancy and neonatal period, since both are where infant are firstly exposed to food allergens. Early intervention for prevention could be implemented on maternal diet or in infants diet. Different trials establish that preventive diets on high-risk infants, may have a preventive effect on food allergy, mainly on milk allergy, and on atopic dermatitis. There is no evidence of preventive effect of maternal dietary intervention during neither pregnancy or lactation. Secondary prevention is based on avoidance of offending food. This avoidance has sometimes a important impact in children and their families. Difficulties to carry out dietary rsetriction on food allergic children are important issues when a child is diagnosed antihistamines and steroids and self-administered epinephrine. The latter is of utmost importance in high allergic subjects and parents and tutors should know how to administer it. New treatments for food allergy are currently under investigation</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez Sandín, M. D. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Lebrero, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos años se ha debatido ampliamente la posibilidad de prevenir la alergia a alimentos en niños. La prevención primaria se plantea en dos grandes niveles: sobre la dieta materna y sobre la dieta del lactante. Las dietas preventivas en lactantes de alto riesgo pueden tener efecto preventivo sobre la alergia a alimentos, especialmente sobre la alergia a proteinas de leche de vaca y la dermatitis atópica. No existen evidencias convincentes sobre el efecto preventivo de la dieta materna durante el embarazo o la lactancia. La prevención secundaria se basa en la evitación del alergeno. La realización correcta de estas dietas es complicada y requiere una gran atención por parte del entorno del niño, por lo que tiene un impacto sobre su familia y sobre toda la trama social. En este artículo se analizan las dificultades para realizar correctamente estas dietas, como es el etiquetado de los alimentos, los aspectos psicosociales y nutricionales sobre los que se tiene que poner una especial atención cuando se diagnostica a un niño de alergia a alimentos. Aunque los antihistamínicos y los corticoides pueden ser útiles en el tratamiento de las reacciones alérgicas a alimentos, lo fundamental es que los pacientes o cuidadores de niños alérgicos a alimentos con riesgo de presentar reacciones graves dispongan de adrenalina autoinyectable y estén entrenados para su administración. Actualmente se están abordando nuevas terapéuticas esperanzadoras, pero en fase de investigación</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;62(1): 74-85, ene.-feb. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054127</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevención y tratamiento de la alergia a alimentos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5651^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5654</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6793^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5651^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33510^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
