<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112629</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Caregivers burden in bipolar disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The excessive workload of the caregivers of patients with bipolar disorder has been studied with special attention in recent years. This review article intends to sum up the information and conclusions reported in studies to date. Specifically, we attempt to describe how the level of overload may be assessed, which clinical variables are associated with a greater or lesser overload, what coping mechanisms adopted by caregivers may be more adequate, what type of repercussions or impact may be suffered by the caregiver in terms of family, work, economic or legal matters, and which psychoeducational programs have proven more effective for treating caregivers (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Ortega, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Martín, Francisco D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Rojas, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La sobrecarga del cuidador de pacientes con trastorno bipolar ha sido estudiada con especial atención en los últimos años. Este artículo de revisión pretende hacer un resumen sobre esta cuestión. En concreto queremos conocer como es el nivel de sobrecarga en esta enfermedad, cuales son las variables clínicas que se asocian a un nivel mayor o menor de sobrecarga, que estilos de afrontamiento desarrollados por los cuidadores son más adaptativos para soportar dicha carga, cual es el impacto que sufre el cuidador a nivel sanitario, familiar, legal, económico y laboral, y que programas psicoeducativos han demostrado ser eficaces a la hora de tratar a los cuidadores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;29(2): 624-632, mayo-ago. 2013. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112629</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La sobrecarga del cuidador en el trastorno bipolar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29745</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
