<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95069</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The palliative sedation as lex artis in the care of end-of-life</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">All healthcare professionals are faced, at one time or another, with the need to attend patients during the final part of their lives. This can be a rather disconcerting experience owing to the general lack of resources and skills acquired in the course of their training. Science and medicine are often accused of prolonging death and therefore also prolonging suffering and anguish. The difficulty of treating patients who are dying resides in the fact that it imposes certain psychological demands that create and resolved through proper training and preparation. What would we need if we were in their place? It is essential provide guidelines to face end of life care. We must learn to convert ordinary events into meaningful experience. In this paper we think about needs of dying patients, refractory symptoms, palliative sedation and ethics problems, and promote the best end of life care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La presencia de pacientes con síntomas refractarios e intensas crisis emocionales en la fase final de la vida irrumpen en la actividad diaria de los profesionales sanitarios. Esta eventualidad puede convertirse en una experiencia desconcertante por la escasez de recursos y habilidades adquiridas durante el periodo de formación. La medicina y sus profesionales son inculpados de prologar el proceso de agonía y no aliviar el sufrimiento y la angustia. La dificultad de atender al paciente moribundo reside en las demandas psicológicas que produce y los conflictos internos que genera. ¿Qué se necesitaríamos nosotros en esa situación?. Es imprescindible disponer una guía de actuación que oriente nuestro proceso terapéutico defendiendo siempre el mejor interés de la persona. En el presente trabajo se hacen algunas reflexiones sobre la muerte, el y carencias de las personas en la fase final de sus vidas, las directivas anticipadas, los síntomas refractarios y la sedación paliativa y en cómo saber actuar en situaciones donde las fronteras éticas y legales están poco definidas o en debate permanente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);5(2/3): 265-278, dic. 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95069</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La sedación paliativa como lexartis en el cuidado del final de la vida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7170^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33200</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28849</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36358</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
