<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121512</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mastopexy with implants: tri-planar technique with fish tail flap in breast with poor quality coverage</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Primary augmentation/mastopexy is an increasingly popular procedure that requires careful preoperative planning and surgical execution. Breasts disfigured by prolonged breastfeeding and/or massive weight loss are especially challenging, with numerous factors contributing to the risk of unsatisfactory long-term results. Authors have cited striated skin, little subcutaneous tissue, loss of breast parenchyma and poor quality of coverage as factors that make successful enhancement especially challenging. With retromuscular placement of implants, surgeons must also consider the potential for double breast contour, asymmetry, and implant displacement. The objectives of this study are to describe the new triplanar method as a useful alternative for primary augmentation/mastopexy to attain better results in patients with poor quality coverage, and to analyze the results obtained in a large patient group utilizing the triplanar technique. This is an observational, descriptive, prospective study, conducted in a group of 268 patients diagnosed with breast ptosis and hypotrophy with poor quality and striated skin, limited subcutaneous tissue, and breast parenchyma loss secondary to prolonged breastfeeding and massive weight loss. All patients underwent (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Berrocal-Revueltas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La mastopexia con implantes de silicona, es uno de los procedimientos más frecuentes en la práctica diaria en Cirugía Plástica. Sin embargo, la pobre calidad de la cobertura de las mamas, relacionada con piel estriada, escaso tejido subcutáneo y pérdida del parénquima mamario secundarios a la lactancia prolongada y a la pérdida masiva de peso, son causa del incremento progresivo de resultados insatisfactorios a medio y largo plazo que han sido evaluados, analizados y discutidos por los especialistas. Los resultados insatisfactorios más frecuentes en mastopexia con implantes en posición retromuscular son: doble contorno mamario, asimetrías y desplazamiento de los implantes. Los objetivos del presente estudio son: describir el nuevo método triplanar como alternativa útil para lograr mejores resultados en pacientes con mala calidad de cobertura y analizar los resultados obtenidos con el mismo. Realizamos un estudio observacional, descriptivo, prospectivo, en un grupo de 268 pacientes con diagnóstico de ptosis mamaria con hipotrofia y mala calidad de cobertura por piel estriada, escaso tejido celular subcutáneo y pérdida del parénquima mamario, secundarios a lactancia prolongada y pérdida masiva de peso, entre otros, a las que se les practicó mamoplastia de aumento con implantes de silicona mediante la aplicación del método triplanar  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;39(4): 349-359, oct.-dic. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121512</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mastopexia con prótesis: técnica triplanar con colgajo en cola de pez para mamas con pobre calidad de cobertura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29995^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32332</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13208</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1965^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
