<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164823</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bereavement support for adult patients on palliative care and their relatives</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to understand the role of Nursing professionals in bereavement support for adult palliative patients and their relatives.  Method: a narrative review of literature was conducted through bibliographic search on the Health Science databases Pubmed and Cuiden, between the years 2006 and 2016. Additionally, there were searches in websites by associations relevant in the area of palliative care.  Results: eleven (11) articles were selected. The following categories were the result of their analysis: palliative care bases, factors with influence on bereavement in patients on palliative care and their family, and the nursing role in bereavement support for palliative care.  Conclusions: even though Nursing Degrees have incorporated new contents regarding palliative care, there is still no formal training to cover the complexity involved by said care. This review demonstrated that there is lack of training for bereavement care by nurses, in terms of emotional skills and communication targeted to meet the spiritual needs of patients and relatives. The Spanish Nursing Association for Palliative Care states the need for the formal implementation of specific training for nurses, suggesting three levels of training: a basic level corresponding to the current areas of general nurse training, an intermediate level, and an advanced level (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Blanco, Jonathan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: analizar el rol del profesional enfermero en la atención al duelo en el paciente adulto con cuidados paliativos y su familia. Método: se llevó a cabo una revisión narrativa de la literatura mediante una búsqueda bibliográfica en las bases de datos del área de las Ciencias de la Salud Pubmed y Cuiden, entre los años 2006 y 2016. Adicionalmente se realizaron consultas en sitios web de organizaciones relevantes para el cuidado paliativo.  Resultados: se seleccionaron 11 artículos. Del análisis de los mismos resultaron las siguientes categorías: bases del cuidado paliativo, factores que influyen en el duelo en el paciente con cuidados paliativos y su familia y rol de la enfermera en la atención al duelo en cuidados paliativos.  Conclusiones: aunque en los Títulos de Grado en Enfermería se han incorporado nuevos contenidos relativos a los cuidados paliativos, aún no existe formación reglada que abarque la complejidad que implican estos cuidados. Esta revisión evidencia que para la atención de Enfermería en el duelo existe falta de formación en habilidades emocionales y comunicación orientada a satisfacer las necesidades espirituales del paciente y su familia. La Asociación Española de Enfermería en Cuidados Paliativos (AECPAL) considera necesario el establecimiento reglado de formación específica enfermera, proponiendo tres niveles de capacitación: un nivel básico correspondiente a las actuales áreas de instrucción de la enfermera generalista, un nivel intermedio y un nivel avanzado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;20(6): 67-73, jul.-ago. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164823</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Atención al duelo en el paciente adulto con cuidados paliativos y su familia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22845</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36317</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11798</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55419^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11797</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30048^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23274</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
