<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137816</identifier>
<setSpec>1577-0354</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacy of different recovery strategies in elite soccer players</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">After a soccer match or high intensity training, suitable recovery will help not to decrease performance and to prevent injuries. The aim of this study was to test the effectiveness of different combined recovery strategies in comparison with a simple one, after a specific soccer training session. Twenty elite players participated in the study. A randomized crossover design was used to determine the effect of 4 post-training session recovery strategies. Tympanic temperature was measured, as well as Total Quality Recovery (TQR) and Category Ratio Scale (CR10) subjective scales. Results show that none of the recovery strategies proved more effective than others. However, the use of combined strategies tended to be more effective than a simple strategy after a high intensity training session in soccer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peinado, AB</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alvero-Cruz, JR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paredes Hernández, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Concepción, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Una correcta estrategia de recuperación (ER) tras la competición o el entrenamiento de alta intensidad en fútbol ayudará a no disminuir el rendimiento y a prevenir lesiones. El objetivo de este trabajo fue estudiar la eficacia de diferentes estrategias de recuperación combinadas en comparación con una simple, tras una sesión de entrenamiento específico de fútbol. Participaron 20 jugadores de fútbol de élite y se utilizaron cuatro estrategias de recuperación de forma aleatoria y contrabalanceada a lo largo de 4 semanas de entrenamiento. Se midió temperatura timpánica y las escalas subjetiva Total Quality Recovery (TQR) y Category Ratio Scale (CR10). Los resultados exponen que ninguna de las ER estudiadas muestra ser más eficaz que las demás. No obstante, la realización de protocolos de recuperación combinados llevados a cabo tras la sesión de entrenamiento de fútbol, tiende a una mayor eficacia respecto al protocolo que incluía únicamente estiramientos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. int. med. cienc. act. fis. deporte;15(58): 355-369, jun. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137816</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia de diferentes estrategias de recuperación en jugadores de fútbol de élite</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1856</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54263^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52426</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12566^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33888^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
