<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80881</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5735</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The resilience factors in traumatic situations. Analysis after the terrorist assault in a sample of patients in the mental health services of Alcalá de Henares</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The 11th of Marchbomb attack in Madrid suponed a challenge for themadrilenian health sistem, due to the great numberof affected and victims. This demand was specificallyvisible in the Mental Health Services of Alcaláde Henares, that by his geographic situation it had todo in front of great number of affected. The aim ofthis study is to know 2,5 years after the attacks thefactors that the patients consider more have helpedfor overcoming this traumatic situation (resiliencefactors).Material and Method: The sample was conformedfor the patients that went to the Mental Health Serviceswith a reason for consultation in relation tothe terrorist attack, of legal age with a period of inclusionof 3 months and a half after the attacks. Thefinal sample was conformed by 104 patients whichwas contacted by phone between the months of Februaryand March of 2007 so tha they responded to5 questions between it was regarding the resiliencefactors. The answers were transcribed literally andafterwards was elaborated a series of labels or categoriesthat included all the answers.Results: 78 of the 104 patients of the sample werecontacted of whom 76 acceded to answer. The resiliencefactor more mentioned was the sociofamiliarfactor followed of the treatment factor and thirdlythe individual response to the trauma and the owncharacteristics of the individual, other resiliencefactors were mentioned to a lesser extend.Conclusions: Our findings emphasizes the importanceof the sociofamiliar factors as the factors ofgreater utility for the readjustment after a traumaticexperience, as the majority of the studies agrees...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Benito Ruiz, Adolfo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Liria, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lahera Forteza, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oudda Santos, Laila</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benito Ruiz, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los atentados del 11Mdel 2004 en Madrid supusieron un reto para la sanidadmadrileña, debido al gran número de afectadosy víctimas. Esta demanda fue especialmente visibleen el CSM de Alcalá de Henares, que tuvo que hacerfrente a gran número de afectados. El objetivo delestudio es conocer a los dos años y medio de losatentados los factores que los pacientes consideranmás les han ayudado a la superación de una situacióntraumática (de resiliencia).Material y Método: Se recogió la población de pacientesque acudieron al CSM con un motivo de consultaen relación a los atentados terroristas, mayoresde edad con un periodo de inclusión de 3 mesesy medio tras los atentados. La muestra final estabaconformada por 104 pacientes, se contactó entre losmeses de febrero y marzo del 2007 telefónicamentepara que respondiese a 5 cuestiones entre la que seencontraba la relativa a los factores de resiliencia.Las respuestas se transcribieron literalmente y posteriormentese elaboraron una serie de etiquetas ocategorías que englobasen a todas las respuestas.Resultados: De los 104 pacientes se logro contactarcon 78 y de ellos 76 accedieron a contestar. El factorde resiliencia más mencionado fue el asociado alentorno sociofamiliar, seguido del tratamiento y entercer lugar la respuesta individual al trauma y las característicaspropias del individuo, otros factores deresiliencia fueron mencionadas en menor medida.Conclusiones: Nuestros hallazgos resaltan la importancia de el entorno sociofamiliar como el factor de mayor utilidad para la readaptación tras una vivencia traumática, coincidiendo con la mayoría de los estudios...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Neuropsiquiatr;30(107): 375-391, jul.-sept.. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80881</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los factores de resiliencia ante las situaciones traumáticas. Análisis tras los atentados del 11 de marzo en una muestra de pacientes en el CSM de Alcalá de Henares</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30184^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23905^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35120</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35430^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34598</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12491</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
