<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135638</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reduction mamoplasty without vertical scar: skin gathered in 6 cases. Clinical Note</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper deals with a serie of 6 successful cases of reduction mammoplasty, avoiding a vertical scar.  The incisions performed, the maintenance of sensitivity and areole nipple cornplex lactation function are essential factors  which must be taken into account. Most of the techniques already described employ a vertical scar which is quite more detectable  than the one in the submammary sulcus. We have applied to 6 patients, from 1995 to 1998, suffering from bilateral gigantomastia, a technique that avoid vertical scar. The principie of the  marnas "skin gathered", is applied in this case in horizontal line. The principal complication is a scar complication of this technique in submarnrnary sulcus medium line (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hijano Mir, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torreira Carballo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Fernández, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcos Vivas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta la experiencia clínica en 6 casos de mamoplastia de reducción sin cicatriz vertical.  Aspectos fundamentales a tener en cuenta en la elección de la técnica de reducción mamaria deben ser las incisiones practicadas, así como la conservación de la sensibilidad y función de lactación del complejo areola pezón. La mayoría de las técnicas actualmente  empleadas, pasan por la creación de cicatriz vertical, mucho más visible que en el surco submamario. Desde 1995 hasta 1998 ha sido  empleada en 6 pacientes con gigantomastia bilateral, una técnica de reducción mamaria que evita la cicatriz vertical. El principio de  "fruncido cutáneo" de la mama, es aplicado en este caso en sentido horizontal. La complicación principal de esta técnica es la escara en la línea media del surco submamario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;29(3): 243-246, jul.-sept. 2003. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135638</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mamoplastia de Reducción sin cicatriz vertical. Aplicación del Principio de fruncido cutáneo transitorio en 6 casos clínicos. Nota clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29995^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2947^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29995^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2947^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2947^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7163^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23992^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
