<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050795</identifier>
<setSpec>1697-641X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Supernumerary teeth: a diagnosis and therapeutic approach</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Supernumerary teeth are those that are additional to the normal complement. They may occur singly or multiply, unilaterally or bilaterally, in one or both jaws and in one or both dentitions. Supernumerary teeth are classified according to location, morphology, number and type of dentition. Usually they remain unerupted and do not produce any symptoms, but they can also produce crowding or other complications. Seldom they erupt in the arch or ectopically. Diagnosis of supernumeraries is achieved with a meticulous clinical and radiographic examination. The management of supernumeraries should form part of a comprehensive treatment plan and can include monitoring without removal, extraction, or exceptionally location in the arch with aesthetic restorative treatment as needed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Milla Sitges, Bárbara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Osorio Campuzano, Marina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz de Atauri Bosch, Magdalena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez García, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los DSN son aquellos en exceso sobre la dotación dentaria normal. Pueden ser únicos o múltiples, unilaterales o bilaterales, y desarrollarse en una o las dos arcadas y en una o ambas denticiones. Se clasifican por su ubicación, morfología, número y por la dentición a la que afectan.    En muchos casos permanecen sin erupcionar y son un hallazgo casual con clínica silente, sin embargo, en otros pueden dar lugar a apiñamiento u otras complicaciones. De forma más excepcional erupcionan en la arcada o en posiciones más o menos ectópicas. El diagnóstico se basa en la exploración clínica y radiográfica. El tratamiento debe formar parte de una evaluación global. Las opciones terapéuticas posibles son abstención de todo tratamiento, extracción o colocación en la arcada con tratamiento ortodóncico y odontología estética en caso necesario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cient. dent. (Ed. impr.);3(3): 225-233, sept.-dic. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050795</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dientes supernumerarios: consideraciones diagnósticas y terapéuticas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14471^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14486^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8483^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14486^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
