<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126032</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Peripapillary intrachoroidal cavitation in pathological myopia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report: A 54 year old woman with pathological myopia, presented with an elevated, yellowish-white lesion at the inferior border of the myopic conus in her left eye. The optical coherence tomography (OCT) demonstrated an intrachoroidal hyporeflective space. The fluorescein angiography examination (FA) showed early hypofluorescence with delayed staining, with no leakage of contrast. Discussion: Recognition of «peripapillary intrachoroidal cavitation» as an own entity associated with pathological myopia is important to avoid confusion with other possible retinal lesions which require further investigation and treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marticorena-Álvarez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Clement-Fernández, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias-Ussel, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Mujer de 54 años, miope magna, que presentaba una lesión sobreelevada y blanco-amarillenta en la parte inferior del conus miópico de su ojo izquierdo. La tomografía de coherencia óptica (OCT) mostró un espacio hiporreflectivo intracoroideo. En la angiografía con fluoresceína (AFG) se apreciaba una hipofluorescencia precoz con tinción tardía, sin fuga del contraste. Discusión: El reconocimiento de la «excavación intracoroidea peripapilar» como una entidad propia asociada a la miopía patológica es importante para evitar la confusión con otras posibles lesiones retinianas susceptibles de más estudios y tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;89(8): 316-319, ago. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126032</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Excavación intracoroidea peripapilar en miopía patológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d38637^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24564^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
