<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104150</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Trends in systemic antifungal use in critically ill patients. Multicenter observational study, 2006-2010</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: There are limited data about the use of antifungal agents (AF) in critically ill patients and treatment trends since the inclusion of the new generation AF. The use of these agents may have a significant influence on the development of new resistances. Methods: Observational prospective study of the systemic use of AF in patients admitted to Spanish intensive care units (ICU) participating in the ENVIN-HELICS register, from 2006 to 2010. The annual use, the indications that led to that use and, the intra-ICU infections, the AF employment related to the hospital size, and per 1000 patients/day, were compared. Results: Of the 8240 prescriptions for AF, fluconazole and caspofungin were the most often employed (55%and 19.5%, respectively). An increase in use was observed to the year 2008, with subsequent stabilisation. A decrease in the use of fluconazole and an increase in echinocandins consumption was observed overtime. As regards the intra-ICU infections, the AF were ordered empirically in 47.9% of the indications. Fluconazole was more frequently used in medium size hospitals than in the large ones (60.4% versus 53.3%;P = .036) and the opposite occurred in the case of caspofungin (15.8% versus 21.8%; P &lt; .001). Fluconazole was more prematurely employed (median 12 days since ICU admission) and the duration of the therapy was similar to the other AF (median 8 days). The total therapy days were 39.51 per 1000 patient/day, with predominance in fluconazole use (21.48 per 1000 patients/day).Conclusions: Fluconazole is the most used antifungal agent in critically ill patients in any of the indications, although a progressive decrease in its use is observed, with a proportional increase in the use of echinocandins (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Olaechea-Astigarraga, Pedro M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gracia-Arnillas, María Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Otal-Entraigas, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Pueyo, M. Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seijas-Betolaza, Iratxe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Lerma, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Insausti-Ordeñana, Josu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gimeno-Costa, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palomar-Martínez, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Hay poca información sobre el consumo de antifúngicos (AF) en pacientes críticos y las variaciones temporales desde la introducción de nuevos AF. Este consumo puede tener influencia en la aparición de resistencias. Métodos Estudio observacional prospectivo del consumo de AF sistémicos en pacientes ingresados en unidades de cuidados intensivos (UCI) españolas del registro ENVIN-HELICS durante los años 2006 a 2010. Se compara la utilización anual, el consumo según prescripciones y para infecciones intra-UCI, el calculado por tamaño de hospital y por 1.000 días de estancia. Resultados De 8.240 prescripciones de AF registradas, los AF más frecuentemente empleados fueron el fluconazol y la caspofungina (55 y 19,5%, respectivamente). Existió un incremento del consumo hasta el año 2008 y una estabilización posterior. Anualmente, se comprobó la disminución del uso de fluconazol y el crecimiento del consumo de equinocandinas. Predominó la utilización de fluconazol en hospitales de tamaño mediano con respecto a hospitales grandes (60,4% versus 53,3%; p=0,036), y lo contrario con respecto a la utilización de caspofungina (15,8% versus 21,8%; p&lt;0,001). El fluconazol se empleó más precozmente (mediana desde el ingreso en UCI: 12 días) y durante un tiempo similar a otros AF (mediana: 8 días). El total de días de tratamiento fue de 39,51 días por 1.000 estancias, con predominio de fluconazol (21,48 días por 1.000 estancias).Conclusiones El fluconazol es el AF más utilizado en pacientes críticos en cualquiera de las indicaciones, aunque se constata un progresivo descenso en su consumo y un incremento proporcional del empleo de equinocandinas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;30(8): 435-440, oct. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104150</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución del consumo de antifúngicos en pacientes críticos. Estudio multicéntrico observacional, 2006-2010</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4422^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11742^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
