<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110994</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the associations between the illness perception dimensions and quality of life, assessing the modulatory role of psychological distress in patients with breast cancer, identifying which of these dimensions explained further variability in the different aspects of the quality of life. Methods: Seventy-five patients were evaluated with the Brief Illness Perception Questionnaire and the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) Quality of Life Questionnaire (QLQ-30). We calculated bivariate and partial correlations to evaluate the associations between the illness perception dimensions and different aspects of quality of life, controlling for a distress measure. Subsequently, we performed linear regression analysis to evaluate the illness perception dimensions that could explain the variability in the quality of life scores. Results: Although significant associations between subscales of perception of illness and quality of life were found, most of them lost their significance when controlled by distress. In the regression models, variables that best predicted the variability in the quality of life were psychopathological diagnostic and distress.  Conclusions: According with the study results, psychological distress and psychopathological iagnostic were the two variables that explained better the variability in the quality of  life. For this reason it is essential to learn more about the role of these variables on the quality of life and morbidity and mortality associated with them (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morgenfeld, Mirta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosell, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gercovich, Daniela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Deza, Ernesto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, Pablo Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bortolato, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Margiolakis, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: estudiar las asociaciones entre las dimensiones de percepción de enfermedad y la calidad de vida, evaluando el rol modulador del distrés psicológico en pacientes con cáncer de mama e identificando cuáles de dichas dimensiones explicaba en mayor medida la variabilidad en los distintos aspectos de la calidad de vida. Método: setenta y cinco pacientes fueron evaluadas con el Cuestionario de Percepción de Enfermedad Breve y el Cuestionario de Calidad de Vida de la Organización Europea para la Investigación y el Tratamiento de Cáncer (EORTC QLQC30). Se calcularon correlaciones bivariadas y parciales para evaluar las asociaciones entre las dimensiones de percepción de enfermedad y distintos aspectos de la calidad de vida, controlando por una medida de distrés. Posteriormente, se ha realizado un análisis de regresión lineal para evaluar las dimensiones de percepción de enfermedad que podrían explicar la variabilidad en la calidad de vida. Resultados: si bien se encontraron asociaciones significativas entre las subescalas de percepción de enfermedad y calidad de vida, la mayoría de ellas perdían su significación cuando se controlaba por distrés. En los modelos de regresión, las variables que mejor predecían la variabilidad de la calidad de vida fueron el diagnóstico psicopatológico y el distrés.  Conclusiones: de acuerdo a los resultados del presente estudio, el distrés psicológico y el diagnóstico psicopatológico fueron las dos variables que más explicaban la variabilidad de la calidad de vida. Por tal motivo se hace imprescindible profundizar en el rol de dichas variables en la calidad de vida y en la morbimortalidad asociada a ellas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);9(2/3): 403-414, dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110994</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rol del distrés psicológico en la relación entre percepción de enfermedad y calidad de vida en pacientes con cáncer de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
