<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118152</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality of life in patients with cerebral palsy during aging process</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine quality of life (QoL) of adult patients with cerebral palsy (CP) during the ageing process and to analyze the effect of motor function, communication disorders, and intellectual disability (ID) on QoL. Material and method: A cross-sectional study on adults with CP was performed. A questionnaire to collect sociodemographic characteristics related to the disability, and two scales to assess the level of motor function Gross Motor Function Classification System (GMFCS) and a scale to measure QoL (GENCAT Scale) were used. Statistical analysis: T tests were performed to make a comparison with standard scores, and ANOVAS to analyze the incidence of motor function level, ID, and communication disorders. Results: Participants were 46 patients (27 males, 19 females; age: M±SD, 50±7.9). They presented low levels of QoL in interpersonal relations, self-determination, and social inclusion, and rights, and good levels of emotional well-being. No significant effects were found for motor function level, but ID and communication disorders produced significant effects, and interactions with QoL dimensions were also significant. Conclusions: QoL of adults with CP is satisfactory in emotional well-being and lower in selfdetermination and rights. Degree of motor impairment has an impact on material and physical well-being; degree of ID affects personal development and self-determination; and communication problems influence diverse dimensions of QoL, although physical well-being to a lesser degree (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Pedraza, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orgaz-Baz, M. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco-Pedraz, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Badia-Corbella, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar la calidad de vida (CV) de los pacientes adultos con parálisis cerebral (PC) en proceso de envejecimiento, y analizar el efecto de la función motora, los trastornos de la comunicación y la discapacidad intelectual (DI) sobre la CV. Material y método: Estudio transversal en personas adultas con PC. Se administró un cuestionario para recoger las características sociodemográficas relacionadas con la discapacidad, y 2 escalas para evaluar el nivel de la función motora Gross Motor Function Classification System (GMFCS) y de la CV (escala GENCAT). Análisis estadístico: se realizaron la prueba de la t de Student para comparar con las puntuaciones estándar, y el análisis ANOVA para analizar la incidencia del nivel de función motora, la DI y los trastornos de comunicación . Resultados: Participaron 46 pacientes (27 varones y 19 mujeres; edad: M ± DE = 50 ± 7,9). Presentaron niveles inferiores de CV en relaciones interpersonales, autodeterminación, inclusión social y derechos, y buenos niveles en bienestar emocional. No se obtuvieron efectos significativos del nivel de función motora, pero sí del grado de DI y de los trastornos de comunicación, y fueron significativas las interacciones con las dimensiones de CV. Conclusiones: La CV de los adultos con PC es buena en bienestar emocional, no tanto en autodeterminación y derechos. El grado de afectación motora incide sobre el bienestar material y físico; el grado de DI, sobre el desarrollo personal y la autodeterminación; y los problemas de comunicación, sobre las diferentes dimensiones de CV, aunque en menor medida sobre el bienestar físico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);47(4): 194-199, oct.-dic. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118152</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida en los pacientes con parálisis cerebral en proceso de envejecimiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4581^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30935^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2587^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2587^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
