<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155939</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Opinion of professionals in an intensive care unit on the limitations of therapeutic effort</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine the opinion held by professionals in an intensive care unit on the limitation of therapeutic effort process at the end-of-life (LTE). To collect this information, and then use it to improve the basic aspects that the LTE have on the quality of care by intensive care unit staff. Material and methods. A prospective descriptive study was carried out in the Intensive Care Unit of a third level public university hospital. A questionnaire was prepared that included questions on their demographic profile and others to provide an ethical valuation profile, as well as to find out the knowledge and information that the professional had on the LTE. Descriptive study of the sample and comparative statistics were performed using the chi-squared statistical test. Results. A total of 65 valid questionnaires were obtained from a convenience sample of 70 professionals. Almost all of them (98%) were in favour of the limitation of therapeutic effort. The LTE was considered as some kind of euthanasia (active or passive) in up to 28% of the replies, valuations by professional categories is shown in. More than three-quarters (77%) had the belief that not to start treatment was not the same as withdrawing an already established treatment. Just over half (52%) of the respondents believe the value that should have more weight when considering LET would be the prognosis of the current illness of the patient, and 46% the future quality of life of the patient. The economic cost of treatment to be applied was not considered in any case. Conclusions. The LTE is approved by the majority of professionals in our Intensive Care Unit. Although a non-negligible percentage understood it as a form of euthanasia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Azcune, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peñasco, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Castro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojas, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer la opinión que tienen los profesionales de una unidad de cuidados intensivos sobre el proceso de limitación del esfuerzo terapéutico (LET) con el fin de mejorar los aspectos básicos que influyen en la calidad asistencial. Material y métodos. Estudio descriptivo prospectivo, llevado a cabo en la Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos de un hospital universitario público de tercer nivel. Cuestionario confeccionado con cuestiones de perfil sociodemográfico y cuestiones para conocer la valoración ética, así como el conocimiento y la información que de la LET tenía el personal encuestado. Análisis descriptivo de la muestra. Estadística comparativa utilizando el test estadístico de chi-cuadrado. Resultados. De una muestra de conveniencia de 70 profesionales se obtuvieron 65 encuestas válidas. El 98% de ellos se mostró a favor de la LET. Hasta en un 28% de las respuestas se consideró la LET como algún tipo de eutanasia (activa o pasiva). Un 77% tenían la creencia de que no era lo mismo no iniciar un nuevo tratamiento que retirar un tratamiento ya instaurado. Para el 52% de los encuestados, el factor que más peso debiera tener a la hora de considerar una LET sería el pronóstico de la enfermedad actual, y para el 46%, la calidad de vida futura del paciente. El coste económico del tratamiento a aplicar no fue considerado en ningún caso. Conclusiones. La LET es una práctica aprobada por los profesionales de nuestra Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos de forma mayoritaria. No obstante, un porcentaje no desdeñable lo entiende como alguna forma de eutanasia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;31(5): 262-266, sept.-oct. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155939</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Opinión de los profesionales de una unidad de cuidados intensivos sobre la limitación del esfuerzo terapéutico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29106^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30048^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36291^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32151</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28008^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33118^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
