<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054687</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5665</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Incidence and risk factors for neck pain in spanish orchestras musicians</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The neuromuscular complexity and the high-level of mastering        that the musical interpretation demands, make musician susceptible        to a wide variety of discapacities that may influence        and rebound seriously in their profession, up to a point that        musicians are included in a risky profession of suffering        various medical problems. Approximately 50% of them suffer        muscle-skeleton dysfunctions at some time of their lives,        being between 24% and 38% of the cases communicated        with cervical syntomatology. In this sense, we have carried out        a study referred to the neck pain syndrome centered in professional        experienced musicians, to analyze the appearance        of this syndrome among these musicians and the most related        risk factors.        We carry out a survey that was answered by the members of        two professional Spanish orchestras. The results were later        analyzed by the Rasch method, there was a high incidence of        neck pain, of multifactorial nature, being the most important        factor the laboral stress, without a clear relation between the        instrument played and the years of professional activity, neither        with the sex or age</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Navia Álvarez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ardiaca Burgués, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Martínez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arráez Aybar, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La complejidad neuromuscular y el alto nivel de maestría que        exige la interpretación musical, hacen que los músicos sean        susceptibles a una amplia variedad de problemas discapacitantes        que pueden influir y repercutir seriamente en su profesión,        hasta el punto que se incluya a los músicos en una profesión        de riesgo para sufrir diversos problemas médicos. Aproximadamente        el 50% sufre en algún momento de su vida trastornos        musculoesqueléticos, habiéndose comunicado entre el        24% y el 38% de los casos con sintomatología cervical. En        este sentido, hemos querido realizar un estudio referido al síndrome        de dolor cervical centrado en músicos profesionales        con experiencia, para analizar la aparición de este síndrome        entre estos músicos y los factores de riesgo más relacionados.        Para ello, realizamos una encuesta que contestaron los miembros        de dos orquestas españolas profesionales. Los resultados        se analizaron posteriormente mediante el método de Rasch,        destacando una elevada incidencia de cervicalgia entre los        músicos, de naturaleza multifactorial, siendo el factor predisponente        el estrés laboral sin que exista una relación clara entre el        instrumento practicado y los años de profesional, así como tampoco        con el sexo o la edad</dc:description>
<dc:source>MAPFRE med;18(1): 27-35, ene.-mar. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054687</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incidencia y factores de riesgo de dolor cervical en músicos de orquestas españolas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22981^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2614^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32948^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9339</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30392^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
