<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125765</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The interpretation of transference in borderline pathology. Clinical presentation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present the case of an adult female patient, with a borderline personality organization, who, in the seventh year of treatment begins a regressive process accompanied by overwhelming ansiety, negative and erotisized transference that lead her to consider interrupting the treatment. The clinical material shows how, due to primitive thought, symbolic equation, and the approaching of the patient´s sexual problems, the sessions were experimented as a realization of her sexual desires, which generated the development of erotic transference and overwhelming anxiety when she came to and was in the consulting room, making it intolerable for her to be in it. The interpretation of the transference and the symbolic equation, and talong a methodological decision allowed us to recuperate the analytic process and stimulate its favorable evolution (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lara Cabeza, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta el caso de una paciente adulta, con organización límite de la personalidad, que en el séptimo año de tratamiento psicoanalítico realiza un proceso regresivo acompañado de angustia desbordante, transferencia negativa y erotizada que la llevan a plantear la interrupción de tratamiento. El material clínico muestra cómo, a consecuencia del pensamiento primitivo, de la ecuación simbólica, y del abordaje de la problemática sexual existente en la paciente, las sesiones fueron vividas como una realización de sus deseos sexuales, lo cual generó el desarrollo de transferencia erótica y angustia desbordante al acudir y estar en la consulta, haciendo intolerable su permanencia en ella. La interpretación de la transferencia, del pensamiento en ecuación simbólica, y la toma de una decisión meto do lógica permitieron recuperar el proceso analítico y estimular su evolución favorable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(53): 193-204, ene.-abr. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125765</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La interpretación de la transferencia en la patología límite: presentación clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12012^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1907^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1907^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12012^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12012^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1907^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
