<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97015</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Measurement of hepatitis C virus RNA 12 weeks after treatment predicts sustained virological response in HIV-HCV co-infected patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective The aim of this study was to assess whether measurement of hepatitis C virus RNA (HCV-RNA) at 12 weeks post-treatment could predict sustained virological response (SVR) to antiviral therapy for chronic hepatitis C (pegylated interferon alfa-2a and ribavirin) in HIV-co-infected patients. Patients and methods HIV-HCV co-infected patients were included if they completed a full course of anti-HCV therapy, achieved an end-of-treatment response and complied with the week +12 and +24 post-treatment follow-up schedule for serum HCV-RNA determination (Real-time HCV (Abbott, Wiesbaden, Germany) (lower limit of detection, 12 IU/ml).Results Forty out of 66 patients (61%) showed an end-of-treatment response. They were assessed in a follow-up visit at +12 and at +24 weeks post-treatment. Serum HCV-RNA was undetectable in 28 of them at +12 weeks, and 100% of these remained undetectable at 24 weeks post-treatment (the gold standard of (SVR). The positive predictive value was 100% (95% confidence interval, 98.21-100%).Conclusion Post-treatment follow-up to identify virological relapse could be shortened to 12 weeks, providing a new definition of sustained virological response (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Girón-González, José-A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corchado, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerrero, Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Gutiérrez, Clotilde</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez, María-José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Aspas, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montes De Oca, Monserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soto, María-José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar si la determinación de RNA del virus de la hepatitis C (VHC-RNA) a las 12 semanas tras la finalización del tratamiento podía predecir la respuesta viral sostenida al tratamiento anti-VHC (interferón pegilado alfa-2a y ribavirina) en enfermos coinfectados por el virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana (VIH).Enfermos y métodos Fueron incluidos los pacientes coinfectados por VIH y VHC que completaron un curso completo de tratamiento anti-VHC y que fueron evaluados a las semanas +12 y +24 tras la finalización del tratamiento para determinación del HCV-RNA sérico (RealTime HCV (Abbott, Wiesbaden, Alemania) (límite inferior de detección, 12 U/ml).Resultados Cuarenta de los 66 enfermos tratados (61%) presentaron una respuesta al final del tratamiento. Se les realizó una valoración a las 12 y 24 semanas tras el fin de la terapia. El VHC-RNA sérico fue indetectable en 28 de ellos a la semana +12, y el 100% de ellos permaneció indetectable a la semana +24 (el patrón de referencia de respuesta viral sostenida). El valor predictivo positivo fue 100% (intervalo de confianza al 95% 98,21-100%).Conclusión La evaluación posterior al tratamiento de la hepatitis crónica C en enfermos coinfectados por VIH para detectar la presencia de recaída virológica puede ser realizada a la semana +12, en lugar de a la semana +24, proporcionando así una nueva definición de respuesta virológica sostenida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;30(1): 15-17, ene. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97015</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La valoración de RNA del virus de la hepatitis C realizada a las 12 semanas de finalizar el tratamiento predice la respuesta virológica sostenida en enfermos con coinfección por VIH y VHC</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29469^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33344^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33123^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22286^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31852^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33344^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12663^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201201</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
