<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113254</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Which Molecular Biology techniques must conform to the armamentarium for Basic research in Uro-Oncology?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Molecular biology has been one of the scientific disciplines in which there has been more advances in the last years. The first impulse in the study of genetic alterations came from the discovery of DNA structure, followed by elucidation of the genetic code, the discovery of restriction enzymes and subsequently the invention of PCR, not forgetting the exponential development of computer science. All of them have allowed us to know much more about our genome and its regulation than we could imagine. The impulse in proteomics has been especially in tune up of soft methods of ionization coupled with mass spectrometry. Nevertheless, this seems to be only the beginning since today there are continuous methodological advances that will increase more, without doubt, the knowledge and applications in this discipline (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oriola, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Biología Molecular ha sido una de las disciplinas científicas en las que se ha avanzado más en los últimos años. El primer impulso en el estudio de alteraciones genéticas, provino del descubrimiento de la estructura del DNA, seguido de la dilucidación del código genético, del descubrimiento de los enzimas de restricción y luego, de la invención de la PCR, sin olvidar por supuesto del exponencial desarrollo de la informática. Todo ello nos ha permitido conocer mucho más acerca de nuestro genoma y su regulación de lo que podíamos imaginar. El impulso en proteómica ha sido sobretodo la puesta a punto de métodos suaves de ionización acoplados a la espectrometría de masas. Sin embargo esto parece ser solo el comienzo ya que hoy en día continúan habiendo avances metodológicos que sin duda aumentarán aun más los conocimientos y las aplicaciones en esta disciplina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;66(5): 409-415, jun. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113254</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Qué técnicas de biología molecular deben conformar el armamentario para la investigación básica en uro-oncología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24373^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35417^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29575^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9157^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13441^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53221^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37630^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
