<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80967</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-0921</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper has tried to show the profile of the informal caregivers of dependent elders. This profilehas been built with some socio-demographic and psychological variables. Also, we have intended tocheck what variables influence the informal caregivers in the interpersonal relation that they have withthe dependent elder.The participants of this study were formed by 42 caregivers extracted from different social and geographiccontexts. In order to get data, we used standardized questionnaires, such as &#147;Zarit&#148; and &#147;STAI&#148;,among others constructed by the authors: the Caregiver&#146;s Descriptive Questionnaire, the ValuationScale for the Caregiver&#146;s Old Age and the Caregiver&#146;s Stress Questionnaire.The results show a caregiver&#146;s profile similar to IMSERSO information in which women dominate, (averageage of 51&#146;5 years old), the most frequent caregivers are daughters; caregivers rarely receive anyeconomic support as they state they have a good economic situation; and in general, the physic andpsychic health perceived range among a normal and good health. Stress, anxiety and overload levelsproduced by the care lead to high values.Lastly, we observe how variables belonging to the closer context and to the furthest context are relatedto the caregiver&#146;s high levels of stress, anxiety and overload(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calero, Ruth M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roa, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente trabajo se ha realizado un perfil del cuidador/a informal de personas dependientes;dicho perfil se construyó con variables sociodemográficas y psicológicas. También, se ha pretendidoconstatar el efecto que dichas variables tienen sobre el cuidador informal en la relación interpersonalcon la persona dependiente.Los participantes han sido 42 cuidadores/as extraídos de diferentes ámbitos sociales y geográficos.Los datos se han obtenido de cuestionarios estandarizados como el &#147;Zarit&#148; y el &#147;STAI&#148; y otroselaborados por los autores, como el Cuestionario Descriptivo del Cuidador, la Escala Valorativa de lasCaracterísticas de la Vejez y el Cuestionario de Estrés del Cuidador.Los resultados muestran un perfil del cuidador/a próximo al publicado por el IMSERSO en 2004. Predominanmujeres, (edad media de 51,5 años), suelen ser las hijas, los cuidadores no suelen recibirayuda económica manifestando una buena situación económica y, en general, la salud física y psíquicapercibida oscila entre normal y buena. Los niveles de estrés, ansiedad y sobrecarga producida porel cuidado alcanzan valores altos.Por último, observamos como variables pertenecientes tanto al entorno inmediato, como al entornomás alejado del cuidador/a, se relacionan con los altos niveles de estrés, ansiedad y sobrecarga en elcuidador(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. multidiscip. gerontol;19(1): 12-19, ene.-mar. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80967</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El cuidador informal y su relación con la persona mayor dependiente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29745</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32193^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3878</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
