<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-28224</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bone morrow stromal cells. An alternative source of restorative therapy in degenerative diseases of the central nervous system</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims. The aim of this study is to describe the capacity of bone marrow cells to limit or slow down the damage and chronic neuronal degeneration produced by degenerative diseases of the central nervous system (CNS), as well as the potential capacity of the method to provide other substances or genetic material. Development. The search for new sources of cells that maintain the ability to divide and distinguish themselves from different cellular phenotypes opens up huge new opportunities in the restorative therapy of these clinical entities. Bone marrow cells, and especially stromal stem cells, have been seen to conserve a high capacity to distinguish and originate different strains of characteristic brain cells (neurons, astrocytes, and glial cells), and also the capacity to restore the population of stem cells when they are stimulated in a suitable fashion. Conclusions. Future experimental studies will be aimed at searching for new ways to enhance the composition, viability and differentiation of the cells to be implanted and will evaluate their effects on diseases of the CNS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Demostrar las capacidades de las células de la médula ósea para limitar o desacelerar el daño y la degeneración neuronal crónica que se producen en las enfermedades degenerativas del sistema nervioso central (SNC), además de la potencialidad del método para suministrar otras sustancias o material genético. Desarrollo. La búsqueda de nuevas fuentes de células que conserven la capacidad de dividirse y diferenciarse hacia distintos fenotipos celulares, abre enormes oportunidades en el tratamiento restaurador de estas entidades. En este sentido, las células de la médula ósea, especialmente las células madre estromales, han demostrado que conservan un alto potencial de diferenciación para originar distintas estirpes celulares características del cerebro (neuronas, astrocitos y glías), así como la capacidad de restablecer la población de células madre cuando se estimulan adecuadamente. Conclusiones. Los futuros estudios experimentales tendrán como propósito la búsqueda de nuevas vías para mejorar la composición, viabilidad y diferenciación de las células que se implanten y evaluarán su efecto sobre las enfermedades del SNC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;37(8): 752-758, oct. 2003. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Células estromales de la médula ósea: una fuente terapéutica alternativa en la restauración de enfermedades degenerativas del sistema nervioso central</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Albert Amador, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Miniet, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-28224</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d37572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10833</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33354</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30496</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2527</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22362</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
