<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039040</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Development and optimization of an observational tool for singles tennis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper is the result of the development and optimization of the categories system ad hoc for singles tennis that allows a description of the interaction contexts put in play. The complexity associated to a game like tennis, with different levels of interaction between its elements, make the process of selection of the pertinent traits much more difficult in order to build up a taxonomical system. The second step, the optimization of the provisional categorical system, includes a strict control of the quality of data, by the implementation of the previous agreement between observers, firstly, and the generalizability theory, secondly</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez de Santos, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Mendo, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gorospe Egaña, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Anguera, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo describe el proceso de desarrollo y optimización de un sistema de categorización «ad hoc» en el tenis de individuales que permite una descripción de los contextos interaccionales puestos en práctica durante el proceso de la acción de juego. Los diferentes niveles de interacción generan un amplio abanico de configuraciones posibles de los elementos que pueden incidir en los aspectos relevantes del juego, dificultando un proceso de selección y conceptualización en la combinación de los criterios y niveles adoptados en el sistema de categorías. El proceso de optimización del sistema de categorías incluye el control de calidad de los datos, destacando a este respecto la aplicación de la concordancia consensuada y la teoría de la generalizabilidad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);17(1): 123-127, feb. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039040</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desarrollo y optimización de una herramienta observacional en el tenis de individuales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24807</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27850^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d190</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
