<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102955</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ankle brachial index as indicator for vascular mortality</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The ankle-brachial index (ABI) is a simple test showing the relationship between systolic blood pressure in the upper and the lower limbs. This parameter widely studied in literature has been reported as an excellent vascular and all-cause death predictor when exceeds the normal values (0.90-1.30). In such situation the ABI can early detect periferic arterial disease (PAD) in asymptomatic phase and be a cutoff parameter to consider more aggressive preventive interventions before the existing vascular damage becomes symptomatic. This test is a powerful assessment tool for nurses to select those patients needing to maximize preventive cares. The nursing staff training for ABI measurement, the provision of suitable equipment by the Health Institutions and the development of reliable and more simple measurement methods are key issues that would facilitate its routinely and systematically use to improve the preventive strategy in vascular diseases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Martínez, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gala Chacón, Encarnación</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juárez Martín, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arévalo Manso, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El índice tobillo-brazo (ITB) es un parámetro que muestra la relación entre la tensión arterial sistólica de la extremidad superior y la extremidad inferior. Este indicador, ampliamente estudiado y presente en la bibliografía, se ha mostrado como excelente predictor de mortalidad tanto vascular como por causas generales cuando presenta valores fuera del rango establecido como normal (0,90-1,30). En dichas situaciones la utilidad del ITB reside en detectar precozmente la existencia de enfermedad arterial periférica (EAP) durante su fase asintomática y servir como parámetro de corte para el establecimiento de medidas preventivas más contundentes antes de que el daño vascular existente se haga sintomático. Para el profesional de enfermería este parámetro constituye una potente herramienta de valoración, objetiva y cuantitativa, que permite seleccionar aquellos pacientes en los que es preciso potenciar al máximo los cuidados preventivos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);23(2): 88-91, Jun. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102955</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El índice tobillo-brazo como predictor de mortalidad vascular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19270^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29897^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
