<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147298</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The transformation of the healthcare model in Catalonia to improve the quality of care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The changes taking place in western countries require health systems to adapt to the public's evolving needs and expectations. The healthcare model in Catalonia is undergoing significant transformation in order to provide an adequate response to this new situation while ensuring the system's sustainability in the current climate of economic crisis. This transformation is based on converting the current diseasecentred model which is fragmented into different levels, to a more patient-centred integrated and territorial care model that promotes the use of a shared network of the different specialities, the professionals, resources and levels of care, entering into territorial agreements and pacts which stipulate joint goals or objectives. The changes the Catalan Health Service (CatSalut) has undergone are principally focused on increasing resolution capacity of the primary level of care, eliminating differences in clinical practice, evolving towards more surgery-centred hospitals, promoting alternatives to conventional hospitalization, developing remote care models, concentrating and organizing highly complex care into different sectors at a territorial level and designing specific health codes in response to health emergencies. The purpose of these initiatives is to improve the effectiveness, quality, safety and efficiency of the system, ensuring equal access for the public to these services and ensuring a territorial balance. These changes should be facilitated and promoted using several different approaches, including implementing shared access to clinical history case files, the new model of results-based contracting and payment, territorial agreements, alliances between centres, harnessing the potential of information and communications technology and evaluation of results (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guarga, Àlex</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padrosa, Josep Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Robert, Roger</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brosa, Francesc</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los cambios que se están produciendo en los países occidentales obligan a los sistemas sanitarios a adaptarse a las nuevas necesidades y expectativas de la población. En Cataluña se está produciendo una profunda transformación del modelo asistencial, con el fin de poder dar una respuesta adecuada a esta nueva situación y a la vez garantizar la sostenibilidad del sistema en un contexto de crisis económica. Esta transformación se basa en convertir el actual modelo asistencial centrado en la enfermedad y fraccionado por niveles en otro centrado en la persona, integrado y de base territorial, que promueva el trabajo compartido en red de los diferentes profesionales, dispositivos y niveles asistenciales, estableciendo objetivos comunes explicitados en acuerdos y pactos territoriales. Los cambios que ha llevado a cabo el Servei Català de la Salut (CatSalut) pasan principalmente por incrementar la capacidad de resolución de la atención primaria, reducir la variabilidad de la práctica clínica, evolucionar hacia hospitales más quirúrgicos, potenciar las alternativas a la hospitalización convencional, desarrollar modalidades de atención no presencial, concentrar y sectorizar territorialmente la atención de alta complejidad y diseñar códigos sanitarios específicos, como respuesta a situaciones de emergencia. La finalidad de estas actuaciones es mejorar la efectividad, la calidad, la seguridad y la eficiencia del sistema asegurando la equidad de acceso de la población y el equilibrio territorial. Entre los instrumentos que deben facilitar y promover estos cambios cabe destacar la historia clínica compartida, el nuevo modelo de contratación y pago por resultados, los pactos territoriales, las alianzas entre centros, el aprovechamiento de las potencialidades de las tecnologías de la información y la comunicación, y la evaluación de resultados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);145(supl.1): 13-19, nov. 2015. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147298</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La transformación del modelo asistencial en Cataluña para mejorar la calidad de la atención</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6448^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20208^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6448^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20208^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33920^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33920^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10112^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54390^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
