<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115533</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-6045</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pulmonary function. the physical factors that determine it and its importance for the physiotherapist</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Within their assessment tools, the physical therapist uses those designated for the measurement of lung function. Having extensive knowledge about the physical factors affecting normal lung function is important for the physical therapist. This paper aims to clarify those physical factors that condition pulmonary function. Aims: To review the bibliography available that relate the physical factors having an influence on pulmonary function. Search strategy: The search was made with the following databases: CINAHL, Ovid, Scopus, ScienceDirect and PubMed, with time antiquity limited to the last 25 years. Synthesis of results: A total of 90 articles were obtained from the search. The authors have stated that physical factors of pulmonary function include age, sex, height, weight and ethnic group. In recent year, many authors have also added musculoskeletal factors, morphology of the thoracic cavity and muscle development. Conclusions: The different studies associate age, sex, race, height and weight and thoracic musculoskeletal factors to pulmonary function. However, more studies are needed to explain this influence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valenza, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Revelles Moyano, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valenza Demet, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Botella Lopez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castellote Caballero, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martin Martin, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Guzman, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Sánchez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El fisioterapeuta emplea, dentro de sus herramientas de valoración, aquellas destinadas a la medición de la función pulmonar. Todos los factores que afectan la función pulmonar deben ser conocidos de manera exhaustiva por el fisioterapeuta. Este trabajo pretende esclarecer aquellos factores, de carácter físico, que condicionan la función pulmonar. Objetivo. Revisar la bibliografía disponible que relacione los factores físicos que influyen en la función pulmonar. Estrategia de búsqueda. Revisión bibliográfica sistemática en las bases de datos: CINAHL, ScienceDirect, Ovid, Scopus y PubMed. Con antigüedad inferior a 25 años. Síntesis de resultados. Se obtuvo un número total de 90 artículos. Los autores han reconocido que entre los factores físicos de la función pulmonar se encuentran la edad, el sexo, la talla, el peso y el grupo étnico. A estos factores se han sumado en los últimos años, gracias a numerosos autores, los musculoesqueléticos, como la morfología de la caja torácica y el desarrollo muscular. Conclusiones. Los diferentes estudios asocian la edad, el sexo, la raza, el peso y la altura, y los factores musculoesqueléticos torácicos a la función pulmonar. Sin embargo, son necesarios más estudios que expliquen esta influencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. iberoam. fisioter. kinesiol. (Ed. impr.);14(2): 83-89, jul.-dic. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115533</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La función pulmonar, factores físicos que la determinan y su importancia para el fisioterapeuta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1969^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1969^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28107^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27867^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1969^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1969^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27779^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1969^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27779^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
