<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-18228</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of a 'Community drug service' treatment satisfaction using the 'Treatment Perceptions Questionnaire' (TPQ)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Satisfaction level reflected by 100 Drug Treatment Centre users is evaluated through a Treatment Perceptions Questionnaire (TPQ), in addition to the possible differences shown in two specific programmes within the TPQ: the Free Drugs Programme (n=50) and the Methadone Maintenance Programme (n=50). Cross section observational study is carried out with a systematic selection of subjects. The results show an acceptable level of satisfaction, expressed mainly among the drug-free programme users, with regard to the total instrument score, as well as its two dimensions: satisfaction with the programme and satisfaction with the therapist staff. Total sample results compared with three other European sample data show equivalence in the total satisfaction score, but differences in the sub-dimension scores. The TPQ is shown to be a useful instrument, which with a minimum number of personnel and time, enables us to obtain a clearer view of how our users see us (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Socidrogalcohol</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se valora mediante el 'Treatment Perceptions Questionnaire (TPQ)' el nivel de satisfacción reflejado por 100 usuarios de un Centro de Tratamiento de Toxicomanías, así como las posibles diferencias manifestadas en dos programas específicos del mismo: el Programa Libre de Drogas (n=50) y el Programa de Mantenimiento con Metadona (n=50). Para ello se realiza un estudio observacional de corte transversal donde los sujetos son seleccionados de forma sistematizada. Los resultados muestran un nivel aceptable de satisfacción, que se expresa en mayor medida entre los usuarios del programa libre de drogas tanto respecto a la puntuación total del instrumento como atendiendo a sus dos dimensiones: satisfacción con el programa y satisfacción con el equipo terapeútico. La comparación de los resultados de la muestra total con los datos ofrecidos en otras tres muestras europeas evidencia una equivalencia en las puntuaciones totales de satisfacción, pero diferencias en las puntuaciones por subdimensiones. El TPQ se muestra como un instrumento útil el cual nos permite con un mínimo de requerimiento personal y de tiempo obtener una visión más clara de cómo nos perciben nuestros usuarios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);14(4): 417-424, oct. 2002. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la satisfacción con el tratamiento en un centro ambulatorio de drogodependencias a través del 'Treatment Perceptions Questionnaire' (TPQ)</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iraurgi, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murua, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Lerma, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bacigalupe, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chavarri, MR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balsategui, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-18228</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
