<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038714</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Health advocacy in violence against women: an experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The development of political responses to a problem needs for its construction as a social problem of a continuous epidemiological surveillance system available for the affected public and key decision makers. A women's health advocacy net based initiative was launched in November 2003. Every month the epidemic index of deaths (ratio of deaths in that month and median of deaths occurring the previous 5 years) due to Intimate Partner Violence (IPV) is published in a section called «Violence Alert» of e-leusis.net a women's web page. The objective was giving visibility to information contributing to shape the problem. from a population perspective. The initiative was introduced at the beginning to journalists and every month a press release with the index results and a comment on it is circulated. More than half of the months studied (January 2003-December 2004) were epidemic (epidemic indexb &amp;#8805; 1.25). «Violence alert» has received 2330 visits since then, an average of 65 visits per week. The page attracted media coverage from radio, TV and newspapers</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Dardet, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bertomeu, Angustias</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Colomer, Concha</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vives-Cases, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El desarrollo de respuestas políticas para los problemas de salud en la comunidad necesita para su concepción como problema social un sistema de vigilancia epidemiológica continuo y accesible para la población y de decisores que contribuyan a ello. En noviembre de 2003 comenzó una iniciativa de defensa de la salud de las mujeres en Internet con el objetivo de contar con una información que contribuya a la construcción de un enfoque poblacional del problema de la violencia del compañero íntimo (VCI). Desde entonces, mensualmente se publica en e-leusis.net (página de Internet dedicada a las mujeres) el índice epidémico (razón entre las muertes sucedidas en el mes correspondiente y la mediana de muertes del quinquenio anterior) de muertes por VCI en la sección «Alerta Violencia». Más de la mitad de los meses estudiados (enero 2003-diciembre 2004) resultaron epidémicos (índice epidémico &amp;#8805; 1,25). La iniciativa se hizo pública en una rueda de prensa y cada mes se difunde una nota de prensa en la que se da a conocer el índice epidémico de muertes por VCI. Desde su puesta en marcha, «Alerta Violencia» ha recibido 2.330 visitas, con una media aproximada de 65 visitas semanales. Las noticias son cubiertas por varios periódicos, informativos de televisión y emisoras de radio</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;19(3): 262-264, may.-jun. 2005. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038714</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Una experiencia de defensa de la salud en violencia contra las mujeres</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3273</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33921</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15329</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6864^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28583</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28442</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12530</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31499^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31499^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
