<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88696</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Testosterone deficit syndrome and erectile dysfunction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: To analyze the relationship between testosterone deficit syndrome (TDS) and erectile dysfunction and its diagnostic and therapeutic implications.METHODS: Bibliographic review in the Pub Med database of the US National Library of Medicine.                                  RESULTS: The real TDS is unknown, due to the lack of uniform diagnostic criteria on what fraction should be measured (total, free or bioavailable) and what the diagnostic values are. Despite this fact, it is estimated that between 5-15% of males with erectile dysfunction show diminished testosterone levels. There is a solid research base demonstrating that testosterone plays an essential role in the physiology of erection, both at central and peripheral levels. Nevertheless, evidence obtained in human studies is not that strong, mainly in old patients with TDS. The results of some metaanalysis show that substitutive treatment with testosterone improves erections and sexual desire. However, not every patient with TDS will benefit from testosterone substitution therapy, probably because in some cases the origin of erectile dysfunction is multifactorial. Combined treatment with testosterone plus phosphodiesterase 5 (PDE 5) seems to be an adequate alternative to rescue patients with erectile dysfunction and hypogonadism not responding to monotherapy, be it with testosterone alone or PDE 5 inhibitors alone.CONCLUSIONS: Systematic determination of serum testosterone in patients consulting for erectile dysfunction is highly recommendable, because testosterone substitution therapy enables, in a number of patients, improvement of erections and sexual desire. Moreover, testosterone substitution therapy may improve the other symptoms of TDS and increase the efficacy of PDE5 inhibitors when they are not effective in monotherapy(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Jabaloyas, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Salom, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Analizar la relación entre el síndrome de déficit de testosterona (SDT) y la disfunción eréctil y sus implicaciones diagnósticas y terapéuticas.MÉTODO: Revisión bibliográfica mediante la base de datos de Pubmed de la US National Library of Medicine.RESULTADOS: La real prevalencia del SDT es desconocida, debido a la falta de criterios diagnósticos uniformes en cuanto a qué fracción de testosterona debe medirse (total, libre o biodisponible) y cuáles deben ser los valores diagnósticos. A pesar de ello, se estima que entre un 5-15% de varones con disfunción eréctil presentan niveles séricos disminuidos de testosterona. Existe una sólida base experimental que demuestra que la testosterona juega un papel fundamental en la fisiología de la erección, tanto a nivel central como periférico. No obstante, las evidencias obtenidas en humanos no son tan firmes, especialmente en los varones mayores con SDT. Los resultados de algunos meta-análisis demuestran que el tratamiento sustitutivo con testosterona (TST) permite mejorar las erecciones y el deseo sexual. Sin embargo, no todos los varones con SDT se benefician del TST, probablemente porque en algunos casos el origen de la disfunción eréctil es multifactorial. El tratamiento combinado con testosterona más inhibidores de fosofodiesterasa 5 (PDE5) parece ser un recurso adecuado para rescatar pacientes con disfunción eréctil e hipogonadismo que no responden a la monoterapia, ya sea ésta testosterona sóla o inhibidores de PDE5 sólos.CONCLUSIONES: La determinación sistemática de testosterona sérica en los pacientes que consultan por disfunción eréctil es altamente recomendable, ya que el TST permite, en una proporción de pacientes, mejorar las erecciones y el deseo sexual. Además, el TST puede mejorar el resto de síntomas del SDT y aumentar la eficacia de los inhibidores de la PDE5 cuando éstos no son eficaces como monoterapia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;63(8): 663-670, oct. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88696</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de déficit de testosterona y disfunción eréctil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14118^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7184^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7184^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14118^s22015</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14118^s22007</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
