<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054491</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Guidelines for the treatment of child spasticity using botulinum toxin</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims. The introduction of botulinum toxin has been a significant step forward in the treatment of spasticity in    children and is now considered to be the preferred treatment in focal spasticity. With the aim of optimising this therapeutic    resource, a group of Spanish neurologists and specialists in rehabilitation have drawn up these therapeutic guidelines based    on the currently available evidence on its use and indications, and on their own experience. Development. Spasticity in    childhood is mainly caused by infantile cerebral palsy. Its natural history is not favourable due to the negative effect of growth    and it should be treated before permanent deformities in bones and joints appear. Treatment with botulinum toxin diminishes    hyperactivity and muscle tone, and allows the muscle to grow longitudinally, which prevents permanent contractions. The    advantages of botulinum toxin are obvious (ease of use and dosing, long-lasting effects, reversibility in case of adverse    responses, and so forth) and outnumber by far the few drawbacks it offers. Before it can be used patients, treatment goals and    the muscle areas to be treated must all be selected correctly and, at the same time, a tailored rehabilitation scheme must also    be developed. The growing body of experience suggests that its early administration is effective in preventing or reducing the    severe complications of spasticity. Conclusions. Botulinum toxin type A is very effective in the treatment of spasticity. These    guidelines offer the well-documented experience gained from its use and our knowledge about its indications, effects and    safety in clinical practice</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grupo Español de Espasticidad</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. La introducción de la toxina botulínica en el tratamiento de la espasticidad en niños ha supuesto un    avance significativo y se considera el tratamiento de elección en la espasticidad focal. Para conseguir la optimización de este    recurso terapéutico, un grupo de neurólogos y rehabilitadores españoles ha elaborado esta guía terapéutica basada en las    evidencias disponibles sobre su uso e indicaciones y su propia experiencia. Desarrollo. La espasticidad en la infancia se produce    principalmente por la parálisis cerebral infantil. Su evolución natural no es buena por el efecto negativo del crecimiento,    y conviene tratarla antes de que aparezcan deformidades osteoarticulares fijas. El tratamiento con toxina botulínica disminuye    la hiperactividad y el tono muscular, y permite el crecimiento longitudinal del músculo, lo que evita las contracturas    fijas. Las ventajas de la toxina botulínica son evidentes (facilidad de uso y dosificación, larga duración de efecto, reversibilidad    en caso de respuesta inadecuada...) y superan ampliamente sus escasos inconvenientes. Para su utilización es necesaria    una buena selección de los pacientes, de los objetivos de tratamiento y de las áreas musculares a tratar, y desarrollar conjuntamente    un plan de rehabilitación personalizado. La creciente experiencia sugiere que su administración precoz es eficaz para    evitar o reducir las graves complicaciones de la espasticidad. Conclusión. La toxina botulínica de tipo A es muy efectiva en el    tratamiento de la espasticidad. En esta guía se aporta la experiencia bien documentada de su uso y el conocimiento de sus    indicaciones, efectos y seguridad en la práctica clínica</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;44(5): 303-309, mar. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054491</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Guía terapéutica de la espasticidad infantil con toxina botulínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33081^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32365^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32365^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9322^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33081^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
