<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151766</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of pharmacotherapy complexity on compliance with the therapeutic objectives for HIV+ patients on antiretroviral treatment concomitant with therapy for dyslipidemia. INCOFAR Project</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To analyze the relationship between pharmacotherapeutical complexity and compliance of therapeutic objectives in HIV+ patients on antiretroviral treatment and concomitant dyslipidemia therapy. Materials and methods: A retrospective observational study including HIV patients on stable antiretroviral treatment during the past 6 months, and dyslipidemia treatment between January and December, 2013. The complexity index was calculated with the tool developed by McDonald et al. Other variables analyzed were: age, gender, risk factor of HIV, smoking, alcoholism and drugs, psychiatric disorders, adherence to antiretroviral treatment and lipid lowering drugs, and clinical parameters (HIV viral load, CD4 count, plasma levels of total cholesterol, LDL, HDL, and triglycerides). In order to determine the predictive factors associated with the compliance of therapeutic objectives, univariate analysis was conducted through logistical regression, followed by a multivariate analysis. Results: The study included 89 patients; 56.8% of them met the therapeutic objectives for dyslipidemia. The complexity index was significantly higher (p = 0.02) in those patients who did not reach the objective values (median 51.8 vs. 38.9). Adherence to lipid lowering treatment was significantly associated with compliance of the therapeutic objectives established for dyslipidemia treatment. A 67.0% of patients met the objectives for their antiretroviral treatment; however, the complexity index was not significantly higher (p = 0.06) in those patients who did not meet said objectives. Conclusions: Pharmacotherapeutical complexity represents a key factor in terms of achieving health objectives in HIV+ patients on treatment for dyslipidemia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Galán, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montes Escalante, Inés María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morillo Verdugo, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Analizar la relación entre complejidad farmacoterapéutica y cumplimiento de los objetivos terapéuticos en pacientes VIH+ con tratamiento antirretroviral activo y concomitante para la dislipemia. Material y métodos: Estudio observacional retrospectivo. Se seleccionaron pacientes con VIH en tratamiento antirretroviral estable durante los últimos 6 meses y tratamiento para la dislipemia entre enero-diciembre de 2013. Se calculó el índice de complejidad a través de la herramienta desarrollada por Mc Donald et al. Otras variables analizadas fueron: edad; sexo; factor de riesgo de adquisición del VIH; consumo de tabaco, alcohol y drogas; alteraciones psiquiátricas; adherencia al TAR y a fármacos hipolipemiantes y parámetros clínicos (carga viral VIH, recuento de CD4, niveles plasmáticos de colesterol total, LDL, HDL, y triglicéridos). Para determinar factores predictivos asociados con el cumplimiento de los objetivos terapéuticos se realizó un análisis univariante mediante regresión logística y, posteriormente, un análisis multivariante. Resultados: Se incluyeron 89 pacientes. El 56,8% cumplieron los objetivos terapéuticos para la dislipemia. El índice de complejidad fue significativamente mayor (p = 0,02) en pacientes que no alcanzaron los valores objetivo (mediana de 51,8 vs 38,9). La adherencia al tratamiento hipolipemiante fue relacionada de forma significativa con el cumplimiento de los objetivos terapéuticos establecidos para el tratamiento de la dislipemia. El 67,0% cumplieron los objetivos para el TAR, sin embargo el índice de complejidad no fue significativamente mayor (p = 0,06) en los pacientes que no cumplían objetivos. Conclusiones: La complejidad farmacoterapéutica constituye un factor clave en la consecución de los objetivos de salud en pacientes VIH+ que reciben tratamiento para la dislipemia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;40(2): 90-101, mar.-abr. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151766</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de la complejidad farmacoterapéutica en el cumplimiento de los objetivos terapéuticos en pacientes VIH+ con tratamiento antirretroviral y concomitante para la dislipemia. Proyecto INCOFAR</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52955^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50514^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38332^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53262^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
