<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152849</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-7279</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The different technical advances in the field of medicine that took place throughout the twentieth century and the controversies which arose from different research experiences that did not meet any kind of ethical principle, led to the emergence and organization of the so-called Ethics Committees which dealt both of bioethical problems that arose in the field of research and in the field of clinical care. In this paper we make an historical reviewed of the origin of the Ethics Committees, explain the characteristics of this committees and go over the trajectory of the Assistential Ethics Committee of Benito Menni CASM (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gías Gil, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los diferentes avances técnicos en el campo de la medicina que tuvieron lugar a lo largo del siglo XX y las controversias que surgieron a partir de diferentes experiencias de investigación que no cumplían ningún tipo de principio ético dieron lugar a la aparición y organización de los llamados Comités de ética que se ocuparon tanto de los problemas bioéticos que surgían en el campo de la investigación como en el campo asistencial. En este artículo se realiza una revisión histórica de los orígenes de los comités de ética, se explican las características de dichos comités y se repasa la trayectoria del Comité de Ética Asistencial de Benito Menni CASM</dc:description>
<dc:source>Inf. psiquiátr;(223): 61-68, ene.-mar. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152849</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comités de ética asistencial, orígenes y funcionamiento desde la experiencia del comité de ética de Benito Menni CASM</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51553</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30112^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1698</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5082</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
