<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053033</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of the simulated client technique in non-medical services in the healthcare setting</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The simulated client technique (SCT) has been little used in the evaluation of patient advice and liaison services.                 Objectives: To evaluate non-medical services and to propose improvements.                 Material and method: Firstly, the elements and situations to be evaluated were determined and standards for an appropriate response to each were defined. Amateur actors aged between 20 and 50 years old were selected, excluding those with familial or professional links to the institution. The actors were trained in the SCT and were provided with an adapted script and a checklist to be completed. Seventy situations with 16 dimensions to be evaluated in distinct shifts and professional groups were selected. Finally, staff members were informed that the study would take place but were not told the start date.                 Results: For telephone staff, noncompliance with the standard appropriate response of 90% was found in two formal elements and noncompliance of 75% was found in one of the situations. For porters, noncompliance was found in five of the 10 formal elements and in two of six situations. In administrative staff, noncompliance ranging between 63% and 33% was found in formal elements. In two of the five situations evaluated, there was 100% compliance with the standard for appropriate response.                 Conclusions: The results of this study reveal opportunities for improvement and provide answers to the objectives proposed. The use of the SCT represents a step forward in the concept of the patient as client but should be complemented by other evaluations</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ávila, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernando, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lechuga, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La técnica del cliente simulado (CS) ha tenido poca utilización en la evaluación de servicios de atención al cliente en instituciones sanitarias.                 Objetivos: Valorar la atención de los profesionales no asistenciales. Realizar propuestas de mejora.                 Material y método: En primer lugar se ha de determinar los aspectos y situaciones que se van a evaluar, así como definir los estándares de respuesta correcta para cada uno de ellos. Se escogió a actores amateurs de edades entre los 20 y 50 años, y se excluyó a los vinculados familiares o profesionales con la institución. Se les formó con objeto de usar correctamente la técnica del CS disponiendo de un guión adaptado y una check-list que cumplir. Se planificaron 70 acciones con 16 dimensiones a evaluar en diferentes turnos y colectivos profesionales. Finalmente, se informó a los profesionales del inicio del estudio, sin determinar cuándo.                 Resultados: Para telefonía hay un incumplimiento del 90% en dos aspectos formales y un 75% en una de las situaciones. Para ordenanzas se da un incumplimiento de 5 de los 10 estándares formales; respecto a las situaciones, el incumplimiento se da en 2 de 6. En los administrativos, los formales oscilan del 63 al 33% de incumplimiento, y en 2 de las 5 situaciones evaluadas obtienen el 100% de respuesta adecuada.                 Conclusiones: Los resultados de esta experiencia ofrecen posibilidades de mejora y permiten dar respuesta a los objetivos planteados. La utilización de CS implica un paso más en la concepción del paciente como cliente, pero es conveniente y se ha de complementar con otras evaluaciones</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;22(2): 78-84, mar. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053033</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La utilización del cliente simulado en la evaluación de los servicios de atención al cliente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d288^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29901</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23897</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
