<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053750</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Schwannoma of the external auditory canal: an exceptional location</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Solitary schwannoma is a benign, encapsulated tumour of Schwann cell origin, therefore the olfactory and optic nerves are never affected. About 25 %-45 % of all schwannomas occur in the head and neck but schwannoma of the external auditory canal is a rare finding, and we have found only 6 previous cases reported in the literature world-wide. Our patient was discovered by chance during a stapedectomy because the tumour was sited in the external auditory canal without distorting it</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ovelar, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morais, Darío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El schwannoma es un tumor benigno encapsulado que puede afectar a cualquier nervio del organismo que tenga células de Schwann, nunca al nervio olfatorio ni el óptico. Un 25-45 % aparece en cabeza y cuello, pero en el conducto auditivo externo es excepcional, y solamente se han publicado en la literatura mundial otros 6 casos previos. Presentamos un caso descubierto accidentalmente al realizar la incisión en un conducto normal, no abombado, durante una estapedectomía</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;58(4): 169-170, abr. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053750</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Schwannoma de conducto auditivo externo: una localización excepcional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13588</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22433^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4492^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9635^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
