<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98002</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Avoidable intracranial hemorrhages associated with oral anticoagulants in patients with atrial fibrillation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: The increase in oral anticoagulants prescription has caused an increase in intracranial hemorrhages, the most adverse reaction to this pharmacological group. The objective of this study is to evaluate the avoidability of the intracranial hemorrhages associated with oral anticoagulants that require hospitalization of patients with atrial fibrillation. Methods: Survey of the medical histories  of the patients who were hospitalized in the University Hospital «Virgen del Rocío» (from 01/01/03 to 03/31/07) with intracranial hemorrhages and atrial fibrillation, considering as intracranial hemorrhages associated with oral anticoagulants those with a probable relationship applying the causality algorithm of the Spanish Pharmacological Surveillance System. In order to evaluate the avoidability of the intracranial hemorrhage the risk/benefit ratio of the use of oral anticoagulants has been studied. Results: At least 20 out of 57 (35.1%) intracranial  hemorrhages associated with oral anticoagulants were potentially avoidable, in 7 cases out of those 20 (35 %) death was the outcome, and  in 8 out of the remaining 13 (61.5%) the survivors suffered after&#150;effects. Omeprazole was the drug more frequently involved in interactions with oral anticoagulants in 11 out of 57 cases (19%) although this interaction is categorized as highly probable in the bibliography and the  protocols of the Hospital. Conclusions: The risk / benefit ratio of oral anticoagulants, the strict control of the International Normalized Ratio and the possible drug interactions, must be assessed individually and regularly to minimize the risk of intracranial hemorrhage that is often a potentially avoidable lethal adverse event (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castillo Ferrando, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torello Iserte, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Luque, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo. El aumento de la prescripción de anticoagulantes orales ha provocado un aumento de hemorragias intracraneales, la reacción adversa más grave asociada a este grupo farmacológico. El objetivo del estudio es evaluar el carácter evitable de hemorragias intracraneales asociada a anticoagulantes orales que causan ingreso hospitalario en pacientes con fibrilación auricular. Método. Supervisión de las historias clínicas de los pacientes que ingresaron en los Hospitales Universitarios Virgen del Rocío (01/01/03 al 31/03/07) con hemorragia intracraneal y fibrilación auricular; considerando hemorragia intracraneal asociada a anticoagulantes orales aquellas con una relación &amp;#8805; posible al aplicar el algoritmo de causalidad del Sistema Español de Farmacovigilancia. Para valorar el carácter evitable de la hemorragia intracraneal se ha estudiado la relación beneficio/riesgo del uso de anticoagulantes orales. Resultados. Al menos 20/57 (35,1%) hemorragias intracraneales asociadas a anticoagulantes orales pudieron ser potencialmente evitables, de las cuales en 7/20 (35%) el desenlace fue mortal, presentando secuelas 8/13 (61,5%) de los supervivientes. El fármaco sospechoso de interaccionar con anticoagulantes orales referenciado con  mayor frecuencia fue el omeprazol, 11/57 (19%), a pesar de estar documentada esta interacción como altamente probable en la bibliografía y en los protocolos del Hospital. Conclusiones. La relación beneficio/riesgo del uso de anticoagulantes orales, el control estricto del Índice Normalizado Internacional, junto con las posibles interacciones medicamentosas deben ser evaluadas de forma individualizada y periódicamente para minimizar el riesgo de hemorragia intracraneal, que en un porcentaje elevado de casos es una reacción adversa potencialmente evitable y mortal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;67(4): 354-360, oct.-dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98002</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hemorragias intracraneales de carácter evitable asociadas a anticoagulantes orales en pacientes con fibrilación auricular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2582^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4409</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2582^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
