<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146667</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Co-payment on prescription drugs in the Spanish public health system: Certainty, risk and selection of risks</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The model of co-payment on prescription drugs in the Spanish National Health System (NHS) changed on 1 July 2012. For more than three decades that it was not modified. This article provides a brief historical reminder of the evolution of this model of co-payment. The basic characteristics of this model are compared with the model of copayment on prescription drugs of the Administrative Mutualism (Civil Servants). The document provides detailed information on the percentage of effective copayment, fundraising effects, the economic participation of the patient, among others, in both models. Finally, listed pending improvements not addressed by 2012 changes such as the concentration of the co-payment in the active patient population and risk selection promoted by the differences in the financial contribution between the two models of co-payment (NHS and Mutualist) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Simó Miñana, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El modelo de copago en farmacia de receta del SNS cambió el 1 de julio de 2012. Hacía más de 3 décadas que no se modificaba. En este artículo se hace un pequeño recuerdo histórico de la evolución del modelo de copago en farmacia de receta del SNS introducido por primera vez en 1967. Se comparan las características básicas del mismo con el copago en farmacia de receta del Mutualismo Administrativo. Se proporciona información detallada referida al porcentaje de copago efectivo, los efectos recaudatorios, la participación del paciente, entre otros, en ambos modelos. Por último, se señalan las mejoras pendientes no abordadas por la modificación de 2012, como son la concentración del copago en la población de pacientes activos y la selección de riesgos promovida por las diferencias en la aportación de ambos modelos de copago (SNS y Mutualista) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;47(10): 669-673, dic. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146667</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Copago en farmacia de receta en la sanidad pública española: certezas, riesgos y selección de riesgos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3380^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13318^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7524^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11742^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20208^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20208^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7524^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30175^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53391^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28152^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53391^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13318^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28152^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11742^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3380^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
