<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133923</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-031X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Study of dynamics of sperm deoxyribonucleic acid fragmentation in young men</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe and analyze sperm DNA fragmentation and its dynamics after ejaculation in young men. Material and method: This is a cross-sectional study conducted between 2010 and 2011 in young university students (n = 114) from the Murcia Region (Spain). Sperm DNA fragmentation index (SDF) was defined as the percentage of sperm with fragmented DNA divided by the total amount of assessed sperm. The rate of sperm DNA fragmentation (rSDF) was determined by periods of incubation according to the sperm chromatin dispersion test. SDF and its dynamics were evaluated after incubation for 2.5, 17 and 24 h at 37 °C. Parametric and non-parametric tests were used for statistical analyses. Results: Mean basal SDF was 27.2% (SD 14.4) and rSDF was significantly higher in the first period of incubation compared to the following periods of incubations. The rate of sperm DNA degradation during the first 2.5 h (5,5%/h) was significantly higher in those samples with a basal SDF above 30%. Conclusions: These results indicate that our mean values of SDF are relatively higher compared to other published studies and corroborate that rSDF is significantly higher during the first hours after ejaculation. Moreover, samples with basal SDF above 30% showed higher rSDF during the first hours of incubation compared to the samples with basal SDF below 15% (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gosálvez, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendiola, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarabia-Cos, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arense-Gonzalo,  Julián J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres-Cantero, Alberto M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mínguez-Alarcón, Lidia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo de este estudio es describir y analizar los niveles basales y la dinámica de fragmentación del ADN espermático tras la eyaculación en varones jóvenes. Material y método: Se trata de un estudio transversal realizado en jóvenes universitarios sanos (n = 114) de la Región de Murcia entre 2010 y 2011. La fragmentación del ADN espermático (SDF) se definió como el porcentaje de espermatozoides con el ADN fragmentado con respecto al total de los espermatozoides analizados. Se calcularon las tasas de incremento de fragmentación (rSDF) por tramos de incubación utilizando el test de dispersión de la cromatina espermática. Se estudiaron los valores basales de la SDF, así como los valores tras la incubación de las muestras a 37 °C durante 2,5, 17 y 24 h. Los análisis estadísticos se realizaron mediante pruebas paramétricas y no paramétricas. Resultados: El SDF basal medio obtenido fue de 27,2% (DE 14,4), y la rSDF fue significativamente mayor durante el primer intervalo de incubación comparada con los valores obtenidos en los siguientes intervalos. La tasa de degradación durante las primeras 2,5 h (5,5%/h) resultó significativamente mayor en aquellas muestras con un nivel de fragmentación basal superior al 30%. Conclusiones: Observamos unos valores medios de SDF basal relativamente altos comparados con los de otros estudios publicados y corroboramos que la rSDF es mayor durante las primeras horas tras la eyaculación. Por otra parte, las muestras con SDF basal superior al 30% presentan mayor rSDF durante las primeras horas de incubación comparadas con muestras con niveles basales inferiores al 15% (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. int. androl. (Ed. impr.);13(1): 1-7, mar. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133923</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de la dinámica de fragmentación del ácido desoxirribonucleico espermático en jóvenes varones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13477^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13477^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13477^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53222^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53222^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53222^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53222^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22152^s22007</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22152^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22152^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22152^s22065</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
