<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129105</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nutritional assessment and food habits in health personnel in shift work</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Foundations: There is limited knowledge about the impact of alternated shift work for health and nutrition. Our aim was to analyze the food and nutritional habits in health  professionals with shift work rotation. Methods: Some 15 voluntary healthy women, health  personnel, with normal weight were recruited. They  completed a 24-hour dietary recall and a daily Food  Frequency Questionnaire for 7 days. Nutrient analysis was performed with DIAL software. Results: The study group had energy intakes above  recommendations (2209.13±16.4 Kcal), as well as proteins (96.15±6.88 g) and lipids (108.29±8.61 g), with high  consumption for oils and fats), dairies and meats and fish, and intakes below recommendations for carbohydrate  (192±14.37 g), with lower consumption for cereals and  sweets. Regarding macro and micronutrients, intakes for vitamins niacin, B12, C and K as well as for sodium and phosphorus were above twofold of the RDA. Intakes for zinc, iron, iodine, magnesium and folic acid, as well as for  fluoride, potassium, calcium and vitamin D were far below RDA. Conclusion: The study group under rotating shift work had an unbalanced diet, which should turn into higher  carbohydrate intake and adequate intakes for calcium, now deficient, and excessive sodium intake, risk factors for osteoporosis and high blood pressure, respectively (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bravo Santos, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez López, Cristina Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, Eulalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barriga Ibars, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cubero Juánez, JAvier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco Hernández, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Moratinos, Ana Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: Todavía son poco conocidas las  especificidades que la organización alternada de turnos de trabajo puede representar para la salud y en particular para la alimentación y nutrición. El objetivo de este trabajo fue  analizar los hábitos alimenticios y nutricionales en  profesionales con turno rotatorios. Métodos: Se enrolaron 15 mujeres, personal sanitario,  voluntarias sanas con normopeso. Rellenaron un recordatorio de 24 h y un cuestionario de frecuencias  autocompletadas diariamente, de forma exhaustiva, con los alimentos consumidos durante 7 días. El análisis dietético y nutricional fue llevado a cabo mediante: Programa DIAL. Resultados: La ingesta de energía fue superior a la  recomendada (2209,13±16,4 Kcal), así como proteínas (96,15±6,88 g), y lípidos (108,29±8,61 g), con un alto  consumo de raciones diarias de aceites y grasas), lácteos y carnes y pescados. La ingesta de hidratos de carbono fue menor (192±14,37 g) de la recomendada, con un mejor  consumo en raciones de cereales y azucares. La ingesta  de las vitaminas niacina, B12, C y K, así como sales  minerales, especialmente sodio y fosforo, fueron superiores al doble de las CDR. Se detectaron deficiencias  nutricionales en su dieta diaria para zinc, hierro, iodo,  magnesio y ácido fólico, e ingestas muy por debajo del CDR para flúor, potasio, calcio y vitamina D. Conclusión: El colectivo estudiado sometido a turnos  rotatorios mantuvo una dieta no equilibrada que debería  balancearse hacia los hidratos de carbono, además de  corregir el consumo diario deficiente en calcio y excesivo en sodio, factores de riesgo para la osteoporosis e HTA  respectivamente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;18(1): 32-38, ene.-mar. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129105</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis nutricional y hábitos alimentarios en personal sanitario con turnos rotatorios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2280^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2560^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5639^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52503^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16571</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
