<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95821</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Screening of the nutritional risk in elderly hospitalized patients with different tools</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Nutritional assessment in the elderly is difficult and different fromthat performed in younger people. There are specific tools for that purpose, such as the GeriatricNutritional Risk Index (GNRI). The study objective was to compare this index to the NutritionalRisk Index (NRI).Materials and methods: A retrospective, observational analytical study including 113 hospitalizedpatients over 75 years of age receiving nutritional support. Weight, height, age, lengthof stay, Mini Nutritional Assessment (MNA), nutrition type and duration, and occurrence ofcomplications were collected. GNRI and NRI were calculated. Both indexes were compared toeach other and with parameters measured. Results: Mean GNRI was 88.79 (SD: 13.1), mean NRI 79.96 (SD: 10.8), and mean MNA 17.49 (SD:4.9). Complications occurred in 50.4% of patients, and 14% died. NRI and GNRI did not correlatewith length of stay (R = 0.136) or with length of nutrition (R = 0.041). No significant correlationwas seen between GNRI and complications, but a significant relationship was found with NRI.After stratification into surgical and medical patients, NRI was seen to be significantly relatedto complications in surgical patients only (p &lt; 0.05). GNRI was not related to complications ineither surgical or medical patients.Conclusions: In hospitalized elderly patients, NRI is a better predictor of complications and maybe more appropriate for assessing the risk of death than GNRI. GNRI underestimated nutritionalrisk as compared to NRI (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fariza-Vicente, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calleja-Fernández, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidal-Casariego, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias-García, Rosa María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballesteros-Pomar, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brea-Laranjo, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano-Rodríguez, Isidoro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Gómez, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes y objetivo La valoración nutricional en el paciente anciano es compleja y no comparable a la de personas más jóvenes. Para ello existen herramientas específicas como el Índice de riesgo nutricional geriátrico (GNRI). El objetivo del estudio fue comparar este índice con el Índice de riesgo nutricional (NRI). Material y métodos Estudio observacional analítico retrospectivo que incluyó a 113 pacientes hospitalizados mayores de 75 años en seguimiento nutricional. Se recogió: peso, talla, edad, estancia media, Mini Nutritional Assessment (MNA), tipo de nutrición y duración de la misma y presencia de complicaciones. Se calcularon el NRI y el GNRI. Se compararon ambos índices entre sí y con los parámetros medidos. Resultados La media del GNRI fue 88,79 (DE: 13,1), la del NRI 79,96 (DE: 10,8) y la del MNA 17,49 (DE: 4,9). Un 50,4% sufrió complicaciones y un 14% fue éxitus. No se correlacionó el NRI ni el GNRI con estancia media R=0,136 ni con duración de la nutrición R=0,041. Al relacionar el riesgo nutricional con la presencia de complicaciones se observó que no había relación significativa con el GNRI, pero sí cñon el NRI (p&lt;0,05). Estratificando en pacientes quirúrgicos y médicos existió relación significativa del NRI con las complicaciones sólo en pacientes quirúrgicos (p&lt;0,05), siendo no significativa en pacientes médicos. Al analizar el GNRI se observó que no había relación significativa en ninguno de los grupos. Conclusiones En pacientes ancianos hospitalizados, el NRI predice mejor las complicaciones y podría ser más adecuado a la hora de valorar el riesgo de éxitus que el GNRI. El GNRI infraestima el riesgo nutricional respecto del NRI (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;58(3): 104-111, mar. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95821</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración del riesgo nutricional en pacientes ancianos hospitalizados mediante diferentes herramientas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28940</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30401</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28162^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7471</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
