<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78822</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Melasma Update</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Melasma is a common acquired hyperpigmentary disorder of the face. However, the pathogenesis of melasma remains largely unknown and the treatment is still challenging. This article discusses histology of melasma in view of melanin pigmentation with a more in depth question about number of melanocytes and melanophages in dermis of melasma. We also explore the current understanding of etiopathogenesis of melasma. We conclude the review with a discussion of important issues that should be addressed in future research to find effective treatment modality of melasma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Young Kang, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortonne, JP</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El melasma es un trastorno de la pigmentación facial, adquirido y frecuente. Sin embargo, se desconoce en gran medida su patogenia y el tratamiento continúa siendo un reto. En este artículo se discute la histología del melasma desde la perspectiva de la pigmentación melánica, profundizando más sobre el número de melanocitos y melanófagos en la dermis del melasma. También se comenta el conocimiento actual sobre la etiopatogenia del melasma. Concluimos la revisión con una discusión sobre aspectos importantes que se deben abordar en futuras investigaciones para encontrar un tratamiento eficaz del melasma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;100(supl.2): 110-113, dic. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78822</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actualización en Melasma</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11292^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8716^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34313^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8716^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38104</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34313^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11292^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
