<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95803</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-2399</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Physical compatibility of sodium bicarbonate with other drugs often administered in the intensive care unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction Acid-base disorders are associated with many diseases of the critically ill patient. Early treatment with sodium bicarbonate of these metabolic disorders is required for their normalization. This is an alkaline electrolyte solution administered by continuous or intermittent infusion. Its incompatibility due to its alkaline pH has been described, as it produces insoluble carbonate precipitation and causes carbon dioxide gas when mixed with acidic solutions. Material and method An in vitro experimental study was performed. Bicarbonate was mixed with 13 drugs simulating Y-site administration. We combined 5ml bicarbonate with 5ml of every drug, at highest daily concentration used. The samples were visually examined to detect color changes, cloudiness, precipitation or gas formation, pH measurement and spectrophotometric analysis at 450nm and 620nm. The samples were evaluated at 0, 15, 30, 60 and 120minutes. The compatibility criteria were absence of visual changes, pH changes&lt;0.5 and variability of absorbance &lt;0.01.ResultsWe studied each drug individually and mixed with bicarbonate with 27 samples, and 135 measurements were performed. The incompatibilities did not always produce visual changes. Knowing the pH of drugs does not guarantee the compatibility of the mixture. Nitroglycerin with pH 4 is compatible with bicarbonate. Thiopental with pH 11 makes precipitation. Higher absorbances showed color changes, cloudiness and precipitation. Conclusions Bicarbonate is physically compatible with esmolol, furosemide, heparin, insulin, morphine, nimodipine, nitroglycerin and urapidil and incompatible with amiodarone, cisatracurium, haloperidol, midazolam and thiopental (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ribas Nicolau, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Juan, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arévalo Rubert, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maqueda Palau, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amorós Cerdá, S. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción Las alteraciones acidobásicas se asocian a muchas afecciones del paciente crítico. Estos trastornos metabólicos requieren pronta normalización mediante bicarbonato sódico. Esta solución electrolítica alcalinizante se administra en infusión continua o intermitente. Se ha descrito su incompatibilidad por su pH alcalino, que produce precipitación de carbonatos insolubles y origina gases de dióxido de carbono al mezclarlo en soluciones ácidas. Objetivo Determinar la compatibilidad física del bicarbonato sódico 1M administrado en Y con fármacos de uso común en UCI.Material y método Estudio experimental in vitro. Se mezcló el bicarbonato con 13 fármacos simulando la administración en Y. Se combinaron 5 ml de bicarbonato con 5 ml de cada fármaco, eligiéndose concentraciones máximas utilizadas en la práctica. Las muestras se examinaron visualmente para detectar cambios de color, turbidez, precipitación o formación de gas; medición del pH y análisis espectrofotométrico a 450 nm y 620 nm. Se evaluaron las muestras a 0, 15, 30, 60 y 120 min. Los criterios de compatibilidad fueron: ausencia de cambios visuales, cambio pH&lt;0,5 y variabilidad de absorbancia &lt; 0,01.ResultadosSe estudiaron los fármacos individualmente y en mezcla con el bicarbonato, y resultaron 27 muestras, con las que se realizaron 135 determinaciones. Las incompatibilidades no siempre producen cambios visuales. Conocer el pH de los fármacos no garantiza la compatibilidad de la mezcla. La nitroglicerina con pH 4 es compatible. El tiopental con pH 11 precipita. Las absorbancias elevadas se acompañan de cambios de color, turbidez y precipitación.Conclusiones El bicarbonato es físicamente compatible con esmolol, furosemida, heparina, insulina, morfina, nimodipino, nitroglicerina y urapidil e incompatible con amiodarona, cisatracurio, haloperidol, midazolam y tiopental (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Intensiva;22(2): 78-82, Abr. -Jun. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95803</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Compatibilidad física del bicarbonato sódico con fármacos de uso frecuente en la unidad de cuidados intensivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31036^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4406</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4409</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
