<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147141</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-0771</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Open elbow dislocation assocciated to brachial artery disruption: an infrequent emergency</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Open elbow dislocation is a rare pathology that may be associated with neurovascular injuries. We report the case of a patient with an open elbow dislocation and section of the brachial artery. Case report: A 65-year-old woman presented to her local emergency department for functional impotence of the left forearm and wound with bone exposure in the antecubital fossa after accidental falling down the stairs at home. Physical examination revealed a solution of continuity of skin with humerus trochlea and capitellum exposure in the left antecubital fossa. Radial pulse is not appreciated and the patient complained of paresthesias. With the diagnosis of open elbow dislocation and high suspicion of vascular injury, the patient was operated urgently finding a complete section of the humeral artery. Vascular end-to-end anastomosis of the brachial artery and elbow external fixation was performed. After 8 months of follow up, the patient presents good elbow and wrist mobility, and no signs of distal ischemia. Conclusion: Open elbow dislocation can associate a brachial artery injury, the reason why it is a surgical emergency and it should not delay its treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cobo Cervantes, Clara Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velasco Medina, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Pérez, Ángel David</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La luxación abierta de codo es una patología infrecuente que puede asociar lesiones neurovasculares. Presentamos el caso clínico de una paciente con una luxación abierta de codo y sección de la arteria humeral. Caso clínico: Mujer de 65 años, que tras caída accidental por las escaleras de su domicilio, acude a urgencias con impotencia funcional del antebrazo izquierdo y herida a nivel de fosa antecubital con exposición ósea. En la exploración física, se evidenció a nivel de la fosa antecubital izquierda una solución de continuidad de la piel con exposición de tróclea y cóndilo humeral. A nivel distal del antebrazo no se apreciaba pulso y presentaba parestesias. Con el diagnóstico de luxación abierta de codo y alta sospecha de lesión vascular se intervino de urgencia hallando una sección completa de la arteria humeral. Se realizó sutura vascular término-terminal de la arteria humeral y fijación externa del codo para corregir la luxación. Tras 8 meses de seguimiento, la paciente presenta buena movilidad articular de codo y muñeca, sin signos de isquemia distal. Conclusiones: La luxación abierta de codo puede asociar una lesión de la arteria humeral, motivo por el cual es una emergencia quirúrgica y no debe demorarse su tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Andal. Traumatol. Ortop. (Ed. impr.);32(2): 98-98, jul.-dic. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147141</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Luxación abierta de codo con rotura de la arteria humeral: una emergencia infrecuente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1164^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4624^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13918^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53994^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15080^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22831^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12319^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53994^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1164^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15080^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4624^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12319^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29193^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1168^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53994^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
