<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73169</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Preclinical atherosclerosis in a group of young subjects with type 1 diabetes from a Mediterranean area</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Carotid intima-media thickness (cIMT) and presence of atherosclerotic plaques were evaluated in a cross-sectional study performed in a group of type 1 diabetes mellitus (T1D) subjects from a Mediterranean area without additional cardiovascular risk factors. These results were compared to those obtained from a reference population. Patients and methods: Twenty-two patients with T1D (age 34.6 (7.9) years) and a disease duration of 15.3 (5.9) years) were included. B-mode IMT measurements were used to evaluate cIMT and the presence of plaques. Results: A significantly higher cIMT and max-cIMT were found in patients with T1D in comparison with the age-reference population (0.52 (0.08) vs. 0.46 (0.09)mm; p&lt;0.001 and 0.63 (0.13) vs. 0.55 (0.12); p&lt;0.007 for cIMT and max-cIMT, respectively). The proportion of subjects affected by plaques within the group of T1D subjects was equivalent to the value observed in the 46&#150;55 year-old reference group. Conclusion: Even in the absence of major cardiovascular risk factors, subjects with T1D from a low prevalence CVD risk area display signs of an increased and accelerated preclinical atherosclerotic process (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gilabert, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conget, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giménez, Marga</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo; El grosor del complejo íntima-media carotídeo (cIMT) y la presencia de placas de ateroma se evaluaron mediante un estudio transversal en un grupo de sujetos con diabetes mellitus de tipo 1 (DM1) de un área mediterránea que no presentaban otros factores de riesgo cardiovascular (FRCV). Estos resultados se compararon con los obtenidos en una población de referencia. Pacientes y método: Se incluyeron 22 pacientes con DM1 (media de edad de 34,6 años [desviación estándar DE de 7,9] y una media de 15,3 años [DE de 5,9] de evolución de diabetes). Para evaluar el cIMT y el grosor máximo del complejo íntima-media carotídeo (máx-cIMT) o placas se utilizó ecografía en modo B. Resultados: Los valores del cIMT y del máx-cIMT fueron significativamente mayores en los pacientes con DM1 en comparación con la franja etaria correspondiente de la población de referencia (cIMT: 0,52mm [DE de 0,08] frente a 0,46mm [DE de 0,09]; p&lt;0,001 y máx-cIMT: 0,63mm [DE de 0,13] frente a 0,55mm [DE de 0,12]; p&lt;0,007). La proporción de pacientes que presentaban placas de aterosclerosis fue equivalente a la del grupo etario de 46 a 55 años de referencia. Conclusiones: En ausencia de otros FRCV, los pacientes con DM1 de un área geográfica considerada de baja prevalencia para enfermedad cardiovascular presentan signos de aceleración de aterosclerosis preclínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);132(19): 740-742, mayo 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73169</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aterosclerosis preclínica en un grupo de pacientes jóvenes con diabetes de tipo 1 de un área mediterránea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30469^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50504^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32692^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50504^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200905</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
