<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152742</identifier>
<setSpec>1697-641X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacy of a bioadhesive dental gel containing precipitated silica particles, potassium nitrate, and sodium monofluorophosphate in patients with dentin hyperesthesia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Dentin hypersensitivity is characterized by an acute pain of short duration associated with exposure of dentin to thermal, tactile, osmotic or chemical stimuli. It shows increasing prevalence and reduces the quality of life of patients. The main objective was to evaluate the effectiveness of a dental bio-adhesive gel with precipitated amorphous silica, potassium nitrate, and sodium monofluorophosphate in patients with dentin hypersensitivity. The secondary objective was to evaluate acceptability and tolerance of the product. Methods: The product was applied for 14 days, 3 times / day after habitual cleanliness routine and was not rinsed for 30 minutes. Its efficacy was evaluated by sensitive touch and air jet techniques. At the end of the study the patients filled a subjective questionnaire about the perception of the product. Results: The dental evaluation showed a significant reduction of dental hypersensitivity at all time points of the study (p&lt;0.05) according to the sensitive touch and air jet technique results. This improvement increased as the treatment progressed. All questions about the effectiveness of the product and its organoleptic characteristics received a positive answer. Treatment results were considered very satisfactory or satisfactory by 95% of patients. No significant adverse reactions associated to the product were observed. Conclusions: Dental bio-adhesive gel with precipitated amorphous silica, potassium nitrate, and sodium monofluorophosphate, administered 3 times / day resulted in a significant reduction of dental hypersensitivity, and this improvement increased with time. The product showed very good acceptability and tolerance (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zaldívar Notario, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mira Otal, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vivancos Cuadras, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La hiperestesia dentinaria se caracteriza por un dolor intenso, de corta duración, asociado a la exposición de la dentina en respuesta a estímulos térmicos, táctiles, osmóticos o químicos. De prevalencia creciente, reduce la calidad de vida del paciente. El objetivo principal fue evaluar la eficacia de un gel bioadhesivo dental con dióxido de silicio obliterante, nitrato potásico y monofluorofosfato sódico en pacientes con hiperestesia dentinaria. Como objetivo secundario se valoraron su aceptabilidad y tolerancia. Métodos: El producto se aplicó durante 14 días, 3 veces/día, después de la limpieza dental y se mantuvo sin aclarar 30 minutos (n=19). Se evaluó su eficacia mediante exploración odontológica por técnica táctil y de chorro de aire. Al finalizar el estudio los pacientes completaron un cuestionario de percepción del producto. Resultados: La evaluación odontológica mostró una reducción significativa de la hipersensibilidad dental en todos los puntos temporales del estudio (p&lt;0,05) mediante técnica táctil y de chorro de aire. Esta mejoría fue sostenida y aumentó a medida que avanzó el tratamiento. Todas las preguntas sobre la eficacia del producto y sus características organolépticas percibidas tuvieron una respuesta positiva. Los resultados del tratamiento fueron considerados muy satisfactorios/satisfactorios por un 95% de los pacientes. No se observó ninguna reacción adversa significativa derivada del uso del producto. Conclusiones: El gel bioadhesivo dental con dióxido de silicio obliterante, nitrato potásico y monofluorofosfato sódico, administrado 3 veces/día, consiguió una reducción significativa de la hipersensibilidad dental, mejoría que fue aumentando con el tiempo. El producto presentó muy buena aceptabilidad y tolerancia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cient. dent. (Ed. impr.);13(1): 33-40, ene.-abr. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152742</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia de un gel bioadhesivo dental con dióxido de silicio obliterante, nitrato potásico y monofluorofosfato sódico en pacientes con hiperestesia dentinaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13354^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7121^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53669^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5922^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31916^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3823^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
