<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147111</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Our scientific production in the field of spondyloarthritis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">GRESSER (the Spondyloarthritis Study Group of SER) reunites, since 1999, Spanish rheumatologists interested in learning and disseminating knowledge on spondyloarthritis, and over the years has maintained an important scientific activity based on the development of various research projects (Regisponser and follow up cohorts: Early and EA, respondia, the ESPERANZA Program, etc.,) which has resulted in interesting scientific publications and high impact communications in national and international journals. However, and despite this production being very noticeable, Gresser has managed, above all, to draw attention to these diseases by Spanish rheumatologists and create an interesting field of study that offers new and young professionals, in one way or another, access to these intriguing conditions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Collantes Estévez, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">GRESSER (Grupo de Estudio de Espondiloartritis de la SER) reúne desde 1999 a reumatólogos españoles interesados en profundizar y difundir el conocimiento de las espondiloartritis. A lo largo del tiempo, ha mantenido una importante actividad científica basada en el desarrollo de diferentes proyectos de investigación (Regisponser y sus cohortes de seguimiento: Early y EA, Respondia, Programa Esperanza, etc.), de los cuales se ha derivado una interesante producción científica en publicaciones científicas en revistas de alto factor de impacto y en comunicaciones en congresos nacionales e internacionales. Sin embargo, y a pesar de ser muy notable esta producción, GRESSER ha conseguido, sobre todo, llamar la atención de estas enfermedades a los reumatólogos españoles y crear un campo de estudio interesante que ofrecer a los nuevos y jóvenes profesionales que, de una u otra forma, se acerquen a estas patologías tan intrigantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);8(supl.1): 42-45, mar. 2012. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147111</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuestra producción científica en el campo de las espondiloartritis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24527^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27794^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36004^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
