<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127457</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Imported parasitic diseases in the immigrant population in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Migration has contributed to the emergence of certain infectious diseases in host countries. In Spain the number of immigrants has increased exponentially in recent decades. The aim of this review is to identify and analyze the available information on imported parasitic diseases in immigrant population in our country. Methods: A scope review of original articles published on imported parasitic diseases between 1998 and 2012. Study populations from Latin America, Africa, Asia, Eastern Europe and individuals who are under the definition of an immigrant from International Organization for Migration were included. The literature search was performed in the Medline and MEDES-MEDicina databases. Results: A total of 51 descriptive studies were included in the analysis. Most immigrants attended at referral health facilities were originally from sub-SaharanAfrica (between 16%-87%), followed by LatinAmerica (13%-37%), while Asia was the region less represented (0.2%-8.8%). A considerable proportion (6.5-31%) of inmigrants that attended to referal units of tropical medicine or inmigrant health, and that were originally from Latin America, particularly those from Bolivia, are affected by the Chagas disease, and several cases of mother-to-child transmission have been registered in our country. Conclusion: Imported parasitosis is a frequent diagnosis among migrant population. This review highlight the impact that migration has had on the emergence of certain imported parasitic diseases, being Chagas disease the most paradigmatic example (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bardají Alonso, Azucena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinazo Delgado, María Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gascón Brustenga, Joaquim</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilajeliu Balagué, Alba</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz-Barreda, Gaby</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heras Prat, Paula de las</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: La migración ha contribuido a la emergencia de ciertas enfermedades infecciosas en los países receptores de inmigrantes. En España el número de inmigrantes ha crecido exponencialmente en las últimas décadas. El objetivo de esta revisión es identificar y analizar la información disponible sobre parasitosis importadas en población inmigrante en nuestro país. Métodos: Revisión de conjunto de artículos originales publicados sobre parasitosis importadas publicados entre 1998 y 2012. Se incluyeron trabajos realizados con poblaciones procedentes de Latinoamérica, África, Asia y Europa del Este o que cumplieran la definición de inmigrante de la Organización Internacional de Migraciones. La búsqueda bibliográfica se realizó en Medline y MEDES-MEDicina. Resultados: Se incluyó un total de 51 estudios descriptivos en el análisis. La mayor parte de los inmigrantes atendidos procedieron del África Subsahariana (16%-87% según estudios), seguidos de América Latina (13%-37%), siendoAsia la región menos representada (0,2%-8,8%). Destaca que el 6,5-31% de los inmigrantes atendidos en unidades de medicina tropical o de atención al inmigrante y procedentes de América Latina, en particular de Bolivia, están afectados por la enfermedad de Chagas y la existencia en nuestro país de casos de transmisión congénita de esta enfermedad. Conclusiones: Las parasitosis importadas son un diagnóstico frecuente entre la población inmigrante. Esta revisión pone de manifiesto el impacto que ha tenido la migración en la emergencia de ciertas enfermedades parasitarias importadas, siendo un ejemplo paradigmático la enfermedad de Chagas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;88(6): 783-802, nov.-dic. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127457</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Parasitosis importadas en la población inmigrante en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8462^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10461^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10461^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8462^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30425^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30425^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10461^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53393^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14563^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
