<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128964</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4603</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Language and behavior: determinants of academic and social failure. A review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">One of the issues that is currently gaining wide social importance is the increase in violence and truancy among Spanish adolescents. This situation greatly hampers the work of teachers, increasing conflicts between staff and students. The academic performance of these youngsters is weakened to the point of dropout. Identifying the maximum number of variables involved in academic failure and the social development of adolescents, as well as their causes, should be a current research priority. Such research would help to optimize educational conditions by implementing prevention programs and intervention strategies with all the actors involved in the learning process. In the last few years, numerous investigations have analyzed language and behavioral skills. The present study aims to provide a comprehensive and integrated view about the current state of the relationship between these two variables and their role in academic failure and social development in adolescents, as well as to indicate future research lines in the field of education(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Parra, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendoza Lara, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Mezcua, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Rubio Martínez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Uno de los debates que actualmente está cobrando mayor relevancia social son las cada vez más frecuentes situaciones de violencia y absentismo escolar en los adolescentes de nuestra sociedad. Esta situación empeora el trabajo docente, y se observa un aumento de relaciones conflictivas entre el profesorado y el alumnado. El rendimiento académico de estos jóvenes se resiente hasta el punto del abandono escolar. Identificar el mayor número posible de variables implicadas en el fracaso académico y social de los adolescentes, así como sus causas, debe ser un objetivo prioritario en la investigación actual, con el fin de poder optimizar las condiciones educativas de los alumnos, e implementar programas de prevención e intervención con todos los actores implicados en el proceso de aprendizaje. Durante los últimos años, numerosas investigaciones han incluido entre sus objetivos el estudio de las habilidades lingüísticas y conductuales. El presente trabajo pretende ofrecer una visión general e integrada sobre la situación actual en el estudio de la relación entre estas dos variables, y su papel en el fracaso académico y social de los adolescentes, así como abrir futuras líneas de investigación dentro del campo educativo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. logop. foniatr. audiol. (Ed. impr.);30(3): 144-150, jul.-sep.2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128964</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lenguaje y conducta: determinantes del fracaso académico y social. Una revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d300^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d300^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d301^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d301^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14876</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36411</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
