<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100225</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidural posterior migration of disc fragment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The posterior epidural migration of a fragment of lumbar disc herniation is a rare clinical presentation. Case report. We report the case of a 76-year-old with back pain and progressive paraparesis in the lower limbs, with the emergence of a cauda equina syndrome 4 days after admission. MRI showed lumbar spondylosis and a well-defined intra-spinal mass in the posterior epidural space. Surgical resection of the epidural mass was performed. The pathological study revealed an intervertebral disc fragment; thus it was a complete migration of a herniated lumbar disc. The patient was healed after surgery and specific rehabilitation treatment. Conclusions. Patients with posterior migration of disc fragment may present with severe neurological deficits, such as cauda equina syndrome. Because the radiological images of disc fragments are similar to those of other lesions, such as metastasis, synovial cyst, dural abscess or haematoma, definitive diagnosis is made by excision and pathological study. Emergency surgery is required to prevent severe neurological deficits (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aguas Valiente, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Altemir Martínez, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Curiá Jové, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mas Atance, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jové Talavera, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chárlez Marco, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La migración posterior epidural de un fragmento de hernia discal lumbar es una presentación clínica infrecuente. Caso clínico. Presentamos el caso de un paciente varón de 76 años, que acude por dolor lumbar y paraparesia progresiva en extremidades inferiores, con la aparición a los 4 días del ingreso de un síndrome de cauda equina. La resonancia magnética muestra espondilosis lumbar y una masa intrarraquídea bien delimitada en el espacio epidural posterior. Se realiza una exéresis quirúrgica de la masa epidural. El estudio anatomopatológico informó de fragmento de disco intervertebral, por lo que se trataba de una migración completa de una hernia discal lumbar. Tras la intervención quirúrgica y un tratamiento rehabilitador específico remitió la clínica del paciente. Conclusiones. Los pacientes con migración posterior de un fragmento de disco presentan graves déficits neurológicos como el síndrome de cauda equina. Debido a que las imágenes radiológicas de los fragmentos del disco son similares a los de otras lesiones como metástasis, quiste sinovial, absceso dural o hematoma, el diagnóstico definitivo se realiza mediante exéresis y estudio anatomopatológico. El tratamiento quirúrgico urgente es necesario para evitar déficits neurológicos severos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);56(3): 224-226, mayo-jun. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100225</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Migración posterior epidural de fragmento discal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53068^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7568^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53068^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4904^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34329^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4904^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34329^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7568^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7568^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53068^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53068^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7568^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7568^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
