<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93949</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Self-esteem as a predictive psycho-social variable in physical activity in seniors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this study was to investigate the relationship between self-esteem expressed by people over 65 years of age and taking part in physical activity. Self-concept and self-esteem are psychologically fundamental components of quality of life in adulthood and well-being. Selfesteem has been proposed as an area of intervention to improve the quality of life in the senior population. The sample was composed of more than 184 people, 92 of whom took part in physical activity on a regular basis and another 92, who developed sedentary lifestyles. The results of the Rosenberg Self-Esteem Questionnaire applied to the sample showed different levels of self-esteem between seniors who are physically active and those who are not, with self-esteem being significantly higher in active seniors. Studies with similar objectives demonstrate and support the verification of the hypothesis that establishes a positive relationship between self-esteem and participation in physical activity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García, Alfonso J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bohórquez, M. Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El propósito del presente estudio es investigar acerca de la relación existente entre la Autoestima manifestada por personas mayores de 65 años y la realización de actividad física. El autoconcepto y la Autoestima aparecen como componentes psicológicos fundamentales de la calidad de vida durante la adultez mayor y del bienestar personal. La Autoestima ha sido propuesta como un área de intervención para mejorar la calidad de vida en la población mayor. La muestra la componen 184 personas mayores, de las que 92 realizan actividad física frecuentemente y otras 92 desarrollan un estilo de vida sedentario. Se aplicó el cuestionario de Autoestima personal de Rosenberg. Los resultados muestran diferentes niveles de Autoestima entre los mayores que realizan actividad física y los que no, siendo significativamente más alta en los primeros. Estudios con objetivos similares demuestran y apoyan la comprobación de la hipótesis de partida que establece la relación positiva entre la Autoestima y la realización de actividad física (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;21(1): 195-200, ene.-jun. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93949</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Autoestima como variable psicosocial predictora de la actividad física en personas mayores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12034^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36316</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
