<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127089</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-5967</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Early experiences and severe mental illness in childhood</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This work aims to evaluate the factors of risk (ODAT) associations in the first years of life and severity of mental pathology of the child, cross-sectional, descriptive and analytical case-control study, with a selection of subjects by means of a stratified random sampling. We selected three groups of children, one with serious mental disorder, other mental disorders not classified as serious and a last group of children who come to the recognition of the healthy child. Biological alterations detected in the initial periods of life are especially associated with more severe mental pathology. Living with both parents and close relatives, mental pathology and the employment situation of the parents, the loss of significant people also seem to contribute significantly in the child mental pathology. Against factors such as the early incorporation into child care, do not appear as relevant (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Pascual, Ana María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo pretende evaluar las asociaciones de los factores de riesgo (ODAT) en los primeros años de vida y gravedad de la patología mental del niño, a través de un estudio trasversal, descriptivo y analítico de caso control, con una selección de los sujetos mediante un muestreo aleatorio estratificado. Se seleccionaron tres grupos de niños, uno con trastorno mental grave, otro con trastornos mentales no catalogados como graves y un último grupo de niños que acuden al reconocimiento del niño sano. Las alteraciones biológicas detectadas en los periodos iniciales de la vida se asocian sobre todo a la patología mental de mayor gravedad. La convivencia con ambos padres y parientes próximos, la patología mental y la situación laboral de los padres, las pérdidas de personas significativas también parecen contribuir significativamente en la patología mental del niño. Por contra factores como la incorporación temprana a guardería, no aparecen como relevantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psiquiatr. psicoter. niño adolesc;(56): 47-58, jul.-dic. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127089</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencias tempranas y patología mental grave en la infancia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2717</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2699^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
