<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128270</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The clinical semiology of attention déficit hyperactivity disorder according to age, and the effectiveness of treatments at different ages</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) is the most important cause of poor academic performance and is also usually associated with behavioural, emotional and sociability disorders. Aim. To analyse the different clinical features and the response to psychostimulant therapy, according to the age. Subjects and methods.We reviewed the cases of 152 children referred to Neuropaediatrics owing to suspected ADHD over a 6-year period. Diagnosis and comorbidity were investigated by the looking at their case history, by examination and observation, as well as by interviewing the parents (DSM-IV criteria), and by applying Conners&#146; Rating Scale for parents and teachers, in addition to neuropsychological tests. In order to improve data processing, we established four groups according to the patient's age at diagnosis and when treatment was started: G1: 3-5; G2: 6-8; G3: 9-11; and G4: 12-15 years. Results. ADHD was diagnosed in 102 of the 152 children; 53% had the combined type, 26% were of the inattentional type, and 20% were hyperactive/impulsive. Poor school performance increased with age and reached 75% in G4. The same occurred with conduct disorders: at 6 years of age, 23% were found to have oppositional defiant disorder, and from the age of 9 onwards over 60% of them had conduct disorders. Up until 12 years of age they showed some improvement with psychostimulants and later the rate of dropouts from medical clinical controls and from treatment was over 40%. Conclusions. The older patients are and the later ADHD is attended, the more problems they have. If successful preventive measures are to be implemented, it would be advisable to begin treatment even before children start primary education (5 years old), so as to try and avoid the pedagogical and behavioural repercussions observed in these children at the age of 6 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Expósito Torrejón, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintanar Rioja, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Pérez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Granero, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonet Serra, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El trastorno por déficit de atención con hiperactividad (TDAH) es la causa más importante de fracaso escolar, y suele asociarse además a trastornos de conducta, emocionales y de sociabilidad. Objetivo. Analizar las distintas manifestaciones clínicas y la respuesta al tratamiento con psicoestimulantes, en función de la edad. Sujetos y métodos. Se revisan 152 niños remitidos a Neuropediatría por sospecha de TDAH en 6 años. El diagnóstico y la comorbilidad se investiga mediante anamnesis, exploración y observación, entrevista a padres (criterios DSM-IV), cuestionario de Conners para padres y profesores, y pruebas neuropsicológicas. Para mejor tratamiento de los datos, realizamos cuatro grupos según la edad al diagnóstico e inicio del tratamiento: G1: 3-5; G2: 6-8; G3: 9-11 y G4: 12-15 años. Resultados. De los 152 niños, se diagnosticó TDAH en 102; el 53% fueron de tipo combinado, el 26% inatencional, y el 20% hiperactivo/impulsivo. El mal rendimiento escolar aumenta con la edad, y un 75% es en el G4. Lo mismo sucede con los trastornos de conducta: a los 6 años ya encontramos un 23% de trastorno negativista desafiante, y a partir de los 9 años más de un 60% presentan trastornos de conducta. Mejoran con psicoestimulantes un 70% hasta los 12 años, y, después, el índice de abandono del control clínico médico y del tratamiento es de más de un 40%. Conclusiones. Cuanto mayores y más tarde se atienden los TDAH, más problemas tienen. La prevención hace conveniente empezar el tratamiento incluso antes de iniciar la educación primaria (5 años), en un intento de evitar las repercusiones pedagógicas y conductuales observadas ya a los 6 años en estos niños (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;41(9): 517-524, nov. 2005. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128270</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Semiología clínica del trastorno por déficit de atención con hiperactividad en función de la edad y eficacia de los tratamientos en las distintas edades</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8037^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14876</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33525^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8961^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
