<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056029</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-6157</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The oral rehabilitation of pacients with lost of mandibular substance is complicated. The ideal treatment consists in re-establishing the oclusion, the function and an acceptable facial aesthetic. In this article different therapeutic options are shown in various clinical cases. Four clinical cases of head and neck squamous cell carcinoma affected patients that were treated with surgicaI resection and/or radiation therapy and subsequently rehabilitated with prothesis have been revised.  The hemimandibulectomized patient rehabilitation emphasizes the defect surgical reconstruction and the subsequent prosthetic rehabilitation. Factors such opening mouth limitacion, labial support and seal, interoclusal space, soft tissue and tongue state, bone limitations should be kept in mind when an implant rehabilitacion is planed.  The prosthetic rehabilitation depends on the retention that only can be achieved from teeth and implants. The hemimandibulectomized patients need an exhaustive and multidisciplinary planification (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Araiko, Gorka</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rey, Ana del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escuin, Tomás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herreros, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La rehabilitación oral de pacientes con pérdidas de sustancia mandibular es compleja. El tratamiento ideal consistirá en restablecer la oclusión, la función así como una aceptable estética facial. En este artículo se presentan diferentes opciones terapéuticas mostrando la resolución de varios casos clínicos. Se han revisado cuatro casos clínicos de pacientes afectos de carcinoma de células escamosas en cabeza y cuello que fueron tratados mediante resección quirúrgica y/o radioterapia y posteriormente rehabilitados protésicamente.  En la rehabilitacón de pacientes hemimandibulectomizados destaca la reconstrucción quirúrgica del defecto y la rehabilitación protésica posterior. Al diseñar el plan de tratamiento se han de tener en cuenta diversos factores como la limitación de apertura, el soporte y sellado labial, espacio interoclusal, estado de los tejidos blandos y la lengua y las limitaciones óseas para la posible colocación de implantes.  La rehabilitación protésica dependerá de la retención, que sólo se puede obtener a partir de dientes e implantes. Los pacientes hemimandibulectomlzados precisan de una planificación exhaustiva y multidisciplinar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Dentum (Barc.);7(1): 12-16, ene.-mar. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056029</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rehabilitación protésica en pacientes con pérdida de sustancia mandibular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24235^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33574^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2337^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6409^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9259^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
