<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-69859</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To compare the clinical features, mainly adrenergic manifestations, in patients with pheochromocytoma (PCT), sympathetic paraganglioma (SPGL) and parasympathetic paraganglioma (PSPGL).Patients and method: Thirty-four patients consecutively diagnosed and treated for PCT (n = 20), SPGL (n = 9) and PSPGL (n = 5) were included in the present study. The mean age was 44 years (range, 17-74). The forms of presentation, clinical manifestations, results of diagnostic tests, pathological characteristics, and postsurgery outcomes were analyzed. Results: The patients were treated in different medical units in our hospital. Diagnosis of PCT was mainly based on adrenergic symptoms (65%), SPGL on adrenergic symptoms (44%) and compressive symptoms (65%) and PSPGL on the basis of the tumor mass effect (100%). However, exhaustive analysis of adrenergic manifestations revealed that 80%, 66.7% and 40% of patients with PCT,SPGL and PSPGL respectively had adrenergic manifestations. Eighty-two percent of patients with PCT and 100% of those with SPGL showed increased urinaryexcretion of catecholamines and their metabolites. Biochemical studies were not performed in three patients with PCT and five with SPGL and were performed in all patients with PSPGL. The mean tumoral size (in mm) was significantly higher in PCT than in SPGL and PSPGL (59 ± 28, 39 ± 16 and 34 ± 26). After surgery, 17 patients with PCT, seven with PGS and four with PSPGL were considered cured, one patient showed partially persistent PSPGL, one patient with SPGL relapsed, and five patients died (three with PCT and two with SPGL).Conclusions: In the present study, 65% of PCT and 44% of SPGL were diagnosed on the basis of adrenergic symptoms, while 40% of PSPGL also showed symptoms compatible with catecholamine production. We highlight the high percentage of adrenergic manifestations in the group of extra-adrenal tumors, which are not usually investigated in this context. Therefore, we believe that PCT, SPGL and PSPGL should be considered as the same nosological entity in different locations and should be managed in referral units (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Páramo Fernández, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casteràs Román, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luna Cano, Reyes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Encisa de Sá, Jose Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hervás Abad, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Mayor, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Comparar características clínicas, principalmente adrenérgicas, de los feocromocitomas (FC), paragangliomas simpáticos (PGLS) y parasimpáticos (PGLPS).Pacientes y método: Se incluyó en el estudio a 34 pacientes diagnosticados y tratados consecutivamente de FC (20), PGLS (9) y PGLPS (5), con una edad media de 44 (rango, 17-74) años. Se comparó formas de presentación, manifestaciones clínicas, producción hormonal, características patológicas y resultados tras el tratamiento. Resultados: Los pacientes fueron atendidos por múltiples servicios. Los FC se diagnosticaron predominantemente por clínica adrenérgica (65%); los PGLS, por clínica adrenérgica (44%) y por efecto compresivo (45%), y los PGLPS, por efecto masa (100%). Sin embargo, cuando se evaluó de forma dirigida la clínica adrenérgica, el 80% de los FC, el 66,7% de los PGLS y el 40% de los PGLPS la habían manifestado. Presentaron secreción hormonal el 82,4% de los FC y el 100% de los PGLS. No se realizó estudio bioquímico en 3 FC, 5 PGLS y en ningún PGLPS. El tamaño tumoral (en mm) de los FC fue significativamente mayor que los PGLS y PGLPS (59 ± 28, 39 ±16 y 34 ± 26). Tras la extirpación del tumor, 17pacientes con FC, 7 con PGS y 4 con PGLPS quedaron libres de enfermedad, en 1 con PGLPS, éste persiste parcialmente, 1 PGLS recidivó y 5 pacientes murieron (3 con FC y 2 con PGLS).Conclusiones: En nuestro estudio observamos que se diagnostica por clínica adrenérgica los FC (65%) y los PGLS (44%), y además los PGLPS también presentaron clínica compatible con producción de catecolaminasen el interrogatorio dirigido en un 40%. Queremos reseñar el alto porcentaje de manifestaciones adrenérgicas en el grupo de tumores extra adrenales, que no se suele estudiarlos en este sentido, por tanto creemos que deben ser manejados como una misma entidad nosológica por una unidad de referencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;54(10): 519-524, dic. 2007. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-69859</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d24373</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31255^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10868^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10868^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31255^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10868^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10421^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10421^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10421</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31255^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
