<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59135</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Correct placement of left-sided double lumen endotracheal tubes: a simple verification</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJETIVE: Double lumen endotracheal tubes (DLTs)are used in thoracic surgery for selective bronchialintubation, which is required for single lung ventilation.Correct placement of the tube is checked by means offiberoptic bronchoscopy. We present a simple alternativemethod to help confirm the correct placement of left-sidedDLTs. The method consists of passing a suction catheterthrough the tracheal lumen of the tube. Our hypothesiswas that if the catheter can be inserted without difficulty,the tube is correctly placed. The objective was todetermine the sensitivity and specificity of that criterion.MATERIAL AND METHODS: We studied patients scheduledfor elective left pneumonectomy or lobectomy. After passingthe catheter through the left-sided DLT, placement waschecked by means of fiberoptic bronchoscopy (gold standard)and the results were compared with the placementassessment based on ease of insertion.RESULTS: One hundred patients were included. The DLTwas judged to be correctly placed in 88% of patients inwhom the catheter was inserted without resistance.Bronchoscopy corroborated this finding in 84% of cases;the tube was found to be incorrectly placed in theremaining 4% of cases and had to be reinserted. Resistancewas noted in 12% of cases and bronchoscopy confirmedthat the tube was incorrectly placed in those patients.CONCLUSIONS: This technique can be very useful inplacing left-sided DLTs in situations where fiberopticbronchoscopy is not available and if the anesthesiologisthas a thorough command of the method. Our resultssupport the routine use of this criterion as it is simple andeasy to learn. It should be remembered, however, thatconfirmation of placement by means of fiberopticbronchoscopy is currently the gold standard technique (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Belda Nácherc, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Postigo Morales, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aznárez Zango, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Raimundo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jover Pinillos, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maruenda Paulino, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Los tubos endobronquiales de doble luz (TDL)se utilizan en cirugía torácica para la intubación selectiva pulmonar,necesaria para la ventilación unipulmonar. La comprobaciónde su correcta colocación se realiza mediante fibrobroncoscopia.Presentamos un método simple y alternativopara ayudar a la comprobación del posicionamiento de losTDL izquierdos, que consiste en pasar una sonda de aspiraciónpor la rama traqueal del TDL. Nuestra hipótesis es quesi la sonda pasa sin dificultad el tubo estaría colocado correctamente.El objetivo de este estudio fue la determinación de lasensibilidad y especificidad de la prueba.MATERIAL Y MÉTODO: Pacientes programados para cirugíatorácica electiva de neumonectomía o lobectomíaizquierdas. Tras pasar la sonda por el TDL izquierdo secomprobó con el fibrobroncoscopio (técnica de referencia),comparándose ambos métodos.RESULTADO: Se incluyeron 100 pacientes. De los casosestudiados, en el 88% se dedujo una correcta posición delTDL por paso de sonda sin resistencia. De estos, en el 84%la fibrobroncoscopia corroboró esta situación mientras queen el 4% restante no fue así y hubo que recolocarlos. En el12% se encontró resistencia al pasar la sonda verificándoseen éstos una mala colocación por fibrobroncoscopio.CONCLUSIONES: Si dominamos esta técnica o si no disponemosde fibrobroncoscopio, esta maniobra puede ser útily de mucha ayuda durante la colocación de los TDLizquierdos. Nuestros resultados apoyan la práctica cotidianade esta maniobra, ya que es un método sencillo y accesible,pero recordando que la comprobación mediantefibrobroncoscopio es la técnica de referencia actualmente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;55(5): 277-281, mayo 2008. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59135</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Un método sencillo para ayudar a la comprobacióndel correcto posicionamiento de los tubos endotraquealesde doble luz izquierdos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11442^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23183^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7603^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2026^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200805</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
