<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165330</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Study of the mortality in workers of the National Institute of Sanitary Management (INGESA). Period 2000 to 2015</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The daily work in the complex organizations of health that are the hospitals, has its own characteristics that distinguishes from other organizations, since people work 24 hours of 365 days of the year and for working with the health, the disease and the care. For such motives they are exposed to risks different from the rest of the population, which makes interesting the study of their general mortality. For that reason this study considers to describe the mortality and its most important characteristics in workers of the National Institute of Sanitary Management, in the period of 2000 to 2015. Methodology: Descriptive retrospective Study of the mortality in the workers of the INGESA in the period 2000 to 2015. The population were the deceased workers of the INGESA. As a support program has been used SPSS v21. The file consists of 8 variables, such as sex, age, professional category, reason of the death, date of the decease, among others. Results: there have being notified 18 dead, the average of age 51,67 years with standard deviation +/-10,91 years. 72,2 % were men. The professional category with major incident of mortality were doctors with 44,4 %, hospital porter and administrative staff 16,75 % respectively. The most frequent reason of death were neoplasias (44,4 %) followed by the ictus 22,2 % and suicides 11,1 %. The year with more deceases was 2014. Conclusions: The suitable record of the mortality in the services of prevention of labor risks, allows to observe the predominant diseases and on the basis of this information to establish preventive measures adapted to control efficiently the public health of our workers (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pomares, María Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Finol, Alexander</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez, Julián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivero, Johanna</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El trabajo cotidiano en las complejas organizaciones de salud que son los hospitales, tiene características propias que las distingue de otras organizaciones y que sustenta su singularidad y complejidad ya sea por funcionar las 24 horas de los 365 días del año o por trabajar con la salud, la enfermedad y el cuidado. Por tales motivos son expuestos a riesgos diferentes del resto de la población, lo que hace interesante el estudio de su mortalidad general. Por ello este estudio se plantea describir la mortalidad y sus características más importantes en trabajadores del Instituto Nacional de Gestión Sanitaria, en el período del año 2000 al 2015. Metodología. Estudio descriptivo retrospectivo de la mortalidad en los trabajadores del INGESA en el período del año 2000 al 2015. La población fueron los trabajadores del INGESA fallecidos. Se utilizó como soporte informático el programa SPSS v21. El fichero consta de 8 variables, tales como sexo, edad, categoría profesional, causa de la muerte, fecha del deceso, etc. Resultados. Se notificaron 18 muertos, siendo la media de edad 51,67 años con desviación típica +/- 10,91 años. El 72,2% fueron hombres. La categoría profesional con mayor incidencia de mortalidad fueron los médicos con 44,4%, luego celadores y personal administrativo 16,75% respectivamente. La causa de muerte más frecuente fueron las neoplasias (44,4%) seguido de los ictus 22,2% y los suicidios 11,1%. El año con más fallecidos ha sido el 2014. Conclusiones: El registro adecuado de la mortalidad en los servicios de prevención de riesgos laborales, permite observar las enfermedades predominantes y en base a esos datos establecer medidas preventivas adecuadas para controlar eficientemente la salud de forma colectiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;26(2): 121-126, jun. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165330</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de la mortalidad en trabajadores del Instituto Nacional de Gestión Sanitaria (INGESA). Período del año 2000 al 2015</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50219</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28637</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28403^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
