<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048676</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Organic pathology caused by synthesis drugs</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The term of synthesis drugs makes reference to a    heterogeneous group of substances with important    differences in their chemical composition and/or in    the effects they produce, and they may be either    stimulant or anaesthetic substances, with a great    spectrum or variability in their psychoactive effects.    The perception of these drugs as safe and harmless    has make that they were able to reach an important    peak between the young population in the last    years for their utilisation with recreational aims but    their use can lead to a high number of psychiatric    and organic complications. The toxic dose is in    the rage of the used as recreational. The worst    risk of these drugs is due to the ignorance of the    substances that are being taken, the dose given and    the variability of the individual response to them. It    has to be added to these risks, the high frequency    of consumption among them and with other drugs,    mainly tobacco, alcohol, cannabis, cocaine and    hallucinogens. Other factors that may cause an    influence in the damage caused are the surround    of consume (closed locals, high temperature&#133;) and    the particular characteristics of the consumer. To all    this it has to be added the increased risk of traffic    accidents related with changes in concentration and    perception (visual mainly) under their effects. At    this moment, it is demonstrated the capacity of this    group of substances to produce neurotoxicity and,    although we don&#146;t have definitive data to establish    their irreversible nature, the experimentation with    laboratory animals is showing more and more    evidence in this direction</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Martínez, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereiro Gómez, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fontela Vivanco, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El término drogas de síntesis hace referencia a    un grupo heterogéneo de sustancias muy dispares    en su composición química y/o en los efectos que    producen, pudiendo tratarse tanto de sustancias estimulantes    como anestésicas, con un amplio espectro    o variabilidad de efectos psicoactivos. La percepción    de estas sustancias como drogas seguras e inocuas    ha hecho que hayan alcanzado gran auge entre los    jóvenes en los últimos años para su utilización con    fines recreativos pero su consumo puede dar lugar    a gran número de complicaciones tanto orgánicas    como psiquiátricas. Las dosis tóxicas se encuentran    en el rango de las usadas como recreacionales.    El mayor riesgo de estas drogas viene dado por    el desconocimiento sobre las sustancias que se    están consumiendo, las dosis que se administran    y la variabilidad en la respuesta individual. A estos    riesgos hay que añadir la elevada frecuencia de    policonsumo entre ellas mismas y con otras drogas,    básicamente tabaco, alcohol, cannabis, cocaína y    alucinógenos. Otros factores que pueden intervenir    en los daños generados pueden venir condicionados    por el entorno de consumo (locales cerrados, elevada    temperatura &#133;) y las características particulares    del consumidor. A esto se suma el incremento de    riesgo de accidentes de tráfico relacionados con    alteraciones en la concentración y en la percepción    (principalmente visual) bajo sus efectos. Actualmente    está demostrada la capacidad de este grupo de    sustancias para producir neurotoxicidad y aunque no    contamos con datos definitivos para establecer su    carácter irreversible, la experimentación con animales    de laboratorio cada vez muestra más evidencias    en esta dirección</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);18(supl.1): 217-230, 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048676</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patología orgánica por drogas de síntesis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10819^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7170^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8877^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
