<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152248</identifier>
<setSpec>2173-4712</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fear, conformity and silence. Intimate partner violence in rural areas of Ecuador</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The situation of intimate partner violence in Latin America is a complex problem that has serious consequences for thousands of women. In this study the factors and dynamics involved in such violence in a context of small rural communities are analyzed. To do this from an ecological framework of analysis, we have developed a qualitative study in rural communities of the province of Imbabura, in Ecuador. Seven focus groups involving a total of 63 people were held. The results show: (i) the importance of community environment and interactions of victim and perpetrator to the family, neighborhood and police intervention; (ii) the way that the territory structure and state action affect the handling of situations of intimate partner violence, and (iii) the effects of the pressure exerted by the various members of the community can have on the victim and their ability to report the situation. Finally, the possibility that the identified factors can be explanatory and illuminating elements of the dynamics of violence in similar contexts to the case study is targeted (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Boira, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carbajosa, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La situación de la violencia dentro de la pareja en Latinoamérica es un problema complejo que provoca graves consecuencias para miles de mujeres. En este estudio se analizan los factores y dinámicas involucradas en este tipo de violencia en un contexto de pequeñas comunidades rurales. Para ello, a partir de un marco ecológico de análisis se ha desarrollado un estudio cualitativo en comunidades rurales de la provincia de Imbabura, en Ecuador. Se realizaron 7 grupos focales en los que participaron un total de 63 personas. Los resultados muestran: a) la importancia del entorno comunitario y de las interacciones de víctima y agresor con la familia, vecindario y agentes de intervención; b) la influencia de la estructura del territorio y la actuación del Estado en el manejo de las situaciones de violencia dentro de la pareja, y c) los efectos que la presión ejercida por los distintos miembros de la comunidad pueden tener para la víctima y sus opciones de denunciar la situación. Finalmente, se apunta la posibilidad de que los factores identificados puedan ser elementos explicativos y esclarecedores de las dinámicas de violencia en contextos similares al caso estudiado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Interv. psicosoc. (Internet);25(1): 9-17, abr. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152248</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Miedo, conformidad y silencio. La violencia en las relaciones de pareja en áreas rurales de Ecuador</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4552^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5342</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13564^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12797^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56155^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50239</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
