<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164478</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Benefits of acetylsalicylic acid in the recurrence of deep vein thrombosis of the lower limbs in patients over 70 years-old</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The risk of recurrence after an episode of deep vein thrombosis is between 7% and 20% in the 2 years after withdrawal of anticoagulants. The main objective of this article is to study the role of acetylsalicylic acid in the recurrence of deep vein thrombosis once the anticoagulation treatment has ended in patients of 70 years-old and over. Material and methods: A retrospective study was conducted on patients that presented with a first episode of lower limb deep vein thrombosis confirmed by Doppler-ultrasound between the period of January 2008 and December 2009. Their clinical charts were reviewed for the presence of recurrence in the three years following anticoagulation treatment whilst on outpatient follow-up, as well as whether they were on treatment with acetylsalicylic acid for any underlying disease. Results: The study included 246 patients, with a mean age of 78.7 years. The patients were divided into two groups: Group A (n = 106) consisted of patients who took acetylsalicylic acid; and Group B (n = 140) consisted of patients who did not take acetylsalicylic acid. Recurrence of deep vein thrombosis was observed in 28 patients (11.5%), 13 patients in Group A (12.3%) and 15 patients in Group B (10.7%), without observing any statistically significant differences (P = .70) Conclusions: In our population aged 70 years-old and over, it seems that the treatment with acetylsalicylic acid has no influence on deep vein thrombosis recurrence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martí Mestre, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vila Coll, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romera Villegas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riera Mestre, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Guiu, X</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El riesgo de recurrencia, después de un episodio de trombosis venosa profunda, está entre el 7-20% en los 2 años posteriores a la retirada de la anticoagulación. El objetivo de este trabajo es valorar el papel del ácido acetilsalicílico (AAS) en la recurrencia de trombosis venosa profunda, una vez finalizado el tratamiento anticoagulante en pacientes de 70 años o mayores, en nuestra población. Material y métodos: Se realizó un estudio retrospectivo de casos y controles de pacientes que presentaron un primer episodio de trombosis venosa profunda de miembros inferiores, confirmado por ecografía-Doppler, durante el período de enero de 2008 hasta diciembre de 2009. Se valoró, mediante revisión de historias clínicas, la presencia de recidiva en los 3 años siguientes al tratamiento anticoagulante mediante los controles en consultas externas, y la presencia o no de tratamiento con AAS por cualquier enfermedad de base. Resultados: Incluimos en el estudio un total de 246 pacientes con una media de edad de 78,7 años. Se dividieron los pacientes en 2 grupos, el grupo A (n = 106) formado por pacientes que tomaban AAS por cualquier enfermedad de base; y el grupo B (n = 140) formado por pacientes que no tomaban AAS. Se observó recidiva de trombosis venosa profunda en 28 pacientes del estudio (11,5%), registrándose 13 en el grupo A (12,3%) y 15 en el grupo B (10,7%), sin observarse diferencias estadísticamente significativas (p = 0,70). Conclusiones: En nuestra población mayor de 70 años, el tratamiento con AAS no parece disminuir la tasa de recidivas de trombosis venosa profunda (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;69(3): 162-166, mayo.-jun. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164478</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Beneficios del ácido acetilsalicílico en la recurrencia de trombosis venosa profunda de miembros inferiores en pacientes mayores de 70 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27951^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36500</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
