<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87801</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Developing a structured educational program on diabetes for pediatric patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Type 1 diabetes mellitus is a chronic disease that requires a complex treatmentand that generates changes in the patient&#146;s personal and family lifestyle. In orderto understand and self-manage the disease, the patient/family needs toacquire certain knowledge, skills and healthy habits. Structured educationalprograms must be available to facilitate the learning process and help patientsachieving these objectives. When those programs are designed for pediatricpatients objectives, material and activities must be adapted to patient&#146;s age aswell as the distinctive characteristics of childhood. To make sure that childrenare able to adequately self-manage their diabetes by the time they reach adulthood,parents/tutors&#146; attitude and training are of fundamental importance, aswell as providing progressive transfer of responsibilities to them(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Armengol, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Losada, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La diabetes mellitus tipo 1 es una enfermedad crónica que requiere un tratamientocomplejo y que genera cambios en el estilo de vida personal y familiar.El paciente/familia debe adquirir una serie de conocimientos, habilidades yconductas saludables que le permitan comprender su enfermedad y autogestionarla.Para ayudar a conseguir estos objetivos, es necesario disponer de programaseducativos estructurados que faciliten el aprendizaje. Cuando estosprogramas están diseñados para aplicarse en la edad pediátrica, los objetivos,el material y las actividades deben adecuarse a la edad del paciente y a lascaracterísticas propias de la infancia. Para conseguir que el niño llegue a laetapa adulta sabiendo autogestionar correctamente su diabetes, es muy importantela actitud y formación de los padres/tutores, así como la habilidad enel traspaso progresivo de responsabilidades(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;26(3): 203-207, mayo-jun. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87801</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desarrollo de un programa educativo estructurado en diabetes para pacientes pediátricos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30653</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2707^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2707^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
