<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137468</identifier>
<setSpec>2174-0852</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">State, trait anxiety and selective attention differences in Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) subtypes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">One of the disorders that most affects school performance is Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD). The criteria established by DSM distinguish three subtypes: inattentive, hyperactive-impulsive and combined. However, the expression of this disorder can be altered by its association with other disorders such as anxiety. The main goals of this study were to determine whether different patterns of attention (selective and concentration) and anxiety (state and trait anxiety) emerge from ADHD subtypes, and analyze how anxiety predicts the performance of students with ADHD in a selective attention task. The sample was made up of 220 children (6-12 years) divided into four groups: control group (n = 56), inattentive subtype (n = 54), hyperactive-impulsive subtype (n = 53), and combined subtype (n = 57). The results indicated that the groups differed significantly in the attention variables, and in state and trait anxiety. Multiple group comparisons revealed that the combined subtype exhibited higher trait anxiety, whereas the inattentive subtype showed more state anxiety. Additionally, trait anxiety predicted the students&#146; performance in the concentration variable of the attention task. These results suggest a novel path of significant interest concerning objective and reliable diagnostic assessment of ADHD (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alvarez-García, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Trinidad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cueli, Marisol</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Castro, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Celestino</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Uno de los trastornos que más afecta al rendimiento escolar es el Trastorno por Déficit de Atención con Hiperactividad (TDAH). El criterio establecido por el DSM diferencia tres subtipos: inatento, hiperactivo-impulsivo y combinado. Sin embargo, el perfil de este trastorno podría verse alterado por la asociación con otros como la ansiedad. El objetivo de esta investigación es determinar si hay diferentes patrones de atención (selectiva y sostenida) y ansiedad (estado y rasgo) en los tres subtipos de TDAH. Además, el objetivo es analizar cómo la ansiedad predice el rendimiento de los estudiantes con TDAH en una tarea de atención selectiva. La muestra estaba formada por 220 estudiantes (6-12 años): 56 en el grupo control, 54 con TDAH-Inatento, 53 con TDAH-Hiperactivo impulsivo y 56 con el subtipo combinado. Los resultados obtenidos mostraron que los cuatro grupos resultaban significativamente diferentes en las variables atencionales y en los niveles de ansiedad estado y rasgo. Al mismo tiempo, la ansiedad rasgo predijo el rendimiento en la variable de concentración analizada. Los resultados revelan un nuevo patrón de gran interés de cara a la evaluación diagnóstica objetiva y fiable en el TDAH (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int. j. clin. health psychol. (Internet);15(2): 105-112, mayo-ago. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137468</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias en ansiedad estado-rasgo y en atención selectiva en los subtipos de TDAH</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14876</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1294</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
