<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111462</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7113</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Presence of anticoagulant rodenticide residues in five predatory birds species of the Canary Islands, 2002-2011</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Anticoagulant rodenticide (AR) levels were studied in liver of 61 dead raptors of five of the eleven species of the Canary Islands. The animals were delivered to our laboratory from the Centro de Recuperación de Fauna Silvestre de Tafira (Gran Canaria). Anticoagulant residues were detected in 42 (69%) of the studied animals, but only 1 may have died by AR poisoning according to the clinical information, necropsy findings and toxicological analysis. Of the studied raptors Tyto alba and Accipiter nisus were the species with more frequency and higher levels of anticoagulants (85% and 89%). Residues of 5 anticoagulants were detected, all of them of second generation, being the most frequently detected bromadiolone, brodifacoum and difenacoum. A large number of samples (63%) presented more than one residue of anticoagulants in their livers, and we have found as much as 4 different residues in one animal. It was remarkable that most of the animals that had suffered polytraumatism by collision presented residues of anticoagulants, and that species such as the hawk that mainly eat birds frequently presented anticoagulant residues. The results of this study suggest that the high use of anticoagulant rodenticides in the natural environment involves their incorporation into the food chain, and this can affect wildlife species in which these products may cause side effects. This means that the application of anticoagulant rodenticides in open spaces poses a threat to the conservation status of biodiversity in the Canary Islands (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Boada, L. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luzardo, O. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calabuig, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estévez-López, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zumbado, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Hernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Suárez, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Henríquez-Hernández, L. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almeida González, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camacho, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se determinó la presencia de residuos de rodenticidas anticoagulantes por cromatografía de líquidos acoplada a espectrometría de masas de triple cuadrupolo en el hígado de 61 aves rapaces muertas provenientes del Centro de Recuperación de Fauna Silvestre de Tafira (Gran Canaria), pertenecientes a 5 especies de las 11 presentes en el archipiélago canario. Se encontraron residuos en 42 animales (69%) si bien en sólo 1 de ellos se consideró la intoxicación por rodenticidas como causa primaria de muerte, según los datos clínicos, analíticos y de necropsia. De las rapaces estudiadas, fueron las especies Tyto alba y Accipiter nisus las que más frecuentemente presentaron residuos de anticoagulantes (85% y 89% respectivamente). Se detectaron residuos de 5 anticoagulantes, todos ellos de segunda generación, siendo la bromadiolona las más frecuentemente detectada, seguida del brodifacoum y del difenacoum. Un elevado número de las muestras positivas (63%) presentó más de un residuo de anticoagulantes en su hígado, habiéndose encontrado mezclas de hasta 4 productos diferentes. Llamó la atención que la mayoría de los animales que ingresaron en el centro de recuperación por politraumatismo por colisión presentaba residuos de uno o varios anticoagulantes, así como que rapaces que se alimentan principalmente de pájaros también presentaron frecuentemente residuos de estos compuestos. Los resultados de este estudio sugieren que el elevado uso de rodenticidas anticoagulantes en el medio natural implica su incorporación a la cadena trófica, viéndose afectadas especies de fauna silvestre en las que estos productos podrían producir efectos adversos. Esto implica que la aplicación de rodenticidas anticoagulantes en espacios abiertos supone una amenaza para el estado de conservación de la biodiversidad de las Islas Canarias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. toxicol;29(1): 15-19, ene.-jun. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111462</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Presencia de rodenticidas anticoagulantes en cinco especies de aves rapaces de las Islas Canarias, 2003-2011</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23417^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2902^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2850^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23417^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15268^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8573^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24262^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8573^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35510</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2902^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10764^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35512</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7480^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2902^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10764^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1741^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
