<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136541</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Serological markers of fibrosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Liver biopsy has classically been considered the gold standard to evaluate the degree of fibrosis, since it allows direct measurement of this entity. However, this technique carries an inherent risk of complications and observer variability and technical limitations can provoke sampling errors, all of which has prompted the search for alternative, noninvasive methods. The use of routine clinical laboratory tests has been investigated and various indexes that combine indirect serological markers have been developed and validated. These indexes are useful, low-cost, noninvasive tests to detect significant fibrosis or cirrhosis. Direct serological markers are those that reflect changes in the composition of the extracellular matrix. Several studies have analyzed the utility of these markers (either individually or combined with other direct and indirect markers) in the detection of the severity and progression of liver fibrosis and in the follow-up of changes related to antiviral therapy. In the last few years, imaging tests based on the measurement of liver stiffness, such as FibroScan or acoustic radiation force impulse (ARFI), have been found to be rapid and reproducible methods to evaluate liver fibrosis. Recently, the results obtained by combining distinct serological markers and imaging techniques have shown a higher diagnostic yield and this strategy seems promising. The present article reviews the most widely discussed noninvasive markers, the most recent alternatives, and the perspectives for their use in clinical practice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Varo, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La biopsia hepática se ha considerado clásicamente como el estándar de referencia para evaluar el grado de fibrosis, ya que permite una medida directa de la fibrosis. Sin embargo, el riesgo inherente de complicaciones, limitaciones técnicas que provocan errores de muestreo y la variabilidad en las apreciaciones entre diferentes observadores han estimulado la búsqueda de métodos no invasivos que puedan reemplazar a la biopsia en el futuro. Se ha investigado el uso de pruebas de laboratorio clínico de rutina, y se han desarrollado y validado diferentes índices que combinan estos marcadores serológicos indirectos como herramientas no invasivas útiles y de bajo coste para detectar fibrosis significativa o cirrosis. Los marcadores serológicos directos son los que reflejan cambios en la composición de la matriz extracelular. Se han realizado estudios que analizan su rendimiento de forma individual, o en combinación con otros marcadores directos e indirectos en la detección de la gravedad y progresión de la fibrosis hepática, y en el seguimiento de los cambios relacionados con el tratamiento antiviral. En los últimos años, técnicas de imagen basadas en la medición de la rigidez hepática, como Fibroscan o ARFI, se han convertido en métodos rápidos y reproducibles para evaluar la fibrosis hepática. Recientemente, los resultados obtenidos combinando diferentes marcadores serológicos y técnicas de imagen muestran un mayor rendimiento diagnóstico y aparecen como una estrategia prometedora. En este artículo se revisan los marcadores bioquímicos no invasivos más referenciados, las alternativas más recientes y las perspectivas para su uso en la práctica clínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;35(supl.2): 10-16, dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136541</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Marcadores serológicos de fibrosis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
