<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80020</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Massive intravascular hemolysis secondary to sepsis due to Clostridium perfringens</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Massive hemolysis secondary to sepsis caused by Clostridium perfringens is a rare entity but appears fairlyoften in the literature. In nearly all published reports, theclinical course is rapid and fatal. We describe the case of a75-year-old woman with diabetes who was admitted withsymptoms consistent with acute cholecystitis. Deterioratinghemodynamics and laboratory findings were consistentwith intravascular hemolysis, coagulation disorder, andrenal failure. Gram-positive bacilli of the Clostridiumspecies were detected in blood along with worseningindicators of hemolysis. In spite of antibiotic and surgicaltreatment, hemodynamic support and infusion of bloodproducts, the patient continued to decline and died in thepostoperative recovery unit 14 hours after admission.Mortality ranges from 70% to 100% in sepsis due toClostridium perfringens, and risk of death is greater ifmassive hemolysis is present, as in the case we report. Onlya high degree of clinical suspicion leading to early diagnosisand treatment can improve the prognosis. This bacteriumshould therefore be considered whenever severe sepsis andhemolysis coincide(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Camba Rodríguez, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Cabanoa, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agulla Budiño, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarmiento Penidea, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pita Zapataa, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bautista Guilléna, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hemólisis masiva asociada a la sepsis por Clostridiumperfringens, aunque infrecuente, ha sido descritaen un número significativo de casos clínicos. En casitodos ellos la evolución del cuadro ha sido rápidamentefatal. Presentamos el caso de una mujer de 75 años diabéticaingresada por un cuadro compatible con colecistitisaguda que sufrió un deterioro hemodinámico y datosanalíticos compatibles con hemólisis intravascular, coagulopatíae insuficiencia renal. Se detectaron bacilosgram positivo tipo clostridio en sangre y un marcadoempeoramiento de los datos de hemólisis. A pesar deltratamiento antibiótico y quirúrgico y del soporte hemodinámicoy hemoterápico, la paciente evolucionó negativamente,falleciendo a las 14 horas de su ingreso en reanimación.La mortalidad de la sepsis por Clostridiumperfringens llega a ser del 70-100%, sobre todo si se asociaa una hemólisis masiva como ocurrió en nuestrocaso. Sólo un alto grado de sospecha clínica que determineun diagnóstico y tratamiento precoz puede evitar elpronóstico tan infausto. Por ello deberíamos pensar enesta bacteria ante toda sepsis grave asociada a hemólisis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;57(5): 314-316, mayo 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80020</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hemólisis masiva intravascular secundaria a sepsis por Clostridium perfringens</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4272^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3042^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38041^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3041^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
