<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-SMB-14098</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychosocial risk factors as predictors of occupational well-being: A SEM analysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Antecedents: Theoretical approaches on occupational well-being have identified several intervening variables such as satisfaction, motivation and occupational stress. Psychosocial risk factors at work have an influence on these variables as well as on workers' health. Objective: The aim of this study was to validate a model of occupational well-being by assessing perceived psychosocial risk factors in a sample of 865 workers from different service sector businesses by means of the DECORE questionnaire. Subsequently, several confirmatory factor analyses (maximum likelihood estimators) on the different analyzed variables were performed. Results: On having evaluated psychosocial risk factors and occupational well-being, the indexes of adjustment turned out to be appropriate. All the latent variables were included in the same model in order to gather information on the underlying relationships between them. The fit indices were also suitable. Conclusions: Workers' perception of psychosocial risk factors was a predictor of occupational well-being, defined as high levels of satisfaction and motivation together with low levels of perceived stress (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escorial Martín, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-García, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Talavera-Velasco, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luceño-Moreno, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: Las aproximaciones teóricas sobre el bienestar laboral lo identifican con variables como la satisfacción, la motivación y el estrés. A su vez, en estas variables influyen los factores de riesgo psicosocial del entorno laboral, los cuales se relacionan con la salud de los trabajadores. Objetivo: El objetivo de este estudio fue validar un modelo de bienestar laboral a partir de la evaluación de la percepción de los factores de riesgo psicosocial. Se aplicó el cuestionario DECORE a 865 trabajadores de distintas empresas del sector terciario en la Comunidad de Madrid. Posteriormente, se efectuaron diversos análisis factoriales confirmatorios (procedimiento máxima verosimilitud) sobre las distintas variables realizadas. Resultados: Tanto al evaluar los factores de riesgo psicosocial como el bienestar laboral, los índices de ajuste resultan apropiados. Todas las variables latentes se reúnen en un mismo modelo para analizar las relaciones subyacentes entre ellas. Los índices de ajuste son, asimismo, adecuados. Conclusiones: La percepción que tiene el trabajador de los factores de riesgo psicosocial resultó ser un predictor de su bienestar laboral, entendido como altos niveles de satisfacción y  motivación, y bajos niveles de estrés percibido (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;23(2/3): 66-70, jul.-dic. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-SMB-14098</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores de riesgo psicosocial como predictores del bienestar laboral: un análisis SEM</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
