<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79515</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">What research tells us about loss of attachment figures in childhood</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The central question explored in this paper is how much is currently understood the consequences of loss of an attachment relationship in childhood . drawing upon several indicative bodies of research findings, it is suggested that social orienting response mechanism may play an important but, as yet not well understood, role in promoting  children´s recovery from loss. It is also argued that, although simple stage models can be useful as guides, some may need revision in light of new research on young children´s understanding of death and of the importance of ´continuing bonds´ (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barrett, Helen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen: el interrogante clave que aborda este trabajo es cuánto se comprende en la actualidad sobre las consecuencias de la pérdida de una relación de apego en la infancia. En base a diversas investigaciones se sugiere que los mecanismos de repuesta de orientación social podrían desempeñar un importante rol, todavía poco esquemáticos de etapas pueden ser útiles como guía, algunos pueden precisar una revisión a la luz de las últimas investigaciones sobre la comprensión de la muerte durante la infancia y la importancia de los `vínculos continuados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(12): 27-38, nov. 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79515</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Que nos dice la investigación sobre la pérdida de figuras de apego en la infancia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2698^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9954</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200811</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
