<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142348</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Management of the subcutaneous way of administration in paliative care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The population ageing, the increase of chronic-degenerative diseases, together with a higher life expectancy, have led to an increasing number of patients who require palliative care. The administration way of choice to treat symptoms in these patients will be oral, but certain circumstances may render this impossible, making it necessary to resort to other ways. The subcutaneous way represents an alternative option in these situations, as it is a simple, safe, and easy to use technique. The objective of this paper is to contribute towards the good use of this technique and, therefore, to a better control of symptoms, describing the techniques, the advantages and disadvantages of its use in Palliative Care, indications and contraindications, potential complications, insertion sites and technique, subsequent care, as well as the most widely used types of administration and drugs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Yáñez Fernández, Vania</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El envejecimiento de la población, el aumento de enfermedades crónico-degenerativas, junto con una mayor esperanza de vida hacen que cada día el número de pacientes que requieren cuidados paliativos sea mayor. La vía de elección para tratar los síntomas en estos pacientes es la oral, pero ciertas circunstancias pueden imposibilitar su uso, siendo necesario recurrir a otras vías. La vía subcutánea supone una alternativa en estas situaciones al tratarse de una técnica sencilla, segura y de fácil manejo. El propósito de este trabajo es contribuir al buen uso de esta técnica y, por lo tanto, a un mejor control de los síntomas, describiendo la técnica, las ventajas y desventajas de su uso en cuidados paliativos, indicaciones y contraindicaciones, las posibles complicaciones, lugares y técnica de inserción, los cuidados posteriores, así como los tipos de administración y fármacos más empleados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;18(8): 49-53, oct. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142348</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo de la vía subcutánea en cuidados paliativos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53227^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55419^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55419^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53228^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53228^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53228^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7453^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53228^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55419^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30797^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55419^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
