<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-AOT-2183</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Description of postauthorisation observational prospective studies with drugs in the valencian region between 2010 and 2015. Factors associated with their authorisation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Postauthorisation observational studies are crucial source of information on drug effectiveness and safety. The objectives of this work were to describe the characteristics of the postauthorisation observational prospective studies (EPA-SP) for which authorisation was requested in the Valencian region, as well as to explore which factors influenced the aforementioned authorisation. Methods: We performed a retrospective analytical study comprising all the EPA-SP for which authorisation was requested in the Valencian region between 2010 and 2015.The variables associated to the studies (e.g., objectives, studied drug, target disease) as well as those concerning the authorisation process itself (e.g., authorisation status, reason for authorisation refusal, current status of the study) were obtained from relevant databases. The analysis was divided into descriptive and analytical stages. Results: We included a total of 249 studies, out of which 192 (77, 1%) aimed at estimating effectiveness or quality of life. The most frequent types of drugs involved in the studies were the antineoplastic and immunomodulating agents (42%). Only 57% of the studies were granted authorisation, with prescription induction and unusual practice being the most common causes for refusal (40.1% and 39.3%, respectively). The authorisation was linked to the diagnosis (circulatory system OR 10,7, IC95% 2,3 to 49,1), ATC L group (OR 4,2, IC95% 1,9 to 49,1) as well as to whether it had been advocated by the industry (OR 0,5, IC95% 0,3 to 0,9). Conclusion: Given the importance of having information on effectiveness and safety in usual practice, it is a priority for EPA-SP to be directed towards these aims and to promote independent research (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grau Rubio, María Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Martínez, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zapater Hernández, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Pajares, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo María, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: Los estudios posautorización observacionales son una fuente de información clave sobre efectividad y seguridad de los medicamentos. Los objetivos del estudio fueron describir las características de los estudios observacionales de seguimiento prospectivo (EPA-SP) que solicitaron autorización en la Comunitat Valenciana (CV) y explorar qué factores se asociaron con su autorización. Métodos: Se realizó estudio observacional analítico retrospectivo, en el que se incluyeron todos los EPA-SP que solicitaron autorización en la CV desde 2010 hasta 2015. A partir de las bases de datos de la Dirección General de Farmacia y Productos Sanitarios y GESTO se obtuvieron variables referentes al estudio (objetivos, medicamento estudiado, enfermedad diana, etc) y referentes al procedimiento de autorización (autorización, motivo de no autorización y estado actual del estudio). El análisis se organizó en una fase descriptiva y otra analítica mediante regresión logística con variable dependiente la autorización. Resultados: Fueron incluidos un total de 249 estudios, de los que 192 (77,1%) estaban diseñados para estimar efectividad o calidad de vida. Los medicamentos más frecuentemente estudiados fueron los agentes antineoplásicos e inmunomoduladores (42%). Sólo consiguieron la autorización el 57%, siendo las causas más frecuente de denegación la inducción a la prescripción (40,1%) y la práctica no habitual (39,3%). La autorización se asoció con el diagnóstico (aparato circulatorio OR 10,7, IC95% 2,3 a 49,1), grupo ATC L (OR 4,2, IC95% 1,9 a 49,1) y el haber sido promovidos por la industria (OR 0,5, IC95% 0,3 a 0,9). Conclusión: Dada la importancia de contar con información sobre efectividad y seguridad en la práctica habitual, es prioritario que los EPA-SP sean orientados a estos fines y que se potencie la investigación independiente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;91: 0-0, 2017. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-AOT-2183</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Descripción de los estudios posautorización observacionales prospectivos con medicamentos en la Comunitat Valenciana entre 2010 y 2015. Análisis de los factores relacionados con su autorización</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
