<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61432</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Incidence of acute myocardial infarction in the Spanish epic cohort</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. There is some evidence that Mediterraneandiet reduces risk of ischemic heart disease, and this is to beinvestigated in the Spanish cohort of the European ProspectiveInvestigation into Cancer and Nutrition (EPIC). In thispaper we present the incidence of acute myocardial infarction(AMI) in four EPIC Spanish cohorts.Method. Incidence cases were ascertained in EPIC cohortduring the follow up period (from recruitment to the end of2004), by means of self-report questionnaires, hospital morbidityand mortality registries, and population AMI registries.Analysis was restricted to aged 45 to 74. The presentstudy included data from 13,704 women and 19,410 men,after excluding a priori participants with prevalent AMI. Agestandardized incidence rate for each cohort was estimatedand compared with the available population rates.Results. The Median duration of follow-up was 9.3 years, yieldinga total of 297,704 person-years. 391 men and 99 womenpresented AMI in the four cohorts studied. Age standardizedAMI rates in men of the EPIC cohorts go from the lowest 302(CI: 268-335) per 100.000 person-year of Gipuzkoa to the highest330 (CI: 293-367) of Navarra. Women in Navarra presentedthe lowest AMI incidence with 60 (CI: 43-77) per 100,000 andthe highest was observed in Murcia (114, CI: 91-137). The AMIincidence in all EPIC centres are close to the population incidencerates and in any case these are within the EPIC 95% CI.Conclusions. The comparison of incidence in EPIC with populationrates shows very good agreement for acute myocardial infarction(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marín, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amiano, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, C. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larrañaga, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berenguer, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chirlaque, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dorronsoro, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ardanaz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barricarte, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quirós, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Basterretxea, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castilla, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tormo, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agudo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antedecentes. Existen evidencias que sugieren que la dietamediterránea reduce el riesgo de enfermedad cardiaca isquémicay esta asociación va a ser investigada en la cohorteespañola del &#147;Estudio europeo sobre cáncer y nutrición&#148;(EPIC). En este artículo se presenta la incidencia de infartoagudo de miocardio (IAM) en 4 de las cohortes españolas.Método. Los casos incidentes de IAM fueron identificadosen la cohorte EPIC durante el periodo de seguimiento (delreclutamiento a finales de 2004), mediante un cuestionarioautorreportado, el registro de altas hospitalarias y de mortalidady registros poblacionales de IAM. El análisis se centróen el grupo de 45 a 74 años de edad. El estudio incluyó cuatrocohortes compuestas de 13.704 mujeres and 19.410 hombres,tras la exclusión a priori de participantes con IAM prevalentes.Se estimó la tasa de incidencia ajustada por edad paracada cohorte, y se comparó con las tasas poblacionales disponibles.Resultados. La duración mediana del seguimiento fue de9,3 años, que aportó un total de 297.704 personas-año. 391hombres and 99 mujeres presentaron IAM en las 4 cohortesestudiadas. Las tasas ajustadas por edad de IAM, en hombres,en las cohortes EPIC se movieron entre los 302 (CI:268-335) casos por 100.000 personas-año de Gipuzkoa, lamenor tasa observada, hasta los 330 (CI: 293-367) de Navarra.Las mujeres navarras presentaron las tasas más bajasde IAM con unas cifras de 60 (CI: 43-77) casos por 100.000,mientras que las mujeres murcianas presentaron las tasasmás altas (114, CI: 91-137). La incidencia de IAM en todaslas regiones EPIC fué similar a la incidencia poblacional conocidade dichas regiones, o bien se mantienen dentro delintervalo de confianza la 95%.Conclusiones. La incidencia de la cohorte EPIC muestragran concordancia con las tasas poblaciones disponiblespara el IAM(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;32(1): 51-59, ene.-abr. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61432</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incidencia de infarto agudo de miocardio en la cohorte EPIC España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50343</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
