<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138859</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prognostic benefit of beta-blockers after acute coronary syndrome with preserved systolic function. Still relevant today?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. The scientific evidence for using beta-blockers after acute coronary syndrome stems from studies conducted in the days before coronary revascularization and in patients with ventricular dysfunction. The aim of this study was to analyze the current long-term prognostic benefit of beta-blockers in patients with acute coronary syndrome and preserved left ventricular ejection fraction. Methods. We conducted a retrospective cohort study of 3236 patients with acute coronary syndrome and left ventricular ejection fraction &amp;#8805; 50%. We performed a propensity-matched analysis to draw up two groups of 555 patients paired according to whether or not they had been treated with beta-blockers. The prognostic value of beta-blockers to predict mortality during follow-up was analyzed using Cox regression. Results. During the follow-up (median, 5.2 years), 506 patients (15.6%) died. Patients treated with beta-blockers (n = 2277 [70.4%]) had a lower mortality rate (11.6% vs 25.2%; P &lt; .001). After propensity score matching, we found that mortality during follow-up was still lower in the beta-blocker group (14.4% vs 18.9%; P = .020). Therefore, this treatment was an independent protective factor after adjusting for confounding variables in the multivariate Cox regression analysis (hazard ratio = 0.64; 95% confidence interval, 0.48-0.87; P = .004). Conclusions. Beta-blocker treatment in patients with acute coronary syndrome and preserved left ventricular ejection fraction is associated with lower long-term mortality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castiñeira-Busto, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Acuña, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bouzas-Cruz, Noelia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Raposeiras-Roubín, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Ferreiro, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña Gil, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Juanatey, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-López, Andrea</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abu-Assi, Emad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Redondo-Diéguez, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. La evidencia científica para el uso de bloqueadores beta tras un síndrome coronario agudo radica en estudios previos a la era de la revascularización coronaria o en pacientes con disfunción ventricular. Con este trabajo se pretende analizar en la era actual el valor pronóstico a largo plazo de los bloqueadores beta en pacientes con síndrome coronario agudo y fracción de eyección del ventrículo izquierdo conservada. Métodos. Estudio de cohortes retrospectivo que incluyó a 3.236 pacientes con síndrome coronario agudo y fracción de eyección del ventrículo izquierdo &amp;#8805; 50%. Se realizó un análisis mediante propensity score y después un emparejamiento basado en él, con lo que se obtuvieron dos grupos de 555 pacientes emparejados según fueran tratados con bloqueadores beta o no. El valor pronóstico de mortalidad durante el seguimiento con los bloqueadores beta se analizó mediante regresión de Cox. Resultados. Durante el seguimiento (mediana, 5,2 años), murieron 506 pacientes (15,6%). Los pacientes tratados con bloqueadores beta (n = 2.277 [70,4%]) tuvieron menos mortalidad (el 11,6 frente al 25,2%; p &lt; 0,001). Tras emparejar por propensity score, la mortalidad en el seguimiento continuó siendo más baja en el grupo de bloqueadores beta (el 14,4 frente al 18,9%; p = 0,020), por lo que dicha terapia resulta un factor protector independiente tras ajustar por variables confusoras en el análisis multivariable de regresión de Cox (hazard ratio = 0,64; intervalo de confianza del 95%, 0,48-0,87; p = 0,004). Conclusiones. Tratar con bloqueadores beta a pacientes con síndrome coronario agudo y fracción de eyección del ventrículo izquierdo preservada se asocia con menos mortalidad a largo plazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;68(7): 585-591, jul. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138859</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿En la era actual existe beneficio pronóstico del tratamiento con bloqueadores beta tras un síndrome coronario agudo con función sistólica conservada?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d322^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52438</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d322^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13706^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9396^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d322^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31983^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
