<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114650</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spiritual needs in palliative care. Users assesment and experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction Attention to the spiritual needs of patients and caregivers is important in the end of life quality care process. This study aims to assess perception of spiritual care received by patients and main caregivers in a palliative care unit, and to compare this between groups: patient, caregiver during admission, and caregiver in follow-up. Method A descriptive comparative cross-sectional study, using an ad hoc questionnaire (items on emotional state, received spiritual attention and other resources), on a population of 219 users of a palliative care unit with a spiritual care service. Entry criteria: at least two days of admission, a first contact with the spiritual care provider, without cognitive impairment, agreement to participate, and able to respond. Participants A total 145 users were preselected, with a final sample of 66 people (45.5% response rate); 56 (84.8%) were oncology patients; 38 (57.6%) women and 28 (42.4%) men. The mean age was 76 years (standard deviation, 9). Response rate; 36.7% patients (11), caregivers of admitted patients, 44.9% (22) and caregivers of follow up patients, 50% (33). Reasons for rejection: 83.5% (66) refusal to participate, 8.9% (10) not contacted, and 3.8% (3) family did not allow it. Results Spiritual care helped 88% to feel hopeful, 83% comforted, 79.1% to find meaning, and 73.4% to understand the meaning. Al most all (95.2%) valued spiritual care in disease as necessary. Conclusion Although the attempt to quantify the spiritual care substantially reduces its value, our data support the hypothesis that appropriate spiritual care improves the quality of the end of life stage experience and coping with death, and positively influences patient and family members (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gil Vela, Milagros</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermejo Higuera, José Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano González, Bernardino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villacieros Durbán, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción Es importante la atención de las necesidades espirituales de pacientes y familiares para vivir un proceso de final de la vida de calidad. El objetivo del estudio es evaluar cómo perciben los pacientes y los cuidadores principales de una unidad de cuidados paliativos la atención espiritual recibida y compararla entre grupos: paciente, cuidador durante ingreso y cuidador en seguimiento. Método Descriptivo comparativo de corte transversal mediante cuestionario ad hoc (ítems sobre estado emocional, medida de atención espiritual recibida y otros recursos), sobre una población de 219 usuarios de una unidad de cuidados paliativos donde existe servicio de atención espiritual. Criterios de entrada: al menos 2 días de ingreso y un primer contacto con el agente espiritual, sin deterioro cognitivo, que aceptara participar y que pudiera responder. Participantes Se preseleccionaron 145 usuarios, la muestra final fue de 66 usuarios (tasa de respuesta 45,5%), 56 (84,8%) pacientes oncológicos; 38 (57,6%) mujeres y 28 (42,4%) hombres. Media de edad 76 años (desviación típica 9). Tasa de respuesta; pacientes 36,7% (11), cuidadores de ingresados 44,9% (22) y cuidadores en seguimiento 50% (33). Razones de rechazo: 83,5% (66) negativa a participar, 8,9% (10) no contactados y 3,8% (3) el familiar no lo permite. Resultados La atención espiritual ayuda al 88% a sentirse esperanzado, al 83% confortado, al 79,1% a encontrar significado y al 73,4% a comprender el sentido. El 95,2% valora la atención espiritual necesaria en la enfermedad. Conclusión Aunque el intento de cuantificar la atención espiritual reduce sustancialmente su valor nuestros datos apoyan la hipótesis de que una atención espiritual adecuada mejora la calidad de la vivencia de la fase terminal de la vida y el afrontamiento de la muerte influyendo positivamente sobre el paciente y los familiares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;20(3): 93-102, jul.-sept. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114650</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Atención espiritual en cuidados paliativos. Valoración y vivencia de los usuarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d36317</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33200^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
