<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119920</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Limitation of HIF-1&amp;#945; with pentoxifillyne on renal tubular ischemia result of hiperoxaluria and ESWL</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: To evaluate hypoxia-inducible factor 1 subunit &amp;#945; (HIF-1&amp;#945;) expression during the performance of extracorporeal shock wave lithotripsy (ESWL) and to investigate the effects of pentoxyphylline on HIF-1&amp;#945; expression. METHODS: One hundred New Zealand Albino rabbit were used in the study divided in 5 groups. There were 20 rabbits in each group. The groups were divided in two parts: early (7 days) and late period (14 days) according to follow up duration. Immunohistochemical analyses were performed using nuclear staining to show HIF-1&amp;#945; expression in rabbit renal tissue sample. RESULTS: HIF-1&amp;#945; expression was higher in rabbits undergoing ESWL (group 4). In the hyperoxaluria group taking pentoxyphylline before ESWL (group 5), HIF-1&amp;#945; expression was lower in both early and late period subgroups (p &lt; 0.05). CONCLUSION: In this study we evaluated HIF-1&amp;#945; expression and showed that ESWL may cause renal cell injury. Our results suggest that pentoxyphylline, as a circulatory regulator agent, may prevent renal cell injury induced by ESWL (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Karakok, Metin</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seckiner, Ilker</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Celik, Mehmet</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Erturhan, Sakip</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bayrak, Omer</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Valorar la expresión del factor 1, subunidad &amp;#945; (HIF-1&amp;#945;) inducible por hipoxia realizando litotricia extracorpórea con ondas de choque (LEOC), e investigar los efectos de la pentoxifilina en la expresión de HIF-1&amp;#945;. MÉTODOS: En este estudio, se utilizaron un total de cien conejos albinos de Nueva Zelanda y se dividieron en 5 grupos, cada grupo formado por 20 conejos. Los grupos fueron divididos en subgrupos: período corto (7 días) y período largo (14 días) de acuerdo con la duración del seguimiento. Se realizaron análisis inmuno-histoquímicos usando tinción nuclear para mostrar la expresión de HIF-1&amp;#945; en la muestra de tejido renal del conejo. RESULTADOS: La expresión HIF -1&amp;#945; fue más alta en los conejos a los que se les realizó LEOC (grupo 4). El grupo hiperoxalúrico, al que se le administró pentoxifilina antes de la LEOC tuvo una expresión de HIF -1&amp;#945; más baja en ambos subgrupos, períodos corto y largo (grupo 5) (p &lt; 0,05). CONCLUSIÓN: En este estudio se valoró la expresión de HIF -1&amp;#945; y se puso de manifiesto que la LEOC puede causar lesiones de las células renales. Nuestros resultados sugieren que la pentoxifilina como un agente regulador circulatorio puede prevenir el daño celular renal inducido por la LEOC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;67(2): 191-197, mar. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119920</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Limitación de HIF-1&amp;#945; con pentoxifilina en isquemia tubular renal resultado de hiperoxaluria y ESWL</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10625^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7678^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4255</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10919^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7862^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19612^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19195^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34410^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
