<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101631</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-3334</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A protocol of good practice in intervention with children with conduct disorder in schools</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article argues, from the standpoint of Guidance Teams involved in school and Primary Education and based on the authors' experience, a way to address behavior problems presented by some students. The starting point takes into account the contributions of lapsicología laperspectiva evolutionary behavioral systems. The school is part of the set of related systems where these problems occur and often generate added stress and challenge for the professionals involved. Raised here a series of actions and procedures that the authors have named "best practices" designed to count and to involve the usual formal structures of the centers in order to properly channel the solution of these problems, collaborate with other systems - families, health care, social services, and try to minimize side effects that often occur when to intervene. It concludes with the necessary cooperation between all csitemas lso involved in trying to provide alternatives to the difficulties that arise in these situations and the training of education professionals in the knowledge and implementation of empirically-based intervention (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calvario Pérez, Mercedes del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Aldaz, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vergara Arroniz, María Aranzazu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bazanbide Binaburu, Miren Elisabet</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Ramírez, María Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Romera, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arnal Gimeno, Ana Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Civera Marín, María Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bellido Gómez, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña Capapey, Rosa Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo plantea, desde el punto de vista de los Equipos de Orientación que intervienen en Educación Infantil y Primaria y en base a la experiencia de los autores, una manera de abordar los problemas de conducta que presentan algunos alumnos. El punto de partida tiene en cuenta las aportaciones de lapsicología evolutiva y laperspectiva conductal de sistemas. El centro escolar forma parte del conjunto de sistemas relacionados donde se presentan estos problemas y en muchas ocasiones se generan situaciones de estrés añadido y de reto para los profesionales implicados. Se plantean aquí una serie de actuaciones y procedimientos que los autores han denominado "buenas practicas" dirigidas a contar e implicar a las estructuras formales habituales de los centros con el fin de encauzar de manera adecuada la solución de estos problemas, colaborar con otros sistemas -familias, unidades de salud, servicios sociales- y tratar de minimizar los efectos colaterales que habitualmente se producen a la hora de intervenir. Se con cluye con la necesaria colaboración entre todos lso csitemas implicados para tratar de dar alternativas a las dificultades que se originan en estas situaciones y la formación de los profesionales de la educación en el conocimiento y aplicación de programas de intervención con base empírica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apuntes psicol;29(2): 319-336, mayo-ago. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101631</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Un protocolo de buenas prácticas en la intervención con alumnos con trastorno de la conducta en centros educativos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12953^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12953^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12953^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3487</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13306^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12953^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13306^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d991^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2698^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13331^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13331^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2699^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
