<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86049</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality analysis by external users of the non-medical health transport unit of Alicante</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Non-medical health transport has great health, media and social repercussions and requires a very considerable amount of human and economic resources. Objective. To describe the quality, evaluated by external users of our Health Department, in order to know what are the most important elements for external users. Methods. Cross-sectional, descriptive observational study. Population to study: patients with a social security health card who come to the Hospital of Alicante and are non-medical health transport unit users. Results. Waiting time to be delivered to hospital in 92.7% of the cases was less than an hour, and was between one and two hours for 7.2%. The most frequent destinations were rehabilitation service and outpatient clinics. When users were asked if the would recommend this service, 60.9% said &#147;for sure&#148; and 39.1% said &#147;probably yes&#148;. Conclusions. This study allows us to know patient needs and expectations, as well as the factors they value the most and which of our work areas to improve(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Soriano Clemor, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soriano Cano, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morant Gimeno, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La gestión del transporte sanitario conlleva una gran repercusión sanitaria, mediática y social y requiere una dotación elevadísima de recursos humanos y materiales. Objetivo. Describir la calidad percibida por los usuarios externos de la Unidad de Coordinación de Transporte Sanitario no Asistido de Alicante para conocer qué elementos valoran más los usuarios externos. Método. Estudio observacional transversal descriptivo basado en un cuestionario de calidad percibida respondido mediante entrevista por los usuarios externos de la Unidad de Coordinación de Transporte Sanitario no Asistido de Alicante con tarjeta sanitaria que acuden al Hospital General Universitario de Alicante. Resultados. El tiempo de espera para la recogida en el 92,7% de los traslados fue inferior a una hora y en el 7,2% de los casos se tardó entre 1 y 2h. Los traslados se realizaron en el servicio de rehabilitación y en consultas externas. Al preguntar si recomendarían este servicio, el 60,9% manifestó que &#147;lo recomendaría seguro&#148; y el 39,1%, que &#147;quizá sí&#148; lo recomendaría. Conclusiones. Este estudio nos ha permitido conocer las necesidades y expectativas de los clientes externos, los factores que más valoran y nuestras áreas de mejora(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;26(1): 12-17, ene.-feb. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86049</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la calidad percibida por los usuarios externos de la Unidad de Coordinación de transporte sanitario no asistido de Alicante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14578^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51308</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14578^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14578^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14578^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23920</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14578^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
