<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117580</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anti-NMDA receptor encephalitis: two paediatric cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Encephalitis associated to anti-N-methyl D-aspartate (NMDA) receptor antibodies is an autoimmune neurological pathology that has been reported increasingly more frequently in the paediatric population in recent years. We report two cases from our own experience with similar clinical pictures. Case reports. Case 1: a 5-year-old girl who began with clinical signs and symptoms of convulsions and altered consciousness, associated to movement disorders and regression of previously acquired abilities that developed into autism. Case 2: a 13-year-old girl who presented left-side hemiparesis, abnormal movements, conduct disorder and dysautonomia. In both cases positive anti-NMDA receptor antibodies were obtained in cerebrospinal fluid and they were diagnosed with anti-NMDA receptor encephalitis. In the first case, treatment was established with intravenous perfusion of corticoids and immunoglobulins, and rituximab also had to be associated. In the second case, treatment consisted in corticoids and immunoglobulins. Progress was favourable in both cases, with a slight language disorder as a sequela in the first case and a relapse in the second case, with full resolution. Conclusions. Anti-NMDA receptor encephalitis is a treatable disorder and early diagnosis and treatment are crucial, since this improves the prognosis and diminishes the chances of relapses (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jover Cerdá, Jenaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Toro, M. Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jadraque Rodríguez, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sempere Pérez, Ángela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Gosálvez, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Pastor, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La encefalitis asociada a anticuerpos antirreceptores de N-metil-D-aspartato (NMDA) es una patología neurológica autoinmune documentada en la población pediátrica de manera creciente en los últimos años. Se presentan dos casos de nuestra experiencia con clínica similar. Casos clínicos. Caso 1: niña de 5 años que inicia un cuadro de convulsiones y alteración de conciencia, asociando trastornos del movimiento y regresión de habilidades previamente adquiridas que evoluciona a autismo. Caso 2: niña de 13 años que presenta hemiparesia izquierda, movimientos anómalos, trastorno de conducta y disautonomía. En ambos casos se obtienen anticuerpos antirreceptores de NMDA positivos en el líquido cefalorraquídeo y se diagnostican de encefalitis antirreceptor de NMDA. En el primer caso se inicia el tratamiento con perfusión intravenosa de corticoides e inmunoglobulinas y es necesario asociar rituximab. En el segundo, corticoides e inmunoglobulinas. La evolución fue favorable en ambas pacientes, con una leve alteración del lenguaje como secuela en el primer caso y una recaída en el segundo caso, con resolución completa. Conclusión. La encefalitis antirreceptor de NMDA es un trastorno tratable y es importante el diagnóstico y tratamiento precoz, ya que mejora el pronóstico y disminuye las recaídas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;57(11): 504-508, dic. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117580</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Encefalitis antirreceptor de NMDA: dos casos pediátricos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54482^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7345^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
