<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-32862</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Persistence in the behavioral study of personality</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">From a behavioral outlook persistence would be operativized by means of the maintenance of the response rate in an acquisition/extinction task, under a negative reinforcement program. It is argued the need of distinguishing two ways of persistence behavior: (a) learned persistence, in which the subject maintains the learned response during extinction phase, and (b) motivation persistence, in which persistence is shown in different responses looking for alternative solutions. Pavlov System, developed for research on persistence (Santacreu y García-Leal, 2000) is used for analyzing the relationships between persistence, initial motivation and learning. Results show: (1) there is no direct lineal relationship between initial motivation and learning in the end of the acquisition phase, (2) learned and motivation persistence are not correlated and (3) distribution of motivational index discriminates better than the learned persistence index among subjects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santacreu, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Leal, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde una aproximación conductual, la persistencia se puede estimar a partir del mantenimiento de la tasa de respuesta en una tarea de adquisición / extinción, bajo un programa de reforzamiento negativo. Se plantea la necesidad de diferenciar entre dos formas de conducta persistente: (a) persistencia aprendida, en la que se mantiene la ejecución de la respuesta adquirida durante la fase de extinción, y (b) persistencia motivacional, en la que se mantiene una tasa de respuesta global constante. Se emplea una tarea diseñada para el estudio de la persistencia, el sistema Pavlov (Santacreu y García-Leal, 2000), para el estudio de las relaciones entre persistencia, motivación inicial y nivel de aprendizaje. Los resultados muestran: (1) la ausencia de relación lineal directa entre motivación inicial y nivel de aprendizaje; (2) la inexistencia de relación significativa entre persistencia motivacional y aprendida, y (3) la medida de la persistencia motivacional permite una mejor discriminación entre los sujetos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);16(1): 39-44, feb. 2004. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-32862</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La persistencia en el estudio conductual de la personalidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10742^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5206^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10743^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1541^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
