<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-27841</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Selective dorsal rhizotomy as a therapeutic option in spasticity. Indications and results</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims. Spasticity, which is a very frequent sequela of neurological diseases, is useful for compensating for loss of strength and enabling the patient to stand, if it is not excessive. Otherwise, it is contraindicative and requires specific treatment. Development. Spasticity is a spinal cord dysfunction triggered by the lack of upper motoneuron-inhibiting afferents and, hence, its treatment can be centred either on a level above that of the lesion itself, if the descending pathways remain functional, or on the lesion, that is, on the spinal cord, by means of neurostimulation, intrathecal drugs or ablative procedures. Ablative procedures, which are essentially oriented towards reducing the afferents in order to diminish medullar reflex hyperexcitability, are indicated in children with spastic cerebral palsy. Thanks to a rigorous detailed study that is conducted beforehand, selective dorsal rhizotomy (SDR) allows us to determine which groups of muscles must be treated. Based on intraoperative neurophysiological studies and monitoring and the use of microsurgical techniques, the dorsal rhizome turns out to be very selective after the perfect identification of the rootlets that are to be preserved. Following the qualitative and quantitative valuation of diverse parameters, post-operative results show significant improvements in the functional performance of the child at one year after the intervention, and these are maintained and increase in the next few years. A strict programme of physiotherapy and rehabilitation is very effective and enables patients to enjoy greater autonomy. Conclusions. The use of SDR enables us to remove excessive spasticity, correct anomalous postures and reduce collateral pain. Its successful performance is depends on the work of a multidisciplinary team and on the overall approach to the disease in each case (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. La espasticidad, secuela muy frecuente de las enfermedades neurológicas, es útil para compensar la pérdida de fuerza y posibilitar la bipedestación, si no es excesiva, en cuyo caso es contraproducente y precisa tratamiento especifico. Desarrollo. La espasticidad es una disfunción medular desencadenada por la falta de aferencias inhibidoras de la motoneurona superior y, por ello, su tratamiento puede enfocarse supralesionalmente, si se conservan funcionales las vías descendentes, o lesionalmente, es decir, medular, mediante neuroestimulación, fármacos intratecales o procedimientos ablativos. Los procedimientos ablativos, fundamentalmente orientados a reducir las aferencias para disminuir la hiperexcitabilidad del reflejo medular, están indicados en niños con parálisis cerebral espástica. La rizotomía dorsal selectiva (RDS) permite, gracias a un riguroso y detallado estudio previo, determinar qué grupos de músculos han de tratarse. Basada en estudios y monitorización neurofisiológica intraoperatoria y con técnica microquirúrgica, la rizotomía dorsal resulta muy selectiva tras la perfecta identificación de las raicillas que se han de preservar. Los resultados posoperatorios tras la valoración cualitativa y cuantitativa de diversos parámetros, muestran mejorías significativas en el rendimiento funcional del niño al año de la intervención, que se mantienen e incrementan en los años siguientes. Un riguroso programa de fisioterapia y rehabilitación es, entonces, muy eficaz, y permite una mayor autonomía de los pacientes. Conclusiones. La RDS permite suprimir la espasticidad excesiva, corregir posturas anómalas y reducir el dolor colateral. Su realización y éxito se basan en el trabajo de un equipo multidisciplinar y en el enfoque global de la enfermedad en cada caso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;37(1): 86-88, jul. 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rizotomía dorsal selectiva como opción terapéutica en la espasticidad. Indicaciones y resultados</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Manrique, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-27841</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d9322</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13499</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32619</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
