<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157451</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-9891</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Protocol and methodology of study epidemiological mental health in Andalusia: PISMA-ep</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. This is the general methods describing paper of a cross-sectional study that aims to detect the prevalence of major mental disorders in Andalusia (Southern Spain), and their correlates or potential risk factors, using a large representative sample of community-dwelling adults. Materials and methods. This is a cross-sectional study. We undertook a multistage sampling using different standard stratification levels and aimed to interview 4,518 randomly selected participants living in all 8 provinces of the Andalusian region utilizing a door-knocking approach. The Spanish version of the MINI International Neuropsychiatric Interview, a valid screening instrument ascertaining ICD-10/DSM-IV compatible mental disorder diagnoses was used as our main diagnostic tool. A large battery of other instruments was used to explore global functionality, medical comorbidity, personality traits, cognitive function and exposure to psychosocial potential risk factors. A saliva sample for DNA extraction was also obtained for a sub-genetic study. The interviews were administered and completed by fully trained interviewers, despite most tools used are compatible with lay interviewer use. Results. A total of 3,892 (70.8%) of 5,496 initially attempted households had to be substituted for equivalent ones due to either no response (37.7%) or not fulfilling the required participant quota (33%). Thence, out of 5,496 eligible participants finally approached, 4,507 (83.7%) agreed to take part in the study, completed the interview and were finally included in the study (n=4,507) and 4,286 (78%) participants also agreed and consented to provide a saliva sample for DNA study. On the other hand, 989 (16.3%) approached potential participants refused to take part in the study. Discussion. This is the largest mental health epidemiological study developed in the region of Spain (Andalusia). The response rates and representativeness of the sample obtained are fairly high. The method is particularly comprehensive for this sort of studies and includes both, personality and cognitive assessments, as well as a large array of bio-psycho-social risk measures (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rivera, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Barranco, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez, Blanca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez-Casas, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valmisa, Eulalio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carmona-Calvo, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Küstner, Berta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ching-López, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cervilla, Jorge A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Negro, José Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El presente artículo describe la metodología general de un estudio transversal cuyo principal objetivo consiste en la detección de la prevalencia de los principales trastornos mentales en Andalucía, y el estudio de sus correlatos o posibles factores de riesgo mediante una amplia muestra representativa de adultos que vive en la comunidad. Materiales y métodos. Este es un estudio transversal en el que desarrollamos un muestreo de varias fases utilizando distintos niveles de estratificación habituales y en el que teníamos como objetivo entrevistar a 4.518 participantes seleccionados al azar y representativos de las 8 provincias de la comunidad andaluza, con un enfoque de «llamada a la puerta». Como principal herramienta diagnóstica se utilizó la versión española de la entrevista neuropsiquiátrica internacional MINI, un instrumento válido de detección para el establecimiento de diagnósticos de trastorno mental compatibles con los criterios CIE-10/DSM-IV. Asimismo, se empleó una amplia batería de instrumentos para explorar la funcionalidad global, la comorbilidad médica, las características de la personalidad, la función cognitiva y la exposición a posibles factores de riesgo psicosocial. También se obtuvo una muestra de saliva para extraer ADN para un estudio de asociación genética. Entrevistadores entrenados llevaron a cabo las entrevistas, a pesar de que la mayoría de las medidas son compatibles con entrevistadores legos. Resultados. De los 5.496 hogares seleccionados inicialmente, el 70,8% (3.892) tuvieron que sustituirse por falta de respuesta (37,7%) o por no incluir a ninguna persona que cumpliese las características requeridas (33%). Así, de las nuevas 5.496 personas, a las cuales finalmente se accedió, 4.507 (83,7%) consintieron participar, completaron la entrevista y se las incluyó finalmente en el estudio (n = 4.507), mientras que 4.286 (78%) también proporcionaron una muestra de saliva. Por su parte, 989 (16,3%) rechazaron participar. Discusión. Se trata del estudio de epidemiología de salud mental más amplio desarrollado en la comunidad autónoma más grande y poblada de España (Andalucía). Las tasas de respuesta y representatividad de la muestra son bastante altas. El método empleado es muy completo para este tipo de estudios e incluye tanto valoraciones de personalidad (rasgos y trastorno) como valoración cognitiva, así como un amplio abanico de medidas de riesgo biopsicosocial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psiquiatr. salud ment. (Barc., Ed. impr.);9(4): 185-194, oct.-dic. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157451</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Protocolo y metodología del estudio epidemiológico de la salud mental en Andalucía: PISMA-ep</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35170^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12223</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
