<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112009</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reintroduction of vaginal breech delivery and external cephalic version</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To review the obstetric and neonatal outcomes of the application of an updated vaginal breech delivery protocol 10 years after this practice had been discontinued. Methods: Breech presentations were referred to a dedicated breech unit at 36 weeks where the external cephalic version was offered. If breech presentation persisted, the patients were selected to undergo attempted vaginal delivery if the following criteria were met: a) estimated fetal weight of 2.500-3.600 g; b) frank or complete breech presentation; c) absence of hyperextension of the fetal head; and d) a clinically adequate pelvis. Intrapartum criteria included: a) progression of labor of   1 cm/hour in the first hour; b) In the second stage, 90 minutes were allowed for adequate descent of the breech, and 1 hour of active pushing, and c) the availability of an on-call expert. Results: A total of 93 patients showed single live pregnancies in breech presentation after external cephalic version. Sixty-nine patients (73.4%) underwent elective prelabor cesarean delivery, and 24 (26.6%) progressed to attempted vaginal breech delivery, which was successful in 19 (20.1%). Cesarean indications for breech presentation were reduced from 5.7% in 2009 to 2.02% after the application of external cephalic version and vaginal breech delivery (P&lt;.001). We observed no fetal deaths, no Apgar test at 5 minutes of less than 7, no umbilical artery pH of less than 7, and no fetal injuries. Conclusions: . When antepartum and intrapartum criteria are met, vaginal breech delivery is safe. The availability of an on-call expert allows vaginal breech delivery to be safely performed. The combination of external cephalic version and vaginal breech delivery decreases the cesarean rate for breech presentation(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Medina Díaz, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Adánez, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro López, Marina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquerizo Ruiz, Oscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernandez Ferrera, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pagola Limón, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escudero Gomis, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Se analizan retrospectivamente los resultados obstétricos y neonatales de la aplicación de un protocolo de parto vaginal de nalgas tras 10 años de su abandono. Métodos. Las pacientes eran derivadas a una unidad específica en la semana 36 donde se les ofrecía una versión cefálica externa. Si la presentación de nalgas persistía, eran seleccionadas para intento de parto vaginal si cumplían los siguientes criterios: a) peso fetal estimado 2.500-3.600g; b) nalgas puras o completas; c) cabeza fetal no hiperextendida, y d) pelvis clínicamente adecuada. El progreso del parto requería: a) primer estadio &amp;#8805;1cm/h; b) segundo estadio 90 min para el descenso pasivo de las nalgas y una hora de pujos activos, y c) se estableció la disponibilidad de experto localizado. Resultados. Se encontró a 93 pacientes con presentación de nalgas única y viva tras la aplicación de la versión cefálica externa. En 69 (73,4%) se indicó una cesárea electiva, y 24 (26,6%) fueron candidatas para parto vaginal, 19 de las cuales lo lograron (20,1%). La tasa de cesáreas por esta indicación se redujo significativamente del 5,7% en 2009 a 2,02% (p&lt;0,001). No se observó ningún resultado fetal adverso (muerte fetal, test de Apgar&lt;7 en 5 min, pH de la arteria umbilical &lt; 7 o traumatismos fetales). Conclusiones. El cumplimiento de los criterios anteparto e intraparto y la disponibilidad de expertos localizados hacen posible un parto vaginal seguro. La aplicación combinada de versión e intento de parto vaginal reduce la tasa de cesáreas por presentación de nalgas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);56(5): 248-253, mayo 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112009</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recuperación del parto vaginal de nalgas y versión cefálica externa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28631^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29146^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29146^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15114^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15114^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15114^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15114^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23557^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15114^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1971^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23557^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1971^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201305</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
