<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166438</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Aliskiren in clinical practice: safety and efficacy in mono- and combination therapy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Recently published studies evaluating the efficacy of aliskiren, the first direct renin inhibitor available to treat hypertension, have focused on the effects of this drug on office diastolic blood pressure (DBP), when given either as monotherapy or in association with other antihypertensive drugs. Safety and tolerability were analyzed using standard parameters. The effects on systolic blood pressure (SBP) and on blood pressure (BP) control rates have been addressed as secondary objectives. This article provides a short review of the efficacy and safety of aliskiren reported in clinical trials. The studies were performed in patients with mild-tomoderate essential hypertension treated with different doses (from 75 to 600 mg a day) of aliskiren given once daily as monotherapy and comparisons were made with placebo or other antihypertensive drugs. Studies of the short- and long-term effects of combining aliskiren with hydrochlorothiazide, ramipril or amlodipine are also described. As a consequence of its mechanism of direct renin inhibition, aliskiren markedly reduces BP throughou the 24-hour period, in both monotherapy and combination therapy. The magnitude of the BP reduction is similar to that observed with other antihypertensive drugs when used at equipotent doses. Drug tolerability is similar to that of placebo. The combination of aliskiren with other antihypertensive drugs enhances their efficacy without increasing adverse effects and can even reduce cough induced by angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors and ankle edema induced by calcium channel blockers. The potential therapeutic role of aliskiren, as an alternative to monotherapy with other antihypertensives or given in combination with them, opens a new chapter in the treatment and control of hypertension as well as in the more effective protection of vital organs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Coca, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sierra, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domenech, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los estudios actualmente publicados para evaluar la efectividad clínica de aliskiren, el primer inhibidor directo de la renina disponible para el tratamiento de la hipertensión arterial, tienen como objetivo primario los efectos antihipertensivos en la presión arterial diastólica en la consulta, tanto en monoterapia como en combinación con otros antihipertensivos, mientras que la tolerabilidad se ha analizado siguiendo los parámetros habituales. Como objetivos secundarios se han analizado los efectos en la presión arterial sistólica y las tasas de normalización de la presión arterial (PA). En este artículo se incluyen resultados de eficacia y seguridad de distintos estudios clínicos en pacientes con hipertensión arterial esencial leve y moderada tratados en monoterapia con aliskiren 75 a 600 mg/día en comparación con placebo y con otros antihipertensivos. Del mismo modo se exponen los resultados de algunos estudios de combinación de aliskiren con hidroclorotiazida, ramipril y amlodipino, a corto y a largo plazo. Merced a su mecanismo de acción consistente en la inhibición directa de la renina, aliskiren ofrece una potente reducción de la PA que se mantiene las 24 h, tanto en monoterapia como combinación, de similar magnitud a la observada con los antihipertensivos disponibles cuando se utilizan a dosis equipotentes. Su tolerabilidad es similar a la del placebo. La combinación de aliskiren con otros antihipertensivos aumenta su eficacia sin incrementar los efectos adversos e incluso puede reducir la tos inducida por los inhibidores de la enzima de conversión de angiotensina y el edema maleolar relacionado con el uso de antagonistas del calcio. El potencial papel terapéutico de aliskiren, como alternativa a cualquier monoterapia o combinado con otros antihipertensivos, abre una nueva expectativa para el tratamiento y el control de la hipertensión arterial, así como para una más eficiente protección orgánica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);9(supl.A): 49a-59a, 2009. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166438</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aliskiren en la práctica clínica: eficacia y seguridad en monoterapia y en combinación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22333^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1821^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22334^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29553^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28570^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22832^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200900</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
