<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115415</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of identity development in adolescence (AIDA)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Identity is integrated as a central diagnostic criterion for personality disorders in the current revisión of the American Diagnostic and Statistical Manual (DSMV). As there is no elaborated self-rating questionnaire to assess identity development in healthy and disturbed adolescents, we developed an inventory to assess pathology-relaed identity development in adolescence (AIDA) and evaluated its psychometric properties in a mixed school and clinical sample. Test construction was deductive, referring to psychodynamic as well as social-cognitive theories, and led to a special item pool that was tested in 305 students aged 12-18 attending a public school and 52 child and adolescent psychiatric inpatients and outpatients with diagnoses of personality disorders (N=20) or other mental disorders (N=32). AIDA showed excellent scale and subscale reliabilities. The AIDA total scale &#147;Identity Diffusion&#148; and each of the primary scales &#147;discontinuity&#148; and &#147;incoherence&#148; differed significantly between personality disordered patients and control with remarkable effect sized (d) of 2.17 and 1.94 standard deviations. Referring to these results, AIDA can be seen as a reliable and valid instrument to assess normal and disturbed identity in adolescents (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Goth, Kirstin</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schlüter-Muller, Susanne</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schmeck, Klaus</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Foelsch, Pamela</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La identidad se integra como un criterio central en el diagnóstico de los trastornos de la personalidad en el actual DSM V. Ante la falta de un cuestionario autoadministrado que evalúe el desarrollo de la identidad en adolescentes sanos o con trastornos, si diseñó un inventario de evaluación de la patología relacionada con el desarrollo de la identidad en la adolescencia (AIDA) y sus propiedades psicométricas en una muestra escolar y clínica. A partir del método deductivo y tomando como referencia teorías psicodinámicas y cognitivo sociales, se elaboró una tabla especial de ítems que contestaron 305 estudiantes (de 12 a 18 años) de una escuela pública y 52 niños y adolescentes pacientes psiquiátricos hospitalizados y ambulatorios con diagnóstico de trastorno de personalidad (N=20) u otros trastornos mentales (N=32). La AIDA mostró excelentes índices de fiabilidad en las escalas y subescalas. El total de la escala &#147;difusión de la identidad&#148; y cada una de las escalas primarias &#147;discontinuidad&#148; e &#147;incoherencia&#148; diferían significativamente entre los pacientes con trastornos de personalidad y los controles con un tamaño de efecto notable de 2,17 y una desviación estándar de 1,94. Con estos resultados, la escala AIDA puede verse como un instrumento fiable y válido para evaluar la identidad normal y alterada en los adolescentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(21): 19-30, abr. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115415</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación del desarrollo de la identidad en la adolescencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10746</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
