<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82375</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6982</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of an additional inspiration CT scan on the conventional protocol of the 18F-FDG PET-CT in the detection of small pulmonary nodes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To determine the impact of an additional inspiration CT scan on the conventional 18F-FDG PET-CT protocol in the detection of small pulmonary nodules. Method. One hundred consecutive patients who presented with one or various nodules were studied. Whole-body PET-CT was performed using Gemini (Philips). CT acquisition parameters were 120Kv/25mAs, the same as those for the transmission/fusion CT (mild expiration) and inspiratory CT. Results. A total of 188 nodules were detected in the inspiratory CT with sizes between 0.3&#150;3cm. Non-inspiratory CT did not show 20/188 nodules (10.6%) with sizes between 0.3&#150;1cm, this corresponding to 17 patients. The most frequent localization of non-detectable nodules in non-inspiratory CT was the lower lobes.18F-FDG uptake was detected by the PET in 83.9% and 72% of nodules with &gt;1cm and between 0.7 and 1cm, respectively. However, only 10.5% of nodules &lt;0.7cm showed increased metabolic activity. Conclusion. In selected patients, inspiratory CT added to conventional PET-CT significantly improves the detection of small nodules (10.6%), especially in those lesions located in the lower lobes, due to respiratory movements, and may have an impact on patient management(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lozano, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lomeña, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuertes, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soler, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alvarez Moro, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arribas, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riera, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar el impacto de una TAC en inspiración adicional al protocolo convencional de la PET-TAC con 18F-FDG en la detección de nódulos pulmonares de pequeño tamaño. Método. Hemos estudiado consecutivamente 100 pacientes que presentaban uno o varios nódulos pulmonares radiológicos. A todos los pacientes se les practicó un PET/TAC (Gemini, Philips). Los parámetros de adquisición fueron los mismos para la TAC no inspiratoria/fusión y la TAC en inspiración: 120kV, 25mAs. Resultados. Un total de 188 nódulos fueron detectados en la TAC inspiratoria, con tamaño entre 0,3 y 3cm. Resultados. La TAC no inspiratoria no evidenció 20/188 nódulos (10,6%) con tamaño entre 0,3 y 1cm: correspondiendo a 17 pacientes. La localización más frecuente en la que no se evidenciaron nódulos en la TAC fue en lóbulos inferiores. Resultados. La PET visualizó hipercaptación de 18F-FDG en el 83,9% y el 72% de los nódulos &gt;1cm y entre 0,7 y 1cm, respectivamente. Sin embargo, únicamente el 10,5% de los nódulos &lt;0,7cm mostraron aumento de actividad metabólica. Conclusiones. En pacientes seleccionados, la práctica de una TAC inspiratoria adicional al estudio PET/TAC aumenta de forma significativa la detección de pequeños nódulos pulmonares (10,6%), especialmente de los localizados en lóbulos inferiores, debido a los movimientos respiratorios y puede tener un impacto en el manejo del paciente(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Med Nucl;29(6): 285-288, nov.-dic. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82375</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de una TAC en inspiración adicional al protocolo convencional de la PET-TAC con 18F-FDG en la detección de nódulos pulmonares de pequeño tamaño</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2894^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2894^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27848^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35392^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7145^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7145^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9871^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6793^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9871^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9871^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d488^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
