<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154545</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Medication reconciliation: from admission to primary care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To implement a medication reconciliation circuit of inter-level, comprehensive and multidisciplinary approach in an integrated health organization. To measure the discrepancies detected in each of the steps studied. Method. A prospective intervention study of one-year duration. The medication is reconciled at admission to the hospital, at discharge and when the patient goes to his Primary Care physician. The number and type of discrepancies detected each time the medication is reconciled are collected and resolved, as well as the total number of drugs before and after each reconciliation process quantified. Results. Between November 1, 2013 and October 31, 2014 the medication had been reconciled to 77 patients, 63% male, mean age 69,5 years. Mean admission discrepancy per patient was 7,85, 3,67 at discharge and 2,19 at Primary Care. Conclusions. This program of medication reconciliation, in addition to detect and resolve discrepancies, has been a starting point for establishing new channels of communication between the different health professionals who have participated in the program and disseminate the safety culture within the organization (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ariz, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valverde, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendizabal, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mitxelena, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Igea, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Implementar un circuito de conciliación de la medicación interniveles, integral y multidisciplinar en una organización sanitaria integrada. Medir las discrepancias detectadas en cada uno de los pasos estudiados. Método. Estudio de intervención, prospectivo y de un año de duración. La medicación se concilió en 3 momentos distintos del paso del paciente por el sistema sanitario: al ingreso en el hospital, al alta y cuando el paciente acudió a su médico de Atención Primaria. Se recogieron y resolvieron las discrepancias detectadas cada vez que se concilió la medicación, y se cuantificó el número total de medicamentos antes y después de cada proceso de conciliación. Resultados. Entre el 1 de noviembre de 2013 y el 30 de octubre de 2014 se concilió la medicación a 77 pacientes, 63% hombres, con una media de edad de 69,5 años. La media de discrepancias por paciente fue de 7,85 al ingreso, 3,67 al alta y 2,19 en Atención Primaria. Conclusiones. Este programa de conciliación de la medicación, además de detectar y resolver las discrepancias, ha sido un punto de partida para establecer nuevas vías de comunicación entre los diferentes profesionales sanitarios que han intervenido en el programa y difundir la cultura de seguridad dentro de la organización (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;31(supl.1): 62-65, jun. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154545</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conciliación de la medicación: desde el ingreso hasta la atención primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54220^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54220^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54220^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10545^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
