<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052409</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characteristics and trends of newly diagnosed HIV-infections, 2000-2004</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe the characteristics and trends of newly diagnosed HIV-infections. Methods: We analysed all newly diagnosed HIV-infections among residents of the Canary Islands, Ceuta, La Rioja, Navarre and the Basque Country (Spain) between 2000 and 2004. Results: In total, 1,807 HIV-infections ­74.4 per million inhabitants, per year­ were diagnosed. The heterosexual transmission category was the most frequent (48.6%), followed by that of homo/bisexual men (23.0%) and injecting drug users (IDU) (22.5%). From 2000 to 2004, the rate of new diagnoses of HIV infection decreased by 29.8% (p &lt; 0.0001). The rate of diagnoses of infections acquired by IDU diminished by 58.5% (p &lt; 0.0001), and the rate of infections associated with homo/bisexual practices in men descended by 33.9% (p = 0.0318). Nevertheless, the rate of diagnoses of infections by heterosexual transmission has not undergone significant changes. In the period 2002-2004, 28.7% of cases were diagnosed in foreigners, but the rate of diagnoses in the population of non-Spanish origin diminished by 24% (p = 0.0534). 39.7% of HIV diagnoses were delayed (with CD4 &lt; 200 cells/microlitre or coinciding with the diagnosis of AIDS). This situation was less frequent in women (odds ratio = 0.5; p &lt; 0.001) and increased with age amongst people over 30. The proportion of delayed diagnoses reached a maximum in 2001 (47.5%) and then declined until 2004 (38.6%; p = 0.022). Conclusions: Although none of the analysed indicators evolved unfavourably, it is important to insist on the prevention of sexual transmission, the early diagnosis of HIV infection, and the need to adapt preventive activities and focus them on people from other countries</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lezaun, María Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perucha, Milagros</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nuñez, Domingo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Iribas, Conchi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castilla, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>R'kaina Liesfi, Cleopatra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Daniel Zulaika, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir las características y tendencias de los nuevos diagnósticos de infección por el virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana (VIH). Métodos: Se analizaron los nuevos diagnósticos del VIH entre los residentes en Canarias, Ceuta, La Rioja, Navarra y País Vasco desde 2000 hasta 2004. Resultados: Se diagnosticaron 1.807 infecciones, 74,4 por millón de habitantes y año. Predominó la categoría de transmisión heterosexual (48,6%), seguida por la homosexual/bisexual (23,0%) y la de usuarios de drogas por vía parenteral (UDVP) (22,5%). Entre 2000 y 2004, la tasa de diagnósticos del VIH ha disminuido un 29,8% (p &lt; 0,001). La tasa de diagnósticos de infecciones de la categoría de UDVP disminuyó un 58,5% (p &lt; 0,001) y, en hombres, la de infecciones de la categoría homosexual/bisexual disminuyó un 33,9% (p = 0,032). La tasa de diagnósticos de infecciones de la categoría heterosexual no ha presentado cambios significativos. En el período 2002-2004, el 28,7% de los casos correspondía a extranjeros, pero la tasa de diagnósticos en personas de otros países disminuyó un 24% (p = 0,053). El 39,7% de los diagnósticos del VIH fueron tardíos (con CD4 &lt; 200 células/µl o coincidiendo con el sida). Esta situación fue menos frecuente en mujeres (odds ratio = 0,5; p &lt; 0,001) y aumentó con la edad a partir de 30 años. La proporción de diagnósticos tardíos alcanzó el máximo en 2001 (47,5%) y disminuyó hasta 2004 (38,6%; p = 0,022). Conclusiones: Aunque ninguno de los indicadores analizados ha evolucionado desfavorablemente, se debe insistir en la prevención de la transmisión sexual, en el diagnóstico precoz de la infección por el VIH y en la adaptación de estas actividades a personas de otros países</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;20(6): 442-448, nov. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052409</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características y tendencias de los nuevos diagnósticos de infección por el virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana (2000-2004)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22069</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14563</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31670</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
