<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146166</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cost-effectiveness of early nutritional therapy in malnourished adult patients in a high complexity hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: hospital malnutrition is a frequent worldwide problem and its potential issues related include increased complications, length of stay, mortality, and healthcare costs. Objectives: the aim of this study was to establish the cost-effectiveness of early nutritional therapy for malnourished patients in a high complexity hospital. Materials and methods: this analytical study with economic assessment included 227 adult hospitalised and malnourished according to the Subjective Global Assessment. The cohort prospective received Early Nutrition Therapy (ENT), whereas the cohort retrospective received Delayed Nutrition Therapy (DNT). The measures of cost-effectiveness included costs by: length of stay, complications and discharge condition. Results: the cohorts were similar in demographic and clinical characteristics, except that the median age, for the ENT was 61 years (interquartile range [IQR]: 48-71) and for the DNT was 55 years (IQR: 44-67) (p = 0.024). The median length of stay was lower in the ENT (11 days, IQR: 7-17) than in the DNT (18 days, IQR: 10-28) (p &lt; 0.001). The cost per patient discharged alive was US $ 10,261.55 in the ENT and US $ 15,553.11 in the DNT (p=0.043); the cost per patient with complications was US $ 13,663.90 in the ENT and US $ 17,860.32 in the DNT (p= 0.058). ENT increased the likelihood of being discharged alive, RR adjusted=0.31; 95% confidence interval (CI): 0.1; 0.6; (p&lt;0.001) and decreased the likelihood of complications RR crude=0.8; 95% CI: 0.6; 0.9; (p=0.006). Conclusion: early nutritional therapy for malnourished adult patients appears to be cost-effective because it can reduce the length of stay, complications, mortality and associated costs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sosa Cardona, Yuliet Paulina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roldán Cano, Paula Andrea</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giraldo Giraldo, Nubia Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vásquez Velásquez, Johanna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ospina Astudillo, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la malnutrición hospitalaria es un problema frecuente en el mundo que aumenta las complicaciones, los días de estancia, la mortalidad y los costes sanitarios. Objetivos: el objetivo de este estudio fue establecer el coste-efectividad de la terapia nutricional precoz en pacientes malnutridos en un hospital de alta complejidad. Materiales y métodos: este estudio analítico con valoración económica, incluyó 227 adultos hospitalizados y malnutridos según Valoración Global Subjetiva. La cohorte prospectiva recibió Terapia Nutricional Precoz (TNP), mientras que la cohorte retrospectiva recibió Terapia Nutricional Tardía (TNT). Las medidas del coste-efectividad incluyeron costes por: días de estancia, complicaciones y condición de egreso. Resultados: las cohortes fueron similares en cuanto a características clínicas y demográficas, excepto en la mediana de edad; para la TNP fue 61 años (rango intercuartil [RIQ]: 48-71) y para la TNT fue 55 años (RIQ: 44-67) (p=0,024). La TNP se encontró costo-efectiva en la reducción de los días de estancia hospitalaria (11 días, RIQ: 7-17) en comparación con la TNT (18 días, RIQ: 10-28) (p&lt;0,001). La TNP registró costos de 10.261,55 $ US por paciente egresado vivo, inferiores a los obtenidos en la TNT 15.553,11 $ US (p=0,043); el coste por paciente con complicaciones fue 13.663,90 $ US en la TNP y 17.860,32 $ US en la TNT (p=0,058). La TNP incrementó la probabilidad de egresar vivo, RR ajustado=0,31; intervalo de confianza (IC) 95%: 0,1; 0,6; (p&lt;0,001) y disminuyó la probabilidad de complicaciones RR crudo=0,8; IC 95%: 0,6; 0,9; (p=0,006). Conclusión: la terapia nutricional precoz en pacientes adultos malnutridos parece ser coste-efectiva porque puede reducir los días de estancia, las complicaciones, la mortalidad y los costes asociados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(6): 2938-2947, dic. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146166</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Coste-efectividad de la terapia nutricional temprana en pacientes adultos malnutridos en un hospital de alta complejidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38344^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32108^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50303</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
