<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131911</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Implementation of an indirect method for the measurement of memory in th elderly</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. There is interference between emotional factors and intellectual output in the elderly, in whom there is a high prevalence of depression. Low output in conventional psychological tests may lead to false positive diagnoses of dementia. Patients and methods. We evaluated 48 patients aged between 50 and 84 years with regard to their emotional and intellectual state by means of the SCAN system. We also used a test designed by ourselves to implicitly examine memory. This consisted of a task involving naming objects. Six stimuli were repeated three times, seeking an effect of perceptual representation of &#145;priming&#146; which facilitated later recall. Results. The results showed that patients with dementia recalled 0 to 2 of the repeated stimuli, as a result of weakened priming. Meanwhile the non-demented persons, in spite of having other neurological disorders answered between 4 and 6 times. Multivariate analysis of the variance showed that measurement of memory, both implicit and explicit, allowed discrimination between patients with and without dementia. However, the explicit results were not independent of the effects of depression. Conclusions. Implicit measurements of memory were superior to direct or explicit measurements in the diagnosis of dementia. Patients with other degenerative conditions, such as Parkinsonism and multisystemic atrophy, had above average results. This corroborates the view that the neurological basis of this type of memory is not at subcortical level (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bringas, Mª L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendizábal, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Mena, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Existe una interferencia entre los factores emocionales y el rendimiento intelectual en la tercera edad, donde hay una alta prevalencia de depresión. Un bajo rendimiento en las pruebas psicológicas convencionales puede provocar falsos positivos en el diagnóstico de la demencia. Pacientes y métodos. Se evaluó a 48 pacientes de entre 50 y 84 años en cuanto a su estado emocional e intelectual a través del sistema SCAN. Se empleó, además, una prueba diseñada por nosotros para explorar de forma implícita la memoria, que consistía en una tarea de nominación de objetos. Se incluían seis estímulos que se repetían tres veces buscando un efecto de representación  perceptual o &#145;priming&#146;, que facilitaría su evocación posterior.Resultados. Los resultados revelan que los pacientes con demencia evocaban entre 0 y 2 del total de estímulos repetidos, como una consecuencia del debilitamiento del &#145;priming&#146;, mientras que los no dementes, aunque tuvieran otra enfermedad neurológica, respondían entre 4 y 6. Un análisis multivariado de la varianza demostró que las mediciones de memoria tanto explícitas como implícitas permitían discriminar entre los pacientes portadores o no de la demencia. Sin embargo, las explícitas no resultaron independientes del efecto de la depresión. Conclusiones. Las medidas de memoria implícita resultan superiores que las directas o explícitas para el diagnóstico de demencia. Pacientes portadores de otras enfermedades degenerativas como Parkinson y atrofia multisistémica obtenían una ejecución por encima de la media, lo cual corrobora el criterio de que las bases neuronales de este tipo de memoria no están a nivel subcortical (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;30(9): 818-822, mayo 2000. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131911</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implementación de un método indirecto para medir la memoria en la tercera edad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28470</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
