<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107621</identifier>
<setSpec>1697-641X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Update in whitening techniques less aggressive on vital teeth: an ethical and legal necessity (first part)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This work deals with reviewing those whitening techniques that are less aggressive on tissues of the teeth themselves as well as on the adjacent tissues, evaluating their advantages and disadvantages compared to other more aggressive techniques that are currently disseminated, supported by some very aggressive advertising campaigns and upon occasion lacking sufficient scientific support. In it we present some clinical cases dealing with less aggressive whitening techniques that can serve as support for the opinions that will be presented here (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gomez Font, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Quesada, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrillo Baracaldo, José Santos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente trabajo trata de revisar aquellas técnicas de blanqueamiento menos agresivas tanto para los tejidos propios del diente como para los tejidos adyacentes evaluando sus ventajas e inconvenientes frente a otras técnicas más agresivas y que actualmente se encuentran muy difundidas a través  de campañas publicitarias muy agresivas, en ocasiones carentes de suficiente sustentación científica. En el mismo presentamos algunos casos clínicos tratados con técnicas de blanqueamiento de baja agresividad, que pueden servir de apoyo a las opiniones que aquí serán vertidas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cient. dent. (Ed. impr.);9(3): 223-232, sept.-dic. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107621</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actualización en técnicas de blanqueamiento de baja agresividad sobre dientes vitales: una necesidad ética y legal (primera parte)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14464^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14462^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14464^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54185^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
