<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95426</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Methodology for the adaptation of evaluation instruments</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective The present paper reviews the methodology used to translate and adapt measurement instruments from one language and its culture to another one and the verification of its metric properties.Search strategiesThe sources of information used for the development of this paper have focused on the methods to establish translation equivalences, on the problems that may arise in this procedure and their possible solutions as well as how the psychometrics properties of the resulting instrument are verified empirically.Synthesis of the ResultsThe procedure of cross-cultural adaptation of an instrument is complex and monitoring of practical guidelines is recommendable in order to avoid biases. Furthermore, empirical verification of validity and reliability is important for the instrument be considered as well adapted.Conclusions The evidence recommends using the method of the inverse translation and indicates that following the guidelines of the International Commission of Tests minimizes the errors when adapting a test (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cardoso Ribeiro, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Conesa, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hidalgo Montesinos, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo El presente trabajo revisa la metodología para la realización de la traducción y adaptación de instrumentos de medida de un idioma y su cultura a otro, y la comprobación de sus propiedades métricas. Estrategia de búsqueda Las fuentes de información utilizadas para el desarrollo de este trabajo se centran en los métodos para establecer equivalencias de traducción, en los problemas que pueden surgir en dicho proceso y posibles soluciones, así como en la forma de comprobar empíricamente las propiedades psicométricas del instrumento resultante.Síntesis de los resultados El proceso de adaptación transcultural de un instrumento es complejo, siendo recomendable el seguimiento de directrices prácticas para evitar la aparición de sesgos. Además la comprobación empírica de la validez y de la fiabilidad es fundamental para que un instrumento se considere bien adaptado.Conclusiones La evidencia recomienda emplear el método de la traducción inversa, y refiere que el seguimiento de directrices de la Comisión Internacional de Tests minimiza los errores a la hora de adaptar un test (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);32(6): 264-270, Nov. -Dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95426</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Metodología para la adaptación de instrumentos de evaluación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3487</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
