<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042580</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Structural differences between alcoholic and diabetic parotid sialosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Between the sialosis&#146; etiologic agents, we can find the chronic alcoholism and diabetes. Both nosologic entities are descirbed using a similar histopathologic pattern. ;;Objectives: The purpose of this work has been analyzing and comparing the histopathological differences between the diabetic and alcoholic sialosis.Study design: We studied 7 parotid glands samples of diabetic patients and 4 samples of normal glands obtained from surgical material were used as a control. For the comparative study, we used 12 parotid glands from chronic alcoholic patients with clinical diagnosis of cirrhosis and 6 autopsies on individuals who had died from alcoholic hepatic cirrhosis. This material was fixed in formaline, processed for embedding in paraffin, standart coloration techniques and immunotechnique for cytokeratin EA/1 y EA/3. ;;Results: In the cases of diabetics, the parotid gland was characterised by the presence of small acini, a bigger number of lipid intracytoplasmic droplets in the acinar and ductal cells, as well as an abundant adipose infiltration in the stroma when compared to the alcoholics. We observed that the cytoqueratins&#146; expression was heterogeneous at the acinar level, and very positive in the hyperplasic ducts, compared to the alcoholic and control groups. ;;Conclusions: These qualitative valorations indicate the differences between the histopathologic pattern of sialosis with different origins</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arriaga, Adriana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peydró, Amando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carranza, Miriam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carda, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz, Anselmo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gomez de Ferraris, Maria Elsa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Entre los agentes etiológicos de la sialosis se citan el alcoholismo crónico y la diabetes. Ambas entidades nosológicas se describen con un cuadro histopatológico similar.Objetivos: El objetivo de este trabajo fue analizar y comparar las modificaciones estructurales de la sialosis diabética con las de etiología alcohólica.Diseño del estudio: Se analizaron 7 biopsias de glándula parótida de individuos diabéticos y 4 de pacientes no diabéticos (controles), con patología oncológica en regiones vecinas. El estudio comparativo se efectuó con muestras de archivo que comprendieron 12 biopsias parotídeas de pacientes con diagnóstico clínico de cirrosis hepática alcohólica y 6 autopsias de individuos que fallecieron por cirrosis hepática alcohólica. El material fijado en formol e incluído en parafina, se coloreó con técnicas de rutina y se marcó con anticuerpos para citoqueratinas EA/1 y EA/3.Resultados: En los diabéticos, la parótida se caracterizó por presentar acinos de tamaño más reducido, mayor cantidad de inclusiones lipídicas intracitoplasmáticas en las células acinares y ductales e infiltración grasa abundante en el estroma, comparado con los alcohólicos. Se observó que la expresión de citoqueratinas fue heterogénea a nivel de los acinos e intensamente positiva en los ductos hiperplásicos, comparada con los grupos alcohólico y control.Conclusion: Estas valoraciones cualitativas indican diferencias en el cuadro histopatológico entre estas sialosis de distinto origen</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);10(4): 309-314, jul.-ago. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042580</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias estructurales entre las sialosis parotidea de etiología diabética y alcohólica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10495^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7144</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32615^s22051</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7802^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8230^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10496^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10495^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
