<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-64207</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cardiovascular disease is nowadays the first cause of morbimortality in industrializedcountries. Hypercholestorolemia is one of the most important cardiovascular risk factors, with a clearcausal role in atherosclerosis progression. This process begins in early childhood and tends tocontinue and progress until adult life; hence the importance of primary prevention in childrenand adolescents.We present a systematic review of literature on current knowledge about hypercholesterolemiain children, its prevalence, the meaning of cholesterol in childhood, the influence of feeding,its relation to other risk factors associated to atherogenic lipid levels, the possibilities ofscreening and the strategies of hypercholestorolemia prevention in childhood and adolescence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cortés Ricoa, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Actualmente la enfermedad cardiovascular es la principal causa de morbimortalidad en lospaíses desarrollados.La hipercolesterolemia es uno de los principales factores de riesgo cardiovascular, con unclaro papel causal en la progresión de la arterioesclerosis, proceso que se inicia ya desde la infanciay tiende a persistir y progresar hasta la edad adulta; de ahí la importancia de la prevención primaria en la población infantojuvenil. En el artículo se realiza una revisión sistemática de la literatura de los conocimientos actuales sobre la hipercolesterolemia en los niños, su prevalencia, el significado del colesterol en lainfancia, la influencia de la alimentación, su relación con otros factores de riesgo asociados conun perfil lipídico aterogénico, las posibilidades de cribado y las estrategias de prevención de la hipercolesterolemia en la infancia y adolescencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;9(34): 245-279, abr.-jun. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-64207</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23101</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
