<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87885</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of antimitochondrial antibody 113-1 in diagnosis and classification of salivary gland tumours with oncocytic differentiation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: Salivary gland tumours usually show great variability both in their morphopathology as well as their clinical behaviour. In the present study, the usefulness of antimitochondrial monoclonal antibody 113-1 in the diagnosis and categorization of salivary tumours was studied. Material and methods: A series of 22 benign and malignant salivary tumours and 5 non-tumoral salivary gland specimens were immunohistochemically analysed using an antimitochondrial monoclonal antibody (Ab Mo 113-1), which recognises a non-glycosylated mitochondrial protein of 60 Kd. Results: The use of this antibody allowed us to recognize all salivary tumours with oncocytic differentiation. Two salivary tumours (1 papillary cystadenoma and 1 epithelial-myoepithelial carcinoma) (2/22; 10%) were also reclassified as oncocytic tumoral subtypes, in principle unidentified. Conclusion: Our study highlights the usefulness of this antibody to facilitate the classification of salivary tumours, an aspect that may sometimes have not only diagnostic implications, but also prognostic (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vera-Sempere, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vera-Sirera, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: Los tumores de glándulas salivales se caracterizan por presentar una gran variabilidad y heterogeneidad, tanto en su morfopatología como en su evolutividad clínica. En el presente estudio se analiza la utilidad del anticuerpo antimitocondrial (Ac.113-1) en el diagnóstico y categorización de los tumores salivales. Material y métodos: Se estudian inmunohistoquímicamente una serie de 22 tumores benignos y malignos salivales, así como 5 especímenes correspondientes a glándulas salivales no tumorales aplicando un anticuerpo monoclonal antimitocondrial (Ac Mo 113-1), que reconoce una proteína no glicosilada de 60 Kd mitocondrial. Resultados: La utilización del anticuerpo 113-1 permitió reconocer todos los tumores con diferenciación oncocítica y además dos tumores salivales (un cistoadenoma papilar y un carcinoma epimiopitelial) (2/22; 10%) fueron reclasificados como variedades tumorales oncocíticas en principio no identificadas. Conclusión: El estudio realizado resalta la utilidad de este anticuerpo al facilitar la categorización de los tumores salivales, aspecto este que puede tener en ocasiones implicaciones no sólo diagnósticas sino también pronosticas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;62(1): 1-9, ene.-feb. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87885</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad del anticuerpo antimitocondrial 113-1 en el diagnóstico y categorización de los tumores de glándula salival con diferenciación oncocítica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12844^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22664^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12844^s32386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3556^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9041^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
