<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112192</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A school breaks card game improves eating habits in adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Feeding habits among the Spanish population are currently an increasing and concerning problem, especially during adolescence. Objectives: To improve feeding habits (breakfast, consumption of fruit and water, soft drinks, pastries, sweets and fried food) in adolescents. Methods: The intervention was conducted for 3 months in students from 12 to 16 years old, through an educational proposal based on a card game (built ad hoc) called "Fighting for my health", which was developed during the school breaks. This game was supplemented with the methodology of a healthy commitment, based mainly on the cooperative work between schools and families and the promotion of the responsibility among students about their health. Two groups were included (intervention and control), each one with a total number of 48 adolescents. Results: After the intervention, significant improvements were achieved in 5 of the 6 habits addressed (the exception was consumption of fried food) in the intervention group. Among them, it is necessary to highlight the significant difference (p &lt; 0.001) obtained in breakfast and consumption of fruit between pretest and posttest and between pretest and retest. However, in the control group there were no significant differences in any of them. Conclusion: A school-based intervention conducted from the Department of Physical Education, through healthy commitments using a card game, improved the feeding habits in adolescents (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Delgado Fernández, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez López, IJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los hábitos alimentarios de la población española son un problema cada vez más preocupante en la actualidad y, en especial, durante la adolescencia. Objetivos: Mejorar los hábitos alimentarios saludables (desayuno, ingestas de fruta y agua, consumo de refrescos, bollería-golosinas y fritos) en adolescentes. Métodos: La intervención se llevó a cabo durante 3 meses, con alumnos de entre 12 y 16 años, mediante una propuesta educativa a través de un juego de cartas (construido ad hoc), denominado "Fighting for my health", y que se desarrolló en los recreos escolares. Éste se complementó con la metodología del compromiso saludable, caracterizado fundamentalmente por el trabajo colaborativo entre escuela y familia y por el fomento de la responsabilidad del alumnado hacia su salud. Se contó con 2 grupos (experimental y control), cada uno de ellos con un número total de 48 adolescentes. Resultados: Tras la puesta en práctica de la intervención se lograron mejoras significativas en 5 de los 6 hábitos trabajados (la excepción fue el consumo de fritos) en el grupo experimental. Entre ellas sobresale especialmente la diferencia altamente significativa (p &lt; 0,001) obtenida en el Desayuno y la Fruta, entre pretest y postest y entre pretest y retest. Sin embargo, en el grupo control no se produjeron diferencias significativas en ninguno de ellos. Conclusión: Una intervención escolar realizada desde el departamento de Educación Física, mediante compromisos saludables a través de juego de cartas, mejora los hábitos alimentarios en adolescentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;27(6): 2055-2065, nov.-dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112192</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Un juego de cartas durante los recreos escolares mejora los hábitos alimentarios en adolescentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d16566</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11416^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5657</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
