<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132857</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">From the symptom to the disease: asthenia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Asthenia is a common symptom that is shown to be a cause of medical consultation in teenagers, but is also in common in children and breastfed infants. Two clinical cases are presented, one of a 4-year-old girl and another of a 14-year-old teenager who, from the same asthenia symptom, two different diagnoses were arrived at in the Primary Care clinic: infectious Mononucleosis due to Epstein-Barr virus associated with pneumonia and acute renal failure. This article also deals with the anamnesis, physical examination, aetiological diagnosis, complementary examinations, and finally, for the paediatrician, the most common reasons for asthenia in children and adolescents (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casanovas Gordó, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La astenia es un síntoma frecuente que se manifiesta como motivo de consulta en adolescentes, pero también en niños y lactantes. Se presentan los casos clínicos de una niña de 4 años y una adolescente de 14 años, que a partir del mismo síntoma de astenia, llegan a dos diagnósticos diferentes desde la consulta de Atención Primaria: mononucleosis infecciosa por el virus de Epstein-Barr asociada a neumonía e insuficiencia renal aguda. Se habla de la anamnesis, exploración física, diagnóstico etiológico, exámenes complementarios y, finalmente, las causas más frecuentes para el pediatra de la astenia en la infancia y adolescencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;11(supl.17): s425-s431, nov. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132857</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Del síntoma a la enfermedad: astenia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3981^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7421^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1255^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200911</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
