<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124527</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of falls, drugs consumption, presence of illnesses and quality of life among community-dwelling elderly people</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: This study has aimed to describe the prevalence of falls, presence of illnesses, drugs consumption, and quality of life and their association with falls among community-dwelling elderly people (ages 65 to 75). Material and methods: A cross-sectional, observational study was performed. We randomly selected 198 of 1214 community-dwelling people aged 65 to 75. Sociological data, illnesses, falls and health-related quality of life (HRQL) data were recorded with the EuroQol-5D (EQ-5D) protocol, use of multiple medication (medications &gt; 4), psychoactive medication and anticon vulsants. A bivariate analysis was made to assess the effect of the independent variables over tendency to fall. Results: Prevalence of falls was 16.67%. Serious illnesses of the nervous system (OR = 63.10),acute infections or in&amp;#64258;ammation (OR = 3.72), severe limitation of mobility (OR = 2.91) and having EQ-5D limitations were related to falls. Percentage of subjects with EQ-5D limitations was: mobility 34.1% (women: 42.4%, men 25.8%), self-care 14.4% (women: 19.8%; men 8.9%), usual activities 29.65% (women: 44.7%, men 14.1%), pain/discomfort 69.1% (women: 81.7%, men 56.9%) and anxiety/depression 35.1% (women: 50.0%, men 19.8%). EQ-5D&#146;s Visual Analogue Scale average score was 68.5 ± 20.8 (women: 61.8 ± 23.0, men 75.0 ± 16.1.). Conclusions: The prevalence of falls was 16.67%. We found a high percentage of polymedication, mobility problems, pain/discomfort, anxiety/depression and poor self-perceived HRQL among elderly people. Women declared more problems than men on all of the EQ-5D dimensions. We therefore recommend including programs aimed at improving mobility, and HRQL and that prevent risk of falls, with special attention on women (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Saiz Llamosas, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santamarta Solla, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Rebollar, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casado Vicente, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: El objetivo de este estudio ha sido estudiar la prevalencia de las caídas y la presencia de enfermedades, consumo de fármacos y calidad de vida relacionada con la salud (CVRS) y su asociación con las caídas, en personas de 65-75 años, residentes en la comunidad. Material y métodos Estudio observacional transversal. Se seleccionó a 198 sujetos entre 1.214 de 65 a 75 años, que viven en la comunidad, seleccionados por muestreo aleatorio. Se registraron datos sociológicos, enfermedades, caídas, encuesta de CVRS EuroQol-5D (EQ-5D), polimedicación (&gt; 4 fármacos), psicofármacos y antiepilépticos. Se realizó un análisis bivariado con variable dependiente las caídas. Resultados La prevalencia de caídas fue del 16,67%. Se asociaron a enfermedades graves del sistema nervioso (OR = 63,10), inflamaciones/infecciones agudas (OR = 3,72), limitación severa de la movilidad (OR = 2,91) y a tener problemas en las dimensiones del EQ-5D (p &lt; 0,05). El porcentaje de sujetos con problemas en las dimensiones del EQ-5D fue: movilidad 34,1% (mujeres: 42,4%; hombres 25,8%), cuidado personal 14,4%(mujeres: 19,8%; hombres 8,9%), actividades cotidianas 29,65%(mujeres: 44,7%; hombres 14,1%), dolor/malestar 69,1%(mujeres: 81,7%; hombres 56,9%) y ansiedad/depresión 35,1%(mujeres: 50%; hombres 19,8%). La puntuación media ± desviación típica de la escala visual analógica del EQ-5D fue 68,5 ± 20,8 (mujeres: 61,8 ± 23,0, hombres: 75,0 ± 16,1).ConclusionesLa prevalencia de caídas fue del 16,67%. Se encontró un elevado porcentaje de problemas de movilidad, dolor/malestar, ansiedad/depresión y polimedicación. Las mujeres mostraron peor percepción de la CVRS en todas las dimensiones del EQ-5D. Son necesarias intervenciones que mejoren la movilidad y la calidad de vida, y prevengan las caídas, con especial atención a las mujeres (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);36(4): 153-159, jul.-sept. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124527</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de caídas, consumo de fármacos, presencia de enfermedades y calidad de vida de las personas mayores que viven en la comunidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28587</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28470</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19050^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4419</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
