<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148252</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Markers, renal predictors, and factors, of renal and cardiovascular risk factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">An important task of the nephrologists during the last century, it has been the search of elements and means that allow us , with the adequate precision, to correlate the functional deterioration of the kidney, and the patient&#146;s clinical reality. And the continuous searching of factors and markers that injure them, the prognosis, and early diagnosis, to be able to predict the degree of the organs and patient&#146;s survival. Almost parallel survival presage in the natural history of the illness, almost one century ago. In the second half of the XX century, in the developed countries, appear modifications of the social, cultural, and sanitary conditions, that make appear some very different partner-sanitary and epidemic circumstances, and take place like they are, among others: 1. An increase of per cápita private rents, what takes place to increase of the level of social life and the population&#146;s health. With increment of the longevity, and smaller incidence and prevalence of classic process, as malnutrition, infections, infantile mortality, so increasing the weight of the cardiovascular diseases and death. This is potentiated for the increment and the incidence of environmental cardiovascular risk&#146;s factors (like high caloric and fatty-rich diets, smoke, alcohol, disappearance of the physical work, inactivity, etc). And that situations are also product of the change of the outline of human and social values and guides. 2. Access of the whole population to a sanitary attention of more quality and effectiveness. It allows the biggest survival of patients that suffer vascular crisis, (as angina, miocardial infarction or cerebrovascular accident), that few years ago they have had a higher morbimortality and an inferior survival (2). 3. The execution of big epidemic studies has been able to, not only characterize and test with scientific evidence to numerous factors and markers, that induce renal and cardiovascular prejudicial changes, but risk and death probability prediction.And also, its possible association nexuses, its injuring mechanisms , and the characterization of the new «emergent» renal and cardiovascular risk&#146;s markers and factors. 4. The impact on the possibility to treat the end stage renal disease with effective and prolonged procedures, by hemodialisis or kidney transplantation, has been occured. The affected population&#146;s survival with the adequacy renal-sustitution treatment, and the possibility of indefinite duration of its treatment, has also impacted on the public health, and its resources, in an evident way. Simultaneouslyto increase of the incidence in the population , the electivity for the treatment has been enlarged and extended increasing it exponentially. These facts are documented here, and are defined the characteristics of the factors and markers of risk, of renal and cardiovascular diseases. The defined factors are valued to mark, so far as with the well-known evidence is possible, the prediction and the progression of the renal and cardiovascular functional deterioration. The hypertension, cardiovascular remodeling, the arterial stiffness, the heart rate, the sympathetic activation, the modification of the physiological response of the target organ to the overcharge, the metabolic syndrome, the obesity, the insulin resistance, the altered lipid profile, and metabolism of the fatty acids, the salt-sensibility, the decrease of the renal functional reserve, the glomerular hyperfiltration, the absence of the arterial pressure nocturnal descent, the abnormal excretion of proteins for the urine, the phenomenon induced by dysfunctions of the clotting, superoxide production, growth factors, the production of chronic inflammation and its markers, the factors of the glomerulosclerosis progression, the hiperuricemic status, the endothelial dysfunction and others, are evaluated. As well as their association among them and with other factors of risk not changeable like the age, and in turn, with other acquired voluntearely factors of risk, as the smoking habit and the alcohol. These facts are now impacting on the population&#146;s sanity. And also in the professional nephrologyc exercise, so much for the cardiovascular and renal morbimortality increased, as for the increase of the incidence of end-stage renal disease susceptible to treat with of substitutive procedures. They try to justify the sentence of Alan Weder of the heading, and other concepts like «epidemic factors of the XXI century», and intuitive expressions like «predialitic endothelial disruption or ruin» (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Andrade, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Una parte importante del afán de los nefrólogos desde el siglo pasado, ha sido la búsqueda de elementos y medios que permitan con la precisión necesaria correlacionar el deterioro funcional renal y la realidad clínica del paciente. Y la búsqueda de factores y marcadores lesionales, diagnósticos y pronósticos, para poder predecir el grado de supervivencia del órgano y del paciente. Pronósticos de supervivencia casi paralelos en el tiempo de la historia natural de la enfermedad, hace casi un siglo. En la segunda mitad del siglo XX, en los «países desarrollados» se producen modificaciones de las condiciones sociales, culturales y sanitarias que hacen aparecer unas circunstancias socio-sanitarias y epidemiológicas muy diferentes, como son entre otras: 1. Aumento de renta per cápita, lo que lleva a aumento del nivel de vida social y sanitario de la población. Con incremento de la longevidad, y menor incidencia y prevalencia de procesos «clásicos», como desnutrición, infecciones, mortalidad infantil, aumenta el peso de la enfermedad y muerte cardiovascular. Hecho potenciado por el incremento de la incidencia de factores de riesgo cardiovascular medioambientales (dietas grasas hipercalóricas, tabaquismo, alcohol, desaparición del trabajo físico, inactividad, etc.), que son también producto del cambio del esquema de valores sociales e individuales. 2. Acceso de toda la población a una atención sanitaria de mayor calidad y eficacia, que permite la mayor supervivencia de pacientes que sufren crisis agudas vasculares (como el infarto agudo de miocardio o ictus apoplético), y que hace pocos años tenían una morbi-mortalidad muy superior y una supervivencia inferior. 3. La ejecución de grandes estudios epidemiológicos han conseguido caracterizar con pruebas de evidencia no sólo a numerosos factores y marcadores que inducen cambios lesivos renales y cardiovasculares, y de predicción de muerte, sino también sus posibles nexos de asociación, sus mecanismos lesionales, y la caracterización de los mismos. 4. El impacto que ha producido la posibilidad de tratamiento sustitutivo, eficaz, sobre la supervivencia de la población con insuficiencia renal terminal, y la posibilidad de duración indefinida de su tratamiento, ha impactado también sobre la salud pública, y sus recursos, de forma evidente. Simultáneamente a un aumento de la incidencia en la población de la insuficiencia renal crónica, las indicaciones del tratamiento se han ampliado y extendido incrementándola exponencialmente. Se documentan estos hechos, se definen las características de los factores y marcadores de riesgo, y se valoran los factores definidos, que marcan con la evidencia conocida hasta la fecha, la predicción de la progresión del deterioro funcional renal y cardiovascular: La hipertensión arterial, el remodelado cardiovascular y la rigidez arterial, la frecuencia cardíaca, la activación simpática, la modificación de respuestas a las sobrecargas, el síndrome metabólico, la obesidad, la resistencia a la insulina, la dislipemia, el metabolismo alterado de los ácidos grasos, la sal-sensibiliad, la disminución de la reserva funcional renal, la hiperfiltración glomerular, la ausencia del descenso nocturno de la presión arterial, la excreción anormal de proteínas por la orina, la insuficiencia renal, los fenómenos inducidos por trastornos de la coagulación, la producción de superóxidos, de factores de crecimiento, de marcadores de inflamación crónica, los factores de la progresión de la glomérulosclerosis, la hiperuricemia, la disfunción endotelial,y otros, son valorados. Así como su asociación entre ellos y con otros factores de riesgo no modificables como la edad, y a su vez, con otros factores de riesgo adquiridos como el tabaquismo y el alcohol. Todo ello para valorar asimismo la trascendencia que tienen estos hechos que inciden en la sanidad de la población, y en el ejercicio profesional del nefrólogo, tanto por la morbi-mortalidad cardiovascular incrementada como por el aumento de la incidencia de insuficiencia renal susceptible de tratamientos sustitutivos. Se intentan justificar documentalmente desde la frase de Alan Weder del encabezamiento hasta conceptos como «epidemias del siglo XXI», y expresiones intuitivas como «ruina endotelial prediálisis» (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;22(supl.1): 2-29, feb. 2002. ^tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148252</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Marcadores y predictores renales y factores de riesgo renal y cardiovascular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33775^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7849^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11946</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14926^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5331^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8248^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1821</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7849^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200200</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
