<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59570</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Post-traumatic cyclodialysis cleft treated with transscleral diode laser</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report: A 28-year-old man who received ablunt trauma in his left eye, presented with persistentocular hypotony (intraocular pressure:4 mmHg) as well as loss of visual acuity (0.4), opticdisc edema and chorioretinal folds in the macula.The foveal thickness, measured by optic coherencetomography, was 326 microns. Using ultrasoundbiomicroscopy, a desinsertion of the nasal iris and a360º choroidal detachment was observed. Thehypotony did not respond to conservative treatmentand 10 months after the trauma he underwent atransscleral cyclopexy with contact diode laser. Oneyear after the laser treatment the visual acuity was1.0, the intraocular pressure 14 mmHg and the fovealthickness 240 microns.Discussion: Transscleral cyclopexy with diodelaser may be an effective alternative treatment toresolve post-traumatic cyclodialysis that does notrespond to medical treatment(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Negrete, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rebolleda, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cerio-Ramsden, C. D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso Clínico: Paciente varón de 28 años, que trastraumatismo contuso en su ojo izquierdo, presentauna hipotonía ocular persistente (presión ocular4 mmHg) acompañada de pérdida de agudezavisual (0,4), edema de papila y pliegues coriorretinianosa nivel macular. El grosor foveal, medidocon tomografía de coherencia óptica, era de 326micras. Mediante biomicroscopia ultrasónica seaprecia una desinserción de iris nasal y un desprendimientocoroideo de 360°. El cuadro no cede contratamiento conservador, por lo que 10 meses tras eltraumatismo se le realiza una ciclopexia transescleralcon láser diodo de contacto. Un año tras la aplicacióndel láser, la agudeza visual era 1, la presiónocular 14 mmHg y el grosor foveal 240 micras.Discusión: La ciclopexia transescleral con láserdiodo puede ser una alternativa eficaz para la resoluciónde ciclodiálisis postraumáticas que no respondena tratamiento médico(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;84(1): 47-50, ene. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59570</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ciclodiálisis postraumática tratada con láser diodo transescleral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27865^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27865^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28016^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28016^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24808^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8204^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28016^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1291^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24808^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8440^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8440^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9041^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2879^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8440^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28016^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52877^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24366^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200901</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
