<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037460</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Affective disorders and solar activity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The present work discusses the link between solar activity and appearance of affective disorders. Solar activity is reflected by the Wolf number, which is given by the formula R = K (10 g + f), where g corresponds to the groups of sunspots and f is the total number of sunspots.     Methods. We examined 1,212 clinical files at the Clínica Psiquiátrica Universitaria, Santiago de Chile. Patients with major depressions and manic disorders, who were admitted to the clinic for the first time and had no previous treatment were considered. We examined the correlation between annual incidence of hospitalization and average Wolf numbers for those years, included in the period 1990-2000, which corresponds to a complete solar cycle of 11 years.         Results. An important number of hospitalizations of depressive patients occurred during years of low solar activity, and there was a slight increase in the number of manic patients during years of high solar activity. Depressive disorders showed a negative correlation with solar activity, the Pearson coefficient being equal to -0.72. Manic disorders showed a positive correlation, with coefficient equal to +0.334.         Conclusions. Depressive disorders have an inverse correlation with solar activity, while manic disorders have a positive correlation</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ivanovic-Zuvic, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rentería, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega, R. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ivanovic-Zuvic, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Este trabajo presenta las relaciones entre la actividad solar y la incidencia de desórdenes afectivos. La actividad solar está representada por el número de Wolf mediante la fórmula R = K (10 g + f), donde g corresponde al grupo de manchas solares y f es el número total de manchas solares.     Métodos. Se revisaron 1.212 historias clínicas de la Clínica Psiquiátrica Universitaria de Santiago de Chile. Se consideraron sólo pacientes con depresiones mayores y manías que fueron hospitalizados en el primer episodio y sin tratamientos previos. Se examinó la correlación entre la incidencia anual de hospitalizaciones y el número de Wolf promedio para ese determinado año durante el período comprendido entre los años 1990 a 2000, ambos inclusive, lo que corresponde a un ciclo solar completo de 11 años.         Resultados. Un número importante de hospitalizaciones de depresiones mayores ocurrieron en años de baja actividad solar, mientras que las manías mostraron un aumento en años con mayor actividad solar. Los cuadros depresivos mostraron una correlación inversa con la actividad solar, con un coeficiente de rango de correlación de Pearson de -0,72. Las manías mostraron una correlación positiva, con un índice de +0,334.         Conclusiones. Los desórdenes depresivos poseen una correlación inversa con la actividad solar, mientras las manías poseen una correlación positiva</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;33(1): 7-12, ene.-feb. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037460</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedades afectivas y actividad solar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33172</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
