<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-70737</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To analyze the physiological and clinical characteristics of diabetes mellitus(DM) in young immigrants from Hindustan. Material and methods: We performed a descriptive analysis of clinical and laboratory variables related to DM indiabetic Hindustanis aged between 15 and40 years old. Body mass index (BMI) and waist perimeter (WP) were calculated. The immunology of DM and baseline C-peptide were studied and insulin resistance (IR)was determined by Homeostasis Model Assessment: Insulin Resistance (HOMA-IR).Results: The final sample consisted of 30patients. The prevalence of DM was 0.84%.All patients had DM2 and 50% had high IR. aseline C-peptide secretion wasp reserved in all patients. The cut-off points that best predicted IR in this ethnic group were a BMI higher than 25 and a WC of more than 95 cm. Conclusions: Most young Hindustani immigrants with diabetes have DM2 with preserved baseline insulin secretion and IR. Lower degrees of obesity than in the Spanish population were associated withIR (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rus Calafell, Neus</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mérida Martos, Ana María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morato Griera, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franch Nadal, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrillo Aparicio, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Peinado, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: analizar las características fisiopatológicas y clínicas de la diabetes mellitus (DM) en pacientes inmigrantes indostanos jóvenes. Material y métodos: Diabéticos indostanos de 15-40 años. Analisis descriptivo de variables clínicas y analíticas relacionadas con la DM. Cálculo del índice de masa corporal (IMC) y el perímetro de la cintura(PC). Estudio de la inmunología de la DM, péptido C basal y resistencia ala insulina (RI) mediante el Homeostasis Model Assessment: Insulin Resistance (HOMA-IR).Resultados: Muestra final de 30 casos. Prevalencia de DM del 0,84%.Todos los casos fueron DM2, el 50% con manifiesta RI. Secreción basal depéptido C conservada en todos los casos. El IMC &gt; 25 y el PC &gt; 95 cm fueron los puntos de corte que mejor predijeron la RI en este grupoétnico. Conclusiones: La mayoría de los sujetos diabéticos indostanos jóvenes presentan DM2 con reserva insulínica basal conservada y RI. Grados menores de obesidad que en la población española ya se relacionan con RI (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;55(10): 454-458, dic. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-70737</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d2130^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14563^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
