<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045193</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nutritional aspects related to hematopoietic precursor cell, lung and liver transplantation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Nutrition plays an essential role in the processes of healing and maintaining health. Nutritional intervention is required in the recovery of malnourished patients and is cost-effective. Malnutrition is common in patients waiting for an organ transplant and represents a risk factor for post-transplant morbidity. Patients at any stage of the transplantation process are at high nutritional risk and should undergo careful nutritional assessment for the early identification of nutritional support requirements. There are only a few prospective, randomized, controlled trials that have investigated the role of nutritional support in organ transplantation. This review discusses some of the most important issues in nutritional support in candidates for hematopoietic stem cell, lung, and liver transplantation</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calañas-Continente, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tratamiento nutricional es un elemento esencial para la cicatrización y el mantenimiento de la salud. Es necesario para conseguir la recuperación del enfermo desnutrido y es coste-efectivo. La desnutrición es frecuente en enfermos en lista de espera para un trasplante y constituye un factor de riesgo de morbilidad postrasplante. Los enfermos en cualquier momento del proceso del trasplante tienen un alto riesgo de desnutrición, por lo que es aconsejable una adecuada y cuidadosa evaluación nutricional que permita identificar precozmente a los candidatos que precisan tratamiento específico. Disponemos en la actualidad de escasos estudios prospectivos, aleatorizados y controlados sobre la importancia del tratamiento nutricional en el trasplante. Este artículo revisa algunos de los aspectos nutricionales más importantes en candidatos a trasplantes de precursores hematopoyéticos, de pulmón y hepático</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;53(5): 315-325, mayo 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045193</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aspectos nutricionales relacionados con los trasplantes de precursores hematopoyéticos, pulmonar y hepático</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32203</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30324^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30401^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20180^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32108^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29477</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29476</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
