<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120693</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Complications and level of satisfaction after dermolipectomy and abdominoplasty post-bariatric surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background Body contouring surgery is in high demand following the increase in bariatric surgery. But these types of procedures are associated with high complication rates that cause long hospital stays and have a negative effect on patient satisfaction. The purpose of this study is to identify predictors of complications in order to optimize outcomes in these patients and find a relationship between complication rate and satisfaction. Material and methods Out of a group of 175 post-bariatric patients, 72 patients underwent body contouring surgery following massive weight loss from 2003-2008. They were reviewed retrospectively for demographic data, pre- and postoperative weight status, co-morbidities and complications and reoperation rate. Patient satisfaction was evaluated. Results a) Complications: The overall complication rate was 45.8%. The most frequent were seromas (23.6%); infection (13.9%), bleeding (11.1%), hematoma (6.9%) (needing transfusions [6.9%]), skin necrosis (6.9%) and umbilical necrosis (4.2%). A total of 8 patients required reoperation (11.1%).b) Satisfaction rating: 1) very satisfied: 51.4%, 2) satisfied: 31.9%, 3) dissatisfied: 8.3%, 4) very dissatisfied: 8.3%.c) The presence of complications was significantly associated with patients&#146; satisfaction, reoperation rate and longer hospital stays (P&lt;.001).Conclusions Post operative complications were frequent. No predictors could be found to prevent these complications and optimize patient selection and appropriate timing of surgery. Patients with complications had a significantly higher reoperation rate, longer hospital stay and more dissatisfaction. The patients&#146; satisfaction was negatively influenced by complication occurrence and not by the aesthetic results (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lirón-Ruiz, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-García, María Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguel-Perelló, Joana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mengual-Ballester, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torralba-Martínez, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campillo-Soto, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Lorenzo, Juan Gervasio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguayo-Albasini, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción Las abdominoplastias se han convertido en un proceso quirúrgico frecuente en pacientes con pérdida masiva de peso tras cirugía bariátrica. Este tipo de procedimientos no están exentos de complicaciones que afectan a la calidad de vida y satisfacción del paciente. El objetivo de este estudio es encontrar los factores de riesgo para desarrollar dichas complicaciones y evaluar la satisfacción de nuestros pacientes. Material y métodos A un total de 72 pacientes, de los 175 intervenidos de cirugía bariátrica, se les realizó una abdominoplastia entre 2003 y 2008. Fueron revisados, retrospectivamente: datos demográficos, estado pre- y poscirugía, comorbilidades, tasa de complicaciones y reintervención. El nivel de satisfacción fue medido mediante una encuesta expresada en una escala tipo Likert. Se realizó un análisis comparativo de las distintas variables entre pacientes con y sin complicaciones. Resultados a) Complicaciones: tasa global del 45,5%. La más frecuente fue el seroma (23,6%); infección (13,9%), sangrado (11,1%), hematoma (6,9%) (requiriendo transfusión [6,9%]), necrosis de piel (6,9%) y necrosis umbilical (4,2%). Se reintervino a 8 pacientes (11,1%).b) Satisfacción: 1) muy satisfecho: 51,4%; 2) satisfecho: 31,9%; 3) insatisfecho: 8,3%; 4) muy insatisfecho: 8,3%.c) Se encuentra una relación estadísticamente significativa entre complicaciones, reintervención, estancia media y satisfacción (p &lt; 0,001).ConclusiónLas complicaciones son relativamente frecuentes en este tipo de pacientes, alargando la estancia media y posteriores controles ambulatorios. No hemos identificado factores de riesgo que ayuden a prevenir este tipo de complicaciones. El grado de insatisfacción está en relación con las complicaciones postoperatorias del procedimiento quirúrgico y no con el resultado estético (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);92(4): 254-260, abr. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120693</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Complicaciones y nivel de satisfacción tras la realización de una dermolipectomía y abdominoplastia después de efectuar una cirugía bariátrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23742^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51221^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55026^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
