<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154166</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Keratolimbal autograft transplantation as a possible new treatment of Lisch epithelial corneal dystrophy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report: The case concerns 64-year-old woman with visual acuity of 20/40 in the right eye. Slit-lamp examination revealed a grey, feathery corneal opacification with intraepithelial microcysts compatible with Lisch epithelial corneal dystrophy (LECD). It was treated with epithelial debridements, contact lenses and mitomycin C, but the opacification recurred within months. The removal of limbus sector and autologous limbal transplantation (KLAT) were used successfully without recurrence. Conclusions: After removal of damaged limbus, KLAT should be considered as a treatment option for asymmetric LECD when other treatments have failed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Avendaño Cantos, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cebrian Rosado, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Celis Sánchez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González del Valle, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Romero Moraleda, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mesa Varona, DV</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Presentamos el caso de una mujer de 64 años con agudeza visual de 20/40 en su ojo derecho, debida a una opacificación grisácea y plumosa con microquistes en el epitelio corneal, compatible con una distrofia epitelial de Lisch. Se trató secuencialmente con varios desbridamientos epiteliales, lente de contacto y mitomicina C, a pesar de los cuales, recidivaba. La extirpación de un sector limbar y el trasplante de limbo autólogo obtuvieron buenos resultados y sin recurrencia. Conclusión: El trasplante autólogo de limbo tras extirpar la zona de limbo afectado puede ser considerado como una nueva opción terapéutica en el tratamiento de la distrofia epitelial de Lisch asimétrica, cuando otros tratamientos han fallado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;91(7): 333-336, jul. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154166</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trasplante autólogo de limbo como nuevo tratamiento de la distrofia corneal epitelial de Lisch</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3336^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14573^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24366^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3336^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30006^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52116^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29961^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10063^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
