<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-16368</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characteristics of Antibiotic Prescription in the Ambulatory Consultation of the Department of Medicine at the Cayetano Heredia Hospital, Lima, Perú</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The present descriptive cross-sectional study, assesses the proportion of antibiotic prescription (PPA), and the quality of it (CPA) in the ambulatory consultation of the department of medicine at the Cayetano Heredia Hospital, as an approach to antibiotic use in Peruvian hospitals. Methods: The study population was conformed by the patients who went to outpatient care from January 8th to February 2nd, 2001; a sample size of 120 patients was determined out of 1449 patients, to assess CPA. Data on antibiotic prescription was collected, revised and qualified by three experienced physicians, using as gold standard the United States Pharmacopeial Drug Information criteria. Results: PPA was 13,53% (CI 95%: 11.77%-15.29%), without significant differences according to age, sex, doctor's offices and turns. The most frequent diagnoses with antibiotic prescription were: urinary tract infection and pharyngoamigdalitis; the antibiotics more frequently prescribed were: ciprofloxacine and cotrimoxazol. Of the antibiotics, 70,00% were prescribed as non commercial name and 70,83% were registered in the National Petitory of Essential Drugs. We found that 81,67% (CI 95%:79.68%-83.66%) of the prescriptions were inadequate mainly due to: duration (59.20%) and dose (20.00%) of the antibiotic treatment. Conclusions: PPA obtained is lower than those published in, and CPA is as high as the reported one in other studies. The investigations in this field are still scarse. It is important new research in order to know about prescription, use and adverse reactions of antibiotics. It is necessary to develop a antibiotic policy to improve access and rational use of antibiotic (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ministerio de Sanidad y Consumo</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: La prescripción adecuada de medicamentos incluye, entre otros aspectos, la elección de determinado medicamento en dosis y tiempo requeridos, considerando además su eficacia y conveniencia. El presente estudio transversal descriptivo, tiene como objetivo evaluar la prescripción antibiótica: proporción de prescripción y calidad de la misma, en la consulta ambulatoria del servicio de medicina del Hospital Cayetano Heredia. Métodos: La población estuvo formada por las 1.449 personas que acudieron a la consulta del 8 de enero al 2 de febrero del 2001. Para determinar la calidad se calculó una muestra de 120 personas a partir de las que formaban la población de estudio. La información fue revisada y calificada por tres médicos especialistas, teniendo como patrón referencial la United States Pharmacopeial Drug Information. Resultados: La proporción de prescripción fue del 13,53 per cent (IC 95 per cent: 11,77 per cent-15,29 per cent), sin diferencias estadísticamente significativas según edad, sexo, y consultorios. Los diagnósticos más frecuentes con prescripción antibiótica fueron: infección urinaria y faringoamigdalitis; los antibióticos más prescritos fueron: ciprofloxacina y cotrimoxazol. 70,00 per cent de antibióticos indicados fueron prescritos con nombre genérico y 70,83 per cent se encuentran en el Petitorio Nacional de Medicamentos Esenciales. En relación a la calidad, encontramos 81,67 per cent (IC 95 per cent: 79,68 per cent-83,66 per cent) de prescripciones inadecuadas, en cuanto a duración (59,20 per cent) y dosis (20,00 per cent) del antibiótico. Conclusiones: La proporción de prescripción de antibióticos encontrada fue baja e inferior a la reportada en la literatura, mientras que la calidad inadecuada fue elevada, con valores semejantes a otros estudios. Las investigaciones en este campo son todavía escasas, siendo importante realizar más estudios que permitan documentar las características de la prescripción. Es necesario contar con una política de antibióticos que establezca estrategias dirigidas a mejorar su acceso y uso racional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;76(3): 207-214, mayo 2002.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características de la prescripción antibiótica en los consultorios de medicina del Hospital Cayetano Heredia de Lima, Perú</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Contreras Ríos, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayca Pérez, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llanos Zavalaga, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-16368</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10757</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d555</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2435</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
