<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131117</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To study and understand the needs for informations of the patients in our environment, analyzing specifically the needs for information about their illness and care at the end of life after being diagnosed with cancer. Methods: 820 patients in a survey about diagnosis, prognosis, treatment efficacy and toxicity, as well as palliative care, clinical research, psychological support, spiritual care and wishes of the end of life. Results: Patients majority (695) was aware of their diagnosis, knowing more who had higher education and an age range of 50-70 years. Six hundred seventy-four patients wanted to know their prognosis, being more likely to know those who had secondary and higher education. The majority (562 patients) wanted to know everything about the treatment utility, as well as with respect to toxicity (443) and would value to have information on palliative care and research. Hospitalization also considered as the best place to die (331).  omen were more likely to receive psychological and spiritual help. The most valued physician conditions were knowledge (52.7%), honesty (45.5%) and Humanities (44.3%). The 82.3% of patients appreciated the survey, while 58% considered it useful. However, 23.7 % would recommend it. Conclusions: This study represents, to our knowledge, the first attempt in our country to identify the needs and wishes of patients to know about issues related to their illness. We have observed a search for active participation in decisions related to information management and treatments by patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rivarola, Edgardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Deza, Ernesto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morgenfeld, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montiel, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gercovich, Daniela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Reinas, Gastón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Gerardi, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gercovich, Felipe Gustavo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tognelli, Flavio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudiar las necesidades de los pacientes oncológicos sobre la información referida a su enfermedad y los cuidados al final de la vida. Métodos: 820 pacientes participaron de una encuesta sobre diagnóstico, pronóstico, eficacia y toxicidad de los tratamientos, así como también sobre cuidados paliativos, investigación clínica, apoyo psicológico, cuidados espirituales y deseos del final de la vida. Resultados: 695 pacientes conocen su diagnóstico, especialmente quienes tenían un mayor nivel educativo y un rango etario de 50-70 años. Seiscientos setenta y cuatro pacientes deseaban conocer su pronóstico, estando más predispuestos a conocerlo quienes tenían educación secundaria y superior. La mayoría (562 pacientes) deseaba conocer todo con respecto a la utilidad de los tratamientos, al igual que con respecto a la toxicidad (443) y valoraría contar con información sobre cuidados paliativos e investigación. Además consideraba la internación hospitalaria como el mejor lugar para morir (331). Las mujeres se mostraron más propensas a recibir ayuda psicológica y espiritual. Las condiciones más valoradas en el médico fueron: conocimiento (52,7%), Honestidad (45,5%) y Humanidad (44,3%). Un 82,3% de los pacientes valoraron positivamente la encuesta, mientras que el 58% la consideró útil. Sin embargo un 23,7% la recomendaría. Conclusiones: El estudio representa, en nuestro conocimiento, el primer intento en nuestro medio por identificar las necesidades y los deseos de los pacientes por conocer cuestiones vinculadas con su enfermedad. En este sentido hemos observado una búsqueda de participación activa en las decisiones vinculadas al manejo de la información y los tratamientos por parte de los pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);11(2/3): 389-401, dic. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131117</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de las necesidades de los pacientes respecto a la información y los cuidados médicos tras el diagnóstico de cáncer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32094</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33920</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36317</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36354</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
