<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144184</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship with the Media</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present article discusses the information provided by the Gregorio Marañón University Hospital on 11 March. Firstly, the organization of the hospital's communications office, as well as its functions and objectives are described. Subsequently, we describe the steps taken in the management of information about the crisis provoked by the terrorist attacks in Madrid on 11 March, from the first press conference called by the hospital to requests by the distinct media for information from both the hospital staff and hospitalized patients. Lastly, the public figures who visited the hospital on the day of the attack and on subsequent days are mentioned (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Morante, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se describe la actuación informativa del Hospital General Universitario Gregorio Marañón en la jornada del 11 de marzo. En primer lugar se describe la organización del Gabinete de Comunicación del hospital, sus funciones y sus objetivos. A continuación se detallan los pasos dados en la gestión informativa de la crisis que supuso el atentado terrorista que sufrió Madrid el 11 de marzo, desde la primera rueda de prensa ofrecida por un hospital hasta las solicitudes de información por parte de los distintos medios de comunicación, tanto a profesionales del hospital como a pacientes ingresados. Por último se hace una relación de las personalidades que visitaron el hospital durante el día del atentado y en las jornadas siguientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);124(supl.1): 53-53, mar. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144184</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relaciones con los medios de comunicación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3173</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6904^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3177^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3177^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6904^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3177^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34808</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35430^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6904^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6904^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50135</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
