<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94493</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Care protocol ENLACE-PREALT</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The preparation program on discharge (PREALT-Preparation on Discharge)from the CatSalut (Catalan Health Service) is aimed at patients that are discharged from the hospital and who need domiciliary primary care for 24-48 hours after leaving the hospital. The program is a tool that improves coordination among the different healthcare levels. A need to extend the program was detected and the concept of LIAISON nursing was included in the program: ensuring follow up visits at home or at the primary care centre in less than five natural days to provide continuity of care to all those patients who following their hospital discharge are in need of care.The program was simultaneously designed using the bi-directionality allowed by the flow of information between Primary Care (PC)and Specialised Care in both directions. Between 2007-2008, PCliaison nurses assessed 1.282 patients. 298 required PREALT and 570LIAISON. 202 subjects were interviewed regarding the above mentioned coordination project with a mean of 9,3 (on a scale from de0 to 10). The holistic assessment and the follow up carried out by the PC liaison nurse with a primarist perspective on the hospitalised patient provides an added value both to the primary care teamand to the patient promoting his or her self-autonomy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Puig Girbau, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lladó Blanch, M. Magdalena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El programa de preparación al alta (PREALT) del CatSalut, dirigido a los pacientes que postalta hospitalaria precisan atención domiciliaria en 24-48 h por Atención Primaria, es un instrumento que mejora la coordinación entre los distintos niveles asistenciales. Se percibió la necesidad de ampliarlo con el concepto de ENLACE: garantizar visita a domicilio o en el centro de salud en menos de cinco días naturales, para dar continuidad asistencial a todos los pacientes que postalta hospitalaria requieran continuidad de cuidados.Al mismo tiempo se perfiló con la bidireccionalidad, que permite el flujo de información entre Atención Primaria (AP) y especializada en ambos sentidos. Entre 2007-2008 las enfermerasde enlace de AP valoraron 1.282 pacientes. 298 pacientes precisaron PREALT y 570 ENLACE. Se encuestaron 202 personas que valoraron con una media de 9,3 (en una escala de de 0 a 10) este proyecto de coordinación. La valoración holística y el seguimiento querealiza la enfermera de enlace de AP con perspectiva primarista al paciente ingresado en el hospital, aporta un valor añadido tanto alequipo de Atención Primaria como al paciente y fomenta su autonomía (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;14(6): 61-65, jul. 2011. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94493</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Protocolo de actuación ENLACE-PREALT</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3285^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32196^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29493^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10545^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9922^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201107</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
