<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136897</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Seasonal influenza as the cause of labour disability in health workers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In&amp;#64258;uenza represents an important problem of public health since it is one of the principal causes of respiratory infection  in the general population and is highly contagious. Health workers  are included among risk groups for the disease. This work analyzes the impact that in&amp;#64258;uenza and other acute respiratory infections have as the cause of labour disability in health workers in the Valencian Community and the possible determining factors of it in the period analyzed. We analyze the vaccination coverage in health workers in the last years. Therefore, and with the participation of the occupational medicine department we purpose the strategies to increase this coverage, inmunization is the most effective preventive measure to  avoid the spread of the disease, thus reducing the amount of worker  sick leave (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vico Garcerán, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ligro López, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La gripe representa un importante problema de salud pública ya que es una de las principales causas de infección respiratoria en la población, con elevada capacidad de transmisión. El personal sanitario se considera un colectivo de riesgo para contraer dicha enfermedad. Este trabajo  analiza el impacto que tienen la gripe y otras infecciones respiratorias agudas, como causa de incapacidad laboral en el personal sanitario en la Comunidad Valenciana y posibles factores determinantes de dicha situación en el periodo estudiado. Se analizan las cifras de cobertura vacunal en los últimos años y se proponen estrategias de intervención por parte del Servicio de Prevención de Riesgos Laborales, dirigidas a mejorar la cobertura en los trabajadores expuestos al riesgo de contraer gripe, dado que la vacuna de la gripe estacional es la medida preventiva más e&amp;#64257;caz para evitar la enfermedad, reduciendo así las posibles situaciones de incapacidad temporal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;24(1): 9-16, mar. 2015. graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136897</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La gripe: causa frecuente de incapacidad temporal en personal sanitario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23109</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6432^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d44</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23109^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
