<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041626</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Estimation of vitamin supplements and minerals consumption dispensed through pharmacy offices in the province of Las Palmas</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Vitamin supplements and minerals consumption (SPM) is increasing in occidental societies due to the growing concern abouthealth by the population. Objectives: To have a initial approaching to the to SPM consumption in the Province of Las Palmas through 2000 and 2001. To identify SPM proportions that are dispensed as pharmaceutical specialities and those who are sold as parapharmacy products. Finally, to describe the evolution of this consumption throughout a year. Method: The information was obtained through the list of the whole pharmaceutical specialities and parapharmacy products through 200 and 2001 who have at least a vitamin in its composition and/or a mineral. Results: Usually, 297 pharmaceutical specialities and 216 parapharmacy products are currently being sold. Pharmaceutical specialities comprised 65.6% of the whole products sold and within them, vitamins were the most dispensed (41.5%). Regarding parapharmacy products, vitamins and minerals compounds were the products more sold (34.6%). Comparing to 2000, during 2001 there was a statistically significant increase in the consumption of parapharmacy products, remaining without changes the use of pharmaceutical specialities. Conclusion: On the basis of sold XX SPM consumption seems to bedue mainly by pharmaceutical specialities rather than parapharmacy products. Nevertheless through 2001 there was an increase only in theparapharmacy products</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marrero Montelongo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laínez Sevillano, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sosa Henríquez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serra Majem, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almazán La-Clave, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Rodríguez, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saavedra Santana, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: El consumo de suplementos polivitamínicos y minerales (SPM) está aumentado en las sociedades occidentales como consecuencia de la preocupación de la población por la salud. Objetivos: Tener una primera aproximación al consumo de SPM en la provincia de Las Palmas en los 2000 y 2001. Identificar las proporciones de SPM que son dispensados como especialidades farmacéuticas y los que lo hacen como productos de parafarmacia. Describir cual es la tendencia evolutiva en el consumo de estos SPM en el período de un año. Método: La información se obtuvo de los listados de ventas de todas las especialidades farmacéuticas y productos de parafarmacia de los años 2000 y 2001, que contienen en su composición al menos una vitaminay/o un mineral. Resultados: habitualmente se dispensan 297 especialidades farmacéuticas y 216 productos de parafarmacia. Las especialidades farmacéuticas constituyeron el 65,6% de las ventas y entre ellas, las vitaminas resultaron ser las más dispensadas (41,5%). En las especialidades de parafarmacia, las más vendidas fueron los compuestos de vitaminas y minerales (34,6%). Con respecto al año 2000, en el año 2001 se produjo un aumento estadísticamente significativo en el consumo de productos de parafarmacia, permaneciendo estable el de las especialidades farmacéuticas. Conclusión: en base a las ventas realizadas, en la provincia de Las Palmas el consumo de SPM parece realizarse mayoritariamente por medio de especialidades farmacéuticas y en menor grado mediante productos de parafarmacia. Sin embargo, en el período 2000-2001, se observó un incremento del consumo sólo en los productos de parafarmacia</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;22(10): 469-472, oct. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041626</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estimación del consumo de suplementos vitamínicos y minerales dispensados a través de las oficinas de farmacia de la provincia de Las Palmas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33546</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14523</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4422</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15217</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
