<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130721</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The role of knowledge and of general intellectual skills in the acquisition of complex learning</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The main aim of this work is to examine the relation existing between intellectual ability and the ability to organize knowledge, within the scope of a more general model on the factors explaining the acquisition of knowledge and skills. It attempts to check if a compensatory effect takes place between the general intellectual ability and the ability to organize knowledge. It also attempts to establish whether the learning in people with broader knowledge of a specific domain is determined or explained by the same variables accounting for the learning in people who get smaller knowledge. The results, in a sample of university students, reveal that no interaction takes place between both factors; rather than that, intellectual ability and the quality of the conceptual organization have an additional effect. Nevertheless, it is observed that the effect of intelligence is not the same on the different levels of acquired knowledge (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castejón, Juan L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, Antonio M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gilar, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto, María D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo principal del presente trabajo es examinar la relación existente entre la habilidad intelectual y la habilidad de organización del conocimiento dentro de un modelo más general sobre los factores explicativos de la adquisición de conocimientos y habilidades. Se trata de comprobar si se produce un efecto compensatorio entre la habilidad intelectual general y la habilidad para organizar el conocimiento, así como establecer si el aprendizaje de los sujetos que obtienen un mayor conocimiento en un dominio particular viene predicho/explicado por las mismas variables que explican el aprendizaje de los sujetos que obtienen un menor conocimiento. Los resultados, en una muestra de estudiantes universitarios, indican que no se produce un efecto de interacción entre ambos factores, sino más bien un efecto aditivo. No obstante, sí se observa que el efecto de la inteligencia no es el mismo en los distintos niveles de conocimiento adquirido (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);16(4): 600-605, oct.-dic. 2004. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130721</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El rol del conocimiento y de las habilidades intelectuales generales en la adquisición del aprendizaje complejo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8776</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7528</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54394</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
