<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89351</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation and diagnostic approach to the child with mental retardation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The assessment of a child with developmental delay/mental retardation should be carried out following the current evidence-based recommendations. Establishing an etiological diagnosis allows to provide valuable information on the prognosis and clinical management of the child, and offer genetic counseling to his family. The main elements of the assessment include a detailed medical history, a thorough physical examination, and the judicious use of available tests and investigations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Miñaúr, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La valoración y el estudio de un niño con retraso del desarrollo psicomotor /retraso mental debe hacerse de forma adecuada y de acuerdo con la recomendaciones vigentes basadas en la evidencia científica. Establecer un diagnóstico etiológico en estos casos permite aportar información muy valiosa para la atención y el seguimiento del niño y para el asesoramiento genético de su familia. Los elementos fundamentales de dicha valoración incluyen una historia clínica detallada, una exploración minuciosa, y un ejemplo razonado de las pruebas complementarias disponibles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;65(1): 20-23, ene.-feb. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89351</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración y aproximación diagnóstica al niño con retraso mental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5950^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2704^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28219^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28087^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12033^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
