<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94723</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endovascular treatment for acute stroke: an open field to begin</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The evidence that recanalization and reperfusion of the distal vascular bed in appropriately selected patients is crucial to achieve good functional outcome has triggered interest and research into endovascular treatment of acute ischemic stroke.Development: Intravenous (iv) thrombolytic therapy is the treatment of choice in patients with acute ischemic stroke, however, it has certain limitations. Endovascular treatment is a promising alternative with theoretical advantages over iv therapy, such as an increased frequency of recanalization and longer therapeutic windows. Endovascular reperfusion strategies include intra-arterial fibrinolysis with drugs, or endovascular mechanical devices for thrombectomy or thrombus disruption, thromboaspiration, or thrombus entrapment in the vessel wall. The ideal of comprehensive treatment of acute stroke would provide specificity to treat an individual patient: with specific arterial occlusion and collaterals and a determined physiology of acute cerebral ischemia. With all this information, we would decide the best therapeutic strategy for the patient, and move from just a time-based approach to include a pathophysiology approach as well, and thus different patients could have different therapeutic windows. The endovascular treatment situation in Spain is heterogeneous and requires human and material resources to enable it to be implemented throughout the country.  Conclusions: Endovascular treatment of stroke is a new therapeutic tool for achieving reperfusion safely in patients ineligible for Alteplase or who have failed reperfusion with an iv fibrinolytic (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Serna Candel, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matías Guiu, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Ibor, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La evidencia de que la recanalización y la reperfusión del lecho vascular distal de pacientes adecuadamente seleccionados son fundamentales para lograr un buen pronóstico funcional ha disparado el interés y la investigación sobre el tratamiento endovascular del ictus isquémico agudo. Desarrollo: La fibrinólisis intravenosa (i.v.) es el tratamiento de elección en pacientes con ictus isquémico agudo, aunque presenta ciertas limitaciones. El tratamiento endovascular supone una alternativa prometedora con ventajas teóricas sobre el tratamiento i.v., como una mayor frecuencia de recanalización y mayor ventana terapéutica. Las estrategias de reperfusión endovascular incluyen fibrinólisis intraarterial con fármacos o tratamiento mecánico con dispositivos que permiten extracción, aspiración, disrupción o atrapamiento del trombo en la pared. El ideal del tratamiento integral del ictus agudo sería aportar especificidad al paciente individual: tratar una oclusión arterial con unas colaterales y con una fisiología de la isquemia cerebral aguda determinadas. Con todos estos datos, ante cualquier paciente podremos decidir la mejor estrategia terapéutica y pasar de un enfoque del paciente basado únicamente en el tiempo a un enfoque basado también en la fisiopatología; por lo tanto, distintos pacientes tendrían diferentes ventanas terapéuticas. La situación del tratamiento endovascular en España es heterogénea y precisa de recursos materiales y humanos para conseguir su implantación en todo el territorio. Conclusiones: El tratamiento endovascular del ictus supone una nueva herramienta terapéutica para lograr la reperfusión de una forma segura en los pacientes no candidatos a alteplasa o que no han conseguido reperfundir con el fibrinolítico i.v (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;25(5): 273-278, jul. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94723</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento endovascular del ictus agudo: un campo muy abierto que está por iniciar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29633</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24892^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30438^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5453^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23812^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54238^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201007</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
