<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74772</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Maxillofacial injury by bull goring: literature review and case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Injuries produced by bull goring are relativelycommon in Spain and South American countries, where bullfightsare scheduled regularly. These wounds have specific characteristicsthat differentiate them from any other type of wounds.Material and methods. In the summer of 2005, an 18-year-oldmale patient was brought to the Hospital 12 de Octubre byemergency services after being gored in the cervicofacial regionduring the running of the bulls in San Sebastián de los Reyes. Thepatient had an anfractuous, penetrating and blunt wound extendingfrom the left supraclavicular region to the left lip commissure,comminuted fracture of the left mandibular angle and rightmandibular body, dentoalveolar fractures of pieces 1.3 to 2.3, andsevere laceration of the lingual musculature and mouth floor.Discussion. Most patients who suffer multiple injuries as a result ofbull goring are men, with a mean age of 30 years. Victims usuallyare spontaneous participants, bullfighting fans rather thanprofessional bullfighters. The wounds produced by the horns of thebull may be located anywhere in the body, but the most frequentlocation in all the series reviewed was the lower limb. The cervicofacialregion is one of less frequently affected regions in all the series. Allauthors agree that these injuries have a low incidence despite thehuge number of bullfight fans and curious spectators who areattracted by bullfight events. Emergency treatment is requiredbecause of the particular characteristics of the mechanism of injury.The patient should be taken as rapidly as possible to a hospital.Authors generally agree that any patient who has been gored by abull must be considered initially, for purposes of management, asa patient with multiple injuries...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montalvo Moreno, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arenaz Búa, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luaces Rey, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rey Biel, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo Escudero, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Rozado, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Cedrún, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las heridas por asta de toro son relativamente frecuentesen España y países iberoamericanos, donde los espectáculos con estos animalesson habituales. Dichas heridas presentan unas características específicas que las diferenciande cualquier otro tipo de heridas.Material y método. Se presenta el caso de un paciente varón de 18 años, remitido alHospital 12 de Octubre por el SAMUR tras sufrir una cornada en la región cérvicofacialdurante los encierros de San Sebastián de los Reyes en el verano de 2005. Elpaciente presenta una herida inciso-contusa y anfractuosa desde la región supraclavicularizquierda hasta la comisura labial ipsilateral, con fractura mandibularconminuta a nivel de ángulo izquierdo y cuerpo derecho, fractura dentoalveolar depiezas 1.3 a 2.3, y laceración severa de la musculatura lingual y suelo de boca.Discusión. La mayor parte de los politraumatizados por asta de toro son varones, conuna edad media de 30. Las victimas suelen ser participantes espontáneos, aficionadosa los eventos taurinos y no toreros profesionales.Si bien las heridas por asta de toro pueden producirse en cualquier parte del cuerpo,la localización más frecuente en todas las series revisadas es el miembro inferior. Laregión cérvicofacial es una de las menos afectadas en todas las series. Todos los autorescoinciden en la baja incidencia de heridas pese a la gran cantidad de aficionadosy curiosos atraídos y por esta modalidad de festejos taurinos. Por todas las característicasparticulares del mecanismo de lesión, el tratamiento debe ser urgente y deberealizarse un traslado lo más rápidamente posible a un hospital. Todos los autoresestán de acuerdo en que inicialmente el paciente con una lesión por asta de torodebe ser considerado un paciente politraumatizado y tratado como tal...AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;30(5): 353-362, sept.-oct. 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74772</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Herida por asta de toro en el área maxilofacial: revisión de la literatura y presentación de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22947^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8613^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15348^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15348^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
