<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108987</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-1959</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">COPD and smoking habit: what do we see in a Primary Care Medical Office?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To know the prevalence of smoking in patients diagnosed of COPD in our Primary Health Care Site, and the profile of the patients who smoke and are ex-smokers, to optimize their health care. Patients and methods. Observational study on 94 patients diagnosed of COPD, collecting the variables regarding their smoking habit using a targeted questionnaire. Results. A total of 93.6% of the patients were male, with mean age of 74±10 years; 74.5% were exsmokers, 20.2% active smokers and 5.3% non-smokers. Of the smokers, 47.4% had mild dependence on nicotine, 47.4% moderate and 5.2% severe; 78.9% of all of them had low motivation to quit smoking, this being moderate in 15.5% and high in 5.3%. A total of 63.15% were in the precontemplation phase. 31.6% in contemplation phase and 5.3% in preparation phase. Some previous attempts to quit smoking had been made by 78.9% of the smokers, with a mean of 1.66 attempts. Relapses were due to abstinence syndrome in 53.3%, and to social pressure in 26.7%. Pharmacological help had been received by 4.3% of the ex-smokers, all through Specialized Care. Both cardiovascular diseases and neoplasms were more frequent in the ex-smokers than in the smokers (40% versus 23.3%, and 28.6% versus 15%, respectively, p&gt;0.05 for both comparisons). Conclusions. A total of 20.2% of our patients with COPD are smokers, more than 50% of them have moderate-high nicotine dependence and 63% of them are in pre-contemplation phase.  Knowing the profile of COPD patients regarding their smoking habit will allow us to improve their health care, without forgetting that training and motivation of the professionals is fundamental to achieve and maintain smoking cessation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pulido Fernández, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alzate Gallego, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo Fernández, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Ruiz, C. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parra Caballero, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Pulido, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Conocer la prevalencia de tabaquismo en los pacientes diagnosticados de EPOC en nuestro Centro de Atención Primaria, así como el perfil de los pacientes fumadores y exfumadores, para optimizar su atención sanitaria. Pacientes y método. Estudio observacional sobre 94 pacientes diagnosticados de EPOC, recogiendo las variables referentes a su tabaquismo mediante cuestionario dirigido. Resultados. El 93,6% de los pacientes fueron varones, con una edad media de 74±10 años; 74,5% eran exfumadores, 20,2% fumadores activos y 5,3% no fumadores. De los fumadores, 47,4% tenían una dependencia leve a la nicotina, 47,4% moderada y 5,2% grave; 78,9% de todos ellos tenían una motivación baja para el abandono, siendo esta moderada en 15,5% y alta en un 5,3%. El 63,15% se encontraban en fase precontemplativa, el 31,6% en fase contemplativa y el 5,3% en fase de preparación. El 78,9% de los fumadores había tenido algún intento previo de deshabituación, con una media de 1,66 intentos; el 53,3% de las recaídas se debieron al síndrome de abstinencia, y el 26,7% a la presión social. El 4,3% de los exfumadores habían recibido ayuda farmacológica, todos ellos a través de Atención Especializada. Tanto las enfermedades cardiovasculares como las neoplasias fueron más frecuentes en los exfumadores que en los fumadores (40% frente a 23,3%, y 28,6% frente a 15% respectivamente, p&gt;0,05 para ambas comparaciones). Conclusiones. El 20,2% de nuestros pacientes con EPOC son fumadores, más del 50% de ellos tienen moderada-alta dependencia por la nicotina y el 63% de ellos se encuentran en fase de precontemplación. Conocer el perfil de los pacientes EPOC respecto a su tabaquismo nos permitirá mejorar su atención sanitaria, sin olvidar que la formación y motivación de los profesionales es fundamental para lograr y mantener la deshabituación tabáquica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prev. tab;14(4): 159-164, oct.-dic. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108987</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">EPOC y hábito tabáquico: ¿qué nos encontramos en una consulta de Atención Primaria?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33882^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9723^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9723^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
