<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72870</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-695X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Do we need new tools to evaluate Primary Care house physicians?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The education of house physicians should include an evaluation of the competence they have acquiredduring their training. The current programme for this speciality establishes a training evaluationsystem whose aim is to monitor the achievement of teaching objectives. For this purpose tools suchas self-assessment of objectives and activities performed, analysis of clinical records, analysis ofcase studies, demonstrations of diagnostic and treatment techniques, analysis of records in theSpecialist in Training Book, analysis of other records concerning theoretical-practical activities, videorecordings, objective, structured clinical evaluation, as well as other systems for the evaluation ofteaching objectives. Furthermore for the total evaluation, in addition to the above mentioned tools,the following are proposed: a record of the compliance to the activities, a record of attendance tothe programmed activities, written multi-test assessments and others that the Evaluation Committeemay propose.We propose the use of a new tool: the Script Concordance Test, based on a cognitive theory ofthe development of clinical expertise (&#147;the scripts theory&#148;). This test places examinees in written,but authentic, clinical situations in which they must interpret data to make decisions. It is a writtensimulation test and can be either paper- or computer-based and can be used in undergraduate, postgraduate,or continuing medical education. It is designed to probe whether the clinical knowledge ofexaminees is effi ciently organized for making appropriate clinical decisions, whether these are relatedto diagnosis, investigation or treatment(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Torres Hidalgo, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escobar Rabadán, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La tutorización de residentes debe incluir una evaluación de la adquisición de competencias a lolargo de su formación. El actual programa de la especialidad establece un sistema de evaluaciónformativa con el fi n de monitorizar la consecución de los objetivos docentes, para la que se proponeninstrumentos como la autovaloración de objetivos y actividades realizadas, análisis de registrosclínicos, análisis de casos clínicos, demostraciones de técnicas diagnósticas y terapéuticas, análisisde los registros anotados en el Libro de especialista en formación, análisis de otros tipos de registrosreferentes a actividades teórico-prácticas, vídeo-grabaciones, evaluación clínica objetiva y estructurada,no descartando otros sistemas de valoración de objetivos docentes. Por otra parte, parala evaluación sumativa, además de los anteriores instrumentos, se proponen el registro de cumplimientode actividades, el registro de asistencia a actividades programadas, evaluaciones escritasmultitest y otros que puedan ser propuestos por la Comisión de Evaluación.Proponemos el uso de un nuevo instrumento: el Test de Concordancia de Scripts, basado en unateoría cognitiva del desarrollo de la pericia clínica (&#147;teoría de los scripts&#148;). Este test sitúa a los examinadosante situaciones clínicas escritas, pero auténticas, en la que tienen que interpretar datospara tomar decisiones. Pertenece al tipo de simulaciones escritas, pudiendo ser realizada con papelu ordenador, y puede ser usado en no graduados, graduados o en educación médica continuada. Eltest está diseñado para probar si la organización del conocimiento clínico permite decisiones clínicasadecuadas, ya sean diagnósticas, de investigación o terapéuticas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. clín. med. fam;2(6): 280-285, feb.2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72870</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Necesitamos nuevos instrumentos para la evaluación de los residentes de Medicina de Familia?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7560^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11253^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11253^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11253^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11253^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11253^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
