<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91363</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Obstetrical care provided by advanced life support units of the out-hospital 061 emergency services of Aragón</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to analyse, depending on sociodemographic variables, the outhospitalobstetrical care provided by Advance Life Support Units (ALS)of the 061 Emergency Services of Aragón.Material and methods: cross-sectional descriptive study of the 061ofAragón between 2004 and 2008 by review of clinical records. 265obstetrical care visits were analysed based on the following variables:maternal age, gestational age, immigration status, parity, pregnancy care,and ALS unit. Descriptive statistical indexes were calculated and a bivariateanalysis performed by means of the ANOVA and chi square test.Results: the prevalence of obstetrical care was 0.25%, normal deliverybeing the most common cause for the provision of emergency care in76,6% of the cases. Mean age of the pregnant women whom receivedcare was 27,9. Mean gestational age was 37,6 weeks in patients with anormal delivery, although it significantly decreased (p &lt;0,001) in patientsthat had pregnancy pathology. Pregnancies that had had prenatalcare resulted in normal delivery in 75% of the cases, versus 49% in caseswith no prenatal care (p = 0,015).Conclusions: maternal age, parity, immigration status and ALS unit didnot have an impact on the type of obstetrical care provided by an out-hospitalemergency service. A possible relationship between gestational age,pregnancy/prenatal care and type of obstetrical care provided wasobserved. Further additional research is needed to gain further insightinto this phenomenon (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mir Ramos, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Azón López, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: analizar, en función de variables sociodemográficas, la asistenciaobstétrica extrahospitalaria prestada por unidades de Soporte Vital Avanzado(SVA) del 061 Aragón.Material y métodos: estudio descriptivo transversal realizado en 061Aragón entre 2004 y 2008 mediante revisión de historias clínicas. Seanalizaron 265 asistencias obstétricas en función de las variables: edadmaterna, edad gestacional, inmigración, paridad, control del embarazo yunidad de SVA. Se calcularon índices de estadística descriptiva y análisisbivariante mediante el test de ANOVA y el de Ji Cuadrado.Resultados: la prevalencia de asistencia obstétrica fue del 0,25%, siendoel parto normal la causa más común de atención en el 76,6% de loscasos. La edad media de la gestante atendida fue de 27,9. La edad gestacionalmedia fue de 37,6 semanas en pacientes con parto normal, perodisminuía significativamente (p &lt;0,001) en pacientes con patología de embarazo.Los embarazos controlados culminaron en parto normal en el75% de los casos, frente a un 49% en el caso de que el embarazo no hubieraestado controlado (p = 0,015).Conclusiones: la edad materna, paridad, inmigración y unidad de SVAno influyen en el tipo de asistencia obstétrica prestada por un servicio deemergencias extrahospitalarias. Se sugiere una posible relación entreedad gestacional, control del embarazo y tipo de asistencia obstétricaprestada. Se precisa investigación adicional para comprender mejor estefenómeno (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;14(5): 20-24, jun. 2011. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91363</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asistencia obstétrica por unidades de soporte vitalavanzado del servicio de emergenciasextrahospitalarias 061 de Aragón</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35396^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7922^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
