<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156670</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Onychomycosis by yeast not common in diabetics of a health center</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Mexican diabetic population frequently presents mycosis under foot hyperkeratosis; however, in another type of onychomycosis as the ones that is assumed Candida albicans is the causal agent, it is unknown the frequency, the prevalence and if another Candida species or other yeasts are found. Objective. Evaluate the frequency of yeasts causing onychomycosis in diabetic patients looked after in public institutions of health of the State of Hidalgo, Mexico, and its association with clinical epidemiological variables. Materials and methods. An observational, descriptive and transversal study was made on 261 patients, from which one nail sample of each one was obtained, used to isolate and identify dermatophytes and yeasts; the results were statistically correlated with 24 epidemiological parameters. The clinical study was done through interrogation and by medical exploration in order to evaluate Tinea pedis and onychomycosis. Results. Onychomycosis were caused by Candida guilliermondii, Candida parapsilosis, Candida glabrata, Candida krusei, Candida spp., Kodamaea ohmeri, Prototheca wickerhamii and unidentified yeasts. The prevalence for general onychomycosis, by dermatophytes, mixed onychomycosis and by yeasts were: 24.1, 19.5, 2.3 and 14.6%, respectively. Patients with significant probability to be diagnosed as having onychomycosis by yeasts are those wearing open shoes (2.59%); technicians and professionals (10.49%) and alcohol drinkers (3.72%). Conclusion. The fact that Candida albicans is not present in this study as causal agent of onychomycosis, and emerging and non-common yeasts were indeed isolated, creates new challenges. It is remarked the clinical criterion that when onychomycosis is suspected in diabetics, the diagnosis for culturing dermatophytes and yeasts should be included (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Imbert, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blasco, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gomez, JVG</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escudero, RB</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La población diabética mexicana frecuentemente presenta micosis bajo la hiperqueratosis del pie; sin embargo, en otro tipo de onicomicosis, como las supuestamente causadas por Candida albicans, no se conoce la frecuencia, la prevalencia y si se encuentra otra especie de Candida u otras levaduras. Objetivo. Evaluar la frecuencia de levaduras causantes de onicomicosis en pacientes diabéticos atendidos en instituciones públicas de salud del Estado de Hidalgo, México, y su asociación con variables clínico-epidemiológicas. Materiales y métodos. Se realizó un estudio observacional, descriptivo y transversal en 261 pacientes, de los que se obtuvo una muestra de uña de los pies, de la cual se aislaron e identificaron dermatofitos y levaduras; los resultados se correlacionaron estadísticamente con 24 variables epidemiológicas. El estudio clínico fue mediante interrogatorio y exploración médica, evaluando Tinea pedis y onicomicosis. Resultados. Las onicomicosis las causaron Candida guilliermondii, Candida parapsilosis, Candida glabrata, Candida krusei, Candida spp., Kodamaea ohmeri, Prototheca wickerhamii y levaduras no identificadas. Las prevalencias de onicomicosis general, por dermatofitos, mixta y por levaduras fueron de 24,1, 19,5, 2,3 y 14,6%, respectivamente. Los pacientes con probabilidades de onicomicosis por levaduras son los que utilizan calzado abierto (2,59%); con ocupación técnica o profesional (10,49%) y que consumen alcohol (3,72%). Conclusión. El no encontrar Candida albicans en este estudio como causa de onicomicosis, y sí, en cambio, levaduras emergentes y no comunes, plantea nuevos retos. Se recomienda el criterio clínico de que al sospechar onicomicosis en diabéticos, el diagnóstico incluya cultivo para dermatofitos y levaduras (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);42(7): 449-457, oct. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156670</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Onicomicosis por levaduras no comunes en diabéticos de un centro de salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15401^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30899^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24426</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2208^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30899^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
