<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163893</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Surrogate motherhood and woman dignity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Motherhood by subrogation is an issue that directly affects human rights and, ultimately, human dignity. Therefore, if we want to give an adequate response to this issue, it is essential to reflect on how this practice affects the dignity and rights of the people involved in it and, more specifically, the pregnant mother. This study tries to show how in relation to the latter, maternity by subrogation directly contradicts some basic requirements of human dignity, since it reifies, instrumentalizes, convert into an object of commerce, and disregards the personal uniqueness of pregnant women (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aparisi Miralles, Ángela</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La maternidad por subrogación es una cuestión que afecta directamente a los derechos humanos y, en definitiva, a la dignidad humana. Por ello, si se quiere dar una adecuada respuesta a este tema, es imprescindible reflexionar sobre cómo dicha práctica afecta a la dignidad y a los derechos de las personas implicadas y, más en concreto, a la madre gestante. En este estudio se intenta mostrar cómo en relación a ésta última, la maternidad por subrogación contradice directamente algunas exigencias básicas de la dignidad humana, ya que, en definitiva, mercantiliza, instrumentaliza, cosifica, discrimina y disgrega la unicidad personal de la mujer gestante (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad Bioet;28(93): 163-175, mayo-ago. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163893</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Maternidad subrogada y dignidad de la mujer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37617</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27859</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36369</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36358</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29201^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6958</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
