<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78658</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-1285</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Participation of dentist in oral cancer control: management in prevention, treatment and rehabilitation. Review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cancer is a complex disease, beeing a major cause of morbidity. Mortality is high, with less than 50% of oral cancer patients have no cure. Dentist have a unique opportunity to detect malignant neoplasms while they are asymptomatic and unsuspected. Hence early diagnosis of a lesion, combined with adequated treatment, seems to be the most effective way to improve oral cancer control. Therefore the importance of dentist who share a relevant responsibility in the management of oral cancer, from diagnosis through rehabilitation. The dentist is most often the first clinician consulted for oral complaints and therefore has the responsibility of differentiating bening from precancerous and malignity and the opportunity to early derivation. When diagnosis is comfirmed by experts, the public health programs are critical in emphasizing the need for a previous routine oral examination, in order to promove oral health before oncologic therapy. Treatment of oral cancer often produces certain dysfunctions in speech, mastication, swallowing and dental and mucosa complains, therefore, oral rehabilitation becomes a major consideration to the patient. Optimal oral cancer control calls for a diversity of approaches among many health professionals. The complexities of optimal diagnosis, management and control require a multidisciplinary team (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casariego,  ZJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cáncer es una enfermedad compleja siendo una de las mayores causas de morbilidad. La mortalidad es alta, ya que menos del 50% de los pacientes curan. El odontólogo tiene una única oportunidad de reconocer neoplasias malignas cuando ellas todavía son asintomáticas e insospechadas. Por lo cual, la detección temprana de una lesión, combinada con una tratamiento adecuado, parecería ser el modo más efectivo para mejorar el control del cáncer. De ahí la importancia del odontólogo, quien adquiere una real responsabilidad en el manejo del cáncer oral, desde el diagnóstico hasta la rehabilitación. En la mayoría de los casos, éste es el primer clínico consultado ante un dolor bucal y tiene la responsabilidad de diferenciar entre una lesión precancerosa y una malignidad y la derivación oportuna. Confirmado el diagnóstico por los expertos, los programas de salud pública son críticos hoy en día en enfatizar la necesidad del examen odontológico de rutina previo y promover un estado de salud bucal. El tratamiento del cáncer oral a menudo produce disfunciones y distorsiones en el habla, masticación, salivación, dolor de las piezas dentales y de la mucosa, de ahí que la rehabilitación oral es la mejor consideración que se le puede brindar al paciente. El control óptimo del cáncer oral necesita de una cantidad de medidas entre muchos profesionales de la salud. La complejidad de un diagnóstico óptimo, manejo y control requiere de un equipo multidisciplinario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av Odontoestomatol;25(5): 265-285, sept.-oct. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78658</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La participación del odontólogo en el control del cáncer oral: Manejo en la prevención, tratamiento y rehabilitación. Revisión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22570^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22570^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22570^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
