<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166665</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The aims of the Stent-for-Life initiative in Spain in 2010-2013</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The mission of the Stent-for-Life (SFL) Initiative is to improve the delivery of and access to the life-saving indication of primary percutaneous coronary intervention, thereby reducing mortality and morbidity in patients with acute coronary syndrome. In October 2009, Dr. Fina Mauri signed the SFL Initiative certificate and committed the Spanish Society of Cardiology to this European program. Between June 2010 and June 2013, a range of projects will be developed under the SFL Initiative in Spain. Their success crucially depends on the involvement of all sectors of the health-care system. The aim of this article was to describe the projects planned under the SFL Initiative for Spain over the next 3 years (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Goicolea, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabaté, Manel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Feldman, Matías F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macayad, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de Stent for Life en España es mejorar el acceso de los pacientes con infarto agudo de miocardio a la intervención coronaria percutánea primaria y conseguir una tasa de reperfusión mediante esta técnica con el fin de reducir la morbilidad y la mortalidad de los pacientes que sufren esta enfermedad aguda. En octubre del año 2009, la Dra. Fina Mauri, expresidenta de la Sección de Hemodinámica y Cardiología Intervencionista de la Sociedad Española de Cardiología, en el Congreso PCR en Barcelona, firmó el certificado de adhesión de la Sociedad Española de Cardiología a la iniciativa europea Stent for Life. Para conseguir el éxito de este programa, es de vital importancia contar con todos los actores participantes en el sistema de salud. A continuación se detallan los principales objetivos de esta iniciativa en España para el periodo comprendido entre junio de 2010 y junio de 2013 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);11(supl.C): 6c-8c, 2011. ilus, mapas</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166665</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Objetivos de Stent for Life en España para el periodo 2010-2013</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16833</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6448^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23771^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55037^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6438</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201100</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
