<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-66874</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report: We report the follow-up of a case ofchoroideremia who underwent three white-on-whiteautomated visual field and three scanning laserpolarimetry (SLP) examinations by means of aGDx VCC in the course of one year. A bilateralperimetric deterioration in indices and scotomaswas found. As a result, retinal nerve fiber layerretardation parameters and maps changed on GDxVCC advanced serial analyses in both eyes.Discussion: Serial analyses with GDx VCC may beused as objective and quantitative tests to assess theprogression of chorioretinal dystrophies like choroideremia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zanón-Moreno, VC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Medina, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Medina, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinazo-Durán, MD</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego-Pinazo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Presentamos el seguimiento de uncaso de coroideremia que fue sometido a tres camposvisuales automatizados blanco-blanco y trespolarimetrías láser (PL) con GDx VCC en el transcursode un año. Se encontró un deterioro perimétricoen índices y escotomas. En concordancia, losparámetros de retardo de la capa de fibras nerviosasde la retina y los mapas cambiaron en un análisisserial avanzado con GDx VCC en los dos ojos.Discusión: El análisis con GDx VCC puede ser unmétodo objetivo y cuantitativo para evaluar la progresiónde las distrofias coriorretinianas como lacoroideremia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;83(8): 487-492, ago. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-66874</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24565^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10129^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23247^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24565^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12987^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12987^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8013^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12987^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12987^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200808</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
