<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88399</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical and radiological study of three cases of aggressive course testicular lymphomas</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: To describe the clinical and radiological features, and the role of imaging in diagnosis and extension study of testicular lymphoma (TL).METHODS: Testicular and inguinal color Doppler ultrasound, extension-study Multidetector Computed Tomography (MDCT), and Doppler ultrasound and MDCT in an upper extermity metastasis were performed.RESULTS: Case 1: A 65-year-old man with TL 11 years ago, recurrence in the contralateral testis 5 years later, orbital involvement at 8 years and currently recurrence in the arm with ulnar nerve infiltration. Case 2: A 44-year-old man with TL and metastatic inguinal lymphadenopathy. Case 3: An 85 year-old man with TL, retroperitoneal lymph nodes and obstructive uropathy. Histological subtype: B-cell non-Hodgkin´s lymphoma.CONCLUSIONS: TL typically presents as an aggressive disease with contralateral testicular involvement and spreading to regional lymph nodes and non-contiguous extranodal sites. The main radiological techniques are Doppler ultrasound for the study of the primary disease and MDCT in the evaluation of disease extension. Diagnosis is usually obtained after orchiectomy by histological study, and despite the aggressive treatment modalities (surgery associated with radiotherapy or chemotherapy) prognosis remains poor(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sáez Barranquero, Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanes Berenguel, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicioso Recio, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego Domínguez, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Illescas Megías, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez Moreno, Antonio Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Describir las características clínico-radiológicas y las pruebas de imagen en el diagnóstico y extensión/seguimiento del linfoma testicular (LT).MÉTODOS: Se realizó ecografía-doppler color testicular, inguinal, estadiaje con Tomografía Computarizada Multidetector (TCMD); y ecografía-doppler y TCMD en una metástasis cutánea.RESULTADOS: Caso 1: Paciente de 65 años con LT hace 11 años, recidiva en el testículo contralateral 5 años después, metástasis orbitaria a los 8 años y actualmente recidiva con infiltración del nervio cubital. Caso 2: Paciente de 44 años con LT y adenopatías inguinales metastásicas. Caso 3: Paciente de 85 años con LT, adenopatías retroperitoneales y uropatía obstructiva.Histología: LNH difuso B.CONCLUSIONES: El LT suele cursar de forma agresiva, con afectación testicular contralateral, extensión extratesticular o a distancia. Las principales técnicas radiológicas son la ecografía-doppler para el estudio de la enfermedad primaria y el TCMD en la extensión. El diagnóstico es histológico y el tratamiento quirúrgico asociado a radioterapia o quimioterapia, siendo el pronóstico malo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;64(2): 124-129, mar. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88399</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio clínico-radiológico de tres casos de linfomas testiculares de curso agresivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8384^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14115^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22878^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8398^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9557^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
