<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117159</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Emotional Inteligence in Sport: Validation of the Schutte Self Report Inventory (SSRI) in Spanish athletes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this study we analyzed the validation and reliability of the SSRI Schutte's et al. (1998) Inventory of Emotional Intelligence using EFA and CFA with Spanish athletes of different expertise level. This sample was comprised of 2091 athletes (1519 males and 572 females) with a mean age of 20.8 years (ST: 6.14) and an age range of 11 to 59 years. The results obtained in this study presented a four dimensions structure (Emotional perception, self-emotional management, hetero-emotional management and emotional utilization), and a global score of emotional intelligence in Sport. Psychometric properties and reliability of this instrument permits to offer an inventory apt to be applied in sport contexts (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palomo-Nieto, Miriam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Coll, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Graupera-Sanz, José-Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Pérez, Luis-Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El propósito del estudio fue validar el Inventario de Inteligencia Emocional (SSRI) de Schutte et al. (1998) en una muestra de deportistas españoles de diferente nivel de pericia. Participaron 2091 deportistas (1519 hombres y 572 mujeres) de edades comprendidas entre los 11 y los 59 años (M= 20.8; DT= 6.14). Los resultados de los AFE y AFC mostraron que el cuestionario presenta una estructura de cuatro dimensiones (percepción emocional, gestión auto-emocional, gestión hetero-emocional y utilización emocional), además de permitir obtener un valor de la escala general denominado Inteligencia Emocional en el Deporte. Las propiedades psicométricas y fiabilidad de la escala permiten presentar un inventario apto para la medición de la inteligencia emocional en el deporte (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;13(1): 25-36, ene.-jun. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117159</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inteligencia Emocional en el Deporte: Validación española del Schutte Self Report Inventory (SSRI) en deportistas españoles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53742</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7529</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
