<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128089</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Model of huntington disease induced with-3 nitropropionic acid</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Huntington&#146;s disease is an autosomal dominant hereditary disorder. This neurodegenerative illness is characterized by mutation of the huntingtin protein gene, causing the formation of intracellular protein aggregates. Development. Intensive research efforts have been made to investigate the molecular mechanism involved. For this reason, the development of animal and cellular models of Huntington&#146;s disease has offered alternative approaches to study of this disease. The alteration of succinate dehydrogenase activity has been linked to Huntington&#146;s disease. 3-nitropropionic acid is an inhibitor of this enzyme, prompting oxidative stress and death neuronal, mimic some aspects of Huntington&#146;s disease as anatomical, physiological and chemical changes. Conclusion. This model is a useful tool to study the mechanisms involved in this disease and to evaluate new therapeutic strategies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santamaría, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Túnez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La enfermedad de Huntington es un trastorno hereditario autosómico dominante. Esta patología neurodegenerativa se genera aparentemente por la mutación del gen que codifica para la proteína huntingtina, y resulta en la formación de agregados intracelulares. Desarrollo. Se han llevado a cabo hasta ahora diversos esfuerzos para investigar los mecanismos moleculares patogénicos. Por ello, el desarrollo de modelos animales y celulares de la enfermedad de Huntington ofrece valiosas aproximaciones para el estudio de esta enfermedad. La alteración de la actividad de la enzima succinato deshidrogenasa se ha ligado al desarrollo de la enfermedad de Huntington. El ácido 3-nitropropiónico es un inhibidor de esta enzima que induce estrés oxidativo y muerte neuronal, así como mimetiza algunos aspectos de la enfermedad de Huntington como los cambios neuroanatómicos, fisiológicos y químicos. Conclusión. Este modelo constituye una herramienta útil para el estudio fenomenológico de los mecanismos involucrados en esta enfermedad y para el análisis de nuevas estrategias terapéuticas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;48(8): 430-434, abr. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128089</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Modelo de enfermedad de Huntington inducido con ácido 3-nitropropiónico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13770^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32101^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4813^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30920^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4255</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30204^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
