<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-MFM2-10779</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The Marshmallow Challenge: Working on skills for teamwork, leadership, and problem solving</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">According to 'orden CIN' (CIN/2134/2008) and the White Paper on Nursing, the teaching staff must work with Nursing students on four different areas: professional values, communication skills and interpersonal relations, decision making in clinical practice, and teamwork management. In the setting of game-based pedagogy, the introduction in the classroom of the 'Marshmallow Challenge' was considered a useful activity to reflect and delve into teamwork aspects, promoting the skills of collaboration, shared leadership, empathy and creativity from a recreational approach and through everyday situations away from the clinical level. This work was conducted with Nursing Degree students in their third year, within the subject Tutored Practices III. The activity consisted primarily in working on teamwork and shared leadership skills through the game, and subsequently translating the knowledge generated into a clinical situation by solving a case. The activity was evaluated very positively by students; they considered that introducing the game in the classroom was a very creative and useful manner to develop skills that can be subsequently implemented in the performance of their professional role (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Blázquez, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Gil, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arlandis Casanova, Matilde</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sellán Soto, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Gallardo, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palmar Santos, Ana M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Según la orden CIN (CIN/2134/2008) y el Libro Blanco de Enfermería, el personal docente ha de trabajar con los estudiantes de Enfermería en cuatro dominios diferentes: valores profesionales, habilidades de comunicación y relaciones interpersonales, toma de decisiones en la práctica clínica y gestión del trabajo en equipo. En el marco de la pedagogía basada en el juego se planteó introducir en el aula el Reto del Malvavisco como una actividad para reflexionar y profundizar sobre aspectos de trabajo en equipo, fomentando las capacidades de colaboración, liderazgo distribuido, empatía y creatividad desde un planteamiento lúdico y a través de situaciones cotidianas alejadas del plano clínico. Se trabajó con estudiantes del Grado de Enfermería de tercer curso, en la asignatura de Prácticas Tuteladas III. La actividad consistió primeramente en trabajar habilidades de trabajo en equipo y liderazgo compartido a través del juego para, posteriormente, transferir el conocimiento generado a una situación clínica mediante la resolución de un caso. La actividad fue evaluada por los estudiantes de forma muy positiva. Consideraron que introducir el juego en el aula es una forma muy creativa y muy útil para desarrollar habilidades que pueden implementar posteriormente en el desempeño de su rol profesional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;20(9): 73-78, nov. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-MFM2-10779</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El Reto del Malvavisco: trabajando competencias de trabajo en equipo, liderazgo y resolución de problemas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8035</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11775</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
