<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90720</identifier>
<setSpec>0465-546X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The consumption of alcohol and other drugshas high prevalencia in the society in general, andin the population of workers especially, affectingon the occupational area. The repercussion of theconsumption of these substances in the workingenviroment is very important (diseases, occupationalaccidents, absenteeism, occupational disabilities,decrease of the productivity&#133;). They arenecessary political measurements in the occupationalarea to prevent and to minimize the risksderived from the consumption of these substances.There should be included programs of preventionand support, which offer basic information andorientation to the medical aproach of the affectedworkers (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Madoz Gúrpide, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ochoa Mangado, Enriqueta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El consumo de alcohol y otras drogas tiene unaelevada prevalencia en la sociedad en general, ytambién entre la población trabajadora, repercutiendosobre el medio laboral. La repercusión delconsumo de estas sustancias en el medio laboral esmuy importante (enfermedades, accidentes laborales,absentismo, incapacidades laborales, disminuciónde la productividad&#133;). Se valora lanecesidad de una política en el medio laboralencaminada a prevenir o minimizar los riesgoslaborales derivados del consumo de estas sustancias,con programas de prevención y apoyo queaporten información básica de referencia y orientenal abordaje asistencial de los trabajadores afectados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;54(213): 25-32, oct.-dic. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90720</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consumo de alcohol y otras drogas en el medio laboral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24887^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30459^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51562</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
