<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105905</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Control of bronchial asthma in children seen in a Primary Care Centre</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: This study aimed to assess the level of asthma control in children aged 6 to 14 years old in a Primary Care Centre. Methodology: A cross-sectional descriptive study was conducted on asthmatic children aged 6 to14 years old followed up in a Primary Health Care Centre in a metropolitan area of Barcelona. The Asthma Control Test (ACT) was the tool used to measure asthma control. Asthma was considered to be well controlled with an ACT score &gt;20. Demographic and disease speci&amp;#64257;c data were also collected. Results: A total of 46 patients (45% girls, 55% boys) completed the ACT. Their mean age was 8,9 years (SD 2.8). The prevalence of poorly controlled asthma was 41.3%. A family history of asthma was found in 36% of the children, and 43% of them declared to have activity limitations. Conclusions: The high percentage of poorly controlled asthma in children raises the need for reviewing the effectiveness in the processes to improve asthma control in these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Raventós-Jurado, Paola</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casado-Montañés, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Osuna-Gomera, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laserna-Jiménez, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moya-Calaf, Griselda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mulero-Madrid, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos Los objetivos de este estudio fueron conocer el grado de control del asma bronquial en niños entre 6 y 14 años atendidos en un centro de Atención Primaria. Método Estudio descriptivo transversal que incluyó a niños de entre 6 y 14 años diagnosticados de asma bronquial, atendidos por un equipo de Atención Primaria del área metropolitana de Barcelona. La determinación del control del asma bronquial se realizó mediante el test de control del asma (TCA). Se consideró que tenían un buen control del asma los niños que obtenían una puntuación en el TCA superior a 20.ResultadosSe encuestaron un total de 46 pacientes (45% niñas y 55% niños), con una edad media de 8,9 (DE 2,8) años. La prevalencia del asma mal controlada fue del 41,3%. Un 36% de los niños tenían antecedentes familiares de asma y un 43% de los niños refirieron tener dificultades para realizar actividad física. Conclusiones El alto porcentaje de mal control del asma bronquial en niños plantea la necesidad de revisar la efectividad de los protocolos de intervención existentes para mejorar su control (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);22(4): 209-213, jul.-ago. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105905</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El control del asma bronquial en niños atendidos en un centro de Atención Primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
