<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151028</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Non-speech oral motor treatment efficacy for children with developmental speech sound disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. In the treatment of speech disorders by means of speech therapy two antagonistic methodological approaches are applied: non-verbal ones, based on oral motor exercises (OME), and verbal ones, which are based on speech processing tasks with syllables, phonemes and words. In Spain, OME programmes are called &#145;programas de praxias&#146;, and are widely used and valued by speech therapists. Aim. To review the studies conducted on the effectiveness of OME-based treatments applied to children with speech disorders and the theoretical arguments that could justify, or not, their usefulness. Development. Over the last few decades evidence has been gathered about the lack of efficacy of this approach to treat developmental speech disorders and pronunciation problems in populations without any neurological alteration of motor functioning. The American Speech-Language-Hearing Association has advised against its use taking into account the principles of evidence-based practice. The knowledge gathered to date on motor control shows that the pattern of mobility and its corresponding organisation in the brain are different in speech and other non-verbal functions linked to nutrition and breathing. Conclusions. Neither the studies on their effectiveness nor the arguments based on motor control studies recommend the use of OME-based programmes for the treatment of pronunciation problems in children with developmental language disorders (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ygual Fernández, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cervera Mérida, José F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En el tratamiento logopédico de las dificultades de habla se practican dos enfoques metodológicos antagó-nicos: los no verbales, basados en ejercicios de motricidad oral (EMO), y los verbales, que se basan en tareas de procesamiento de habla con sílabas, fonemas y palabras. En España, los programas de EMO se llaman &#145;programas de praxias&#146;, están muy difundidos y son apreciados por los logopedas. Objetivo. Revisar los estudios sobre la eficacia de los tratamientos basados en EMO aplicados a niños con trastornos de habla y los argumentos teóricos que podrían justificar o no su utilidad. Desarrollo. Durante las últimas décadas se han acumulado pruebas sobre la falta de eficacia de este enfoque en el tratamiento de los trastornos evolutivos del habla y en las dificultades de pronunciación de poblaciones sin alteración neurológica de la función motriz. La American Speech-Language-Hearing Association ha desaconsejado su uso atendiendo a los principios de práctica basada en la evidencia. Los conocimientos acumulados sobre el control motor demuestran que el patrón de movilidad y su correspondiente organización cerebral son diferentes en el habla y en otras funciones no verbales ligadas a la alimentación y la respiración. Conclusiones. Ni los estudios sobre su eficacia ni los argumentos a partir de estudios del control motor aconsejan el uso de los programas basados en EMO para el tratamiento de las dificultades de pronunciación en niños con trastornos evolutivos del lenguaje (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;62(supl.1): s59-s64, 21 feb., 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151028</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia de los programas de ejercicios de motricidad oral para el tratamiento logopédico de las dificultades de habla</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1191^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7983^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13448^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13455^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7983^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56099^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13448^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29287^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13455^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29287^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56099^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1191^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1191^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13455^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56099^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
