<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036430</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tobacco smoking during pregnancy in Spain: an analysis according to years, autonomous communities and mother characteristics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE: The information about the convenience of non-smoking during pregnancy has increased in recent years. For this reason, we studied weather there has been any variation in smoking habits by pregnant women in Spain. SUBJECTS AND METHOD: We used data from 31,056 mothers of infants without congenital defects, from all the Spanish Autonomic Regions. These data had been collected with the same methodology all over the country. The evolution of maternal smoking habit was analyzed by years, Autonomic Regions and maternal characteristics. RESULTS: During the last years of the study (1995-2002), 30.31% of mothers smoked duringpregnancy, with variations among different ethnic groups. It was observed a secular increase in the prevalence of smoker mothers from 1978 to 1991, which was further stable in about 27-28%. There was no secular decrease in the analyses by maternal age, number of cigarettes, and Autonomic Regions. Only smoker mothers with higher educational levels diminished smokingin 1993, with it being stable in about 23%. Mothers younger than 25 years were the heaviest smokers in all the years of the study. We confirmed a close relationship between tobacco, alcohol and illegal drugs consumption. CONCLUSIONS: Our data indicate that the prevalence of women smoking during pregnancy has notdiminished over the years or by Autonomic Regions, although 19.19% of smoker pregnant women quit smoking during the first months of pregnancy. Moreover, the heaviest smoker mothers were the youngest ones in all the years of the study. These results show the need to increase the information for women so that they quit smoking before pregnancy</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Frías, María Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Pinilla, Elvira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermejo, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">FUNDAMENTO Y OBJETIVO: Desde hace años se ha venido informado sobre la conveniencia de que las mujeres embarazadas no fumen. Por ello, hemos estudiado si se ha producido alguna variación en el hábito de fumar durante el embarazo en España. SUJETOS Y MÉTODO: Utilizamos datos de 31.056 madres de niños sin defectos congénitos, procedentes de todas las autonomías, recogidos con la misma metodología en todo el país. Se analiza la evolución del hábito de fumar por años, comunidades autónomas, características y otros hábitos maternos. RESULTADOS: En los últimos años del estudio (1995-2002), el 30,31% de las madres fumó durante el embarazo, con variaciones entre diferentes grupos étnicos. Se observa un incremento secular de la prevalencia de madres fumadoras entre 1978 y 1991, estabilizándose posteriormente en el 27-28%. No se observa una disminución secular en los análisis por edades maternas, cantidades y autonomías. Sólo las madres de mayor nivel de escolaridad muestran un descenso del hábito de fumar en 1993, estabilizándose en alrededor del 23%. Las madres con menos de 25 años son las que más fuman en todos los años. Se ha confirmado la estrecha relación entre el tabaco, el alcohol y otras drogas comentada por otros autores. CONCLUSIONES: Nuestros datos indican que no ha disminuido la prevalencia de mujeres que fuman durante la gestación ni por años ni por comunidades, aunque el 19,19% dejó de hacerlo en los primeros meses de embarazo. Además, las madres más fumadoras en todos los años son las más jóvenes. Estos resultados muestran la necesidad de aumentar la información para que las mujeres dejen de fumar antes del embarazo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);124(3): 86-92, ene. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036430</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consumo de tabaco durante el embarazo en España: análisis por años, comunidades autónomas y características maternas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22968</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9723^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
