<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118008</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease is the most frequent hereditary kidney disease. However it lacks a specific treatment. Its prevalence is 1/800 and causes the need for renal replacement therapy in 8-10% of patients on dialysis or kidney transplant. It is caused by mutations in the PKD1 and PKD2 genes, which cause a series of alterations in the polycystic cells, which have become therapeutic targets. There are many molecules that are being tested to counteract the alterations of these therapeutic targets. There are studies in all phases of research, from phase i to phase iv. Some of the molecules being tested are tolvaptan, mTOR inhibitors and, among many other, somatostatin analogues. These drugs are extensively reviewed in this article. Based on the accumulated experience the primary objective of the trials is the slowing of the increase in renal volume. Yet other renal end points such as renal function and hypertension are necessary. It is expected that in the coming years we can have specific, well tolerated, effective and affordable drugs for the treatment of autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torra, Roser</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La poliquistosis renal autosómica dominante es la enfermedad renal hereditaria más frecuente. Carece de un tratamiento específico. Su prevalencia es de 1/800 y provoca la necesidad de tratamiento renal sustitutivo en un 8-10% de los pacientes en diálisis o trasplante renal. Está causada por mutaciones en los genes PKD1 y PKD2, que condicionan una serie de alteraciones en la célula poliquística, las cuales se han convertido en dianas terapéuticas. Existen muchas moléculas que están siendo testadas para contrarrestar las alteraciones de estas dianas. Hay estudios en todas las fases de investigación, desde la fase i a la iv . Algunas de las moléculas objeto de estudio son el tolvaptán, los inhibidores de mTOR y los análogos de la somatostatina, entre muchos otros. De acuerdo con la experiencia acumulada, el objetivo primario de los ensayos es el enlentecimiento del aumento del volumen renal. Pero se hacen necesarios otros objetivos tales como función renal, hipertensión, etc (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);142(2): 73-79, ene. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118008</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de la poliquistosis renal autosómica dominante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31085^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7852^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30024^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201401</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
