<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042755</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Expansion of primary epithelial cell cultures</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Cell cultures provide a good model for studying lung diseases but they are difficult to reproduce and the number of cells obtained is limited. The aim of this study was to develop a way to increase the production of human bronchial epithelial cells (BEC) in primary cultures.         Material and methods: A total of 12 samples (9 from surgical specimens and 3 from endoscopic biopsies) were processed on plates coated with type I collagen with growth medium supplemented for BEC. When cell proliferation started, the explants were removed for successive subculturing. The remaining cells were left to proliferate and were trypsinized after 50% confluence. We recorded the number of cells obtained, cell viability, and the percentage positive for cytokeratin 7.                 Results: The total number of cells obtained by this method was 3-fold the number of human BEC obtained with simple primary cultures. The maximum number of subcultures was 5, mean (SD) cell viability was 91.9% (11.7%), and the percentage of cells positive for cytokeratin 7 was 30.71% (10.68%).                 Conclusions: The described method for expanding primary BEC cultures increases cell production</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casan, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanchis, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Margarit, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Belda, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Los cultivos celulares son un buen modelo para el estudio de las enfermedades pulmonares, pero son difíciles de reproducir y producen un número limitado de células. El objetivo de este estudio ha sido desarrollar un método que incrementase la producción de células epiteliales bronquiales (CEB) humanas en cultivos primarios.                 Material y métodos: Se procesó un total de 12 muestras (9 procedentes de muestras quirúrgicas y 3 de biopsias endoscópicas) en placas recubiertas de colágeno tipo I con medio suplementado para CEB. Al iniciarse la proliferación celular a su alrededor, los explantes se extrajeron y subcultivaron sucesivamente. Las células restantes se dejaron proliferar y se tripsinizaron tras alcanzar más del 50% de confluencia. Se valoraron el número de células obtenidas, la viabilidad y la citoqueratina 7.                 Resultados: El número total de células obtenidas con este método superó en una media de 3 veces el número de CEB humanas obtenidas en cultivos primarios simples. El número máximo de subcultivos fue de 5, la viabilidad media (± desviación estándar) fue de 91,9 ± 11,7% y el porcentaje de células positivas para la citoqueratina 7 del 30,71 ± 10,68%.                 Conclusiones: El método descrito para amplificar cultivos primarios de CEB permite incrementar la producción de células obtenidas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;41(9): 524-527, sept. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042755</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Método para amplificar cultivos primarios de células epiteliales bronquiales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4926^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12530</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2010^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2512</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
