<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120436</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of a nutrition education and physical activity intervention in Chilean low socioeconomic women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and Objectives: Advanced Chronic Kidney Disease (ACKD) is associated with high prevalence of malnutrition. The habitual continuous dietary restrictions used in clinical practice. increased the malnutrition risk. The aim of this study was to evaluate the effects of a Nutritional intervention Program (NIP) on renal function and nutritional status in patients with ACKD. Patients and Methods: 93 patients, (53.7% men, 66 ± 17 years) were included in a prospective longitudinal study. The patients recived a NIP during 6 months with mensual visits. At baseline and six months the outcome assessed were: nutritional status by Chang criteria, anthropometric, dietetic and biochemical parameters (albumin, prealbumin, creatinine clearance, serum phosphorus, potassium, total-Cholesterol, LDL, HDL, triglycerides, and PCR). Results: After intervention, caloric intake decreased in nourished patients (1833 ± 318 vs 1571 ± 219 kcal p = .001). and it was constant in malnourished patients. The intake of protein (69,9 ± 16,6 vs 54,9 ± 11 g p &lt; 0.001), potassium (2938 ± 949 vs 2377 ± 743 mg p &lt; 0.001) and phosphorus (1180 ± 304 vs 946,6 ± 211 mg p &lt; 0.001) significantly decreased. 16.5% patients required supplementation. A total of 41.7% of patients were malnourished at baseline (27.8% mild, 10.10% moderate and 3.8% severe), and 16.8% at the end (8% mild, 5% moderate and 3.8% severe) by Chang criteria. At the end of NIP, patients significantly increased creatinine clearance (17,8 ± 5,2 vs 19,4 ± 6,9 ml/min, p &lt; 0,01), albumin (3,3 ± 0,5 vs. 3,5 ± 0,4 g/dL, p &lt; 0,05), and decreased serum potassium (4,8 ± 0,6 vs 4,5 ± 0,5 mmol/L, p &lt; 0,05), total cholesterol (179,8 ± 44,3 vs 170,0 ± 15,1 mg/dL, p &lt; 0,05), LDL (113,2 ± 37,0 vs 108,3 ± 27,3 mg/dL, p &lt; 0.01) and tryglicerides (141.9 ± 60.8 vs 129.9 ± 52.7 mg/dL, p &lt; 0.05). Conclusions: The study reflected a NIP usefulness in the nutritional status and renal function improvements within an interdisciplinary framework during ACKD consultations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palma Milla, Samara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peso, Gloria del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Candela, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>María Bermejo, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Torres, Almudena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Selgas, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bajo, M Auxiliadora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Villanueva, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y Objetivos: La Enfermedad Renal Crónica Avanzada (ERCA) se asocia a una elevada prevalencia de malnutrición. La práctica habitual en estos pacientes va dirigida a reducir la ingesta proteica, recomendación que podría favorecer esta situación. Por ello, el objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar el efecto de un programa de intervención nutricional (PIN) sobre la función renal y el estado nutricional en pacientes con ERCA. Pacientes y Métodos: Se diseñó un estudio longitudinal y prospectivo con 93 pacientes (53,7% hombres, 66 ± 17años) que participaron en un PIN durante 6 meses con visitas mensuales. Al inicio y al final de la intervención se evaluaron: estado nutricional en función de los criterios de Chang, datos antropométricos, dietéticos y bioquímicos (albúmina, prealbúmina, aclaramiento de creatinina, fósforo y potasio séricos, Colesterol-total, LDL, HDL, triglicéridos y PCR). Resultados: Tras el PIN la ingesta calórica disminuyó en los normonutridos (1833 ± 318 vs 1571 ± 219 kcal p &lt; 0,001) y se mantuvo en los malnutridos. Se redujo significativamente la ingesta proteica (69,9 ± 16,6 vs 54,9 ± 11 g p &lt; 0,001), potasio (2938 ± 949 vs 2377 ± 743 mg, p &lt; 0,0001) y fósforo (1180 ± 304 vs 946,6 ± 211 mg, p &lt; 0,0001). Un 16,5% requirió suplementación. El porcentaje de pacientes que presentaba malnutrición según criterios de Chan disminuyó tras el PIN (41,7 % (27,8% leve, 10,10% moderada y 3,8% grave) vs 16,8% (8% leve, 5% moderada y 3,8% grave)). Tras el PIN incrementó significativamente el aclaramiento de creatinina (17,8 ± 5,2 vs 19,4 ± 6,9 ml/min, p &lt; 0,01), albúmina (3,3 ± 0,5 g/dL vs 3,5 ± 0,4 g/dL, p &lt; 0,05) y disminuyó el potasio sérico (4,8 ± 0,6 vs 4,5 ± 0,5 mmol/L, p &lt; 0,05), Colesterol Total (179,8 ± 44,3 vs 170,0 ± 15,1 mg/dL, p &lt; 0,05), LDL colesterol (113,2 ± 37,0 vs 108,3 ± 27,3 mg/dL, p &lt; 0.01) y trigli-céridos (141,9 ± 60,8 vs 129,9 ± 52,7 mg/dL, p &lt; 0,05). Conclusiones: La mejoría del estado nutricional y de la función renal conseguidos ponen de manifiesto la utilidad de este PIN dentro de un marco interdisciplinar en las consultas de ERCA (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;28(6): 2252-2260, nov.-dic. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120436</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de un programa de Programa de Intervención Nutricionalen pacientes con enfermedad renal crónica avanzada (ERCA)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32108</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33546^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
