<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-70147</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-6585</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The aim of this clinical case was to report the histologic and clinical outcome of treatment with dental implants inserted by sinus floor elevation technique. Clinical Case. A 45-year woman treated with anterior fixed bridge and removable posterior prosthesis in maxilla is diagnosed for implant treatment. Treatment planning including elimination of prosthesis and teeth-supported, insertion of implants by bilateral sinus floor elevation and posterior fixed rehabilitation. Sinus floor elevation was realized using betatricalcium phosphate KeraOs® grafting. After a time period of 8 months, 10 Microdent® sand blasted surface implants were inserted in maxilla. In same intervention a cylinder sample of grafting bone were collected by trephine for histologic study than showed a good regenerate tissue. Implants were loaded after a healing free-loading period of 6 months, with cemented fixed rehabilitation. Not complications were observed after a 12 months follow-up (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Méndez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velasco Ortega, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pato Mourelo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Frías, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medel Soteras, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El objetivo del presente caso clínico era mostrar los resultados histológicos y clínicos del tratamiento con implantes dentales insertados mediante la técnica de elevación del seno maxilar. Caso Clínico. Una mujer de 45 años tratada con prótesis fija anterior y esquelético en el maxilar superior es valorada para tratamiento implantológico. El plan de tratamiento comprende la eliminación de sus prótesis y de los dientes pilares, inserción de implantes con elevación sinusal bilateral y posteriormente una rehabilitación fija. En la elevación del seno maxilar se utiliza betafosfato tricálcico KeraOs® como material de injerto. Después de 8 meses se insertan 10 implantes Microdent® con superficie con chorreado de arena. En la misma intervención se toma una muestra de tejido injertado con trefina para estudio histológico que demuestra una buena respuesta regenerativa. Los implantes fueron cargados después de un periodo de cicatrización de 6 meses con una rehabilitación fija cementada. Después de un periodo de carga funcional de 12 meses, no ha habido complicaciones. Conclusiones. Este estudio indica que el tratamiento con implantes dentales mediante la técnica de elevación sinusal constituye una terapéutica implantológica, histológica y clínicamente, con éxito (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. periodoncia implantol. oral;20(3): 147-154, dic. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-70147</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d10709^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24600^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8506^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8506^s22070</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10709^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33598^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10709^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33598^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33598^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
