<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046712</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cholesterol, alpha-tocopherol, and retinoid concentrations in silicone oil used as a vitreous substitute</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To verify the existence of organic lipophylic compounds in silicone oil extracted from human eyes following its use for previous retinal detachment, and to determine the intraocular permanence time of these substances in the oil.Methods: Concentrations of retinoic acid, retinol, retinal, cholesterol and alpha-tocopherol were detected by HPLC in 23 samples of silicone oil extracted from patients with complicated retinal detachments. The time interval between the time of injection of the silicone oil and the subsequent assessment varied from 3 to 50 months (the permanence time).Results: All tested compounds were found in the samples, but these were most commonly cholesterol and less frequently alpha-tocopherol. There was an inverse relationship between retinoic acid concentration and age (p=0.023), and a direct relationship between cholesterol concentration and permanence time (p=0.0008) at least up to 20 months.Conclusions: These findings confirm that silicone oil is not an inert substance but is capable of extracting lipophylic compounds from the intraocular tissues. There is a clear linear elevation of cholesterol levels with increased intraocular permanence time. This finding could be used to further establish a safe permanence time for intraocular silicone oil used in ophthalmologic surgery. More studies with larger samples are warranted to evaluate this further</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díez, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nozal, M. J del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastor, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marinero, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar si existen concentraciones de compuestos lipofílicos de origen orgánico en muestras de aceite de silicona extraídas de ojos humanos y comprobar si existe alguna relación con el tiempo de permanencia intraocular del aceite.Métodos: Por cromatografía líquida de alta resolución (HPLC) se han determinado las concentraciones de ácido retinoico, retinol, retinal, colesterol y a-tocoferol en 23 muestras de aceite de silicona de 1.000 cs, extraídas de pacientes con desprendimientos complejos de retina con tiempos de permanencia intraocular variables (3 a 50 meses).Resultados: Se han encontrado concentraciones de todos los compuestos, sobre todo de colesterol, y en menor medida de alfa-tocoferol. Se ha observado una correlación inversa de la edad y las concentraciones de ácido retinoico (p=0,023). Y una correlación directa entre el tiempo de permanencia intraocular del aceite y los niveles de colesterol (p=0,0008) que se mantiene hasta los 20 meses.Conclusiones: Se confirma que el aceite de silicona no es una sustancia tan inerte ya que es capaz de disolver compuestos lipídicos procedentes de tejidos intraoculares. Existe una elevación linear de los niveles de colesterol que podría utilizarse como orientación para decidir cuándo extraer el aceite de silicona, aunque hacen falta estudios con series más grandes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;81(1): 13-19, ene. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046712</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Concentraciones de colesterol, alfa-tocoferol y retinoiodes en aceite de silicona tras su utilización como sustitutivo vítreo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15224</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36123^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12592^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20181^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19347^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2834^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
