<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118952</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ectopic acromegaly due to a bronchial carcinoid</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Tumours that cause ectopic acromegaly can do so through the secretion of GH or GHRH. A hundred cases of ectopic acromegaly due to secretion of GHRH have been described. Given the rarity of this pathology, we present a clinical case with the aim of contributing our diagnostic-therapeutic experience and the subsequent follow-up. We present the case of a patient with acromegaloid physical features that had evolved over several years. Concomitantly, he also presented other accompanying symptoms that suggestive of a possible bronchial origin. Facing the clinical suspicion of acromegaly, we opted to confirm it biochemically and subsequently through image study. A hypophysary origin was ruled out, so we carried out screening for a bronchial neuroendocrine and/or gastrointestinal tumor as they are the most frequent localizations. The treatment of choice was surgical resection (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rojo Álvaro, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez García, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pineda Arribas, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Anda Apiñániz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lafita Tejedor, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Forga Llenas, Ll</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los tumores que causan acromegalia ectópica pueden hacerlo a través de la secreción de GH o de GHRH. Se han descrito un centenar de casos de acromegalia ectópica por secreción de GHRH. Dado la rareza de esta patología presentamos un caso clínico con el objetivo de aportar nuestra experiencia diagnóstico-terapéutica y de seguimiento posterior. Se presenta el caso de una paciente con rasgos físicos acromegaloides de varios años de evolución. Deforma concomitante también presentaba otros síntomas acompañantes sugestivos de posible origen bronquial. Ante la sospecha clínica de acromegalia se optó por confirmarlo bioquímicamente y posteriormente mediante estudio de imagen. Se descartó el origen hipofisario por lo que se realizó el despistaje de un tumor neuroendocrino bronquial y/o gastrointestinal por serlas localizaciones más frecuentes. El tratamiento de elección fue la resección quirúrgica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;36(3): 563-567, sept.-dic. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118952</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acromegalia ectópica por carcinoide bronquial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2319^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2014^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d178^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31255^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
