<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-18800</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-6585</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Er: YAG laser in periodontic. A review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Different lasers, such as CO2, the Nd:YAG and the ArF have been proposed for use in periodontal therapy. Most systems have not reached clinical significance because of the unsattisfactory results of laser treated root surfaces, emergence of severe side effects, or the lack of suitable delivery systems. However, the recently introduced Er:YAG laser radiation appears to be a promising alternative means of removing microbial plaque and calculus from diseased tooth root surfaces, due to its thermo-mechanical ablation properties and the lack of thermal side effects. The purpose of this article is to review current applications of laser Er:YAG to periodontal practice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ediciones Avances, S.L.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Diferentes láseres, como el COZ, Nd:YAG y ArF se han propuesto en la terapéutica periodontal. La mayor parte de ellos no han alcanzado relevancia clínica, debido a los resultados insatisfactorios obtenidos en las superficies radiculares tratadas, la generación de efectos colaterales o la ausencia de terminales de aplicación adecuados. Sin embargo, el nuevo láser Er:YAG se muestra como una prometedora alternativa en la remoción de placa bacteriana y cálculo de las superficies radiculares afectas, gracias a su mecanismo de ablación termomecánica y a la ausencia de efectos térmicos secundarios. El propósito de este artículo es revisar las actuales aplicaciones del láser Er:YAG en la práctica periodontal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. periodoncia implantol. oral;14(2): 63-68, jul. 2002. tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Láser Er:YAG en Periodoncia. Revisión bibliográfica</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Herrero Sanchez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garcia Nuñez, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-18800</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3788^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22125^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8013^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14485^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10701^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6021^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6508</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
