<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144760</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1837</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Angiotensin receptor antagonists (ARB) and angiotensin converting-enzyme (ACE) inhibitors are the two most widely used drug classes in the treatment of hypertension and in the prevention and treatment of cardiovascular and renal diseases. Studies with ARB have been able to replicate the benefits previously obtained in studies with ACE inhibitors, while direct-comparison studies have shown the two drugs to have a similar preventive efficacy. Other studies comparing ARB with other therapeutic strategies have shown these drugs to prevent cardiovascular disease at all stages of its development and progression and to be superior to other drugs in the primary and secondary prevention of stroke. In addition to this therapeutic efficacy, ARB are the cardiovascular drug class associated with the most favorable tolerability, leading to greater treatment adherence and persistence. All the evidence seems to indicate that, in the long term, this phenomenon possibly improves protection against cardiovascular disease. Likewise, the evidence also indicates that both ACE inhibitors and ARB are drug classes that include agents with a long future in the treatment of several generations and that they will probably be used in similar indications. Unless new data appear in the future, given the equal effectiveness of both drug classes, the better tolerability of ARB places them in a preferential position as renin-angiotensin system blockers in the treatment of chronic asymptomatic diseases such as hypertension (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sierra, Alejandro de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los antagonistas de los receptores de angiotensina II (ARA II) y los inhibidores de la enzima de conversión de la angiotensina (IECA) son las 2 clases terapéuticas más utilizadas en el tratamiento de la hipertensión arterial, y en la prevención y tratamiento de las enfermedades cardiovascular y renal. Los estudios con ARA II han demostrado una replicación de los beneficios obtenidos anteriormente en los estudios con IECA, al igual que una efectividad preventiva similar en los estudios de comparación directa. En otros estudios comparativos frente a otras estrategias terapéuticas han demostrado prevenir la enfermedad cardiovascular en todos sus estadios evolutivos, así como una superioridad frente a otros fármacos en la prevención primaria y secundaria del ictus. Añadido a esta efectividad terapéutica, los ARA II son la clase terapéutica cardiovascular asociada a una mejor tolerabilidad. Este fenómeno se traduce en una mayor adherencia al tratamiento prescrito, así como en su mayor persistencia. Todo parece indicar que, a largo plazo, este hecho se traduce en la mejor protección posible frente a la enfermedad cardiovascular. Asimismo, todo apunta a que tanto los IECA como los ARA II contienen fármacos de largo recorrido en el tratamiento de varias generaciones y deberán convivir en indicaciones similares. Salvo que aparezcan nuevos datos en el futuro, a igualdad de efectividad, la mejor tolerabilidad de los ARA II los posiciona como la forma preferente del bloqueo del sistema renina-angiotensina en el tratamiento de enfermedades crónicas asintomáticas, como la hipertensión arterial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Hipertens. riesgo vasc;30(supl.1): 3-10, ene. 2013. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144760</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Antagonistas de los receptores de la angiotensina II en el tratamiento de la hipertensión arterial, las enfermedades cardiovasculares y las renales. Realidad y futuro</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22832^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54126^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54125^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201301</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
