<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138045</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neurotology and cochlear implants</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this review we analyse cochlear implantation in terms of the fundamental aspects of the functioning of the auditory system. Concepts concerning neuronal plasticity applied to electrical stimulation in perinatal and adult deep hypoacusis are reviewed, and the latest scientific bases that justify early implantation following screening for congenital deafness are discussed. Finally, this review aims to serve as an example of the importance of fostering the sub-specialty of neurotology in our milieu, with the aim of bridging some of the gaps between specialties and thus improving both the knowledge in the field of research on auditory pathologies and in the screening of patients. The objectives of this review, targeted above all towards specialists in the field of otorhinolaryngology, are to analyse some significant neurological foundations in order to reach a better understanding of the clinical events that condition the indications and the rehabilitation of patients with cochlear implants, as well as to use this means to foster the growth of the sub-specialty of neurotology (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Merchán,  Miguel A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En esta revisión se analiza la implantación coclear en relación con los fundamentos del funcionamiento del sistema auditivo. Se revisan los conceptos sobre plasticidad neuronal aplicados a la estimulación eléctrica en la hipoacusia profunda perinatal y del adulto, y se comentan las bases científicas actuales que justifican la implantación precoz tras el cribado de la sordera congénita. Finalmente, se propone esta revisión como un ejemplo de la importancia de fomentar la subespecialidad de neurotología en nuestro medio, a fin de tender puentes entre especialidades que mejoren tanto el conocimiento en el campo de la investigación de la patología auditiva como en el cuidado de los pacientes. Los objetivos de esta revisión, dirigida sobre todo a especialistas del campo de la otorrinolaringología, son los de analizar algunos fundamentos neurológicos de relevancia para comprender mejor los eventos clínicos que condicionan las indicaciones y la rehabilitación de los pacientes con implantes cocleares, así como estimular por este medio la potenciación de la subespecialidad en neurotología (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;60(9): 413-419, 1 mayo, 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138045</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neurotología e implantación coclear</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9665^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55120^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3655^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3085^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33580^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1313^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6460^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1312^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3655^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
