<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76146</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Risk of Contracting HIV. Social activities by university students in Lisbon, Portugal1</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The authors identify social activities related to the risk of contracting HIV in nursing students, bearing in mind their influence while using bio-secure methods, by means of an exploratory and qualitative study; 168 Superior School of Nursing in Lisbon, Portugal students participated in this study. Data were gathered by means of a Free Association Word Test which includes social demographic variables related to the participants. 90% of the 168 students in this study were female and 10% male. The majority, 79,2%, of the participants age fell between 21 and 25 years and 97,6% of these participants were Portuguese. In the free association word test when responding to the stimulus HIV/AIDS, participants expressed disease (which is contagious in a clinical setting), and death as the awaited outcome for it. For the test term «risk of contagion when dealing with an AIDS patient» the participants often mentioned the words protection against contagion, as well as fear to contact blood and gloves as the main prevention method. To the stimulus measures of bio-security, the words most frequently cited were glove as a protective measure in the context of professional activity, and preservative (condom) to avoid contagion in other social contexts experienced by the participants</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peixoto Becerra, Valeria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alves, Maria do Socorro C. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gaspar, Maria Filomena M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se identifican las representaciones sociales sobre riesgo de contagio por el VIH en los estudiantes de enfermería comprendiendo su influencia en el uso de las medidas de bioseguridad, mediante un estudio exploratorio y cualitativo, realizado con 168 estudiantes de una Escuela Superior de Enfermería en Lisboa (Portugal). Los datos han sido recogidos a través del Test de Asociación Libre de Palabras que incluye variables socio-demográficas de los participantes. De los 168 estudiantes, 90% fue de sexo femenino y 10% del masculino. La mayoría de los participantes tiene entre 21 y 25 años (79,2%) y es de Portugal (97,6%). En la asociación libre de palabras referente al estímulo VIH/SIDA, los participantes expresan enfermedad (cuyo contagio la caracteriza en el ámbito clínico), y muerte como evolución esperada. La representación sobre «riesgo de contagio de cara al enfermo con SIDA», muestra frecuentemente las palabras protección contra el contagio, incluyendo el miedo al contacto con sangre, y los guantes como principal protección para la prevención. En cuanto al estímulo medidas de bioseguridad las palabras más citadas son el guante como medida de protección en el contexto de la actividad profesional, y el preservativo para evitar el contagio en otros contextos sociales vividos por ellos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;32(4): 271-276, abr. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76146</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Riesgo de contagio por el VIH. Representaciones sociales de estudiantes universitarios en Lisboa-Portugal1</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13725^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11613^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29422^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13725^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
