<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143195</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacy and safety of fentanyl pectin nasal spray in Radiation Oncology: clinical cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Approximately 60% of patients with a cancer diagnosis require radiotherapy. Although usually well tolerated, this treatment can sometimes produce radiation-related moderate-to-severe pain in certain locations or during painful procedures required for radiotherapy administration. This article describes two clinical situations of breakthrough pain in routine practice in radiotherapy departments: firstly, pain secondary to mucositis, which leads to weight loss and impaired quality of life; secondly, incidental pain caused by positioning and the maneuvers required for treatment administration. In both situations, we designed two prospective studies of fentanyl pectin nasal spray in the Fundación Jiménez Días. The results were satisfactory for both patients and healthcare professionals. These two studies remain open and are recruiting patients to confirm these results (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Prieto Muñoz, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Aproximadamente un 60% de los pacientes diagnosticados de cáncer requiere, en algún momento de su enfermedad, radioterapia. Aunque suelen ser tratamientos bien tolerados, en ocasiones los pacientes presentan dolor de intensidad moderada-severa en relación con la irradiación de determinadas localizaciones o al realizar dolorosos procedimientos necesarios para administrar el tratamiento. Este trabajo describe 2 situaciones clínicas con dolor irruptivo frecuentes en la asistencia diaria de los servicios de radioterapia: en primer lugar, el dolor secundario a la mucositis, que conlleva pérdida de peso y detrimento de la calidad de vida del paciente y, en segundo lugar, el dolor incidental producido por los posicionamientos y maniobras necesarias para administrar el tratamiento. Para ambas situaciones, en la Fundación Jiménez Díaz se diseñaron 2 estudios prospectivos introduciendo el fentanilo intranasal con pectina, con eficacia y resultados satisfactorios para pacientes y profesionales sanitarios. Estos 2 estudios continúan abiertos y se sigue reclutando pacientes para confirmar estos resultados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;22(supl.1): 86-90, mayo 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143195</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Casos clínicos de eficacia y seguridad del fentanilo intranasal con pectina en Oncología Radioterápica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12314^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28037^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22320</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54518^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50478^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6409^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
