<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138742</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cerebrospinal fluid cytotoxicity in lateral amyotrophic sclerosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The cytotoxicity of cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) in patients with lateral amyotrophic sclerosis in cell cultures that include neurons may be considered as a diffusion mechanism of the disease, due to the proximity of the CSF to the spinal column. Development: Various literature studies suggest that the motor neurons are more susceptible to cytotoxicity compared to other neuron cells, including glial, in cell cultures. The review of the composition of CSF in lateral amyotrophic sclerosis gives few clues on how this mechanism causes pre-apoptotic and apoptotic changes on the addition on CSF to the cultures, although it could be associated with the glutamate receptors, to a greater extent in those that respond to AMPA/kainate, and have a role in ion channels. Conclusions: The cytotoxicity of CSF is a peculiarity of lateral amyotrophic sclerosis, which could explain some aspects of how the disease progresses. More studies are required in order to understand more about this mechanism, including better identification of patients from whom samples are obtained, as well as their characteristics, differentiating them into familial or sporadic (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barcia, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matías-Guiu, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Ramos, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galán, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerrero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La citotoxicidad del líquido cefalorraquídeo (LCR) de pacientes con esclerosis lateral amiotrófica en cultivos celulares que incluyen neuronas puede plantearse como un mecanismo de difusión de la enfermedad, debido a la cercanía del LCR a la médula espinal. Desarrollo: Los diferentes estudios de la literatura indican una mayor susceptibilidad del efecto citotóxico en las motoneuronas, frente a otro tipo de células neuronales y la inclusión de glía en los cultivos. La revisión de la composición del LCR en la esclerosis lateral amiotrófica no permite indicar mediante qué mecanismo se producen cambios preapoptóticos y apoptóticos con la adición del LCR a los cultivos, aunque podría estar relacionado con los receptores del glutamato, en mayor medida, aquellos que responden a AMPA/kainato, e intervenir en canales iónicos. Conclusiones: La citotoxicidad del LCR es una singularidad de la esclerosis lateral amiotrófica que podría explicar aspectos evolutivos de la enfermedad. Para el mejor conocimiento de este mecanismo, es necesario que nuevos estudios incluyan una mayor identificación de los pacientes de quienes se obtienen las muestras, así como sus características, y diferenciar si son formas familiares o esporádicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;25(6): 364-374, jul.-ago. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138742</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La citotoxicidad del líquido cefalorraquídeo en la esclerosis lateral amiotrófica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9666^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2594^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d704^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d704^s22043</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
