<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81590</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-6157</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Intraoral contact allergy reactions often attributed to dental materials. Although appear to be less frequent, there are many published papers of reactions to dental restorative materials, mercury amalgam being the most common. However, it is very difficult to find references in the literature about these reactions to metals presents in metal alloys of dental prosthesis. We report a clinical case of a 60 year-old woman with oral lichenoid lesions located in hard palate and alveolar ridge, all lesions were located under the base of the prosthesis. Incisional biopsy was made and the histopathological study revealed changes compatible with oral lichen planus. The epicutaneous test showed a sensitivity to chloride of cobalt, ammonium hexacloroplatinato and chloride of aluminium. Treatment consisted of the removal the prosthesis and amalgam fillings, obtaining a considerable improvement in lesions and symptoms of patient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bullón, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cobos, M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallardo, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armas, Jose R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Sahuquillo, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las reacciones alérgicas de contacto intraoral se atribuyen con frecuencia a materiales de uso odontológico. Aunque se consideran poco frecuentes, existen muchas publicaciones de reacciones a materiales de restauración, sobre todo a la amalgama. En cambio, resulta muy difícil encontrar referencias en la literatura de este tipo de reacciones a metales presentes en aleaciones metálicas de prótesis dentales. Presentamos el caso de una mujer de 60 años que presenta lesiones de tipo liquenoide en paladar duro y en reborde alveolar, todas las lesiones se hallaban bajo la base de la prótesis. Se realiza una biopsia incisional y el estudio histopatológico mostró cambios compatibles con liquen plano oral. Las pruebas epicutáneas mostraron una sensibilización a cloruro de cobalto, amonio hexacloroplatinatoy cloruro de aluminio. Como medidas terapéuticas se recomendó retirar la prótesis y recambiar las obturaciones de amalgama, consiguiendo una mejoría considerable en las lesiones y la sintomatología que presentaba la paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Dentum (Barc.);9(1): 19-23, ene.-mar. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81590</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lesiones liquenoides orales asociadas a metales presentes en una prótesis parcial removible tipo esquelético: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7147^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7147^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3735^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31345^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31345^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
