<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129449</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Socioeconomic pattern in unhealthy diet in children and adolescents in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To investigate the possible association of dietary patterns associated with obesity and socioeconomic status in Spanish children and adolescents. Design: Cross-sectional study. Participants: Data were drawn from the 2007 National Health Survey, conducted on a representative sample of Spanish 0-15 years. In this study we have analyzed 6143 subjects from 5 to15 years. Main measurements: It has been estimated prevalence of breakfast skipping, the prevalence of low consumption of fruit and vegetable and the prevalence of high fast food, snacks and sugary drinks consumption. Socioeconomic status indicators were educational level and social class of primary household earner. In each type of food consumption socioeconomic differences were estimated by prevalence ratio using the higher socioeconomic status as reference category. Results: Both in childhood and adolescence, the magnitude of the prevalence ratio shows an inverse socioeconomic gradient in all foods consumption investigated: the lowest and highest prevalence ratios have been observed in subjects from families of higher socioeconomic status and lower, respectively. Conclusion: Unhealthy food related with obesity show a clear socioeconomic pattern in Spanish children and adolescents (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miqueleiz, Estrella</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Astasio, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Regidor, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lostao, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, Juana M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Investigar la posible asociación de patrones alimentarios relacionados con la obesidad y la posición socioeconómica en la población infantil y adolescente española. Diseño: Estudio descriptivo transversal. Participantes: Los datos proceden de la Encuesta Nacional de Salud de 2007, realizada a una muestra representativa española de 0 a 15 años. En este estudio se han analizado 6.143 sujetos de 5 a 15 años. Mediciones principales: Se ha estimado la prevalencia de omisión de desayuno, la prevalencia de bajo consumo de fruta y verdura y la prevalencia de alto consumo de comida rápida, snacks y bebidas azucaradas. Los indicadores de posición socioeconómica han sido el nivel de estudios y la clase social de la persona que aportaba más ingresos económicos al hogar. En cada consumo de alimentos se han estimado las diferencias socioeconómicas mediante la razón de prevalencia, tomando como referencia la categoría socioeconómica más alta. Resultados: Tanto en la infancia como en la adolescencia la magnitud de la razón de prevalencia muestra un gradiente socioeconómico inverso en todos los consumos de alimentos investigados: la menor y la mayor razón de prevalencia se observa en los sujetos de familias de posición socioeconómica más alta y más baja, respectivamente. Conclusión: En la población infantil y adolescente española la alimentación no saludable relacionada con la obesidad muestra un patrón socioeconómico claro (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;46(8): 433-439, oct. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129449</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patrón socioeconómico en la alimentación no saludable en niños y adolescentes en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33527^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33527^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33527^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55220^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33527^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
