<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91057</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fungal growth in culture media simulating an extreme environment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. There is an increasing interest in the study of microorganisms that inhabit extreme environments for reasons that vary from gaining insight into the origin of life to the searching of new biotechnological applications. Aims. In this work, we studied the tolerance of fungi isolated from the Aguas Agrias Stream (AAS; Tharsis, Huelva, Spain), an acidic metal-rich environment, to a culture medium prepared with water from this extreme ecosystem (AASW medium). The ability of some culture collection strains of moulds and yeasts to grow on AASW medium was also assessed. Methods. For moulds, a tolerance index was calculated by dividing the growth diameter of colonies on AASW medium by the diameter in the control medium, and their germinative potential was recorded. For yeasts and yeast-like fungi, the minimum inhibitory concentration of AASW was determined. Results. In general, the fungi isolated from the AAS showed differences in their ability to germinate and grow on AASW medium. Collection strains of the genus Aspergillus could grow on AASW medium, but showed some differences in tolerance when compared to environmental isolates. Conclusions. Extremotolerant fungi can manifest differences in their tolerance to culture media that simulate the conditions of their natural habitat. The results of this work suggest that the ability of fungi to grow in acidic, metal-rich environments might be more widespread than previously thought, and highlight the importance of determining the factors that are responsible for tolerance to these extreme environments(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Pérez, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Marta E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alba, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. Hay un creciente interés por el estudio de los microorganismos que habitan ambientes extremos por razones que van desde incrementar el conocimiento sobre el origen de la vida hasta la búsqueda de nuevas aplicaciones biotecnológicas. Objetivos. En el presente trabajo se aborda el estudio de la tolerancia de hongos aislados del Arroyo de Aguas Agrias (AAS; Tharsis, Huelva, España), un ambiente ácido y rico en metales, frente a medios de cultivo preparados con agua procedente de este ecosistema extremo (medio AASW). También se investigó la posibilidad de crecimiento en estas condiciones de cepas de colección de hongos y levaduras. Métodos. Para los hongos miceliares se calculó un índice de tolerancia, definido como el cociente entre el diámetro de crecimiento de las colonias sobre AASW y el que se produce en un medio control. Para las levaduras se determinó la concentración mínima inhibitoria de AASW. Resultados. En general, los hongos aislados del AAS manifestaron diferencias en su capacidad para germinar y crecer sobre el medio AASW. Las cepas de colección del género Aspergillus fueron capaces de crecer sobre el medio AASW, pero mostraron diferencias en su tolerancia al mismo en comparación con los aislamientos ambientales. Conclusiones. Los hongos extremotolerantes pueden manifestar diferencias en su tolerancia a medios de cultivo que simulan las condiciones de su hábitat natural. Los resultados de nuestro trabajo sugieren que la capacidad de los hongos para crecer en ambientes ácidos, ricos en metales, puede ser más común de lo que pudiera pensarse, y pone de manifiesto la importancia de determinar los factores específicos que son responsables de la tolerancia a esos ambientes extremos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;28(4): 159-165, oct.-dic. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91057</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Crecimiento fúngico en medios de cultivo que simulan un ambiente extremo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1237^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19089^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19089^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9364^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24929^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3491^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3491^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32965^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53322^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
