<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59812</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Is topical treatment indicated in otitis that occurs with otorrhea in the child? Therapeutic contribution of topical ciprofloxacin</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Otorrhea is a symptom present in different clinical conditions and not a diagnosis. There are several and important reasons to consider topical treatment as a useful therapy in the treatment of otorrhea in the child. The low concentrations needed for the pharmacological agents administered topically to be effective and the low grade of adverse events together with low risk of systemic complications are sufficiently valid premises to consider topical treatment as a higher effective alternative or therapeutic complement in different clinical conditions that occur with otorrhea. Topical treatments generally include antimicrobial agents. There is evidence that the topical aminoglycosides may cause ototoxicity. Non-aminoglycoside antimicrobial agents, especially fluoroquinolones, are recommended when it is necessary to access the middle ear. Topical ciprofloxacin has demonstrated its elevated therapeutic efficacy in external otitis, persistent otorrhea, post acute otitis media, simple chronic otitis media, pre-tympanostomy prophylaxis and otorrhea through transtympanic ventilationtubes, diseases with elevated prevalence in the pediatric age (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ballesteros, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabater Mata, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Homs, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pumarola, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La otorrea es un síntoma no un diagnóstico presente en distintas entidades clínicas. Existen diversas e importantes razones para considerar el abordaje tópico como una terapia útil en el tratamiento de la otorrea en el niño. La bajas concentraciones con las que son eficaces los agentes farmacológicos administrados por vía tópica, así como el bajo grado de reacciones adversas unido al bajo riesgo de complicaciones sistemáticas, son premisas lo suficientemente válidas para considerar el tratamiento tópico como una alternativa o complemento terapéutico altamente eficaz en distintas situaciones clínicas que cursan con otorrea. Los tratamientos tópicos incluyen habitualmente agentes antimicrobianos. Hay evidencia de que los aminoglucósidos tópicos pueden causar ototoxicidad. Los antimicrobianos noaminoglucósidos, especialmente las fluoroquinolonas, están recomendadas cuando hay que acceder a oído medio. Ciprofloxacina tópica ha demostrado su elevada eficacia terapéutica en otitis externa, otorrea persistente post otitis media aguada, otitis media crónica simple, profilaxis pre-timpanostomía y otorrea a través de tubos de ventilación transtimpánicos, todas ellas patologías de elevada prevalencia en la edad pediátrica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;64(3): 193-199, mayo-jun. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59812</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Está indicado el tratamiento tópico en las otitis que cursan con otorrea en el niño? Aportación terapéutica de ciprofloxacina tópico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d287</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19022^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23317^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
