<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038841</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Is clinical observation enough in doubtful cases of acute appendicitis?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Diagnosis of acute appendicitis is still one of the most usual problems in emergency departments. The aim of our study is to evaluate the results of clinical observation in patients with doubtful clinical features of acute appendicitis, comparing with a series of patients initially diagnosed and operated on. Methods: A series of 547 patients operated with diagnosis of acute appendicitis in a period of 4 years are studied. Patients are divided in 2 groups: Group A, 310 patients initially diagnosed and operated and Group B, 237 patients with doubtful diagnosis and left under clinical observation and operated lately. Demographic data and chronological data (time elapsed since the begin of suymptomatology to operation) are analysed, and the number of unnecessary appendectomies and gangrenous-perforated appendicitis. Results: There were not differences in general characteristics between both groups, except a higher incidence of women and radiological explorations in group B. There was a significative diagnostic delay in group B, the clinical observation do not decrease unnecessary appendectomies (7.7% in group A vs. 8.4% in group B) neither gangrenousperforated appendicitis (25.2% in group A vs. 37.1% in group B). Conclusions: Although our results could be considered as acceptable, clinical observation in doubtful cases, with or without radiological explorations have not been useful in our experience. In doubtful cases it had better a more aggressive diagnostic approach, probably performing an abdominal CT scan (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bianchi Cardona, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suñol Sala, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hidalgo Grau, L. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heredia Budó, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Admella Salvador, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Cuyàs, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El diagnóstico de apendicitis aguda sigue siendo uno de los problemas más habituales en los servicios de urgencias. El objetivo del presente estudio es evaluar los resultados de la observación clínica en pacientes con clínica dudosa de apendicitis aguda, comparándolos con los de una serie contemporánea de pacientes diagnosticados e intervenidos de inicio. Métodos: Se estudia una serie de 547 pacientes intervenidos por apendicitis aguda en un período de 4 años divididos en 2 grupos: Grupo A, 310 pacientes diagnosticados de entrada de apendicitis aguda e intervenidos y Grupo B, 237 pacientes con diagnóstico dudoso sometidos a observación clínica y posteriormente intervenidos. Se analizan los datos demográficos, los datos cronológicos desde el inicio del cuadro al ingreso y a la intervención, y el número de apendicectomías innecesarias y de apendicitis gangrenosas-perforadas. Resultados: No se evidenciaron diferencias significativas en las características generales de los 2 grupos, salvo un mayor número de mujeres en el grupo B, y un mayor porcentaje de pacientes sometidos a exploraciones complementarias. Con respecto a los datos cronológicos, existen diferencias significativas entre ambos grupos que evidencian un retraso diagnóstico, siendo el dato más importante que esta conducta de observación clínica no reduce el número de apendicectomías innecesarias (7,7% por 8,4%) ni de apendicitis gangrenosas-perforadas (25,2% por 37,1%). Conclusiones: Aunque los resultados son en líneas generales aceptables, la actitud de observación clínica en pacientes de diagnóstico dudoso, con o sin exploraciones complementarias, no ha sido satisfactoria en nuestra experiencia. En los casos de duda debería seguirse una actitud diagnóstica más agresiva, posiblemente mediante la realización de tomografía axial computadorizada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);17(4): 176-179, ago. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038841</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Es suficiente la observación clínica en los casos dudosos de apendicitis aguda?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1070^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26426^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1070^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1068^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1070^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1070^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26426^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
