<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151437</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0316</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The patient burnt victim is a patient who re-dresses an enormous gravity simultaneously that involves a big complexity in his handling, his initial handling will mark the morbimortalidad in the later days. The initial treatment of the burnt victim forces to continue in a firm way the protocol of attention to a polytraumatized patient: a) the first step continuing will be fixed in withdrawing the patient of the source that is provoking the injuries and in turn stopping the process of combustion as soon as posible; b) to value the permeability of the air route, to look for injuries for inhalation of smoke, injuries in mouth, orofaringe for air inhalation to high temperatures what will be indicative of possible commitment/obstruction of the air route in a brief time period indicating the application of an immediate way of measurements of support ventilatory; c) to restore venous accesses of thick caliber to initiate the perfusión of liquids; d) to avoid as far as possible the hipotermia, this one can turn out to be mortal in this type of patients; e) to evaluate of rapid form across simple rules the extension and depth of the burns since they will contribute clarity on the state of the patient and possibility of survival; and f) move of the patient burnt victim to a useful center (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romero, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Portas, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El paciente gran quemado es un enfermo que reviste una enorme gravedad a la vez que implica una gran complejidad en su manejo. Su manejo inicial marcará la morbimortalidad en días posteriores. El tratamiento inicial del paciente gran quemado obliga a seguir de manera firme el protocolo de atención a un paciente politraumatizado: a) el primer paso a seguir se fijará en retirar al paciente de la fuente que está provocando las lesiones y a su vez detener el proceso de combustión lo antes posible; b) valorar la permeabilidad de la vía aérea, buscar lesiones por inhalación de humo, lesiones en boca, orofaringe por inhalación de aire a altas temperaturas lo que será indicativo de posible compromiso/obstrucción de la vía aérea en un breve espacio de tiempo indicando la aplicación de manera inmediata de medidas de soporte ventilatorio como la IOT; c) instaurar accesos venosos de grueso calibre para iniciar la perfusión de líquidos; d) evitar en la medida de lo posible la hipotermia, esta puede resultar mortal en este tipo de pacientes; e) evaluar de forma rápida a través de reglas sencillas la extensión y profundidad de las quemaduras pues aportarán claridad sobre el estado del paciente y posibilidad de supervivencia; y f) traslado del paciente gran quemado a un centro útil (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Puesta día urgenc. emerg. catastr;7(4): 139-146, oct.-dic. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151437</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento inicial extrahospitalario del paciente gran quemado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5574^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d405^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5574^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5574^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2088^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2085^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2088^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10222^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2088^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
