<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053373</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Progressive facial hemiatrophy: Parry-Romberg syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report a case of Parry-Romberg syndrome in an 11-year-old girl with a left facial hemiatrophy, with no other associated symptoms. This is an uncommon disorder of unknown origin, characterized by a slowly progressive atrophy, generally unilateral, of the skin and soft tissues in the region of the trigeminal nerve. These changes lead to facial asymetry that can be accompanied by neurological, ocular and/or cutaneous abnormalities. The syndrome is more common in females and the diagnosis is based on the clinical findings. The most important differential diagnosis is linear scleroderma en coup de sabre, although the distinction can be difficult because of the possible coexistence of the two entities. Some authors have conclude that this syndrome could be regarded as a variant of linear scleroderma and consider that they both pertain to the same clinicopathological spectrum. the only specific treatment is plastic surgery to correct the deformity and improve cosmetic disfigurement</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barchino Ortiz, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernanz Hermosa, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabeza Martínez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leis Dosil, V. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos un caso de síndrome de Parry-Romberg en una niña de 11 años con una hemiatrofia facial de la región izquierda, sin otra sintomatología asociada. Se trata de una entidad poco frecuente y de origen desconocido que se caracteriza por una lenta y progresiva atrofia, generalmente unilateral, de las estructuras del territorio del nervio trigémino. Esta atrofia conduce a una asimetría facial que puede acompañarse de otras alteraciones neurológicas, oculares o cutáneas. Es más frecuente en mujeres y el diagnóstico se basa en unas manifestaciones clínicas características. el diagnóstico diferencial se debe llevar a cabo fundamentalmente con al esclerodermia lineal frontoparietal o en coup de sabre, pero en ocasiones puede llegar a ser imposible, dada la coexistencia de ambas, e incluso llevar a plantearse el hecho de que este síndrome sea una variante grave de esclerodermia lineal y que ambos procesos formen parte del mismo espectro clínico. No hay un tratamiento específico, salvo la cirugía plástica con la finalidad de mejorar el aspecto físico</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;65(3): 126-128, mar. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053373</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hemiatrofia facial progresiva. Síndrome de Parry-Romberg</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5251^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12975^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
