<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80340</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-2399</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Monitoring of deep sedation. The BIS® monitor</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Adequate monitoring of analgesia and sedation should be one of the main goals in the IntensiveCare Units. Once the analgesia is assured, the correct dosage of the sedatives will dependon the correct monitoring of the sedation level. For years, clinical scales have beenused to evaluate the sedation level. These scales are appropriate for the evaluation of mildsedation but they cannot correctly evaluate deeply sedated patients or those patients whorequire continuous intravenous administration of neuromuscular blockade agents. In thischapter, we review the most used monitor to control the adequate level of sedation in theIntensive Care Units as well as the BIS® Monitor, which is the one recommended by the Analgesiaand Sedation Work Group of the Spanish Society of Critical Care Medicine (SEMICYUC) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín Vivas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva Obregón, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romera Ortega, M. Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saboya Sánchez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chamorro Jambrina, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>La Torre Marco, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camarero Jorge, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La correcta monitorización de la analgesia y la sedación debe ser uno de los objetivosprincipales en las Unidades de Cuidados Intensivos. Una vez asegurada la analgesia, lacorrecta dosificación de los sedantes va a depender de la monitorización correcta delnivel de sedación. Desde hace años se han utilizado sistemas de monitorización basadosen escalas. Estas escalas son adecuadas para la monitorización de la sedación superficial,pero no son capaces de evaluar el grado de sedación en pacientes profundamente sedadoso con bloqueantes neuromusculares en perfusión continua. Actualmente disponemosde diferentes sistemas de monitorización que nos facilitan llegar donde las escalas noalcanzan. En este capítulo revisaremos el monitor más empleado en la actualidad en lasUnidades de Cuidados Intensivos, y el recomendado por el grupo de trabajo de Sedacióny Analgesia de la Sociedad Española de Medicina Intensiva, Crítica y Unidades Coronarias(SEMICYUC) para la monitorización de la sedación profunda, el Monitor BIS® (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Intensiva;20(4): 159-166, dic. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80340</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Monitorización de la sedación profunda. El monitor BIS®</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7530</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52865</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9183^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
