<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-68190</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Patients with inflammatory bowel disease present higher risk for hyponutrition. For this reason, an adequate nutritional support is frequently needed. In these patients, enteral nutrition should be used unless there exist contraindications. Nutritional support as the primary therapy is no indicated in adults (since steroidal therapy has shown to be more effective) but in the case of intolerance or lack of response to medical treatment. By contrast, enteral nutrition is considered a first line therapy in children. There is no clear benefit with the use of specific formulas (modified fat, glutamine...), so that their routine use is not recommended. In spite of the great technical and scientific advances, there are still many fields in which knowledge should be broaden; some of them are pointed out in this publication (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Puebla Maestu, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Tárrago, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miján de la Torre, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los pacientes con enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal presentan mayor riesgo de malnutrición. Por este motivo es muy frecuente que se precise un adecuado soporte nutricional. En estos pacientes se debe utilizar la nutrición enteral a menos que existan contraindicaciones. El soporte nutricional como tratamiento primario no está indicado en adultos (al haberse demostrado una mayor eficacia del tratamiento esteroideo) salvo en caso de intolerancia o falta de respuesta al tratamiento médico. Por el contrario, la nutrición enteral se considera el tratamiento de primera línea en niños. No existe un claro beneficio con el uso de fórmulas específicas (grasa modificada, glutamina...) por lo que no se aconseja su uso rutinario. A pesar de los grandes avances técnicos y científicos existen aún numerosos campos en los que ampliar conocimientos; algunos de los mismos se esbozan en la presente publicación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;23(5): 417-427, sept.-oct. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-68190</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23971^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32108^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
