<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152631</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-2841</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive:  Measure the adherence to hand higiene (HH) recommendations among different healthcare workers and units in Poniente hospital of Almeria. Methods. An cross-sectional study was developed. The research consisted in observing the hand hygiene practices of staff by anonymous observers, with the methodology proposed in WHO Guidelines on Hand Hygiene. Results. A total of 1018 opportunities for hand hygiene were observed in 332 professionals. The mean compliance was 23,6% ICU and haemodialysis had 6,5 (adjusted OR: 0,15, IC 95% (0,08-0,27) and 3,2 (adjusted OR: 3,1, IC 95% (0,14-0,68)) higher a likely to comply with HH guidelines than medicine wards. The moment 'after contact with fluids' had 5,3 more likelihood to performance HH in comparison with 'after contact with patient' (adjusted OR: 0,19; IC 95% (0,09-0,40)). Conclusions: The low adherence observed of compliance to HH practices suggests that motivational  campaigns focused on professional groups in the majority of wards could improve this situation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lucerna Méndez, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maldonado Valverde, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Carretero, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Medir la adherencia a las recomendaciones en higiene de manos (HM) por categorías profesionales y servicios asistenciales en el hospital de Poniente de Almería. Métodos: Estudio observacional descriptivo. Se observaron las prácticas en HM de los profesionales por evaluadores anónimos, según la metodología de la Organización Mundial de la Salud. Resultados: Se estudiaron 332 profesionales. Se realizaron 1.018 observaciones. La tasa media de adherencia fue 23,6%. La UCI y la hemodiálisis obtuvieron 6,5 (OR ajustada: 0,15, IC 95% (0,08-0,27) y 3,2 veces (OR ajustada: 3,1, IC 95% (0,14-0,68)) más posibilidades respectivamente de realizar una correcta HM comparando con medicina interna. El momento 'después de contacto con fluidos' obtuvo 5,3 veces más probabilidades de HM (OR ajustada: 0,19; IC 95% (0,09-0,40)) comparado con 'tras contacto con el paciente'. Conclusiones. La baja tasa de adherencia a las recomendaciones en HM supone dirigir campañas de concienciación a los profesionales de la mayoría de servicios asistenciales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. prev;21(1): 21-26, 2015. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152631</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variablidad en las practices de higiene de manos entre profesionales y áreas asistenciales de un hospital comarcal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55164^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55164^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55164^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55164^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53262^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
