<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125721</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Freud and the subjective de-naturalizations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The autor argues that, after a remarkable attempt to naturalize Psycho-analysis in the Project for a Scientific Psychology (1895), Freud´s theory progressively developed towards a non-naturalization of the human subject, particularly in his papers On Narcissism (1914), Beyond the Pleasure Principle (1920), and Inhibition, Symptoms and Anxiety (1926). This had important effects on the understanding of signification, of the death instinct, and of the ethical paradox that cuts across all human subjects. This complexity evidences the traces that the process of becoming human produced in the natural subject by the unavoidable passage of what Freud considered the nuclear complex of the neuroses, the Oedipus complex (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Szpilka, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Intentamos mostrar como después de un loable propósito de naturalizar al psicoanálisis que Freud realizó en el Proyecto para una psicología científica, fue sin embargo desarrollando un progresivo camino de desnaturalización subjetiva que se destaca sobre todo en "Introducción del narcisismo", "Más allá del principio de placer" e "Inhibición, síntoma y angustia". Esa desnaturalización ha tenido importantes efectos en la comprensión de la significación, de la pulsión de muerte y de la paradoja ética que atraviesa al sujeto humano, una complejización que evidencia las marcas de la hominización que produjo en el sujeto natural el obligado pasaje por lo que Freud consideró como el complejo nuclear de las neurosis, el complejo de Edipo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(47): 257-278, ene.-abr. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125721</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Freud y las desnaturalizaciones subjetivas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9999</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9686^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9686^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9484</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
