<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049241</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4603</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Aging effects on the tip-of-the-tongue phenomenon. Suggestions for intervention on lexical access</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The main important difficulty of lexical access for the elderly consists in a failure to recall a word of which one has knowledge that has been called «the tip-of-the-tongue phenomenon» (TOT). That failure has negative consequences on the normal flow of conversation and communication and can produce emotional disturbances in the elderly. We carried out an experimental study on the influence of aging on incidence and resolution of IOT events with the aim of knowing some guide lines for intervention that can help aged people to successfully resolve these situations.    In this study, 57 adults grouped into three groups of    age (young, middle age, old) participated in an experiment using definitions about common names, proper names, adjectives and verbs to elicit TOTs. They also were induced to resolve the TOTs introducing a freeevocation-of-words task and a priming task presented as a fluency and a pronunciation task respectively. Results confirm a higher incidence of TOTs and a lower effect of phonological priming on the older than on the younger people. From our results we suggest that the more efficacious strategies to facilitate lexical access in the elderly are those that are based on a conscious and top-down processing without temporal constraints and implemented by tasks using contextual and semantic cues</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Facal, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereiro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juncos-Rabadán, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La principal dificultad de acceso al léxico de las personas mayores normales consiste en un fallo para recordar palabras conocidas que ha sido llamado «fenómeno de la punta de la lengua» (PDL). Este fallo puede tener consecuencias negativas sobre el normal desarrollo del proceso de conversación y comunicación y puede producir problemas emocionales en los mayores. Con el objetivo de conocer algunas pautas que puedan ayudar a las personas mayores a resolver las situaciones de PDL hemos realizado un estudio experimental sobre la incidencia y naturaleza del PDL. En el estudio, 57 adultos agrupados en tres grupos de edad (jóvenes, mediana edad y mayores) participaron en un experimento de definiciones de palabras (nombres comunes, nombres propios, verbos y adjetivos) para elicitar PDL. Para inducir la resolución utilizamos también una tarea de evocación libre de palabras, presentada como una tarea de fluidez, y una tarea de primado, presentada como una tarea de pronunciación. los resultados confirman una mayor incidencia de los PDL y un menor efecto de la facilitación fonológica en las personas mayores. A partir de los resultados, se sugiere que las estrategias más eficaces para mejorar el acceso al léxico en este grupo de edad, son aquellas que se basan en el procesamiento consciente, arriba-abajo, no constreñido por el tiempo y con tareas que utilicen claves contextuales y semánticas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. logop. foniatr. audiol. (Ed. impr.);25(3): 115-120, jul.-sep. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049241</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos del envejecimiento en el fenómeno de la punta de la lengua. Sugerencias para la intervención en el acceso al léxico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3178^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7985^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15334</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
