<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161539</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">High incidence of type 1 diabetes in the immigrant population of Osona and Baix Camp</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: It has been postulated that migration could act as a modifying factor in the incidence of Type 1 diabetes mellitus (T1DM), so the aim of this study is to determine if there are differences in the incidence of T1DM by origin. Material and methods: Retrospective study of cases of T1DM onset in the population younger than 19 years old in Osona and Baix Camp between 2000 and 2012, using the medical histories of endocrinology units of the health centres and demographics from Catalonia Statistical Institute as sources. Results: The child population in Osona and Baix Camp increased by 36.6%, with 18.9% in the local population, and 482% in the immigrant population, and most of this increase (90%) in the Maghreb immigrant group. A total of 118 diabetics onset were found, 66.9% in the local population, 32.2% Maghrebi population, and 0.9% in children from other countries, with a total incidence rate of 14.4 cases per 100,000 population/year (c/105p-y). The incidence is higher in the Maghrebi population compared to the local population, 37.1 vs 11.2 c/105p-y (P&lt;.001), and in children under 5 years compared to the 5-18 years group, 18.9 vs 12.5 c/105p-y (P&lt;.05), with no differences between sexes (P&gt;.05). The relative risk is 3.1 for the Maghrebi population, and 1.5 for children under 5 years. Conclusions: The total incidence of T1DM remains stable, but is higher in the Maghrebi than in the local population, and in children under 5 years compared to 5-18 years group. These results opens a study field of which risk factors could be affecting this immigrant population in their destination countries (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Porcar-Cardona, Ines</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Feliu-Rovira, Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torrabías-Rodas, Meritxell</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Altimiras-Roset, Jacint</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Se ha postulado que la migración podría actuar como factor modificador de la incidencia de diabetes tipo 1 (DM1), por lo que el objetivo de este estudio es determinar si existen diferencias en la incidencia de DM1 según el origen. Material y métodos: Estudio retrospectivo de los casos de debut diabético tipo 1 en menores de 19 años en las comarcas de Osona y Baix Camp entre los años 2000 y 2012, utilizando la historia clínica de las unidades de endocrinología y los datos demográficos del Institut d´Estadística de Catalunya. Resultados: La población infantil en Osona y el Baix Camp aumentó un 36,6%, un 18,9% los autóctonos y un 482% los inmigrantes, a expensas mayoritariamente del colectivo magrebí (90%). Han acontecido 118 debuts diabéticos, 66,9% en nativos, 32,2% en magrebíes y 0,9% en niños de otros países, con una tasa de incidencia total de 14,4 casos/100.000 habitantes/año (c/105 h-a). La incidencia es mayor en magrebíes respecto a autóctonos, 37,1 vs. 11,2 c/105 h-a (p &lt; 0,001), y en menores de 5 años respecto a los de 5 a 18 años, 18,9 vs. 12,5 (p &lt; 0,05), sin observar diferencias entre sexos (p &gt; 0,05). El riesgo relativo es 3,1 para magrebíes y 1,5 para menores de 5 años. Conclusiones: La incidencia total de DM1 se mantiene estable, pero es mayor en magrebíes que en nativos y en menores de 5 años respecto a los de 5-18 años. Estos resultados abren un campo de estudio sobre los factores de riesgo que podrían estar incidiendo sobre esta población en los países de destino (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);86(4): 176-181, abr. 2017. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161539</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alta incidencia de diabetes tipo 1 en población magrebí de Osona y Baix Camp</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22190^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22190^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14563^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
