<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79771</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Urgent attention to an alcoholic patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction The identification of the alcoholic patient is sometimes hindered by the concealment of consumption. Able to label as an alcoholic in a patient with acute pathology can define more precisely the differential diagnosis of the syndrome.Objective To analyze alcoholism from the perspective of internal medicine through the presentation of a clinical case discussion.Methods We present a male patient with stigmata of chronic alcoholism and alcoholic liver disease presents with fever and abdominal pain. We discuss how to proceed to the identification of these signs and discuss the differential diagnosis of various medical problems presented with references pathophysiology. Finally, it suggests the diagnostic and therapeutic procedure.ConclusionsThis highlights the need to identify alcoholic patients and evaluate and integrate together all the medical problems it presents(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Chamorro Fernández, A. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laso Guzmán, F. Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción La identificación de un paciente alcohólico plantea frecuentemente dificultades al ocultarse el consumo del tóxico. Poder etiquetar como alcohólico a un enfermo con patología aguda permite delimitar de forma más precisa el diagnóstico diferencial del síndrome que presenta.Objetivo Analizar el alcoholismo desde la perspectiva de la medicina interna, mediante la exposición de un caso clínico discutido. Material y métodos Se presenta un paciente varón alcohólico crónico que acude al hospital por fiebre y dolor abdominal. Se expone el diagnóstico diferencial de los diferentes problemas médicos que presenta, con referencias fisiopatológicas y se razona el procedimiento diagnóstico y terapéutico.ConclusionesSe resalta la necesidad de identificar al paciente alcohólico y valorar e integrar en conjunto todos los problemas médicos que presenta(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;210(6): 291-297, jun.2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79771</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Atención urgente a un paciente alcohólico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8282^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8282^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d436^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8657^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
