<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-13977</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spatial memory and c-Fos expresssion in suprammamillary nucleus, anterior cingulated gyrus and entorhinal cortex</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To investigate brain substrates of spatial memory, the cellular expression of c-Fos protein in rats was studied after training the animals to perform a spatial reference memory task and a working reference memory task in a Morris water maze. The number of c-Fos positive neuronal nuclei was quantified in several brain regions: entorhinal cortex, anterior cingulate gyrus, and supramammillary nucleus. The results showed that spatial training in reference and working memory tasks increased the number of entorhinal cortex activated neurons (c-Fos positive neurons). No clear association was found between c-fos activation in the anterior cingulate gyrus and either spatial reference or working memory tasks. The number of c-Fos immunoreactive neuronal nuclei in the supramammillary neurons was greater in the spatial working memory groups than in the spatial reference memory groups suggesting that neurons of the supramammillary nucleus plays an important role in spatial processing (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santín, Luis J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Begega, Azucena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias, Jorge L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguirre, José A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miranda, Rubén</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Memoria espacial y expresión de c-fos en núcleo supramamilar, giro cingulado anterior y corteza entorrinal. Este trabajo se aproxima al estudio de los substratos cerebrales de la memoria espacial en ratas, empleando la expresión celular de la proteína c-Fos. Para elo, se analizó la expresiónde la proteína c-Fos después de la ejecución de una tarea de memoria de referencia y otra de trabajo espacial. De este modo, se cuantificó el número de núcleos neuronales c-Fos positivos en varias regiones cerebrales: corteza entorrinal, giro cingulado anterior y núcleo supramamilar. Los resultados mostraron que el entrenamiento espacial en tareas de memoria, incrementa el número de neuronas activadas en la corteza entorrinal (neuronas c-Fos positivas). No se halló una relación clara entre la activación c-fos en el giro cingulado anterior y las demandas de memoria de las tareas. El número de núcleos neuronales c-Fos positivos en las neuronas del núcleo supramamilar, fue mayor en los grupos de memoria trabajo que en los grupos de memoria de referencia, sugiriendo que las neuronas de este núcleo desempeñan un papel importante en el procesamiento espacial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);13(2): 214-221, mayo 2001. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-13977</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Memoria espacial y expresión de c-Fos en núcleo supramamilar, giro cingulado anterior y corteza entorrinal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32263^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6330^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13420^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8738^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29864^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200105</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
