<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89187</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of genetic markers for CYPE1 in the assessment of risks through occupational exposure to styrene using biologic controls</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We have studied the usefulness of geno and phenotyping of the enzyme CYP2E1 for the assessment of risk through occupational exposure to styrene and correlated the results achieved with the habitual biologic markers in Occupational Health programmes (mandelic and phenylglyoxylic acids, the main urinary metabolites of styrene). The study group comprised 49 workers with known exposure to styrene and a control group; CYP2E1 mRNA in blood and enzyme polymorphisms in samples of the oral mucosa were assessed. Our results show that the combined affects of CYP2E1 phenotype and of the CYP2E1*5B and CYP2E1*6 allele genotype may in part explain the variability in the urinary excretion of styrene metabolites. The sampling technique for biologic material from the oral mucosa may be useful in the occupational environment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Prieto Castelló, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roel Valdés, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cardona Llorens, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marhuenda Amorós, Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Hemos estudiado la utilidad del genotipado y fenotipado de la enzima CYP2E1 para la evaluación del riesgo de exposición laboral a estireno, correlacionando los datos obtenidos con los indicadores biológicos habituales en programas de Salud Laboral (ácidos mandélico y fenilglioxílico, principales metabolitos urinarios del estireno). Se examinaron 49 trabajadores con exposición conocida a estireno y un grupo control, determinándose mARN de CYP2E1 en sangre y polimorfismos de la enzima en muestras de mucosa oral. Nuestros resultados muestran que el efecto combinado del fenotipo de CYP2E1 y del genotipo de los alelos CYP2E1*5B y CYP2E1*6 puede explicar en parte la variabilidad en la excreción urinaria de metabolitos del estireno. La técnica de obtención de material biológico a partir de la mucosa oral puede ser de interés en el ámbito laboral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;18(3): 8-21, dic. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89187</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilización de marcadores genéticos de la CYP2E1 en la valoración de riesgos de exposición laboral a estireno mediante control biológico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29063^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13730^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9255^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33012^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24411</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
