<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119567</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1780</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sexual harassment among peers and adolescent dating violence</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper presents a study about peer and dating sexual harassment among adolescents. Specifically, differences by sex, age and the developmental stage of the romantic relationships were analyzed in both, peer and dating sexual harassment in a sample of 490 adolescents (55,7% boys and 44,3% girls, mean age 16.08). Descriptive data showed that the presence of peer and dating sexual harassment was similar. Boys were more perpetrators in both, peer and dating contexts but no differences by sex were found for victimization indexes. An important effect of the developmental-stage of the relationships was found: peer sexual harassment were more frequent in &#147;casual&#148; and &#147;mixed gender&#148; stage whereas dating sexual harassment was more frequent in &#147;serious relationship&#148;. For age, just differences in dating sexual harassment were found: older adolescents were more involved than younger ones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortega, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Rivera, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente estudio ha analizado la presencia de violencia sexual entre compañeros y en las parejas adolescentes y jóvenes. Específicamente se han estudiado las diferencias por sexo, edad y estadio de la relación sentimental tanto en violencia sexual entre iguales como en las parejas, en una muestra de 490 adolescentes (55,7% chicos, 44,3% chicas, edad media 16.08 años). Los resultados descriptivos mostraron la misma incidencia de violencia sexual entre iguales y en las parejas. Respecto al sexo, los chicos presentaron mayor implicación como agresores de sus iguales y de sus parejas, pero no se encontraron  diferencias con relación a los índices de victimización. Se encontró un efecto importantedel estadio de la relación: la violencia sexual entre iguales fue más frecuente entre los que  se encontraban en &#147;relaciones casuales&#148; y &#147;grupos mixtos&#148; mientras que la violencia sexual entre parejas fue más frecuente entre los que se encontraban en &#147;relaciones serias&#148;. Para la edad, solo se encontraron diferencias en la violencia sexual entre parejas, siendo que los chicos y chicas más mayores resultaron más implicados que los más pequeños (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int. j. psychol. psychol. ther. (Ed. impr.);8(1): 63-72, mar. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119567</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Violencia sexual entre compañeros y violencia en parejas adolescentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d378^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33199^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50239</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13564^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
