<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102030</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-7606</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Suicide in people under 26 years of age in Seville</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The overall suicide rate has increased significantly in recent decades, not only in developed countries but also worldwide. It is important to underline the prevalence of suicide among young people 15 to 25 years old, a population in which suicide is the second leading cause of death after traffic accidents. This paper provides a descriptive epidemiological study of confirmed suicides in people less than 26 years of age, which occurred in the province of Seville during the period 2007-2010. The factors associated with suicidal behaviour are presented and compared with those published in the scientific literature on the subject. The average global rate of suicide was 1.38±0.1 cases/100.000 inhabitants with a male/female ratio of 3:1. The overall mean age was of 20.9±3.1 years (21±3 years in men and 20±4 years in women). Twenty-two per cent of suicides occurred in the capital compared to 78% in the rest of the province. Hanging was the most widely used method in both men (71%) and women (62%), followed by jumping from height. The most common location to commit suicide in both sexes was at home (72%). In 44% of cases there was a history of psychiatric illness with being depressive disorder the most frequent (50%), followed by paranoid schizophrenia (14%). Toxicological analysis was positive in 47% cases, with ethanol the most frequently detected chemical (80%), either alone or in combination with other toxics (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marín, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rico, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lucena, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La tasa global de suicidios ha sufrido un aumento importante en las últimas décadas, no sólo en los países desarrollados sino a nivel mundial. Es de destacar el especial dramatismo del suicidio en los jóvenes de 15 a 25 años, grupo de población en el que el suicidio es la segunda causa de muerte después de los accidentes de tráfico. En este artículo se realiza un estudio epidemiológico descriptivo de tipo retrospectivo de las muertes de etiología suicida en menores de 26 años ocurridas en la provincia de Sevilla en el periodo 2007-2010. En él se analizan los factores relacionados con la conducta suicida y se contrastan los resultados con los de la literatura científica existente sobre el tema. La tasa media global de suicidio fue de 1,38±0,1 casos/100.000 habitantes con una relación hombre/mujer de 3:1. La edad media global ha sido de 21±3 años (21±3 años en varones y 20±4 años en mujeres). El 22% de los suicidios ocurre en la capital frente al 78% registrado en el resto de la provincia. La ahorcadura es el mecanismo más empleado tanto en hombres (71%) como en mujeres (62%), seguido de la precipitación. El lugar de comisión del suicidio en ambos sexos es el propio domicilio (72%). En un 44% de los casos existían antecedentes psicopatológicos siendo el trastorno depresivo el más frecuente (50%) seguido de la esquizofrenia paranoide (14%). El análisis químico-toxicológico fue positivo en el 47%, siendo el alcohol etílico la sustancia más detectada (80%), bien de forma aislada o combinado con otros tóxicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. med. forense;18(2): 55-62, abr.-jun. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102030</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Suicidio en menores de 26 años en Sevilla</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13791^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24887^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28637^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1352^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38398^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
