<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85202</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4008</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adjusting of the demand. Diabetic nephropathy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The importance of measuring albumin in urine is well established; however, there is still controversy regarding the recommendations to be used for detecting early renal impairment in diabetic patients. The objective of this work is to evaluate the results and the costs of the screening program for diabetic nephropathy in our health area. Material and methods. A retrospective descriptive study was carried out on the requests for screening for diabetic nephropathy in 2006. We performed 1111 diabetic nephropathy screening tests requested by general practitioners. Patients were classified into different clinical nephropathy stages according to their albumin excretion rate. Results. Only 39.7% of the requests for diabetic nephropathy screening fulfilled all the prescription criteria specified in the program. The frequency of positive results was different in relation to sex and age groups. The cost per positive result was 29.61&#128; for men, whereas it was 71.17&#128; for women, in the 12&#150;70 years age group. Conclusions. The adjustment of the demand is necessary to ensure the efficiency of health care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calvo Malvar, Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benítez Estévez, Alfonso Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La importancia de la determinación de albúmina en orina ha sido claramente establecida; sin embargo, existe controversia sobre las recomendaciones a seguir para su uso en el diagnóstico de la nefropatía diabética. El objetivo de este trabajo es evaluar los resultados y los costes del programa de escrutinio de la nefropatía diabética en nuestra área sanitaria. Material y métodos. Se ha realizado un estudio descriptivo retrospectivo sobre la demanda de escrutinios para detección de la nefropatía diabética en el año 2006. Para ello, se ha analizado una muestra de 1.111 escrutinios solicitados por los médicos de Atención Primaria. Los pacientes se han clasificado en los distintos estadios de la nefropatía diabética de acuerdo a la excreción urinaria de albúmina. Resultados. Solo el 39,7% de los escrutinios cumplieron con todos los criterios de prescripción especificados en el programa. La frecuencia de resultados positivos fue distinta según el sexo y el grupo de edad considerado. El coste por resultado positivo fue de 29,61&#128; para varones mientras que resultó de 71,17&#128; para mujeres, para un intervalo de edad de 12&#150;70 años. Conclusiones. La adecuación de la demanda es necesaria para asegurar la eficiencia de la atención sanitaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. lab. clín;3(2): 63-68, abr.-jun. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85202</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">A propósito de la adecuación de la demanda. Nefropatía diabética</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d422^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3421^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3421</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6453^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3951^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3951^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6453^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d422^s22050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3951^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
