<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163228</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Scientific Evidence relating Sandblasting and Neumopathies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A significant number of studies have recently shown an association between sandblasting use the development of severe varieties of silicosis. Silicosis is a diffuse interstitial pulmonary disease caused by the continuous inhalation of dust containing crystal silica. It has no effective treatment, so the variable presentation and clinical course makes an early prevention and diagnosis two main aspects in its control. Sources of silica exposure are very diverse and almost exclusively work-related. Sandblasting is a medical method which projects blast of air or steam in combination with sand to perform tasks such as clean, polish and improve hard surfaces. The aims of this review are to identify the scientific evidence in the association between using sandblasting use and silicosis development, to determine the dose&#150;response relationship, to identify the associated sandblasting risk factors, to describe vulnerability conditions, to analyze the PPE (Personal Protection Equipment) role in preventing illness among workers and to determine comorbidity. A literature search has been performed between 2006 and December 2015 in the following scientific databases: Medline, Scopus, Lilacs, Ibecs and OSH. 20 articles were selected taking into account the level of evidence according with SIGN criteria (Scottish Intercollegiate Guidelines Network), and the fulfilled inclusion and exclusion criteria. The results of this systematic review suggest that there is a conclusive association between developing silicosis in its most aggressive pathological varieties, and using sandblasting. However, due to the crosssectional and descriptive predominant design of most of the studies, better designed study strategies are required in order to get better levels of evidence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Camargo García, Katlhyn Vanessa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Lucas, Pablo Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santabasilisa Dalmau, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Malo Negrín, Mireymar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Un importante número de estudios publicados recientemente ponen de manifiesto la asociación entre el sandblasting y el desarrollo de silicosis en formas graves. La silicosis es una enfermedad intersticial difusa producida por inhalación mantenida de sílice cristalina. No tiene tratamiento efectivo y su presentación y curso clínico son variables; haciendo la prevención y el diagnostico precoz, dos aspectos fundamentales en su control. Las fuentes de exposición a sílice son muy numerosas y se producen de forma casi exclusiva en el ámbito laboral. El sandblasting consiste en proyectar un chorro de arena contra una superficie con aire comprimido o vapor para limpiar, pulir y mejorar, etc. superficies duras. Los objetivos son: identificar la evidencia científica existente entre sandblasting y el desarrollo de silicosis, si existe relación dosis-respuesta, establecer los factores de riesgos del sandblasting, las condiciones de vulnerabilidad, el papel de los EPI en la prevención de silicosis en estos trabajadores e identificar la comorbilidad. Se ha realizado la búsqueda bibliográfica de artículos publicados entre 2006 y diciembre de 2015 en la siguientes bases de datos: Medline, Scopus, Lilacs, Ibecs y OSH. Se seleccionaron por nivel de evidencia y criterios de inclusión-exclusión un total de 20 artículos. La revisión sistemática de estos artículos parece sugerir una asociación concluyente entre el uso de la técnica de sandblasting y el desarrollo de silicosis en formas agresivas. No obstante el diseño descriptivo y transversal de la mayoría de los artículos seleccionados, invitan a realizar estudios con mejores diseños, para conseguir mayor nivel de evidencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;62(245): 381-401, oct.-dic. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163228</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evidencia científica en sandblasting y neumopatías</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12095^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31916^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53366^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33541</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24975^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13209^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8348^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
