<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102545</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Meningioma spinal. An unexpected finding</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Spinal tumors are rare in the group of all central nervous system (CNS). Among them, meningiomas are one of the most common (25-46% of spinal tumors). Meningioma originate from the meningothelial cells. They are generally benign, slow-growing, and predominate in middle age or elderly women. They are especially located in the thoracic spine. They have no specific symptoms although they usually present with pain, muscle weakness, sensory disturbances and urinary incontinence. This lack of specific symptoms causes late diagnosis and they are usually masked by other more common diseases as herniated disk or degenerative spinal disease. If an early diagnosed is carried out, treatment outcomes are excellent. We present a case of cervical meningioma found by chance thanks to a MRI requested due to suspicion of another disease(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tortosa Grau, M. N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Franco, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayoral Azofra, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macia Pareja, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cifuentes Albeza, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los tumores espinales son raros en el conjunto de todos los tumores del sistema nervioso central (SNC). Dentro de ellos, los meningiomas son uno de los más frecuentes (25-46% de los tumores espinales). Los meningiomas se originan a partir de las células meningoteliales. Son en general benignos, de lento crecimiento, predominan en las mujeres con edades medias-avanzadas y sobre todo en el raquis dorsal. No tienen síntomas específicos, suelen presentar: dolor, debilidad muscular, alteraciones sensitivas e incontinencia urinaria. Esta falta de clínica específica determina que se diagnostiquen tardíamente y que queden enmascarados por otros cuadros más frecuentes como la hernia discal o la enfermedad degenerativa del raquis. Si se realiza un diagnóstico precoz, los resultados del tratamiento son excelentes. Presentamos un caso de meningioma cervical hallado casualmente con una resonancia magnética (RM) solicitada por sospecha de otro proceso(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);46(3): 246-249, jul.-sep.2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102545</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Meningioma espinal. Un hallazgo no esperado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8750^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8750^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13503^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2525^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2525^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13503^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
