<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145013</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Detecting in-hospital stroke: Assessment of results from a training programme for medical personnel</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: In-hospital stroke (IHS) is a frequent event, but its care priority level is not well established in many hospitals. IHS care at our centre has been redefined by implementing a training programme for medical personnel not usually involved in stroke management, in order to optimise IHS detection and treatment. This study evaluates results from the training programme. Methods: Prospective longitudinal intervention study. Neurologists experienced in vascular diseases developed a training programme for medical personnel. We recorded incidence, epidemiological data, reason for hospitalisation, department, aetiology, severity (NIHSS), time from symptom onset to neurological assessment, use of endovascular thrombolysis, exclusion criteria for untreated patients, and 90-day outcome (mortality/disability) in 2 patient groups: patients experiencing IHS in the 6 months before (PRE) and the 6 months after the training programme (POST). Results: Sixty patients were included (19 PRE, 41 POST) with a mean age of 75.3 ± 12.5; 41% were male. There were no differences between groups regarding assessment time, treatment administered, or morbidity/mortality. Overall, 68.3% of the patients were assessed in &lt; 4.5 hours; however, only 6 patients (10%) were able to undergo endovascular therapy. This situation was mainly due to pre-existing disability (26%) and comorbidity (13%). Conclusions: More IHS code activations were recorded after the training programme. However, that increase was not accompanied by a higher percentage of treated patients or improvements in patient prognosis during the study period, and these findings could probably be explained by the high rates of pre-existing disability and comorbidity in this series (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Roquer, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romeral, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuadrado Godia, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Fernández, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Campello, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giralt Steinhauer, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El ictus intrahospitalario (IIH) es frecuente, pero su atención preferente no está bien establecida en muchos centros hospitalarios. En nuestro centro, como medida de calidad asistencial, se intentó reorganizar la atención al IIH mediante un programa de formación teórica y entrenamiento a profesionales sanitarios no implicados habitualmente en el manejo de pacientes con ictus, para optimizar la detección y el tratamiento del IIH. Se evalúan resultados del programa de formación. Métodos: Estudio prospectivo longitudinal de intervención. Se elaboró un programa de formación a personal médico y enfermería. Se registró a los pacientes con IIH pre (PRE) y posformación (POST) (6 meses cada grupo) y se evaluaron los datos de incidencia, datos epidemiológicos, motivo de ingreso y servicio, etiología, severidad, tiempo hasta evaluación por Neurología, tratamiento recanalizador (trombólisis intravenosa/intravascular), criterios de exclusión en no tratados y pronóstico (mortalidad/discapacidad) en ambos grupos. Resultados: Se identificó a 60 pacientes con IIH, con una edad media de 75,3 ± 12,5, 41% hombres; 19 PRE/41 POST. Sin diferencias entre grupos en el tiempo de evaluación, el tratamiento o la morbimortalidad. El 68,3% de ellos fueron evaluados en &lt; 4,5 h, de los cuales solo fue posible administrar tratamiento recanalizador en 6 pacientes (10%), debido fundamentalmente a dependencia previa (26%) y comorbilidad (13%). Conclusiones: El programa de formación realizado permite un mayor número de activaciones de código ictus intrahospitalario. Sin embargo, en el periodo evaluado, esto no se tradujo en mayor porcentaje de pacientes tratados o mejor pronóstico, probablemente debido a la discapacidad previa y comorbilidad elevada en esta serie (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;30(9): 529-535, nov.-dic. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145013</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Detección de ictus intrahospitalario: evaluación de resultados de un programa de formación y entrenamiento a personal médico y de enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2586^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
