<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93686</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endodontic management in horizontal root fractures- Case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The dental trauma occur with great frequency in the maxillary incisors ant they can cause several sequels to the dental and periodontal tissues, such as loss of dental structure with or without pulp involvement, coral and/or root fractures and even loss of the dental element. The root fractures, however, a seen common event that incidence is below 10% of the dental traumatic lesions, however the success is formed by association with the pulp v itality and contamination of the fracture line. The case report the treatment of maxillary permanent incisor with horizontal root fracture at cervical level with displacemtne of the fragments. The fragments were treated separately and after 13 years of control, the interference of conjunctive tissue was evidenced among the fragments and the fracture was considered repaired (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jornada Gomes, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Folgearini Silveira, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Machado Silveira, L. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martos, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los traumatismos dentarios ocurren con gran frencuencia en el área de incisivos superores y pueden causar vairas secuelas a los tejidos dentales y de soporte, como la pérdida de estrucutra dental con o sin compromiso pulpar, fracturas coronarias y/o radiculares hasta la pérdida del elemento dental. Las fracturas radiculares, sin embargo, no representan un evento común haya visto que la incidencia está abajo del 10% de las lesiones traumáticas dentales, sin embargo el pron´sotico está aliado a la vitalidad pulpar y la posible contaminación de la línia de la fractura. El siguiente caso clínico describe el ratamieto deuna fractura radicular horizontal al nivel cervical con la separación de os de ls fragmentos en un incisivo central superior permanente. Lso fragmentso fueron tratados separadamente y después de 13 años de preservación se evidenció la interposicón del tejido conjuntivo entre los fragmentos, lo que denota la reparación. Sin embargo, se observó una fractura apical remodelada en el incisivo central vecino (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);27(1): 31-36, ene.-mar. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93686</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resolución endodóncica de una fractura radicular cervical. Caso Clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12764^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14485^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14474^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
