<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147057</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Emotional profile according to level of expertise: A study of squash players</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to identify the emotional profile of squash players at different levels of expertise. The sample was made up of 80 players, divided into four expertise levels (National First Division, National Second Division, Regional level and Provincial level). The study used the Individual Zones of Optimal Functioning model questionnaire: IZOF-emotion (Hanin, 2000a). The results show emotional profiles which differ in functional content, intensity and impact depending on the level of expertise. Therefore, the results confirm the individualistic nature of emotional profiles and the specific dedication that each player must receive (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pastor-Vicedo, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Víllora, Sixto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Catalán-Eslava, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Contreras-Jordána, Onofre Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente estudio ha sido identificar el perfil emocional de jugadores de squash de diferente nivel de competición. La muestra estaba compuesta por 80 jugadores, divididos en cuatro niveles de competición (Primera categoría nacional, Segunda categoría nacional, nivel autonómico y nivel provincial). Se utilizó el Cuestionario del Perfil Emocional Óptimo Individual del modelo IZOF-Emoción (Hanin, 2000a). Los resultados muestran perfiles emocionales diferenciados tanto en su contenido, intensidad e impacto funcional según el nivel de competición. Por tanto, los resultados confirman el carácter individualizado del perfil emocional y la dedicación específica que debe de recibir cada jugador (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;25(1): 11-17, 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147057</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfil emocional según el nivel de competición: Aplicación al squash</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54366^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54366^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33140^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33544^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
