<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84313</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Most feared situations related to separation anxiety and characteristics by age and gender in late childhood</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article analyzes the most fear-provoking situations related to separation anxiety for a Spanish sample of 1407 children aged between eight and eleven, and examines gender and age differences in late child-hood. It was used a specific self-report measure for separation anxiety disorder, the Separation Anxiety Scale for Children, developed for Spanish-speaking children and based on the DSM-IV-TR and ICD-10 diagnostic criteria. Results showed that children have more cognitive symptoms than psychophysiological or motor responses. The most feared situations found are related to the possibility that something bad happen to the parents and the less common situations are those related to somatic complaints. Separation anxiety symptoms were experienced by 3.9% of the sample, were more common in girls than in boys and decreasing with age. The clinical implications of these and other findings are discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Orgilés, Mireia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espada, José Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hidalgo, M. Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Fernández, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se analizan las situaciones más temidas relacionadas con la ansiedad por separación en una muestra de 1407 niños españoles con edades comprendidas entre 8 y 12 años, y se examinan las diferencias de la ansiedad por separación en función del sexo y la edad en la infancia tardía. Se utilizó una medida de autoinforme para el trastorno de ansiedad por separación, la Escala de Ansiedad por Separación Infantil, desarrollada para niños hispanohablantes y que está basada en los criterios diagnósticos del DSM-IV-TR y del CIE-10. Los resultados mostraron que los niños tienen más síntomas cognitivos que psicofisiológicos o motores. Las situaciones más temidas se relacionaban con la posibilidad de que algo malo les ocurriera a los padres y las menos comunes se relacionaban con las quejas somáticas. El 3.9% de la muestra manifestó síntomas de ansiedad por separación, más comunes en niñas que en niños y disminuyendo con la edad. Se discuten las implicaciones clínicas de estos y otros hallazgos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;27(1): 80-85, ene.-abr. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84313</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Situaciones más temidas en la infancia tardía relacionadas con la ansiedad por separación y sus características en función de la edad y el sexo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1015^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5342^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8519^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10747^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
