<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84393</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Proteomics and genetics aspects of aspirin resistance</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To evaluate the existence of a possible association between Aspirin resistance (AR), COX-1 single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) and the modifications in the plasma proteome of clinically stable coronary patients. Materials and methods: AR was defined according to the PFA-100 assay. AR-sensitive and AR-resistant patients had been taken aspirin for the last 9 months. The proteomic study (19 AR-sensitive, 19 AR-resistant) was performed using IPG strips (17cm, pH 4-7), SDS-PAGE gels (10%) and silver staining. We study three SNPs (A- 842G, C22T y C50T) in 50 AR-sensitive patients, 33 AR-resistant and 83 controls using a real-time PCR. Results: The expression of four alpha1-antitripsin isoforms was increased in the aspirin-resistant patients. No differences were found in the expression of ceruloplasmin, haptoglobin-precursor, apolipoprotein-AI and albumin- precursor between both groups of patients. The A-842G SNP was undetectable in all subjects. The remaining two SNPs (C22T y C50T) showed a low frequency with respect the global population. Conclusions: The low SNPs frequencies were unlikely to explain the difference in aspirin responsiveness between both groups of patients. The changes in alpha1-antitripsin could be linked with a different inflammatory state in these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mateos-Cáceres, P. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Arquero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Orgaz, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernardo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sacristán, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Farré, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macaya, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Ortiz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos-Mozo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Azcona, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar si existe alguna asociación entre la resistencia a aspirina (RA) y la presencia de polimorfismos genéticos de un único nucleótido (SNPs) en el gen de la COX-1, así como su relación con modificaciones en la expresión de proteínas plasmáticas en pacientes con enfermedad isquémica estable y tratamiento continuado de aspirina. Materiales y métodos: Analizamos el proteoma plasmático de 19 pacientes sensibles, 19 resistentes. RA se definió mediante el sistema PFA-100. Se realizó electroforesis bidimensional (IPG 17cm, pH(4-7), geles SDS-PAGE 10%) y tinción con plata. Se analizaron cambios en tres SNPs (A-842G, C22T y C50T) en 50 pacientes sensibles, 33 resistentes y 83 controles mediante PCR a tiempo real. Resultados: La expresión de cuatro isoformas de alfa1-antitripsina estaba aumentada en los pacientes resistentes. No encontramos diferencias en la expresión de ceruloplasmina, precursor de haptoglobina, apolipoproteína AI y precursor de albúmina entre ambos tipos de pacientes. Ningún paciente presentó cambios en el SNP A-842G. La frecuencia de cambio en C22T y C50T fue relativamente baja con respecto a la población total. Conclusiones: No encontramos asociación entre la presencia de polimorfismos en el gen de la COX-1 y la peor respuesta a la aspirina. Los cambios en observados alfa1-antitripsina podrían estar relacionados con un diferente estado inflamatorio entre ambos tipos de pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);19(3): 143-151, jul.-sept. 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84393</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aspectos proteómicos y genéticos de la resistencia a la aspirina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27951^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22164^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5478^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13441^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10788^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34510^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10788^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33840^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34510^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27938^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34510</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27940^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27938^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27940^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27940^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27951^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200809</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
