<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126033</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A combination of topical and systemic carbonic anhydrase in the treatment of chromosome X-linked retinoschisis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report: A 17 year-old male patient, who since 2000 has referred to a progressive bilateral decrease in visual acuity. A «bicycle wheel» macula pattern was observed in his retina. The electroretinogram showed a decrease in the b-wave amplitude. The visual evoked potentials were normal. Optical coherence tomography showed bilateral macular edema. All this supported the diagnosis of X-linked retinoschisis. Discussion: Genetic counseling was given and the pattern of X-linked inheritance was explained.A significant improvement of the macular thickness was observed after treatment with topical dorzolamide and oral acetazolamide (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pareja Ríos, A. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rocha Cabrera, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cordovés Dorta, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mantolán Sarmiento, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano García, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Varón de 17 años que desde el año 2000 refiere disminución progresiva de agudeza visual bilateral. Se observan en la retina máculas en patrón de «rueda de bicicleta». El electrorretinograma informa de disminución en la amplitud de la onda b. Los potenciales evocados visuales son normales. La tomografía de coherencia óptica muestra edema macular bilateral. Todo ello compatible con el diagnóstico de retinosquisis ligada al cromosoma X (RLX). Discusión: Se realiza consejo genético y se explica el patrón de herencia ligada al X.Se instaura tratamiento con dorzolamida tópica y acetazolamida oral evidenciando una mejoría significativa del grosor macular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;89(8): 320-323, ago. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126033</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Combinación de la anhidrasa carbónica tópica y sistémica en el tratamiento de la retinosquisis ligada al cromosoma X</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d287</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5950^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4669^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37285^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30310^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
