<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100389</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-2159</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Disruption of taste trace by MK-801 administration</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Sistemic administration of NMDA antagonists induces a disruption of Conditioned Taste Aversion when the drug is administered before stimuli presentation. However, there is scarce evidence, and such evidence is contradictory, on the role of NMDA receptors on Conditioned Taste Aversion when the drugs are injected in the interval between the Conditioned Stimulus (CS) and the Unconditioned Stimulus (US). In this paper we describe two experiments designed to analyze whether MK-801 (dizolcipine maleate) administration during the interval between the CS and the US disrupts Conditioned Taste Aversion (Experiment 1), and whether the introduction of a delay between MK-801 administration and US presentation prevents such disruption (Experiment 2). The results show the predicted Conditioned Taste Aversion disruption when the drug was injected inmediately before the US, and normal Conditioned Taste Aversion when a delay was introduced between the NMDA antagonist and the US. These results support a relevant role of NMDA receptors in encoding and consolidation of the taste memory trace(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Camino, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casa, L. G. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Traverso, L. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La administración sistémica de antagonistas de NMDA produce una interrupción de la Aversión Condicionada al Sabor cuando el fármaco se inyecta antes de la presentación de los estímulos. Sin embargo, existen en la literatura muy pocos experimentos que analicen la relación entre el aprendizaje de aversión al sabor y la actividad de los receptores NMDA cuando los compuestos farmacológicos se inyectan por vía sistémica entre el Estímulo Condicionado (EC) y el Estímulo Incondicionado (EI), siendo además en estos casos los resultados más contradictorios. En este trabajo presentamos dos experimentos destinados a analizar si la administración de MK-801 (dizolcipina maleate) entre el EC y el EI produce una interrupción de la Aversión Condicionada al Sabor (Experimento 1), y si la introducción de una demora temporal entre el EC y la administración del MK-801 anula el efecto disruptivo de la droga sobre la aversión al sabor (Experimento 2). Los resultados revelan que el MK-801 produce la interrupción de la ACS cuando se inyecta entre el EC y el EI y que el efecto desaparece cuando se introduce un intervalo temporal entre la administración del fármaco y el EI. Estos resultados apuntan al importante papel que los receptores NMDA desempeñan en la codificación y consolidación del trazo de memoria para el sabor(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>PsicolÔogica (Valencia, Ed. impr.);33(2): 237-255, 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100389</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eliminación del trazo gustativo tras la administración de MK-801</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31338</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12026^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14030^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30889^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4471^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13780^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12026^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12026^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3237^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8738^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12039^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12039^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201200</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
