<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111662</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-2841</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: To describe the clinical epidemiological characteristics of patients who were hospitalized in a tertiary hospital in the Canary Island (HUNSC), during the first post-pandemic influenza season. Methods: Prospective study carried out with a validated questionnaire which included hospitalized patients or those who developed influenza in a hospital context (case-patient) between January and March 2011. Severe cases were described as those casepatients  with laboratory-confirmed influenza and pneumonia, multiorganic failure, septic shock, or that who needed admission to intensive care unit (ICU). Results: The total number of case-patients was 189, from which 49 were severe cases (27 patients were male, 1 pregnant woman and 3 kids). The median age was 45 years. Seventeen patients  (34,7%) were admitted to the ICU and 7 patients died during the pandemic wave. The most frequent comorbility shown in severe influenza cases, were hypertension and obesity. Most of the patients who died, were males with normal average ages (except an unweaned baby) and presented primary-viral pneumonia. Conclusión: The clinical epidemiological description of our hospitalized patients during the post-pandemic influenza season was consistent with other reports (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fuiguera Goncalves, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Velasco, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roldán Garrido, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Torres, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padilla Salazar, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Yanes, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Lana, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcoba Flores, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir las principales características clínico-epidemiológicas de los pacientes hospitalizados por gripe en el Hospital Universitario Nuestra Señora de Candelaria (HUNSC), durante la primera temporada pospandémica. Métodos: Se trata de un estudio prospectivo mediante encuesta estandarizada donde se incluyó a todo aquel paciente que ingresaba o que desarrollaba un cuadro intrahospitalario de gripe (casopaciente) desde Enero hasta Marzo de 2011. Caso-grave se definió como aquellos casos-pacientes con gripe confirmada virológicamente y con neumonía, fallo multiorgánico, shock séptico o ingreso en Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos (UCI). Resultados: Se identificaron 189 casos-pacientes y 49 casos-graves. De estos últimos, 27 fueron varones, 1 embarazada y 3 niños. La edad media fue de 45 años. El 34.7% (n=17) ingresó en UCI y 7 pacientes fallecieron durante la onda epidémica. La comorbilidad más frecuente presentada en los casos graves fue la hipertensión arterial y la obesidad. La mayoría de los pacientes fallecidos eran varones, con edades medias (excepto  un lactante) y presentaban neumonía viral primaria. Conclusión: La descripción clínico-epidemiológica de nuestros pacientes hospitalizados durante la temporada postpandémica es consistente con otros estudios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. prev;18(3): 11-15, jul.-sept. 2012. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111662</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Descripción clínico-epidemiológica de los casos graves de gripe A en la temporada 2010/2011 en un hospital de tercer nivel en Canarias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
