<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81026</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the fight against obesity, food manufactures had offer,since several decades ago, a variety of food products namedin the beginnings as &#147;dietetic products&#148; that were basedprincipally in substitutions of sugars and fat by non-nutritivesweeteners and fat replacers. Nowadays, the research anddevelopment of new products, pretends to offer to themarket, new food products indicated specially for obesepeople that besides their low caloric content, can offer thepossibility to influence in the energy metabolism as well asin the metabolic sensation of satiety. On the other hand,the new European regulation regarding food labelling, mayencourage the food industry to carry out more investmentin research and in the determination of the effectiveness ofthe functional products launched to the market at differentlevels (biochemical, molecular, genomic and psychological).In this way, the confidence and scientifically contrastedeffectiveness of these products as preventive and therapytools against obesity, may contribute to reduce the incidenceof obesity in the whole population(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Serrano, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez González, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Para combatir la obesidad, la industria alimentaria haofrecido, desde hace varias décadas, una amplia variedadde productos denominados &#147;dietéticos&#148; que en su iniciose fundamentaban principalmente en la sustitución decarbohidratos simples y grasas por edulcorantes no nutritivosy sustitutos de grasas. Actualmente, la investigacióny el desarrollo de nuevos productos pretenden ofrecer almercado nuevos alimentos frente a la obesidad, en los quese intenta incorporar una mayor variedad de ingredientesfuncionales que además de disminuir el consumo calóricototal, pretenden influir en el metabolismo energético asícomo en la sensación metabólica de saciedad. Por otrolado, la nueva reglamentación europea del etiquetado dealimentos, estimulará a la industria alimenticia a realizarmayores inversiones en investigación para comprobar laefectividad de los alimentos funcionales lanzados al mercadoa diferentes niveles (bioquímico, molecular, genómico ypsicológico). De esta forma, la garantía y la eficacia del usode estos productos, contrastada científicamente, como herramientapreventiva y de tratamiento, contribuirá a reducirla incidencia de obesidad en la población general(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;14(3): 193-200, jul.-sep.2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81026</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tendencias en alimentos funcionales contra la obesidad: ingredientes funcionales, alimentos tecnológicamente modifi cados y dietas completas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d36357^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50326</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4071^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35427^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200809</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
