<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054200</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Up-date of the new 2nd generation vaccines against rotavirus authorized in Spain: perspectives, challenges and opportunities</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A general review and update are done on the importance of the rotavirus and its implication as a source of gastroenteritis in the child. Comments are made on the structure of the virus, classification, pathogeny, symptoms and treatment. The immunological response of the host on protection of wild virus disease is reviewed, indicating how, after first infection, reinfection is increasingly less severe as serious diarrheic disease is prevented. Briefly, the epidemiology and disease load are explained, indicating how the rotavirus is the cause of more than 600,000 deaths yearly in underdeveloped countries elevated, number of hospitalisations, outpatients visits and nosocomial infections and, consequently, the elevated morbidity and mortality that it represents for public health. It sands out that the only possible interventions is the preventive one, since the improvement achieved with health care hygienic conditions, water potability, access to oral rehydration, etc. have not led to a significant decrease in the disease incidence in both industrialized countries and developing ones. The most prevalent rotavirus serotypes and genotypes known in the world and in our country are described. Emphasis is placed on the current emergent serotypes. An extensive review is made of the principal studies that have recently appeared in the scientific literature on the new 2nd generation vaccines against the rotavirus authorized by the European Drug Agency (EMEA) and also in the United States. Although the two vaccines authorized in Spain come from different active ingredients, they have a common objective, the prevention of serious diarrhea dur to rotavirus in the child. Wide designs of safety studies including more than 70,000 children have been necessary given the events that have occurred with rotashield (first human-bovine reassortant rotavirus vaccine used in the United States and currently withdrawn from the market) and its association with bowel intussusception. It has been sufficiently provent that there is no increased risk of bowel invagination associated with the vaccination with both vaccines, Rotarix and RotaTeq TM. Trials on efficacy, immunogenicity, adverse events, etc. have also been reviewed. They have been statistically significant and sufficiently tested within the permissible ranges in relarionship with the placebos. A list is given of the recently appeared ACID (Advisory Committee Immunization Practices) recommendations for the RotaTeq TM. Brief comments are made on several of the pharmacoeconomics studies found in the literature, some of them being cost-effective, although more advanced ones will be necessary onec the vaccines are functioning and the immunization prices established for the public health system. Finally, the opportunities, challenges and perspectives of the current 2nd generation vaccines are discussed. In some of the future ones, the difficulties that they will have to face are indicated. The conclusion is reached on the importance of convincing the pediatricians on the use of these new vaccines, making the parents aware of it, providing both the regulatory authorities and them with health care education in order to include it within the common routine practice of immunizations. This requires pharmacoeconomics studies, with up-dated and real costs of the disease</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Trillo Belizón, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuenca Burgos, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrio Corrales, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Fernández, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se realiza una revisión de conjunto y puesta al día sobre la importancia del rotavirus y su implicación como fuente de gastroenteritis en el niño, haciendo unas consideraciones sobre la estructura del virus, clasificación, patogenia, clínica y tratamiento. Se revisa la respuesta inmunológica del huésped y la protección de la enfermedad por el virus salvaje, señalando cómo tras la primoinfección la reinfección es cada vez menos severa al prevenir la enfermedad diarreica grave. De una forma concisa se detalla la epidemiología y carga de la enfermedad, señalando cómo el rotavirus es el causante de más de 600.000 muertes anuales en países subdesarrollados, un número elevado de hospitalizaciones, visitas ambulatorias e infecciones nosocomiales y por ello de la elevada morbilidad y mortalidad que representa para la salud pública. Se destaca como la única intervención posible es la preventiva, dado que la mejoría lograda con las condiciones higiénico sanitarias, potabilidad del agua, acceso a la rehidratación oral, etc., no han conducido a una disminución significativa de la incidencia de la enfermedad, tanto en los países industrializados como el los de en vías de desarrollo. Se describen los serotipos y genotipos más prevalentes de rotavirus conocidos en el mundo y en nuestro país, haciendo énfasis en los serotipos emergentes en la actualidad. Se hace una revisión amplia de los principales estudios aparecidos recientemente en la literatura científica sobre las nuevas vacunas de 2ª generación frente al rotavirus autorizadas por EMEA (Agencia Europea del Medicamento) y también en Estados Unidos. Aunque las dos vacunas autorizadas en España parten de principios diferentes, tienen un objetivo común, ,la prevención de la diarrea grave por rotavirus en el niño. Dados los antecendentes acontecidos con Rotashield (primera vacuna resortatne bovina-humana utilizada en Estados Unidos frente al rotavirus y actualmente retirada del mercado) y su asociación con la invaginación intestinal, han sido necesarios amplios diseños de estudios de seguridad que incluyeran a más de 70.000 niños. Con ambas vacunas Rotarix y RotaTeq TM ha quedado suficientemente probado que no existe aumento del riesgo de invaginación intestinal asociado a la vacunación. Igualmente se han revisado los ensayos sobre eficacia, inmunogenicidad, efectos adversos, etc., que han resultado ser estadísticamente significativos y suficientemente probados dentro de los rangos permisibles en relación con losa placebos. Se relacionan las recomendaciones del ACIP (Advisory Committee Inmunization Practices) para la vacuna RotaTeq TM aparecidas recientemente. Se hacen unas breves consideraciones sobre varios de los estudios de fármaco-economía encontrados en la literatura, mostrando ser coste efectivos algunos de ellos, aunque sean necesarios otros más avanzados una vez que las vacunas estén funcionando y se fijen los precios de la inmunización para la sanidad pública. Finalmente se discuten las oportunidades, retos y perspectivas de las actuales vacunas de 2ª generación y el algunas de las futuras señalando las dificultades con las que tendrán que enfrentarse. Se llega a la conclusión de la importancia en la mentalización de los pediatras en el uso de estas nuevas vacunas, sensibilización de los padres, educación sanitaria de los mismos y la de nuestras autoridades sanitarias para su inclusión en la práctica rutinaria común de las inmunizaciones precisando estudios de fármaco-economía, cargas actualizadas y reales de la enfermedad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;62(5): 403-425, sept.-oct. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054200</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actualización de las nuevas vacunas de 2ª generación frente al rotavirus autorizadas en España: perspectivas, retos y oportunidades</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3994^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31778^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31778^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3994^s32386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12776^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12776^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31778^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35386^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3994^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
