<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127297</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Early detection, prevention and management of renal failure in liver transplantation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Renal failure is a frequent complication in liver transplant recipients and is associated with increased morbidity and mortality. A variety of risk factors for the development of renal failure in the pre- and post-transplantation periods have been described, as well as at the time of surgery. To reduce the negative impact of renal failure in this population, an active approach is required for the identification of those patients with risk factors, the implementation of preventive strategies, and the early detection of progressive deterioration of renal function. Based on published evidence and on clinical experience, this document presents a series of recommendations on monitoring RF in LT recipients, as well as on the prevention and management of acute and chronic renal failure after LT and referral of these patients to the nephrologist. In addition, this document also provides an update of the various immunosuppressive regimens tested in this population for the prevention and control of post-transplantation deterioration of renal function (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cruzado, Josep Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bilbao, Itxarone</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lladó, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oppenheimer, Federico</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castells, Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baliellas, Carme</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Valdecasas, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serón, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esforzado, Núria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rimola, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cantarell, Carme</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La insuficiencia renal es una complicación frecuente de la población con trasplante hepático que se asocia con una elevada morbimortalidad. Se han descrito múltiples factores de riesgo para el desarrollo de insuficiencia renal postrasplante hepático en los periodos pre y postrasplante hepático, así como en el propio momento del trasplante. Para reducir el impacto de la insuficiencia renal postrasplante hepático es necesaria una actitud activa para la identificación de los pacientes con factores de riesgo, la implementación de estrategias preventivas y la detección precoz del deterioro de la función renal. Tomando como base las evidencias publicadas y la experiencia clínica, el presente documento incluye recomendaciones para la monitorización de la función renal en los pacientes con trasplante hepático, la prevención y el manejo de la insuficiencia renal postrasplante hepático, y la derivación al nefrólogo. Asimismo, se actualizan las pautas inmunosupresoras probadas para la prevención o el control del deterioro de la función renal tras el trasplante hepático (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;37(8): 480-491, oct. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127297</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Detección precoz, prevención y manejo de la insuficiencia renal en el trasplante hepático</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33809^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38622^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29476^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19185^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
