<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167238</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-9891</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reaction time, processing speed and sustained attention in schizophrenia: impact on social functioning</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Previous studies have linked processing speed with social cognition and functioning of patients with schizophrenia. A discriminant analysis is needed to determine the different components of this neuropsychological construct. This paper analyzes the impact of processing speed, reaction time and sustained attention on social functioning. Material and methods. 98 outpatients between 18 and 65 with DSM-5 diagnosis of schizophrenia, with a period of 3 months of clinical stability, were recruited. Sociodemographic and clinical data were collected, and the following variables were measured: processing speed (Trail Making Test [TMT], symbol coding [BACS], verbal fluency), simple and elective reaction time, sustained attention, recognition of facial emotions and global functioning. Results. Processing speed (measured only through the BACS), sustained attention (CPT) and elective reaction time (but not simple) were associated with functioning. Recognizing facial emotions (FEIT) correlated significantly with scores on measures of processing speed (BACS, Animals, TMT), sustained attention (CPT) and reaction time. The linear regression model showed a significant relationship between functioning, emotion recognition (P=.015) and processing speed (P=.029). Conclusions. A deficit in processing speed and facial emotion recognition are associated with worse global functioning in patients with schizophrenia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vicens, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brañas, Antía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orozco, Arantxa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lahera, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Estudios previos han relacionado la velocidad de procesamiento con la funcionalidad y la cognición social de los pacientes con esquizofrenia. Se necesita un análisis más discriminativo de los diferentes componentes de este constructo neuropsicológico. El presente trabajo analiza el impacto de la velocidad de procesamiento, del tiempo de reacción y de la atención sostenida sobre el funcionamiento social. Material y métodos. Un total de 98 pacientes ambulatorios de entre 18 y 65 años con diagnóstico DSM-5 de esquizofrenia, con un período de 3 meses de estabilidad clínica, fueron reclutados. Se recogieron datos sociodemográficos y clínicos, y se midieron: velocidad de procesamiento (Test del Trazo [TMT], codificación de símbolos [BACS], fluidez verbal), tiempos de reacción simple y electiva, atención sostenida, reconocimiento de emociones faciales y funcionalidad. Resultados. Las medidas que se asociaron con funcionalidad fueron: velocidad de procesamiento (medida solo a través de la BACS), atención sostenida (CPT) y tiempo de reacción electiva (pero no simple). El reconocimiento de emociones faciales (FEIT) se correlacionó de forma significativa con la puntuación en las medidas de velocidad de procesamiento (BACS, Animales, TMT), atención sostenida (CPT) y tiempo de reacción simple. El modelo de regresión lineal mostró una relación significativa entre funcionalidad, reconocimiento de emociones (p=0,015) y velocidad de procesamiento (p=0,029). Conclusiones. El déficit en velocidad de procesamiento y reconocimiento facial de emociones se asocia a peor funcionamiento global en pacientes con esquizofrenia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psiquiatr. salud ment. (Barc., Ed. impr.);10(4): 197-205, oct.-dic. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167238</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tiempo de reacción, velocidad de procesamiento y atención sostenida en esquizofrenia: impacto sobre el funcionamiento social</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2798^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12946</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33140</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12364^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3102^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
