<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-18233</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Post traumatic stress and addiction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The scientific literature includes the prevalence of posttraumatic stress disorder associated with drug use. Both overlap each other, making a therapeutic approach difficult. The diagnosis of both, their coexistence and their evolutionary course, is seen to be implicated in the result of therapeutic action. Therefore, it is essential to discard it when diagnosing any addictive disorder of a poor evolution. We are presenting ten cases in which we found clinical comorbidity from drug abuse/dependence disorder or post-traumatic stress, pointing out the importance of the dual diagnoses in order to carry out a complete treatment and thus improve the prognosis for both processes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Socidrogalcohol</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La literatura científica recoge la prevalencia del trastorno de estrés post-traumático asociado al consumo de drogas. Ambos se complican entre sí dificultando el abordaje terapéutico. El diagnóstico de ambos, su coexistencia y su curso evolutivo se ven implicados en el resultado de las actuaciones terapéuticas. De ahí que resulte imprescindible descartarlo, a la hora de realizar el diagnóstico de cualquier trastorno adictivo con evolución tórpida. Presentamos una serie de diez casos en los que hallamos comorbilidad clínica de trastorno por abuso/dependencia de drogas y estrés post-traumático, señalando la importancia del diagnóstico dual para realizar el tratamiento integral y mejorar, así el pronóstico de ambos procesos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);14(4): 487-490, oct. 2002. tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrés post-traumático y adicciones</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Lloréns, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente, T de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calatayud, MD</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-18233</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30236^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30236^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30236^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
