<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107262</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cervical cystic lymphangioma: still a challenge</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Cervical lymphangiomas can not only cause severes equelae (aesthetic, phonatory or deglutory) but can also be life the reatening due to airway compresion or massive bleeding. This paper analyzes our surgical results, the value of prenatal diagnosis and the use of new techniques such as the EXIT procedure for airway control in sereve cases .Patients and methods. We retrospectively reviewed the medical record of patients with cervical lymphangiomas treated in our center between 1986 and 2009, according to our Clinical Documentation Database. Data referred to prenatal diagnosis, intrapartum airway management, surgical procedures and morbidity, sclerosing substance infiltration and long term sequelae was analyzed. Results. Thirteen cases were identified. 53.8% of the patients were (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Vaquero, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillén, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carreras, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peiró, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lloret, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marhuenda, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Ibáñez, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molino, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los linfangiomas cervicales de gran tamaño pueden no solo asociarse a graves secuelas estéticas, fonatorias o deglutorias, sino amenazar la supervivencia del paciente por compresión de la vía aérea o sangrados masivos. El objetivo de este trabajo es evaluar nuestros resultados quirúrgicos, el valor del diagnóstico prenatal y la aplicación de técnicas como el EXIT (Ex-Utero Intrapartum Treatment)para el control de la vía aérea en casos graves. Pacientes y métodos. Revisión retrospectiva de los linfangiomas cervicales tratados en nuestro centro entre 1986 y 2009, según el registro de Documentación Clínica. Se han analizado datos referentes al diagnóstico prenatal, manejo intraparto de la vía aérea, tratamiento quirúrgico y sus complicaciones, uso de esclerosantes y secuelas a (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;23(3): 147-152, jul. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107262</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Linfangioma quístico cervical: todavía un reto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6409^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31330^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24871^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201007</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
