<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82947</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bibliometric study of casuistic papers published in the Spanish Journal of Pathology between 2005 and 2009</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bibliometric studies provide information about the status of a particular area of research.The present study examined the sources of reference of casuistic articles published in the Spanish Journal of Pathology between 2005 and 2009. The following indicators were evaluated: authors and collaborators, article category, year of publication and source, Bradford distribution, obsolescence index, Price index, language and insularity index. 120 articles from 5 editions of the journal were studied. The average number of authors per article was 4.22 and the average number of citations 13.96, the majority of which were taken from scientific journals. The authors tended to refer to recent publications, predominantly in English, with 9 journals being cited most frequently; the inslularity index was 8.92%. Although this pattern coincides with bibliometric studies of other Spanish journals, some unexpected charactistics were found which should be analyzed further in the future. The overall conclusion is that authors of casuistic articles in the Spanish Journal of Pathology make use of recent publications, mainly from North American and English journals(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Camps, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los estudios bibliométricos permiten conocer el estado de un área o campo de investigación. Este trabajo se realizó para conocer los patrones de citación de los artículos de casuística publicados en la Revista Española de Patología. Se estudiaron los artículos de casuística publicados entre los años 2005 y 2009, y se consideraron los siguientes indicadores: autoría y colaboración, tipología documental, año de publicación, distribución en áreas de Bradford, índice de obsolescencia, índice de Price, idioma de las referencias e índice de aislamiento. De los cinco volúmenes estudiados se analizaron 120 manuscritos, con 4,22 firmas por artículo. Los manuscritos presentaron un promedio de 13,96 citas, con predominio de las revistas científicas. Los autores citaron literatura actualizada con un núcleo de nueve revistas citadas con mayor frecuencia. El idioma predominante en las referencias fue el inglés, y el índice de aislamiento fue del 8,92%. El patrón es coincidente con estudios bibliométricos en otras revistas españolas, aunque presenta características particulares que deberán ser analizadas y estudiadas en el futuro. Se puede concluir que los autores que publican en la Revista Española de Patología utilizan recursos actualizados, de origen anglosajón, y sus estudios se basan en literatura reciente(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;43(4): 196-200, oct.-dic.2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82947</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio bibliométrico de artículos de casuística publicados en la Revista Española de Patología, 2005&#150;2009</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8545</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10530^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10530^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
