<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-65794</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-6157</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Zirconium dioxide, sometimes known as zirconia or baddeleyite, is a white crystalline oxide of zirconium is one of the most studied ceramic materials. Several different oxides are added to zirconia to stabilize, but in dentistry the yttrium oxide is the main element. Initially it&#146;s use was focused as a refractory material, ceramic glazes and in the aerospace industry, nowadays find application in the medicine. The titanium and metal alloys used in restorative and implant dental can have a negative influence on cell metabolism and hence can cause some damage. This appear to be the main reason for the search of new metal-free materials, including dental implants. The positive materials properties of dioxide zirconium include: biocompatibility, biofunctionality, aesthetic, adequate mechanical behaviour, good temperature resistance, reduced tendency towards corrosion, low solubility, increased our chances to obtain patient&#146;s satisfaction from all standpoint (AU) </dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villarreal, Einer</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Soler, Luis A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Masip, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espías Gómez, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El dióxido de circonio, también conocido como, zirconio o badeleyitaes un material cerámico blanco cristalino de los más estudiados. Requiere la agregación de estabilizadores, teniendo el óxido de y trioamplia aplicación en odontología. En sus inicios, su uso estuvo enfocado como: material refractario, cerámica de vidrio, o como componente de partes desarrollada por la industria aeroespacial. Actualmente, su uso en medicina está muy difundido. El titanio y las aleaciones metálicas usadas en odontología restauradora e implantológica pueden tener un efecto negativo sobre el metabolismo celular, pudiendo causar daños. Este hecho, al parecerse convierte en el principal motivo para ir en busca de materiales libres de metal, incluso para su aplicación en implantes dentales. Dentro de las principales propiedades positivas tenemos: biocompatibilidad, biofuncionalidad, estética, adecuada conducta mecánica, resistencia a la temperatura, reducida tendencia corrosiva, baja solubilidad; incrementando nuestras posibilidades de obtener la satisfacción del paciente desde todo punto de vista (AU) </dc:description>
<dc:source>Dentum (Barc.);7(3): 113-117, jul.-sept. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-65794</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d3778^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24600^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15435^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15435^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8483^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14464^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14464^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14414^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5046^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3778^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3778^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5046^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
