<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166252</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ethical considerations in presymptomatic diagnosis of autosomal dominant spinocerebellar ataxias</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Information on achieving presymptomatic diagnosis of spinocerebellar ataxia (SCA) is limited. The advent of molecular diagnosis makes it possible to identify the carriers of different diseases and has also introduced the prospect of detecting diseases even before their onset. This has drawn attention to the ethical implications that must be considered in these subjects with a view to preserving their physical and psychological well-being. Development: SCA is composed of a group of neurodegenerative disorders with autosomal dominant inheritance. Only a few publications have described the genetic counselling processes and guidelines to be followed during the process of presymptomatic diagnosis (PSD). The size of the multidisciplinary teams, their areas of expertise, and the number of counselling sessions are different for each of the studies analysed here. However, the basis of presymptomatic diagnosis originates in common guidelines to which members of our team have contributed recently. Conclusion: Presymptomatic diagnosis should be performed according to guidelines that safeguard the subjects&#146; welfare. The diagnostic process is only recommended for patients over 18 years old with symptoms suggesting SCA, and a minimum risk of 50%. Genetic counselling programmes must be available in all centres that offer presymptomatic diagnosis of SCA (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Cruz, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orozco-Gutiérrez, MH</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cervantes-Aragón, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Existe información limitada de la realización de diagnóstico presintomático en ataxias espinocerebelosas (SCA) autosómicas dominantes. La llegada del diagnóstico molecular, además de brindar la posibilidad de realizar identificación en pacientes portadores de distintas enfermedades, permitió también la posibilidad de detectar enfermedades incluso antes de su presentación. Esto atrajo la atención sobre las implicaciones éticas que deberían ser consideradas en estos sujetos, con la finalidad de salvaguardar su bienestar físico y psicológico. Desarrollo: La SCA está compuesta por un grupo de trastornos neurodegenerativos con patrón de herencia autosómico dominante. Existen pocas publicaciones que describen el proceso de asesoramiento y los lineamientos considerados durante el proceso de diagnóstico presintomático. El número de integrantes de los equipos multidisciplinarios, sus áreas de especialidad y número de sesiones durante el asesoramiento es variable en cada uno de los trabajos analizados. Sin embargo, las bases para su realización tienen origen en documentos comunes, en los cuales algunos de los autores han participado en fechas más recientes. Conclusiones: El diagnóstico presintomático debe ser realizado bajo lineamientos que salvaguarden el bienestar de los sujetos. Sería recomendable que el diagnóstico de SCA sea realizado solo a pacientes con clínica sugestiva, mayores de 18 años y con un riesgo mínimo del 50%. Deben estar disponibles esquemas de asesoramiento genético en todos aquellos centros que pretenden realizar diagnóstico de SCA antes de la presentación de síntomas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;32(7): 469-475, sept. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166252</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consideraciones éticas en el diagnóstico presintomático de ataxias espinocerebelosas autosómico dominantes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5950^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29177^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34243^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34293^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33354^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
