<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-70092</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The antithrombotic therapy in paediatric patients is carried out using guides extrapolated from adults, in spite of their different haemostatic condition. In the treatment with heparins, the unfractionated heparin (UH) is used in a continuous infusion in a dose suitable to the patient&#146;s age and body weight (in children under the age of one 28 U/kg/h and in children over the age of two 20 U/kg/h). In low-molecular-weight heparins (LMWH), sometimes alternatives to oral anticoagulants, the dose varies according to the age, body weight and type of heparin with the therapeutic objective of achieving an anti-Xa level of between 0.5-1 U/mL 4 hours after administration. As regards the oral anticoagulant therapy, its application is problematic because of the different haemostatic conditions of children, with serious hemorrhagic complications accounting for 2% of the cases; the duration varies depending on whet herit is a thromboembolism because of thrombophilia (6 months)or whether it is secondary to a disease (minimum 3 months). In acute venous thrombosis a therapy with UH must be started followed by an OAT. In the antiplatelet therapy, used in the arterial thromboembolic processes, the most commonly used drug is aspirin (1-5 mg/kg/day), followed by dipiridamol in doses of 2-5 mg/kg/day. The use of thrombolytics requires a detailed evaluation of the potential risks due to the decrease of the total capacity of the fibrinolytic system. The two most commonly used thrombolytics are urokinase and the tissue plasminogen activator (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Iriarte Ezcurdia, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vacas Rius, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáez Meabe, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molinero de Miguel, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Rubio, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáez de Lafuente Chivite, J. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sagastagoitia Gorostiza, J. D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tratamiento antitrombótico en los pacientes pediátricos se realiza utilizando guías extrapoladas de adultos, a pesar de su diferente condición hemostática. En el tratamiento con heparinas,la heparina no fraccionada (HNF) se utiliza en perfusión continua en dosis adecuada a la edad y el peso corporal (en niños menores de un año 28 UI/kg/h, y en los mayores de dos años 20 UI/kg/h). En las heparinas de bajo peso molecular(HBPM), a veces alternativas a los anticoagulantes orales, la dosis varía en función de la edad, el peso corporal y el tipo de heparina, con el objetivo terapéutico de conseguir un nivel de anti-Xa entre 0,5 y 1 UI/mL a las 4 horas de administración. En cuanto al tratamiento anticoagulante oral, su aplicación es problemática debido a las diferentes condiciones hemostáticas de los niños; en un 2% de los casos las complicaciones son las hemorragias graves; la duración es variable según sea una tromboembolia por trombofilia (6 meses) o secundaria a una enfermedad(mínimo 3 meses). En las trombosis venosas agudas se debe iniciar el tratamiento con HNF seguido de tratamiento anticoagulante oral. En el tratamiento antiagregante, utilizado en los procesos tromboembólicos arteriales, el fármaco más utilizado es el ácido acetil salicílico (1-5 mg/kg/día), seguido del dipiridamol en dosis de 2-5 mg/kg/día. La utilización de trombolíticos requiere una evaluación escrupulosa de los riesgos potenciales debido a la disminución de la capacidad total del sistema fibrinolítico; los dos más utilizados son la urocinasa y el activador tisular del plasminógeno (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;66(9): 431-440, oct. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-70092</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23279^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2384^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2384^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2384^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
