<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61855</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of endoscopic visualisation for identifying premalignant gastric lesions in a Columbian population using histopathology as a reference</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To evaluate the performance of endoscopic visualization in the identification of premalignant gastric lesions, with histopathological examination of biopsy samples as a reference test, in Bucaramanga, Colombia. Location: League for the Fight Against Cancer, Bucaramanga, Colombia. Design: Diagnostic technology evaluation with cross-sectional sampling. Measurements: We calculate the sensitivity, specificity, positive predictive value, negative predictive value, likelihood ratio (+), likelihood ratio (&amp;#8722;), kappa index and the prevalence rate kappa. Results: A total of 155 patients were studied, with a mean age of 45.43 (14.15) years and an approximate male:female ratio of 2:1. The endoscopic visualization had a sensitivity of 87.84%, a specificity of 55.56%, a positive predictive value of 64.36%, a negative predictive value of 83.33%, a likelihood ratio+of 1.98, a likelihood ratio&amp;#8722;de 0.22 and a kappa index of 0.4272, in the identification of preneoplastic lesions of the stomach in a population with a disease prevalence of 47.74%. Conclusions: The endoscopic visualization of the gastrointestinal mucosa, allows a moderate and fast identification of early preneoplastic lesions, providing an opportunity of its early histopathological diagnosis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Ramírez, Carlos Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivero Rendon, Luis Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olarte Villamizar, Javier Mauricio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Pérez, Julio Alexander</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orozco Vargas, Luis Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferreira Bohorquez, Edgar Julián</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: evaluar el rendimiento de la visualización directa por endoscopia en la identificación de lesiones gástricas premalignas, utilizando como prueba de referencia el examen histopatológico de muestras obtenidas por biopsia. Emplazamiento: liga de Lucha Contra el Cáncer, de Bucaramanga, Colombia. Diseño: estudio de evaluación de tecnologías diagnósticas con muestreo transversal. Mediciones principalesse calculó la sensibilidad, la especificidad, el valor predictivo positivo, el valor predictivo negativo, el likelihood ratio positivo, el likelihood ratio negativo, el índice kappa y la prevalencia. Resultados: se estudió a 155 pacientes con una media de edad de 45,43±14,15 años y una relación varón:mujer aproximada de 2:1. La visualización por endoscopia tuvo una sensibilidad del 87,84%, una especificidad del 55,56%, un valor predictivo positivo del 64,36%, un valor predictivo negativo del 83,33%, un likelihood ratio positivo de 1,98, un likelihood ratio negativo de 0,22 y un índice kappa de 0,4272, en la identificación de lesiones preneoplásicas del estómago en una población con una prevalencia de la enfermedad del 47,74%. Conclusiones: la visualización mediante endoscopia de la mucosa gastrointestinal permite una rápida y moderada identificación de lesiones preneoplásicas tempranas, lo que da la posibilidad de su diagnóstico histopatológico precoz(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;41(2): 85-89, feb. 2009. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61855</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la visualización por endoscopia en la identificación de lesiones gástricas premalignas en una población colombiana con prueba de referencia histopatológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11665^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3137</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29396</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5894^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
