<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84440</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessing frail patients in the emergency department</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Frail, elderly patients appropriately use hospital emergency services with increasing frequency. An effective evidence based model for evaluating such patients in the emergency department has not been developed. Nonetheless, when assessing the frail elderly we are advised to establish clear objectives appropriate to their overall situation so that a multidimensional diagnosis can be made and treatment priorities set. An evaluation of functional status is useful for planning continuity of care to be provided by the primary care team after these patients are discharged (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Duaso, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Soto, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los pacientes ancianos frágiles utilizan cada vez más y de forma adecuada los servicios de urgencias hospitalarios (SUH). No existen evidencias que demuestren la efectividad de un modelo concreto de valoración geriátrica aplicado en los servicios de urgencias. Sin embargo, la valoración del paciente frágil en los SUH se debería utilizar adecuándola al entorno y con unos objetivos claros que permitieran realizar un diagnóstico multidimensional y establecer prioridades terapéuticas. La valoración del estado funcional aporta beneficios en la continuidad de cuidados por parte de la atención primaria, cuando los pacientes son dados de alta del SUH (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);21(5): 362-369, oct. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84440</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración del paciente frágil en urgencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28940^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24693^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
