<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109017</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact on the implementation of patient controlled epidural analgesia for pain management during labor. A survey in a university hospital in Chile</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Analgesia for labor is a legal obligation in Chile. In our institution we implemented patient controlled analgesia for pain relief during labor. We describe the perception of the several professionals involved in the medical care of patients in labor in terms of effectiveness, usefulness, satisfaction, and safety. Material and methods. A self-reported questionnaire was given to the professionals involved, and the obstetrical and neonatal outcomes were recorded along with the workload indices. Twenty-five structured questions were presented with a Likert type score to evaluate analgesia quality, workload of professionals involved, adverse effects, patient satisfaction, and healthcare workers satisfaction. Finally, a question was asked about the overall perception. Results. We found that the overall perception of the analgesic technique was (mean) 6.0 (SD) (0.88). A decrease in the anesthesiologist workload was observed, without affecting obstetric outcomes. Conclusion. Considering the study design limitations, absence of knowledge of economical impact, and the satisfaction level of patients under standard epidural analgesia, we recommend the patient controlled analgesia technique due to its good obstetric outcomes, general satisfaction and workload decrease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferdinand, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lacassie, HJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montaña, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. La administración de analgesia para el parto es una obligación legal en Chile. Este trabajo describe la percepción de los profesionales involucrados en la atención de las pacientes que están en trabajo de parto, con relación a la implantación del uso de la técnica de analgesia controlada por la paciente en cuanto a los resultados obstétricos obtenidos, satisfacción de los profesionales, impacto en la carga de trabajo y seguridad. Material y métodos. Se aplicó una encuesta autoadministrada a todos los profesionales que trabajan en el área de partos de la institución y se revisaron las incidencias de los resultados obstétricos y de carga de trabajo. La encuesta incluyó 25 preguntas estructuradas utilizando una escala tipo Lickert evaluando las dimensiones de calidad analgésica, carga y forma de trabajo en el Servicio, efectos colaterales, satisfacción de paciente y personal. Concluía la encuesta con una pregunta de percepción global. Resultados. La percepción global de satisfacción tras la introducción de la técnica para trabajo de parto fue de 6,0 (±0,88). En el grupo de anestesiólogos se evidencia una reducción de la carga laboral, sin afectar el resultado obstétrico ni neonatal. Conclusión. Considerando las limitaciones del tipo de trabajo, de no conocer el impacto económico ni la satisfacción de las pacientes en las cuales se utiliza la técnica de analgesia epidural, recomendamos la utilización de la analgesia controlada por la paciente para esta indicación, dada la buena percepción del equipo de trabajo con relación a los resultados obstétricos, la satisfacción con la técnica y la disminución en la carga de trabajo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;60(1): 23-28, ene. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109017</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de la implantación y desarrollo de la analgesia epidural administrada por la paciente para el tratamiento del dolor del parto. Encuesta en un hospital universitario en Chile</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6940^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28857^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d778^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38636^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6940^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23557^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35120</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23557^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28857^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28857^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201301</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
