<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112854</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship between psychopathological comorbidity and outcomes variables in-treatment cocaine dependent subject in therapeutic community</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Over the last years, the therapeutic community treatment with people who have cocaine problems and psychopathological comorbidity has been increasing and it is important to know more about the success of these treatments. The aim of this paper is to study the psychopathological profile of cocaine-dependent patients and its association with outcome variables. It is interviewed by the Psychiatric Research Interview for Substance and Mental Disorders (PRISM-IV) and the Conners&#146; Adult ADHD Diagnostic Interview for DSM-IV (CAADID) a total sample of 218 patients who sought treatment at any of the six public therapeutics community of Andalusia (Spain). The results show that the retention rate after three months of 68.3% (149), 43.5% that leaves the resource with a therapeutic discharge and 52.8% with clinically significant changes. Besides, the 57.8% have psychopathological comorbidity. Finally, there is a higher treatment success (measured by days of stay, type of discharge and therapeutic community outcome clinical impression) among people without psychopathological comorbidity. These data show the need to adapt the therapeutic communities to treat people with comorbid psychopathology and, thus, improve therapeutic success (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Calderón, Fermín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Betanzos Espinosa, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vergara-Moragues, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Saiz, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bilbao Acedos, Izaskum</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Verdejo García, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano-Rojas, Oscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez García, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El ingreso en comunidad terapéutica de personas con problemas de consumo de cocaína y comorbilidad psicopatológica ha ido aumentando en los últimos años y es importante conocer más sobre el éxito de estos tratamientos. El objetivo de este trabajo es estudiar el perfil psicopatológico de los pacientes dependientes de cocaína y su asociación con las variables de resultados. Se entrevistaron mediante la Psychiatric Research Interview for Substance and Mental Disorders (PRISM-IV) y la Conners&#146; Adult ADHD Diagnostic Interview for DSM-IV (CAADID) a una muestral total de 218 pacientes que solicitaron tratamiento en alguna de las seis comunidades terapéuticas públicas de Andalucía. Los resultados exponen que el porcentaje de retención a los tres meses es del 68.3% (149). De los cuales, el 43.5% abandona el recurso con un alta terapéutica y el 52.8 % con cambios clínicamente relevantes. Además, el 57.8% presentan comorbilidad psicopatológica. Por último, existe un mayor éxito terapéutico (medidos por días de estancias, tipo de altas y objetivos cumplido tras el tratamiento) entre las personas sin comorbilidad psicopatológica. Estos datos sugieren la necesidad de adaptar las comunidades terapéuticas en el tratamiento de personas dependientes de cocaína con comorbilidad psicopatológica y, de esta manera, mejorar el éxito terapéutico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);25(2): 128-136, abr.-jun. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112854</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre la comorbilidad psicopatológica y las variables de resultados en dependientes de cocaína tratados en comunidad terapéutica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3187^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31511^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
