<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055442</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Areolar approach in augmentation mammaplasty</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Augmentation mammoplasty has gained acceptance as a safe surgical procedure with fast recovery and a readily predictable outcome. Increasing patient expectations impose demands on natural appearance without signs of surgery. All standard incision areas for insertion of implant leave visible scars. For women with large areolar diameter, it is possible to leave a hidden scar at the aerola-nipple junction by conducting an intra- areolar approach. The technique is described and its intended application and advantages and disadvantages are discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villamán González, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo Delgado, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Troncoso Rigotti, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prado Scott, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuentes Freire, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La mamoplastia de aumento se ha consolidado como una cirugía segura, de rápida recuperación y con resultados predecibles e inmediatos. Las expectativas de las pacientes son cada vez mayores, exigiendo resultados naturales y sin estigmas quirúrgicos. Todas las vías de abordaje clásicas, para la colocación de implantes mamarios, dejan cicatrices visibles. En mujeres con areolas de diámetro grande, es posible emplear un abordaje dentro de la areola, que deja una cicatriz oculta en su unión con el pezón. Se describe la técnica y posteriormente se discuten sus indicaciones, ventajas y desventajas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;33(2): 91-96, abr.-jun. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055442</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abordaje areolar en mamoplastia de aumento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29995^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29995^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11916^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11916^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29995^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13900^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13900^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13900^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
