<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-32914</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Auditory abilities in children with cleft lip and / or palated according to Fisher's</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">AIM: Patients with cleft palate and/or lip have similar behaviors to those with auditory processing disorders (APD), then the aim of this study was to investigate auditory abilities in the population with cleft lip/palate. MATERIAL AND METHODS: 100 children between 7 and 12 years old with cleft and 65 between 6 and 10 years old without it. Conventional audiological evaluations such as pure tone, word discrimination audiometry and acoustic immittance measures. A questionnaire (Fisher) was given to parents, with 25 items about behaviors found in children with APD. RESULTS: 100% of children with cleft lip/palate showed some indicative behaviors of APD. CONCLUSION: There was significant occurrence of suggestive behaviors of APD, what points out the importance of inclusion of auditory processing tests in evaluation of children with cleft lip/palate (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sanidad y Ediciones (SANED, S.L.)</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: los pacientes con hendidura labial y / o palatatina poseen comportamientos similares a aquellos con desorden del procesamiento auditivo (DPA), de esta manera, este trabajo tiene por objetivo investigar las habilidades auditivas en la población con hendidura de labio y / o paladar. Método: 100 niños de 7 a 12 años con hendidura y 65 de 6 a 10 años sin hendidura. Fue realizada una evaluación audiológica clínica convencional (audiometría, logoaudiometría e imitanciometría) en seguida fue aplicado un cuestionario (FISHER) a los padres, compuestos de 25 preguntas referentes a los comportamientos encontrados en niños con DPA. Resultados: 100 por ciento de los niños con hendidura presentaron algún comportamiento indicativo de DPA. Conclusión: Hubo gran ocurrencia de las manifestaciones sugestivas de DPA, conduciendo a pensar en la inclusión de pruebas especiales del procesamiento auditivo en la evaluación de niños con hendidura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;55(4): 160-164, abr. 2004. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Habilidades auditivas de niños con hendidura labial y / o palatina según el cuestionario Fisher</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Ulhôa, FM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribeiro Feniman, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cayres Minardi, CG</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferreira Campos, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernandes Souza, AC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paranhos Netto, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sodário Cruz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-32914</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d1306</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6462^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29352^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29353</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
