<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159582</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A longitudinal comparison of metacognitive therapy and acceptance and commitment therapy models of anxiety disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Metacognitive therapy (MCT) suggests that anxiety disorders are caused by the cognitive attentional syndrome (CAS), which is supported by dysfunctional metacognitive beliefs. Acceptance and commitment therapy (ACT) emphasizes the role of cognitive fusion and experiential avoidance in the development of these disorders. In this study, it was hypothesized that the ACT concepts of cognitive fusion and experiential avoidance would mediate the relationship between dysfunctional metacognitive beliefs and anxiety/stress symptoms. A longitudinal design was employed. One hundred and six nonclinical participants responded twice to an online survey with a lapse of nine months. Cognitive fusion at Time 2 mediated the effect of negative metacognitive beliefs at Time 1 on anxiety symptoms at T2, whereas both cognitive fusion and experiential avoidance mediated the effect on stress symptoms. Cognitive fusion mediated the effect of positive metacognitive beliefs only on stress symptoms. These results warrant further comparison of the MCT and ACT model (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Odriozola González, Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La terapia metacognitiva (MCT) sugiere que los trastornos de ansiedad son causados por el síndrome atencional cognitivo (CAS), que es apoyado por creencias metacognitivas disfuncionales. La terapia de aceptación y compromiso (ACT) enfatiza el rol de la fusión cognitiva y la evitación experiencial en el desarrollo de estos trastornos. En este estudio se hipotetizó que los conceptos de fusión cognitiva y evitación experiencial mediarían la relación entre las creencias metacognitivas disfuncionales y los síntomas de ansiedad/estrés. Se utilizó un diseño longitudinal. Ciento seis participantes respondieron en dos ocasiones a una encuesta online en el lapos de nueve meses. La fusión cognitiva en el Tiempo 2 medió el efecto de las creencias metacognitivas en el Tiempo 1 en los síntomas de ansiedad en el Tiempo 2, mientras que la fusión cognitiva y la evitación experiencial mediaron el efecto en los síntomas de estrés. La fusión cognitiva medió el efecto de las creencias metacognitivas positivas sólo en los síntomas de estrés. Los resultados justifican comparaciones adicionales de los modelos de MCT y ACT (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;33(1): 7-17, ene. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159582</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Una comparación longitudinal de los modelos de los trastornos de ansiedad de la terapia metacognitiva y la terapia de aceptación y compromiso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55386^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56084</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
