<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98355</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Career counselling effectiveness in career decision making</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study analyzes the effectiveness of a career counselling program aimed to help students to make a vocational choice in a career decision point. 178 students between 13 and 17 years of age participated in 5 weekly sessions of 90 minutes, and 143 other subjects composed the control group. Career exploration and vocational indecision were the assessed dependent variables. There were differences between groups in the pre test concerning sex distribution, career exploration and vocational indecision measures. In the post scores, experimental group had significantly higher scores in several career exploration dimensions and significantly lower scores in vocational indecision. The between-groups effect size (d Cohen) was medium to high for several career exploration dimensions and indecision, in the experimental group, and almost null in the control group. We can conclude that the counselling program is effective for the increase of exploratory behaviours and for the reduction of vocational indecision. Implications for counselling psychology practice and research are discussed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Maia, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Do Céu Taveira, Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Farial, Liliana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio analiza la eficacia de un programa de consejo psicológico destinado a ayudar a los alumnos a tomar decisiones vocacionales después de la etapa de escolaridad obligatoria. Participaron 178 estudiantes entre 13 y 17 años que asistieron a cinco sesiones semanales de 90 minutos, y 143 estudiantes como grupo control. Se evaluaron la exploración y la indecisión vocacional antes y después del programa. Se constataron diferencias previas entre grupos en la distribución del sexo y en las puntuaciones de exploración e indecisión vocacional. Una vez realizado el programa, el grupo de intervención obtuvo puntaciones superiores en algunas escalas de la exploración vocacional y puntaciones inferiores en la indecisión vocacional. La magnitud del efecto pre-post (d de Cohen) fue medio alto en varias escalas de la exploración y en la indecisión en el grupo de intervención y prácticamente nulos en el grupo control. El programa es eficaz en el aumento de la conducta exploratoria y en la reducción de la indecisión. Se discuten implicaciones del estudio para la práctica e investigación clínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;17(3): 623-641, sept.-dic. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98355</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia del consejo vocacional en años de transición escolar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5204</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3675</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15232^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
