<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054995</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship between renal function and bone mineral density in postmenopausal women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">As osteoporosis and renal insufficiency are two prevalent pathologies in the aging        population we decided to evaluate retrospectively the renal function (estimated        by formula) in postmenopausal women who came to our Institute for bone mass        determination to establish the relationship between them. Thus, we studied 300        postmenopausal women with a mean age of 66.9 ± 6.8 years who had a bone        densitometry performed; we chose total femur bone mineral density (TFBMD) for        defining osteopenia and osteoporosis as this measurement included substantial        amounts of both trabecular and cortical bone; osteopenia/osteoporosis was diagnosed        using T score criteria recommended by the WHO. We also measured BMD        at the femoral neck. Renal function was estimated by the Cockcroft-Gault formula        using serum creatinine determination. We found osteoporosis in 61 patients        (20.3%). Of them, el 81.9% have renal insufficiency (estimated creatinine clearance-        ECrC &lt;= 60 ml/min), compared to 54% of 239 women who had normal        BMD/osteopenia (p &lt; 0.001). Six of 61 (9.8%) women with osteoporosis had severe        renal insufficiency (ECrC &lt;= 36 ml/min) versus 4/239 (1.6%) women with        normal BMD/osteopenia (p = 0.001). Women with osteoporosis were older, and        had a significantly lower weight and ECrC compared to patients without osteoporosis        (ECrC 52 ± 11 ml/min vs 59 ± 12 ml/min; p &lt; 0.0001). We found a significant        positive correlation between TFBMD and ECrC (r = 0.389) as well as with        weight (r = 0.422) and a negative correlation between age and ECrCE (r = -0.51)        and with TFBMD (r = -0.22). In the multiple regression analysis only weight continued        to correlate significantly with TFBMD (Beta = 0.344). When FNBMD was        considered as the dependent variable, we found a significantly negative correlation        with age (r = -0.30) and significantly positive correlations with height (r =        0.16), weight (r = 0.33) and ECcr (r = 0.39). In the multiple regression analysis        only age (Beta = -0.20) and weight (Beta = 0.20) continued having an independent        correlation FNBMD. We conclude that our data confirm that there exists a        substantial prevalence of renal insufficiency, even severe, among patients with densitometric        osteoporosis that should be kept in mind when one is considering the        prescription of medications as bisphosphonates that have renal clearance, so as        not to jeopardize the efficacy and the security of these drugs</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zanchetta, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lombas, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Negri, A. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Ya que la osteoporosis y la insuficiencia renal son dos patologías prevalentes en la        población que envejece quisimos evaluar en forma retrospectiva la función renal (estimada        por fórmula) en mujeres postmenopáusicas que concurrían a nuestro Instituto        para evaluación de su masa ósea y establecer que tipo de relación existía entre las        mismas. Así estudiamos 300 mujeres postmenopáusicas con una edad promedio de        66,9 ± 6,8 años a las que se les efectuó una densitometría ósea de cadera total        (DMOCT) y cuello femoral (DMOCF); se diagnosticó osteoporosis sobre la base de        los criterios de T score de la OMS. La función renal se estimó por fórmula de Cockcroft-        Gault sobre la base de la medición de la creatinina sérica. Encontramos osteoporosis        en cadera total en 61 pacientes (20,3%). De ellas, el 81,9% presentó insuficiencia        renal (clearance de creatinina estimado &#151;CcrE &lt;= 60 mil/min), contra el 54%        de 239 mujeres que presentaron DMO normal u osteopenia (p &lt; 0,001). Seis de 61        (9,8%) mujeres con osteoporosis presentaron insuficiencia renal severa (CcrE &lt;= 36        ml/min) contra 4/239 (1,6%) mujeres con DMOCT normal u osteopenia (p = 0,001).        Las mujeres con osteoporosis fueron más añosas, y tuvieron un peso y un CcrE significativamente        menor que el de las pacientes sin osteoporosis (CcrE 52 ± 11 ml/min        vs 59 ± 12 ml/min; p &lt; 0,0001). Encontramos una correlación positiva significativa        entre DMOCT y CcrE (r = 0,389) así como con el peso (r = 0,422) y una correlación        negativa entre la edad y CcrE (r = -0,51) y con la DMOCT (r = -0,22). En la        correlación múltiple solo el peso continuó correlacionando en forma significativa con        la DMOCT (Beta = 0,344). Cuando se consideró la DMOCF como la variable dependiente,        encontramos una correlación negativa significativa con la edad (r = -0,30)        y correlaciones significativas positivas con la talla (r = 0,16), con el peso (r = 0,33)        y con el CcrE (r = 0,39). En el análisis de correlación múltiple solo la edad (Beta =        -0,20) y el peso (Beta = 0,20) continuaron presentando una correlación significativa        independiente con la DMOCF. En conclusión, nuestros datos confirman que existe una        sustancial prevalencia de insuficienica renal, incluso severa, entre las pacientes que        presentan osteoporosis densitométrica que debería ser tenida en consideración al decidir        la prescripción de medicaciones que como los bisfosfonatos se eliminan por vía        real, para no comprender la eficacia o la seguridad de estas drogas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;26(supl.2): 206-211, 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054995</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre función renal y densidad mineral ósea en mujeres posmenopáusicas que realizan evaluación de masa ósea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24823^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24823^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24823^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24823^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24543^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3732^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
