<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92222</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Osteoarticular infections in children. Review of the casuistic between 1997 and 2007 in a general Hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bone and joint infections are more frequent in children tan in adults and cause orbidity and important long-term sequels. A retrospective analysis of all the diagnosed cases of bone and/or joint between 1997 and 2007 was performed. 16 children were diagnosed of bone and/or infection, 7 (43%) in the last 2 years. Septic arthritis (SA) was found in 9 patients (56%), one of them with bone extension, and acute osteomyelitis (AO) in 7 (44%). Children with SA had ages between 13 and 150 months (median 33). The most frequently affected joints were the knee and the ankle. We documented microbiologically 3 cases (33%), (s. aureus, s. pneumonia and P. aeruginosa). The days of antibiotic therapy ranged between 18 and 40 (mean 30), and those of intravenous therapy between 8 and 24 (mean 13). The age of children diagnosed of AO ranged between 16  and 168 months (median 92). The most frequent location was the tibia. In 2 occasions, surgical drainage was performed. The microbiologic diagnosis was made in 4 cases (57%). All of them were S. aureus. The day of antibiotic therapy ranged between 24 and 53 days (mean 35), our of which between 7 and 46 days (mean 14) was made intravenous. Bone and joint infections are still frequent. The incidence seems to increase in the last years. S. aureus in the main responsible agent, so the empirical antibiotic treatment should be directed against this microorganism (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Mondéjar, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mato Martínez, G. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Otheo de Tejada, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ros Pérez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Buenache Espartosa, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rizo Pascual, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las infecciones osteoarticulares son más frecuentes en niños que en adultos y causan morbilidad y secuelas a largo plazo importantes. Hemos realizado un estudio retrospectivo de los casos de infección ósteo-articular (IOA) (artritis séptica, osteomielitis aguda o ambas) diagnosticados en nuestro hospital entre 1997 y 2007. Se diagnosticaron 16 niños con IOA, 7 (43%) en los últimos 2 años. Feuron artritis séptica (AS) 9 (56%), uno con afectación ósea asociada, y 7 (44%) osteomielitis aguda (OA). Entre los niños con AS la edad osciló entre 13 y 150 meses (mediana, 33). Las articulaciones más afectadas fueron la rodilla y el tobillo. Se documentaron microbiológicamente 3 casos (33%), (S. aureus, S. pneumoniae y P. aeruginosa). Los días totales de antibioterapia oscilaron entre 18 y 40 (media, 30). Entre los niños con OA, la edad varió entre 16 y 168 meses (mediana, 92). La localización más frecuente fue la tibia. Se documentaron microbiológicamente 4 casos (57%). Todos fueron S. aureus. La duración de la antibioterapia varió entre 24 y 53 días (media, 35). Las infecciones osteoartículares siguen siendo frecuentes, con  una aumento progresivo en la incidencia. La principal etiología sigue siendo el S. aureus, por lo que la cobertura antibiótica empírica debe dirigirse contra este microorganismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;65(6): 537-540, nov.-dic. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92222</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infecciones osteoarticulares en niños. Revisión de la casuística entre 1997 y 2007 en un hospital General</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10199^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13683^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13596^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11988^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23949^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
