<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117885</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">According to the patient&#146;s autonomy law (Law 41/2002, of November 14), is the patient who has the right to be informed and the owner of the information it receives. It has developed a structured interview was administered randomly to the relatives of the patients in the care process Palliative Care Unit (PCU) of the Virgen de las Nieves Hospital of Granada, to assess the level of awareness about this law. In addition to assessing the level of knowledge that the patient has about their diagnosis / prognosis. The data obtained in this study contrast with the Act, where less than half of patients, according to their families, know their disease and a lower figure is reported fourth of its forecast. Also, most advanced patient relatives are against the law of patient autonomy. This requires that more professionals we strive to achieve a communicative process that brings the patient to his reality and support in their last phase of life (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martin Sánchez, Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Rodríguez, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín de Rosales Martínez, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Tapia, Fátima</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Cotelo, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galvez Mateos, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Según la Ley de Autonomía del paciente (Ley 41/2002, del 14 de Noviembre), es el paciente quien tiene derecho a ser informado y el titular de la información que reciba. Se ha elaborado una entrevista estructurada que se ha administrado de forma aleatoria a los familiares de los pacientes incluidos en el proceso asistencial Unidad de Cuidados Paliativos (UCP) del Hospital Virgen de las Nieves de Granada, para evaluar el grado de conocimiento sobre esta ley. Además de evaluar el nivel de conocimiento que el paciente dispone sobre su diagnóstico/pronóstico. Los datos obtenidos en este estudio contrastan con esta ley, donde menos de la mitad de los pacientes, según sus familiares, conocen su enfermedad y una cifra inferior la cuarta parte está informado su pronóstico. Asimismo, la mayoría de los familiares de pacientes avanzados se muestran en contra de la ley de Autonomía del Paciente. Este hecho obliga a que los profesionales nos esforcemos más en lograr un proceso comunicativo que acerque al paciente a su realidad y acompañamiento en su última fase de la vida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);10(2/3): 425-432, dic. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117885</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El manejo de la información en cuidados paliativos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d36354^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14746^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3243^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36355</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
