<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100622</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0620</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evolution of the need and coverage of opioid substitution treatments and needle exchange programmes in Spanish prisons, 1992-2009</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Spain is one of the few countries to have widely implemented opioid substitution treatments (OST) and needle exchange programmes (NEP) for drug users in prison. We analyze the evolution of the need, coverage and the timeliness of these interventions in Spain between 1992 and 2009. Methods: Data on the provision of interventions is taken from official publications. The need was calculated by applying multiplicative methods to secondary data from several sources. Coverage was estimated as the quotient between provision and need. Temporal opportunity was estimated by observing the gap between the acme of the incidence of consumption, of HIV infection or need and the curve of provision. Results: OST&#146;s began to be implemented in 1992. In 2002 they reached their maximum coverage (63.8%) and subsequently stabilized. NEP&#146;s started in 1997. Their maximum coverage reached 20.7% in 2006, but halved in a period of two years. The delay between the epidemic acme and the need and maximum intervention coverage was of 8-25 years. Conclusions: OST and NEP introduction in Spanish prisons was a great advance, but the delay in their implementation and the low level of NEP coverage could have limited their potential impact on the improvement of the health of incarcerated drug users. The decline of NEP coverage in recent years is a cause of major concern for the evolution of HIV and Hepatitis C epidemics(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fuente, L. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sordo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Mejías, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pulido, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bravo, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrio, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: España es de los pocos países que ha implementado generalizadamente tratamientos con sustitutivos opioides (TSO) y programas de intercambio de jeringas (PIJ) para los consumidores de drogas en prisión. Se analiza la evolución de la necesidad, cobertura y oportunidad temporal de estas intervenciones en España durante 1992-2009. Material y métodos: La provisión de intervenciones procede de publicaciones oficiales. La necesidad se estimó aplicando métodos multiplicativos a datos secundarios de varias fuentes. La cobertura se estimó mediante el cociente entre provisión y necesidad, y la diferencia entre dichas magnitudes. La oportunidad temporal se estimó observando el decalaje entre el acmé de incidencia de consumo, de infección por VIH o de necesidad y las curvas de provisión. Resultados: Los TSO comenzaron en 1992. Su máxima cobertura se alcanzó en 2002 (63.8%), y posteriormente se estabilizó. Los PIJ comenzaron en 1997. Su máxima cobertura se alcanzó en 2006 (20.7%), pero disminuyó a la mitad en dos años. El retraso entre el acmé de las epidemias o de la necesidad y la máxima cobertura de las intervenciones fue de 8-25 años. Conclusiones: La implementación de TSO y PIJ en las prisiones españolas supuso un enorme avance de salud pública, pero el retraso en su implementación y la baja cobertura de los PIJ pueden haber limitado mucho su impacto potencial en la mejora de la salud de los consumidores de drogas en prisión. El descenso de la cobertura de los PIJ a la mitad en los últimos años es especialmente preocupante para la evolución de las epidemias de VIH y hepatitis C(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. sanid. penit;14(2): 67-77, 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100622</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución de la necesidad y cobertura de los programas de tratamiento con sustitutivos opioides e intercambio de jeringas en las prisiones españolas, 1992-2009</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29941^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29941^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d715^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30351^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9487^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29941^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29941^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37608^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37608^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201200</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
