<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108145</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-6581</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validity and reliability of isokinetic strength ratios for estimating muscle imbalances</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Several isokinetic strength ratios (bilateral and unilateral) of the knee have been extensively used: (i) to identify possible anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) and hamstring strain injury risk factors; (ii) to monitor the effectiveness of rehabilitation programs; and (iii) to determine if an athlete is able to return safely to training and competition sessions after finishing a specific rehabilitation program. However, the precision of these isokinetic strength ratios to evaluate muscle imbalances has been accepted based on theoretical and empirical knowledge, and less based on the scientific evidence regarding their validity and reliability. The purposes of this literature review were: (1) to analyse and compare the validity and reliability of unilateral and bilateral isokinetic strength ratios of the knee for estimating and monitoring possible muscle imbalances; as well as (2) to report cut-off values to categorize the muscle function as normal or with significantly high injury risk. A total of 13 scientific studies fulfilled all the previously established inclusion and exclusion criteria. After analysing all the studies, it was possible to conclude that: (i) very few studies have analysed the validity and reliability of bilateral and unilateral (conventional and functional) isokinetic strength ratios of the knee to identify muscle imbalances; (ii) a bilateral imbalance lower than 10-15% and unilateral imbalances lower than 20-40% could be an appropriate cut-off score to reduce the likelihood of developing hamstring strains and ACL injuries; (iii) the isokinetic strength ratios of the knee appear to present moderate absolute reliability scores (standard error of the measurement &lt;15%); and (iv) more studies are needed to determine the validity and reliability of the isokinetic strength ratios of the knee in different sport modalities(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ayala, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ste Croix, Mark de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santonja, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sainz de Baranda, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Varios índices de fuerza isocinética (bilateral y unilateral) de la rodilla han sido extensivamente empleados para: a) identificar posibles factores de riesgo de lesión del ligamento cruzado anterior (LCA) de la rodilla y/o desgarros de la musculatura isquiosural; b) monitorizar la eficacia de programas de rehabilitación, y c) determinar si un deportista puede regresar al entrenamiento y/o a la competición de forma segura tras haber superado un proceso de rehabilitación. Sin embargo, la precisión de estos índices isocinéticos para evaluar desequilibrios musculares ha sido aceptada en base a conocimientos teóricos y empíricos, y en menor medida a la evidencia científica existente con respecto a su grado de validez y fiabilidad. Por ello, los objetivos de esta revisión bibliográfica fueron: 1) analizar y comparar la validez y la fiabilidad de los índices de fuerza bilateral y unilateral de la rodilla para la estimación y monitorización de posibles desequilibrios musculares, así como 2) aportar valores de referencia para categorizar la función muscular como normal o con riesgo significativo de lesión. Un total de 13 artículos científicos cumplieron los criterios de inclusión y exclusión inicialmente establecidos. Tras el análisis de los estudios se puede concluir que: a) son muy escasos los trabajos científicos que analizan la validez y la fiabilidad de los índices de fuerza bilateral y unilateral (convencional y funcional) para identificar desequilibrios musculares; b) un desequilibrio bilateral menor del 10-15% y un desequilibrio unilateral menor de 45-60% podrían ser un buen umbral de seguridad para reducir la probabilidad de sufrir una lesión de la musculatura isquiosural y del LCA; c) los índices de fuerza de la rodilla parecen presentar moderados valores de fiabilidad absoluta (error estándar de la medida &lt;15%), y d) son necesarios más estudios que aborden la determinación de la fiabilidad y la validez de los índices de fuerza en diferentes modalidades deportivas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apunts, Med. esport (Internet);47(176): 131-142, oct.-dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108145</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validez y fiabilidad de los ratios de fuerza isocinética para la estimación de desequilibrios musculares</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7679^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50351^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7893^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23143</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
