<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79133</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Management of postpartum hemorrhage with uterine balloon tamponade</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To demonstrate the usefulness of uterine balloon tamponade in postpartum hemorrhage. Material and methods: Five term pregnancies with postpartum hemorrhage were studied. The criterion for balloon placement was persistent bleeding despite pharmacological treatment. Results: Balloon placement was successful in 100% of the patients. The mean decrease in hemoglobin was 3.2g/dl (range: 1-5) and an average of three units of packed red blood cells per patient were required (range: 0-6). The mean volume of saline solution per balloon was 312ml (range: 160-420) and the mean duration of treatment was 22hours (range: 12-30). Conclusions: Uterine balloon tamponade is an efficient method to control postpartum hemorrhage. Training is not required for the application of this technique, which can obviate the need for surgery. Because of its ease of use and reasonable cost, this method can be used in any hospital setting (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Cantador, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodó Rodríguez, Carlota</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laín Llach, Josep Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jovell Fernández, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Demostrar la utilidad del taponamiento mecánico del útero con balón en el tratamiento de la hemorragia posparto. Material y métodos: 5 gestantes a término, tratadas por hemorragia posparto precoz. El criterio para colocar el balón fue el sangrado persistente a pesar del tratamiento farmacológico. Resultados: La colocación del balón fue exitosa en el 100% de los casos. El descenso medio de hemoglobina fue de 3,2g/dl (rango [r]=1-5) y se requirió una media de 3 concentrados de hematíes por paciente (r=0-6). El volumen medio de suero por balón fue de 312ml (r=160-420) y el tiempo medio de tratamiento fue de 22h (r=: 12-30). Conclusiones: El taponamiento uterino con balón constituye un método eficiente para el control de la hemorragia uterina posparto. Su aplicación no precisa entrenamiento y puede evitar la cirugía. Por su fácil manejo y coste asequible, es aplicable en cualquier medio hospitalario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);53(4): 163-166, abr. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79133</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de la hemorragia uterina posparto mediante taponamiento mecánico con balón intrauterino</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35394^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22596^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23183</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6641^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29962^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8941^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14993^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14993^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14993^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
