<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100928</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patient safety in management contracts</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Patient safety is becoming commonplace in management contracts. Since our experience in patient safety still falls short of other clinical areas, it is advisable to review some of its characteristics in order to improve its inclusion in these contracts. In this paper opinions and recommendations concerning the design and review of contractual clauses on safety are given, as well as reflections drawn from methodological papers and informal opinions of clinicians, who are most familiar with the nuances of safe and unsafe practices. After reviewing some features of these contracts, criteria for prioritizing and including safety objectives and activities in them, and key points for their evaluation are described. The need to replace isolated activities by systemic and multifaceted ones is emphasized. Errors, limitations and improvement opportunities observed when contracts are linked to indicators, information and adverse event reporting systems are analysed. Finally, the influence of the rules of the game, and clinicians behaviour are emphasised(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Campillo-Artero, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La seguridad del paciente está adquiriendo carta de naturaleza en los contratos de gestión de los servicios de salud. Como la experiencia acumulada en seguridad es menor que en otras áreas asistenciales, conviene revisar algunas de sus vertientes para mejorar su inclusión en los contratos. En este artículo se ofrecen opiniones y recomendaciones sobre diseño y revisión del apartado de seguridad de los contratos de gestión, y reflexiones extraídas de trabajos metodológicos publicados y de opiniones recabadas informalmente de clínicos, quienes mejor conocen los entresijos de las prácticas seguras e inseguras. Tras repasar ciertas particularidades de estos contratos, se describen criterios para priorizar en ellos objetivos y acciones en seguridad, claves de su evaluación y se subraya la necesidad de sustituir intervenciones aisladas por actuaciones sistémicas y multifacéticas. Por último, se analizan errores, limitaciones y oportunidades de mejora que se observan al vincular los contratos con indicadores, sistemas de información y de notificación de eventos adversos, y se destaca la influencia que ejercen en su cumplimiento las reglas de juego y factores conductuales de los profesionales(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;27(4): 233-239, jul.-ago. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100928</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La seguridad del paciente en los contratos de gestión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31061^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3303^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37687^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31061^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3303^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31061^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17099^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50210</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
