<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-14642</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Construction and psychometric analysis of a questionnaire for the evaluation of public transportation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this work has been the construction and psychometric analysis of a questionnaire for the evaluation of the urban bus system from the user perspective. Two studies have been carried out. In the first study, an initial version of the questionnaire with 25 items was administered. Through psychometric analysis the number of items was reduced to 16. A representative sample of the urban Galician population participate in the second study. It has been found that those 16 items could be grouped into 6 statistical factors, which comprise the following urban bus system relevant aspects: bus stops, information to users, timetable fulfilment, bus-drivers&#146; professionality, service sufficiency, buses condition, special populations conditioning, and service satisfaction. Scale internal consistency and validity values were .8410 and .68, respectively (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Seoane Pesqueira, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arce Fernández, Constantino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez González, M. Soledad</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo central del presente trabajo consistió en la construcción y análisis psicométrico de un cuestionario para la evaluación del sistema de autobuses urbanos por medio de sus usuarios. Se realizaron dos estudios. En el primero, se partió de un cuestionario inicial compuesto por 25 ítems. El análisis psicométrico permitió reducir el número de ítems a tan solo 16. En el segundo estudio, que fue realizado con una muestra representativa de la población urbana gallega, se encontró que los 16 ítems se agrupaban en 6 factores estadísticos en los que aparecen recogidos los siguientes aspectos relevantes del sistema de autobuses urbanos: paradas de autobús, información al usuario, cumplimiento de horarios, profesionalidad de los conductores, suficiencia del servicio, estado de los autobuses, acondicionamiento para poblaciones especiales y satisfacción con el servicio. La consistencia interna fue de .8410 y la validez de .68. (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);12(3): 399-405, ago. 2000. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-14642</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Construcción y análisis psicométrico de un cuestionario de evaluación de los medios de transporte público</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14578</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3277^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
