<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166780</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">News in drug-eluting stents. update and future developments</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">With the aim of overcoming the limitations of firstgeneration drug-eluting stents, a new generation of stents has been developed to improve safety and biocompatibility by optimizing their three main components: the stent platform, coating and drug. In addition, other lines of research have focused on developing new devices either with biodegradable polymers or without polymers, including so-called bio-active stents, in which the stent surface is modified to optimize arterial endothelialization. Finally, prototypes of fully biodegradable stents are also being developed. The effort put into basic research, studies of anatomy and pathology, and engineering design in recent years in this field has been impressive. As a result, the amount of data that has been produced in a short time has also been remarkable. This review provides an analysis of developments in and studies on drugeluting stents that have taken place in the last 3 years. Improvements in second-generation stents are discussed and the nature of the so-called third or next generation of drug-eluting stents is described (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vaquerizo Montilla, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miranda Guardiola, Faustino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serra Peñaranda, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Con el objetivo de mejorar las limitaciones de la primera generación de stents farmacoactivos, las nuevas generaciones se han desarrollado para mejorar su seguridad y su biocompatibilidad optimizando sus tres principales componentes: la plataforma, el polímero y el fármaco. Además de estas, otras líneas de investigación se centran en desarrollar nuevos dispositivos con polímeros biodegradables, sin polímero, entre los que se incluyen los llamados stents bioactivos, que introducen mejoras en la superficie del stent para optimizar la reendotelización arterial, y finalmente prototipos completamente biodegradables. Es impresionante el esfuerzo en investigación básica, estudios de anatomía patológica e ingeniería de diseño que se ha realizado en los últimos años en este campo. Por lo tanto, la información que ha surgido en poco tiempo también es increíble. En esta revisión se hace un análisis de las novedades y los estudios aparecidos en los últimos 3 años en relación con los stents farmacoactivos. Se analizan las mejoras en la segunda generación y se describe la llamada tercera o siguiente generación de stents farmacoactivos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);10(supl.C): 2c-11c, 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166780</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Novedades en stents farmacoactivos. Actualización y futuros desarrollos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11545^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52881^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33879^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
