<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056570</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Autoimmune hepatitis in pediatric patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: autoimmune hepatitis (AIH) is an inflammatory        disease of unknown origin that is responsible for progressive liver        necrosis and ultimately cirrhosis.        Objective: our aim was to evaluate the characteristics of autoimmune        hepatitis presenting in the pediatric age.        Material and methods: we conducted a retrospective study        of all patients diagnosed with AIH in our hospital department during        the last 10 years. Variables analyzed included age, sex, clinical        presentation, hepatic function, immunoglobulins, autoimmunity        markers, histology, treatment, need for transplant, and clinical        evolution. According to the positive level of auto-antibodies, AIH        patients were classified as type I AIH (ANA and/or smooth-muscle        antibodis) and type II (anti-LKM-1).        Results: seven patients were diagnosed in this period &#150;5 girls        (71.5%) and 2 boys (28.5%). Five patients presented with type-I        serological markers, and two with type-II markers. Age range at        diagnosis was from 21 months to 12 years. In the type-I group, 3        patients presented with acute hepatitis while 2 other patients were        diagnosed from laboratory findings while asymptomatic. Elevated        aminotransferase (10 times the normal level) was observed in        71.5%, and 85% had elevated immunoglobulins. Treatment with        azathioprine and prednisone was started after diagnosis with an        average time to remission of 14 months. Two patients relapsed        following steroid withdrawal.        Conclusion: AIH can have different forms of clinical presentation,        and is sometimes indistinguishable from viral hepatitis. AIH        must be ruled out in patients presenting with concomitant elevation        of aminotransferases and immunoglobulins. The commonly        accepted treatment is a combination of azathioprine and corticosteroids.        A high percentage of patients experience a relapse of disease        after steroids are withdrawn. Therefore, some patients will        need to stay on combined therapy with minimal doses of steroids</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Romero, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín de Carpi, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinillos Pisón, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varea Calderón, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernal Cuartas, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la hepatitis autoinmune es una enfermedad inflamatoria        de origen desconocido responsable de una destrucción        progresiva del hígado y evolución hacia la cirrosis.        Objetivo: el objetivo es evaluar las características de las hepatitis        autoinmunes en la población infantil.        Material y métodos: estudio retrospectivo de pacientes diagnosticados        en nuestro servicio en los últimos 10 años. Las variables        analizadas son: edad, sexo, forma de presentación, función        hepática, inmunoglobulinas, autoinmunidad, histología, tratamiento,        necesidad de trasplante y evolución clínica. Según la positividad        de los auto-anticuerpos se clasifican en tipo I (ANA y/o        ASMA) y tipo II (LKM-1).        Resultados: se diagnostica a siete pacientes, 5 mujeres        (71,5%) y 2 varones (28,5%); tipo I 5 y tipo II dos pacientes. La        edad al diagnóstico es 21 meses a 12 años. En el tipo I la presentación        clínica es como hepatitis aguda en 3 casos y 2 pacientes        con insuficiencia hepática progresiva. Las tipo II se diagnostican        tras un hallazgo analítico siendo asintomáticas. La elevación de        transaminasas (x10 su valor) se observa en el 71,5% e hipergammaglobulinemia        en el 85%. El tratamiento instaurado es azatioprina        y corticosteroides con un tiempo medio de remisión de 14 meses.        Dos pacientes recaen al retirar corticosteroides.        Conclusión: las formas de presentación son variadas y puede        ser indistinguible a una hepatitis viral. Se debe sospechar ante una        elevación de las aminotransferasas y la presencia de hipergammaglobulinemia.        Con buenos resultados el tratamiento recomendado        sería azatioprina y corticosteroides. Existen altos porcentajes de        recaídas al retirar la corticoterapia por lo que algunos pacientes        precisarían de dosis mínimas para mantener la remisión</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;99(5): 255-258, mayo 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056570</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hepatitis autoinmune en la edad pediátrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1394^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33349^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7122^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33349^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d650^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31670</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
