<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141512</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Off-label prescription of anti-asthmatic agents in Primary Care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: off-label prescribing is when performed outside of the official information of the product. Overall figures of off-label prescribing in primary care in different countries are 3-67%. The aim of the study was to determine the intensity of this type of prescription in anti-asthmatic agents in a recent period of time, in Castilla y León. Methods: the requirements for the therapeutic subgroup R03 (anti-asthmatic agents) prescribed in children less than 14 years of age in the Castilla-León health service from 2005 to 2010 were analyzed. Information on off-label prescribing is shown in number of anti-asthmatic prescriptions consumed at doses and/or at ages not recommended in its technical specifications. Results: a total of 394 876 prescriptions for anti-asthmatic agents were performed to an exposed population of 1 580 229 person-years. Children under four years received the highest levels of anti-asthmatic agents. The maximum prescription of bronchodilators occurred in children under 2 years, and of montelukast and single inhaled corticosteroids at one year of age. 46% of prescriptions of systemic salbutamol and 15.9% of maintenance therapy prescriptions were made in an off-label manner. Conclusions: the study shows an important and very early use of anti-asthmatic agents at ages where it is difficult to make a diagnosis of asthma and also a remarkable consumption of controller therapy at not authorized dose and/or ages. Off-label prescription do not presuppose inappropriate prescription but it should have a real benefit to the patient and be supported by scientific guarantees to justify its use (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cano Garcinuño, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez García, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Quirós, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casares Alonso, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: se denomina prescripción off-label a la realizada fuera de las condiciones autorizadas en la ficha técnica de un medicamento. En Atención Primaria se publican cifras globales de prescripción off-label en diferentes países del 3-67%. El objetivo del estudio ha sido conocer la intensidad de este tipo de prescripción en el caso de los antiasmáticos en un periodo reciente, en Castilla-León (España). Métodos: se analizaron las prescripciones correspondientes al subgrupo terapéutico R03 (medicamentos para enfermedades obstructivas respiratorias) realizadas a menores de 14 años entre 2005-2010 en el sistema público de salud autonómico. La información sobre el uso off-label se presenta en número de prescripciones consumidas de antiasmáticos a dosis y/o edades no recomendadas en su ficha técnica. Resultados: se realizaron 394876 prescripciones de antiasmáticos a una población expuesta de 1 580229 personas/año. Los menores de cuatro años fueron los que más antiasmáticos recibieron. La máxima prescripción de broncodilatadores ocurrió en menores de dos años, la de montelukast y corticoides inhalados monofármaco al año de edad. El 46% de las prescripciones de salbutamol sistémico y el 15,9% de las de la terapia de mantenimiento se prescribieron off-label. Conclusiones: el estudio muestra un uso importante de antiasmáticos a edades muy tempranas en las que es difícil hacer el diagnóstico de asma y un consumo notable de fármacos controladores a dosis y/o edades no autorizadas. La prescripción off-label no presupone una prescripción inadecuada, pero debería tener un beneficio real para el paciente y estar apoyada por avales científicos que justifiquen su uso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;17(67): 237-246, jul.-sept. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141512</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prescripción off-label de antiasmáticos en Atención Primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53206^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53206^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53206^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11742^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32858^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2021^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d423^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
