<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103889</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-1285</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Histological changes in samples of gingival overgrowth biopsies obtained through conventional scalpel and electro surgical scalpel</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Literature Reports are scarce regarding histological changes observed on gingival tissues, but they are scarcer when gingival overgrowth from human tissues are considered. When histological slides are compared, the question arises if there are histological differences between samples obtained with electrosurgical versus conventional scalpel. Methods. A comparative study was performed in 21 patients, 90 samples. Cross control strategy was used to allocate the surgical site for each treatment, facilitating to evaluate both treatments in the same subject (electrosurgical versus conventional scalpel) in a random manner for both arches. Data was entered in an Excel data base and analyzed with STATA 9.1 statistical software. Fischer´s exact test, p=0.05 significance level was used. Results. Collagen burning and coagulation were observed in 72.7% of the cases, being higher for connective tissue samples obtained with electrosurgical scalpel, 79.5% regarding burning, being higher with electrosurgical scalpel for epithelial tissue. Connective tissue showed inflammation in 95.6% of the cases for conventional scalpel, mediated by lymphocytes and plasmatic cells; neutrophils were seen in 17.8% of the sample and inflammation was seen in 100% of the samples for electrosurgical and conventional scalpels, which evidenced 97.8% lymphocytes and plasmatic cells and 37.8% neutrophils. Conclusions. Different histological phenomena were observed in gingival biopsies obtained with electrosurgical versus conventional scalpel; this facilitates understanding gingival overgrowth associated with orthodontic treatment. Some damage was observed in several biopsy samples which in some cases rendered the samples unusable for histological evaluation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fang Mercado, LC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrios García, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Caballero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera Herrera, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: Es poco lo que se dice en la literatura sobre cambios histológicos observados en la encía y aún menos comparándolo en caso de agrandamiento gingival obtenido de tejidos humanos. Al realizar estos recortes surge la pregunta si existe alguna diferencia histológica al comparar las muestras obtenidas con electrobisturí y bisturí convencional. Métodos: Se implementó un estudio descriptivo comparativo, sobre 21 pacientes obteniendo 90 muestras. La asignación de los sitios quirúrgicos para cada uno de los tratamientos se hizo con la estrategia de control cruzado, evaluando ambos tratamientos en el mismo sujeto (electrobisturí y bisturí convencional), en forma aleatoria en ambas hemiarcadas. Los datos se incluyeron en una base de datos en Excel, se analizaron en un software estadístico STATA 9.1. Se utilizó el test exacto de Fischer, con significancia p=0,05. Resultados: Se observó carbonización y coagulación del colágeno en el 72,7% siendo superior en las muestras obtenidas con electrobisturí en el tejido conectivo, el 79,5% de diferencia de carbonización siendo superior con el electrobisturí en el tejido epitelial. Con  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av Odontoestomatol;28(3): 141-150, mayo-jun. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103889</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambios histológicos en muestras de agrandamientos gingivales obtenidas a través de biopsias con electrobisturí y bisturí convencional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4671^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6029^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6020^s22071</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32943^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
