<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036684</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of the incorporation of a general practitioner on emergency department effectiveness</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: To know the effect that the presence of a general practitioner (GP) has on emergency department's effectiveness, efficiency and health care. Patients and method: Prospective interventional study carried out in the emergency medicine unit fast track area (FTA), which is ideally opened from 8 am to 12 am, and staffed by 2 residents. Intervention: 8 resident hours (from 4 pm to 12 am) were substituted by 8 GP hours. The study period was August 2002 (GP presence), and the control period, October 2002. From each period, 10 days and 100 patients were randomly selected. From each day, FTA census (P), percentage of revisits and patients leaving without being seen, elapsed time to FTA actual closing (OT), percentage of patients moved to the observation area, and percentage of admissions were recorded. From each patient, epidemiological and clinical characteristics, waiting time to be seen (WT), number of tests performed, elapsed time to treatment (TT), and length of stay (LOS) were collected along with the number of patients finally discharged without hospital specialist consultation and those discharged with no test ordered. To assess perceived care quality, a telephone survey was performed. Three effectiveness indexes were defined and determined: P/WT (E1), P/OT (E2), and perceived care quality/perceived WT (E3). Finally, fixed and variables costs (C) from both periods were calculated, and cost-effectiveness analysis for each effectiveness index and period performed. Results: Periods showed no differences regarding daily census and patient characteristics. In the study period (GP presence), all time variables significantly improved: 20% reduction in WT, 25% in TT, 36% in LOS, and 17.5% in OT. A decrease in the number of tests ordered (41% less), in the percentage of patients moved to the observation area (78% less), and in the revisit rate (75% less) was also noted. Finally, E1 improved in 77% and E2 in 51%. Cost-effectiveness analysis clearly supported the study period, showing a decrease in C/E1 (55% less), in C/E2 (33% less), and in C/E3 (6% less). From the telephone survey, no differences between periods were detected except a perceived WT in the study period lower than that in the control period. Conclusions: The presence of a GP in a FTA leads to an improvement in the effectiveness and quality of care received by attended patients. In addition of these important features, this presence is also efficient. Therefore, it is an intervention that could be taken into account by administrators to better manage emergency departments</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miró, Òscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coll-Vinent, Blanca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Red, Gloria de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Senar, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, Sònia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Asenjo, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bragulat, Ernest</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salmerón, Juan Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivos: Conocer el efecto que tiene la incorporación de un médico especialista en medicina familiar y comunitaria (MFC) en la efectividad, la eficiencia y la calidad de un servicio de urgencias hospitalario (SUH). Pacientes y método: Estudio prospectivo e intervencionista realizado en el área de visita rápida (AVR) que idealmente está abierta de las 8.00 a las 24.00 h y asistida por dos residentes. La intervención consistió en sustituir 8 h de guardia de un residente (16.00 a 24.00) por 8 h de guardia de un especialista de MFC. El período de estudio fue agosto de 2002 (presencia de un especialista de MFC) y el período control, octubre de 2002. De forma aleatoria se evaluaron 10 días y 100 pacientes de cada período. Se analizaron para cada día las siguientes variables: número de visitas (P), revisitas en 72 h y fugados, tiempo de apertura (TA) real del AVR y porcentaje de observaciones e ingresos. Se analizaron para cada paciente diversos aspectos: características clínicas y epidemiológicas, tiempo de espera para ser visitado (TE), número de exploraciones complementarias realizadas, tiempo de demora en la administración del tratamiento (TT), tiempo total desde el inicio de la visita hasta la salida (TO) y número de pacientes dados de alta sin necesidad de exploraciones complementarias o consulta a otros especialistas de guardia del hospital. Se realizó un análisis de la calidad percibida mediante encuesta telefónica. Se definieron y calcularon 3 índices de efectividad: P/TE (E1), P/TA (E2) y valoración global de la visita/valoración del TE (E3). Finalmente, se calcularon los costes (C) fijos y variables de ambos períodos, y se realizó un análisis coste-efectividad (C/E). Resultados: El número de visitas y las características clínicas y epidemiológicas de los pacientes fueron similares en ambos períodos. Durante el período de estudio (presencia de MFC) todas las variables mejoraron significativamente: reducción del 20% en el TE, el 25% en el TT, el 36% en el TO y el 17,5% en el TA. Se registró una reducción del 41% en el número de exploraciones complementarias, del 78% en el porcentaje de observaciones y del 75% en el porcentaje de revisitas. Finalmente, el E1 y el E2 mejoraron un 77 y un 51%. El análisis coste-efectividad mostró una disminución, durante el período de estudio, para el C/E1 del 55%, para el C/E2 del 33% y para el C/E3 del 6%. La encuesta telefónica no reveló diferencias en ambos períodos pero el TE durante el período de estudio fue percibido con más frecuencia como adecuado. Conclusiones: La presencia de un médico de MFC en el AVR supuso una mejoría de la efectividad y de la calidad percibida por los pacientes. Además, esta presencia fue eficiente. Por ello, es una intervención que debería ser considerada por la administración para una mejor utilización de los SUH</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);125(4): 132-137, jun. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036684</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad de la incorporación de un médico especialista en medicina familiar y comunitaria en un servicio de urgencias hospitalario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11253^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
