<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-64168</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Antiepileptics, in particular carbamazepine and valproate, have been used in the treatment of some psychiatric disorders characterised by affective and behavioural disturbances practically from their introduction into the clinics. However, in the last decade the appearance of a generation of safer and more easy-to-use anticonvulsants has prompted the widespread use of these agents by psychiatrists. New anticonvulsants are better tolerated and safer when compared with the classic ones and they have more convenient pharmacokinetics and less drug-drug interactions. While anticonvulsants have shown to be effective in a number of psychiatric disorders (notably in the treatment of affective bipolar disorder) as yet, their efficacy in many other conditions has not been well established by means of randomized clinical trials. In fact, the use of some anticonvulsants in many psychiatric entities is largely based on open or case series studies. Since the mechanisms of action of the different anticonvulsants are diverse, their efficacy in different psychiatric disorders is not a class effect. Therefore, further studies are needed to clearly define which agents and to which disorders they are more useful (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arranz Estévez, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Doménech Bisén, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los antiepilépticos, especialmente la carbamazepina y el valproato, se han utilizado en el tratamiento de algunos trastornos psiquiátricos caracterizados por alteraciones afectivas y conductuales prácticamente desde su introducción en la clínica. Sin embargo, en la última década la aparición de una generación de anticonvulsivantes más seguros y manejables ha promovido el uso generalizado de estos agentes por parte de los psiquiatras. Los nuevos anticonvulsivantes son mejor tolerados y más seguros en comparación con los antiepilépticos clásicos y presentan una fármaco cinéticamás conveniente y menos interacciones farmacológicas. Aunque los anticonvulsivantes han demostrado ser eficaces en algunos trastornos psiquiátricos, especialmente en el tratamiento del trastorno afectivo bipolar, su eficacia en muchos otros trastornos no está todavía suficientemente contrastada mediante ensayos clínicos aleatorizados. De hecho, el uso de algunos anticonvulsivantes en muchas entidades psiquiátricas se basa en gran medida en estudios abiertos o en series de casos. Puesto que los mecanismos de acción de los diferentes anticonvulsivantes son diversos, su eficacia en diferentes trastornos psiquiátricos no es un efecto de clase. Por consiguiente hacen falta más estudios para definir con mayor nitidez qué agentes son eficaces y en qué trastornos presenta mayor utilidad cada uno de ellos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;36(supl.3): 63-74, mar. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-64168</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29291^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4418^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4418^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2256^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d346^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2256^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
