<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75993</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Headache, does it cause a health care overload in Primary Health Care? Urban area vs rural area medical visit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. Headache causes an overload and a problemto out-patient neurology. There are few studies that quantify the overload that the headache causes in a PrimaryHealth Care out-patient clinic visit. The aim of thepresent study is to identify and quantify the real loadthat this disease supposes in two Primary Health Careconsultations, one located in a rural area and another inan urban area.Material and methods. A 6 month long observationaland descritive study. The total number of patients seen,the number of patients seen for headache and theirdiagnostic classification were recorded.Results. A total of 6,014 visits were counted. Only46 patients consulted due to headache (0,76%). Tensionalheadache was the most frequently diagnosed headache(43.48%) followed by migraine (23.91%).Conclusions. Our study verifies that published byother authors and determines that, on the contrary tothat which occcurs in the neurology out-patient clinic,headache does not cause a daily work overload for thegeneral practitioner. The scarce number of consultationsfor headache, with the diagnosis and management involvedin this disease, makes it necessary to consider a multidisciplinaryhealth care problem such as headache differentlyaccording to the health care level involved (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Genovés, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medrano, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esquembre, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El dolor de cabeza supone una sobrecargay unun problema asistencial en cualquier consulta ambulatoriade neurología. Existen pocos estudios que cuantifiquen lasobrecarga que supone el dolor de cabeza en una consultade atención primaria. El objetivo del presente estudio esidentificar y cuantificar realmente la carga que esta patologíasupone en dos consultas de atención primaria, una localizadaen un ámbito rural y otra en un ámbito urbano.Material y métodos. Estudio observacional y descriptivode 6 meses de duración. Se registra el total de pacientesatendidos, el número de pacientes asistidos por dolor de cabezay su clasificación diagnóstica.Resultados. Se contabilizó un total de 6.014 consultas.Sólo 46 pacientes consultan por cefalea (0,76%). La cefaleatensional es el dolor de cabeza diagnosticado con más frecuencia(el 43,48%), seguido de la migraña (el 23,91%).Conclusiones. Nuestro estudio certifica lo publicadopor otros autores y determina que, contrariamente a lo quesucede en la neurología ambulatoria, la cefalea no suponeuna carga en el trabajo diario de un médico de familia. Elescaso número de consultas por cefalea, con los problemasde diagnóstico y manejo que rodea a esta patología, originanque un problema de atención multidisciplinar como lacefalea se afronte de diferente manera según el nivel asistencialdonde uno se encuentre (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;23(5): 269-274, jun. 2008. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75993</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cefalea, ¿una sobrecarga asistencial en atención primaria? Consulta urbana frente a consulta rural</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32616^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6412^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9068^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25658</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
