<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044431</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Contrast sensitivity to intraocular lens TECNIS Z-9000</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To evaluate the increase in contrast sensitivity to intraocular lens TECNIS Z-9000 (Pfizer) compared with other intraocular lenses. Method: We implanted a TECNIS Z-9000 lens in 18 patients who had another type of intraocular lens implanted in their other eye. We then tested contrast sensitivity under both mesopic and photopic conditions using the VCTS (Vision Contrast Test System) provided by Vistech Consultants Inc. Results: There was an improved contrast sensitivity at low and medium frequencies, following TECNIS-Z 9000 lens implantation, however this improvement did not reach statistical significance. There were significant differences at high frequencies, which are directly related to the quality of visual function. Conclusions: TECNIS Z-9000 lens implantation (with a modified anterior surface) achieves a significant improvement in contrast sensitivity, meaning in practice an increase in the quality of visual function</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palacios-Pozo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Taboada-Esteve, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lanzagorta-Aresti, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hurtado, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Menezo, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar el incremento en la sensibilidad al contraste de las lentes TECNIS Z-9000 (Pfizer) respecto a otras lentes.Método: Se implantó la lente TECNIS Z-9000 en 18 pacientes que ya habían sido intervenidos de un ojo con otro tipo de lente intraocular. Se les midió la sensibilidad al contraste en condiciones fotópicas y mesópicas mediante el test VCTS (Vision Contrast Test System) de Vistech Consultants Inc.Resultados: Aunque la tendencia es hacia una mejoría de la sensibilidad al contraste en las frecuencias bajas y media, no existen diferencias significativas. Sí que demuestran de forma significativa la mayor sensibilidad al contraste en las frecuencias altas, que son las que están directamente relacionadas con la calidad de la función visual.Conclusiones: Las lentes TECNIS, mediante una modificación de su cara anterior, consiguen de manera significativa una mejoría de la sensibilidad al contraste, que se traduce en un incremento de la calidad de la función visual</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;80(11): 541-657, nov. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044431</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sensibilidad al contraste en las lentes TECNIS Z-9000</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8088</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23596^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
