<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148726</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Update on Hidradenitis Suppurative (Part II): Treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Although hidradenitis suppurativa is a common and serious skin condition, its treatment is not well established. It is now accepted that the moderate and severe forms of the disease are associated with marked systemic inflammation. The goal of treatment in hidradenitis suppurative is therefore to achieve systemic control of inflammation. In some cases, surgery may also be necessary to reduce the severity of the manifestations of cutaneous inflammation. Recent advances in our understanding of hidradenitis suppurativa have been accompanied by the emergence of novel approaches to its treatment, including the use of certain biologic drugs. Several clinical trials have been undertaken to test the effects of biologics (mainly adalimumab) in this setting. In this review, we analyze the different treatments available for hidradenitis suppurativa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martorell, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villarrasa, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salgado, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereyra-Rodríguez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Gallo, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A pesar de la importancia y de la gravedad de la hidradenitis supurativa, el tratamiento de esta enfermedad no se encuentra bien definido. Hoy en día, la hidradenitis es considerada una enfermedad cutánea que principalmente en las formas moderadas y severas se asocia a un marcado componente inflamatorio sistémico. Por lo tanto, el tratamiento de esta enfermedad irá enfocado hacia un manejo sistémico del control de la inflamación, que ocasionalmente irá acompañado de la intervención quirúrgica para reducir la carga de inflamación localizada en la piel. Los recientes avances en el conocimiento de la enfermedad se han acompañado de novedades terapéuticas, especialmente representadas por el desarrollo de ensayos clínicos de determinadas terapias biológicas, principalmente adalimumab, orientados al tratamiento específico de esta enfermedad. En la presente revisión se pretende analizar las diferentes alternativas terapéuticas existentes en el manejo de la hidradenitis supurativa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;106(9): 716-724, nov. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148726</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actualización en hidradenitis supurativa (II): aspectos terapéuticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5538^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1716^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12705^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30874^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30699^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30699^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5538^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23201^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30699^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30164^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28169^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3641^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
