<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049131</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">CA-P control in haemodialysis and k/doqi guidelines</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Backgroung: The publication in 2003 of the K/DOQI Clinical Practice Guidelinesfor Bone Metabolism and Disease in Chronic Kidney Disease recommendedtargets levels for serum iPTH, Ca, P, and CaxP product. However, many patientsdo not achieved these target ranges. It is necessary to known the percentage ofpatients out of range in order to prevent the development of bone disease and toreduce mortality and morbidity.Objectives: To know the degree of control of Ca-P metabolism in haemodialysispatients in our haemodilalysis facilities and the achievement of target levels recommendedby K/DOQI Guidelines.Patients and methods: We have retrospectively investigated in 190 prevalenthaemodialysis patients (males 58,2%, ratio M/F 1,4, mean age 70 years, range 17-87 years, at least 3 months in haemodialysis) the serum levels of Ca, albumin-correctedserum Ca, P, CaxP product and iPTH in all analitycal determinations performedin 2004. In each patient we have obtained the average (and median) ofthese serum markers. Cut-off levels were carried out following the recommendationsof the K/DOQI Guidelines.Results: The average of serum Ca and albumin-corrected serum Ca is normal(means ± SD = 8,9 ± 0,6 mg/dL and 9,2 ± 0,7 mg/dL, respectively); however,53,7% has normal values, 9,1% hypocalcemia and 37,1% hypercalcemia. Theaverage of serum P is also normal (mean ± SD = 5,0 ± 1,3 mg/dL); however, only57,2% has normal values, and 11,7% has hypophosphoremia and the remaining31,1% hyperphosphoremia. The CaxP product is normal (mean ± SD = 46,3 ±13,3 mg2/mL2) , 4,9% with low values and 23,4% with high values. The medianof serum iPTH is 253 pg/mL, but only 31,1% of them have normal values, 25,1%low range values and 43,7% has hyperparathyroidism; 9,3% with iPTH higherthan 800 pg/mL. The percentage of patients with hyperphosphoremia is higher inthe group with iPTH higher than 300 pg/mL (23,3% vs 40%, chi2, p= 0,006). Inpatients with PTHi in normal range, 3,6% have low CaxP product and the remaining17,8% high CaxP product. Overall, only 25% of patients falls within recommendedranges for all indicators of mineral metabolism and 17% has all serummarkers outside these recommendations.Conclusions: The degree of control of mineral metabolism in haemodyalisis patientsif clearly insufficient and a large percentage of them do not achieved therecommended serum targets recommended by K/DOQI Guidelines. This groupsof patients are exposed to a increased risk for oseous and cardiovascular morbimortality.The analysis of adequacy must be performed with percentage of patientsout of range in order to apply new therapeutical strategies</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Echarri, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vozmediano, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcaide, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez de la Nieta, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Anaya, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carreño, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivera, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Desde la publicación de las Guías K/DOQI en 2003 sobre metabolismomineral en la enfermedad renal crónica se ha observado que algunospacientes no alcanzan en la práctica clínica un adecuado control y es necesarioconocer el porcentaje de ellos que están fuera de rango normal, para evitar complicacionesmetabólicas y cardiovasculares.Objetivos: Conocer el grado de control del metabolismo Ca-P en pacientes tratadoscon hemodiálisis en nuestra provincia, estudiando los valores de tendenciacentral y el porcentaje de casos que se encuentran dentro y fuera de rango.Pacientes y métodos: Estudio retrospectivo realizado en 190 pacientes (58,2%varones, V/H 1,4, mediana de edad 70 años, rango de edad 17-87 años) incluidosen hemodiálisis durante al menos 3 meses, durante todo el año 2004. Decada paciente se obtiene la media (y mediana) de los valores de Ca, Ca corregidocon albúmina, P, producto CaxP y PTHi. Los niveles de corte se establecensegún las recomendaciones de las Guías K/DOQI de 2003.Resultados: Las medias de Ca total y corregido con albúmina están en rangonormal (medias ± DE = 8,9 ± 0,6 mg/dL y 9,2 ± 0,7 mg/dL, respectivamente);no obstante el 53,7% de ellos tienen valores de normocalcemia, mientras que el9,1% tiene hipocalcemia y el 37,1% hipercalcemia. La media de P también seencuentra en rango normal (media ± DE = 5,0 ± 1,3 mg/dL); no obstante sóloel 57,1% de ellos tienen valores en rango normal, mientras que el 11,7% tienehipofosforemia y el 31,1% hiperfosforemia. El producto CaxP se encuentra enrango normal (media ± DE = 46,3 ± 13,3 mg2/mL2, pero un 4,9% tiene valoresdisminuidos y un 23,4% valores elevados. La mediana de PTHi es 253 pg/mL,pero sólo el 31,1% se encuentra en el rango normal mientras que el 25,1% tienevalores disminuidos y un 43,7% en rango de hiperparatiroidismo, entre ellos un9,3% con niveles por encima de 800 pg/mL. El porcentaje de casos con hiperfosforemiaes superior en el grupo de pacientes con niveles de PTHi superiores a300 pg/mL (23,3% vs 40%, chi2, p = 0,006). Entre los pacientes con valores dePTHi en rango normal, un 78,6% tienen un producto CaxP normal, un 3,6% disminuidoy el 17,8% restante elevado. Al analizar los resultados globales, sólo lacuarta parte de los pacientes presenta un perfil completo en rango normal y un17% tiene todos los parámetros fuera de rango. Conclusiones: El control del metabolismo Ca-P es insuficiente y muchos pacientesno se encuentran en los rangos recomendados por las Guías K/DOQI de2003, por lo que están expuestos un mayor riesgo de complicaciones óseas y cardiovasculares.El análisis de la adecuación de los parámetros del metabolismo Calcio-Fósforo debe realizarse mediante porcentajes para conocer el grupo de pacientesque requieren nuevas estrategias terapéuticas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;26(3): 351-357, mar. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049131</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Control del metabolismo calcio-fósforo en hemodiálisis y su adecuación a las guías K/DOQI 2003</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11186^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28261^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
