<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125769</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hilflosigkeit (the mourning process due to the human helplessness)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The autor considers the situation of human helplessness as the main traumatic factor. From this premise he understands that the function of maternal and analytic reverie are crucial in the long and complex process os dtructuring narcissism and ideality, which will favour the establishment of a healthy Edipus and its elaboration. All this will promote the acceptance by the efo of ideality, human helplessness and death (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Erroteta Palacio, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Partiendo del desvalimiento humano como el esencial factor traumático común, el autor sostiene la necesidad imperiosa de la función de reverie maternal y analítica para que, a través del largo proceso que supone la estructuración del narcisismo y de la idealidad, se sienten las premisas adecuadas para un Edipo saludablemente complejo y su elaboración, con la asunción por el yo de la instancia ideal y la aceptación del desamparo y de la muerte (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(54): 69-93, mayo-ago. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125769</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hilflosigkeit (el proceso de duelo por el desvalimiento humano)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3660</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9999</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23274</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22845</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9484</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200808</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
