<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143548</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Chapter 1: generalities of the lymphedemas and lymphatic circulation: pathogeny and pathophysiology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Lymphoedema represents an abnormal increase of protein-rich fluid inside the interstitial space due to an impairment of lymphatic transport capacity in the lymphatic system. It causes swelling in different parts of the body that results in a disability for the patient that fundamentally affects their physical and psycho-social areas. Since ancient times, different authors have attempted to discover the relationship between this fluid and lymphatic circulation. Lymphoedema can be classified into two groups: primary and secondary (with other sub-classifications that are of clinical interest). Filariasis represents the highest incidence of lymphoedema worldwide. However, in developed countries, lymphoedema is mostly secondary to surgery and radiotherapy, above all in breast cancer. Nevertheless, the incidence of this condition is decreasing nowadays due to the sentinel node biopsy technique. High molecular weight proteins as well as other substances are transported by the lymph and unloaded in both of the yugular-subclavian venous angles. The theories of Guyton and Casley-Smith explain lymph formation in the interstitial space and its transport. The functional unit of the lymphatic collector is the lymphangion, which can automatically contract, and leads the lymph in a centripetal direction along the superficial lymphatic pathways and other depths, but which are perfectly interconnected. In addition, other factors are going to be equally important in this process. Two factors contribute to the generation of lymphoedema: the alteration of the lymphatic load and the transport mechanisms of the lymph. Once the stasis in the interstitial tissue is generated, it may undergo various processes, such as progressive fibrosis. Therefore, this tends to be a chronic condition in favor of different pathophysiological conditions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lanzas Melendo, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varela Donoso, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González López-Arza, MV</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Atín Arratíbel, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El linfedema es un aumento anormal de líquido rico en proteínas, en el espacio intersticial, debido a una alteración de la capacidad de transporte del sistema linfático, lo que ocasiona una hinchazón en diferentes partes del cuerpo, junto con una discapacidad para el paciente que afecta fundamentalmente a su área física y psicosocial. Desde la antigüedad, muchos ¨ autores han tratado de encontrar la relación entre este líquido y la circulación linfática. Existen dos diferentes formas de clasificar el linfedema: primario y secundario, con otras subclasificaciones de interés clínico. La incidencia mayor de linfedema de manera global es como consecuencia de la filariasis, aunque en los países desarrollados es el secundario a cirugía y/o radioterapia, fundamentalmente en el cáncer de mama, hoy día en claro descenso debido a la técnica de la biopsia del ganglio centinela. Por la linfa son transportadas hasta la sangre proteínas de alto peso molecular, así como otras sustancias, que son llevadas hasta ambos ángulos venosos yugulosubclavios. Las teorías de Guyton y Casley-Smith, explican la formación de la linfa en el espacio intersticial y su transporte. La unidad funcional del colector linfático es el linfangión, el cual puede contraerse autónomamente, conduciendo la linfa en sentido centrípeto a lo largo de unas vías linfáticas superficiales y otras profundas pero que están perfectamente conectadas entre s&amp;#305;´; además, otros factores van a ser igualmente importantes en este proceso. Dos factores intervienen en la generación de los linfedemas: la alteración de la carga linfática y la de los mecanismos de transporte de la linfa. Una vez generado el estasis en el tejido intersticial, este puede sufrir distintos procesos, como es una fibrosis progresiva, tendiendo, por tanto, a la cronicidad y favoreciendo diferentes situaciones fisiopatológicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);44(supl.1): 2-7, oct. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143548</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Capítulo I: generalidades de los linfedemas y de la circulación linfática: patogenia y fisiopatología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8375^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8385^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8386^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35392^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8386^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
