<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116946</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Morphometric analysis of the liver cell after administration of different abuse drugs</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Have been described, various changes caused by the consumption of drugs of abuse at the level of different organs is one of the most relevant, by the developed functions, the liver. Quantifying these changes is the main goal scored at work. MATERIAL AND METHODS: we performed an experimental study in the albino mouse in order to evaluate from the standpoint of possible alterations morphometric three drugs of abuse such as cocaine, ecstasy and heroin, produced in the liver from the ultrastructural view. Poisoning takes animal and a study is made of the liver, after processing of the parts under transmission electron microscopy, and morphometric evaluation of the intracellular organelles. RESULTS: the study showed a decrease in mitochondrial density and area of these organelles ballooning. Increase in number  of lysosomes and their size also thickening them. Significant diminution of the endoplasmic reticulum and number of ribosomes. Also shown glycogen rosettes decreased but increased the size and number of fat vacuoles. Alterations shown in all animalsintoxicated with drugs being the most relevant group of heroin. DISCUSSION. The results show a severe disruption of the intracellular organelles liver both the number and the structure thereof, being indicative of cell suffering and malfunctioning complex ultrastructural hepatocyte. These changes are most relevant  in the group intoxicated with heroin and less on that of ecstasy and cocaine. Can be considered that although the dose treated animals there is a large intracellular destruction if there is a disturbance at the level of organelles and especially those related to energy device or cell protein production as mitochondria or ribosome, appearing or increasing the cell lysis such  as lysosomes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vaquero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agudo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diago, M. V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Verona, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se han descrito, diferentes alteraciones producidas por el consumo de las drogas de abuso a nivel de distintos órganos siendo uno de los más relevantes, por las funciones por el desarrolladas, el hígado. Cuantificar estas alteraciones es el objetivo principal marcado en el trabajo. MATERIAL Y MÉTODOS: se realiza un trabajo experimental en el ratón albino con el fin de valorar desde el punto de vista morfométrico las posibles alteraciones que tres drogas de abuso como son la cocaína, el extasis y la heroína , producen a nivel del hígado desde el punto de vista ultraestructural. Se realiza la intoxicación de los animales y se realiza un estudio del hígado, después del procesamiento de las piezas bajo microscopía electrónica de transmisión y valoración morfométrica de las organelas intracelulares. RESULTADOS: el estudio mostró una disminución de la densidad y área mitocondrial con abalonamiento de estas organelas. Incremento del número de lisosomas y de su tamaño también con engrosamiento de las mismas. Diminución muy significativa del retículo endoplásmico y número de ribosomas. También se muestran disminuidas las rosetas de glúcógeno, pero incrementado el tamaño y número de vacuolas grasas. Alteraciones que se muestran en todos los animales intoxicados con las drogas siendo mas relevantes las del grupo de heroína. DISCUSIÓN. Los resultados muestran una grave alteración de las organelas intracelulares hepáticas tanto en el número como  en las estructura de las mismas, siendo indicativo de sufrimiento celular y mal funcionamiento del complejo ultraestructural del hepatocito. Estas alteraciones son más relevantes en el grupo intoxicado con heroína y menos en el de extasis y cocaína. Se puede considerar que aunque a las dosis tratadas a los animales no exista una gran destrucción intracelular, si que hay una alteración a nivel de organelas y sobre todo las relacionadas con el aparato energético de la célula o de producción proteica como mitocondrias o ribosomas, apareciendo o incrementándose las de lisis celular como son los lisosomas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;16(3): 107-112, jul.-sept. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116946</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio morfométrico de las organelas del hepatocito tras la administración de drogas de abuso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8994</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8939^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23789^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35288^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3070^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3959^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
