<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-AOT-2249</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Acute chest pain is a distressing sensation between the diaphragm and the base of the neck and it represents a diagnostic challenge for any physician in the emergency department. Objective: To establish the main clinical and epidemiological characteristics of patients who present with chest pain to the emergency department in a private clinic from the city of Medellin. Methods: Cross-sectional retrospective observational study, were patients who consulted for chest pain in the emergency department who met the eligibility criteria during 2014-2015. The information was analyzed in SPSS program vr.21; qualitative variables were described through relative frequencies, and the quantitative through mean and standard deviation or medians according to their distribution in the study population. Results: A total of 231 patients were evaluated, the mean age was 49.5 ± 19.9 years, 56.7 % were females. The most frequent pathological antecedents were hypertension 35.5 %, diabetes 10,8 %, dyslipidemia 10.4 % and coronary disease 5.2 %. Regarding pain features, in 40.3 % of the patients the pain began abruptly, in 38.2 % it had a precordial location, for 20 % of the cases physical activity acted as a trigger, and 60.6 % was oppressive. Costochondritis was the most common cause of chest pain among patients with an established etiologic diagnosis, representing the 18.2 %. Conclusions: Although the clinical features of pain reported coincide with the clinical presentation of an acute coronary syndrome, the most common cause of chest pain in study population was costochondritis instead, indicating that it is a differential diagnostic in the approach of patients with pain acute chest (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jaramillo-Jaramillo, LI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bañol-Betancur, JI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Mejía, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Gázquez, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Tamayo, AM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Sánchez, LM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bahamonde-Olaya, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El dolor torácico agudo es una sensación dolorosa que se manifiesta entre el diafragma y la base del cuello, e implica un reto diagnóstico para cualquier médico en el servicio de urgencias. Objetivo: Determinar las principales características clínicas y epidemiológicas de los pacientes que consultan por dolor torácico en una clínica privada de la ciudad de Medellín. Metodología: Estudio observacional retrospectivo transversal, realizado con la información consignada en las historias clínicas de los adultos que consultaron por dolor torácico en el servicio de urgencias, en el periodo 2014-2015, y que cumplieron con los criterios de elegibilidad. La información se analizó en el programa SPSS 21, a las variables cualitativas se les calcularon frecuencias absolutas y relativas y a las cuantitativas se utilizaron promedios con desviación estándar o medianas. Resultados: Se evaluaron un total de 231 historias clínicas de pacientes que consultaron por dolor torácico. La edad promedio fue 49,5 ± 19,9 años, sexo femenino 56,7 %. Los antecedentes personales más frecuentes fueron hipertensión arterial 35,5 %, diabetes 10,8 %, dislipidemia 10,4 % y enfermedad coronaria 5,2 %. Respecto a las características del dolor, el 40,3 % fue de inicio súbito, de localización precordial el 38,2 %, para el 20 % el desencadenante fue la actividad física y el 60,6 % era de carácter opresivo. De los pacientes con diagnóstico etiológico, el más frecuente fue costocondritis con 18,2 %. Conclusiones: A pesar de que las características clínicas del dolor reportadas coinciden con la presentación clínica de un síndrome coronario agudo, la etiología más frecuente no fue esta, sino que fue la costocondritis, indicando que es un diagnóstico diferencial en el enfoque de un paciente con dolor torácico agudo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;24(6): 288-293, nov.-dic. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-AOT-2249</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Caracterización del dolor torácico en pacientes que consultan al Servicio de Urgencias de una institución de salud de alto nivel de complejidad, en el periodo 2014-2015, en Medellín, Colombia</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
