<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59928</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Stroke code implementation in a large hospital: outcomes, the role of the emergency department, and analysis of the learning curve</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze the implementation of a stroke code protocol and the results obtained in an initial phase inside a hospital and in a second phase during which the stroke code was also used for attending emergencies outside thehospital. Methods: Retrospective analysis of 20 months' application of the stroke code protocol. Two periods were defined for analysis. During the first period of 8 months, the code was used inside the hospital. In a second period of 12 months the code was used both inside and outside the hospital. Data collected for analysis of each period were the numbers of strokes diagnosed according to the stroke code criteria, the number of times the protocol was activated, the number of code procedures finalized, and the number of patients who received fibrinolytic therapy. The results obtained during the2 periods were compared (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Obach, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Choco, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miró, Òscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bragulat, Ernesto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Angelats, Elisenda</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Conclusiones: Estos resultados reflejan que la puesta en marcha de una atención protocolizaday consensuada entre los dispositivos extra e intrahospitalarios para los pacientescon ictus de menos de 3 horas de evolución consigue un porcentaje final de ictus fibrinolizadosdel 6%, lo cual no supone un incremento porcentual de tratamiento fibrinolíticorespecto al periodo de protocolo exclusivamente intrahospitalario. De este estudio seextrae, además, que las principales causas por las que no se consigue aumentar esteporcentaje son por una parte la tardanza en la llegada del paciente a urgencias y la presenciade diagnósticos alternativos, por otra. [Emergencias 2009;21:105-113]</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);21(2): 105-113, abr. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59928</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados alcanzados con la puesta en marcha del circuito &#147;Código Ictus&#148; en un gran hospital: papel de urgencias y análisis de la curva de aprendizaje</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10221</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24892^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
