<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74509</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">How to identify adverse events in emergency services? A guide agreed for the screening</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveSince a third of adverse events (AE) occur outside hospital, the Emergency Services are a suitable place to look at their incidence. We considered designing a screening guide, adapted to the conditions of the emergency services, to identify AE.Material and methodsA qualitative technique was applied (nominal group) in which 14 professionals participated. They analysed which factors of intrinsic risk, extrinsic risk, and alert conditions, were suitable for a screening guide of AE in emergency services. The session was chaired by a specialist in these types of techniques.ResultsConsensus was high in that the most frequent AE in emergencies were those related to medicines, diagnostic tests and with the correct identification of the reason for emergency. With respect to screening guide, the group proposed adding alcohol abuse, patient social problems, cognitive deterioration, basal autonomy and disability. In relation to extrinsic risk factors, they pointed to the need of including defibrillation, spinal tap or drainage implantation. With respect to the alert conditions form, the professionals agreed in that all the criteria seemed correct and suitable, except for that related to damage relation childbirth or amniocentesis.ConclusionsBy using this technique we have managed to validate materials already recognized, and widely used in our country. The screening guide was considered useful, with slight modifications in some risk factors and alert conditions. The professionals agreed that the MRF2 modular questionnaire is appropriate for the characterisation of AE in emergencies(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gea, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bartolomé, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rey, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mira, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Limón, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puy, A. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Requena, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ziadi, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aranaz, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lerma, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrasco, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miralles, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomas, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guilabert, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoDado que un tercio de los efectos adversos (EA) ocurren antes de la hospitalización, los servicios de urgencias constituyen un lugar idóneo para estimar su incidencia. Nuestro objetivo fue diseñar una guía de cribado para identificación de los EA debidos a la asistencia adecuada a las condiciones de urgencias.Material y métodosTécnica cualitativa de grupo nominal. Participaron 14 profesionales que analizaron qué factores de riesgo intrínseco, riesgo extrínseco y condiciones de alerta eran los idóneos para cribado de EA en urgencias. Moderada por un especialista en este tipo de técnicas.ResultadosExistió alto consenso en que los EA más frecuentes en urgencias son los relacionados con medicamentos, pruebas diagnósticas e identificación correcta del motivo de urgencia. Se propuso añadir a la guía de cribado abuso de alcohol, problemática social del paciente, deterioro cognitivo y autonomía basal. En relación con los factores de riesgo extrínsecos, apuntaron la necesidad de incluir la realización de cardioversión, punción lumbar o colocación de drenajes. Respecto al formulario de condiciones de alerta, todos los criterios parecieron correctos y adecuados, salvo el relacionado con daño en relación con el parto.ConclusionesMediante esta técnica se ha logrado validar unos materiales ya reconocidos y en nuestro país ampliamente utilizados. La guía de cribado se consideró apta con leves modificaciones en algunos factores de riesgo y condiciones de alerta, mientras que respecto al cuestionario Modular Revision Form (MRF2), los profesionales estuvieron de acuerdo con que, en general, es adecuado para la caracterización del EA que se produce en urgencias(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;24(6): 272-279, nov.-dic.2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74509</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Cómo identificar los efectos adversos en urgencias? Una guía consensuada para el cribado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4705^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22082</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
