<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82356</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Carotid artery stiffness as an early marker of vascular lesions in children and adolescents with cardiovascular risk factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. The availability of a noninvasive marker of vascular lesions that enables their detection in the preclinical phase would be of great benefit for cardiovascular disease prevention. The aim of this study was to investigate the usefulness of a range of indices of arterial wall stiffness in the common carotid artery, as derived using high-resolution Doppler ultrasonography, for identifying vascular damage in children with risk factors. Methods. The study involved 99 children (age, 8-16 years) divided into two groups: 65 had cardiovascular risk factors (45 obesity, 20 dyslipidemia) and 34 were controls. Family histories of cardiovascular risk factors and anthropometric and biochemical measurements were recorded. Functional parameters of arterial stiffness (i.e., arterial compliance, elastic modulus, beta stiffness index, pulse wave velocity, and augmentation index) and the intima-media thickness were also measured. Results. Some functional vascular parameters were higher in obese children than controls: there were significant differences in beta stiffness index (P&lt;.02), elastic modulus (P&lt;.001) and pulse wave velocity (P&lt;.01). There was a significant difference in arterial compliance between dyslipidemics and controls (P&lt;.05). No significant difference in intima-media thickness was found between the groups. In obese children, there were positive correlations between body mass index, systolic pressure and triglyceride levels and vascular parameters (i.e., elastic modulus and pulse wave velocity); in dyslipidemic children, triglyceride levels and the same parameters were correlated. Conclusions. Ultrasonographic measurement of arterial stiffness is a sensitive technique that can detect vascular damage in children with cardiovascular risk factors earlier than intima&#150;media thickness measurement (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Costa, Cecilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morata, Julia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brines, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Zahonero, Julia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chorro, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Para la prevención de la enfermedad cardiovascular resulta de gran interés disponer de un marcador incruento de lesión vascular que permita su detección en fase preclínica. Nuestro objetivo fue analizar diversos índices de rigidez arterial de la carótida común mediante ultrasonografía Doppler de alta resolución para definir su utilidad como detector de daño vascular en niños con factores de riesgo. Métodos. Se estudió a 99 niños (edades, 8-16 años) divididos en dos grupos: 65 niños con factores de riesgo cardiovascular (45 obesos, 20 dislipémicos) y 34 controles. Se recogieron antecedentes familiares de riesgo cardiovascular y variables antropométricas y bioquímicas. Se midieron parámetros funcionales de rigidez arterial (compliance arterial, módulo elástico, índice beta de rigidez, velocidad de la onda de pulso e índice de aumento) y el grosor íntima-media. Resultados. Los niños obesos presentaron parámetros vasculares funcionales elevados respecto a los controles, que fueron significativos para el índice beta (p &lt; 0,02), el módulo elástico (p &lt; 0,001) y la velocidad de onda del pulso (p &lt; 0,01). En los dislipémicos constatamos diferencias significativas en la compliance arterial respecto a los controles (p &lt; 0,05). No hubo diferencias significativas en el grosor íntima-media entre grupos. Encontramos correlación positiva entre el índice de masa corporal, la presión sistólica y los triglicéridos con los parámetros vasculares (módulo elástico y velocidad de onda del pulso) en los obesos y, entre triglicéridos y los mismos parámetros en los dislipémicos. Conclusiones. La medida ultrasonográfica de la rigidez arterial es un procedimiento sensible que puede resultar más precoz que el grosor íntima-media para detectar daño vascular en niños con factores de riesgo cardiovascular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;63(11): 1253-1260, nov. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82356</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Medida de la rigidez de la arteria carótida como marcador precoz de lesión vascular en niños y adolescentes con factores de riesgo cardiovascular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2381^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19139^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34244^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34244^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34244^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201011</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
