<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143846</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Women with metabolic syndrome improve antrophometric and biochemical parameters with green banana flour consumption</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Consumption of green banana flour (GBF) may promote health benefits, such as, decreased appetite, weight loss, glycemic control, intestinal function and lipid profile improvement, aging delay, cancer and heart disease prevention. The aim of this study was to evaluate the effects of green banana flour consumption on anthropometric and biochemical parameters in overweight women. Methods: The glycemic index of flour in the study was determined. The effects of consumption of 20 g of green banana flour/day on weight, body mass index (BMI), blood pressure, waist and hip circumference, body composition, hemoglobin, lipid profile, glucose, insulin, insulin resistance, liver function and energy intake were evaluated in 25 overweight women for 45 days. Results: The glycemic index of the flour under study was classified as low. Reduction (p &lt; 0.05) in systolic blood pressure, hip circumference and fasting glucose levels were found in women who had metabolic syndrome criteria. Conclusions: Consumption of green banana flour (20 g/day) for 45 days did not promote weight loss or changes in body composition in overweight women. It was noted, however, decreased hip circumference. Significant health parameter improvements were also noted in individuals with metabolic syndrome, which showed a reduction in systolic blood pressure and fasting glucose (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dos Santos, Carolina Araújo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Girondoli, Yassana Marvila</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lima, Mario Flávio C de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bressan, Josefina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva, Sandra Tavares da</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coelho, Raquel Cristina Lopes Assis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moraes, Luís Fernando de Sousa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schitini, Josiane Keila Viana Gomes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Azeredo, Luiza Mello de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El consumo de «green banana flour» (GBF) puede contribuir para la salud como, por ejemplo, aumento en las sensaciones de saciedad , pérdida de peso , control de la glucemia y mejora de la función intestinal y el perfil lipídico, retraso del envejecimiento y la prevención del cáncer y de las enfermedades del corazón. El objetivo del estudio fue evaluar los efectos del consumo de GBF sobre los parámetros antropométricos y bioquímicos de las mujeres con exceso de peso. Métodos: Se determinó el índice glucémico de la harina en el estudio. Los efectos del consumo diario de 20 g de GBF en peso, índice de masa corporal (IMC), presión arterial, circunferencia de la cintura y de la cadera, la composición corporal, los niveles de hemoglobina, glucosa e insulina, resistencia insulínica, en la función del hígado y la ingesta alimentaria se evaluaron en 25 mujeres con exceso de peso durante 45 días. Resultados: El índice glucémico de harina estudiada fue clasificado como bajo. Fue encontrado reducción (p &lt; 0,05) en la presión arterial sistólica, en la circunferencia de la cadera y en la glicemia en mujeres que tenían los criterios de síndrome X metabólico. Conclusiones: El consumo de harina de plátano sin madurar durante 45 días no promueve la pérdida de peso o los cambios en la composición corporal en mujeres con sobrepeso. Sin embargo, hubo una reducción de la circunferencia de la cadera. Se observó también una mejoría significativa en importantes factores de salud en mujeres con síndrome X metabólico, tales como una reducción en la presión arterial sistólica y de la glucemia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;29(5): 1070-1080, mayo 2014. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143846</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las mujeres con síndrome metabólico mejoran los parámetros antropométricos y bioquímicos con el consumo de «green banana flour»</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37656^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33519^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35972</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5566^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
