<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128437</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mediterranean spotted fever: a case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Typical symptoms of Mediterranean spotted fever (FBM) include fever, generalized rash and the presence of a black eschar that may go unnoticed. Usually follows a benign course, but occasionally serious complications occur. Although the disease was first described a century ago, a few questions about the actual vector and reservoir of the disease remain unclear. We present a typical case of FBM and propose a hypothesis about the mode of transmission of Rickettsia in our patient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Villacampa, M. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Menéndez Martínez, Mª A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casado Carreto, Mª C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres León, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segovia Abad, Mª E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los síntomas típicos de la fiebre botonosa mediterránea (FBM) incluyen fiebre, un rash cutáneo generalizado y la presencia de una escara negra que puede pasar desapercibida. Por lo general sigue un curso benigno, aunque ocasionalmente aparecen complicaciones graves. A pesar de que la enfermedad fue descrita hace un siglo, algunas preguntas acerca del vector y el reservorio real de la enfermedad siguen sin aclararse. Presentamos un caso típico de FBM y planteamos una hipótesis sobre la forma de transmisión de la Rickettsia en nuestro paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;70(3): 185-187, jul.-sept. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128437</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fiebre botonosa mediterránea: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27857^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14375^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33722^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24377</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22363^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
