<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125493</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sinusitis associated to allergic respiratory condition</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. To draw attention to the high incidence of sinusitis, whose most prominent symptom usually is cough, which may predominate in prone position, in children with asthma and similar pathology. Material and methods. Review of 100 medical history of children under 18 years old, visited consecutively, with symptoms suggestive of asthma, bronchitis or allergic rhinitis. Furthermore history and physical examination, prick test, assessment of total and specific IgE to suspected allergens, other Igs (G,M,A), blood count, lung function and methacholine challenge test in children of the right age and collaborators, were realized. Sinus radiography and measurement of eosinophils in mucus, when cough was present, particularly at night, was a significant symptom. Results. In 53 children the diagnosis of asthma was confirmed, 10 of with also suffered from allergic sinusitis, whereas infectious sinusitis was present in 8. In other 26 the existence of asthma was not confirmed, but another bronchial disease was present; allergic sinusitis accompanied in 2 cases, and infectious sinusitis in another 7. Rhinitis only, was diagnosed in 10 children, and accompanied by allergic sinusitis in other 2 and infectious sinusitis in 9. Conclusion. Allergic sinusitis was suffered by 15 children who did not require specific treatment for it; while the 24 in which infectious sinusitis diagnosis required specific treatment, specially with antibiotics and nasal decongestants and in some cases topical corticosteroids and/or antihistaminics (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz López, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Llamar la atención sobre la elevada incidencia sinusitis, cuyo síntoma más destacado suele ser la tos, que puede predominar en posición de cúbito, en niños con asma y patología similar. Material y métodos. Revisión de 100 historias clínicas de niños hasta 18 años de edad, visitados consecutivamente, con sintomatología sugestiva de asma, bronquitis  o rinitis alérgicas. Además de la historia y examen clínicos, se hicieron pruebas alérgicas (prick-test), valoración de IgE sérica total y específica para los alérgenos sospechosos, otras Igs (G, M, A), hemograma, función pulmonar y test de metacolina, en niños colaboradores y de edad adecuada. Radiografía de senos paranasales y valoración de eosinófilos en moco, cuando la tos y sobre todo nocturna, dominaban el cuadro clínico. Resultados. En 53 años se confirmó el diagnóstico de asma, de los cuales 10 padecían también sinusitis alérgica y 8 infecciosa. En otras 26 no se confirmó la existencia de asma, sino broncopatía, acompañada de sinusitis alérgica en 2 de ellos y sinusitis infecciosa en otros 7. Solo rinitis se diagnosticó en 10 niños ya acompañada de sinusitis alérgica en otros 2 e infecciosa en otros 9. Conclusiones. Sinusitis alérgica la padecían 14 niños, que no necesitaron tratamiento específico para la misma, mientras que si lo precisaron los 24 en los que se diagnosticó sinusitis infecciosa,  especialmente con antibióticos y descongestivos nasales en y en algunos casos corticoides tópicos y/o antihistamínicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;69(2): 74-78, mar.-abr. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125493</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sinusitis asociada a patología respiratoria alérgica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12551^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13233^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2020^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28064^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15066^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
