<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76380</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4603</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Phonological divergences between adult´s speech and children´s in the Spanish of Lima (Peru)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article compares the adult speech production of the Spanish spoken in Lima (Peru) to the speech of monolingual children from the same city, between the ages of two and a half and five. No of the subjects present any articulatory, auditory or mental disability. In particular, this article focuses on which phonological features show divergences when adult and child speech are compared. It also discusses the age until which those divergences remain in the speech of children. The main result is the identification that between the ages of two and a half and three and a half, a significant decrease of the divergences occurs. The results are of great importance for language therapists who work with preschoolers. In addition to corroborating that the phonological system is progressively acquired, this provides a point of reference that will help language therapists detect and give early treatment to children who may show minor phonological disorders or specific language impairments(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montezuma del Castillo, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ciccia Gabillo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gabillo Ciccia, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echenique Herrera, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elías-Ulloa, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Raffo Castro, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seminario Olórtigue, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este artículo es comparar el habla del modelo adulto del español hablado en la ciudad de Lima (Perú) con el habla de niños limeños monolingües, cuyas edades varían de 2,6 años a 5 años y que no presentan aparentes limitaciones articulatorias, auditivas o intelectuales. En particular, esta investigación se centra en el estudio de qué rasgos fonológicos muestran divergencias cuando se comparan ambos tipos de producciones, así como determinar hasta qué edad dichas divergencias subsisten en el habla de los niños. Uno de los principales resultados de este estudio es la identificación del momento en que se produce una disminución significativa en las divergencias observadas entre el habla del modelo adulto del español de Lima y el habla de los niños. Este momento ocurre entre los 2,6 años y 3,6 años. Estos resultados son de gran importancia para los terapeutas del lenguaje que trabajan con niños en edades preescolares. Además de corroborar que el sistema fonológico se va adquiriendo de manera progresiva, este estudio brinda un punto de referencia que ayudará a detectar y tratar a tiempo a niños que potencialmente podrían presentar retrasos simples del habla o trastornos específicos del lenguaje(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. logop. foniatr. audiol. (Ed. impr.);26(4): 215-230, oct.-dic. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76380</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las divergencias fonológicas entre el habla adulta y el de los niños en el español hablado en Lima (Perú)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13448^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13452</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1307^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13446^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1191^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13447^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
