<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038971</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Risks of estrogen treatment in gender identity disorders: apropos of a case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The potential risks of estrogen treatment when the male-to-female (M-to-F) transsexual patients are treated with estrogens should not be forgotten. We report the case of a M-to-F transsexual patient undergoing treatment with ethinyl estradiol who developed deep vein thrombosis of the lower extremity after a period of immobility because of a sprain. Thrombophilia study revealed that she was a heterozygous carrier of factor V Leiden. Estrogens were therefore contraindicated. We recommend screening for thrombophilic defects in patients at high risk for deep vein thrombosis before starting estrogen therapy. In addition, these patients require thromboembolic prophylaxis if there are concomitant triggering factors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vayá, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cubells, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casañ, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solá, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garzón, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Torres, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los riesgos potenciales del tratamiento estrogénico se deben tener en cuenta al tratar a los pacientes transexuales de varón a mujer con estos fármacos. Presentamos el caso de una paciente transexual de varón a mujer que estaba siendo tratada con etinilestradiol y sufrió un episodio de trombosis venosa profunda en el miembro inferior tras inmovilización por un esguince. Dicha paciente fue sometida posteriormente a un estudio de trombofilia y se detectó que era portadora heterocigota del factor V Leiden, por lo que se contraindicó el tratamiento con estrógenos de por vida. Debemos valorar, en los pacientes con mayor riesgo de trombosis venosa profunda, la realización de un estudio de trombofilia previo al tratamiento, así como la necesidad de profilaxis tromboembólica en caso de coexistir un reto trombótico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;52(6): 321-322, jun. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038971</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Riesgos del tratamiento estrogénico en trastornos de identidad sexual: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33361^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5059^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22170^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5089^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33361^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14582</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
