<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101726</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Arterial hypertension in Pediatrics. Inflammatory risk factors and salt taste sensitivity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In order to detect a case of arterial hypertension in a pediatric patient often requires ruling out an associated organic disease, generally kidney disease. In recent years, however, more and more cases are being diagnosed of essential or primary hypertension, fundamentally due to the increase of the prevalence of obesity and overweight-ness in children and adolescents. In the present review, the relationships existing between arterial hypertension and obesity with other cardiovascular risk factors, both classical and the new inflammatory type factors of recent appearance are analyzed. The knowledge of the canalization phenomenon or tracking and the study of these factors will allow for a better characterization of the risk of our pediatric patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Málaga, s</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Argüelles, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vijande, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Detectar un caso de hipertensión arterial en un paciente pediátrico obliga las más de las veces a descartar una enfermedad orgánica asociada, generalmente, una nefropatía. Entre los últimos años, sin embargo, se diagnostican cada vez más casos de hipertensión arterial esencial o primaria, debido fundamentalmente al aumento de la prevalencia de obesidad y sobrepeso en los niños y adolescentes. En la presente revisión se analizan las relaciones existente entre la hipertensión arterial y la obesidad con otros factores de riesgo cardiovascular tanto clásicos como con los nuevos factores de tipo inflamatorio de reciente aparición. El conocimiento del fenómeno de canalización o tracking y el estudio de estos factores permitirán una menor caracterización del riesgo de nuestros pacientes pediátricos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;67(6): 366-371, nov.-dic. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101726</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hipertensión arterial en Pediatría. Factores de riesgo inflamatorios y sensibilidad gustativa salina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1822^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14030^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
