<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128464</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Breathing disorders during sleep and the circadian rhythm of strokes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Similar to myocardium infarct and sudden death, stroke presents a circadian rhythm with a maximum incidence of the beginning of the symptoms during the first morning hours. It is believed that this morning pick is secondary to haemodynamic, haemostatic and autonomic changes that happen during sleep, the sleep-awake transition and after wake up. About 25% of stroke, especially lacunar and atherothrombotic infarcts, occurs during night sleep. Usually, the symptoms are perceived for first time when the individual wakes up in the morning although stroke could have occurred long time before. These individuals are excluded from thrombolytic treatments and therapeutic trials. The patients that develop an ischemic stroke when sleeping presents more obstructive apneas during the acute phase of stroke than patients that suffer stroke during wakefulness. It is known that apneas are associated to oxyhemoglobin desaturations and to important haemodinamic changes and their treatment reduce cerebrovascular morbidity. These findings suggest that apneas, likely associated with other risk factors, can worsen or precipitate an ischemic stroke (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Iranzo de Riquer, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santamaría Cano, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">De manera similar al infarto de miocardio y la muerte súbita, los ictus presentan un ritmo circadiano con una máxima incidencia del inicio de los síntomas en las primeras horas de la mañana. Se cree que este pico matinal es secundario a cambios hemodinámicos, hemostásicos y autonómicos que ocurren durante el sueño, la transición sueño-vigilia y tras el despertar. Aproximadamente un 25% de los ictus, especialmente los infartos lacunares y aterotrombóticos, se instauran durante el sueño nocturno. Habitualmente los síntomas se perciben por primera vez cuando el sujeto se despierta por la mañana, aunque en realidad el ictus puede haberse instaurado mucho tiempo antes. A estos sujetos se les excluye de un tratamiento trombolítico y de entrar en ensayos terapéuticos. Los pacientes que desarrollan un ictus isquémico durante el sueño presentan más apneas obstructivas durante la fase aguda del ictus que los que desarrollan el ictus durante la vigilia. Se sabe que las apneas se asocian a desaturaciones de la oxihemoglobina y a importantes cambios hemodinámicos, y que su tratamiento reduce la morbilidad cerebrovascular. Estos hallazgos sugieren que las apneas, probablemente asociadas a otros factores de riesgo, pueden agravar o precipitar la instauración de un ictus isquémico durante el sueño (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;41(supl.3): s17-s19, oct. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128464</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos respiratorios durante el sueño y el ritmo circadiano del ictus</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26973</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2600^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35313^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34202^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
