<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114292</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Present features of congenital muscular dystrophies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Congenital muscular dystrophies(CMD) are a heterogeneous group of muscular diseases relatively frequent, of autosomical recesive heredity, that usually make their début at birth or in the first months of life with muscular weakness hypotonicity, contractures, myopathic electromyography, and a histological muscular picture with characteristic features of dystrophy. Its great clinical variety is determined by various degrees of delay in the motive development, physical inability, specific underliyng muscular pathology, and the presence or absence of mental retardation. In the last years, besides de mapping and identification of the responsible gen in various forms of CMD, it has been defined the clinical and pathological foundation of a significant number of new syndromes that present with CMD. These circumstances have lead to the drawing up of new classifications, based in the knowledge or ignorance of the respective gen, or if they have mental retardation or not. For they definitive diagnostic approach are essential the following facts: a) existence or absence of involvement of the central nervous system, in terms of severe mental retardation and/or structural cerebral defects, or eye defects; b) to know the expression of the protein merosine at muscular leves; c) to assess the presence of spine rigidity, muscular hypertrophies o distal hyperalasticity. In the present review are describe firstly the CMD without mental retardation, and secondly those with involvement of the central nervous system or with other associated facts (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blanco Barca, M. O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro Gago, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Novo Rodríguez, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Eirís Puñal, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pintos Martínez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las distrofias musculares congénitas (DMC) constituyen un grupo heterogéneo de enfermedades musculares relativamente frecuentes y con herencia autosómica recesiva, que habitualmente debutan al nacimiento o en los primeros meses de vida por hipotonía, debilidad muscular, contracturas, electromiografía miopática y un patrón histológico muscular con hechos característicos de distrofia. Su gran diversidad clínica está determinada por el diferente grado de retraso en el desarrollo motor, por la discapacidad física, por la patología muscular específica subyacente y por la presencia o no de retraso mental. En los últimos años, al margen de haberse mapeado o identificado/caracterizado el gen en varias formas de DMC, se han definido los fundamentos clínicos y patológicos de un número no desdeñable de nuevos síndromes que cursan con DMC. Estas circunstancias han conducido a la elaboración de nuevas clasificaciones, fundamentándose unas en el conocimiento o no del respectivo gen, y otras en si cursan o no con retraso mental. Para su aproximación diagnóstica definitiva son fundamentales los siguientes hechos: a) existencia o no de participación del sistema nervioso central, en términos de un retraso mental grave y/o defectos cerebrales estructurales o bien afectación ocular; b) conocer la expresión de la proteína denominada merosina a nivel muscular; c) valorar la existencia de rigidez de la columna, de hipertrofias musculares o de laxitud distal. En la presente revisión se describe inicialmente las DMC en las que no existe retraso mental, y posteriormente aquellas que cursan con participación del sistema nerviosos central o bien con otros hechos asociados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;60(6): 451-467, nov.-dic. 2004. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114292</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aspectos actuales de las distrofias musculares congénitas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2527^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9328^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9328^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
