<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89826</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Family caregiver&#146;s self-perceived health status and its relation to burden</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The study aims to analyze how health is self-perceived by a sample of caregivers of dependant relatives and how it compares with general Spanish population scores. The study also focuses on the relations between self-perceived health and burden. The sample comprised 1,257 caregivers living in Biscay who completed the protocol including sociodemographic data, measures of health-related quality of life (SF-36) and burden (Zarit Burden Inventory). Results show that the health perception of the caregivers taking part into the study reached lower scores in comparison to general Spanish population and that this perception was lower in mental than in physical health. Correlational data supports previous findings indicating that high levels of burden are associated with a worse perception of mental and physical health and provide information on how to guide interventions to improve family caregivers&#146; quality of life (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Marqués, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrasco Zabaleta, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández de Larrinoa Palacios, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Marroquín, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solabarrieta Eizaguirre, Josu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Rodríguez, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del estudio es conocer cómo percibe su estado de salud una muestra de cuidadores familiares de la provincia de Vizcaya y comparar los resultados con datos referidos a población general española. Además se pretende comprobar si existe relación entre la salud percibida y el nivel de sobrecarga. La muestra consta de 1.257 cuidadores/as de personas dependientes. Se ha utilizado un protocolo elaborado para recoger información sobre aspectos sociodemográficos, salud percibida relacionada con la calidad de vida (SF-36) y sobrecarga (Zarit Burden Inventory). Los resultados muestran que la percepción general de salud de las personas cuidadoras que han participado en el estudio es peor que la de la población general española y que esta percepción es especialmente acusada en lo que se refi ere al componente de salud mental. Además, las correlaciones muestran que cuanto peor es la salud percibida mayor es la sobrecarga. Estos resultados confirman los hallazgos obtenidos en otros estudios y proporcionan claves para orientar las intervenciones dirigidas a mejorar la calidad de vida de las personas cuidadoras (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);23(3): 388-393, jul.-sept. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89826</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Autopercepción del estado de salud en familiares cuidadores y su relación con el nivel de sobrecarga</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1853</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
