<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74306</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1582</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Recent studies using microarray technologyhave resulted in a new prognostic classification of breast cancer,based on the genetic profile of the tumors. The differencesin survival between the women belonging to the differentsubgroups established by this new classification are highlysignificant. However, none of the cited studies has stratifiedthe tumors by histology or size. In the present paper, we havereclassified our early breast cancers (pT1) belonging exclusivelyto the ductal infiltrating variety, according to a simplifiedversion of the above cited molecular classification, as proposedby their authors.Materials and methods: We studied 346 unifocal, pT1ductal infiltrating carcinomas. Of them, 251 (72.5%) wereclassified as luminal A type (ER+, PR+, c-erb-B2 -); 45 (13%)were triple-negative, 20 (5.8%) expressed at the same timehormonal receptors and c-erb-B2 (luminal B type), and 30(8.7%) expressed c-erb-B2, with absent hormone receptor expression(HER2 type).Results: During the statistical workup, it became evidentthat luminal B and HER2-type tumors showed identical, or almostidentical correlations with the studied clinical and molecularparameters, and were finally regrouped into a single categoryof c-erb-B2-expressing tumors, regardless of theirhormone receptor status. Comparing the tumors of the luminal A group with therest, the former showed a significant inverse correlation withhistologic and nuclear grade 3 (r = - 0.15, p = 0.004 and r = -0.40, p &lt; 0.0001, respectively), with p53 expression (r = -0.45, p &lt; 0.0001), as well as with a Ki67 labelling index&gt;20% (r = - 0.42, p &lt; 0.0001)...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Perea, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejerina Gómez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schneider, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejerina Bernal, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lucas, A. R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: Trabajos recientes, utilizando la tecnologíade &#147;microarrays&#148; han resultado en una nueva clasificaciónpronóstica del cáncer de mama basada en el perfil genético delos tumores. Las diferencias en la supervivencia de las pacientespertenecientes a los diferentes subgrupos que estableceesta nueva clasificación son altamente significativas. Sin embargo,ninguno de los citados estudios ha estratificado los tumorespor histologías o por tamaños. En el presente trabajo,hemos reclasificado nuestros cánceres de mama más precoces(pT1), pertenecientes exclusivamente al tipo ductal infiltrante,de acuerdo con una versión simplificada de la clasificación moleculararriba aludida, propuesta por sus propios autores.Material y métodos: Estudiamos 346 cánceres de mamaductales infiltrantes, unifocales, pT1. De ellos, 251 (72,5%) seencuadraron en el grupo luminal A (RE+, RP+, c-erb-B2 -); 45(13%) fueron triple-negativos, 20 (5,8%) expresaron al mismotiempo receptores hormonales y c-erb-B2 (tipo luminal B), y30 (8,7%) expresaron c-erb-B2 en ausencia de receptores hormonales(tipo HER2).Resultados: Durante el análisis estadístico, resultó evidenteque los tumores tipo luminal B y los HER2 presentaban idénticas,o casi idénticas correlaciones con los factores clínicos ymoleculares estudiados, y fueron finalente encuadrados en unsolo grupo de tumores con expresión de c-erb-B2, sin teneren cuenta la coexpresión o no de receptores hormonales.Comparando los tumores del grupo luminal A con el resto,los primeros mostraron una correlación significativamente inversacon un grado histológico y nuclear 3 (r = - 0,15, p =0,004 y r = - 0,40, p &lt; 0,0001, respectivamente), con la expresiónde p53 (r = - 0,45, p &lt; 0,0001) y un índice de KI67superior al 20% (r = - 0,42, p &lt; 0,0001)...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. senol. patol. mamar. (Ed. impr.);21(2): 62-66, 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74306</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Clasificación molecular simplificada del carcinoma ductal infiltrante unifocal pT1: identificación de subgrupos biológicamente diferenciados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31593^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31593^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9157^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7802</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38036^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200800</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
