<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159412</identifier>
<setSpec>2173-9218</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perceived effectiveness and safety of symptomatic slow action drugs for osteoarthritis (SYSADOA) for treating osteoarthrosis from community pharmacy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Osteoarthritis is a degenerative joint process a deep, chronic and poorly localized pain. The SYSADOA are slow-acting drugs that prevent the deterioration of cartilage, reduce pain and improve joint function. Objectives: To study the perception of effectiveness and safety of SYSADOA for the treatment of osteoarthritis in the community pharmacy. Method: Cross-sectional study in eight community pharmacies in Madrid between the months of December 2015 and January 2016 by conducting surveys. Results: A sample of 103 patients was included, where the mean age was over 60 years (47.9%) and 70.9% female. 32 interviewees (31%) mentioned healthy lifestyles. 54 patients (52.4%) suffer from other diseases: hypertension (34.0%), hypercholesterolemia (28.2%), diabetes (15.5%). The SYSADOA most frequently dispensed was chondroitin sulphate. Data analysis reveals that 53.4% of patients saw an improvement in mobility, 50.5% improved their quality of life and 49.5% improved their mood. Sixty-three patients (61.2%) reported that SYSADOA were effective. 2.9% of patients who had taken analgesics in combination with SYSADOA previously reported they were doing better with SYSADOA. Medication adherence was found in 76 (73.8%) patients. Fourteen (13.5%) Drug-Related Problems (DRPs) were found and thirteen (12.6%) Negative Outcomes Related to Medicines (NOM) were detected, two of them (1.8%) safety risk. Conclusions: Patients suffering from osteoarthritis are very adherents and SYSADOA drugs are perceived as effective and safe. They refer improvement in joint mobility, quality of life and mood (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Juan, Beatriz de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castellano, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Adrián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Alcalde, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Adán, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molinero, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matute, Evelin</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peral, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Araño, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La osteoartrosis es un proceso degenerativo articular que genera un dolor profundo, crónico y mal localizado. Los SYSADOA son fármacos de acción lenta que previenen el deterioro del cartílago, reducen el dolor y mejoran la función articular. Objetivos: Estudiar la percepción de efectividad y seguridad de los SYSADOA como tratamiento farmacológico de la artrosis. Material y métodos: Estudio observacional transversal en ocho farmacias comunitarias de Madrid entre los meses de diciembre de 2015 y enero de 2016 mediante la realización de una encuesta estructurada. Resultados: Se realizaron 103 dispensaciones, principalmente a mujeres (70,9%) mayores de 60 a.os (47,9%). Un 31% de los encuestados seguía hábitos de vida saludables. El 52,4% de los pacientes padecía otras enfermedades: hipertensión arterial (34,0%), hipercolesterolemia (28,2%), diabetes (15,5%). El SYSADOA dispensado con mayor frecuencia fue el condroitón sulfato. Del análisis de las encuestas obtuvimos que un 53,4% de los pacientes percibía una mejoría en la movilidad, un 50,5% mejora su calidad de vida y un 49,5% su estado anémico. El 61,2% de los pacientes refería que los SYSADOA son efectivos. De los pacientes que habían tomado analgésicos en combinación con SYSADOA con anterioridad, el 2,9% apuntaba que les iba mejor con SYSADOA. La adherencia al tratamiento fue de un 73,8% en los encuestados. Se detectaron 14 PRM (13,5%) y 13 RNM (12,6%), de los cuales 2 fueron de inseguridad (1,8%). Conclusiones: Los pacientes que padecen osteoartrosis son muy adherentes a sus tratamientos y perciben los SYSADOA como fármacos efectivos y seguros, así como refieren mejoría en la movilidad articular, calidad de vida y estado anémico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm. comunitarios (Internet);8(4): 5-17, dic. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159412</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Percepción de efectividad y seguridad de los fármacos de acción lenta para osteoartritis (SYSADOA) en el tratamiento de la artrosis desde la farmacia comunitaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53262^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55468</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5289</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2401^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2401^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
