<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81221</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-695X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The practice of Thai-Chi prevents falls in the institutionalized elderly: a clinical trial</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine whether practicing Thai Chi for 2 hours a week for 9 months decreasesthe risk of falls in elderly people aged 65 years or over living in residential carehomes.Design. Randomised, non-blind clinical trial with two groups.Setting. Two residential care homes in the city of Cuenca.Participants. A total of 94 institutionalized elderly persons between 65 and 90 years. Thecontrol group comprised 43 persons and the Thai Chi group 51 persons.Main measurements. The main measurements were number of falls and their severity, thenumber of stumbles and losses of balance determined by a weekly interview with one ofthe investigators.Results. The incidence of falls was 13.7% in the Tai Chi group and 32.5% in the controlgroup. (p &lt;0.03); Relative Risk, (RR) = 0.42, representing a risk reduction of 18.8%. Fiveelderly persons in the control group (11.6%) and none in the Thai Chi Group (p&lt; 0.02) sufferedbone fractures as result of the falls. We found significant differences in the numberof stumbles, 16 in the Thai Chi group (31.3%) and 49 in control group (113.9%) (p&lt;0.04;RR = 0.28; RAR = 0.826). Likewise, the differences in the number of losses of balance wassignificant, 12 in the Thai Chi group (23.5%) and 37 in the control group (86%) (p &lt; 0.02;RR = 0.27; RAR = 0.625).Conclusions. Regular Thai Chi practice may reduce the number of falls, the incidence ofbone fractures, the number of stumbles and losses of balance in elderly people living inresidential care homes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Franquelo Morales, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León Belmar, Javier de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valero Serrano, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quijada Rodríguez, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Martínez, Félix</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar si la práctica de dos horas de Tai Chi semanal durante 9 meses disminuyeel riesgo de caídas en ancianos de edad igual o superior a 65 años.Diseño. Ensayo clínico con aleatorización por grupos sin cegamiento.Emplazamiento. Dos residencias de ancianos de la ciudad de Cuenca.Participantes. Un total de 94 ancianos institucionalizados, de entre 65 y 90 años. Grupocontrol de 43 y grupo de intervención de 51 practicantes de Tai Chi.Mediciones principales. Mediante entrevista semanal, realizada por uno de los investigadores,se recogieron como eventos principales el número de caídas, número de fracturas,número de tropiezos y pérdidas de equilibrio.Resultados. La incidencia de caídas en el grupo de Tai Chi fue del 13,7% y en el grupocontrol del 32,5% (p &lt; 0,03); Razón de Riesgo [RR] = 0,42, lo que supone una Reducciónde Riesgo (RAR) del 18,8%. Como resultado de estas caídas, 5 ancianos de los controles(11,6%) sufrieron fracturas óseas y ninguna en el grupo de Tai Chi (p &lt; 0,02). Encontramosdiferencias estadísticamente significativas en cuanto al número de tropiezos, 16 en el grupode Tai Chi (31,3%) y 49 en los controles (113,9%) (p&lt;0,04; RR = 0,28; RAR = 0,826).Igualmente las diferencias en el número de pérdidas de equilibrio fue significativa, 12 enel grupo de Tai Chi (23,5%) y 37 en el grupo control (86%) (p &lt; 0,02; RR = 0,27; RAR =0,625).Conclusiones. La práctica regular de Tai Chi probablemente disminuye el número de caídas,la incidencia de fracturas, el número de tropiezos y las pérdidas de equilibrio en pacientesancianos institucionalizados(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. clín. med. fam;3(1): 34-38, feb.2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81221</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La práctica del Tai Chi previene las caídas en el anciano institucionalizado: un ensayo clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36278^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5179^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d61^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19050^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
