<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91154</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Preoperative mood disorders in patients undergoing cardiac surgery: risk factors and postoperative morbidity in the intensive care unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. To estimate the preoperative levels of anxiety and depression in patients awaiting heart surgery and to identify the risk factors associated with the development of these mood disorders. To evaluate the relationship between preoperative anxiety and depression and postoperative morbidity. Methods. Prospective longitudinal study in a sample of 100 patients undergoing heart surgery. We carried out a preoperative structured interview in which the patient completed the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale, and sociodemographic (age, sex, marital status, and income) and surgical variables (surgical risk, type of surgery, length of preoperative hospital stay, and surgical history) were also recorded. Pain, analgesic use, and postoperative morbidity were evaluated in the intensive care unit. Results. Thirty-two percent of the patients developed preoperative anxiety and 19%, depression. Age&lt;65 years (odds ratio=3.05; 95% confidence interval, 1.27-7.3) was the only significant risk factor for developing preoperative anxiety. A length of preoperative hospital stay &amp;#8805;3 days was the main risk factor for preoperative depression (odds ratio=4.59; 95% confidence interval, 1.6-13.17). Preoperative anxiety significantly increased the postoperative pain and analgesic consumption. Neither anxiety nor depression significantly modified the rest of the postoperative variables associated with morbidity in the intensive care unit. Conclusions. Anxiety and depression are mood disorders that are detected in patients awaiting heart surgery, with age &lt;65 years and a prolonged preoperative hospital stay being decisive factors in the development of these conditions. Although preoperative anxiety increased the postoperative pain in these patients, their state of mind did not modify their postoperative course (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sorbet-Amóstegui, María R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martorell-Gurucharri, Ainhara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín-Fernández, Blanca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Aizpún, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Induráin-Fernández, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carlos-Alegre, Vanessa de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordoñez-Ortigosa, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Irigoyen-Aristorena, María I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto-Guembe, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro-García, Miguel A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elizondo-Sotro, Arantzazu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Oroz, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Estimar niveles de ansiedad y depresión preoperatorios en pacientes sometidos a cirugía cardiaca y delimitar los factores de riesgo involucrados en la génesis de estos trastornos. Evaluar la relación entre ansiedad y depresión preoperatorias y morbilidad postoperatoria. Métodos. Estudio prospectivo y longitudinal en una muestra de 100 pacientes sometidos a cirugía cardiaca. Se realizó entrevista preoperatoria en la que se completó el Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (cuestionario de ansiedad y depresión hospitalaria) y se registraron variables sociodemográficas (edad, sexo, estado civil y renta) y quirúrgicas (riesgo quirúrgico, tipo de cirugía, días de ingreso preoperatorio y antecedentes quirúrgicos). En la unidad de cuidados intensivos se evaluó dolor, consumo analgésico y morbilidad clínica postoperatoria. Resultados. El 32% de los casos sufrieron ansiedad preoperatoria y el 19%, depresión. La edad &lt; 65 años (odds ratio=3,05; intervalo de confianza del 95%, 1,27-7,3) fue el único factor de riesgo de ansiedad preoperatoria significativo. La estancia hospitalaria preoperatoria &amp;#8805; 3 días fue el principal factor de riesgo de depresión preoperatoria (odds ratio=4,59; intervalo de confianza del 95%, 1,6-13,17). La ansiedad preoperatoria incrementó significativamente el dolor y el consumo analgésico postoperatorio. La ansiedad y la depresión preoperatorias no modificaron significativamente la morbilidad postoperatoria en la unidad de cuidados intensivos. Conclusiones. Ansiedad y depresión son trastornos del ánimo presentes en el paciente quirúrgico cardiaco, y la edad &lt; 65 años y la estancia hospitalaria preoperatoria prolongada son factores determinantes en la aparición de estos trastornos. Aunque la ansiedad preoperatoria incrementó el dolor posquirúrgico de los pacientes, el estado de ánimo no modificó su evolución postoperatoria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;64(11): 1005-1010, nov. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91154</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos del ánimo preoperatorios en cirugía cardiaca: factores de riesgo y morbilidad postoperatoria en la unidad de cuidados intensivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28598</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14290^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6500^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14543^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6500^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11621^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201111</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
