<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051817</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Historical review of the borderline personality disorder concept</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The concept of borderline syndrome is the subject of current debate because of its ambiguity and lack of homogeneity. Furthermore, the concept is rejected by many authors as a common category for atypical and non-specific disorders that cannot be classified elsewhere. The current use of the term borderline seems to be more a consequence of its historic use than its true clinical meaning. There is discrepancy on whether this term determines a level of severity, an organization of personality or a defined syndromic entity. In 1938, Stern was the first author to use the term borderline, and it was not introduced in the DSM III until 1980.    Objective. This work makes a historical review of the use of the term borderline and also of those terms that have been used to define patients with the same characteristics.        Conclusion. The different schools (psychoanalytic, biological, eclectic and biosocial) have different concepts on the term borderline. There is still no concise and exact definition for the diagnostic criteria of borderline and it is even possible the best term for this group of patients has still not been determined. It will be important to consider the contributions of the DSM V or ICD 11 in the next years</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Vives, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Ibor Aliño, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Marsá, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuentenebro, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrasco, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La utilización del término borderline sigue generando incertidumbre por su inespecificidad y ambigüedad. Además, múltiples autores opinan que quizá es el término más desafortunado para designar a este tipo de pacientes, y muchos otros consideran que se usa como cajón de sastre para pacientes que no pueden ser clasificados en otros diagnósticos. El uso del término borderline actual parece ser más una consecuencia de su uso histórico que su verdadero significado clínico. Hay discrepancia sobre si este término determina un nivel de gravedad, una organización de personalidad o una entidad sindrómica definida. Stern en 1938 fue el primer autor en utilizar el término borderline, y no se incluyó en el DSM-III hasta el año 1980.    Objetivo. Este trabajo realiza una revisión histórica de la utilización del término borderline y también de aquellos términos que se han usado para definir a pacientes con las mismas características.        Conclusión. Las distintas escuelas (psicoanalítica, biológica, ecléctica y biosocial) tienen concepciones distintas del término borderline. Aún no se ha llegado a una definición concisa y exacta para los criterios diagnósticos del borderline, y quizás, incluso, no se ha llegado a determinar cuál es el mejor término para este grupo de pacientes. Será importante tener en cuenta las aportaciones del DSM-V o la CIE-11 en los próximos años</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;34(5): 336-343, sept.-oct. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051817</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión histórica del concepto de trastorno limítrofe de personalidad (borderline)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28405</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1907</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
