<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91527</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness of hydrotherapy in people with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The aim of this study is to detect the levels of evidence and grades of recommendation of therapeutic aquatic exercise interventions in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) based on a systematic review. Design. The following databases were reviewed: Medline, Web of Knowledge, CINAHL, PsycInfo, Sport Discus, SCOPUS, Oaister, DOAJ, Cochrane, EMBASE and Pedro. Material and methods. A search for randomized clinical trials, cohort studies and case studies published 1996 to 2010 was made. The documents selected were classified according to the grades of recommendation of the DUODECIM Finnish society. Methodological quality of the 16 trials selected was assessed using the Delphi list. Results. Two primary documents showed clinical changes on the quality of life of questionnaire aimed at respiratory patients. Those subjects who performed incremental exercise in the water showed functional changes in the distance walked in the walking test, in forced vital capacity and forced expiratory volume. The incremental therapeutic water exercise recommended in the articles had an intensity ranging from 50% to 90% of VO2max with a frequency of two to five days a week. The sessions ranged from 30 to 50minutes within a treatment period going from 8 to 24 weeks with water temperature varying from 29°C to 38°C. In future studies, subgroups of the patients can be made based on their initial physical condition in order to improve the outcomes of the intervention(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cuesta-Vargas, A. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Labajos-Manzanares, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Valero, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El objetivo de este estudio es detectar los niveles de evidencia y grados de recomendación de la intervención acuática terapéutica en personas con enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica (EPOC) basado en una revisión sistemática. Diseño. La bases de datos revisadas son las siguientes: Medline, Web of Knowledge, CINAHL, PsycInfo, Sport Discus, SCOPUS, Oaister, DOAJ, Cochrane, EMBASE y Pedro. Material y método. Los límites de la búsqueda son ensayos clínicos aleatorios, estudios cohortes y estudios de casos que fueron publicados desde 1996 hasta 2010. Los documentos seleccionados fueron clasificados según los grados de recomendación de la sociedad finlandesa DUODECIM. La calidad metodológica de los dieciséis ensayos seleccionados se evaluó usando la lista Delphi. Resultados. Dos documentos primarios mostraron cambios clínicos en el cuestionario de calidad de vida específico para enfermos respiratorios. Las personas que realizaron ejercicio incremental en el agua presentaron cambios funcionales en la distancia recorrida en la prueba de test de marcha, en la capacidad vital forzada y en el volumen espiratorio forzado. La intervención acuática terapéutica que se recomienda es a una intensidad del 50 al 90% del VO2max, con una frecuencia de dos a cinco días a la semana, con sesiones de 30 a 50 minutos, durante un período de tratamiento desde 8 a 24 semanas de duración y una variabilidad de la temperatura del agua desde 29°C hasta 38°C. En futuros estudios sería posible hacer subgrupos de los pacientes en función de sus condiciones físicas de partida para mejorar los resultados de la intervención(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);45(4): 335-343, oct.-dic.2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91527</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad de la hidroterapia en las personas con enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7028^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7028^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
