<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153591</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Trait Anxiety and State Anxiety in Manager and Clinical Nurses in the Autonomous Community of Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: to analyze the level of anxiety among nurses in the Healthcare System of Madrid, to determine if there are differences between State Anxiety and Trait Anxiety between manager and clinical nurses, and to detect the influence of socio-occupational factors on anxiety. Method: a transversal descriptive study conducted with nursing professionals with clinical and management performance, in the public hospitals of the Healthcare System of Madrid. The State-Trait Anxiety Inventory by Spielberger was used as a tool to measure anxiety. The rates of descriptive statistics and bivariate analysis were calculated through Student&#146;s T test or Mann-Whitney&#146;s U Test. Results: the study included 184 nurses; 96 of them worked inpatient care, and 88 were managers. No statistically significant differences were observed for State Anxiety, while a significant difference (p= 0.018) was found for Trait Anxiety, which was lower in manager nurses. Conclusions: state and Trait Anxiety in hospital nurses from the Healthcare System of Madrid is lower than the mean level among the Spanish population; besides, the Trait Anxiety in manager nurses is significantly lower than that of Clinical Nurses, which could indicate a higher tolerability and resistance to stress among this group (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Colomer Sánchez, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera Peco, Iván</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayuso Murillo, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: analizar el nivel de ansiedad en las enfermeras del Servicio Madrileño de Salud, determinar si existen diferencias en cuanto a la ansiedad-estado y ansiedad rasgo entre enfermeras gestoras y clínicas, y detectar la influencia de factores sociolaborales en la ansiedad. Método: estudio descriptivo transversal realizado en profesionales de Enfermería con desempeño clínico y de gestión, en los hospitales públicos del Servicio Madrileño de Salud. Como herramienta para medir la ansiedad se utilizó el State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI) de Spielberger. Se calcularon índices de estadística descriptiva y análisis bivariante mediante la prueba T de Student o la prueba U de Mann-Whitney. Resultados: fueron estudiadas 184 enfermeras de las cuales 96eran asistenciales y 88 eran gestoras. No se observaron diferencias estadísticamente significativas para la ansiedad estado, mientras que para la ansiedad rasgo se encontró una diferencia significativa (p= 0,018), siendo menor en los enfermeros gestores. Conclusiones: la ansiedad estado y rasgo en las enfermeras/os hospitalarias del Servicio Madrileño de Salud es inferior a la media poblacional española; además la ansiedad rasgo de las enfermeras gestoras es menor significativamente que la de las enfermeras clínicas, lo que podría indicar una mayor tolerancia y resistencia al estrés en este grupo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;19(3): 21-26, abr. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153591</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ansiedad rasgo y ansiedad estado en enfermeras gestoras y clínicas de la Comunidad de Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17193^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9912^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
