<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101084</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Regression in the psychoanalytic process</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Regression is inherent to every analytic process which is well constituted. Here, the author presents a theoretical development concerning regression as well as the clinical case of an adult patient. In the theoretic part a parallelism is established between the evolution of the theory of regression and the different moments that occur within the regressive movement. In each of these moments we can detect different positions of the patients and analyst. A special disposition is required form the analyst to pilot the regression towards progression. In the clinical case presented various psychopathological elements are enhanced, transgenerational, guilt feelings, inadequate management of aggression and the tendency towards submission. Under these circumstances, the separation in relation to the lover, as well as a brief interruption of the analytic treatment generated intense feelings of lost and narcissistic wounds, stimulating a regressive process characterized predominantly by depression with melancholic elements. The analysis and interpretation of the transgenerational psychopathology as well as the pathological identification induced together with other identifications bond to the oedipal complex, made possible the modification of the psychic organization of the patient. On the other hand, the analysis and interpretation of transference and of relationship established between the psychic instances determined the evolution of the depressive clinic towards its resolution. By this way, a work of rebinding of the impulses could be done, that enabled a solution to the regressive process transforming what could have been a malignant regression into a regression at the service of the cure (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lara Cabeza, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La regresión es inherente a todo proceso analítico bien constituido. Se presenta un desarrollo teórico sobre la regresión y el caso clínico de una paciente adulta. En la parte teórica, se establece un paralelismo entre los desarrollos en la teoría que se han ido sucediendo en el tiempo, y los diferentes momentos que se establecen dentro del movimiento regresivo. En cada uno de esos momentos se pueden detectar posiciones diferentes por parte del analizando y del analista. Se requiere una especial disposición del analista para conducir la regresión al destino final de la progresión. Resultado final que siempre debe tener su expresión en el trabajo de la simbolización, gracias a la función interpretante. Como consecuencia del mismo, se amplía la capacidad de autointerpretación del mundo psíquico del sujeto. En el caso clínico que se presenta destacan elementos psicopatológicos trangeneracionales, intensos sentimientos de culpa, inadecuado manejo de la agresividad y tendencia al sometimiento. Bajo estas circunstancias, la separación, en la relación con su amante, y una breve interrupción del tratamiento psicoanalítico generaron intensos sentimientos de pérdida y de herida narcisista, estimulándose un proceso regresivo caracterizado preferentemente por depresión con rasgos melancólicos. El análisis e interpretación de la psicopatología transfenaracional, junto con las identificaciones patológicas que había inducido, añadidas a otras identificaciones ligadas al conflicto edípico, posibilitaron la modificación de la organización psíquica de la paciente. De otro lado, el análisis e interpretación de la transferencia y de la relación establecida entre las instancias psíquicas determinaron la evolución de la clínica depresiva hacia su resolución. De esta manera, se pudo hacer un trabajo de religazón pulsional que permitió resolver el proceso regresivo transformando lo que puede ser una regresión maligna en una regresión al servicio de la cura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(62): 192-206, jun. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101084</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Depresión, regression y funcionamiento límite</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12012^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12465</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9484</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
