<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77661</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of two proposals based on clinical factors for selecting what male patients with rheumatoid arthritis should undergo a bone densitometry</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Criteria based on age, inflammation, and immobility have been proposed to identify which patients with rheumatoid arthritis (RA) should be examined by dual energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA) to diagnose osteoporosis. Recently, a modified version of the criteria by including weight and the use of corticosteroids has been proposed. These two set of criteria have not been tested in male patients in a clinical setting. Objective: To analyse, in a group of patients followed in a teaching hospital, the value of two proposals to select men with RA for bone densitometry. Patients and method: Clinical and demographic data were collected from the charts of a total of 65 men with RA, submitted to the bone densitometry unit during a fouryear period. Bone mineral density (BMD) was measured in spine and femoral neck by DXA. Two set of criteria were tested: a) three item criteria (age, inflammation and immobility), and b) five item criteria (age, inflammation, immobility, weight, and ever use of corticosteroids). Sensitivity, specificity, positive predictive value (PPV) and negative predictive value (NPV) were calculated Results: Thirty five (54%) patients fulfilled the three item criteria and 38 (59%) the five item criteria. For the diagnosis of osteoporosis using the three item criteria, the sensitivity was 62%, specificity 48%, PPV 23% and NPV 83%; using the 5 item criteria the sensitivity was 90%, specificity 47%, PPV 23%, and NPV 96%. Conclusions: The five item criteria are a more accurate tool to identify, in clinical practice, male patients with RA and osteoporosis than the three item criteria. It seems a good screening method for the selection of those patients with RA whose BMD should be assessed, as the sensitivity and NPV seem acceptable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nolla, Joan M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rozadilla, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Aguilà, Dolors</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Vaquero, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romera, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Narváez, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En 1998, se propusieron unos criterios basados en la edad, la actividad de la enfermedad y el grado de inmovilidad para seleccionar a pacientes con artritis reumatoide (AR) tributarios de la realización de una densitometría. Con posterioridad, se ha postulado una versión modificada en la que se incluye, además, el peso y la toma de glucocorticoides. Hasta la actualidad no se ha comprobado su valor en pacientes varones en un contexto asistencial. Objetivo: Analizar la utilidad de ambas propuestas en un grupo de varones con AR controlados de forma habitual en un hospital universitario. Pacientes y método: Se incluyó a 65 varones con AR remitidos a la unidad de densitometría durante un período de 4 años. Mediante la revisión de las historias clínicas, se obtuvieron los datos clínicos y demográficos necesarios para llevar a cabo el estudio. La densidad mineral ósea en columna lumbar y en cuello femoral se evaluaron por absorciometría fotónica dual de fuente radiológica. Se calcularon la sensibilidad, la especificidad, el valor predictivo positivo (VPP) y el valor predictivo negativo (VPN) de la propuesta de 3 ítems (edad, inflamación e inmovilidad) y de la propuesta de 5 ítems (edad, inflamación, inmovilidad, peso y tratamiento con glucocorticoides). Resultados: Del total, 32 (54%) pacientes cumplían los requisitos de la propuesta de 3 ítems y 38 (59%), los de la propuesta de 5 ítems. Para el diagnóstico de osteoporosis, con la propuesta de 3 ítems la sensibilidad fue del 62%; la especificidad, del 48%; el VPP, del 23%, y el VPN, del 83%, mientras que con la propuesta de 5 ítems fueron del 90, el 47, el 23 y el 96%, respectivamente. Conclusiones: La propuesta de 5 ítems resulta más útil en la práctica asistencial que la propuesta de 3 ítems para decidir a qué varones con AR se practica una densitometría. La propuesta de 5 ítems puede ser un buen método de cribado, ya que los valores obtenidos en cuanto a sensibilidad y VPN parecen aceptables (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);3(2): 63-66, mar.-abr. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77661</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de dos propuestas basadas en factores clínicos para seleccionar a qué varones con artritis reumatoide debe realizarse una densitometría ósea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6082^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3732^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1178^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
