<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-28605</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-6585</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Are there relation between cardiovascular disease and periodontitis?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The infectious theory to explain atherosclerosis has allowed researchers to advance quickly on the knowledge about pathogenia of cardiovascular disease. Even more, the concept of coronary disease as an inflammatory disease has developed new pathways for investigating the ischaemic cardiac.  Recent investigations suggest that the use of inflammatory markers may help for early detecting patients who present high risk of cardiovascular strokes appearance.  Also, epidemiological essays have revealed that periodontitis is a risk factor for cardiovascular disease to develop. Periodontitis is a source of bacterias or their wastes, and provoke a hyperinflammatory response on the hostage, liberating cytokines for long periods.  Due to chronicity of both cardiovascular and periodontal disease, they may have some similar ethilogycal ways (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ediciones Avances, S.L.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hipótesis infecciosa de la aterosclerosis ha permitido un rápido avance en el conocimiento sobre los mecanismos patogénicos de la enfermedad coronaria. Más aun, el concepto de la enfermedad coronaria como una enfermedad inflamatoria ha abierto nuevos caminos para la investigación en el campo de la cardiopatía isquémica. Estudios recientes han sugerido que el empleo de marcadores de inflamación ayudaría en la identificación de pacientes con alto riesgo de padecer eventos cardiovasculares. También los estudios epidemiológicos han implicado a la periodontitis como un factor de riesgo para el desarrollo de la enfermedad cardiovascular. La enfermedad periodontal proporciona una fuente de bacterias o de sus productos, y citoquinas de respuesta hiperinflamatoria del huésped por largos periodos de tiempo. Dada la cronicidad de la enfermedad cardiovascular y de la enfermedad periodontal probablemente comparten algunos caminos de común etiología (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. periodoncia implantol. oral;15(3): 113-119, dic. 2003. tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Existe relación entre enfermedad cardiovascular Y periodontitis?</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Sicilia Felechosa, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejerina Lobo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Menéndez Collar, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuesta Frechoso, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-28605</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50504^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10709^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
