<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115079</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Two cases of systemic mastocytosis with a lymphoma-like presentation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Mastocytosis is a group of clonal neoplastic disorders characterized by tissue proliferation of mastocytes morphologically and/or molecularly abnormal, being systemic when it has extracutaneous location. The clinical picture is variable and nonspecific. Cases have been described associated to other hematological neoplasms, especially those of myeloid and, to a lesser extent, lymphoid type. We present two cases of systemic mastocytosis involving bone marrow, lymph nodes and skin in elderly female patients which were initially diagnosed clinically as lymphoma. However, an abnormal proliferation in cumulus of mastocytes was identificated histologically using Giemsa and confirmed by CD117, CD25 and CD45. One of the patients had a rapid, unfavorable clinical evolution(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Piras, María A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Massarelli, Giovannino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fermín-Santana, Ileana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lissia, Amelia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lubo-Julio, Idania</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las mastocitosis son un grupo de trastornos neoplásicos clonales caracterizados por proliferación tisular de mastocitos morfológica y/o molecularmente anormales; son sistémicas cuando tienen localización extracutánea. El cuadro clínico es variable e inespecífico. Se han descrito casos asociados a otras neoplasias hematológicas, especialmente las de tipo mieloide y, en menor medida, linfoide. En la presente revisión informamos los casos de 2 mujeres en la sexta y séptima décadas de la vida con mastocitosis sistémica que involucraba la médula ósea, el ganglio linfático y la piel, con diagnóstico clínico inicial de linfoma en el que tras la reevaluación histológica con la coloración de Giemsa se identificaron mastocitos, agregados en acúmulos, morfológicamente anormales que fueron confirmados mediante la positividad para CD117, CD25 y CD45. Uno de los casos presentó una evolución clínica rápidamente desfavorable(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;46(3): 191-194, jul.-sept. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115079</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mastocitosis sistémica: comunicación de 2 casos con presentación clínica semejante a linfoma</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32639</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37263^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37263^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37263^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52346^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
