<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149820</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Health related quality of life [HRQOL] in childhood and adolescence: a review of the literature and instruments adapted in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aims of this study were to systematically review the availability and characteristics of generic instruments of health-related quality of life (HRQOL) for use in childhood and adolescence published in the literature, and to revise generic or disease-specific measures adapted or developed for use in Spain. Questionnaires were selected if they had been developed specifically for use in children and/or adolescents. The data bases consulted were Medline, HealthSTAR and PsycLIT (1980-August 2001). Combinations of key words were used with no restriction on language. The main characteristics analyzed were the content and psychometric properties of the questionnaires retrieved. For instruments adapted for use in Spain, the quality of the adaptation process was also reviewed. Fifteen generic HRQOL instruments for use in children and adolescents were found. The measures were designed for the age range 4-18 years. The number and content of domains, and the number of items included in each measure varied greatly. Test-retest reliability was analyzed in half of the instruments, and all authors analyzed at least one aspect of validity. Two generic and five specific instruments have been developed or adapted in Spain. The adaptation process was generally acceptable. Sensitivity to change has been assessed only in two of the instruments analyzed (one generic and one specific). HRQOL measurement in children and adolescents is in initial stages. The next step will be to investigate the utility of these measures in clinical practice and public health (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Serra-Sutton, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rajmil, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herdman, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estrada, MD</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los objetivos del presente trabajo fueron revisar de forma sistemática los instrumentos genéricos de calidad de vida relacionada con la salud (CVRS) en la infancia y adolescencia publicados en la bibliografía, y aquellos, ya sean genéricos o específicos, que han sido adaptados o creados en España. Se consideraron los cuestionarios que presentaban versiones infantiles y/o para adolescentes. Las bases de datos consultadas fueron Medline, HealthSTAR y PsycLIT (1980-agosto 2001). La estrategia combinó diferentes palabras clave sin exclusión de ningún idioma. Las principales características analizadas fueron el contenido de los instrumentos y sus propiedades psicométricas. En el caso de los instrumentos adaptados en España, se analizó, además, la calidad del proceso de adaptación. Se localizaron y analizaron 15 instrumentos genéricos de CVRS. El rango de edades de los instrumentos genéricos es de 4-18 años. Existe gran variabilidad en el número y características de las dimensiones y en el número de ítems. La mitad de los instrumentos ha evaluado la fiabilidad test-retest. Todos los autores han analizado al menos un tipo de validez. Dos genéricos y cinco específicos han sido creados o adaptados en España. El proceso de adaptación ha sido, en general, aceptable. De todos los instrumentos analizados, sólo dos (uno genérico y otro específico) han evaluado la sensibilidad a los cambios. Las medidas de la CVRS en niños y adolescentes se encuentran en fase inicial de desarrollo. En los próximos años se espera la evaluación de su utilidad en la práctica clínica y en salud pública (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;15(supl.4): 34-43, dic. 2001. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149820</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida relacionada con la salud (CVRS) en la infancia y la adolescencia: revisión de la bibliografía y de los instrumentos adaptados en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28417</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
