<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045648</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Magnetic resonance imaging with spectroscopy, perfusion and cerebral diffusion in the diagnosis of brain tumours</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. We review three of the most important functional techniques in magnetic resonance imaging, it means spectroscopy,perfusion and diffusion; we do emphasize in its applications, particularly in the diagnostic and treatment of braintumors. First, we discuss the physical principles and results interpretation of each technique. After that, we discuss its majorapplications. Development and conclusions. Choline containing compounds using contralateral creatine and choline fornormalization or ipsilateral N-acetyl-aspartate appeared to correlate best with the degree of tumor infiltration, regardless otumor histological grade. Magnetic resonance spectroscopy imaging (MRSI) seems more accurate than conventional magneticresonance imaging (MRI) in defining indistinct tumor boundaries and quantifying the degree of tumor infiltration. MRSI is thechoice of site within a lesion for biopsy and use in image-guided therapy, including definition of radiation ports. Angiogenesis,and increased vascular permeability, are characteristic of cerebral neoplasms; these processes can be imaged using perfusionMRI. Most commonly, tumor perfusion is measured using rapid gradient T2-weighted imaging during bolus injection ofgadolinium dimeglumine gadopentetate. Care has to be taken to avoid blood-brain barrier leakage affecting perfusion results.Pharmacokinetic models are available for estimation of blood-brain permeability. Cerebral blood volume increases withtumor grade, and maybe helpful in identifying tumor recurrence, and peri-tumoral edema, and distinguishing malignant frombenign lesions</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Modrego-Pardo, P. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales-Ramos, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fayed-Miguel, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Se revisan las técnicas de espectroscopia, perfusióny difusión por resonancia magnética (RM), haciendo particularénfasis en sus aplicaciones para el diagnóstico y tratamientode los tumores cerebrales. Se discuten los principios físicos de cadatécnica y el significado e interpretación de sus resultados, dejandoen última instancia sus principales aplicaciones. Desarrolloy conclusiones. Las lesiones que contienen colina relacionadas conla creatina y con la colina del hemisferio contralateral, así como elN-acetil-aspartato ipsilateral, tienen buena correlación con el gradode infiltración o grado histológico tumoral. La espectroscopiapor RM es más precisa que la RM convencional para definir losmárgenes tumorales y cuantificar el grado de infiltración tumoral.La espectroscopia por RM está indicada para seleccionar el lugardonde se debe realizar la biopsia o biopsia estereotáxica, así comopara definir la zona a irradiar. La angiogénesis y el incremento dela permeabilidad vascular son característicos de las neoplasiascerebrales; esto se puede reproducir con la utilización de la perfusiónpor RM. Habitualmente, la perfusión tumoral se mide usandoimágenes rápidas en gradiente T2 durante el paso de un bolo decontraste paramagnético intravenoso. Los resultados pueden verseafectados si existe una ruptura de la barrera hematoencefálica.Pueden utilizarse modelos farmacocinéticos para estimar la permeabilidadde la barrera. El volumen sanguíneo cerebral se incrementacon el grado tumoral, pudiendo servir de ayuda para identificarrecidivas tumorales o el edema perilesional y diferenciar lesionesmalignas de benignas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;42(12): 735-742, jun. 2006. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045648</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resonancia magnética con espectroscopia, perfusión y difusión cerebral en el diagnóstico de los tumores cerebrales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1958^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37550^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
