<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123122</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Longitudinal assessment of body composition by different methods as product of a integral intervention for treating obesity in Chilean children school</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: In Chile, the main nutritional problem of children, is obesity. The alarming increase in childhood obesity, has generated an urgent need to develop prevention and treatment programs, unfortunately, the results have been disappointing because they have not achieved the expected impact on the nutritional status of the target population. For this it is necessary to use other strategies, such as incorporating exercise of muscle strength. Objective: To determine the impact of an integral intervention (exercise, nutritional education and psychological support) in the body composition of obese school children after the intervention and post-intervention. Methods: The sample consisted of 61 obese children (BMI &gt; p 95) of both sex, between 8 and 13 years old, who participated in an integral intervention for treating childhood obesity in the short term (3 months) and medium term (12 months). Body composition was assessed by isotope dilution, plethysmography, radiographic absorptiometry and four-compartment model of Fuller. Results: There was a significant increase over time in FFM (kg) by 4C in both sex, GC (%) by isotope dilution in boys was reduced in the post-intervention, while in girls decreased significantly over time and FFM (kg) by isotope dilution significantly increased in both sex. According to the magnitude and direction of change in time, there was only significant difference by sex in FFM (%) by isotope dilution, the increase was significantly higher in boys a result of the intervention (p = 0,000). Conclusions: An intervention that includes programmed exercise improves body composition. However, its effect is reversed in the medium term if training ceases. This reaffirms the need for sustainability of interventions over time (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Burrows, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diaz, Erik</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vásquez, Loretta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vásquez, Fabián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lera, Lydia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Anziani, Alyerina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leyton, Bárbara</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En Chile, el principal problema nutricional de la población infantil, lo constituye la obesidad. El alarmante incremento de la obesidad infantil, ha generado la imperiosa necesidad de desarrollar programas de prevención y tratamiento, pero los resultados han sido poco alentadores ya que no han logrado el impacto esperado en el estado nutricional de la población objetivo. Para lo cual es necesario utilizar otras estrategias, como la incorporación del ejercicio físico de fuerza muscular. Objetivo: Determinar el impacto de una intervención integral (ejercicio físico, educación alimentaria y apoyo psicológico) en la composición corporal de escolares obesos al finalizar la intervención y en la post-intervención. Métodos: La muestra fue de 61 niños obesos (IMC &gt; p 95) de ambos sexos, entre 8 y 13 años, que participaron en una intervención integral para tratar la obesidad infantil a corto plazo (3 meses) y mediano plazo (12 meses). Se evaluó la composición corporal por dilución isotópica, pletismografía, absorciometría radiográfica y el modelo de cuatro compartimentos de Fuller. Resultados: En ambos sexos se produjo un incremento significativo en el tiempo en MLG (kg) por 4C, en GC (%) por dilución isotópica en niños se redujo en la post-intervención, mientras en las niñas disminuyó significativamente en el tiempo y en MLG (kg) por dilución isotópica aumentó significativamente en ambos sexos. En relación a la magnitud y dirección de los cambios en el tiempo, sólo hubo diferencia significativa por sexo en MLG (%) por dilución isotópica, el incremento fue significativamente mayor en niños, como producto de la intervención (p=0,000). Conclusiones: Una intervención que incluye ejercicio físico programado mejora la composición corporal, pero su efecto se revierte a mediano plazo si el entrenamiento cesa. Lo anterior, reafirma la necesidad de la sostenibilidad de las intervenciones en el tiempo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;28(1): 148-154, ene.-feb. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123122</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación longitudinal de la composición corporal por diferentes métodos como producto de una intervención integral para tratar la obesidad en escolares chilenos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d20182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
