<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045375</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1473</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Related factors with the failed surgery of herniated lumbar disc</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The surgery for herniated disc is the most common operation at the level of the lumbar spine. The failed surgery rates range between 10% and 40%, conforming what is known as Failed Back Surgery Syndrome (FBSS). Return to work after surgery occurs in 70-85% of the cases. There are a few studies analysing the quality of life after the operation. The aims of this study are to know the incidence of the herniated disc lumbar failed surgery in our area, identify those factors influencing its development, and study behavioural parameters as the return to work and the quality of life at a middle term after surgery, also its relation with the success or failure surgery. Material and methods. A descriptive transversal study of 117 patients operated for herniated lumbar disc during the first six months of the year 2003 is reported. In order to evaluate the incidence of failed surgery and the related factors, the clinical records were retrospectively analyzed. Ninety one patients were interviewed by phone using the Health Questionnaire SF-36, in order to analyze the non clinical factors related to FBSS, such as labour reincorporation, satisfaction with surgery, realization of rehabilitation treatment and quality of life after surgery. For the statistical analysis of the results, we used the program SPSS 11.01. Results. In a sample in which the proportion between both sexes was 1/1, and the middle age was over 45 years [35-54], in which the most frequent clinical symptom was right sciatica, lasting more than 6 months, correlated to disc herniation at L5-S1 level, 37'9% of the patients presented FBSS. Although there were a few patients with reoperation in our study, the incidence of FBSS in these patients was higher (52,9%) than in patients who suffered this surgery for first time (32%). The predictive clinical factors of an unfavourable result in patients operated on for first time were bilateral sciatica, the presence of stenosis associated to herniated disc and comorbidity factors. On the other hand the socio-labor factors identified were a low culture level and those working as drivers, building and service sectors. Return to work occurred in the 64% of the active workers before surgery. Only around 10% of patients were dissatisfied with surgical result and there was a significant relationship between this and the physical function, pain, vitality and emotional status in the SF-36 with the FBSS. Conclusions. One out of three patients operated of herniated lumbar disc in our area presented failed disc surgery and the return to work occurred in 2 out of three patients active before the operation. The failed surgery patient suffers from pain, that interferes and limits the labor and home activities. Furthermore, the patient presents frequent sensation of fatigue and exhaustion and also emotional problems that contribute to interfere with work and activities of the daily life (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez-Campos, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echevarría-Ruiz de Vargas, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-García, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Expósito-Tirado, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Gastaldo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez-Sousa, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cantador-Hornero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cayuela-Domínguez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La cirugía descompresiva de herniadiscal es la intervención quirúrgica más frecuente a nivel de la columna lumbar. La cirugía fallida oscila entre un 10 y un 40% de los casos, constituyendo el denominado Síndrome de la Cirugía Raquídea Fracasada (SCRF). La reincorporación laboral a medio plazo tras la cirugía se sitúa en torno al 70-85%, y existen pocos estudios que analicen la calidad de vida tras la intervención. Los objetivos de este estudio son conocerla incidencia de cirugía fallida de hernia discal lumbar en nuestro medio, identificando aquellos factores que puedan influir en su aparición; y estudiar factores ambientales como la reincorporación laboral y la calidad de vida a medio plazo tras esta cirugía, así como su relación con el éxito o fracaso quirúrgico. Material y métodos. Estudio descriptivo transversal de 117 pacientes intervenidos de hernia discal lumbar durante el primer semestre del 2003 en nuestro hospital. Para valorar la incidencia de cirugía fallida y factores relacionados se han recogido datos clínicos de la Historia Clínica de los pacientes de la muestra. Y, asimismo, se ha entrevistado telefónicamente a 91 de ellos -los que contestaron- para valorar factores no clínicos relacionados con el SCRF, tales como reincorporación laboral, satisfacción con la cirugía, realización de tratamiento rehabilitador y calidad de vida a través del Cuestionario de Salud SF-36. Para el análisis de resultados se ha empleado el programa estadístico SPSS 11.01. Resultados. En una muestra en la que la proporción ente ambos sexos es de 1/1 y la edad media de 45 [35-54]años, con una clínica más frecuente de ciática derecha, de más de 6 meses de evolución, correlacionada con el hallazgo radiológico de hernia L5-S1, un 37,9% ha presentado el SCRF. Aunque es escaso el número de pacientes que en nuestra serie afrontan una reintervención, se ha observado en ellos una incidencia del SCRF notablemente superior (52,2%) a los que se someten a una primera cirugía (32%). Los factores clínicos predictivos de resultados desfavorables en pacientes sometidos a primera cirugía han sido la clínica precirugía de ciática bilateral, el hallazgo de estenosis de canal asociada a hernia discal y la comorbilidad; mientras que los sociolaborales han sido pacientes sin estudios y aquellos que trabajan en los sectores de la conducción, construcción y hostelería. La reincorporación laboral se produjo en el 64 % de los trabajadores activos previamente. Sólo entorno al 10% se encuentran insatisfechos con la opción quirúrgica, relacionándose significativamente tanto estocomo las dimensiones de función física, dolor, vitalidad y rol emocional en el SF-36 con el SCRF. Conclusiones. Uno de cada 3 pacientes intervenidos de hernia discal lumbar en nuestro medio presenta cirugía fallida, reincorporándose laboralmente 2 de cada 3pacientes previamente activos. El paciente con cirugía fallida se encuentra afectado por dolor, hasta el punto de repercutir y limitar las actividades del hogar y las laborales. Además presenta frecuentemente sensación de cansancio o agotamiento, y problemas emocionales que interfieren tanto en las actividades de la vida diaria como en el trabajo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurocirugia (Astur);16(6): 507-517, dic. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045375</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores relacionados con la cirugía fallida de hernia discal lumbar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8334^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33888</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12508</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8334^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7568^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7568^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7568^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
