<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159415</identifier>
<setSpec>2173-9218</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pharmaceutical counselling for back pain in patients with diabetes or hypertension in community pharmacy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Lumbar pain is a frequent reason for consultation in the pharmacy, so the pharmaceutical indication must be based on scientific criteria that contribute to solve it, without the control of the blood pressure or blood sugar figures can be altered in the case of patients with hypertension or diabetes. Through a systematic review of Clinical Practice Guidelines (CPG) aimed at addressing back pain, as well as other literature sources, recommendations have been made on minor ailment scheme for patients with diabetes and/or hypertension who come to the office of Pharmacy requesting pharmacological treatment for said symptom. After designing a search strategy, the selection of the bibliographic sources was carried out and the collection of information was carried out. The literature search was conducted in the following web storage resources or GPC search: Medline, GuíaSalud, National Guideline Clearinghouse, CMA Infobase, Scottish Intercollegiate Guidelines Network, Australia&#146;s Clinical Practice Guidelines Portal, Trip Database and National Health Service Evidence. As additional sources, were consulted of UpToDate, Database BOT plus 2.0 and a treaty of Human Pharmacology. Specific recommendations on drug treatment were formulated taking into account their level of evidence and possible interactions and contraindications of drugs in patients with hypertension and/or diabetes mellitus. Likewise, performance algorithm were built, following Good Practices in Community Pharmacy in Spain of General Council of Official Colleges of Pharmacists. The recommendations refer to the management of non-specific low-back pain and generally include, as a first-line treatment due to its better risk / benefit profile, the use of paracetamol in acute or subacute low back pain in isolation and of musculoskeletal origin, without exceeding 3 or 4 g / day (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carbajal de Lara, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Torres Hidalgo, Mª Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Torres López, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El dolor lumbar constituye un motivo muy frecuente de consulta en la farmacia, por lo que la indicación farmacéutica debe estar basada en criterios científicos que contribuyan a resolverlo, sin que el control de las cifras de presión arterial o de glucemia pueda verse alterado en el caso de pacientes con hipertensión arterial o diabetes. Mediante una revisión sistemática de Guías de Práctica Clínica (GPC) dirigidas al abordaje del dolor lumbar, así como de otras fuentes bibliográficas, se han elaborado recomendaciones sobre indicación farmacéutica a pacientes con diabetes y/o hipertensión arterial que acuden a la oficina de farmacia solicitando tratamiento farmacológico para dicho síntoma. Tras diseñar una estrategia de búsqueda, se realizó la selección de las fuentes bibliográficas y se llevó a cabo la recogida de información. La búsqueda bibliográfica se realizó en los siguientes recursos web de almacenamiento o búsqueda de GPC: Medline, GuíaSalud, National Guideline Clearinghouse, CMA Infobase, Scottish Intercollegiate Guidelines Network, Australia&#146;s Clinical Practice Guidelines Portal, Trip Database y National Health Service Evidence. Como fuentes complementarias, se consultó UpToDate, Base de Datos BOT plus 2.0 y un tratado de Farmacología Humana. Las recomendaciones específicas sobre tratamiento farmacológico fueron formuladas teniendo en cuenta su nivel de evidencia y se revisaron las posibles interacciones y/o contraindicaciones de los fármacos en los pacientes con hipertensión arterial y/o diabetes mellitus. Así mismo, se construyó un algoritmo de actuación, siguiendo las Buenas Prácticas en Farmacia Comunitaria en España elaboradas por el Consejo General de Colegios Oficiales de Farmacéuticos. Las recomendaciones se refieren al manejo del dolor lumbar inespecífico e incluyen por lo general, como tratamiento de primera línea por su mejor perfil riesgo/beneficio, el uso de paracetamol en el dolor lumbar agudo o subagudo de forma aislada y de origen musculoesquelético, sin sobrepasar 3 ó 4 g/día (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm. comunitarios (Internet);8(4): 34-41, dic. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159415</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Indicación farmacéutica para el dolor lumbar en pacientes con diabetes y/o hipertensión arterial que acuden a la farmacia comunitaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51728^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4424^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4424^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4424^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4424^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51728^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3008^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3008^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
