<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105054</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Rescue of a pedicled trapezious muscle flap with skin paddle in a patient with spinal cord injury who needded inmediate rehabilitation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Negative pressure therapy (subatmospheric) is a non invasive treatment modality included in the armamentarium of any Service of Plastic Surgery and also in General Surgery, Vascular Surgery and Traumatology Services. It can be applied in the treatment of both chronic and acute wounds to decrease the time and number of priests and also to reduce surgeries with high morbidity for the patient. We present a patient with depressive syndrome secondary to an unfortunate postoperative course of a vertebroplasty that produced an spinal cord injury, classified as ASIA C, level D4. The patient suffered a high dorsal ulcer with 6 months of complicated evolution which finally was covered with a pedicled trapezious flap with skin paddle and, again iatrogenicaly, suffered a partial loss of the paddle and a significant seroma at the donor site. In our opinion, this case is interesting because the use of negative pressure therapy with VAC® system allows: 1) Minimize the loss of flap tissue. 2) To decrease the number of cures. 3) To decrease the time  in each healing. 4) Allows the patient to move in his wheelchair with two portable VAC® systems to assist to the gym and follow his rehabilitation program. 5) With this unexpected and fast evolution, the patient had a significant clinical improvement of his depressive-anxious state and 6) The final placement of a latest generation VAC-VIA® systems on autografts allowed the patient to go on with his occupational therapy and physiotherapy for the upper extremities. We think that VAC-VIA® therapy is completely indicated to complex acute and chronic wounds because it can save time in terms of total hospital stance and avoid unnecessary surgeries with high risk morbidity for the patien (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arévalo Velasco, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín Martín, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espino Rodríguez, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juan García, J. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barriga Martín, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La terapia por presión negativa (subatmosférica) es una modalidad no invasiva de tratamiento que hoy en día está incluida en el arsenal terapéutico de cualquier Servicio no sólo de Cirugía Plástica, sino también de Cirugía General, Cirugía Vascular y Traumatología. Se puede aplicar en el tratamiento de heridas tanto crónicas como agudas más o menos complejas, con el fin de evitar aumentar el tiempo y el número de curas necesarias y además el realizar cirugías que conlleven una elevada morbilidad para el paciente. Presentamos el caso de un paciente con cuadro depresivo secundario a la mala evolución clínica sufrida tras el desarrollo de una lesión medular transversa D4 ASIA C (incompleta) de causa iatrogénica postquirúrgica( vertebroplastia-fusión vertebral por aplastamiento vertebral D3-D4), en el que tras más de 6 meses de evolución tórpida de una úlcera dorsal alta, se realizó un colgajo de músculo trapecio pediculado con paleta cutánea para cobertura del defecto, en cuyo postoperatorio inmediato sufrió, de nuevo iatrogénicamente, una pérdida parcial de dicha paleta y un seroma importante en la zona dadora. Consideramos de interés este caso porque la aplicación de terapia depresión negativa empleando el sistema VAC® nos permitió: 1) Minimizarla pérdida de tejido del colgajo. 2) Disminuir el número de curas semanales hasta 1 ó 2. 3) Disminuir también el tiempo empleado en cada cura.4) Que el paciente pudiera desplazarse en su silla de ruedas con dos sistemas VAC® portátiles hasta el gimnasio para no abandonar su programa de rehabilitación. 5) Que ante una evolución rápida e inesperada, el paciente experimentara una notable mejoría clínica de su estado depresivo-ansioso y 6) La colocación final de un sistema VAC-VIA® de última generación sobre los autoinjertos, para que el paciente pudiera continuar su (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;37(supl.1): s25-s29, dic. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105054</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rescate de colgajo muscular de trapecio con isla cutánea en paciente lesionado medular que precisa rehabilitación inmediata</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54250^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53846^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13502^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
