<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043492</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatmetn of oropharyngeal mycosis with a single dose of fluconazole. A descriptive analysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: oropharyngeal candidiasis is a frequent infection inpatients receiving palliative care for advanced cancer. Most common treatmentsinclude oral nystatin and fluconazole for one or two weeks. It hasbeen suggested that a single dose of fluconazole may also be effective,which would mean an easier dosage and lower costs.Objectives: to describe our department's experience with the the useof single doses (150 mg) of fluconazole in advanced cancer patients. Toestablish the prevalence of oropharyngeal candidiasis, and to find potentiallyrelated factors.Methods: all advanced cancer patients followed by a home palliativecare team during 2002 were retrospectively studied. Information on diagnosis,treatment, and treatment effectiveness was obtained from patientfollow-up records.Results: ninety-six of 102 patients were included. Twenty-four ofthem (25%) had at least one episode of oropharyngeal candidiasis. In onecase treatment was considered ineffective because of the development of anew episode in less than 7 days. All patients completed their treatmentappropriately. Use of steroids (p = 0.03) and lymphopenia (p = 0.04) weredetected as factors related to oropharyngeal candidiasis.Conclusions: A single dose of fluconazole (150 mg) seems effective forthe treatment of oropharyngeal candidiasis in advanced cancer patients.Further clinical trials are needed to compare this regimen with othertreatments available. Use of steroids and lymphopenia were recognized asfactors related to oropharyngeal candidiasis in these patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santiago Ruiz, A. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Babarro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boya, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varela Cerdeira, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: la candidiasis orofaríngea es frecuente en pacientes terminales.Los tratamientos habituales son nistatina oral y fluconazol enpautas largas. Se ha sugerido que una pauta con dosis única de fluconazolpodría ser igualmente efectiva, lo cual supondría una mayor comodidadposológica y un menor coste del tratamiento.Objetivos: describir la experiencia de nuestro servicio en el tratamientode la candidiasis orofaríngea en pacientes con enfermedad oncológicaavanzada con una dosis única de 150 mg de fluconazol. Analizar la frecuenciay posibles factores asociados con la aparición de candidiasis orofaríngeaen estos pacientes.Método: se estudiaron retrospectivamente todos los pacientes oncológicosterminales atendidos por un servicio de Cuidados Paliativos Domiciliariodurante el año. Se recogieron datos de la historia clínica sobre eldiagnóstico (según criterios clínicos), tratamiento y eficacia.Resultados: se incluyeron 96 de 102 pacientes. 24 pacientes (25%)tuvieron al menos un episodio de candidiasis orofaríngea. Un caso se considerócomo ineficacia del tratamiento al tener un nuevo episodio enmenos de 7 días. Todos los pacientes cumplieron adecuadamente el tratamiento.Como factores asociados con la aparición de candidiasis orofaríngease detectó el uso de corticoides (p = 0,03) y la linfopenia (p = 0,04).Conclusiones: la dosis única de 150 mg de fluconazol parece eficazpara el tratamiento de la candidiasis orofaríngea en pacientes oncológicosterminales. Se precisan ensayos clínicos que comparen esta pauta conotros tratamientos empleados habitualmente. Los factores asociados conla aparición de candidiasis orofaríngea detectados en nuestro estudio fueronel tratamiento con corticoides y la linfopenia</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;12(4): 204-209, oct.-dic. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043492</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de la micosis orofaríngea con dosis única de fluconazol. Análisis descriptivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2212^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24654^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26452</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33200</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8402^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10138^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
