<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-62807</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of the demand for dermatological care in the immigrant population served by Hospital Miguel Servet in Saragossa, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. In recent years there has been an increase in the size of the immigrant population consulting dermatology services in Spain. The aim of this study was to describe the epidemiological characteristics of this sector of the population in the health care area served by Miguel Servet Hospital in Saragossa, Spain. Material and methods. Data were collected on immigrant patients seen in the dermatology department of our hospital during 2004. Dermatological diagnoses were classified according to the International Classification of Diseases, Ninth Revision, Clinical Modification. Statistical analysis was undertaken using the SPSS statistical package, Access database management software, and Excel spreadsheets. Results. A total of 706 patients were seen, corresponding to approximately 4 % of all first appointments, and more women were seen than men, a difference that was statistically significant. The mean age of the patients was 31 years and there were no statistically significant differences in age between the sexes. In order of frequency, the most common countries of origin of the patients were Ecuador, Colombia, Romania, Morocco, Gambia, Guinea, and Senegal. The most common skin diseases in this population group were infectious diseases, in particular mycoses, followed by viral diseases and pyodermatitis, as well as sexually transmitted diseases. In all cases, the incidence of the disease was higher than in the Spanish population. Conclusions. An appropriate knowledge of dermatological diseases in this population group is necessary both to obtain correct diagnosis and to develop preventative measures for imported diseases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zubiri, ML</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Porta, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Simal, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ara, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Juan, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baldellou, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Se ha observado en los últimos años un aumento en la población inmigrante que acude a nuestras consultas. Pretendemos describir en el presente estudio las características epidemiológicas dermatológicas de este grupo de población en el área de salud del Hospital Miguel Servet de Zaragoza. Material y métodos. Se han recogido los datos de los pacientes inmigrantes atendidos en nuestras consultas de Dermatología durante el año 2004. Los diagnósticos dermatológicos se han codificado según el ICD-9-CM. El estudio estadístico se ha realizado con el programa SPSS, el gestor de base de datos Access y la hoja de cálculo Excel. Resultados. Se han atendido un total de 706 pacientes inmigrantes, lo que supone el 4 % aproximado del total de primeras visitas, apreciándose una mayor frecuencia de mujeres, con diferencias significativas. La edad media es de 31 años, sin que se aprecien diferencias significativas entre ambos sexos. Ecuador, Colombia, Rumanía, Marruecos, Gambia, Guinea y Senegal son por este orden los países de origen que con más frecuencia se han detectado entre nuestros pacientes. Las enfermedades dermatológicas más frecuentes en este grupo de población han sido las de origen infeccioso, sobre todo micosis, siguiendo las de origen viral y las piodermitis así como las enfermedades de transmisión sexual, apreciándose en todas ellas una incidencia superior a la de la población autóctona. Conclusiones. Se hace necesario un adecuado conocimiento de la patología dermatológica en este grupo de población con el fin de realizar tanto un correcto diagnóstico y tratamiento como de desarrollar medidas de prevención de enfermedades importadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;99(2): 127-133, mar. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-62807</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la demanda asistencial de Dermatología en la población inmigrante del área de salud del Hospital Miguel Servet de Zaragoza</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13255^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3900^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4716^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3900^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14563^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
