<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-15504</identifier>
<setSpec>1136-4890</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pattern of neurofilament expression in the developing cochleovestibular ganglia in vivo, and modulation by neurotrophin 3 in vitro</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Neurofilaments are the cytoskeletal intermediate filaments in neurons. They consist of three proteins (NFPs) with estimated molecular masses of 68, 160 and 200 kDa. The expression of NFPs by cells is regarded as a hallmark of neuronal differentiation and evolution. In the present study we analyzed the pattern of NFP expression in the neurons of the chicken cochleo-vestibular ganglion (CVG) during development and early post-hatching stages. We also investigated the expression of NFPs "in vitro" and their regulation by the neurotrophic factor NT3 to assess the participation of NFPs in neurotrophin-induced effects. The occurrence of NFP immunoreactivity (IR) "in vivo" and "in vitro" was studied using both Western-blot and immunohistochemistry on whole mount embryos, tissue sections and primary cultures. The 68 kDa NFP subunit was expressed as from stage E4 to E10, while the 160 kDa NFP subunit was found in all developmental stages and on the early post-hatching days (P10). The 200 kDa NFP subunit was observed at later developmental stages from E10 to P30. The immunoreactivity for each NFP subunit detected in inner ear sections was consistent with the data obtained by immunoblotting. NFPs were localized in the neuronal perikarya and their processes, allowing us to establish the temporal pattern of innervation of the sensory neuroepithelia located in the inner ear. Primary cultures with NT3 reproduced the "in vivo" pattern of NFP expression. The present results demonstrate that NFP subunits are developmentally regulated, suggesting that they may be specifically involved in the maturation of CVG neurons. Furthermore, the findings obtained in cultured neurons point to a regulation of NFP expression by neurotrophin-3 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sociedad Anatómica Española</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los neurofilamentos son los filamentos intermedios citoesqueléticos en las neuronas. Constan de tres proteínas (NFPs) con masas moleculares estimadas de 68, 160 y 200 kDa. La expresión de NFPs por las células se considera típica de la diferenciación y evolución neuronal. En este estudio analizamos el patrón de expresión de NFP en las neuronas del ganglio cocleo-vestibular (GCV) del pollo durante la fase de desarrollo y la fase temprana post-eclosión. También investigamos la expresión de NFPs in vitro y su regulación por el factor neurotrófico NT3 (neurotrofina 3) para evaluar la participación de NFPs en los efectos inducidos por la neurotrofina. La presencia de inmunorreactividad (IR) a las NFPs in vivo e in vitro se estudió utilizando tanto el método de Western-blot como la inmunohistoquímica sobre preparaciones completas de embriones, secciones tisulares y cultivos primarios. La subunidad de NPF de 68kDa fue expresada a partir de la fase E4 hasta la E10, mientras que la subunidad de NPF de 160 kDa se encontró en todas las fases de desarrollo y en los días tempranos post-eclosión (P10). La subunidad de NFP de 200 kDa se observó en fases posteriores de desarrollo a partir de E10 hasta P30. La inmunorreactividad hacia cada subunidad detectada en secciones del oído interno fue consistente con los datos obtenidos con la inmunotransferencia. Los NFPs estaban localizados en los pericarion neuronales y sus procesos, permitiéndonos establecer el patrón temporal de inervación de los neuroepitelios sensoriales ubicados en el oído interno. Los cultivos primarios con NT3 reprodujeron el patrón &#147;in vivo&#148; de expresión de NFP. Los resultados aquí obtenidos demuestran que las subunidades de NFP son reguladas según su grado de desarrollo, lo cual sugiere que es posible que estén implicadas específicamente en la maduración de neuronas del GCV. Además, los hallazgos encontrados en neuronas en cultivo apuntan hacia una regulación de la expresión de NFP por la neurotrofina 3 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Eur. j. anat;4(2): 111-120, sept. 2000. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patrón de expresión de neurofilamentos en los ganglios cocleo-vestibulares en desarrollo in vivo y modulación por neurotrofina 3 in vitro</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Carreres, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San José, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Represa, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabo, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-15504</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d34466^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29931^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28224</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9667</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31554^s22023</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2688</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28304^s22023</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23422</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
