<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90726</identifier>
<setSpec>0465-546X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Eye protection: Importance and use</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Ten percent of the overall traumas in Spain are in theeye, these accidents where mostly at work. The aim of ourstudy is to determine the prevalence and etiology in ourarea and propose preventive measures to decrease thenumber of accidents and their severity.We conducted a descriptive study in 41 workers attendedin an eye emergency department (Hospital San Carlos-April2006) with a specific questionnaire (variables: age,sex, occupation, industry, supply and use of eye protection,recidivism, diagnosis and medical care).The results showed 25.6% of industrial eye accidents,87.2% where in males with an average age of 35.15 years,85.4% belong to the construction sector. The most frequentdiagnosis was the impact of foreign body. We realize that51.2% do not have safety glasses, and between those whohave it, 48% do not wear it. So, our efforts must be gearedto information and training on eye protection, worker andemployer.The 46.3% of accidents only need ambulatory treatment,this implies that occupational medical should be trainedin handling of eye injuries by their frequency and needfor immediate treatment in the workplace (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>O´Connor Pérez, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Bajo, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jerez Fidalgo, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caso Pita, Covadonga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Ramos, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bardón Fernández-Pacheco, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La traumatología ocular supone el 10% de la traumatologíageneral en España, siendo los accidentes oftalmológicosde origen laboral en su mayoría. Nuestroobjetivo es conocer la prevalencia y etiología en nuestromedio, proponiendo medidas preventivas para disminuirlosen número y gravedad.Realizamos un estudio descriptivo trasversal en 41 trabajadoresatendidos en un Servicio de Urgencias Oftalmológicasen un Hospital del Servicio Público de Salud de la Comunidadde Madrid durante el mes de Abril de 2006. Mediantecuestionario específico analizamos las siguientes variables:edad sexo, profesión, sector, dispensación y uso de protecciónocular, reincidencia, diagnóstico y asistencia médicaLos resultado obtenidos muestran que un 25.6% de accidentesoculares son de origen laboral, que se dan en el 87 %en varones, con una edad media de 35 años; pertenecen alsector de la construcción un 85.4 %, que maneja equipo desoldadura o radial. El diagnóstico más frecuente es el impactode cuerpo extraño y se trataba de accidente reiterado en el32% de los casos. No posee protección ocular el 51.2% y delos que la poseen no la usa el 48%. Por todo ello nuestroesfuerzo debe encaminarse a la información y formaciónsobre la protección ocular, en trabajador y empresarioEl hecho de que el 46% podría haber sido tratado deforma ambulatoria supone que médico del trabajo debeestar entrenado en el manejo de la traumatología ocular porsu frecuencia y la necesidad de tratamiento inmediato en ellugar de trabajo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;54(213): 81-86, oct.-dic. 2008. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90726</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Protección ocular: Importancia y uso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5237^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28016^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d61^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
