<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146086</identifier>
<setSpec>1577-0354</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">'Rev int med cienc ac'. A bibliometric approach to the 2000-2011 period</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The International Journal of Medicine and Science of Physical Activity and Sport is a Spanish magazine indexed in the two most important databases globally, with which impact indexes are calculated: Web of Science and Scopus. The present study analyses bibliometrically this magazine from its appearance until 2011. A total of 287 articles were published, with an average of 2.8 authorships per article. We can conclude that it is one of the best magazines in Spanish dealing with sports sciences and that the articles published in this primary source enjoy excellent visibility. Likewise, in light of the results, possible improvement actions are suggested: increasing the amount of articles per number, increasing the percentage of women and the internationality of the members of the different Boards of the magazine, and offering the possibility that researchers that do not speak Spanish may publish their articles in English only (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lorite, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castejón-Oliva, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejero-González, CM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Revista Internacional de Ciencias de la Actividad Física y del Deporte es una revista española indexada en las dos bases de datos más importantes a nivel internacional sobre las que se calculan los índices de impacto: Web of Science y Scopus. El presente trabajo analiza bibliométricamente esta revista desde su nacimiento hasta el año 2011. En total se publicaron 287 artículos, con un promedio de 2,8 autorías por trabajo. Se concluye que es una de las mejores revistas en lengua española de ciencias del deporte y que los trabajos publicados en esta fuente primaria optan a una excelente visibilidad. Asimismo, en virtud de los resultados, se argumentan posibles acciones de mejora: aumentar el número de artículos por número, incrementar el porcentaje de mujeres y la internacionalidad de los miembros de los distintos Consejos de la revista, y ofrecer la posibilidad de que los investigadores que no hablen español puedan publicar sus artículos exclusivamente en inglés (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. int. med. cienc. act. fis. deporte;15(60): 719-737, dic. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146086</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La 'rev. Int. Med. Cienc. Act. Fis. Dep'. Una aproximación bibliométrica del periodo 2000-2011</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50088</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33663</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53384</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
