<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75194</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4603</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Linguistic and social skills in adolescents with behavioural disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">One issue of concern today for parents, teachers,educational institutions and the general public, isthe social adjustment of children to their familyand school. Recent cases of violence in schools andcreated unrest among the education professionalsat the apparent lack of motivation and disciplinein students, are attracting new interest in findingout what determinants lead to children to developbehavior inadequacy in their social environment.The present study intends to analyze the influenceof linguistic and social skills on behavioural disordersin a sample of 48 adolescents whose agesranged from 12 to 16. All the adolescents wereattending a public high school in Granadaprovince. The participants were previously assignedto two groups: a group with behavioural disordersand a control group. Statistically significant differencesbetween the groups were found in all linguisticand reading variables, while regardingsocial skills, only self-control in social relationshipswas found to be statistically differentbetween the groups. The results of the discriminantfunction analysis supported by the strong linguisticskills in problem behavior defined on the basis ofserious sanctions school. With regard to academicperformance, behavior problems both as alterationsin the development of language, as variableswere directly involved in the success or failure inacademic secondary education(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Parra, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Rubio, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendoza, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Una cuestión que preocupa hoy día a padres, maestros,instituciones educativas, así como a la opiniónpública en general, es el ajuste social de los niños a suentorno familiar y escolar. Los recientes casos de violenciaen la escuela y el malestar generado entre losprofesionales de la educación por la aparente falta demotivación y disciplina en los alumnos, están despertandode nuevo el interés por averiguar qué determinantesllevan a los niños a desarrollar conductasde inadaptación en su entorno social. El presenteestudio pretende analizar la influencia de las habilidadeslingüísticas y sociales sobre los problemas deconducta de una muestra de 48 adolescentes de entre12 y 16 años, escolarizados en un instituto público dela provincia de Granada, asignados previamente a ungrupo con problemas de conducta y un grupo control.Se encontraron diferencias significativas entrelos dos grupos en todas las variables lingüísticas analizadas,y únicamente en el autocontrol en las relacionessociales para la variable habilidades sociales. Losresultados del análisis de la función discriminanteapoyaron de forma robusta la influencia de las habilidadeslingüísticas en los problemas de conductadefinidos en base a las sanciones escolares graves.Respecto al rendimiento académico, tanto los problemasde conducta como las habilidades lingüísticas,se mostraron como variables directamente implicadasen el éxito o fracaso académico durante la educaciónsecundaria(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. logop. foniatr. audiol. (Ed. impr.);29(4): 237-248, oct.-dic.2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75194</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Habilidades lingüísticas y sociales en adolescentes con problemas de conducta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38359^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1083^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
