<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143854</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The role of prenatal nutrition assistance on the prevalence of night blindness in pregnant adults</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: In developing countries, night blindness is a very common public health problem among pregnant women. Objective: Evaluate the effect of the changes occurred on prenatal care concerning prenatal nutritional care on the occurrence of night blindness (XN) in adult pregnant women in public maternity hospital in Rio de Janeiro between 1999-2001 and between 2007-2008. Methods: Two cross-sectional studies were conducted, been the first one conducted between 1999-2001 and the second one between 2007-2008. Were studied 402 puerperal women, 225 between 1999-2001 (GI) and 177 between 2007-2008 (GII). The gestational XN was investigated during the immediate puerperium (GI) and during the prenatal/puerperium (GII), diagnosed by the World Health Organization. The study collected sociodemographic, clinical, obstetric, anthropometric and prenatal care information. Results: It verified significant reduce of prevalence of gestational XN (GI = 18.7% e GII = 0.6%, p &lt; 0.001). The occurrence of gestational XN was associated to sanitary conditions, education level, more than six prenatal consultations, miscarriage at last pregnancy, higher average number of deliveries, average number of prenatal care consultations and prenatal nutritional (p &lt; 0.05). There was no association between gestational XN and marital status, skin color, pre-gestational nutritional status, adequacy of gain of total gestational weight, gestational anaemia and average number of pregnancies (p &gt; 0.05). Conclusion: The inclusion of nutritional care in routine prenatal care may have contributed to the reduction of gestational XN. Studies to assess the nutritional intervention in the prevention and treatment of gestational XN at regions at greatest risk are suggested (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramalho, Andrea</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padilha, Patricia de Carvalho</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saunders, Cláudia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Neves, Paulo Augusto Ribeiro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En los países en desarrollo, la ceguera nocturna (CN) es un problema muy común de la salud pública entre las mujeres embarazadas. Objetivo: Evaluar el efecto de los cambios ocurridos en la atención prenatal sobre el cuidado nutricional prenatal sobre la aparición de CN en mujeres adultas embarazadas en una maternidad pública en Rio de Janeiro entre 1999-2001 y entre 2007-2008. Métodos: Se realizaron dos estudios transversales, el primero entre 1999-2001 y el segundo entre 2007-2008. Se estudiaron 402 mujeres puérperas, 225 entre 1999-2001 (GI) y 177 entre 2007-2008 (GII). La CN gestacional fue investigada durante el puerperio inmediato (GI) y durante el prenatal/puerperio (GII), diagnosticada por la Organización Mundial de La Salud. El estudio incluyó informaciones sociodemográficas, clínicas, obstétricas, antropométricas y del cuidado prenatal. Resultados: Se verificó reducción significativa de la prevalencia de CN gestacional (GI = 18,7% e GII = 0,6%, p &lt; 0,001). La ocurrencia de CN gestacional se asoció con las condiciones sanitarias, el nivel de educación, más de seis consultas prenatales, abortos espontáneos en el último embarazo, mayor número promedio de partos, el número promedio de consultas de atención prenatal y de nutrición prenatal (p &lt; 0,05). No hubo asociación entre CN gestacional y el estado civil, color de piel, estado nutricional pregestacional, adecuación de la ganancia de peso durante la gestación, incluyendo anemia gestacional y el número medio de embarazos (p &gt; 0,05). Conclusión: La inclusión de la atención nutricional en el cuidado prenatal de rutina puede haber contribuido para la reducción de CN gestacional. Se sugiere más estudios para evaluar la intervención nutricional en la prevención y el tratamiento de CN gestacional en las regiones de mayor riesgo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;29(5): 1132-1140, mayo 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143854</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El papel de la asistencia nutricional prenatal sobre la prevalencia de la ceguera nocturna en adultas embarazadas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52506</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15203^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38344^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28296^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
