<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055132</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-7606</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Victimology in children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The study of victimology in children, and the general    worry that has brought attention to the violence that    children suffer, comes itself from very early dates. First it    rose interest through situations and bad deals that the    children suffered. Little by little, studies though recent, have    expanded on the different types of violence that the    children suffer; everything from their prenatal state to late    adolescence. This article intends to offer a general vision of    how throughout history violence toward children has    acquired importance, to give further insight on the different    forms of victimology in children, and to show how studies    of victimization have permitted us to know more about this    childlike violence</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morilla, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Millán, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hurtado, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sepúlveda, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El estudio de la victimología infantil, y la preocupación    general que ha despertado la violencia que sufren los    niños y niñas, se viene desarrollando desde fechas muy    recientes. Primero se despertó el interés por las situaciones    de malos tratos que padecían los niños, poco a poco,    estudios más recientes han ido ampliando los distintos    tipos de violencia que sufren los menores desde su estadío    prenatal hasta una tardía adolescencia. El presente    articulo pretende ofrecer una visión general de cómo a lo    largo de la historia, la violencia hacia los niños ha ido    adquiriendo importancia, de cuales son las distintas tipologías    de la misma, y que estudios de victimización nos    han permitido conocer más acerca de esta violencia    infantil</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. med. forense;12(43/44): 7-19, ene.-abr. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055132</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Victimología infantil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31499</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2696</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d378</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19101</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33199</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
