<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139890</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pre-competitive stress in adolescent bádminton players</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The paper was based on finding out the order of stress-related symptoms in pre- competition hours. We also compared total stress between categories (Under-13 and Under-17) and gender, and determined whether there existed any correlations between stress and hours of training, and stress and players&#146; position in the ranking. The study sample consisted of 128 subjects and was carried out during a top level badminton National Junior Circuit. The instrument used was the pre-competitive stress symptoms list - children and youths (De Rose Jr., 1996). The symptoms of pre-competitive stress most frequently found in players were related to emotions and behaviors. Girls under 17 had higher levels of stress than boys in the same category, in the hours before the competition (boys = 74.40 ± 16.11, girls = 80.75 ± 15.22; P &lt; .05), which could be related to the higher dropout from sport of this group. There was no relationship between stress and hours of training (r = .01; P = .92) or position in the ranking (r = -.12; P = .116). In conclusion, Under-17 girl badminton players had higher levels of stress compared to boys in the same category, and youth badminton players are enthusiastic about the arrival of competition (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Abián, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abián-Vicén, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Báguena Mainar, José Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El trabajo se basó en comprobar el orden de los síntomas relacionados con el estrés en las horas previas a la competición. También se comparó el estrés total entre categorías (sub 13 y sub 17) y sexos (masculino y femenino), y se determinó si existían correlaciones entre el estrés con las horas de entrenamiento y la posición que ocupaban los jugadores en el ranking. La muestra que participó en el estudio fue de 128 sujetos y se realizó durante un Circuito Nacional de Categorías Inferiores (sub-13 y sub-17) de máximo nivel. El instrumento utilizado fue la lista de síntomas de estrés precompetitivo Infanto Juvenil (De Rose Jr., 1996). Los síntomas de estrés pre-competitivo que se encontraron con mayor frecuencia en los jugadores estaban relacionados con las emociones y conductas. Por otro lado, las chicas de la categoría sub-17 presentaron mayores niveles de estrés en relación a los chicos de su misma categoría, en las horas previas a la competición (Masculino = 74.40 ± 16.11, Femenino = 80.75 ± 15.22; P &lt; .05) que podrían estar relacionados con el mayor abandono en la práctica deportiva de este colectivo. No hubo relación entre el estrés y las horas de entrenamiento (r =.01; P = .92) o la posición en el ranking (r = -.12; P = .116). En conclusión las chicas jugadoras de bádminton sub-17 presentaron mayores niveles de estrés en relación a los chicos de su misma categoría y los jugadores adolescentes de bádminton se muestran entusiasmados ante la llegada de la competición deportiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;24(2): 217-224, 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139890</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrés pre-competitivo en jugadores adolescentes de bádminton</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24846^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54747^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3194</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
