<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158228</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Multilocus Sequence Typing analysis of human Campylobacter coli in Granada (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Different subtypes of Campylobacter spp. have been associated with diarrhoea and a Multilocus Sequence Typing (MLST) method has been performed for subtyping. In the present work, MLST was used to analyse the genetic diversity of eight strains of Campylobacter coli. Material and methods. Nineteen genetic markers were amplified for MLST analysis: AnsB, DmsA, ggt, Cj1585c, CJJ81176-1367/1371, Tlp7, cj1321-cj1326, fucP, cj0178, cj0755/cfrA, ceuE, pldA, cstII, cstIII. After comparing the obtained sequences with the Campylobacter MLST database, the allele numbers, sequence types (STs) and clonal complexes (CCs) were assigned. Results. The 8 C. coli isolates yielded 4 different STs belonging to 2 CCs. Seven isolates belong to ST-828 clonal complex and only one isolate belong to ST-21. Two samples came from the same patient, but were isolated in two different periods of time. Conclusions. MLST can be useful for taxonomic characterization of C. coli isolates (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Ruiz, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrillo-Ávila, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sorlózano-Puerto, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Fernández, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Diferentes subtipos de Campylobacter spp. se han asociado con diarrea y la técnica de tipado mediante análisis de secuencias de múltiples locus (MLST) se ha empleado para la tipificación genética. En el presente trabajo, la técnica MLST se utilizó para analizar la diversidad genética de ocho cepas de Campylobacter coli. Material y métodos. 19 marcadores genéticos fueron amplificados mediante el análisis MLST: AnsB, DmsA, ggt, Cj1585c, CJJ81176-1367/1371, Tlp7, cj1321-cj1326, fucP, cj0178, cj0755/cfrA, ceuE, pldA, cstII, cstIII. Después de comparar las secuencias obtenidas con la base de datos MLST para Campylobacter, se asignaron el número de los alelos, los secuenciotipos (STs) y los complejos clonales (CCs). Resultados. Las 8 cepas de C. coli aisladas mostraron 4 STs diferentes pertenecientes a 2 CCs. Siete aislamientos pertenecieron al complejo clonal ST-828 y sólo un aislado perteneció al ST-21. Dos aislados pertenecieron al mismo paciente, pero fueron obtenidos en diferentes periodos de tiempo. Conclusiones. La técnica MLST puede ser útil para la caracterización taxonómica de aislados de C. coli (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;29(6): 332-335, dic. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158228</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tipificación mediante secuencias multilocus de cepas humanas de Campylobacter coli en Granada (España)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2201^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2201^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54262^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2201^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54262^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24411^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54262^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24411^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30217^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30217^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54262^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30522^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
