<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90947</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of therapeutic compliance in women with osteoporosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess therapeutic compliance in osteoporosis in women in a Primary Care (PC) setting. Patients and methods: Observational, descriptive, cross-sectional and multicenter study, conducted in PC centers of the 17 Spanish Autonomous Regions. 1,649women who had initiated treatment for osteoporosis at least 3 months before entering the study were recruited. To assess therapeutic compliance, two questionnaires, the Haynes-Sackett or self-communicated compliance test (AC) and the Morisky-Green test (MG) were used. Results: Patients&#146; mean age (±SD) was 66.59 years (9.5) and the mean time since diagnosis was 5.08 years (4.87). Bisphosphonates were the most precribed drugs (82% of the patients) and only 52% of the patients were taking calcium and vitaminDsupplements. Analysis of the therapeutic compliance level shows that, as per the MG test, 68.7% of the patients were non-compliers, and 11.2% were non-compliers as per the AC test. Conclusions: An important percentage ofwomenwith post-menopausal osteoporosis in Spain&#146;s PC setting show a high level of non-compliance(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guañabens Gay, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Regadera Anechina, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Taverna Llauradó, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carbonell Abella, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín Rives, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayechu Redín, Manuel Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar el cumplimiento del tratamiento farmacológico de la osteoporosis en mujeres atendidas en el ámbito de la Atención Primaria (AP). En la osteoporosis, como en otras enfermedades crónicas, el fomento del tratamiento a largo plazo es fundamental. Pacientes y métodos: Se trata de un estudio observacional, descriptivo, transversal y multicéntrico, realizado en Centros de Salud de AP de las 17 Comunidades Autónomas. Se reclutaron 1.649 mujeres que habían iniciado tratamiento farmacológico para la osteoporosis al menos 3 meses antes. Para evaluar el cumplimiento se utilizaron dos cuestionarios: el test de Haynes-Sackett o de cumplimiento autocomunicado (CA) y el test de Morisky-Green (MG). Resultados: La edad media (± DE) de las pacientes era de 66,6 a&#152;nos (9,5) y el tiempo medio desde el diagnóstico era de 5,1 años (4,9). El tratamiento más prescrito fueron los bisfosfonatos (82% de las pacientes) y sólo un 52% recibía suplementos de calcio y vitamina D. El análisis del nivel de cumplimiento muestra que el 68,7% fue incumplidora según el test de MG, y el 11,2% fue incumplidora según el test de CA. Conclusiones: Un porcentaje importante de las mujeres con osteoporosis posmenopáusicas atendidas en AP en España presenta un elevado incumplimiento terapéutico(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);7(5): 299-304, sep.-oct.2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90947</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis del cumplimiento terapéutico en mujeres con osteoporosis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15208^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24823^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24823^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28261^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4220^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
