<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116028</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">European innovation partnership on active and healthy aging: moving from policy to action</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Demographic change and aging are a common challenge in Europe. The rising number of elderly people will need support at home, and will consume more healthcare services, putting further pressure on the welfare system. Collaborative, integrated and people-centered care provision, whether in hospitals, homes or in the community, is a way forward to sustainable and efficient care systems. Innovative treatments to address chronic diseases and the functional decline of older people will enable them to live longer in better health and with a better quality of life. To fully unleash the potential of aging in the European Union, the European Commission -within its Innovation Union policy- launched the first European Innovation Partnership on Active and Healthy Ageing (EIP AHA). Promoting engagement and partnerships among all stakeholders in the healthcare chain is essential. This article describes the theoretical foundations, the development and expectations of the initiative, and its first actions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Lizana, Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El envejecimiento es un reto común en la Unión Europea, que incrementará la necesidad de ayuda a domicilio y el consumo de servicios sanitarios, presionando con ello nuestro sistema de bienestar. Una visión más colaborativa, integrada y centrada en el paciente-ciudadano parece ofrecer una respuesta más sostenible y eficiente a los modelos actuales. Abordajes innovadores para la patología crónica y la prevención del deterioro funcional permitirán vivir más y con mejor calidad de vida. Para hacer realidad el potencial beneficio de estas intervenciones, la Comisión Europea, en su política de "Unión para la innovación", ha lanzado la iniciativa "Cooperación para la innovación europea en el envejecimiento activo y saludable". La promoción de la participación y la colaboración de todos los actores en la cadena de cuidados son esenciales. Este artículo describe el fundamento teórico, el desarrollo de la iniciativa, sus expectativas y las primeras acciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;27(5): 459-462, sept.-oct. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116028</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cooperación para la innovación europea en el envejecimiento activo y saludable: de la política a la acción</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37738^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32630^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30481^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5160</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
