<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049928</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Myocardial remodeling and immunologic activation in patients with heart failure</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. Immune response-mediated regulation of myocardial collagen remains poorly understood. Our objective was to investigate the relationship between ventricular remodeling and immunologic activation in patients with heart failure (HF) by comparing dilated and ischemic cardiomyopathy. Methods. We studied 94 patients with HF and dilated cardiomyopathy (n=46) or ischemic cardiomyopathy (n=48). We recorded left ventricular (LV) volumes, E/A ratio, and ejection fraction. Plasma concentrations of tumor necrosis factor &amp;#945; (TNF&amp;#945;), soluble TNFa receptor I (sTNF-RI), sTNF-RII, interleukin-6 (IL-6) and IL-10 were measured. The serum procollagen type-III amino-terminal propeptide (PIIINP) level was also obtained. Results. Ventricular volumes were greater in the dilated cardiomyopathy than in the ischemic cardiomyopathy group (P&lt;.05). However, sTNF-RI, sTNF-RII and PIIINP levels were higher in the ischemic group (P&lt;.05). In this group, there were significant correlations between ventricular volumes and IL-10 and sTNF-RII levels. There was also a significant correlation between PIIINP and sTNF-RII levels (r=0.30; P&lt;.05). In the dilated cardiomyopathy group, there was a significant correlation between ventricular volumes and IL-10 level, and between PIIINP level and IL-6 (r=0.32; P&lt;.05) and sTNF-RII levels (r=0.32; P&lt;.05). Multiple linear regression analysis, which included cytokine levels, age, sex and ventricular function, showed that the sTNF-RII level was an independent predictor of the PIIINP level (adjusted r²=0.16; P&lt;.0001) and of ventricular volumes (LV end-systolic volume index, adjusted r²=0.034; P&lt;.05; and LV end-diastolic volume index, adjusted r²=.048; P&lt;.05) in both groups. Conclusions. In HF, there is an interaction between proinflammatory cytokines and the extracellular matrix. Immunologic implications vary according to disease etiology. The elevation in proinflammatory cytokine and PIIINP levels is greater in patients with ischemic cardiomyopathy. Multiple regression analysis showed that the sTNF-RII level was an independent predictor of ventricular remodeling (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jordán, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sirera, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sancho-Tello, María J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roselló, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valero, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortés, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivera, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Molina, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Taléns-Visconti, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Payá, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Climent, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sevilla, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. No se comprende bien la regulación del colágeno miocárdico mediada por la respuesta inmunitaria. Nuestro objetivo fue determinar las relaciones entre remodelado ventricular y activación inmunitaria en pacientes con insuficiencia cardiaca comparando miocardiopatía isquémica y dilatada. Métodos. Estudiamos a 94 pacientes con insuficiencia cardiaca: miocardiopatía dilatada (n = 46) e isquémica (n = 48). Determinamos volúmenes ventriculares, E/A y FE. Medimos las concentraciones de TNF&amp;#945;, sTNF-RI, sTNF-RII, IL-6 e IL-10 y calculamos los valores de PIIINP. Resultados. Los volúmenes ventriculares en la miocardiopatía dilatada fueron superiores a los del grupo isquémico (p &lt; 0,05). Sin embargo, los valores de sTNF-RI, sTNF-RII y PIIINP fueron más elevados en el grupo isquémico (p &lt; 0,05). En éste, los volúmenes ventriculares se correlacionaron significativamente con IL-10 y sTNF-RII. El PIIINP se correlacionó significativamente con sTNF-RII (r = 0,30; p &lt; 0,05). En el grupo de miocardiopatía dilatada, los volúmenes ventriculares se correlacionaron significativamente con IL-10 y el PIIINP se correlacionó con IL-6 (r = 0,32; p &lt; 0,05) y sTNF-RII (r = 0,32; p &lt; 0,05). La regresión lineal múltiple, que incluyó citocinas, edad, sexo y función ventricular, demuestra que el sTNF-RII es un factor pronóstico independiente del PIIINP (r² ajustada = 0,16; p &lt; 0,0001) y de los volúmenes ventriculares (IVTSVI, r² ajustada = 0,034; p &lt; 0,05; IVTDVI, r² ajustada = 0,048; p &lt; 0,05) en ambos grupos. Conclusiones. En la insuficiencia cardiaca hay una interacción de citocinas proinflamatorias con la matriz extracelular. La implicación inmunitaria es diferente dependiendo de la etiología. Las citocinas proinflamatorias y los valores de PIIINP son más elevados en los pacientes con miocardiopatía isquémica. La regresión múltiple demostró que el sTNF-RII es un factor pronóstico independiente de remodelado ventricular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;59(9): 911-918, sept. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049928</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Remodelado miocárdico y activación inmunitaria en pacientes con insuficiencia cardiaca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2355^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33914^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2347^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2347^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28903^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2347^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2355^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33914^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2355^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31130^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
