<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127138</identifier>
<setSpec>2254-2884</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Citrate- versus acetate- based dialysate in patients in high-efficiency online hemodiafiltration: parameters to be studied</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Liquid dialysate with acetate (LDA) reported less biocompatible, generating oxidative stress and inflammation. Perceived benefits include its anti-inflammatory citrate buffer effect and antioxidant properties, anticoagulant power, chelating ionized calcium, and improves tolerance to the session. Objective: To compare nutritional and inflammatory parameters, dialysis efficiency, acid-base status, tolerance and calcium balance in on-line hemodiafiltration (OL-HDF) using citrate dialysate (LDC) versus LDA. Methods: Prospective cross OLHDF population in 24 weeks. Begins 35 patients (33 finish), with 57.4 years, 55% male, 54.1 months of permanence. 79% carriers arteriovenous fistula. 2376 sessions are analyzed. The study has two phases. Variables: albumin, CRP, Beta 2 microglobulin (B2MCG), phase angle (PA), body cell mass (BCM), Kt, reinfusion volume, PTTA, hemostasis time, state cameras and dialyzer, pH, bicarbonate, calcium ion, sessions with hypotension and cramps. Statistical analysis SPSS 13.0. Hypothesis testing using T-Student and Wilcoxon W for quantitative variables. Chi-squared qualitative. Statistical significance p &lt;0.05. Results: Significant differences (p &lt;0.001) in albumin, CRP, and B2MCG. BCM (p = 0.001), AF (p = 0.002) and Kt (p &lt;0.001) higher with LDC. Lower post-dialysis bicarbonate (p &lt;0.001) with LDC. Calcium ion pre and post-dialysis (p = 0.007 and p &lt;0.001 respectively) with lower LDC. Conclusion: Dialysis citrate shown in our series more biocompatible and less inflammation, improves nutritional parameters and analytical impedance and increases efficiency dialysis. Reduces post-dialysis bicarbonate. Both pre-and post-dialysis ionized calcium is lower, remaining sta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Martínez, Aránzazu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Clavel, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aznar Barbero, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bel Cegarra, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chica Arellano, Josefa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Badallo Mira, M. Magdalena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carbonell Olivares, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Domingo, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El líquido dializante con acetato se reporta menos biocompatible, generando estrés oxidativo e inflamación. Entre los beneficios asociados al citrato destacan sus propiedades antiinflamatorias y antioxidantes, poder anticoagulante, quelante del calcio iónico, efecto tampón y mejora la tolerancia a la sesión. Objetivo: Comparar parámetros nutricionales e inflamatorios, eficacia dialítica, estatus ácido-base, tolerancia y balance de calcio en hemodiafiltración en línea empleando líquido dializante con citrato frente a líquido dializante con acetato. Material y métodos: Estudio prospectivo cruzado sobre población en hemodiafiltración en línea de 24 semanas. Inician 35 pacientes (finalizan 33), con 57,4 años, 55% hombres, 54,1 meses de permanencia. 79% portadores de fistula arteriovenosa. Se analizan 2376 sesiones. El estudio tiene dos fases. Variables: albúmina, PCR, Beta 2 microglobulinas (B2MCG), ángulo de fase (AF), masa celular corporal (BCM), Kt, volumen de reinfusión, PTTA, tiempo de hemostasia, estado de cámaras y dializador, pH, bicarbonato, calcio iónico, sesiones con hipotensión y calambres. Análisis estadístico SPSS 13.0. Contraste de hipótesis mediante T-Student y W de Wilcoxon para variables cuantitativas. Chi-cuadrado cualitativas. Significación estadística p&lt;0,05. Resultados: Diferencias significativas (p&lt;0,001) en albúmina, PCR, y B2MCG. BCM (p=0,001), AF (p=0,002) y Kt (p&lt; 0,001) mayores con líquido de diálisis con citrato. Bicarbonato postdiálisis menor (p&lt;0,001) con líquido de diálisis con citrato. Calcio iónico pre y postdiálisis (p=0,007 y p&lt;0,001 respectivamente) menores con líquido de diálisis con citrato. Conclusiones: La diálisis con citrato se muestra en nuestra serie más biocompatible y con menor inflamación, mejora los parámetros nutricionales analíticos y por impedancia e incrementa la eficacia dialítica. Reduce el bicarbonato postdiálisis. Tanto pre como postdiálisis el calcio iónico es menor, permaneciendo estable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. nefrol;17(3): 192-197, jul.-sept. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127138</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Líquido dializante con citrato frente a acetato en pacientes en hemodiafiltración on-line de alta eficacia: parámetros a estudio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23663^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31418^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23663^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31418^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31418^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31418^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31418^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29321^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31418^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29413^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d89^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23663^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32979^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
