<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94311</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The foster care evolution. Proposal of actions to prevent its difficulties</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Sometimes the foster care processes have to be interrupted before than expected without achieving the aims that motivated it. In most of the cases the interruption takes place after a crisis in the relationships between the families and the minors. The numbers about the interruption of foster cares worry the professionals working in child protection, and they arouse interest to know the factors related to these interruptions to try to prevent them. With this intention, 77 reports from the Child Care Service and which gather cases of foster care that were ceased at the moment of the research have been analyzed in order to elucidate, through a contingency analysis, the possible variables that took part in these cessations. The results reflect the presence of a series of common factors related to the minor, such a shis age or his previous experiences, to the foster family, such as the relationship with the minor, having other children, having experience in foster care or their educational styles, and to the process itself, such as the form of the foster care, the number of minors assigned to the same family, or the intensity of the monitoring, whose control should guide future practice in the foster care teams (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rosser, Ana María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En ocasiones, los procesos de acogimiento familiar de menores han de interrumpirse antes de lo previsto sin que se hayan logrado los objetivos que lo motivaron. En muchos de estos casos la interrupción se produce tras una crisis en las relaciones entre familias y menores. Las cifras sobre la interrupción de acogimientos preocupan, y despiertan un interés por conocer los factores que se relacionan con estas interrupciones y tratar de prevenirlos. Con esa intención se han analizado 77 expedientes del Sistema de Protección de Menores, en los que se había interpuesto una medida de acogimiento familiar, y que habían cesado en el momento del estudio, al objeto de dilucidar, mediante un análisis de contingencia, las posibles las variables intervinientes en estos ceses. Los resultados reflejan la presencia de una serie de factores, tanto del menor, como su edad o sus experiencias previas, de la familia acogedora como el grado de parentesco con el menor, tener otros hijos, tener experiencia en acogimientos o sus estilos educativos, y del propio proceso, como la modalidad de acogimiento, el número de menores asignados a una misma familia, o la intensidad del seguimiento, cuyo control debería orientar la práctica futura en los equipos de acogimiento familiar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;27(3): 729-738, oct.-dic. 2011. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94311</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución de los acogimientos familiares Propuesta de actuaciones para la prevención de sus dificultades</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13331^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50296</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13331^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23905^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35155</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
