<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058251</identifier>
<setSpec>0301-0546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Immunotherapy with Alternaria alternata: present and future</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The prevalence of fungal allergies is greater than previously believed; consequently, such processes have been underestimated as potential causes of respiratory tract disease. Most patients sensitized to fungi exhibit perennial symptoms, though their intensity increases in the summer and autumn months. Skin reactions to the antigens of Alternaria alternata are associated with a high risk of allergic respiratory conditions in the presence of spores of this fungus ­ fundamentally in children and young adults ­ with a special form of presentation as life-threatening asthma. Very few controlled studies have examined the efficacy and safety of fungal extract immunotherapy ­ the main problem being the lack of standardized extracts for the diagnosis and treatment of such patients. In the year 2005 a tolerance study was made in children in relation to a depot extract containing the predominant antigen of Alternaria, with two different regimens (short and cluster). Tolerance was found to be good, with a 0.95 % incidence of local reactions and a 0.95 % incidence of grade 2 systemic reactions. Few studies involving sublingual immunotherapy have been conducted to date</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valenzuela-Soria, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojo-Hernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Cañavate Burgos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La prevalencia de la alergia a hongos es mayor de la que hasta ahora se pensaba, ya que han sido subestimados como causantes de enfermedades del sistema respiratorio. La mayoría de los pacientes sensibilizados a hongos presentan sintomatología perenne, aunque con mayor intensidad en el periodo estival y el otoño. La reacción cutánea a los antígenos de Alternaria alternata se asocia con un elevado riesgo de cuadros respiratorios alérgicos en presencia de esporas de este hongo, principalmente en niños y adultos jóvenes, con una forma especial de presentación de asma de riesgo vital. Existen muy pocos estudios controlados realizados sobre la eficacia y seguridad de la inmunoterapia con extractos fúngicos, cuyo principal problema es la falta de extractos estandarizados para el diagnóstico y tratamiento de estoa pacientes. En el 2005 se realizó estudio de tolerancia en niños de un extracto depot con el antígeno mayoritario de Alternaria, con dos pautas distintas (corta y cluster); la tolerancia fue buena, con 0.95% de reacciones locales y 0.95% de sistémicas grado 2. Hay pocos estudios con inmunoterapia sublingual</dc:description>
<dc:source>Allergol Immunopathol (Madr);35(6): 259-263, nov. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058251</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inmunoterapia con alternaria alternata: presente y futuro</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d488^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d529^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27801^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7145^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d529^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7145^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7345^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7345^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7345^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7345^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d488^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7345^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7345^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27801^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
