<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93972</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Development and validation of the Childhood Perfectionism Inventory (IPI)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There are a few studies linking children&#146;s perfectionism with diverse internalized or externalized disorders. Likewise, in Spanish, there is no scale that measures the diverse aspects that comprise it. This paper presents the Children&#146;s Perfectionism Inventory (IPI). The sample comprised 2,260 participants (51.2% males and 48.8% females). The age range is between 8 and 13 years (mean= 9.94 and SD= 1.27). Sampling was stratified and random. Of the sample, 78.1% are from public education and 21.9% from private education. 16.2% reside in rural areas and 83.8% in urban areas. To study the validity of the questionnaire, crossvalidation was performed. Initially three factors were obtained through exploratory factor analysis: Self-assessment, Self-imposed and External Pressures, with adequate reliability indices (Cronbach&#146;s alpha= .89, .87 and .88, respectively). Subsequently, using a confirmatory method, it was found that the three initial factors were explained by a single second-order factor called Perfectionism (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lozano González, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Cueto, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Vázquez, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano Fernández, Luis Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Existen pocos estudios que relacionen el perfeccionismo infantil con diferentes trastornos, ya sean internalizados o externalizados. Asimismo, en castellano, no existe una escala que mida los diferentes aspectos que lo conforman. En este trabajo se presenta el Inventario de Perfeccionismo Infantil (IPI). La muestra con la que se ha trabajado está compuesta por 2.260 participantes (51,2% varones y 48,8% mujeres). El rango de edad oscila entre los 8 y los 13 años (Media= 9,94 y Desviación típica= 1,27). El muestreo se realizó de forma aleatorio estratificado. El 78,1% corresponden a enseñanza pública y el 21,9% a enseñanza privada concertada. El 16,2% reside en zona rural y el 83,8% en áreas urbanas. Para estudiar la validez del cuestionario se empleó una validación cruzada. Inicialmente se obtuvieron, a través de un análisis factorial exploratorio, tres factores: Autovaloración, Autoexigencia y Presión externa con unos índices adecuados de fiabilidad (alfa de Cronbach= 0,89, 0,87 y 0,88, respectivamente). Posteriormente, utilizando una metodología confirmatoria se ha comprobado que los tres factores iniciales son explicados por un único factor de segundo orden que se denomina «Perfeccionismo» (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);24(1): 149-155, ene.-mar. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93972</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desarrollo y validación del Inventario de Perfeccionismo Infantil (IPI)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13720^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10746^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10746^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10167^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
