<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113897</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Profile of women with breast disease wich does self-exploration.  Which are the factors associated with this practice?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background/Aims: In recent decades the fight against breast cancer has focused primarily on the treatment and secondary prevention (early detection mainly). In the case of breast self-examination, althought it has not been prove to reduce mortality, it is important in cases detected by women themselves (it is estimated 90% of total), mainly in the interval cancers.  Objectives: To identify within women with breast cancer, how many do self-examination and identify associated factors. Describe the clinical and pathological features of cancers in women who do perform self-examination.  Methodology: In women diagnosed with breast cancer during 2007 in a hospital in the province of Cadiz, Spain, is reconstructed in retrospect the story related the cancer process: symptoms, psychosocial factors that determine the contact with the health system, preventive practices (self-examination, mammography screening). A description of the pathological tumor: presenting symptom, tumor size, node negative, grade of differentiation&#133; Results: We studied 149 women with breast cancer, from whom 52% did self-exploration. Women who performed self-examination were younger (54.78 years) against the women who did not (65.63 years), married (66.2%), active workers and have a higher educational level. The assessment of the first symptoms in these women as «important» is positively correlated with  those women who practice self-examination. For other preventive practices, women who does self-examination are also the most actives in early detection programs (74.4% against 29.5% which didn&#146;t do self-examination). For the pathologic characteristics of tumor in women who did self-examination: the tumor size was 2.5 cm, 50.7 / are well differentiated, and 59.1% of cases the nodes are negative. Conclusions: Women who does self-examination are younger, have higher educational level, are married, are active workers and are often involved in other preventive practices. On them, the tumors diagnosed have a smaller size, are diagnosed at earlier stages and usually present better degree of differentiation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Argeme Serradilla Fernánde, Argeme</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyero Hernández, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerrero Chacón, Blanca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyero Hernández, M. del Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tobajas Tobajas, María Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los pacientes anticoagulados con tratamiento oral (ACO) deben tener unos conocimientos de los riesgos que dicho tratamiento conlleva. Para ello el personal sanitario debe formar tanto al paciente como a su familia. Objetivos. Determinar el nivel de adhesión terapéutica que tienen los pacientes tratados con ACO en una consulta de atención primaria (AP) y en un área de salud urbana, como Plasencia. Material y método. Se realizó un estudio observacional descriptivo retrospectivo con 34 pacientes con tratamiento ACO. Se recogen datos de patologías, parámetros biométricos de las historias clínicas y entrevistas a los sujetos que acuden a la consulta de enfermería. Resultados. Una vez analizados los datos, el número de pacientes &#150;según el sexo&#150; estaba igualado; no sucedía lo mismo por edades donde la población entre 80-90 años constituía el 26,5 % del total; dentro de las patologías de las que se deriva el tratamiento, la fibrilación auricular (FA) es la más frecuente, con un 50%, siguiéndole el tromboembolismo pulmonar, con un 23%. El control de los resultados se distribuía de la siguiente manera: los más jóvenes se controlaban en atención especializada (AE), en su hospital de referencia; los de mayor edad en AP. En relación con la adhesión al tratamiento y la patología principal, quienes padecían FA y portaban una prótesis valvular cumplían el tratamiento en mayor número. Discusión. Para el profesional sanitario es necesario conocer el perfil del paciente con ACO, y si este sabe los riesgos que conlleva el tratamiento. Los enfermos jóvenes con patología cardiovasculares son controlados en el hospital por sus mayores oscilaciones en los resultados; la población mayor es vigilada en la consulta de atención primaria (AP), y los residentes en zonas rurales cuentan con una mayor adherencia y un mejor control. Con una completa información el personal sanitario puede efectuar intervenciones que ayuden a la adhesión, seguimiento del control y tratamiento, así como a la colaboración de familiares(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;36(4): 266-270, abr. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113897</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pacientes con tratamiento anticoagulante oral. ¿qué saben sobre su tratamiento?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14308^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14308^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15100^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15100^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15100^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12092^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12092^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
