<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056436</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interleukin-8 expression in lung tissue during ischemia­ reperfusion</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Local cytokine production is a pathogenic factor in ischemia­reperfusion injury in early graft dysfunction. This study analyzed interleukin 8 (IL-8) messenger RNA (mRNA) expression in lung tissue and the association between IL-8 mRNA levels and interstitial lung changes in an experimental model of warm lung ischemia­reperfusion.     Material and methods: We studied 16 New Zealand rabbits divided into 3 groups: control, ischemia (tissue taken from right lower lobe after 1, 2, or 3 hours of ischemia), and reperfusion (tissue taken from right upper and middle lobes after 1 hour of ischemia and 1, 2, or 3 hours of reperfusion). Expression of IL-8 mRNA was determined by reverse transcription and polymerase chain reaction. Interstitial infiltration by polymorphonuclear neutrophils was determined. The Mann­Whitney U-test was used for statistical comparisons, with P&lt;.05 considered to indicate a significant result.         Results: During ischemia, IL-8 mRNA levels were elevated at the end of hour 1 (P=.009) with respect to the control group, but not thereafter. Interstitial changes were minimal. IL-8 mRNA levels during reperfusion were similar to those observed during ischemia, with a slight increase at the end of hour 2. There were no significant differences between hours 1, 2, and 3. Polymorphonuclear neutrophil recruitment occurred at the beginning of reperfusion (P=.014), but no significant differences were observed at hours 2 or 3. Progressive thickening of alveolar septa and edema was documented.         Conclusions: Changes in IL-8 mRNA expression during ischemia precede interstitial infiltration by polymorphonuclear neutrophils during reperfusion, suggesting that the 2 processes are related. Quantification of IL-8 mRNA expression could facilitate early diagnosis of graft dysfunction</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gayoso, Manuel J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heras, Félix</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matilla, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Yuste, Mariano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Prada, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Crespo, Mariano</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: La generación local de citocinas es un factor patogénico en el daño por isquemia-reperfusión en la disfunción precoz del injerto. Este estudio analiza la expresión en tejido pulmonar de ARN mensajero de interleucina-8 (ARNm de IL-8) y su relación con los cambios intersticiales pulmonares en un modelo experimental de isquemia-reperfusión pulmonar normotérmica.         Material y métodos: Se estudiaron 16 conejos de la raza Nueva Zelanda en 3 grupos de estudio: a) basal; b) isquemia (lóbulo inferior derecho tras isquemia de 1, 2 o 3 h), y c) reperfusión (lóbulos superior y medio derechos tras 1 h de isquemia y 1, 2 o 3 h de reperfusión). Se determinó la expresión del ARNm de IL-8 mediante transcripción inversa y reacción en cadena de la polimerasa y estudió la infiltración intersticial por polimorfonucleares (PMN). Para el análisis estadístico se empleó el test de la U de Mann-Whitney aceptando como significativo un valor de p &lt; 0,05.         Resultados: Durante el período de isquemia se observó respecto al basal elevación del ARNm de IL-8 al final de la primera hora (p = 0,009), pero no durante el resto del período isquémico. Los cambios intersticiales fueron mínimos. Durante la reperfusión los valores de ARNm de IL-8 fueron semejantes a los observados durante la isquemia, con una ligera elevación al final de segunda hora; no hubo diferencias significativas entre la primera, segunda y tercera horas. Hubo reclutamiento de PMN al inicio de la reperfusión (p = 0,014), sin observarse diferencias significativas en la segunda y tercera horas. Se objetivó un engrosamiento progresivo de los tabiques interalveolares y edema.         Conclusiones: Los cambios en la expresión del ARNm de IL-8 durante la isquemia preceden a la infiltración intersticial de PMN durante la reperfusión, lo que señala una relación entre ambos procesos. La cuantificación del ARNm de IL-8 podría ser un procedimiento para el seguimiento diagnóstico de la disfunción precoz del injerto</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;43(10): 542-548, oct. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056436</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de la expresión de interleucina-8 en el tejido pulmonar durante la isquemia-reperfusión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22282</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28995^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4255</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23813^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10269^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22853^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8345^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35425</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32175^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
