<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92769</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-1813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Medical students&#146; perception of the educational environment in a faculty developing a traditional curriculum (UCH-Chile) and another with a problem based learning curriculum (UNC-Argentina)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To assess and compare the perception about the educational environment of medical students from two Latin-American universities, University of Chile (UCH) and National University of Cuyo (UNC), which develop a traditional curriculum and a problem based curriculum, respectively. Subjects and methods. A transversal study was performed in 465 students: 232 from the UCH and 233 from the UNC. The distribution was 84/70 for the first course, 77/97 for the third one and 71/66 for the fifth one, respectively. The DREEM questionnaire, which consists of 50 items, was applied. It covers 5 dimensions of the educational environment: perception about learning, perception about teachers, academic self-perception, perception about educational climate and social self-perception. Results. Total DREEM scores were significantly higher in the UNC. Scores were similar in all courses from both universities, with the exception of fifth course UCH. Regarding their perception about teachers, students of the fifth course UCH showed the lowest score, whereas students of the first course UNC had the best perception. Similar results were obtained for the academic auto-perception; while the perception of the learning environment obtained higher scores in the three courses from the UNC. Social auto-perception was similar in all courses tested in this study. Conclusions. Differences observed between both universities could be attributed to their different curricula. Problem based curriculum seems to be better appreciated than the traditional one. Our study corroborates the efficacy of the DREEM questionnaire to identify strengths and weaknesses of the curriculum and for the assessment of teaching quality in medical schools (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escanero-Marcen, Jesús F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Terán, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Véliz, Gabriela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bianchi, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gorena, Dorian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lafuente-Sánchez, José V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gargiulo, Pascual A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Evaluar y comparar la percepción que del ambiente educativo tienen los estudiantes de medicina de dos universidades iberoamericanas: Universidad de Chile (UCH) y Universidad Nacional de Cuyo (UNC), que desarrollan un currículo tradicional y un currículo basado en problemas, respectivamente. Sujetos y métodos. Participaron 465 estudiantes: 232 de la UCH y 233 de la UNC. La distribución fue de 84 y 70 estudiantes para el primer curso, 77 y 97 para el tercero, y 71 y 66 para el quinto, respectivamente. Se aplicó el cuestionario DREEM, que consiste en 50 ítems, agrupados en cinco dimensiones: percepción de la enseñanza, percepción de los profesores, autopercepción académica, percepción de la atmósfera educativa y autopercepción social. Resultados. Las puntuaciones totales fueron mayores en los tres cursos de la UNC. Resultaron similares en todos los cursos de ambas universidades, excepto en el quinto curso de la UCH. Respecto a la percepción acerca de los profesores, los estudiantes de quinto curso de la UCH mostraron las puntuaciones más bajas, mientras que los estudiantes del primer curso de la UNC tuvieron la mejor percepción. Resultados similares se obtuvieron en la autopercepción académica. La percepción del ambiente de aprendizaje fue mejor en la UNC y la autopercepción social tuvo puntuaciones similares en todos los cursos de ambas universidades. Conclusiones. Las diferencias observadas entre ambas universidades podrían atribuirse a sus diferentes currículos. El currículo basado en problemas parece ser mejor valorado que el tradicional. Nuestro estudio corrobora la eficacia del cuestionario DREEM para identificar fortalezas y debilidades del currículo y para evaluar la calidad de la enseñanza en facultades de medicina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Educ. med. (Ed. impr.);14(1): 27-34, mayo 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92769</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Percepción de los estudiantes de medicina del ambiente educativo en una facultad con currículo tradicional(UCH-Chile) y otra con currículo basado en problemas (UNC-Argentina)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12958^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13321</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32065^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13724^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201105</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
