<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107500</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cervical screening protocols can be applied in daily clinical practice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To evaluate whether screening protocols for cervical cancer can be implemented without delaying the diagnosis of cancer and whether this practice is well accepted by patients. Subjects and methods. In 2005, we developed a protocol for the early diagnosis of cervical cancer based on carrying out cervical smears every 3 years in women over the age of 30 with three previous normal smears. We studied 300 patients who had attended an appointment in 2006 and another 300 in 2008. We reviewed our records to determine whether we had performed a smear and, if one was indicated, whether we had recommended attendance at a follow-up visit 3 years later, and whether the women had returned earlier. Adherence to the protocol in cancers diagnosed from 2005 was also reviewed. Results. The number of smears decreased by 32% in 2008 compared with 2004, the year prior to screening. In 2008, 21% of women were recommended to attend the next review 3 years later and 3% returned earlier. Of 17 cancers diagnosed since 2005, only one woman with adenocarcinoma had undergone screening. Conclusions. The overuse of cytology/smears in daily clinical practice can be avoided (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ribas, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campomanes, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lamelas, M. Luz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejuca, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alvarez, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Evaluar si podemos aplicar protocolos de cribado de cáncer de cérvix sin retrasar el diagnóstico del cáncer y con buena aceptación por las pacientes. Sujetos y métodos. En 2005 elaboramos un protocolo de diagnóstico precoz del cáncer de cérvix basado en realizar citologías cada 3 años a mujeres mayores de 30 años con 3 citologías previas normales. Estudiamos a 300 pacientes que habían acudido a consulta en 2006 y otras 300 en 2008. Revisamos si les habíamos hecho citología y si estaba indicada, las revisiones recomendadas a los 3 años y si volvían antes. También la adhesión al protocolo en los cánceres diagnosticados desde 2005. Resultados. Las citologías se redujeron en un 32% en 2008 con respecto al 2004, año previo al cribado. En 2008 recomendamos al 21% de las pacientes la próxima revisión en 3 años. Un 3% volvió antes. De 17 cánceres diagnosticados desde 2005, solo una mujer con adenocarcinoma había realizado el cribado. Conclusiones. Evitar el sobreúso de la citología en la práctica diaria es posible (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);55(10): 492-494, dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107500</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Es posible aplicar protocolos de cribado de cáncer de cérvix en la práctica diaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2623^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2624^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2624^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2623^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
