<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119231</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1780</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Self-Esteem in Adolescence: Analysis and Intervention Strategies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper reviews the current state of research on self-esteem by focusing on the factors that are relevant for the intervention in adolescents. Firstly, a conceptual distinction is made between self-concept, self-esteem and the perception of self-worth, and the relationship between them is analysed. It also considers the functioning of self-esteem on the basis of the contingencies of reinforcement and reviews their effects on the cognitive styles and behavioural coping. Secondly, it reviews the course of self-esteem on the basis of gender and discusses the role that contingencies of reinforcement play on its decline and instability during early adolescence. Thirdly, it reviews the findings that show the relationship of the shortcomings of self-esteem and the generation of a series of behavioural, emotional and health problems. Finally, the findings of the research on the intervention in self-esteem are reviewed, and the most useful strategies to help promote a change in teenagers are discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Caño González, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Naranjo, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se revisa el estado actual de la investigación sobre autoestima centrándose en los factores que son relevantes para la intervención en adolescentes. En primer lugar, se realiza una distinción conceptual y se analizan las relaciones entre autoconcepto, autoestima y percepción de autovalía. Se analiza también el funcionamiento de la autoestima en base a las contingencias de reforzamiento y se revisan sus efectos en los estilos cognitivos y conductuales de afrontamiento. En segundo lugar, se revisa la trayectoria de la autoestima en función del género y se analiza el papel que juegan las contingencias de reforzamiento en su disminución e inestabilidad durante la adolescencia temprana. En tercer lugar, se revisan los hallazgos que muestran la relación entre las deficiencias de autoestima y la generación de una serie de problemas de conducta, emocionales y de salud. Por último, se revisan los hallazgos sobre la intervención en autoestima y se analizan las estrategias más útiles para su cambio en la adolescencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int. j. psychol. psychol. ther. (Ed. impr.);12(3): 389-403, oct. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119231</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Autoestima en la adolescencia: análisis y estrategias de intervención</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1853</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3102</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38359</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
