<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142073</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Chemical constituents of the fermentation broth of the marine-derived fungus Penicillium roqueforti</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. The filamentous fungus Penicillium roqueforti is a well-known multifunctional cell factory of high added-value biomolecules. Aims. The objective of this work was to carry out a detailed analysis of the metabolites present in the culture broth of a new marine-derived Penicillium roqueforti strain isolated in the Canary Islands, Spain. Methods. The fungal biomass production was carried out in liquid-state fermentation, and after 10&#150;12 days of incubation at 22&#150;25 °C, the supernatant mycelia was separated by filtration, and the culture broth (12 l) was stored in a refrigerator at 4 °C for a subsequent liquid&#150;liquid extraction with dichloromethane (3×), in accordance with the modified Kupchan method. The volatile and semi-volatile organic compounds were separated by chromatography and analyzed using GC&#150;MS and NMR spectroscopy analyses. Results. Several volatile organic compounds involved in the fatty acid pathway were identified: a terpenoid, a cyclic dipeptide, phthalates, and an alkyl adipate. In addition, three categories of non-volatile compounds (alkanes, fatty acids and 1-alkanols) were identified by spectroscopy. The results show that the fermented broth of this fungal strain has no mycotoxins under the culture conditions applied.Conclusions. It is hoped that this chemo-specific information will offer critical input for improving the biotechnological applications of this filamentous fungus (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Toledo Marante, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera Bravo de Laguna, Irma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mioso, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. El hongo filamentoso Penicillium roqueforti es una fábrica celular multifuncional de biomoléculas de alto valor añadido. Objetivos. El objetivo de este trabajo fue realizar un estudio minucioso de los metabolitos presentes en el caldo de cultivo de una nueva cepa de Penicillium roqueforti de origen marino aislada en las Islas Canarias, España. Métodos. La producción de biomasa fúngica se llevó a cabo por fermentación en estado líquido. Tras 10-12 días de incubación a 22-25 °C se separó el micelio sobrenadante por filtración y el caldo de cultivo (12 l) se almacenó en un frigorífico a 4 °C hasta su posterior extracción líquido-líquido con diclorometano (×3) de acuerdo con el método modificado de Kupchan. Los compuestos orgánicos volátiles y semi-volátiles se caracterizaron por GC-MS y análisis espectroscópico (NMR). Resultados. Se identificaron varios compuestos orgánicos volátiles implicados en la ruta de los ácidos grasos, un terpeno, un dipéptido cíclico, varios ftalatos y un adipato de alquilo. Además, fueron identificados por espectroscopía tres tipos de compuestos no volátiles: alcanos, ácido grasos y 1-alcanoles. Los resultados mostraron que el caldo fermentado de esta cepa fúngica no presenta micotoxinas en las condiciones de cultivo empleadas. Conclusiones. Es de esperar que esta información quimio-específica aporte datos críticos para el progreso de las aplicaciones biotecnológicas de este hongo filamentoso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;32(3): 147-152, jul.-sept. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142073</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">/ Componentes químicos del caldo de fermentación del hongo de origen marino Penicillium roqueforti</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53110^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51884^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10993^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10601^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55478</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5394</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25375</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
