<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151827</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cystic degeneration of a prior uterine scar, risk of uterine rupture and literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess whether thinning of the lower uterine segment may increase the risk of obstetric complications and to determine the most effective method to study its correct measurement. Material and method: Literature review and case report. Results case report: We present the case of a pregnant woman with cystic degeneration of a uterine scar during pregnancy. The delivery occurred at term with no obstetric or neonatal complications. Comment, discussion and literature review: Ultrasound is considered an easy-to-use and reproducible technique with a well-defined methodology to assess a prior caesarean scar. Nevertheless, there is still no standardised technique to measure the lower uterine segment. Although most authors and some societies are in agreement, there is a lack of homogeneous studies and a definitive cut-off value. Despite published studies, there are no data to suggest that uterine scar dehiscence requires repair for proper healing. Conclusions: The most effective diagnostic method is hysterosonography. Measurement of the lower uterine segment in the third trimester could be useful to decide the route of delivery. A cut-off cannot be determined to predict the risk of uterine rupture or uterine scar dehiscence. Further studies are required to establish an adequate technique and a cut-off value to classify patients and aid decision-making on the route of delivery. The most clearly defined cut-off for the lower uterine segment is 3.5-3.2. The most important factor in imaging tests is to evaluate whether they are able to predict the obstetric complications that may occur, the risk of maternal or foetal compromise and the option of vaginal delivery. There are no studies on clinical decision-making according to these results (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Olazabal Loyola, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tellería Bereciartua, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urbistondo Lazpita, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lure Berregui, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Valorar si el adelgazamiento del segmento uterino inferior puede aumentar el riesgo de complicaciones obstétricas. Y determinar cuál es el método de elección para su correcta medición. Material y método: Revisión bibliográfica de la literatura y exposición de un caso clínico. Resultados, caso clínico: Presentamos el caso de una gestante con una degeneración quística de la cicatriz uterina que durante la gestación se resuelve: se produce el parto a término y sin complicaciones obstétricas ni neonatales. Comentario, discusión y revisión de la literatura: La ecografía se valora como una técnica fácil, reproducible y con una metodología ya definida a la hora de valorar una cicatriz anterior. Aun así, no disponemos de una técnica estandarizada para la medición del segmento uterino inferior. La mayoría de los autores y algunas sociedadesestán de acuerdo en que faltan estudios homogéneos y un punto de corte definitivo. A pesar de los estudios publicados, no hay datos que indiquen que la dehiscencia de la cicatriz uterina requiere reparación para su adecuada cicatrización. Conclusiones: El mejor método diagnóstico es la histerosonografía. La medición del segmento uterino inferior en el tercer trimestre podría ser útil para decidir la vía de parto. No se puede determinar un punto de corte para predecir el riesgo de rotura uterina o dehiscencia de cicatriz uterina. Se requieren más estudios para establecer una técnica adecuada y un punto de corte mediante el cual se pueda clasificar a las pacientes y tomar decisiones respecto a la vía de parto. El punto de corte más definido en los estudios para el segmento uterino inferior es 3.5-3.2. El factor más importante de las pruebas de imagen es valorar si son capaces o no de predecir las complicaciones obstétricas que pueden suceder, el riesgo de afectación materna o fetal y la opción de la vía vaginal. Faltan estudios para tomar decisiones clínicas conforme a estos resultados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);43(2): 73-80, abr.-jun. 2016. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151827</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Degeneración quística de la cicatriz uterina anterior, riesgo de rotura uterina y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14998^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30787^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3577^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13911^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7424^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31573</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23287^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
