<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043193</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Radiology, research and the future</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This subjective and polemic review of radiology reports and analyzes the status of the field today and discusses some of the positive aspects and some of the problems in routine imaging and in research, in both an individual/academic and an academic/commercial context. Topics approached include the position of radiology in medicine as a whole today; turf wars between radiologists and other disciplines despite the lack of radiologists; the position of non-radiologists in medical imaging and imaging research; the marginalization of radiologists in research; and the question whether radiologists will be needed in the future. Additional aspects are: How can recent advances in digital, cross-sectional, and interventional radiology be turned into real advantages for patient treatment and how should outcomes research influence imaging research? Who should enter imaging research, what is to be expected by and from researchers, and which major themes are promising in the future?</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rinck, Peter A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Esta revisión subjetiva y polémica describe y analiza el estado actual de la profesión. Trata algunos de los aspectos positivos así como los problemas encontrados en su ejercicio rutinario y en la investigación, tanto en el contexto individuo/académico como en el académico/comercial. Los temas abordados incluyen la posición de la radiología en medicina en la actualidad; las disputas entre radiólogos y profesionales de otras disciplinas sobre competencias, a pesar de la falta de radiólogos; el papel de los no-radiólogos en la práctica e investigación de diagnóstico por imagen; la marginalización de los radiólogos en el campo de la investigación; y la pregunta de si los radiólogos serán necesarios en un futuro. Otras preguntas planteadas son: ¿cómo podemos convertir los recientes avances en radiología digital, tomográfica, e intervencionista en ventajas reales para el tratamiento de pacientes?, ¿cómo deberían afectar a la investigación en radiología los estudios sobre el impacto del diagnóstico en el manejo del paciente?, ¿quién debería emprender la investigación en diagnóstico por imagen?, ¿qué puede esperar un investigador de esta actividad?, ¿qué deberíamos esperar de los investigadores?, y ¿cuáles son los temas más prometedores en este campo?</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);48(1): 8-13, ene.-feb. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043193</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Radiología: investigación y futuro</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12309^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4563^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12309^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22878^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29565^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
