<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144189</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dupuytren disease declared as occupational disease in dentist</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The stomatology is a medical speciality which consider treatment of mouth diseases and adjacent. As the odontologists, they are exposed to diverse occupational risk, such as repetitive movements, forced positions, physical and mental fatigue. Clinical case: 56 years old Man, with precedents of arterial hypertension, smoking, dyslipidemia, actinic queratosis in scalp. He continuously presents since 2006, tendon flexor injury in the right hand, valued by the service of prevention of occupational risks, receives treatment with poor clinical improvement and many recurrences. Since the above mentioned evolution, it was decided surgical intervention of the flexor tendon of 2nd finger of right hand with the diagnosis of Dupuytren&#146;s Disease. Later it is proposed to the National Institute of Health Service (INSS) an Occupational Disease, for a disorder derived from the occupational activity, which is admitted in 2007. For the multiple complications in spite of medical and surgical treatment and the days of sick leave in the company, the INSS proposes a permanent total incapacity for the usual profession, with favourable response. The analysis of the case, allows studying the evolution of pathologies in workers, relating the origin of the diseases with the occupational activity, emphasizing the courses of action if this suffering could be demonstrated as occupational disease. It also allows reviewing the different types of disability that can be generated from a disease and its repercussions in the occupational life of the worker (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hurtado Cabrera, Adriana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Fernández, Julián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Martín, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Finol Muñoz, Alexander</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivero Colina, Johanna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Julián</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La estomatología se define como una especialidad médica que se ocupa del tratamiento de enfermedades bucales y adyacentes. Al igual que los odontólogos, estos profesionales están expuestos a diversos riesgos laborales, tales como movimientos repetitivos, posturas forzadas, fatiga física y mental. Caso Clínico: Hombre de 56 años, con antecedentes de hipertensión arterial, tabaquismo, dislipemia, queratosis actínica en cuero cabelludo. Presenta desde el año 2006 de forma reiterada, lesión tendinoflexora en mano derecha, valorados por el servicio de prevención de riesgos laborales, recibe tratamiento rehabilitador con escasa mejoría clínica y múltiples recidivas. En vista de dicha evolución se decide intervención quirúrgica del tendón flexor del 2º dedo de mano derecha con el diagnóstico de Enfermedad de Dupuytren. Posteriormente se propone al Instituto Nacional de Seguridad Social (INSS) una Enfermedad Profesional. por tratarse de un trastorno derivado de la actividad laboral, siendo reconocida en el 2007. Por las múltiples complicaciones a pesar de tratamiento médico y quirúrgico y los días de baja en la empresa, el INSS propone una incapacidad permanente total para la profesión habitual, con respuesta favorable. El análisis del caso, permite estudiar la evolución de patologías en los trabajadores, relacionando el origen de las mismas con su actividad laboral, destacando la conducta a seguir si ese padecimiento fuese demostrado como enfermedad profesional. Así mismo, permite repasar los tipos de incapacidad que pueden generarse a partir de una enfermedad y sus repercusiones en la vida laboral del trabajador (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;24(3): 121-125, sept. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144189</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad de Dupuytren declarada como enfermedad profesional en odonto-estomatólogo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33129^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11249</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16923^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16923^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4447^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4447^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3828^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
