<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119368</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Orexin: clinical and therapeutic implications</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Recent research has reported the existence of a new class of neuropeptides, called orexins or hypocretins,  which are produced by a small group of neurons in the hypothalamus and whose actions are mediated by two types of receptors: OX1R and OX2R. More specifically, the orexinergic neurons have been located exclusively in cells in the lateral, dorsomedial and perifornical areas of the hypothalamus. Despite this highly specific anatomical origin, the orexinergic neurons are projected widely into a number of brainstem, cortical and limbic regions. Development. This fuzzy pattern of distribution of the orexinergic fibres would be indicating the involvement of this peptidic system in a wide range of functions; indeed, it has been related with the mechanisms that enable regulation of the sleep-wake cycle, the ingestion of food and drink, and some particular types of learning, such as learning certain preferences regarding tastes. It has also been suggested that upsets in the functioning of the orexinergic system would explain the appearance of certain clinical disorders like narcolepsy, obesity or addiction to drug of abuse. Conclusions. Further research will help to determine the functioning of orexinergic neurons and the interaction between the systems that regulate emotion, energetic homeostasis and the reward mechanisms, on the one hand, and the systems that regulate the sleep-wake cycle on the other. That knowledge would almost certainly make it possible to develop new drugs that, by acting upon the orexinergic system, would be effective in the treatment of sleep disorders such as insomnia or narcolepsy, eating disorders or drug addiction (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Risco, Severiano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mediavilla, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Se ha descrito recientemente una nueva clase de neuropéptidos, las orexinas, también llamadas hipocretinas,  producidos por un reducido grupo de neuronas hipotalámicas y cuyas acciones son mediadas por dos tipos de receptores, OX1R y OX2R. En concreto, las neuronas orexinérgicas se han localizado en exclusiva en células de áreas del hipotálamo lateral, dorsomedial y perifornical. A pesar de este origen anatómico tan localizado, las neuronas orexinérgicas se proyectan ampliamente a numerosas regiones troncoencefálicas, corticales y límbicas. Desarrollo. Este patrón difuso de distribución de las fibras orexinérgicas estaría indicando la intervención de este sistema peptídico en una amplia variedad de funciones y, de hecho, se ha relacionado con los mecanismos que permiten la regulación del ciclo sueño-vigilia, la ingesta de comida y de bebida y determinados aprendizajes como el aprendizaje de preferencias gustativas. Se ha sugerido también que la alteración en el funcionamiento del sistema orexinérgico  explicaría la aparición de determinados trastornos clínicos como la narcolepsia, la obesidad o la adicción a drogas de abuso. Conclusiones. Nuevas investigaciones ayudarán a conocer el funcionamiento de las neuronas orexinérgicas y la interacción entre los sistemas que regulan la emoción, la homeostasis energética y los mecanismos de recompensa con los sistemas que regulan el ciclo de sueño-vigilia. Se confía en que ese conocimiento permita desarrollar nuevos fármacos que, actuando sobre el sistema orexinérgico, sean eficaces en el tratamiento de las alteraciones del sueño como el insomnio o la narcolepsia, de los trastornos de la alimentación o de la drogadicción  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;58(3): 117-124, feb. 2014. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119368</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Orexina: implicaciones clínicas y terapéuticas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9485^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19260^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7211^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24382^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34359^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
