<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141730</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nebulized medication is not associated with nosocomial infections. A pilot study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Nebulized devices are commonly used in the treatment of respiratory infection, and other respiratory diseases. It has been reported nosocomial infections in cystic fibrosis patients as a result of the use of contaminated devices. However, little is known about nosocomial infections secondary to aerosolized therapy in COPD patients admitted for acute exacerbation. Methods. Thirty consecutive patients (13 males) were included. All of them received aerosolized medication. Each patient used their own facemask and nebulizer cup, which were stored in the room after its use. Samples from nebulizer cups were obtained on days 0, 4 and 7. In addition, sputum samples were obtained on day 0 (prior to any nebulization) and on day 7, and cultivated in enriched media. Results. Only nine nebulizer cups had positive microbiological cultures. Coagulase negative staphylococci (CoNS) were isolated in all cases. Sputum samples could be obtained in 27 patients. None grew CoNS after 7 days of aerosolized therapy. Gram-negative non-fermenting bacilli were isolated in three patients without concomitant grown in nebulizer cups. Conclusions. We did not find any nosocomial infection related to aerosolize medications in COPD patients admitted for acute exacerbation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peña, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Ruigómez, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Quero, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vinuesa, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos, Violeta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parra-Ruiz, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Badiola, Jon</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Medina, Leopoldo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los dispositivos para nebulizaciones se emplean frecuentemente en el tratamiento de las infecciones, y otras patologías respiratorias. Existen comunicaciones sobre infecciones nosocomiales en pacientes con fibrosis quística como resultado de la utilización de dispositivos contaminados. Sin embargo, poco se sabe acerca de las infecciones nosocomiales secundarias a la terapia en aerosol en pacientes con EPOC ingresados por exacerbación aguda. Métodos. Treinta pacientes consecutivos (13 varones) fueron incluidos. Todos ellos recibieron la medicación en forma de aerosol. Cada paciente utilizó su propia máscara y cazoletas de nebulización, que se dejaron en la habitación después de su uso. Las muestras de las cazoletas de nebulización se obtuvieron en los días 0, 4 y 7. Además, se obtuvieron muestras de esputo en el día 0 (antes de cualquier nebulización) y en el día 7, cultivándose en medio enriquecido. Resultados. Sólo nueve cazoletas de nebulización tuvieron algún cultivo positivo, siendo estafilococos coagulasa negativos (ECN) en todos los casos. Se obtuvieron muestras de esputo en 27 pacientes. En ningún caso se obtuvo crecimiento de ECN tras 7 días de tratamiento con aerosolterapia. Finalmente en tres pacientes se obtuvo crecimiento de un bacilo gramnegativo no fermentador en el esputo sin crecimiento en las muestras de las cazoletas de nebulización. Conclusiones. En nuestro estudio no se demostró ninguna infección nosocomial relacionada con el empleo de aerosolterapia en los pacientes con EPOC ingresados por exacerbación aguda (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;28(3): 154-156, jun. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141730</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">/ El empleo de nebulizaciones no se asocia con infecciones respiratorias nosocomiales. Un estudio piloto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
