<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055181</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">An Emergency Medicine blog utility as a communications tool: efficacy assessment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims and purpose: In 2006, SEMES Galicia approved the creation of an Emergency Medicine blog considering the more recent trends in communications. One year later, a study has been carried out to assess the interest level achieved. A number of aspects were analysed, such as, among others, the number of visits, degree of fidelity, dropout rate from the main access page and the relationship between the number of articles published and the number of visits. Material and methods: Descriptive, analytical and correlation studies were performed for the assessment of the number of visits, fidelity, dropout rate and geographical distribution of the readership. The relationship between the number of articles published and the number of visits to the blog was also examined. The Google Analytics and SPSS 12.0 for Windows software packages were used for the analyses. Results: The number of visits increased monthly over the year, from just one page visited in January to 3,800 in December. Spain was the origin of 93% of the visits, with Galicia occupying the first place (50%). The degree of fidelity was classed as medium, high or very high in 49% of the visits. When the accessed page was the home page 52% of the visitors did not drop out and visited several other sections of the blog. The level of frequentation was clearly related to the number of articles published (r = 0.9; p&lt;0.01). Conclusions: The interest on this blog has increased throughout the year studied. Most visitors evidenced a high degree of fidelity, repeating visits and accessing several other sections besides the home page. The number of visits was also directly related to the number of articles published. Visits originated all over the world but mainly in Spain (93%). The SEMES Galicia blog is a powerful and non-expensive communications tool (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díez Lindín, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Rodríguez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Lima, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bugarín González, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aramburu Vilariño, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fandiño Orgueira, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: En 2006 SEMES Galicia aprobó la creación de un blog de medicina de urgencias, adaptándose a las nuevas tendencias en comunicación. Después de un año realizó un estudio para determinar el interés que despertaba, cuyos objetivos fueron, entre otros, analizar su frecuentación, el grado de fidelidad, el porcentaje de abandono desde la misma página de acceso y la relación entre el número de artículos publicados y su frecuentación. Material y método: Se realizaron estudios descriptivos, analíticos y de correlación para determinar la frecuentación, la fidelidad, el porcentaje de abandono desde la página de acceso y la distribución geográfica de los lectores, así como la relación entre los artículos publicados y las visitas recibidas. Se utilizaron los programas Google Analytics y el SPSS 12.0 for Windows. Resultados: A lo largo del año creció la frecuentación del blog cada mes y pasó de una única página vista en el mes de enero a 3.800 en diciembre. El 93% de las visitas procedieron de España, sobre todo de Galicia (50%). La fidelidad fue media, alta o muy alta en el 49%. Cuando la página de acceso al blog era la principal, el 52% no lo abandonaba y se visitaban otras secciones. La frecuentación del blog estaba directamente relacionada con el número de artículos publicados (r = 0,9, p &lt; 0,01). Conclusiones: El interés por el blog ha crecido a lo largo del año. La mayoría de nuestros visitantes fueron fieles, pues repitieron sus visitas, y leyeron otras secciones además de la página principal. La frecuentación del blog estuvo directamente relacionada con el número de artículos publicados. El 93% de visitas procedieron de España. El blog SEMES Galicia es un poderoso y barato medio de comunicación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);19(4): 180-186, jul.-ago. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055181</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración de la eficacia de un blog de medicina de urgencias como medio de comunicación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3177</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37606^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4705</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
