<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-AOT-2131</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Economic impact of cognitive impairment and dementia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Increased life expectancy has had a corresponding socioeconomic impact due to the ageing population and, among other issues, has increased the incidence of diseases related to cognitive impairment, such as dementia. These changes particularly affect the most developed countries. Any analysis of economic costs aiming to study patients with health problems related to cognitive impairment or dementia should consider the reality of the distinct phases of these disorders and should be conducted from the perspective of the payer, that is, the publicly-funded healthcare system. Moreover, given the complexity and importance of cognitive impairment, there is a need to consider both direct healthcare costs, such as hospitalization measures, medication for the treatment of these diseases, specialist consultations, transport (eg, ambulances in severe cases), and direct non-healthcare costs (eg, professional care, nonprofessional care). In addition, indirect costs (related to productivity losses such as sick leave) must be considered for these diseases. Lastly, in 2014, the annual total mean cost (direct and indirect costs) in Spain for each patient with cognitive impairment, dementia and Alzheimer disease, was around &#128;30 000. A large part of this economic burden was due especially to indirect costs, which are usually a borne by affected individuals and their families (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cantarero Prieto, David</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Una mayor esperanza de vida ha venido acompañada del correspondiente impacto socioeconómico de una población más envejecida y, entre otras cuestiones, la incidencia de enfermedades relacionadas con el deterioro cognitivo como la demencia. Todo ello afecta de manera especial a los países más desarrollados. En todo caso, cualquier análisis de costes económicos que tenga como objeto a los pacientes afectados por problemas de salud relacionados con dicho deterioro cognitivo y demencias debe tener en cuenta la realidad de sus distintos grados evolutivos, así como efectuarse desde la perspectiva, al menos, del financiador, es decir, del sistema sanitario público. Además, en un tema de gran complejidad y relevancia como este, se precisa considerar en estas enfermedades tanto sus costes de tipo directo sanitarios (medidas de hospitalización, medicamentos para el tratamiento de estas enfermedades, consultas con especialistas, transportes -p. ej., ambulancias en caso de gravedad-, etc.) como los de tipo directo no sanitarios (cuidados profesionales, cuidados no profesionales, etc.). A todo ello, también han de sumarse los costes indirectos, relacionados con las pérdidas de productividad (bajas laborales, etc.) para este tipo de enfermedades. Por último, y en lo que se refiere al año 2014, puede afirmarse que el coste anual medio total (costes directos e indirectos) en España por cada paciente afectado por deterioro cognitivo, demencia y Alzheimer estaría en torno a los 30.000 euros. Gran parte de dicha carga económica se refiere especialmente a los costes de tipo indirecto que suelen recaer en el individuo afectado por estas enfermedades y sus familiares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);52(supl.1): 58-60, jun. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-AOT-2131</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto económico del deterioro cognitivo y la demencia</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
