<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128452</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychology: in search of identity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper follows the discussion started in previous issues (Carrobles, 2012,  013; Sánchez Reales, Prado Abril &amp; Aldaz Armendáriz, 2013) following thecreation of the new General Health Psychologist profession. We reflect on curricular itineraries and professional training in the field of Health Psychology, considering the narrative that has accompanied this process and its impact in shaping professional identities of Health Psychology. We emphasize the importance of the historical, contextual and legislative aspects and we deepen on the current status of Clinical Psychology in the National Health System, highlighting current opportunities that allow the construction of a coherent professional training itinerary on Health Psychology (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Reales, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prado Abril, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aldaz Armendáriz, José A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo continúa el debate iniciado en números anteriores (Carrobles, 2012, 2013; Sánchez Reales, Prado Abril y Aldaz Armendáriz, 2013) a raíz de la creación de la nueva profesión de Psicólogo General Sanitario. Reflexionamos sobre los itinerarios curriculares que capacitan profesionalmente en el ámbito de la Psicología Sanitaria, considerando la narrativa que ha acompañado este proceso y su repercusión en la configuración de las identidades profesionales de la Psicología Sanitaria. Enfatizamos la importancia de los aspectos históricos, contextuales y legislativos y profundizamos sobre el estatus actual de la Psicología Clínica en el Sistema Nacional de Salud, destacando las oportunidades actuales que permiten la construcción de un itinerario formativo y profesional coherente de Psicología Sanitaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;22(1): 153-160, ene.-abr. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128452</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Psicología Sanitaria: en busca de identidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3499</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12023^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36312</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12021^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1543^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
