<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92518</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Study of tear function and the conjunctival surface in diabetic patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: This study was performed to investigate whether different grades of diabeticretinopathy correlate with tear and ocular surface function in diabetic patients withoutsubjective symptoms of dry eye.Methods: A total of 129 eyes of 72 patients without dry eye, assessed using McMonnies questionnairewere recruited to the study. The tear film and ocular surface were evaluated usingthe Schirmer test, tear film break-up time (BUT), fluorescein and lissamine green stainingtest, and conjunctival impression cytology. The results were analysed.Results: A normal Schirmer test and BUT was obtained in 51 and 67% of the eyes of diabeticspatients, respectively. Fluorescein and lissamine green stainingwere negative in 81 and 95%of the eyes. The area and density of goblet cells was 580.46±370 m2 and 235.58±109.03goblets cell/mm2, respectively.Conclusions: Diabetic retinopathy patients without subjective symptoms of dry eye and normalSchirmer and BUT test showed pathological grades of squamous metaplasia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Rodríguez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Figueroa-Ortiz, L. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Ben, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Campos, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Analizar la relación entre la función lagrimal y la superficie conjuntival con losdiferentes grados de retinopatía en pacientes diabéticos sin sintomatología subjetiva de ojoseco.Métodos: Se estudiaron 129 ojos de 72 pacientes sin sintomatología subjetiva de ojo secosegún el cuestionario de Mc Monnies. La secreción lagrimal y la superficie ocular fueron evaluadasmediante la prueba de Schirmer, la prueba de tiempo de rotura de la película lagrimal(BUT), los grados de tinción con fluoresceína y verde lisamina, y la citología conjuntival deimpresión. Se analizaron los resultados obtenidos.Resultados: El 51 y el 67% de los ojos de pacientes diabéticos mostraron un test de Schirmery BUT dentro de la normalidad. La tinción con fluoresceína y verde lisamina fue negativarespectivamente en el 81 y el 95% de los ojos. Los valores de área y densidad media de célulascaliciformes fueron 580,46±370 m2 y 235,58±109,03 cél. caliciformes/mm2.Conclusión: Los pacientes con retinopatía diabética sin sintomatología subjetiva de ojo seco,aun cursando con la prueba de Schirmer y BUT normal, pueden presentar grados patológicosde metaplasia escamosa(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;86(4): 107-112, abr. 2011. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92518</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de la función lagrimal y la superficie conjuntival en pacientes diabéticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3954^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8855</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27958^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7942^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3252^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
