<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126144</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Development and Validation of a Questionnaire (the IRA-AGHN) to Assess Teachers&amp;#8223; Knowledge of Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this study was to develop a questionnaire, called IRA-AGHN, to assess infant and primary school teachers&#146; knowledge of Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder. The psychometric properties of this questionnaire were examined in a sample of 752 teachers aged between 20 and 64 years (M = 41.57; SD = 9.69). These teachers were employed at 84 randomly selected schools in the Autonomous Community of the Basque Country and Navarre. The factor validity, internal consistency, temporal stability, convergent validity and external validity of the instrument were all analysed.  The results suggest that the IRA-AGHN is a valid and reliable measure for assessing teachers&#146; knowledge of ADHD (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Soroa, Marian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balluerka, Nekane</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gorostiaga, Arantxa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente estudio consistió en desarrollar un cuestionario para evaluar el nivel de conocimiento que los docentes de educación infantil y primaria presentan con respecto al Trastorno por Déficit de Atención con Hiperactividad, el IRA-AGHN. Las propiedades psicométricas del instrumento fueron examinadas en una muestra de 752 maestros cuyo rango de edad oscilaba entre 20 y 64 años (M = 41.57; DT = 9.69). Los maestros pertenecían a 84 centros escolares de la Comunidad Autónoma del País Vasco y Navarra, los cuales fueron seleccionados de forma aleatoria. Se examinaron la validez factorial, la consistencia interna, la estabilidad temporal, la validez convergente y la validez externa del instrumento. Los resultados sugieren que el IRA-AGHN es un instrumento válido y fiable para evaluar el nivel de conocimiento de los docentes con respecto al TDAH (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;30(3): 1035-1043, sept.-dic. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126144</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Elaboración y validación de un cuestionario (el IRA-AGHN) para evaluar el conocimiento de los maestros acerca del Trastorno por Déficit de Atención con Hiperactividad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
