<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80614</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-2074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Down syndrome: an assessment of infant psicomotor development and its impact on social and familial integration</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There are currently no specific tests to observe and assess development in infants with Down syndrome (DS), so follow-up programs and performance assessments are required. Moreover, such programs encourage early and appropriate intervention to ensure psychomotos and cognitive development to the child´s full potential, paving the way for integration at school, at work, in society and within the family. This paper describes a longitudinal prospective study analysing and describing psychomotor and cognitive development to the child´s full potential, paving the way for integration at school, at work, in society and within the family. This paper describes a longitudinal prospective study analysing and describing psychomotor and cognitive assessment in patients with DS in the first two years of life. The included subjects were infants with DS born in the Hospital MAterno Infantil Ramón Sardá (HMIRS) as well as referrals from other institutions aged 1 day to 2 years. The subjects were evaluated over a 12-month period, with the Escala de Evaluación del Desarrollo Psicomotot (EEDP-Psychomotor Development Assessment Scale) by Rodríguez et al. and the Escala Argentina de Inteligencia Sensorio-Motriz (EAIS-Argentine Scale of Sensory-Motor Intelligence by Oberman et al. administered monthly. This provided a mean age of acquisition of early motor milestones and a measurement of deviation from the population-wide mean in every area (language, motor skills, coordination, and social skills) with ensuing detection of the areas most compromised. A survey assessed the emotional, economic and social impact these children had on their families, and whether this impact might influence their development (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Antoniutti, Ana Inés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrari, Alejandra María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aspres, Norma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guardiol, Ana Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schapira, Iris Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bedacarratz, Roxana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la actualidad no existen pruebas específicas para la observación y evaluación del desarrollo de niños con Sandrome de Down (SD). Esta situación obliga a llevar adelante programas de seguimiento y a evaluar su nivel de rendimiento. Por otro lado, facilita una intervención temprana y adecuada a fin de favorrecer el pleno desarrollo de sus potencialidades psicomotoras y cognitivas, abriéndoles camino hacia la integración escolar, laboral, social y familiar. Se realiza un estudio prospectivo longitudinal, analítico y descriptivo de la evaluación del desarrollo psicomotor y descriptivo de la evaluación del desarrollo psicomotor y cognitivo en pacientes con SD durante los dos primeros años de vida. Se incluyen niños con SD nacidos en el Hospital Materno Infantil &#147;Ramón Sardá&#148; (HMIRS) y aquellos derivados al mismo desde otras instituciones, de 1 día a 2 años de edad. Se evaluaron durante un período de doce meses (12 meses) y se controlaron mensualmente utilizando la Escala de Evaluación del Desarrollo Psicomotor (EEDP), de S. Rodríguez y cols. Y la Escala Argentina de Inteligencia Sensorio Motriz (EAIS), de A. Oiberman y cols. Se podrá así observar la edad media en que se producen los hitos iniciales del desarrollo psicomotor y valorar cuánto se desvían de la media poblacional en cada área (lingüística, motriz, de coordinación, social), detectando también las áreas más comprometidas. Se estima mediante una encuesta el impacto emocional, económico y social que provocan estos niños en sus familias, y si esto influye de alguna manera en su desarrollo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SD, Rev. med. int. Síndr. Down (Ed. castell.);11(1): 2-8, mar. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80614</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Down: evaluación del desarrollo psicomotor en menores de dos años y el impacto hacia la integración social y familiar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12034^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23905^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9241^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6278^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
