<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105517</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Giant duodenal ulcer perforation: a case of innovative repair with an antrum gastric patch</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Backgrounds: the treatment of a perforated giant duodenal ulcer (GUDs) represents a formidable surgical challenge regarding the duodenal wall defect repair in severe peritonitis setting. A high incidence of dehiscence and hospital mortality (15-40%- has been reported with the majority of the techniques). We report a case of GUDs perforation successfully treated with a subtotal gastrectomy and a gastric patch with the remnant antrum, for repairing the duodenal defect. Case report: a 63-years-old man with antecedents of peptic ulcer disease presents a large duodenal ulcer perforation with 48 hrs delay and associated with severe peritonitis and a retroperitoneal collection. A subtotal gastrectomy with Billroth II reconstruction and reconstruction of the duodenal defect with a patch of the remnant antrum was carried out. The patient was discharged at 17th postoperative day with good tolerance. Discussion: the duodenal defect repair with a patch of the remant antrum, represents a valid alternative in similar circumstances. To our knowledge, it appears to be the first clinical description of this technique(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bellver, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rotellar, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valentí, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baixauli, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cienfuegos, Javier A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Lizoain, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arredondo, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedano, Nicolás</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: el tratamiento de un ulcus duodenal gigante (UDG; &gt; 2 cm) perforado entraña una gran dificultad técnica, por la reparación del gran defecto duodenal; y por la peritonitis sobreañadida. Todas las técnicas descritas se asocian con un índice elevado de dehiscencias y una mortalidad del 15-40%. Describimos por primera vez el caso de un UDG perforado, tratado mediante una gastrectomía subtotal y con una plastia del antro gástrico remanente. Caso clínico: varón de 63 años que se interviene de un UDG perforado en la 2ª porción duodenal asociado con peritonitis severa y disección de la gotiera parieto-cólica derecha retroperitoneo. Se realiza gastrectomía tipo Bilroth II y reparación del defecto duodenal mediante una plastia con la pared del antro gástrico remanente. El paciente fue dado de alta a los 17 días. Discusión: la reparación del defecto duodenal con una plastia del antro gástrico, puede ser una opción muy valiosa en situaciones similares a la descrita. En nuestro conocimiento, se trata de la primera descripción clínica de esta técnica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;104(8): 436-439, ago. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105517</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perforación de ulcus gigante duodenal: reparación innovadora mediante una plastia del antro gástrico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10728^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5884^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12141^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13666^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5884^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7991^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13666^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7991^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4446^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13666^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4446^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4446^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
