<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037490</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Internal consistency and validity of the spanish version of the St. George´s Respiratory Questionnaire for use in patients with clinically stable bronchiectasis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: To analyze the reliability and validity of the        St. George&#146;s Respiratory Questionnaire (SGRQ) for use in        patients with clinically stable bronchiectasis.        MATERIAL AND METHODS: The SGRQ (50 items on 3 scales&#151;        symptoms, activity, and impact) was administered to 102        patients (mean [SD] age, 69.5 [8.7] years; 63% men) with        clinically stable bronchiectasis. Disease severity was classified        according parameters such as airflow obstruction (forced        expiratory volume in 1 second), colonization by Pseudomonas        aeruginosa, extent of bronchiectasis, symptoms, daily quantity        of sputum, and number of exacerbations. Internal consistency        (Cronbach&#146;s alpha and correlation between items and between        item and scale), concurrent validity (correlation between items        and clinical variables), predictive validity (correlation between        items and severity), and construct validity (factorial analysis of        main components) were assessed.        RESULTS: The internal consistency of the SGRQ was        excellent (Cronbach&#146;s alpha between 0.81 and 0.87 for the        different scales, and 0.90 for the overall score). Concurrent        validity was high, as correlations between items and clinical        variables were significant and followed the expected        distribution. The SGRQ differentiated between degrees of        disease severity, regardless of the clinical variable used. The        factorial analysis showed a construct of 4 factors that were        only moderately similar to the original structure of the        questionnaire, due mainly to inclusion of a small number of        questions with conditioned response and others with low        discriminatory capacity.        CONCLUSIONS: The SGRQ shows excellent concurrent        and predictive internal consistency and validity, though        restructuring of the original construct would be advisable        before use in patients with stable bronchiectasis</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez García, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perpiñá Tordera, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Román Sánchez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soler Cataluña, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Analizar la fiabilidad y validez del St. George&#146;s        Respiratory Questionnaire (SGRQ) para su uso en pacientes        afectados de bronquiectasias estables.        MATERIAL Y MÉTODOS: El SGRQ (50 ítems en 3 escalas:        síntomas, actividad e impacto) se administró a 102 pacientes        (edad media ± desviación estándar de 69,5 ± 8,7 años; 63%        varones) con bronquiectasias clínicamente estables. Se clasificó        la gravedad según diferentes parámetros: obstrucción al        flujo respiratorio (volumen espiratorio forzado en el primer        segundo), colonización por Pseudomonas aeruginosa, extensión        de las bronquiectasias, síntomas, cantidad de esputo        diario y número de agudizaciones. Se calcularon la consistencia        interna (alfa de Cronbach y correlación ítem-ítem e        ítems-escala), la validez concurrente (correlación ítems-variables        medidas), la validez predictiva (correlación ítems-parámetros        de gravedad) y la validez de constructo (análisis        factorial de componentes principales).        RESULTADOS: La consistencia interna del SGRQ fue excelente        (alfa de Cronbach entre 0,81 y 0,87 para las distintas        escalas, y 0,90 para la puntuación total). La validez concurrente        fue elevada, ya que las correlaciones ítems-variables        medidas fueron significativas y se distribuyeron de la forma        prevista. El SGRQ permitió diferenciar adecuadamente los        distintos grados de gravedad de la enfermedad independientemente        de los parámetros utilizados. El análisis factorial        mostró un constructo de 4 factores que se asemejaba tan        solo de forma moderada a la estructura original del cuestionario,        sobre todo por la inclusión de preguntas con bajo        porcentaje de respuestas obligadas y otras con bajo poder        discriminatorio.        CONCLUSIONES: El SGRQ presenta una excelente consistencia        interna y validez tanto concurrente como predictiva,        si bien sería recomendable una reestructuración previa del        constructo original para su uso en pacientes con bronquiectasias        estables</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;41(3): 110-117, mar. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037490</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consistencia interna y validez de la versión española del St. George&#146;s Respiratory Questionnaire para su uso en pacientes afectados de bronquiectasias clínicamente estables</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2017^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2017^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2017^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
