<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165623</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of diachronic relationships in successful and unsuccessful behaviors by world fencing champions using three complementary techniques</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to investigate diachronic relationships in successful and unsuccessful behaviors by world fencing champions using three complementary techniques: T-pattern analysis, lag sequential analysis, and polar coordinate analysis. We employed a nomothetic, point, multidimensional observational design in which we analyzed 24 bouts fenced by six world fencing champions in 2014. The actions were recorded and coded using LINCE software. The results revealed a series of behaviors that were significantly associated with successful outcomes, and also identified actions that contributed to poorer performance. One key conclusion to be drawn from the study is that the use of these complementary techniques is perfectly feasible and holds great potential in the field of sport. Lag sequential analysis of occurrences at lag 0 (co-occurrences) and analysis of basic T-patterns provided tactical insights into the different fencing actions employed. This analysis is focused on the actions and reactions of each fencer and his rival during each exchange. Insights into combat strategy, by contrast, were provided by lag sequential analysis of occurrences at lags -1 to -5 and lags +1 to +5, analysis of T-pattern clusters, and polar coordinate analysis. In the last case, we observed how prospective and retrospective behaviors, reflected in the modification or extension of certain behaviors during each bout, improved the efficacy of actions performed throughout the competition (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tarragó, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Anguera, M Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Sanchis, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arana, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lapresa, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio fue investigar las posibles relaciones diacrónicas en las conductas de éxito y fracaso en campeones del mundo de esgrima desde tres técnicas analíticas complementarias: detección de Tpatterns, análisis secuencial de retardos y análisis de coordenadas polares. Se utilizó un diseño observacional nomotético, puntual y multidimensional en el registro de 24 asaltos de los seis esgrimistas campeones del mundo de 2014. Se utilizó como instrumento de registro el software LINCE. Los resultados revelaron una serie de comportamientos que estaban estadísticamente asociados con la mejora del rendimiento deportivo y también se identificaron acciones que contribuyeron a empeorarlo. Una de las principales conclusiones que pueden extraerse de este estudio es que el uso de estas técnicas complementarias de análisis es perfectamente factible y tiene un gran potencial en el ámbito del deporte. El análisis secuencial en el retardo 0 (coocurrencias) y de las configuraciones básicas de los T-patterns proporcionan conocimientos tácticos sobre las diferentes acciones de esgrima empleadas. Este análisis se produce en el marco de la interacción entre las técnicas ejecutadas por cada tirador y su rival en cada acción del asalto. El análisis secuencial en los retardos -1 a -5 y +1 a +5, las agrupaciones de clusters de los T-patterns y el análisis de coordenadas polares contribuyen al análisis de la estrategia de combate. En este caso, se observaron cómo las conductas prospectivas y retrospectivas determinaron la consolidación o modificación de ciertos comportamientos durante cada asalto, con el fin de mejorar la eficacia de las acciones realizadas a lo largo de toda la competición (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;33(3): 471-485, oct. 2017. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165623</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de las relaciones diacrónicas en los comportamientos de éxito y fracaso de campeones del mundo de esgrima utilizando tres técnicas complementarias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d133</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56062^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29653</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3194</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
