<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153962</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-9891</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish validation of the social stigma scale: Community Attitudes towards Mental Illness</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The stigma against people with mental illness is very high. In Spain there are currently no tools to assess this construct. The aim of this study was to validate the Spanish version of the Community Attitudes towards Mental Illness questionnaire in an adolescent population, and determining its internal consistency and temporal stability. Another analysis by gender will be also performed. Material and methods. A translation and back-translation of the Community Attitudes towards Mental Illness was performed. A total of 150 students of between 14 and 18 years-old were evaluated with this tool in two stages. Internal consistency was tested using Cronbach &amp;#945;; and intraclass correlation coefficient was used for test-retest reliability. Gender-stratified analyses were also performed. Results. The Cronbach &amp;#945; was 0.861 for the first evaluation and 0.909 for the second evaluation. The values of the intraclass correlation coefficient ranged from 0.775 to 0.339 in the item by item analysis, and between 0.88 and 0.81 in the subscales. In the segmentation by gender, it was found that girls scored between 0.797 and 0.863 in the intraclass correlation coefficient, and boys scored between 0.889 and 0.774. Conclusions. In conclusion, the Community Attitudes towards Mental Illness is a reliable tool for the assessment of social stigma. Although reliable results have been found for boys and girls, our results found some gender differences in the analysis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villellas, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguel, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Julia, Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valduciel, Tamara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Morales, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Franco, Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Franco, María Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casellas, Diana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Haro, Josep Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ochoa, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Zambrano, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas-Anguera, Emma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vila-Badia, Regina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arenas, Oti</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balsera, Joaquim</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El estigma hacia las personas con una enfermedad mental es muy elevado. En España no existen instrumentos actuales para evaluar este constructo. El objetivo del presente estudio es validar la versión española del cuestionario Community Attitudes towards Mental Illness en una población de adolescentes, estudiando la consistencia interna del instrumento, así como la estabilidad temporal. Este último análisis se realizará también por género. Material y métodos. Se llevó a cabo una traducción y retrotraducción del Community Attitudes towards Mental Illness. Se evaluaron con este instrumento un total de 150 alumnos de Enseñanza Secundaria Obligatoria, de entre 14 y 18 años, en 2 momentos. Se analizó la consistencia interna del instrumento mediante el &amp;#945; de Cronbach, y la fiabilidad test-retest con el coeficiente de correlación intraclase. Se realizaron análisis estratificados por género. Resultados. El &amp;#945; de Cronbach fue de 0,861 para la primera evaluación y de 0,909 para la segunda evaluación. Los valores del coeficiente de correlación intraclase oscilan entre 0,775-0,339 en el análisis de ítem por ítem, y entre 0,88-0,81 en las subescalas. En la segmentación por género encontramos que las puntuaciones en el coeficiente de correlación intraclase en el grupo de chicas está entre 0,797-0,863 y en los chicos entre 0,889-0,774. Conclusiones. En conclusión podemos afirmar que el Community Attitudes towards Mental Illness es un instrumento fiable para la evaluación del estigma social. A pesar de resultar fiable de la misma manera para chicos y para chicas, se han encontrado algunas diferencias en el análisis por género (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psiquiatr. salud ment. (Barc., Ed. impr.);9(3): 150-157, jul.-sept. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153962</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación al castellano de la escala de estigma social: community Attitudes towards Mental Illness en población adolescente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8779^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10167</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8779^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54298</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
