<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144676</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-7279</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Visual perception is the ability to discriminate and interpret visual stimuli. In this regard and in the absence of visual acuity problems that interferes with perception, Clinical Neuropsychology assess and try to rehabilitate those changes that occur in the process of discrimination and interpretation of what we see as a result of brain dysfunction. In this way, in the field of geriatrics, the normal process of aging results in changes in different aspects of visual perception and visuospatial functions. It is also at this stage of life in which is frequent the occurrence of degenerative processes, acute episodes of stroke that may cause changes in different aspects of the perception process. This presentation will be divided into two parts: The first part, introduce a review of the implications neuroanatomical and cognitive models of visual perception process, alterations and signs of visual perception and processes of brain damage that commonly occur with changes in visual perception in the field of geriatrics. Alteration in the interpretation of what we see related not only to the perception of the stimulus, but the space. At this sense, we may have difficulty not only in perception due to injuries that occur, but also communication problems, because sometimes the connection is broken between the visual and verbal system. Cognitive or neuropsychological rehabilitation is constantly evolving. Based on scientific evidence of its effectiveness we can see that a young science is continually expanding. Only by using techniques which have been demonstrated as effective or at least with signs of it, we can help older people for example that following a stroke or head trauma have lost the ability to pay attention to a part of the visual field. In this sense, of all the cognitive functions, visual perception is the one that have had a smaller number of both experimental and clinical studies and is the field of hemineglect rehabilitation in which have been focused most of such studies. We need further studies about the effectiveness of the techniques we are using. Here, we will introduce some aspects to consider when designing efficacy studies. Therefore in this second part of the presentation, we will review the knowledge we have about the effectiveness of neuropsychological rehabilitation of disturbances in visual perception based on evidence and from it, we will show a proposal of treatment for improving functional disorders resulting from such dependence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jacas, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:source>Inf. psiquiátr;(220): 55-62, abr.-jun. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144676</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rehabilitación de la percepción visual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9654^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9654^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9654^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9654^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d381^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5993^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5993^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15197^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d381^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15197^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5993^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5993^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
