<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88903</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Valoration of the risk of exposition to cytostatic medications in the Hospital of Ciudad Real</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">During the year 2007-2008, is carried out a study from the exposition risk to cytostatic medications to value: The areas in which are manipulated cytostatic, the tasks with exposition risk, the personnel exposed in each one of the working up and the EPIs that are used in each task, with the purpose of determining the preventive measures so much collective as singular to adopt to minimize the risk of the workers&#146; exposition in the whole chain of manipulation of cytostatic (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Riesco García, M. Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marroquí López-Clavero, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Durante el año 2007-2008, se realiza un estudio del riesgo de exposición a medicamentos citostáticos para valorar: Las áreas en las cuales se manipulan citostáticos ,las tareas con riesgo de exposición, el personal expuesto en cada uno de los procedimientos de trabajo y los EPIs que se utilizan en cada tarea, con la finalidad de determinar las medidas preventivas a adoptar tanto colectivas como individuales, para minimizar el riesgo de exposición de los trabajadores en toda la cadena de manipulación de citostáticos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;55(215): 82-85, abr.-jun. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88903</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración del riesgo de exposicióna medicamentos citostáticos en elHospital General de Ciudad Real</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32517</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52851^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6925</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
