<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043278</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Physiotherapist's strategical intervention in the family environment of the disabled patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Disability implicates a bio-psycho-social state in which are involved both, the patient and the family members around. In disabled patients, the caregiver plays a key role in the therapeutic process, so that he/she must take after the patient and his environment needs. The caregiver suffers a high number of physical and psychological problems ocassionated mostly by the permanent attention to his/her disabled family member. The strategy that we propose in this essay would help the physiotherapist to a better understanding the importance of the family environment in the physiotherapist intervention. This strategy is based on psychopedagogy that increases the learning of new habilities in all the family aspects of life</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Catalán Matamoros, D. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Guerrero, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Cruzado y Barba, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Arrondo, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillén Romero, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montoro Fernández, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La discapacidad implica un estado bio-psico-social en el que se encuentran claramente implicados tanto el paciente como los familiares que le rodean. En pacientes discapacitados el "cuidador" ocupa un aspecto clave en el proceso terapéutico, por ello tiene que favorecer las necesidades tanto del paciente como de su entorno. El cuidador padece un alto número de problemas físicos y psicológicos ocasionados, en gran parte, por la situación de cuidados continuada que debe proporcionar a su familiar discapacitado. La estrategia que se presenta en este artículo ayudaría al fisioterapeuta a entender mejor la importancia del entorno familiar en la intervención fisioterápica. Dicha estrategia tiene una base psicopedagógica que incentiva el aprendizaje de nuevas habilidades en todos los aspectos de la vida familiar</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);28(1): 35-40, ene. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043278</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervención estratégica del fisioterapeuta en el entorno familiar del paciente discapacitado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30935^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11797</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36312</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29653</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
