<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100751</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A national survey on current practice of preanaesthetic assessment in elective surgery patients in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To analyse the preanaesthetic assessment prior to elective surgery in hospitals of the Spanish National Health Care System. Methods. A prospective cross-sectional descriptive observational survey was performed. Primary variables were patient characteristics, type of preanaesthetic evaluation and the evaluator, as well as type of support the evaluator received during patient assessment. Secondary variables included the number of operating rooms available for elective surgery, as well as preanaesthesia clinic facilities. Data were analysed by univariate and bivariate descriptive analysis. Results. A total of 214 hospitals of the Spanish Health Care System were invited to participate, and 203 centres responded, with all of them having a preanaesthesia assessment clinic. In 183 of them (90%), elective surgerypatients were interviewed prior to their surgical intervention, and in 202 hospitals (99.5%) a anaesthesiologist physician performed the interview. In 128 hospitals (63%), anaesthesiologists were helped during preoperative assessment by nurses alone (49%) or together with auxillary nurses (14%). In 68 of hospitals (33%) they were supported only by auxillary nurses and in 7 hospitals (3%) they obtained no help at all. In 14 centres (7%) anaesthesia nurses assessed patients directly (under supervision of an anaesthesiologist physician). Hospitals with a higher volume of patients performed more preanaesthesia interviews. Hospitals with more running operating rooms received more nurse support in the preanaesthesia assessment clinic. Conclusions. Some kind of preanaesthesia assessment clinic exists in all Anaesthesia Departments of public Spanish hospitals, although there are differences in design and organisation(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mata, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrera, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Atanassoff, P. G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valldeperas, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Analizar la práctica común en las consultas externas preanestésicas de los pacientes sometidos a cirugía electiva en los hospitales públicos españoles. Material y métodos. Estudio observacional descriptivo transversal. Las variables principales de estudio fueron: características de los pacientes, tipo de evaluación preanestésica realizada, profesional evaluador y tipo de apoyo durante el proceso de evaluación. Como secundarias se contemplaron: número de quirófanos de cirugía programada y número de consultas preanestésicas. Se realizó análisis descriptivo uni y bivariante. Resultados. Fueron invitados a participar 214 hospitales del Sistema Nacional de Salud. Los 203 que finalmente participaron en la encuesta, disponían de consultas externas preanestésicas. En 183 de ellos (90%) pasan por dicha consulta todos los pacientes candidatos a intervención quirúrgica programada y en 202 (99,5%) la valoración preanestésica es realizada por un anestesiólogo del equipo. Reciben apoyo de una enfermera en 128 hospitales (63%), sola (49%) o junto a un auxiliar de enfermería (14%). En 68 de ellos (33%) es un auxiliar de enfermería el que ayuda en la consulta preoperatoria, mientras que en 7 centros (3%) no cuentan con ningún apoyo. En 14 de los centros (7%) las enfermeras realizan en la consulta valoraciones preanestésicas de forma autónoma tuteladas por un anestesiólogo. Centros con un mayor número de pacientes disponen de mayor número de consultas preanestésicas. Hospitales con un mayor número de quirófanos funcionantes reciben en mayor proporción el apoyo de una enfermera en la consulta preoperatoria. Conclusiones. La instauración de algún tipo de consulta externa preanestésica está asumida por la totalidad de los Servicios de Anestesiología de los hospitales públicos españoles. Aunque hay diferencias en el diseño y la organización(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;59(6): 299-305, jun.-jul. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100751</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Encuesta sobre la situación actual de la evaluación preoperatoria en los hospitales de España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d787^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4414^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4414^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35120</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d787^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201207</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
