<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147216</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of the present study was to provide a bibliometric review of the scientific production in handball. Publications were collected from the Web of Science and MEDLINE databases for the period 1900-2012 and 1950-2012 respectively. The analysis assessed the document types and languages, annual trend of published articles, average number of authors per article, research disciplines and topics, trend of publication in research disciplines, major journals, author productivity, and country distribution of publications. Only the papers focused mainly on handball were considered, for a total of 373 articles under study. There was a significant increase in number of published articles and average number of authors per article in recent years, which allows considering handball an expanding research field both in terms of scientific production and research collaboration. Sports medicine was the most active research discipline, the studies focused on injuries the main topic. In the last two decades there was a remarkable annual growth in the disciplines of sport training theory, anthropometry and biomechanics. European authors participated in 87.94% of the articles, Norwegians the most active, revealing Europe&#146;s big dominance in handball research. This study provides baseline information on future research directions for researchers and academic institutions interested in handball (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez, Miguel-Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sampaio, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El propósito de este estudio fue realizar una revisión bibliométrica de la producción científica en balonmano. Las publicaciones se recopilaron de las bases de datos Web of Science y MEDLINE en el periodo 1900-2012 y 1950-2012 respectivamente. El análisis evaluó el tipo de documento, idioma, tendencia anual de publicación, número medio de autores por artículo, disciplinas y temas de investigación, tendencias de publicación en las disciplinas de investigación, principales revistas, productividad de autores y distribución por países. Solo los artículos centrados principalmente en balonmano fueron considerados, para un total de 373 artículos. En los últimos años se observó un incremento significativo en el número de artículos publicados y en el número medio de autores por artículo, lo que permite considerar al balonmano como un área de investigación en expansión, tanto en términos de producción científica como en colaboración entre investigadores. La medicina deportiva fue la disciplina con más publicaciones, siendo los estudios de lesiones el tema principal. En las últimas dos décadas se observó un destacable crecimiento anual en las disciplinas de teoría del entrenamiento deportivo, antropometría y biomecánica. En el 87,94% de los artículos participaron autores europeos, siendo los noruegos los más prolíficos, lo que revela el dominio de Europa en la investigación en balonmano. Este estudio aporta información sobre potenciales líneas de investigación para el futuro, tanto para investigadores como para instituciones académicas interesadas en el balonmano (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;15(3): 145-154, oct. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147216</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50088</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54358</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31204</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12077^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
