<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152487</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Osteomyelitis of the maxilla in a patient with Malignant Infantile Osteopetrosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Osteopetrosis is characterized by a considerable increase in bone density resulting in defective remodeling, caused by failure in the normal function of osteoclasts, and varies in severity. It is usually subdivided into three types: benign autosomal dominant osteopetrosis; intermediate autosomal recessive osteopetrosis; and malignant autosomal recessive infantile osteopetrosis, considered the most serious type. The authors describe a case of chronic osteomyelitis in the maxilla of a 6-year-old patient with Malignant Infantile Osteopetrosis. The treatment plan included pre-maxilla sequestrectomy and extraction of erupted upper teeth. No surgical procedure was shown to be the best to prevent the progression of oral infection. Taking into account the patient's general condition, if the patient develops severe symptomatic and refractory osteomyelitis surgery should be considered. The patient and his family are aware of the risks and benefits of surgery and its possible complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aburad de Carvalhosa, Artur</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tarquinio Marinho, Kelly Cristine</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borges, Álvaro Henrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Magdalena Giovani, Élcio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Souza Castro, Paulo Henrique de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ricci Volpato, Luiz Evaristo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La osteopetrosis se caracteriza por un aumento considerable de la densidad ósea que resulta en un remodelado defectuoso, causado por mal funcionamiento de los osteoclastos, de severidad variable. Usualmente se divide en 3 tipos: osteopetrosis dominante autosómica benigna, osteopetrosis recesiva autosómica intermedia y osteopetrosis infantil recesiva autosómica maligna, considerado el tipo de mayor gravedad. Los autores describen un caso de osteomielitis crónica en el maxilar superior de paciente de 6 años de edad con osteopetrosis infantil maligna. El plan de tratamiento incluyó secuestrectomía y exondoncia de los dientes superiores erupcionados. Ningún procedimento quirúrgico se ha comprobado que sea superior a otros en la prevención del avance de infecciones bucales. Tomando en cuenta las condiciones generales del paciente al desarrollar osteomielitis refractaria y sintomática severa, la cirugía debe ser considerada. El paciente y sus familiares deben ser conscientes de los riesgos y beneficios de la cirugía, así como de sus posibles complicaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;38(2): 96-100, abr.-jun. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152487</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La osteomielitis crónica en pacientes con osteopetrosis maligna infantil. Presentación de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10203^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13546^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13896^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3829^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13896^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14471^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13896^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13896^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32048^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10203^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13546^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10199^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10199^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14471^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
