<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-32456</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intervention in writing composition strategies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present an intervention in writing revision proccesses in a 1st High School classroom, ordinary and computational lessons, composed by 16 students, compared with another two groups (control) whom only received ordinary curriculum. The intervention consisted in the implementation of a process and text planing program focused on revision processes, during a school year, a weekly session into school language timetable. We reached a significative improvement of the experimental group in productivity and coherence in essay task, but not in description nor narration (which require less mental effort), and in reflective disposition. These data suggest that automatization of mechanical aspects of revision and improvement of control of substantive ones, possibly because of computer and pen and pencil uses, and because of the over-exact application of revision estrategies, indicated by essays improvement and writing reflectivity. The need of more specifically additional studies in revision tasks desing and intervention considering its splinter and concrete aspects is suggested (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García, Jesús-Nicasio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias-Gundín, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta una intervención en procesos de revisión del mensaje escrito en un aula de 1° de ESO, ordinaria y de informática (con ordenador), compuesta por 16 alumnos comparada con otros dos grupos (control) que sólo recibieron curriculum ordinario. La intervención consistió en la aplicación de un programa de planificación del proceso y del texto focalizado en los procesos de revisión, durante un curso escolar, una sesión a la semana en horario escolar de Lengua. Se obtiene una mejoría significativa del grupo experimental en productividad y coherencia en la redacción, pero no en la descripción ni en la narración (que requieren menor esfuerzo mental), y en la disposición reflexiva. Los datos sugieren la automatización de 1ª revisión de aspectos mecánicos y aumento del control de los sustantivos, debido posiblemente al uso del ordenador y de lápiz y papel, y por la aplicación minuciosa de las estrategias de revisión indicado por la mejora de la redacción y de la reflexividad hacia la escritura. Se sugiere la necesidad de estudios adicionales más específicos en el diseño de tareas de revisión y de intervención considerando aspectos separados y concretos de la misma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);16(2): 194-202, mayo 2004. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-32456</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervención en estrategias de revisión del mensaje escrito</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15354</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12025</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14876</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
