<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92737</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Healthcare in the 21st Century: The challenge of multicultural care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this paper is to reflect on the challenge that the Spanish Health System must face in tackling the issue of healthcare in a multicultural society like ours. At the same time, it also aims to analyse the different situations and difficulties that immigrants encounter in gaining access to the health system and meeting their health-related needs. Given the changes that our society is undergoing, professionals must be aware what our attitude and position are with regard to cultural diversity. This will help us understand, respect and value the importance of nursing training in cultural skills (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bennasar-Veny, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Artigas-Lelong, Berta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El propósito de este artículo es reflexionar sobre el reto que debe asumir el sistema sanitario español, para afrontar unos cuidados de salud en una sociedad multicultural como la nuestra. Por otro lado, también pretende analizar las distintas situaciones y dificultades por las que deben pasar las personas inmigrantes para acceder al sistema sanitario y satisfacer sus demandas de salud. Sin duda, los cambios que se están viviendo en nuestra sociedad hacen necesario que los profesionales conozcamos cuáles son nuestras actitudes y cómo nos posicionamos respecto a la diversidad cultural. Ello nos ayudará a entender, respetar y valorar la importancia de la formación en competencias culturales de los profesionales de enfermería (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;18(1): 42-46, ene. 2009. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92737</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La salud en el siglo XXI: El reto de los cuidados multiculturales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6448^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32786</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3320</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16689</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16091^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200901</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
