<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76144</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Special surfaces for managing pressure in pediatrics (II). Choice, assigned algorithm (TARISE) and management models</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bed sores among children are an adverse effect provoked by the application of new technology adapted to pediatrics. Special surfaces for managing pressure in pediatrics are a preventive measure effective to avoid the development of these lesions. So that children benefit from this preventive measure, it must be adapted to their specific circumstances. In order for this to occur, it is fundamental to know: the specific characteristics which differentiate children from adults, and the type of special surfaces for managing pressure in pediatrics which are available on the market and to evaluate their appropriateness and effectiveness. The Group of Nurses to Improve Quality in Pediatrics at the University Clinical Hospital in Valencia has developed some tools which make it possible to manage and assign different sizes and types of special surfaces for managing pressure in pediatrics by means of a scientific method (Tarise). These are based on anthropometric measurements (Pediatric Space table) for each age range, the risk to develop a bed sore or skin ulcer due to pressure, the presence of a bed sore, the pathological seriousness and the type of special surfaces for managing pressure in pediatrics(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Balaguer López, Evelin</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Molina, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las UPP en la población pediátrica son un efecto adverso provocado por la aplicación de las nuevas tecnologías adaptadas al contexto pediátrico. Las Superficies Especiales del Manejo de la Presión (SEMP) constituyen una medida preventiva eficaz para evitar el desarrollo de estas lesiones. Para que la población pediátrica se vea favorecida por dicha medida se ha de adaptar a sus circunstancias propias. Para ello es fundamental conocer las características diferenciales respecto a la población adulta, los tipos de SEMP pediátricas que nos ofrece el mercado y evaluar su idoneidad y efectividad. El Grupo de Enfermería para la Mejora de la Calidad en Pediatría (GEMCP) del Hospital Clínico Universitario de Valencia ha desarrollado unas herramientas que permiten gestionar y asignar diferentes tamaños y tipos mediante un método científico (Tarise). Se basa en las medidas antropométricas (Tabla Espacio Pediátrico) de cada rango de edad, el riesgo de desarrollar una UPP, la presencia de las mismas, la gravedad de la patología y el tipo de SEMP(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;32(4): 254-260, abr. 2009. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76144</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Superficie especial del manejo de la presión (SEMP) pediátrica (y II). Elección, algoritmo de asignación (TARISE) y modelos de gestión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1532^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1532^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1532^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1532^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16645</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3380^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3380^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
