<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041990</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of the Spanish version of the Social Functioning Scale</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Social functioning as an outcome variable in therapeutic interventions with schizophrenic patients has been a relatively neglected area. The Social Functioning Scale (SFS) may be a good instrument to evaluate different therapeutical strategies for the rehabilitation of the schizophrenic patient. The aim of this paper is to validate the Spanish version of the SFS. Material and methods. The Spanish version of the SFS was administered to 85 patients with schizophrenia (DSM-IV), and 120 healthy volunteers (60 unemployed and 60 employed). Results. Cronbach&#146;s alpha is between 0.69 and 0.80 in every subscale. Item-total correlations show higher internal consistency than in the validation of the original English version of the SFS. Factorial analysis suggests it could be appropriate to use a mean score from every subscale to make a total score. Discriminant analysis differentiates between patients and controls in a statistically significant way. In order to facilitate the interpretation of the results and their clinical use, a conversion of the direct scores into standardized ones was carried out. Conclusions. Results from three samples show that the Spanish version of the Social Functioning Scale is reliable, valid, and sensitive</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Olivares, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El funcionamiento social, usado como una variable de resultado en las intervenciones terapéuticas con esquizofrénicos, ha sido un área relativamente descuidada. La Escala de Funcionamiento Social (EFS) puede ser un instrumento de gran utilidad a la hora de evaluar la eficacia de las distintas estrategias empleadas en la rehabilitación del paciente esquizofrénico. En el presente estudio se valida la versión en castellano de la EFS. Material y métodos.Se administró la versión española de la escala a 85 sujetos esquizofrénicos (DSM-IV), 60 individuos sanos en paro y 60 sujetos sanos que trabajaban activamente en el momento de la evaluación. Resultados. Los coeficientes alfa se muestran uniformemente elevados (entre 0,69 y 0,80). Las correlaciones entre cada ítem y el total muestran una consistencia interna superior al obtenido en la validación de la versión original inglesa. El anáilis factorial sugiere que puede ser apropiado extraer una puntuación media de todas las subescalas para dar una puntuación total. El análisis discriminante diferencia de un modo muy significativo entre el grupo de esquizofrénicos y los dos grupos control. Para facilitar el uso clínico de la escala y la interpretación de los resultados se decidió convertir las puntuaciones directas de cada subescala en puntuaciones tipificadas. Conclusiones.Los resultados demuestran que la versión española de la Social Functioning Scale (SFS), la EFS, es fiable, válida y sensible</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;33(4): 216-220, jul.-ago. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041990</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación en castellano de la Social Functioning Scale (Escala de Funcionamiento Social)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7980</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12946</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
