<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057157</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of the metabolic syndrome among schizophrenic patients hospitalized in the Canary Islands</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Schizophrenic patients have a higher        standardized mortality rate than that expected for the        rest of the population. The prevalence of the metabolic        syndrome is high among them, this increase coronary        risk twofold to fourfold. This study aims to find out the        prevalence of the metabolic syndrome among patients        with schizophrenia and schizoaffective disorder who have        been admitted to an acute psychiatric ward and the        sociodemographic, evolutive and psychopharmaceutical        variables related to it. We also hope to establish the extent        of coronary risk and its relationship with the metabolic        syndrome.        Method. Cross-sectional observational study including        136 adult patients over 18 years of age. They were        admitted in the year 2004 to the Hospital Universitario        de Gran Canaria Dr Negrín, with the diagnosis of schizophrenia        or SCID-I validated schizoaffective disorder.        The metabolic syndrome and coronary risk were defined        according to NCEP-ATP III criteria.        Results. The prevalence of the metabolic syndrome        in the population studied is 36 % (95 % CI: 29.4 to 45.6).        The metabolic syndrome is associated to an older age        (p &lt; 0.05). Abdominal obesity is more prevalent among        women (p &lt; 0.05). Coronary risk in the next 10 years is        moderate in 52.3 % of cases and high in 2.9 %. Increase        in risk is associated to antipsychotic intake and to suffering        metabolic syndrome (p&lt;0.05).        Conclusions. The prevalence of the metabolic        syndrome among schizophrenic patients is high and it        entails moderate to high coronary risk</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Araña Moreno, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León Pérez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Fleta, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Touriño González, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los pacientes esquizofrénicos tienen una        tasa estandarizada de mortalidad más elevada que la esperada        para el resto de la población. El síndrome metabólico        tiene una alta prevalencia entre ellos, que aumenta entre        dos y cuatro veces el riesgo coronario. El objetivo del presente        estudio es conocer la prevalencia del síndrome metabólico        en pacientes con esquizofrenia y trastorno esquizoafectivo        ingresados en una unidad de agudos y las variables        sociodemográficas, evolutivas y psicofarmacológicas que se        relacionan con ella. Se pretende también conocer el riesgo        coronario y su relación con el síndrome metabólico.        Método. Estudio observacional transversal. Se incluyen        136 pacientes mayores de 18 años ingresados durante el año        2004 en el Hospital Universitario de Gran Canaria Dr. Negrín        con diagnóstico de esquizofrenia o trastorno esquizoafectivo        validado mediante el SCID-I. Síndrome metabólico y riesgo        coronario se han definido según criterios del NCEP-ATP III.        Resultados. La prevalencia de síndrome metabólico en        la población estudiada es del 36 % (intervalo de confianza        [IC] del 95 %: 29,4 a 45,6). El síndrome metabólico se asocia        con una mayor edad (p &lt; 0,05). La obesidad abdominal se        asocia con el sexo femenino (p&lt;0,05). El riesgo coronario en        los próximos 10 años es moderado en el 52,3 % de los casos        y alto en el 2,9 %. El incremento del riesgo se asocia con la        toma de antipsicóticos y con el padecimiento del síndrome        metabólico (p&lt;0,05).        Conclusiones. La prevalencia del síndrome metabólico        en la población de pacientes esquizofrénicos estudiados es        alta y supone un riesgo coronario moderado-alto</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;35(6): 359-367, nov.-dic. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057157</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia del síndrome metabólico en pacientes esquizofrénicos hospitalizados en Gran Canaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12036^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3344^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3345^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29162</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3344^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12036^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
