<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041014</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Need for undergraduate teaching in geriatrics: contribution of a new educational model</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: to analyse knowledge of geriatrics among students of the Medical Faculty of Castilla-La Mancha University (UCLM) in Spain.         Matherial and methods: we performed a survey of 93 fifth-year medical students at the UCLM Medical Faculty before and after they attended a 6-week problem-based training program in geriatrics.         Results: after the learning period, the students had a better knowledge of geriatrics, including its utility, methods, and patient characteristics. At the end of the program, 59.8% were able to identify elderly individuals with potentially reversible, recent-onset disability as the principal users of acute geriatric units; those with stroke, hip fracture or functional decline as the main users of geriatric rehabilitation units and those with cognitive or functional decline, confusion, falls or multiple disorders/medications as the main users of outpatient clinics. Students changed their belief that confusion, depression, urinary incontinence and falls have to be managed by geriatricians. After the program students believed that geriatricians managed more elderly people with good functional status and acute, potentially treatable diseases such as stroke.         Conclusions: education in geriatrics gives medical students a better understanding of the principal users of geriatric medicine and the methodology used, and prepares them to provide better care to the elderly</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Luengo-Márquez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero-Rizos, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abizanda-Soler, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Jurado, P. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Sebastiá, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: analizar la adquisición de conocimientos en la especialidad de Geriatría en estudiantes de la Facultad de Medicina de la Universidad de Castilla-La Mancha (UCLM).         Material y métodos: a 93 alumnos de quinto curso de la Facultad de Medicina de la UCLM se les realizó una encuesta antes y después de recibir la asignatura (6 semanas teoricoprácticas basadas en el aprendizaje por problemas).         Resultados: después de recibir la asignatura de Geriatría, los alumnos mejoraron sus conocimientos sobre la especialidad, tanto en su utilidad como en la metodología y en la tipología de los principales beneficiarios. Al concluir, el 59,8% identificó al anciano con discapacidad reciente potencialmente recuperable como principal beneficiario de una unidad geriátrica de agudos. Los principales beneficiarios de una unidad de recuperación funcional fueron ancianos con ictus, fracturas de cadera y pérdida de funcionalidad. Las afecciones que más se benefician de la atención en consultas externas son el deterioro cognitivo, el síndrome confusional agudo, la pérdida funcional, las caídas y la pluripatología-polifarmacia. Tras la asignatura se produjo un cambio de opinión en los alumnos hacia que los geriatras son quienes deben abordar el síndrome confusional agudo, el trastorno depresivo, la incontinencia urinaria y las caídas. Tras la formación, hay una tendencia a que más ancianos en situación aguda, con buena función previa y con una enfermedad potencialmente recuperable, como el ictus, sean atendidos por un geriatra.         Conclusiones: la enseñanza de pregrado de la Geriatría mejora el conocimiento de la especialidad, aclara cuál es el tipo de paciente que más se beneficia de su metodología de trabajo y prepara a los futuros médicos para prestar mayor calidad en la asistencia a pacientes ancianos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);40(5): 275-284, sep.-oct. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041014</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Necesidad de la enseñanza de pregrado en geriatría: aportaciones de un nuevo modelo educativo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5993^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13724^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12958^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32065^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4572^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3499^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
