<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141322</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">One more step in the study of social inequalitiesin primary care provision from a population-based perspectiveOne more step in the study of social inequalitiesin primary care provision from a population-based perspective</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Evaluation of Primary Care (PC) must include different perspectives. The objective of the study was to know the assessment of the PC in Catalonia and detecting whether or not a pattern of social inequality exists, through user&#146;s experience. A cross-sectional study was conducted, in a representative sample (n = 13,292) of the Catalonia population (aged 15), who identify a reference professional. It was studied an index of experience with PC by personal variables and variables about the reference professional. Negative binomial regression models (bivariate and multivariate) were adjusted to obtain the prevalence ratios and confidence intervals of 95%. The index gained an average of 71 (scale 0-100). A rating above 70 was associated with higher age, greater number of visits in the last year, more time with the same professional and living in an area of lower population density. Items with lower scores: telephone attention and availability of mental health services. We concluded that factors associated with a better experience are associated with more frequent visits to professionals. We did not detect social inequalities (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Berra, Silvina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Sanz, Maica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borrell, Carme</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rocha, Kátia B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pasarín, M. Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La evaluación de la atención primaria (AP) debe contemplar diversas perspectivas. El objetivo del trabajo fue conocer la valoración de la AP en Cataluña y detectar o descartar un patrón de desigualdad social a partir de la experiencia de la población. Se realizó un estudio transversal a una muestra (n = 13.292) representativa de la población residente en Cataluña &gt; 15 años, que identificaba un profesional de referencia. Se estudió un índice de experiencia con la AP según variables personales y del profesional de referencia. Se ajustaron modelos multivariados de regresión binomial negativa para la obtención de las razones de prevalencia y sus intervalos de confianza del 95%. Se obtuvo un índice medio de 71 (escala 0-100). Un índice &gt; 70 se asoció a: mayor edad, más visitas en el último año, más tiempo con el profesional y residir en áreas menos densas. Los ítems con menor puntuación fueron: atención telefónica y disponibilidad de servicios de salud mental. Se concluye que los factores asociados con una mejor experiencia están relacionados con una mayor frecuentación de los profesionales. No se detectaron desigualdades sociales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);137(supl.2): 49-54, dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141322</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Un paso más en el estudio de las desigualdades sociales en la provisión de atención primaria desde la perspectiva de la población</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33118</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52958^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6448^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
