<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043625</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analgesia unit subcutaneous pumas at home</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">AIM: To evaluate the feasibility and security of  the use of an elastomeric pump with 270 mg of        Ketorolac and 300 mg of Tramadol in a saline solution for subcutaneous administration at a rate of 1 ml/hour for analgesic treatment of moderate  pain in Orthopaedic Ambulatory Surgery.  MATERIAL AND METHODS: A retrospective  study with 250 patients was performed. At the end of surgery, Multitrate 2C1154K (Baxter®)  subcutaneous infusor was connected for three  days. We analysed a Phone Score based on: general status, pain level, bleeding, diet,  treatment fulfillment, fever &gt; 38º C and satisfactory wound evolution. According to the  Phone Score obtained we divided the evolution  into three groups: Group I: normal evolution,  correct level of analgesia and good general state of patient; Group II: new call needed; Group III: medical treatment needed. Supplemental oral  analgesia and secondary effects were also  evaluated.  RESULTS: (95.2%) of calls were in Group I; (4%) were in Group II and (0.8%) in Group III. The need of supplemental oral analgesia was  12.2%. The secondary effects observed were:  dizziness: (1.7%); headache: (1.4%); vomiting: (1.4%); nausea: (0.8%); itching: (0.8%);  drowsiness: (0.8%); accidental removal: (0.5%);  no secondary effects: (92.6%).        CONCLUSION: the use of the elastomeric pump Multitrate 2C1154K (Baxter®) for subcutaneous  administration of Ketorolac 270 mg and Tramadol 300 mg at 1 ml/hour ratio is useful and safe for moderate postoperative pain control in  Orthopaedic Ambulatory Surgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barberá Alacreu, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viñoles Pérez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Estudillo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Maqueda, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayala Gallego, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soliveres Ripoll, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Evaluar la efectividad y seguridad del uso de un sistema de bomba elastomérica        con una solución de Ketorolaco 270 mg y  Tramadol 300 mg en suero fisiológico por vía        subcutánea a 1 ml/hora en el tratamiento del dolor postoperatorio moderado-severo en        Cirugía Ambulatoria Ortopédica. MATERIAL Y MÉTODOS: Se realiza un estudio        retrospectivo sobre 250 pacientes sometidos  a diversas intervenciones de Cirugía Ortopédica        Ambulatoria. Después de la intervención son  conectados al infusor subcutáneo Multitrate        2C1154K (Baxter®) con la pauta propuesta  durante tres días. Los parámetros analizados        son: Score Telefónico basado en estado general, dolor, sangrado, tolerancia, cumplimiento del        tratamiento, fiebre &gt; a 38º C y estado de la herida. Según el Score Telefónico obtenido la evolución  se clasifica en Grupo I: evolución normal, correcto nivel de analgesia y buen estado general  del paciente; Grupo II: necesidad de nueva llamada y Grupo III: necesita atención médica. Se evalúa la necesidad de analgesia de rescate y la descripción de los efectos secundarios. RESULTADOS: Llamadas del Grupo I: 95,2%;  Grupo II: 4%; llamadas del Grupo III: 0,8%. Necesidad de analgesia de rescate: 12,2%. Efectos secundarios: mareo: 1,7%; cefalea 1,4%; vómitos: 1,4%; náuseas: 0,8%; picor: 0,8%;  sueño: 0,8%; arrancado 0,5%; no efectos secundarios: 92,6%.  CONCLUSIONES: El uso de analgesia invasiva  domiciliaria por vía subcutánea, mediante una infusión de 1 ml/hora de una mezcla de Ketorolaco y Tramadol es eficaz y seguro para el  control del dolor moderado-severo en Cirugía Ortopédica Ambulatoria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;10(3): 132-137, sept. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043625</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Analgesia domiciliario con infusores subcutáneos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10162^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14538^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19209^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19209^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34399^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
