<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043969</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Malignant mixed mullerian tumor of the fallopian tube (heterologous carcinosarcoma)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Malignant mixed mullerian tumor is anuncommon neoplasm of the female genital tract. The Fallopiantube is most uncommon site. Patients and Methods:The reported case corresponds to a 66 year old woman withabdominal pain. A total hysterectomy with bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy was performed. Results: The neoplasmdistended and distorted the left Fallopian tube. On cut sectionthe tube was filled and expanded by a soft tumor withhemorrhagic areas. Microscopically it was composed ofmalignant epithelial and stromal elements with foci of cartilaginousand rhabdomyosarcomatous differentiation. Conclusions:Four theories have been put forward to explain theorigins of the Fallopian tube carcinosarcomas. C-erbB-2over-expression in both epithelial and mesenchymal componentssuggests a common carcinogenic mechanism for bothcomponents and supports the conversion-histogenesis hypothesisimplicating a dominant role for epithelial component</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Báez Perea, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beltrán Ruiz-Henestrosa, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Añón Requena, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Gómez, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabello Torres, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Gómez, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El Tumor mülleriano mixto maligno esun tumor de localización ginecológica poco común. Latrompa de Falopio es la localización menos frecuente.Material y Métodos: El caso que nosotros describimoscorresponde a una paciente de 66 años con dolor abdominaly presencia de una masa pélvica en el anejo izquierdo. Serealiza histerectomía y doble anexectomía. Resultados: Laneoplasia distendía y distorsionaba la trompa de Falopioizquierda. Al corte, la trompa estaba ocupada por un tumorblando con áreas hemorrágicas. Microscópicamente eltumor estaba compuesto por elementos malignos epitelialesy estromales con focos diferenciación rabdomiosarcomatosay cartilaginosa. Conclusiones: Cuatro teorías han sidoformuladas para explicar la histogénesis tumoral de los carcinosarcomasde trompa de Falopio. La sobreexpresión dec-erbB-2 en ambos componentes, epitelial y mesenquimal,sugiere un mecanismo carcinogénico común y apoya lahipótesis de histogénesis por conversión implicando unpapel dominante del componente epitelial</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;38(2): 109-111, abr.-jun. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043969</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumor mülleriano mixto maligno (carcinosarcoma heterólogo) de trompa uterina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5286^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7225^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13717^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31300^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2340^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
