<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058095</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Predictors of improved left ventricular systolic function after surgical revascularization in patients with ischemic cardiomyopathy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. Although it is known that the presence of myocardial viability predicts an increase in ejection fraction after revascularization in patients with ischemic cardiomyopathy, little is known about other predictive factors. The aim of this study was to identify variables that can predict an increase in ejection fraction after coronary revascularization surgery in patients with ischemic cardiomyopathy and a viable myocardium. Methods. The study included 30 patients (mean age 61.6 [11] years, one female) with ischemic cardiomyopathy (ejection fraction &amp;#8804;40%) who fulfilled criteria for myocardial viability. All underwent ECG-gated single-photon emission computed tomography before and after surgery. Results. An increase in ejection fraction &amp;#8805;5% occurred after surgery in 17 of the 30 patients (56.6%). These patients were characterized by the presence of left main coronary artery disease (P&lt;.004), a large number of grafts (P&lt;.03), a high perfusion summed difference score (P&lt;.012), a low end-diastolic volume (P&lt;.013), and a low end-systolic volume (P&lt;.01). An end-systolic volume &lt;148 mL and a summed difference score &amp;#8805;4 gave the best predictive model (P=.001, R2=0.73) for an increase in ejection fraction. Conclusions. In patients with ischemic cardiomyopathy and a viable myocardium, the main determinants of an increase in ejection fraction after revascularization surgery were low levels of left ventricular remodeling and myocardial ischemia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Candell-Riera, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Igual, Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero-Farina, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castell-Conesa, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León, Gustavo de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguadé-Bruix, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Aunque se sabe que la presencia de viabilidad miocárdica es predictora de mejoría de la fracción de eyección poscirugía de revascularización en los pacientes con miocardiopatía isquémica, es menos conocido si hay otros factores predictores. El objetivo de este estudio ha sido analizar las variables predictoras de mejoría de la fracción de eyección después de la revascularización coronaria quirúrgica en los pacientes con miocardiopatía isquémica y presencia de miocardio viable. Métodos. Se estudió a 30 pacientes (edad media, 61,6 ± 11 años, una mujer), con miocardiopatía isquémica (fracción de eyección &amp;#8804; 40%) y criterios de viabilidad, mediante tomografía cumputarizada por emisión de fotón único sincronizada con el electrocardiograma, antes y después de la cirugía. Resultados. En 17 de los 30 pacientes (56,6%) hubo un aumento &amp;#8805; 5% de la fracción de eyección poscirugía. Estos pacientes se caracterizaron por tener más enfermedad del tronco común (p &lt; 0,004), mayor número de injertos (p &lt; 0,03), mayor suma diferencial de puntuación perfusión (p &lt; 0,012), menor volumen telediastólico (p &lt; 0,013) y menor volumen telesistólico (p &lt; 0,01). El mejor modelo predictor (p = 0,001; R2 = 0,73) del aumento de la fracción de eyección poscirugía &amp;#8805; 5% fue un volumen telesistólico &lt; 148 ml y una suma diferencial de puntuación de perfusión &amp;#8805; 4. Conclusiones. El menor remodelado ventricular izquierdo y la isquemia miocárdica en los pacientes con miocardiopatía isquémica y viabilidad miocárdica son los principales determinantes en la mejoría de la fracción de eyección poscirugía revascularizadora (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;60(9): 943-951, sept. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058095</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variables predictoras de mejoría de la función sistólica ventricular izquierda después de la cirugía de revascularización coronaria en pacientes con miocardiopatía isquémica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33888^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13706^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9396</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31288^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
