<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118607</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish adaptation of the Creative Potential and Practised Creativity scale (CPPC-17) in the workplace and inside the organization</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: This study follows the theoretical framework put forward by Hinton on creative potential and practised creativity. The objective was to adapt the 17-item Creative Potential and Practised Creativity scale into Spanish and examine its psychometric properties. Method: The study sample was made up of 975 Spanish employees (48.5% men and 51.5% women). Results: After performing a confirmatory factor analysis, the findings revealed a three-factor structure: Creative potential, Practised creativity and Perception of organizational support. Furthermore, appropriate reliability was found for all three factors as ell as initial evidence of construct validity in relation to certain external correlates and a series of scales measuring workaholism, irritation, burnout and personality. Conclusions:The present scale may prove ideal for adequately identifying Creative potential, Practised creativity and  Perceived organizational support (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vigil-Colet, Andreu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prizmic-Kuzmica, Aldo-Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boada-Grau, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-García, José Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: este estudio se enmarca dentro de la propuesta de Hinton sobre el potencial creativo y la creatividad practicada. El  objetivo fue realizar la adaptación al español de la escala Creative Potential and Practised de 17 ítems y analizar sus propiedades psicométricas. Método: los participantes de la presente investigación son 975 empleados españoles (48,5% hombres y 51,5% mujeres). Resultados: los resultados obtenidos demuestran, después de realizar análisis confirmatorio, una estructura constituida por tres factores: potencial creativo, creatividad practicada y percepción de apoyo organizacional. Además, los tres factores obtenidos tienen una fiabilidad adecuada e igualmente se constatan evidencias de validez si se toman como referencia algunos correlatos externos y algunas escalas que hacen referencia a la adicción al trabajo, la irritación, el burnout  y la personalidad. Conclusiones: la presente escala puede resultar idónea para identificar de manera apropiada el potencial creativo, la creatividad practicada y el apoyo organizacional percibido (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);26(1): 55-62, ene.-abr. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118607</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación española de la escala de Potencial Creativo y de la Creatividad Practicada (CPPC-17) en el trabajo y en la organización</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10662^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10167^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16054^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10167^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16359^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
