<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056996</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-5981</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Implication of the thermografy in the diagnosis of the sympathetic reflex dystrophy: with regard to a clinic case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Sympathetic Reflex Dystrophy or Complex Regional Syndrome Type I is pathology of difficult diagnostic and treatment    especially due to the ignorance that exists on the    physiopathogenicity of the disease, and that can have serious    consequences.    We presented/displayed the case of a woman of 45 years    diagnosed of this syndrome after undergoing metacarpial    fracture of 5º of right hand. Although no of the complementary    test is definitive, we have made the pursuit with    infrared thermography, observing a parallelism between    the clinical and thermal improvement the three first months of physical therapy and medical treatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fuertes González, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antón Andrés, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blázquez Sánchez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antón Andrés, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Margüello, A. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Rebollo, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Distrofia Simpático Refleja o Síndrome Regional Complejo tipo I es una patología de difícil diagnóstico y tratamiento    especialmente debido al desconocimiento que    existe sobre la fisiopatogenia de la enfermedad, y que    puede tener consecuencias graves.    En el siguiente artículo describimos un caso de distrofia    simpático refleja de 5 meses de evolución de origen postraumático.    Mujer de 45 años diagnosticada de este síndrome    tras sufrir fractura de 5º metacarpiano de mano    derecha. Aunque ninguna de las pruebas complementarias    es definitiva, nosotros hemos realizado el seguimiento    con termografía infrarroja, observando un paralelismo entre    la mejoría clínica y termográfica en los tres primeros meses de tratamiento rehabilitador y farmacológico</dc:description>
<dc:source>Patol. apar. locomot. Fund. Mapfre Med;5(1): 68-74, ene.-mar. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056996</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implicación de la termografía en el diagnóstico de la distrofia simpático refleja: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12448^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7436</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23479^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6382^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
