<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144634</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Antimicrobial resistance, virulence factors and genetic lineages of hospital-onset methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus isolates detected in a hospital in Zaragoza</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: MRSA population dynamics is undergoing significant changes, and for this reason it is important to know which clones are circulating in our nosocomial environment. Materials and methods: A total of 118 MRSA isolates were collected from clinical samples from patients with previous hospital or healthcare contact (named as hospital-onset MRSA (HO-MRSA)) during a one year period. Susceptibility testing was performed by disk diffusion and microdilution. The presence of resistance genes and virulence factors were tested by PCR. All isolates were typed by SCCmec, spa and agr typing. PFGE and MLST were applied to a selection of them. Results: Eighty-three HO-MRSA isolates (70.3%) were resistant to any antibiotic included in the macrolide&#150;lincosamide&#150;streptogramin B group. Among these isolates, the M phenotype was the most frequent (73.5%). One hundred and seven of HO-MRSA isolates (90.7%) showed aminoglycoside resistance. The combination aac(6&#146;)-Ie-aph(2&#146;&#146;)-Ia + ant(4&#146;)-Ia genes was the most frequent (22.4%). Tetracycline resistance rates in HO-MRSA isolates were low (3.4%), although a high level of mupirocin resistance was observed (25.4%). Most of the HO-MRSA isolates (approximately 90%) showed SCCmec type IVc and agr type II. Fifteen unrelated pulsotypes were identified. CC5 was the most prevalent (88.1%), followed by CC8 (5.9%), CC22 (2.5%), CC398 (2.5%) and CC1 (0.8%). Conclusion: CC5/ST125/t067 lineage was the most frequent. This lineage was related to aminoglycoside resistance, and to a lesser extent, with macrolide resistance. The presence of international clones as EMRSA-15 (CC22/ST22), European clones as CC5/ST228, community clones related to CC1 or CC8 and livestock associated clones, as CC398, were observed in a low percentage (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gude, M José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seral, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Algarate, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, Maximiliano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Potel, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Domínguez, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lucía Constenla, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las dinámicas poblacionales de SARM están experimentando cambios significativos en los últimos tiempos. Por ello es importante conocer qué líneas clonales circulan en nuestro ambiente hospitalario. Materiales y métodos: Durante un año, se seleccionaron 118 SARM de muestras clínicas de pacientes con contacto previo con el ambiente hospitalario (SARM de origen hospitalario [SARM-OH]). Las pruebas de sensibilidad se realizaron mediante difusión con discos y microdilución. La presencia de genes de resistencia y factores de virulencia fueron estudiados mediante PCR. Se estableció el tipo de SCCmec, spa y agr en todos los aislados, y en una selección se estudió su relación genética por PFGE y MLST. Resultados: Ochenta y tres SARM-OH (70,3%) fueron resistentes a al menos un antibiótico del grupo de los macrólidos-lincosamidas-estreptograminas B. Entre estos, el fenotipo M fue el más frecuente (73,5%). Ciento siete aislamientos (90,7%) mostraron resistencia a aminoglucósidos. La combinación aac(6&#146;)-Ieaph( 2&#146;&#146;)-Ia + ant(4&#146;)-Ia fue la más frecuente (22,4%). Las tasas de resistencia a tetraciclinas detectadas fueron bajas (3,4%). Se observó un 25,4% de resistencia de alto nivel a mupirocina. Aproximadamente un 90% de SARM-OH mostraron SCCmec tipo IVc y agr tipo II. Se identificaron 15 pulsotipos no relacionados. El CC5 fue el más prevalente (88,1%) seguido de CC8 (5,9%), CC22 (2,5%), CC398 (2,5%) y CC1 (0,8%). Conclusión: La línea clonal CC5/ST125/t067 fue la más habitual. Esta línea se relacionó con resistencia a aminoglucósidos, y, en menor medida, con macrólidos. La presencia de clones internacionales como EMRSA-15 (CC22/ST22), clones europeos como CC5/ST228, clones comunitarios relacionados con CC1 o CC8 y clones asociados al ganado, como el CC398, se observaron en un bajo porcentaje (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;33(9): 590-596, nov. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144634</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resistencia a antibióticos, factores de virulencia y líneas clonales de Staphylococcus aureus resistente a la meticilina de origen hospitalario en un hospital de Zaragoza</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53002^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36322^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29207^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54791</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13590^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24244^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
