<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039549</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Incidental renal cell carcinoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: To report the incidence and management of incidental renal cell carcinoma (RCC). METHODS: We performed a retrospective longitudinal and panel study for our case series between January 1990 and December 2003. Thirty cases of RCC were analyzed, 6 of which were incidental. RESULTS: 4 patients were males (66.6%) and 2 females (33.3%); age ranged between 28 and 72 years. Reason for consultation was related with gastrointestinal symptoms. Ultrasound and CT scan are the most useful studies. Clinical stage was 4 T1(66.6%), 2 T2 (33.3%). 4 radical nephrectomies and 2 conservative surgeries (partial nephrectomy and tumorectomy) were performed. A dose of 3 million units of alpha 2b recombinant interferon (IFN alpha 2b r) was given Intramuscularly two times a week over 6 months. Follow-up ranged between 120 and 60 months and none of the patients had evidence of tumor activity. CONCLUSIONS: The incidence of incidental RCC in our hospital is 20%. Clinical stage was always low and survival is directly related to stage. Conservative surgery showed similar survival than radical surgery</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ares Valdés, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fragas Valdés, Ramiro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Presentar la incidencia y elmanejo del Cáncer de Células Renales (CCR) incidental.MÉTODO: Se realizó un estudio retrospectivo longitudinaly de panel en el hospital Universitario ManuelFajardo de Enero de 1990 a Diciembre del 2003.Universo de trabajo. Se analizaron 30 casos con diagnósticode CCR y de estos 6 fueron incidentales.RESULTADOS: Por lo que se refiere al sexo, 4 fueronhombres (66.6%) y 2 mujeres (33.3%), el rango deedad de 28 a 72 años. La causa de consulta médicaestuvo relacionada con síntomas gastrointestinales. ElUltrasonido (U/S) y la Tomografía Axial Computarizada(TAC) son los estudios de mayor utilidad. El estadio clínicofue T1, 4 (66.6%) y T2, 2 (33.3%) de los pacientes.Se realizaron 4 cirugías radicales y 2 conservadoras(nefrectomía parcial y enucleación). Se administróInterferón alfa 2 b recombinante (IFN alfa 2b r) a unadosis de 3 Millones de Unidades (MU) 2 veces a lasemana durante 6 meses por vía IM. El seguimiento delos pacientes fue entre 120 y 60 meses, ninguno delos pacientes tenía evidencia de actividad tumoral.CONCLUSIONES: La incidencia en nuestro hospital esde 20%. El estadio clínico fue siempre bajo y la sobrevidaesta directamente relacionada con el estadio. Lacirugía conservadora presentó una sobrevida similar ala cirugía radical</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;58(5): 417-420, jun. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039549</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Carcinoma de células renales incidental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2335^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2335^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28583</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
