<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-14671</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Manipulation of the content in the overshadowing in contingency judments</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article studies the process of overshadowing and the predictions realized by the models of contingency judgments. In two different experiments, subjects were provided with four cues, to which they had to respond in one of two possible outcomes. The two experiments differed with respect to the content of their cues and outcomes: symptoms and diseases in the first experiment, letters and numbers in the second one. The results show that content does not seem to affect the subjects&#146; judgment. However, the results do differ with respect to the contingencies established between the cues and the subjects&#146; outcomes. Of all the models studied, only three proved to acceptably fit the empirical data: the Bayes&#146; rule, the Delta O, and the Associative Model (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fuente Solana, Emilia Inmaculada de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arnau Gras, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Tamayo, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente artículo pretendemos estudiar el proceso de ensombrecimiento y la predicción que realizan los modelos establecidos en los juicios de contingencia para explicar este fenómeno. En dos experimentos, los sujetos establecieron sus juicios en una tarea experimental que consistía en predecir dos consecuencias en función de cuatro causas potenciales. Los dos experimentos diferían en cuanto al contenido de las causas y consecuencias (síntomas y enfermedades en el primero y letras y números en el segundo). Los resultados muestran que el contenido parece no afectar a los juicios aunque sí hay diferencias entre ellos en función de las contingencias objetivas establecidas entre las causas y consecuencias. De los modelos estudiados sólo tres de ellos muestran ajustes aceptables a los datos empíricos: Regla de Bayes, Delta o y el Modelo Asociativo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);12(4): 599-604, nov. 2000. tab, graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-14671</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manipulación del contenido en el fenómeno de ensombrecimiento en juicios de contingencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6385</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7768</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200011</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
