<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91597</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevention of diabetes mellitus 2</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Diabetes mellitus type 2, DM2-is a metabolic disorder characterized by hyperglycaemia. This feature causes vascular and nerve disorders that are the basis of long-term complications. The twin-DM2 due to both its aetiology and its broad preclinical period allows strategies to be made that prevent or delay its onset (primary prevention) or to allow early detection (secondary prevention), or once diagnosed, delay or prevent the onset of complications (tertiary prevention). The application or screening tests for the disease is still a controversial issue and hygienic use of dietary or pharmacological treatments in pre-diabetics is recommended to decrease the incidence of this disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Comas Samper, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mediavilla Bravo, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barquilla García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seguí Díaz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carramiñana Barrera, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La diabetes mellitus tipo 2 &#150;DM2- es una enfermedad metabólica caracterizada por hiperglucemia. Este defecto es capaz de producir alteraciones vasculares y nerviosas que son el sustrato de sus complicaciones. La DM2 por su doble componente etiológico y su amplio período preclínico permite establecer estrategias que prevengan o demoren su aparición (prevención primaria), o que permitan su detección precoz (prevención secundaria), o que una vez diagnosticada, retrasen o eviten la aparición de las complicaciones (prevención terciaria). Del mismo modo que la aplicación o no de pruebas de cribado de la enfermedad es aún hoy un asunto controvertido, la utilización de tratamientos higiénico dietéticos o farmacológicos en prediabéticos podría recomendarse en algunas situaciones para disminuir la incidencia de esta enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);37(9): 496-503, nov. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91597</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevención de la diabetes mellitus 2</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7124^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7124^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53393^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201111</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
