<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166175</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidemiology of heart failure in Spain and the importance of adhering to clinical practice guidelines</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article focuses on the magnitude of the challenge of heart failure, with particular reference to the disease burden in Spain. The text also deals with the difficulty of estimating the size of the problem, which stems from the fact that heart failure is a common end-point of numerous conditions. The second part of the article presents some reflections on the value of clinical practice guidelines and on the difficulty of incorporating interventions that have proven their efficacy under the controlled conditions of a clinical trial into everyday clinical practice, thereby maximizing their potential benefits. Finally, some suggestions are made on improving both professionals&#146; adherence to clinical practice guidelines and patients&#146; adherence to recommended treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castro Beiras, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo Leiro, María G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñiz García, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente artículo se abordan aspectos de la magnitud de la insuficiencia cardiaca, con especial mención a la carga que supone la enfermedad en nuestro medio. Se discuten, asimismo, los problemas para estimar esta magnitud debidos al propio carácter de síndrome de esta condición y a constituir un sendero común final a múltiples enfermedades. En un segundo apartado se presentan algunas reflexiones acerca del valor de las guías de práctica clínica y de los problemas para que las intervenciones que han demostrado su eficacia en el entorno controlado de un ensayo clínico se generalicen en la práctica clínica cotidiana, a fin de aprovechar al máximo su potencial beneficio. Finalmente, se sugieren algunos puntos para mejorar tanto la adhesión de los profesionales a las guías de práctica clínica como la de los pacientes al tratamiento que se les indique (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);6(supl.F): 2f-8f, 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166175</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Insuficiencia cardiaca en España. Epidemiología e importancia del grado de adecuación a las guías de práctica clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28628</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
