<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112983</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recomendations of vaccination in patients with inflammatory bowel disease (IBD)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The concept of inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) covers three entities: ulcerative colitis (UC), Crohn&#146;s disease (CD) and indeterminate colitis (IC). These diseases have in common a chronic and relapsing course, alternating periods marked by inflammatory activity with other quiescent periods, in which the patient is asymptomatic. For many years treatment of the disease, especially in acute phases, was based on the use of corticoids. However, in recent decades we have witnessed significant advances from the therapeutic point of view. It is estimated that during the course of the disease&#146;s evolution 80% of patients will need corticoids, 40% immunomodulators (IMM), and as many as 20% will require a biological medicine to control their disease. While all of this is accompanied by an improvement in quality of life, less hospital admissions or surgical interventions, their use also involves an increase in the risk of suffering infections, either due to germs normally found in the community or opportunistic infections. Moreover, infections are a cause of morbidity and mortality associated with IBD and some of them can be prevented with vaccinations, hence the importance that vaccination programs are acquiring in this groups of patients. We present a review of the relevant literature and propose a vaccination protocol for patients diagnosed with IBD (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arín, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabriada, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nantes, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Basterra, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El concepto de enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal (EII) engloba tres entidades: la colitis ulcerosa (CU), la enfermedad de Crohn (EC) y la colitis inclasificable (CI). Estas enfermedades tienen en común el curso crónico y recidivante, alternando épocas de marcada actividad inflamatoria con otras quiescentes, en las que el paciente permanece asintomático. Durante muchos años la base del tratamiento, sobre todo en las fases agudas, se basó en el uso de corticoides. Sin embargo, a lo largo de las últimas décadas hemos asistido a avances importantes desde el punto de vista terapéutico. Así se estima que, a lo largo de la evolución de la enfermedad, el 80% de los pacientes van a precisar corticoides, el 40% inmunomoduladores (IMM) y hasta un 20% necesitará un fármaco biológico para el control de su enfermedad. Si bien todo ello se acompaña de una mejora en la calidad de vida, disminuyendo la necesidad de ingresos e intervenciones quirúrgicas, su uso implica también un incremento en el riesgo de sufrir infecciones, bien por gérmenes habituales en la comunidad o por gérmenes oportunistas. Las infecciones, además, son causa de morbimortalidad asociada a EII y algunas de ellas son prevenibles con vacunas, de ahí la importancia que los programas de vacunación están adquiriendo en este grupo de pacientes. Presentamos una revisión de la literatura al respecto y proponemos unas recomendaciones de vacunación para los pacientes diagnosticados de EII (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;36(1): 63-75, ene.-abr. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112983</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recomendaciones de vacunación en pacientes con enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal (EII)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29592^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30040^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7336^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
