<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-66550</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims: To assess the views of physicians who work in emergency departments (EDs) on the image projected by the EDs in the mass media as well as the mediatic possibilities of these EDs. Methods: Questionnaire given to 140 physicians in charge of Spanish EDs with different levels of complexity. Results: Fifty nine ED physicians responded 88% of whom had appeared in some type 8 mass media. The news was positive in 52% of cases, negative in 25% and neutral in 23%. 87% of the news appeared in local; 63% in regional and 13% in national. As compared to positive news that of negative connotation had the highest probability of appearing in national mass media (p &lt; 0.001). Forty-me percent of the responders reported that positive mews shoud appear in the mass media while 27% considered that news should appear independently of the connotation and 32% stated that ED should never appear in the news. Seventy three percent of ED take part in activities of social projection and this attitude reduced the possibility of being a source of negative news (p &lt; 0.05). Most of the ED physicians who responded to the survey were trained in communication skills or recognised their importance. They believed that the ED was or could be a potential source of positive news and also that their hospital had adequate structures to stablish a good dialogue with the mass media. Conclusions: EDs are often a source of positive news; this good image may be increased using strategies to this end. Most of the physicians surveyed thought that the good image of the EDs could be further improved (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Requena, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer la opinión de los responsables de los servicios de urgencias (SU)acerca de la imagen proyectada por su servicio en los medios de comunicación, así como de las posibilidades mediáticas de dichos SU. Método: Encuesta remitida a 140 responsables de SU del estado español, con representación de todos los niveles de complejidad. Resultados: Respondieron 59 SU. El 88% había aparecido en algún medio de comunicación. En el 52% la noticia fue positiva, en el 25% fue negativa y en el 23% fue neutra. Estas noticias aparecieron en medios de ámbito local en el 87%; de ámbito regional en el 63% y de ámbito nacional en el 13%. La probabilidad de aparecer en medios de comunicación nacionales es superior para las noticias con connotación negativa respecto a las positivas (p &lt; 0,001). El 41% de los encuestados creen que se debe apareceren los medios de comunicación si la noticia es positiva, el 27% creen que se debería aparecer siempre con independencia de la connotación y el 32% creen que no se debiera aparecer nunca. El 73% de los SU participaban en actividades de proyección social y se observó que esta actitud reducía las posibilidades de ser fuente de noticias negativas (p &lt; 0,05). La mayoría de los responsables entrevistados están formados en habilidades de comunicación o bien reconocen la importancia que tiene o creen que sus SU son o pueden llegar a ser una potencial fuente de noticias positivas y disponen en el hospital de estructuras adecuadas para mantener un buen diálogo con los medios de comunicación. Conclusiones: Los SU con frecuencia son fuente de noticias positivas, y se puede incrementar esta buena imagen mediante estrategias dirigidas a esta finalidad. La mayoría de los responsables entrevistados son optimistas de cara a mejorar nuestra imagen (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);20(3): 187-190, jun. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-66550</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d8574</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
