<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046767</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reduction of corneal permeability in patients treated with HP-Guar: a fluorophotometric study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The incidence of dry eye disease, which mainly affects the corneal epithelium, is rising. The main treatment is still the use of artificial tears capable of improving the humidification and lubrication of the corneal epithelium, and avoiding its progressive functional failure. HP-Guar is a new compound used for this purpose. Methods:We performed a prospective, masked and paired study on the left eye of 10 patients suffering from dry eye disease. Corneal permeability measurements were performed by fluorophotometry after instilling 40 mL of a solution of 2% sodium fluorescein, before and after treatment with the HP-Guar drops. The results were analysed using Wilcoxon test for paired data. Results: A mean decrease in corneal permeability of 45%, after the use of HP-Guar drops was found (p=0.002). Conclusions: HP-Guar provides a new therapeutic option significantly decreasing corneal epithelial permeability</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Sánchez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáenz-Francés-San-Baldomero, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benítez-del-Castillo, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cerván-López, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El ojo seco es una enfermedad en laque entre otras estructuras se afecta el epitelio corneal.El tratamiento de primera línea siguen siendolos sustitutivos lagrimales que buscan lograr unabuena humidificación y lubricación del epitelio cornealde estos pacientes, evitando así su progresivodeterioro funcional. El HP-Guar es un compuestonovedoso cuyos resultados sintomáticos en lospacientes con ojo seco están siendo prometedores.Métodos: Presentamos un estudio prospectivo,enmascarado, pareado sobre 10 ojos izquierdos de10 pacientes con ojo seco, a los que se les realizómedidas de la permeabilidad corneal mediante fluorofotometríacon la instilación de 40 microlitros deuna solución de fluoresceína sódica al 2%, antes ydespués del tratamiento con HP-Guar. Se analizaronlos resultados con el test de Wilcoxon paradatos pareados. Resultados: Se observó tuvo una disminución estadísticamentesignificativa de la permeabilidad cornealmedia del 45% tras tratamiento con HP-Guar(p= 0,002).Conclusiones: El HP-Guar constituye una nuevaopción terapéutica que ha demostrado fluotofotométricamentereducir la permeabilidad epitelial cornealtras su uso</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;81(6): 327-332, jun. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046767</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reducción de la permeabilidad corneal en pacientes tratados con HP-Guar: estudio fluorofotométrico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3627^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7944^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24655^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10729^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3334^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10063^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
