<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038289</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6709</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of culture conditions of Gordonia jacobaea MV-26 on canthaxanthin production</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Commercial interest in the use of natural pigments isolated from microorganisms has increased in recent years; hence, molecules belonging to the polyisoprenoid group (i.e. &amp;#946;-carotene, astaxan thin, and canthaxanthin) have beenthe focus of much attention. The bacterium Gordonia jacobaea readily synthesizes and accumulates large amounts of canthaxanthin (&amp;#946;-&amp;#946;&#146; -carotene-4,4&#146; -dione), which is widely used in the food and cosmetics industries. In the present work, the effects of different low-cost raw materials on fermentation and canthaxanthin accumulation by a hyperpigmented strain of G. jacobaea were studied. Canthaxanthin production and peak levels of accumulation varied according to the different media used (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Veiga-Crespo, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Poza, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villa, Tomas G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosa dos Santos, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blasco, Lucia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El interés comercial del uso de pigmentos naturales aislados a partir de microorganismos se ha incrementado en los últimos años y las moléculas pertenecientes al grupo de los poliisoprenoides (p.e. &amp;#946;-caroteno, astaxantina y cantaxantina) se han convertido en un foco de atención. La bacteria Gordonia jacobaea es capaz de sintetizar y acumular grandes cantidades de cantaxantina (&amp;#946;-&amp;#946;&#146; -caroteno-4,4&#146; -diona), muy usada en la industria alimentaria y de cosméticos. En este trabajo estudiamos la influencia de diferentes materias primas de bajo coste en la fermentación y la acumulación de cantaxantina por una cepa mutante hiperpigmentada de G. jacobaea. Se ha observado que la producción de cantaxantina y el momento en el que se alcanza la máxima producción varía según los diferentes medios empleados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int Microbiol;8(1): 55-58, mar. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038289</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de las condiciones de cultivo de Gordonia jacobea MV-26 en la producción de cantaxantina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32985^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11293^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30216^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36610^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3491^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
