<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118710</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Periodic gastroenterology and hepatology meetings with primary care. Reasons for consultation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: care overload, aging of population, and increased chronic diseases lead to increased referrals from primary care, which may sometimes overload the health system. Thus, different interventions have been carried out attempting to improve these aspects. Objectives: to assess the most frequent causes of consultation of general physicians, both in joint consultations and clinical sessions held jointly with specialist consultant in primary care, in the urban and rural setting, and the influence on referrals to first consultations of gastroenterology. Material and methods: a mainly training type of intervention was carried out, consisting of regular meetings in both urban and rural primary care center, to perform joint consultations and clinical sessions on patients and topics related to the specialty of gastroenterology. The intervention period (divided in two subperiods) was compared with a control period. Results: most reasons for consultation were those corresponding to lower gastrointestinal tract, followed by liver disease and upper gastrointestinal tract. Significant differences were only found in distribution of diagnoses between the two centers in joint consultations. There was a relative (percent) decrease in referrals at the global level in both subperiods, only significant in the first (51.45 %), as well as in rural setting (45.24 %). Conclusion: common consultations motifs were similar in urban and rural settings, with some relevance of lower gastrointestinal tract disease. Most of them can be solved at primary care, with the help of consultant specialist. There is impact on referrals to the outpatient first consultations of gastroenterology, mainly in rural setting (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Caro-Patón, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Rodríguez-Vila, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayo, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Otero, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Briso-Montiano, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pradera-Leonardo, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almaraz-Gómez, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mata-Román, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallelado, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Pascual, Agustina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Catón-Valdés, Manuela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villuela-González, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinilla-Gimeno, José Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Río-Hortega, Juan del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laso, Lucinio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castellanos-Alonso, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibañes-Jalón, Elisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sañudo, Soledad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olmo-Martínez, Lourdes del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Gómez, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la presión asistencial, el envejecimiento poblacional y el aumento de enfermedades crónicas incrementan las derivaciones desde atención primaria, pudiendo sobrecargar el sistema sanitario. Se han efectuado diversas intervenciones que intentan mejorar estos aspectos. Objetivos: valorar motivos de consulta más frecuentes de los médicos generales, tanto en consultas compartidas como en sesiones clínicas realizadas conjuntamente con un especialista consultor en atención primaria, en medios urbano y rural, y su repercusión sobre las derivaciones a primeras consultas de gastroenterología. Material y métodos: se efectúa una intervención de tipo fundamentalmente formativo, consistente en reuniones periódicas en dos centros de atención primaria (urbano y rural), con consultas compartidas y sesiones clínicas en relación con pacientes y temas de gastroenterología. El periodo de intervención (dividido en dos subperiodos) se comparó con un periodo control. Resultados: los problemas más comentados corresponden al tracto digestivo inferior, seguido de patología hepática y del tracto digestivo superior. Se encontraron diferencias significativas en la distribución de diagnósticos entre los dos centros en las consultas compartidas. Se detectó un descenso relativo o porcentual de las derivaciones a nivel global en ambos subperiodos, significativo solo en el primero (51,45 %), así como a nivel rural (45,24 %). Conclusión: los motivos de consulta habituales fueron similares en los medios urbano y rural, con cierto predominio del tracto digestivo inferior. La mayoría pueden ser resueltos desde atención primaria, con el apoyo del consultor especialista. Hay repercusión en las derivaciones a las consultas externas de la especialidad, sobre todo a nivel rural (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;105(9): 521-528, oct. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118710</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reuniones periódicas de gastroenterología y hepatología con atención primaria. Motivos de consulta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32616^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32270^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32270^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32616^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5903^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28457^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5903^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5903^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28457^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
