<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90537</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Connective Tissue Diseases and Psoriasis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Psoriasis is an autoimmune chronic inflammatory skin disease that is common in Spain. Connective tissue diseases are a heterogeneous group of conditions characterized by the abnormal function or structure of one or more of the elements that make up connective tissue. These diseases are also autoimmune in origin. In spite of the high prevalence of psoriasis in the general population, its association with a connective tissue disease such as systemic lupus erythematosus, dermatomyositis, scleroderma, or rheumatoid arthritis has only occasionally been reported. It is nevertheless important to have an understanding of such associations, given their significant clinical and therapeutic implications. The association between psoriasis and systemic lupus erythematosus is the one most often described, although the few reports available in the literature have mostly involved single cases. This review will also look at the characteristics of patients with psoriasis and dermatomyositis, mainly focusing on clinical features. The associations between psoriasis and either rheumatoid arthritis or systemic sclerosis will be examined more briefly. The review therefore aims to reflect the literature on psoriasis in association with rheumatic diseases, including coverage of etiologic, pathogenic, clinical, and therapeutic aspects. We emphasize that such cases should be managed by a multidisciplinary team in which care will usually be shared by a rheumatologist and a dermatologist (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cuesta-Montero, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Belinchón, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La psoriasis es una enfermedad cutánea inflamatoria crónica de etiología autoinmune muy frecuente en nuestro medio. Las enfermedades del tejido conectivo constituyen un grupo heterogéneo de enfermedades que se caracterizan por la anormal función o estructura de uno o varios elementos del tejido conectivo, de origen autoinmune. Pese a la alta frecuencia de la psoriasis en la población general, son pocos los casos publicados en los que coexistan psoriasis y enfermedades del tejido conectivo, como lupus eritematoso sistémico, dermatomiositis, esclerodermia o artritis reumatoide. Sin embargo, dadas las implicaciones clínicas y, principalmente, terapéuticas que presentan estos pacientes, resulta importante conocer estas asociaciones. La más frecuentemente descrita es la de psoriasis y lupus eritematoso sistémico, aunque son pocos los estudios publicados y la mayoría se basan en casos únicos. También trataremos las características específicas de los pacientes con dermatomiositis y psoriasis, principalmente de tipo clínico. Abordaremos de forma más breve la coexistencia de esclerosis sistémica y psoriasis, y de artritis reumatoide y psoriasis. Se pretende, por tanto, realizar una revisión de la literatura sobre psoriasis y su coexistencia con enfermedades reumatológicas, que comprende aspectos etiopatogénicos, clínicos y terapéuticos. Además queremos resaltar el manejo multidisciplinar que requieren estos pacientes, generalmente entre el reumatólogo y el dermatólogo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;102(7): 487-497, sept. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90537</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conectivopatías y psoriasis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3260^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8356^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12976^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12002^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1178^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
