<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81331</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-0618</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A «villancico» with numerous medicinal plants (Santa Fe de Bogotá, Colombia, ca. 1722)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the biggest musical Archive of the cathedral of Santa Fe deBogotá (Colombia), very important in all hispanic America, appeara «villancico», with only the words, but no the score, in honour ofSaint Teresa de Jesús. In this religious sing, that we unknown theauthor, many medicinal plants are singing in praise of this Saint. Itwas proximately written circa 1722. In this paper we describe somepersons of the musical chapel of the cathedral, that usually to meetin the small house of a musician, near to cathedral, in order to socialgathering for conversation. This small house had a vegetable gardenwith medicinal plants. We transcribe the curious «villancico» andanalyse, one by one, the medicinal plants cited in the «villancico»sing, with their characteristics. The medicinal plants were introducedin America from Spain(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Francés Causapé, María del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez de la Torre, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el archivo musical de la catedral de Santa Fe de Bogotá (Colombia),uno de los mayores de la América española, aparece laletra, sin partitura, de un villancico en honor de Santa Teresa deJesús, en el que numerosas plantas medicinales alaban a la Santa.El villancico no tiene autor conocido, y está escrito aproximadamentehacia el año 1722. Se estudian algunos personajes de la capillamusical de Bogotá en torno a esta fecha que, quizá, tenían unatertulia cultural en la casa de un músico, al lado de la catedral, quetenía un huerto donde se cultivaban hierbas medicinales. Se transcribeel curioso villancico. Y se analizan, una a una, las diferenteshierbas medicinales que en él se citan, posiblemente traídas todasdesde España(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Real Acad Farm;75(5,n.esp): 639-678, oct. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81331</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Un villancico con numerosas plantas medicinales (Santa Fe de Bogotá, Colombia, ca. 1722)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8686</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9339</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3137</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
