<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124887</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Guidelines for the endoscopic biopsy diagnosis of suspected idiopathic inflammatory bowel disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The lately increasing cases of inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) in the European population have triggered the creation of specific multidisciplinary units in hospitals, and protocols and consensus of specific action that keep pathologist struggling with. Consequently, the increasing demand of endoscopy biopsies reports calls for a set of standard criteria and nomenclatures in guides which help to resolve diagnosis difficulties and improve the precision in communicating the final reports. This guide intends to systematize the interpretation of this kind of biopsies and to reach the diagnosis objectives step by step, assessing the confidence of diagnosis in every level. These steps are summarized in determining if there is disease of ileocolic mucosa, if the disease is chronic and/or active, if the disease can be diagnosed as IBD or if it is necessary to rule out other types of colitis, and, if a IBD is considered likely true, if it could be diagnoses as Crohn's disease (CD) or ulcerative colitis (UC). Among the different assessed issues are the architectural changes which define chronicity of the disease, the inflammatory changes which can be graduated in activity index, the differential diagnosis with other types of colitis and the microscopic features which make possible classify this colitis as CD or UC. In addition, examples in the communication of the histopathology diagnosis are proposed and many frequent errors in microscopic interpretation are commented (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Gil, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Alonso, Guadalupe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salamanca, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Colina, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibarrola, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El reciente aumento en la incidencia de enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal (EII) entre la población europea ha dado lugar a la creación en hospitales de unidades multidisciplinares específicas con protocolos definidos que comprometen a los anatomopatólogos. El consiguiente aumento en el número de biopsias requiere establecer unas pautas, tanto sobre los criterios estándar como sobre la nomenclatura, para facilitar el diagnóstico y mejorar el informe. Dichas pautas tienen como finalidad la sistematización, paso a paso, de la interpretación de las biopsias con objetivos que evalúan la confianza diagnóstica a cada nivel. Los distintos pasos determinarán si existe enfermedad en la mucosa intestinal, si la enfermedad es crónica y/o activa y, si la presencia de una EII se considera probable, si se puede diagnosticar la enfermedad como un Crohn (EC) o bien como colitis ulcerosa (CU). Se considerarán los cambios en la arquitectura celular que indican la cronicidad de la enfermedad, los cambios inflamatorios que se pueden graduar en un índice de actividad, el diagnóstico diferencial con otros tipos de colitis y las características microscópicas necesarias para clasificar la colitis como EC o CU. Además, se proponen ejemplos de la comunicación del diagnóstico histopatológico y se analizan algunos de los frecuentes errores en la interpretación microscópica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;47(3): 161-177, jul.-sept. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124887</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Guía para la interpretación de biopsias endoscópicas con sospecha de enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal idiopática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29636</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23971^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23971^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23971^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
