<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126088</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7113</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">European educational overview for the training for forensics toxicologists</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Educational overview for the training for forensics toxicologists. The uniqueness of Forensic Laboratories and the significance of their results require a specialized task for which it is essential that human and material resources are adequate and also capable of ensuring their continuity and adaptation over time. Basic training in Toxicology, it is shared by different degrees, have adapted teaching plans to the new concept of teaching in the European Higher Education Area with the objective of introducing the under graduate degree in toxicology &amp;#769;s most important aspects. Postgraduate studies are focused on more specific issues such as forensic Toxicology (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Soria Sánchez, ML</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La singularidad de los Laboratorios Forenses así como la trascendencia de los resultados que emiten, requiere una labor especializada para la que es indispensable que los recursos humanos e instrumentales sean los adecuados y garanticen su continuidad y adecuación en el tiempo. La formación básica en Toxicología, que comparten diferentes licenciaturas, han adaptado los planes docentes a la nueva concepción de la docencia en el Espacio Europeo de Educación Superior con el objetivo en el pregrado de introducir al universitario en los aspectos más importantes de la Toxicología siguiendo en el postgrado las ramas especificas entre las que se encuentra la Toxicología forense (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. toxicol;27(1/2): 41-43, 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126088</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Panorama educativo Europeo para la formación de los toxicólogos forenses</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7492^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11813^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13034^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13034^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52454^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7492^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52454^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52454^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4562^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4562^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52454^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52454^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7492^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
