<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60742</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: dyspnea is one of the most prevalent symptoms in advancedlung cancer, and the most distressing one for patients, relatives, andhealthcare staff alike. Its management includes addressing the originaldisease using both pharmacological and non-pharmacological approaches.Pharmacological approaches most commonly include the use of appropriateantibiotics, bronchodilatators, steroids, and opiates (morphine andfentanyl).Clinical case: we report the case of a patient diagnosed with advancedlung cancer in whom the use of morphine together with ketamine alleviatedpain but not associated dyspnea.Conclusion: ketamine is an anesthetic drug with analgesic propertiesdue to its NMDA receptor antagonist activity. As ketamine induces a relaxingeffect on smooth-muscle fibers in the lung, evidence exists regardingits utility in refractory asthma and status asthmaticus (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Canal, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nabal, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cerezo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: la disnea es uno de los síntomas prevalentes en el cáncer depulmón avanzado y, sin duda, el de mayor impacto sobre el paciente, familiay equipo asistencial.El abordaje de la misma incluye medidas dirigidas a la enfermedad debase, medidas farmacológicas y no farmacológicas. Entre las medidas farmacológicasdestacan el uso de antibióticos, broncodilatadores y corticoides,sin olvidar morfina y probablemente fentanilo.Caso clínico: la ketamina es un fármaco anestésico utilizado tambiéncomo analgésico por su actividad antagonista del receptor NMDA. Dadoque actúa también como relajante de la musculatura lisa del árbol bronquial,existe evidencia práctica de su utilidad en casos de asma severa ystatus asmáticus.Conclusión: presentamos el caso de un paciente afecto de una neoplasiade pulmón en fase terminal en el que la utilización de ketamina conjuntamentecon morfina alivió el dolor pero no la disnea asociada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;16(1): 9-11, ene. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60742</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ketamina fue efectiva en el tratamiento del doloren un paciente con neoplasia de pulmón pero noen el tratamiento de la disnea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4479^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9315^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7815^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9211^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200901</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
