<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151745</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-8927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidemiology of beach volleyball and beach soccer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the last years beach sports are becoming more popular, although not many epidemiological studies can be found in the scientific literature. The aim of this paper consists of an epidemiological study focused in Spanish beach volley and beach soccer players, in order to analyze the player&#146;s needs and improve several aspects of those sports. 89 subjects took part in the survey, 54 beach volley players and 35 beach soccer players. Epidemiological and personal data were gathered. Tendon and ligament injuries (36%) are the most common in beach volley. In beach soccer dermatological are the most common injuries (36%). In both sports foot and ankle are the anatomical zones that suffer the higher injury rate; it must be highlighted that the majority are of dermatological nature. The lack of foot protection and the lack of knowledge to characterize the sand are possible reasons for it. To conclude, a good sport gear to protect foot and ankle and a deep study of the sport surface (sand) is deemed necessary to prevent and reduce injury rate in both sports (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alcántara, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vera, PM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alemany, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, AG</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gámez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montaner, AM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los deportes practicados en la arena están experimentando en la actualidad un gran auge, sin embargo y pese a su enorme difusión, la literatura epidemiológica en estos deportes es escasa. El propósito de este trabajo es presentar un estudio epidemiológico de vóley-playa y fútbol playa en el contexto español para conocer sus necesidades y contribuir a mejorar la vida deportiva de sus jugadores. Para ello, se realizó una encuesta a 89 sujetos, 54 jugadores de vóley-playa y 35 jugadores de fútbol playa, en la cual se recogían los aspectos epidemiológicos, así como las molestias y la sensación de disconfort. Los resultados del estudio muestran que las lesiones más habituales en vóley-playa son las de tipo tendinoso o ligamentoso (36%). Siendo las lesiones dermatológicas en fútbol playa las que presentan mayor incidencia (36%). Por zonas corporales, el pie y el tobillo son, en ambos deportes, las partes que sufren un mayor índice de lesión, la mayoría dermatológicas. La falta de protección de los pies y la ausencia de criterios para caracterizar la arena pueden ser dos razones de todo lo anterior. Teniendo en cuenta los resultados obtenidos se puede concluir que una buena protección para los pies así como el estudio de la arena son aspectos fundamentales para prevenir y minimizar las lesiones en estos deportes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Selección (Madr.);15(1): 22-27, 2006. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151745</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio epidemiológico en voley y fútbol playa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56170^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56170^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
