<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96536</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Femoral superficial vein thrombosis due to a large iliopsoas bursitis secondary to polyethylene wear debris in total hip arthroplasty</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A 76 year old male patient with a history of implantation of a total hip arthroplasty Perfecta (Orthomet®), who presented with an iliac fossa mass, increased diameter of the thigh, and pain during hip flexion and extension. CT and ultrasound show the presence of a giant cystic mass in left iliac fossa about 7cm in diameter next to the prosthesis. A pseudo-tumour secondary to wear debris after placement of a total arthroplasty is rare. We present a case of a large iliopsoas bursitis caused by polyethylene particles, which caused compression and thrombosis of the superficial femoral vein (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lajara Marco, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Gálvez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo Plazas, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lax Pérez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lax Pérez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salinas Gilabert, J. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrero Manzanal, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Paciente varón de 76 años, con antecedente de implantación de prótesis total de cadera tipo Perfecta (Orthomet®), que consulta por masa en fosa ilíaca, con aumento del diámetro del muslo y dolor flexión y extensión de la cadera. Los estudios complementarios de ecografía y tomografía evidencian la presencia de una tumoración quística gigante lobulada en fosa ilíaca izquierda de unos 7cm de diámetro en la proximidad de la prótesis. La formación quística ocasionada por la enfermedad del polietileno tras la colocación de una artroplastia total de cadera es poco frecuente. Presentamos un caso de bursitis del psoas de gran tamaño, secundaria a la liberación de partículas del polietileno, que ocasionó compresión y trombosis de la vena femoral superficial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);56(1): 54-58, ene.-feb. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96536</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trombosis de la vena femoral superficial por gran bursitis en psoas secundaria a enfermedad de las partículas en artroplastia total de cadera</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34393^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38813^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5370^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6780^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6780^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5370^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14312^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5370^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5370^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14312^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
