<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109651</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of a short useful questionnaire in Spanish for the epidemiological screening of epilepsy in Spain. EPIBERIA Questionnaire</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: There is a major gap in knowledge about the epidemiology of epilepsy in Mediterranean countries. The EPIBERIA group was formed with the aim of promoting the conducting of epidemiological studies in this area in order to improve this situation. This paper deals with the validation of a brief questionnaire for screening of patients with epilepsy in general population. Methods: We selected an English language questionnaire previously validated by the Ottman group. It was translated, modified to suit the characteristics of the Spanish population, and administered to a sample of 200 patients (93 epileptics and 107 non-epileptic patient controls) sampled consecutively from 5 Epilepsy Units scattered throughout Spain. Both groups were homogeneous in demographic variables, and the control group was representative of the general population. Results: We obtained a sensitivity of 100% and a specificity of 74.77% for the less rigorous correction criteria of the questionnaire, with a sensitivity of 94.62% and a specificity of 99.07% for the most stringent ones. The positive predictive values (PPVs) ranged from 7.48% for the first case to 69.49% in the second, assuming a prevalence for epilepsy of 2%. Conclusions: The questionnaire EPIBERIA is a valid Spanish tool for epilepsy screening of epilepsy in the general population in Spain(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Alvarez, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Ramos, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matías-Guiu, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sancho-Rieger, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Morales, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano-Castro, P. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mauri-Llerda, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Existe una importante laguna de conocimiento sobre la epidemiología de la epilepsia en los países de la cuenca mediterránea. El grupo EPIBERIA nace con el objetivo de promocionar la realización de estudios epidemiológicos en este ámbito, capaces de paliar esta situación. El presente trabajo aborda la validación de un cuestionario breve de cribado de pacientes con epilepsia en población general. Métodos: Se seleccionó un cuestionario de origen anglosajón validado en inglés por el grupo de Ottman. Fue traducido, modificado para adaptarlo a las características de la población española y administrado a una muestra de 200 pacientes (93 epilépticos y 107 controles no epilépticos), extraídos de manera consecutiva de 5 unidades de epilepsia dispersas por España. Ambos grupos fueron homogéneos en variables demográficas y el grupo de control fue representativo de la población general. Se realizó una estimación de la sensibilidad (S), la especificidad (E), los valores predictivos positivos (VPP) y los valores predictivos negativos (VPN) para cuatro diferentes criterios de corrección del cuestionario. Resultados: Se obtuvieron una sensibilidad del 100% y una especificidad del 74,77% para el criterio menos riguroso y una sensibilidad del 94,62% y una especificidad del 99,07% para el criterio más estricto de corrección del cuestionario. Los VPP variaron entre el 7,48% en el primer supuesto y el 69,49% en el segundo, asumiendo una prevalencia pretest para la epilepsia del 2%. Conclusiones: El cuestionario EPIBERIA es un instrumento válido como cuestionario de cribado de epilepsia en la población general en castellano en España(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;28(1): 24-32, ene.-feb. 2013. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109651</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación en castellano de un cuestionario breve útil para cribado epidemiológico de epilepsia en España: Cuestionario EPIBERIA</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
