<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91662</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">One of the most polemic issues regarding the use of deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) in the legal sphere, refers to the creation of DNA databases. Until relatively recently, Spain did not have a law to support the establishment of a national DNA profile bank for forensic purpose, and preserve the fundamental  rights of subjects whose data are archived therein. The regulatory law of police databases regarding identifiers obtained from DNA approved in 2007, covers this void in the Spanish legislation and responds to the incessant need to adapt the laws to continuos scientific and technological progress (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Baeta, Miriam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Jarreta, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Una de las cuestiones más polémicas en relación con el uso del ácido desoxirribonucleico (ADN) en el ámbito penal se refiere a la creación de bases de datos de ADN. Hasta hace relativamente poco tiempo, España carecía de una ley que amparara el establecimiento de un banco nacional de perfiles de ADN confines forenses, y que preservara los derechos fundamentales de los individuos cuyos datos son archivados. La ley reguladora de la base de datos policial sobre identificadores obtenidos a partir del ADN, aprobada en 2007, cubre este vacío de la legislación española y responde a la incesante necesidad de adaptar las leyes a los continuos avances científicos y tecnológicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. derecho genoma hum;(31): 161-183, jul.-dic. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91662</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Situación actual de las bases de datos de AND en el ámbito forense: Nuevos avances, nuevas necesidades jurídica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d36375^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36320^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36354^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38398^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
