<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59260</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The importance of adherence to the treatment in diabetes mellitus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Even the best treatment loses its efficacy if the patient does not followit properly. That explains the importance of therapeutic adherencein chronic diseases from different disciplines. This article reviewsadherence to the treatment in diabetes as a chronic disease.A description of the most common barriers found in patients withdiabetes, different methods for the analysis of therapeutic adherence,as well as control strategies that have proven to be most efficient isfound in this review. Between them, a therapeutic education of patientsand their family members is underline. Finally, this article emphasizesthe position of the World Health Organization on therapeuticadherence(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jansà, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidal, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El mejor tratamiento pierde su eficacia si el paciente no lo sigue deforma adecuada. De ahí la importancia que tiene la adherencia terapéuticaen las enfermedades crónicas de las diferentes disciplinas.En este artículo, se revisa la adherencia al tratamiento de la diabetescon una enfermedad crónica. Se describen las barreras más frecuentesencontradas en los pacientes con diabetes, los diferentesmétodos para analizar la adherencia terapéutica, así como, las estrategiasde control que se han demostrado más eficaces. Entre ellas,destaca la educación terapéutica de los pacientes y de sus familiares.Por último, este artículo incide en el posicionamiento de la OrganizaciónMundial de la Salud sobre adherencia terapéutica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;25(1): 55-61, ene.-feb. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59260</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Importancia del cumplimiento terapéuticoen la diabetes mellitus</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
