<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110992</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this research is to adapt a questionnaire designed for the assessment of needs and resources in patients with onco-haematological diseases &#150; the CMAE-OH- to renal patients under dialysis treatment. We have conducted three different studies. The first one is an inter-judges study to determine the face validity of the tool. The second is a pilot study, to know how the designed tool works when used in renal patients under dialysis. The third study consists of the usage of the questionnaire in a biggest sample to determine the psychometric properties of the tool. After the adaptation of the tool we conclude that the questionnaire we have adapt it is useful to assess needs and resources in renal patients under dialysis, as well as CMAE-OH was when used with oncological patients. On the basis of our study, we reflexionate about the closeness between psychooncology and other subdisciplines in the area of health psychology like psychonephrology (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García LLana, Helena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barbero, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bajo, María Auxiliadora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peso, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Selgas, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Rey, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González García, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Villanueva, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo tiene como objetivo la adaptación de un cuestionario empleado para la evaluación de necesidades y recursos en pacientes con enfermedad onco-hematológica, el CMAE-OH de Arranz y Ulla (2008) a pacientes renales en diálisis. Para ello realizamos tres estudios secuenciales. El primero de ellos es un estudio interjueces, para determinar la validez del cuestionario. El segundo es un estudio piloto para poner a prueba su funcionamiento en pacientes renales. El tercer estudio, consistirá en el empleo de la herramienta en una muestra mayor para determinar las propiedades psicométricas del instrumento. Tras la adaptación del cuestionario, concluimos que la herramienta es útil y adecuada para la evaluación de necesidades y recursos en los pacientes renales en diálisis, así como lo era para el caso de los pacientes oncológicos. Partimos de la adaptación de esta herramienta para iniciar una reflexión acerca de la cercanía, más que el distanciamiento, entre la psicooncología y otras subdisciplinas del ámbito de la Psicología de la Salud como la psiconefrología (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);9(2/3): 369-391, dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110992</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Propiedades psicométricas preliminares de un cuestionario multidimensional de adaptación a la enfermedad para pacientes onco-hematológicos (CMAE-OH) adaptado a pacientes renales en diálisis (CMAE-RD)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33920</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53271</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
