<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058896</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Proposal of a physical therapy protocol in the internal shoulder impingement</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The impingement symptom is a frequent pathology in sportsmen's shoulders which realize the gesture of throwing. It was described the first time in 1991; however, it wasn't until three or four years ago, mainly through arthroscopic surgery, when it started to appear in medical and physiotherapeutic diagnostics.         The objective of the study is to propose guidelines for the correct physiotherapeutic treatment of this syndrome.         For this study, 2 patients diagnosed impingement have been evaluated and treated under the physiotherapeutic protocol adapted to the physiopathology of the injury and the structures implied.         The results obtained in a functional shoulder that realizes the gesture of throwing, and in consequence sports, prove the efficiency of the guidelines proposed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barbero Iglesias, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordóñez López, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orejuela Rodríguez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Sánchez, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calderón Díez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez Sánchez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de impingement o pinzamiento interno es una patología frecuente en el hombro del deportista que realiza lanzamientos. Se describió por primera vez en 1991; sin embargo, no ha sido hasta hace 3 o 4 años, principalmente con el avance de la artroscopia de hombro, cuando se ha comenzado a introducir en los diagnósticos médicos y fisioterápicos.         El objetivo de este estudio es proponer unas pautas de actuación fisioterápica en el tratamiento de este síndrome.         Para ello, se somete a valoración a 2 pacientes diagnosticados de impingement interno y tratados mediante un protocolo fisioterápico justificado en función de la fisiopatología de la lesión y de las estructuras implicadas.         Los resultados obtenidos se resumen en un hombro funcional para el gesto del lanzamiento, y por tanto para el deporte, validando así las pautas propuestas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);29(5): 240-247, sep.2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058896</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Propuesta de un protocolo de fisioterapia en el impingement interno del hombro</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32937^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33888</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32937^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
