<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134381</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Is attention deficit hyperactivity disorder associated with other prevalent pathologies of early childhood?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To determine whether attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) is associated with other prevalent medical pathologies of the paediatric age. Development. Several paediatric pathologies were selected with the aim of reviewing their association with ADHD: in paediatric pulmonology, asthma and other allergic processes; in paediatric neurology, headache and febrile seizures; in paediatric gastroenterology, diarrhoea, constipation, abdominal pain, gastroesophageal reflux and infection by Helicobacter pylori; in paediatric nephrology, enuresis; in paediatric cardiology, bruits and congenital heart disease; in paediatric endocrinology, thyroid disorders and obesity; and in paediatric ophthalmology, ametropia and strabismus. Conclusions. Several studies were found that related ADHD with allergic processes, overweight/obesity, peripheral resistance to thyroid hormone, enuresis, febrile seizures, headache, congenital heart disease, ophthalmic disorders and tooth decay, with some controversial issues and details still to be defined. It can be concluded that further interdisciplinary studies are needed to clarify the associations and underlying mechanisms involved, so as to be able to gain a deeper understanding of the complex entity of ADHD and to suggest preventive, diagnostic and therapeutic interventions with regard to its comorbidities (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cardo, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amengual Gual, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Revisar si el trastorno por déficit de atención/hiperactividad (TDAH) se asocia con otras patologías médicas prevalentes de la edad pediátrica. Desarrollo. Se han seleccionado varias patologías pediátricas con el objetivo de revisar su asociación con TDAH: en neumología pediátrica, asma y otros procesos alérgicos; en neurología pediátrica, cefalea y convulsión febril; en gastroenterología pediátrica, diarrea, estreñimiento, dolor abdominal, reflujo gastroesofágico e infección por Helicobacter pylori; en nefrología pediátrica, enuresis; en cardiología pediátrica, soplos y cardiopatías congénitas; en endocrinología pediátrica, alteraciones tiroideas y obesidad, y en oftalmología pediátrica, ametropía y estrabismo. Conclusión. Se han encontrado varios estudios que relacionan el TDAH con procesos alérgicos, sobrepeso/obesidad, resistencia periférica a la hormona tiroidea, enuresis, convulsión febril, cefalea, cardiopatías congénitas, alteraciones oftalmológicas y caries, con algunas controversias y detalles por definir. Se puede concluir que son necesarios más estudios interdisciplinarios para esclarecer las asociaciones y los mecanismos subyacentes implicados, con la finalidad de conocer mejor la compleja entidad TDAH y plantearse intervenciones preventivas, diagnósticas y terapéuticas en cuanto a sus  comorbilidades se refiere (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;60(supl.1): s109-s113, mar. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134381</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Se asocia el trastorno por déficit de atención/ hiperactividad con otras patologías prevalentes de la infancia?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9591^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9591^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8037^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8037^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55220^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55220^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
