<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164285</identifier>
<setSpec>2014-9832</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Research regarding attitudes towards sciences at San Francisco Xavier of Chuquisaca University on medicine students doing internships</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To analyse the image of science, the teaching of it that medicine students, doing their internships at the San Francisco Xavier of Chuquisaca University, have. Subjects and methods. The research was made among 101 medicine students that are doing their internships at the hospital system in Sucre, Bolivia. A survey that values the attitudes towards science was applied to them; this is, how they value the image of science and how science is taught throughout their university education. Results. It was found that the attitudes among medicine students doing their internships, towards science, are positive; however the praxis of it is still minimal, due to the incipient participations in research projects and publications. Conclusions. The attitudes towards science are positive, however the challenge will be, for the university, to apply and develop the health research policies, this way the social-sanitary indicators will be improved (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Martínez, Ivonne F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villacorta Guzmán, Richar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maldonado Sanabria, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallardo Matienzo, Germán</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Analizar la imagen de la ciencia y la enseñanza de la ciencia en estudiantes universitarios del internado rotatorio en medicina de la Universidad de San Francisco Xavier de Chuquisaca en Sucre, Bolivia. Sujetos y métodos. El estudio se realizó en 101 estudiantes universitarios del internado rotatorio intrahospitalario del municipio de Sucre, Bolivia. Se aplicó un cuestionario que valora las actitudes frente a la ciencia, es decir, la imagen y la enseñanza de la ciencia en su formación universitaria. Resultados. Se encontró que la imagen y la enseñanza de la ciencia en estudiantes del internado de medicina están por encima de la media esperada, aunque la praxis sea aún incipiente, como se observa por la baja participación en proyectos y publicaciones locales. Conclusiones. Las actitudes frente a la ciencia son positivas, pero el reto para la formación universitaria será aplicar las políticas de desarrollo de investigación en salud, si se busca incidir en la mejora de los indicadores sociosanitarios del país (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Fund. Educ. Méd. (Ed. impr.);20(3): 127-132, mayo-jun. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164285</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio sobre actitudes frente a la ciencia de los estudiantes del internado rotatorio de la carrera de medicina en la Universidad de San Francisco Xavier de Chuquisaca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13724^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1863</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23896</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50058^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14893^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
