<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138492</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality of neurological care in the emergency services: a study from the community-hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The medical conditions shared by hospital emergency services and community-hospital neurology clinics (CHNC) have not been described, and the quality of the medical care received in these conditions has not been evaluated in our environment. Methods: Over a 2 month period, those patients presenting at any of the seven CHNC in a Health Care Area 1 of Madrid due to previously attended medical conditions in the emergency services were systematically registered. The area neurologists of the CHNC collected administrative and clinical variables and made a judgment on the medical care (primary outcome measure) and diagnoses (secondary outcome measure) received. Results: A total of 181 patients were included (mean age: 58 years; 60% women). The inclusion rate was one patient per working day, and 31% of patients were visited out of the established quota number of patients for the clinic. The most frequent reasons for visiting the emergency room were: headache (20%), focal neurological syndrome (16%) and loss of consciousness (14%). The most frequent diagnoses at the CHNC were: primary headache (19 %), stroke (11%) and epilepsy (9 %). Emergency care was deemed correct in 56 % of patients. When the patients with intervention were compared to those with no intervention, participation of the neurology service in the emergency room was associated to a greater percentage of correct diagnoses (59% vs. 41%; p=0.019) and care (69% vs. 47%; p=0.003). Conclusions: The medical conditions shared with the emergency services represent a small but relevant proportion of the patients assisted in the CHNC. Some of these conditions (primary headaches, syncopes) should be canalized into primary health care. Others (epilepsy) require a circuit between emergency room and CNNC, but the appointment system should be adapted. The intervention of a neurologist in the emergency room raises the quality of the care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vaquero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villaverde, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olazarán, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillem, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galiano, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los procesos compartidos por los servicios hospitalarios de urgencias y las consultas de neurología del área sanitaria (CNA) no han sido descritos y su calidad asistencial no ha sido evaluada en nuestro medio. Métodos. Durante 2 meses se registraron todos los pacientes que acudieron a las siete CNA 1 de Madrid debido a procesos médicos que habían sido previamente atendidos en urgencias. Los neurólogos del área sanitaria recogieron variables organizativas y clínicas y emitieron un juicio acerca de la asistencia (variable de efecto primaria) y del diagnóstico (variable de efecto secundaria) realizados. Resultados. Fueron incluidos 181 pacientes (edad media: 58 años; 60% mujeres), a un promedio de un paciente por día de consulta. El 31% estaban citados fuera del cupo. Los motivos más frecuentes de la visita a urgencias habían sido: cefalea (20%), focalidad neurológica (16 %) y pérdida de conciencia (14 %). Los diagnósticos más frecuentes en la CNA fueron: cefalea primaria (19%), accidente cerebrovascular (11%) y epilepsia (9 %). La asistencia en urgencias fue correcta en el 56% de los pacientes. Comparado con los procesos en que no intervino, la participación de neurología se asoció a un mayor porcentaje de diagnóstico y de asistencia correctos (59 frente a 41%; p=0,019, y 69 frente a 47%; p=0,003, respectivamente). Conclusiones. Los procesos compartidos con urgencias suponen una proporción pequeña pero no desdeñable del total de pacientes atendidos en las CNA. Algunos de estos procesos (cefaleas primarias, síncopes) deberían canalizarse hacia la asistencia primaria. Otros (epilepsia) precisan del circuito urgencias-CNA, pero el sistema de citaciones debe adaptarse. La actuación del neurólogo en urgencias eleva la calidad asistencial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;24(4): 249-254, 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138492</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de la asistencia neurológica en urgencias: un estudio desde el área</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6920^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4711^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200900</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
