<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160072</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-7546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Physical activity and sleep of persons living with HIV/AIDS: a systematic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of this academic work is to present the evidences available in literature about the relation between physical activity and sleep in regards to individuals living with HIV/AIDS. The databases: Web of Science, PubMed/MEDLINE, Science direct, Bireme, Scopus and EBSCO, were used to identify four articles, published until September 2015 to be included in this systematic review. According to the analyzed studies, interventions with physical activity for persons living with HIV/AIDS were significantly associated with the quality of sleep, total sleep time, efficiency, decreased of number of awakenings during sleep and improvement of sleeping disorders (insomnia). Therefore, the results presented in this research paper makes evident that physical activity has a relation with the quality of sleep amongst this specific population group, causing benefits to the quality of life of the patients. Nonetheless, it has been noticed that there is a necessity for more research and investigation in regards to the topic presented (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santos, IK dos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leitão, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Azevedo, KPM de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silveira, APKF</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bento, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medeiros, HJ de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Knackfuss, MI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dantas, PM da S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo es presentar las evidencias disponibles en la literatura sobre la relación entre la actividad física y el sueño en personas que viven con VIH/sida. Las bases de datos Web of Science, PubMed/MEDLINE, Science Direct, Bireme, Scopus y EBSCO, fueron utilizadas para identificar cuatro artículos publicados hasta septiembre de 2015, para su inclusión en esta revisión sistemática. Según los estudios analizados, las intervenciones basadas en actividad física, para personas que viven con el VIH/sida, se asocian significativamente con la calidad del sueño, el tiempo total del sueño, la eficiencia, la disminución de la fragmentación del sueño y mejoras en trastornos del sueño (insomnio). De esta manera, los resultados de este estudio evidencian que la actividad física está relacionada con la calidad del sueño de este grupo específico de población, generando beneficios en la calidad de vida de los pacientes. Aun así, se ha constatado la necesidad de realizar más investigaciones y estudios sobre el tema presentado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. andal. med. deporte;10(1): 19-24, mar. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160072</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La actividad física y el sueño de las personas que viven con el VIH/sida: una revisión sistemática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13272^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29364^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29416^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29364^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
