<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148442</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9168</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">An updated overview of the high intensity lipid lowering therapy in high cardiovascular risk patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Statins are highly effective drugs to decrease the plasma concentrations of atherogenic lipoproteins and prevent cardiovascular disease. The clinical practice guidelines recommend the use of high-intensity statins to lower LDL-cholesterol by at least 50% in patients with CVD and those at high cardiovascular risk. The recommendations for the treatment of hypercholesterolaemia by the ACC/AHA have led to a paradigm shift in cardiovascular prevention. These recommendations have abandoned the therapeutic goals of LDL-cholesterol, and recommend the treatment with statins of high or moderate intensity in four high cardiovascular risk groups. These recommendations are different from the European guidelines on cardiovascular disease prevention, in which their objectives are still towards LDL-cholesterol. This paper reviews this controversy from different angles and from the perspective of the Spanish Interdisciplinary Committee for Cardiovascular Disease Prevention. Intervention studies with high intensity statins in primary prevention, in patients with acute coronary syndrome, and with stable ischaemic heart disease are also described. Likewise, treatment with statins of high intensity is addressed in terms of their effectiveness in cardiovascular prevention and in terms of their safety, with particular attention to muscle effects, as well as taking into account the pharmacological characteristics of the different statins and the increased safety of those with less potential for interactions. Finally, new agents are described for the treatment of hypercholesterolaemia, with special emphasis on anti-PCSK9 monoclonal antibodies, a new therapeutic group for the treatment of hypercholesterolaemia that will offer a huge progress in the prevention of cardiovascular diseases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pintó, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedro-Botet, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las estatinas son fármacos de alta eficacia para disminuir la concentración plasmática de lipoproteínas aterogénicas y prevenir las enfermedades cardiovasculares. Las guías de práctica clínica recomiendan el uso de estatinas de alta intensidad para disminuir el cLDL al menos un 50% en los pacientes con ECV y en los de alto RCV. Las recomendaciones para el tratamiento de la hipercolesterolemia del ACC/AHA han supuesto un cambio de paradigma en la prevención cardiovascular al abandonar los objetivos terapéuticos del cLDL y plantear el tratamiento con estatinas de alta o moderada intensidad en cuatro grupos poblacionales bien identificados de alto RCV. Dichas recomendaciones son distintas a las de las guías europeas de prevención cardiovascular en las que se mantienen dichos objetivos del cLDL. Este trabajo revisa dicha controversia desde distintos ángulos y desde la perspectiva del Comité Español Interdisciplinar para la Prevención Cardiovascular y también los estudios de intervención con estatinas de alta intensidad en prevención primaria, en pacientes con síndrome coronario agudo y con cardiopatía isquémica estable. Asimismo, se aborda el tratamiento con estatinas de alta intensidad en cuanto a su eficacia en prevención cardiovascular y a su seguridad, con particular atención a los efectos musculares, teniendo en cuenta las características farmacológicas de las distintas estatinas y la mayor seguridad de las que presentan un menor potencial de interacciones. Por último se describen nuevos agentes para el tratamiento de la hipercolesterolemia con especial énfasis en los anticuerpos monoclonales anti-PCSK9, un nuevo grupo terapéutico de alta eficacia hipocolesteremiante que supondrá un enorme progreso en la prevención de las enfermedades cardiovasculares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. arterioscler. (Ed. impr.);28(1): 19-30, ene.-feb. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148442</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Una visión actualizada del tratamiento hipolipemiante de alta intensidad en los pacientes de alto riesgo cardiovascular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d963^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33014^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4421^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
