<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81074</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7709</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the daily clinical practice, constant doubts appearon the etiology, diagnosis, treatment or predictionof the different affections of the feet of our patients.To solve these doubts, we propose to use the CriticalAppraisal Topic. Though this methodology needsof a major effort that the one that it needs to settledoubts by means of other methods, follows the systematicalone of work based on the Evidence BasedMedicine, which grants a great validity to him. TheTopics Valued Critically are documents in the shapeof brief summary of the most relevant scientifictests, in relation to a clinical specific question. Bymeans of this method one tries to formulate correctquestions arisen during the clinical daily practice, tolook for the best available evidence, once opposingone organizes, summarizes, integrates and removesto the practice. Giving response, in real time, toquestions that arise during the daily practice, facilitatingthe process of capture of decisions(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cantó, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padrós, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esther Ortega Díaz, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Campos, Jonatan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López del Amo Lorente, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la práctica clínica diaria, se nos plantean dudasconstantes sobre la etiología, diagnóstico, tratamientoo pronóstico de las distintas afecciones de los piesde nuestros pacientes. Para resolver estas dudas,proponemos utilizar los Temas Valorados Críticamente,del inglés Critical Appraisal Topic. Aunqueesta metodología requiere de un esfuerzo mayorque el que requiere solventar dudas mediante otrosmétodos, sigue una sistemática de trabajo basada enla Medicina Basada en la Evidencia, la cual le otorgauna gran validez. Los Temas Valorados Críticamenteson documentos en forma de resumen breve de laspruebas científicas más relevantes, en relación a unapregunta clínica específica. Mediante este métodose intenta formular preguntas correctas, surgidasdurante la práctica clínica diaria, para buscar lamejor evidencia disponible, una vez encontrada seorganiza, resume, integra y se lleva a la práctica.Dando respuesta, en tiempo real, a cuestiones quesurgen durante la práctica diaria, facilitando elproceso de toma de decisiones(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Peu;28(4): 188-191, oct.-dic. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81074</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Temas valorados críticamente: un aprendizaje basado en la evidencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11462^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3675</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11462^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
