<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043045</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Noninvasive ventilation in infants with Ondine´s syndrome: a real indication?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Ondine's syndrome is a congenital central hypoventilation syndrome due to a disorder in the autonomic control of breathing in the absence of any primary disease that would explain it. Noninvasive ventilation (NIV) has been reported to be effective in the management of these patients, thus avoiding the need for tracheotomy for prolonged mechanical ventilation. We describe our experience of NIV in infants with Ondine's syndrome.         Two infants with Ondine's syndrome were transferred to our center for management and adjustment of therapy. On admission NIV (BiPAP VISION®) was started with nasal interphase in S/T (spontaneous/timed) mode, which failed to provide suitable ventilation (PCO2 &gt; 70 mmHg). Finally, tracheotomy for continuous mechanical ventilation was performed.         Although NIV has been reported to be successful in some patients with Ondine's syndrome, its application in patients younger than 5 years does not seem to be the general norm of treatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Costa Orvay, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pons Ódena, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jordán García, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caritg Bosch, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cambra Lasaosa, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palomeque Rico, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de Ondine se trata de un síndrome de hipoventilación central congénita secundaria a un trastorno en el control autonómico de la respiración en ausencia de enfermedad primaria que lo justifique. Se ha descrito la eficacia de la ventilación no invasiva (VNI) en lactantes afectados del síndrome de Ondine, evitando así la necesidad de una traqueostomía para ventilación mecánica. Se describe nuestra experiencia en VNI en lactantes con síndrome de Ondine.         Se describen 2 lactantes afectados del síndrome de Ondine que son trasladados a nuestro centro para control y adecuación terapéutica. A su ingreso se inicia VNI mediante ventilador presurométrico (BiPAP vision®) con interfase nasal en modalidad S/T (espontánea/controlada) con imposibilidad de conseguir una adecuada ventilación (PCO2 &gt; 90 mmHg). Finalmente se realiza traqueostomía reglada para ventilación mecánica continua.         La aplicación de VNI en pacientes menores de 5 años con síndrome de Ondine, aunque se ha realizado con éxito en algunos casos, no parece ser la norma general de tratamiento</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);63(5): 441-443, nov. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043045</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ventilación no invasiva en lactantes afectados de síndrome de Ondine: ¿una indicación real?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7220^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34201^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7220^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34201^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7220^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29278^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
