<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158403</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Biomarkers of nephrotoxicity in workers exposed to cadmium</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Cadmium (Cd) is a metal which main effect is nephrotoxicity. Its irreversibility alerts of the importance in preventing occupational exposure and early diagnosis of kidney damage. This paper summarizes the scientific evidence between exposure to Cd and alteration of biomarkers of exposure and kidney damage. Material and methods: a systematic review of the scientific literature, published between 2005 and 2015, was conducted in 7 database using equations search with MeSH terms. References were filtered based on the objectives excluding non-original articles. Critical reading is performed based on an array of evidence synthesis, using the SIGN criteria for determination. Results: 968 references were retrieved and included in the review number 8, 90% of cross-sectional design. Association between exposure to Cd and metal levels in blood and urine were found. Kidney damage markers that correlate with exposure are beta2-microglobulin, albumin, enzymes and markers of oxidative stress. The main modifier effect factor is the tobacco. Conclusions: Although it is limited by the design of the analyzed studies, it is without discrepancies scientific evidence in the association between exposure to Cd and alteration of biomarkers a exposure and kidney damage, even at a low levels of exposure to Cd (&lt;2 µg/g Cr in urine). Prospective studies are needed to identify the relevance of proposing a reduction of VLB (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herrero Herranz, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pegenaute Esparza, Carlota María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gonçalves de Freitas, Mariela de Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Valero, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El cadmio (Cd) es un metal cuyo principal efecto es la nefrotoxicidad. Su carácter irreversible alerta sobre la importancia en la prevención de la exposición laboral y el diagnóstico precoz de daño renal. Este trabajo resume la evidencia científica entre la exposición a Cd y la alteración de los biomarcadores de exposición y de daño renal. Material y métodos: se realizó una revisión sistemática de la literatura científica publicada entre 2005 y 2015, en 7 base de datos utilizando ecuaciones de búsqueda con términos MESH. Se filtraron las referencias en base a los objetivos excluyéndose artículos no originales. La lectura crítica se realizó en base a una matriz de síntesis de la evidencia, empleándose los criterios SIGN para su determinación. Resultados: Se recuperaron 968 referencias y se incluyeron en la revisión 8; el 90% de diseño transversal. Se encuentra asociación entre la exposición a Cd y los niveles del metal en sangre y orina. Los marcadores de daño renal que se correlacionan con exposición son la beta2-microglobulina, albúmina, enzimas y marcadores de estrés oxidativo. El principal factor modificador del efecto es el tabaco. Conclusiones: A pesar de la limitación por el diseño de los estudios analizados, existen evidencias científicas sin discrepancias en la asociación entre la exposición a Cd y la alteración de biomarcadores de exposición y de daño renal, inclusive ante niveles bajos de exposición a Cd (&lt; 2 µg/g Cr en orina). Se necesitan estudios prospectivos para identificar la pertinencia de plantear una reducción del VLB (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;62(244): 263-281, jul.-sept. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158403</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Biomarcadores de nefrotoxicidad en trabajadores expuestos a cadmio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29063^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31999^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2139^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7852^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2138^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
