<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036285</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Primary amenorrhea due to hypogonadotrophic hypogonadism</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We describe the case of an adopted 17-year-old girl who consulted because of complete pubertal delay. No specific dysmorphic features were observed and olfaction was normal. The complete absence of pubertal development had severe psychological effects. Basal hormonal determinations confirmed severe hypoestrogenism, with serum gonadotropins within the normal range for the early follicular phase. Serum levels of other pituitary hormones were normal. A sellar magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan was normal. Both gonadotropins increased normally in response to gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH) (100 &amp;#61621;g, IV). Spontaneous gonadotropin secretion through a 12-h nocturnal period showed minimal luteinizing hormone (LH) pulsatility with nocturnal increase and less follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) pulsatility without nocturnal increment. A diagnosis of normosomic hypogonadotropic hypogonadism was made. The patient was treated with progressive doses of conjugated estrogens, with subsequent addition of progesterone in a cyclic regimen. Finally, oral contraception was prescribed. At 26 years of age, she desired fertility and was clinically reevaluated. Partial hypogonadotropic hypogonadism was confirmed, with similar patterns of spontaneous gonadotropin secretion and GnRH response. We discuss the clinical characteristics of this entity, focusing mainly on the cause of normosomic hypogonadotropic hypogonadism, in light of new information about the molecular bases of these disorders. The treatment of hypogonadotropic hypogonadism is also discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Melián, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Vázquez, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Mujer de 17 años, adoptada, que consulta por retraso puberal completo. Presentaba un crecimiento armónico, con olfato normal y repercusión psicológica grave por ausencia completa de desarrollo puberal. El estudio hormonal basal confirma la presencia de hipoestrogenismo grave, ausencia de adrenarquia y valores de gonadotropinas en rango normal para primera mitad de la fase folicular. El resto de hormonas hipofisarias fueron normales. La resonancia magnética hipotálamo-hipofisaria fue normal. El estímulo con 100 &amp;#61621;g de hormona liberadora de hormona luteinizante indujo una respuesta normal de hormona folículo estimulante y hormona luteinizante, y la secreción nocturna (12 h) de gonadotropinas evidenció mínima pulsatilidad de hormona luteínizante, con aumento nocturno y menor pulsatilidad de hormona folículo estimulante, sin aumento nocturno. La paciente fue diagnosticada de hipogonadismo hipogonadotropo normosómico. Se inició inducción de pubertad con estrógenos en dosis progresivas, adición posterior de progesterona y, finalmente, anticonceptivos orales. A los 26 años, se plantea la fertilidad por lo que se revalúa y se confirma hipogonadismo hipogonadotropo parcial, con el mismo perfil de secreción de gonadotropinas, espontánea y en respuesta a hormona liberadora de gonadotropina. Se discuten las características clínicas, con especial atención al diagnóstico etiológico del hipogonadismo hipogonadotropo normosómico, a la luz de la nueva información sobre las bases moleculares del hipogonadismo hipogonadotropo idiopático. Asimismo, se discute el abordaje terapéutico del hipogonadismo hipogonadotropo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;52(5): 209-214, mayo 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036285</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Amenorrea primaria por hipogonadismo hipogonadotropo normosómico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2703^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11807^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7184^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d571^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5059^s22015</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5059^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6209^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
