<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125622</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Person-based contextual therapy applid to a complex case of schizophrenia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Psychological therapies are becoming more and more important in schizophrenia, and not as mere adjuncts to medication. The psychotherapy of schizophrenia is taking on a new lease of life in the wake of person-based phenomenological and psychological developments. Method: The case in question was a complex one, with variegated symptomatology that had persisted over many years. Approaching the case from the perspective of person-based cognitive therapy allowed us to understand the psychotic symptoms in the biographical context and to apply a therapy focused on the patient&#146;s recovery of her sense of self and of life. Results: At the end of the therapy and throughout the 12-month follow-up, the psychotic experiences had practically disappeared, or ceased to be disturbing, and the patient had become re-integrated in social life. Conclusions: Psychotic symptoms take on meaning in the biographical context. Adopting this perspective can aid the psychopathological explanation of the disorder and provide significant therapeutic help, more focused on recovery. Psychological therapy has shown itself to be viable in complex cases treated within the public-sector healthcare context (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Álvarez, Marina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Montes, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fenández Iglesias, Purificación</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallina Fernández, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soto Balbuena, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perona Garcelán, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: las terapias psicológicas están siendo cada vez más importantes en la esquizofrenia, y no como meras adjuntas a la medicación. La psicoterapia de la esquizofrenia está cobrando nueva vida a la luz de desarrollos fenomenológicos y psicológicos centrados en la persona. Método: se presenta un caso complejo, de abigarrada sintomatología y larga duración, sin que hasta ahora la medicación produjera cambios clínicos significativos. La formulación del caso de acuerdo con la terapia cognitiva basada en la persona permitió entender los síntomas psicóticos en el contexto biográfico y llevar a cabo una terapia centrada en la recuperación del sentido del yo y de la vida. Resultados: al final de la terapia y en el seguimiento de un año las experiencias psicóticas habían desaparecido prácticamente o dejado de ser perturbadoras y la paciente se había reintegrado en la vida social. Conclusiones: los síntomas psicóticos cobran sentido en el contexto biográfico. Esto puede servir a la explicación psicopatológica y a una ayuda terapéutica significativa, más centrada en la recuperación que en el mero sostenimiento, que fácilmente termina en "abandono" asistencial y existencial. La terapia psicológica muestra ser viable en casos complejos atendidos en dispositivos públicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);26(3): 299-307, jul.-sept. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125622</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicación de la terapia contextual basada en la persona a un caso complejo de esquizofrenia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26667</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55021^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
