<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154488</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors associated with dietary supplementation among Brazilian athletes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Many factors can influence an athlete to consume dietary supplements, such as age, sex and sports, among others. Few studies regarding the prevalence and associated factors are available for athletes, especially in developing countries. Objective: The aim of the study was to determine the factors associated with the consumption of dietary supplements among Brazilian athletes. Material and methods: This is a cross-sectional study involving 182 athletes of both sexes. The athletes answered a questionnaire containing sociodemographic and sports information, current consumption of supplements, consumption of pharmacological substances and information on body image disorder (Body Shape Questionnaire) and muscle dysmorphia (Muscle Appearance Satisfaction Scale). Analyses were performed using Pearson&#146;s Chi-squared test, the crude prevalence ratio (PR) and Poisson regression with robust variance. Results: In the bivariate analysis, the male gender, age between 25-29 years, engaging in a remunerated activity, consumption of pharmacological substances, body image disorder, risk of muscle dysmorphia, power modality athletes and lack of medical care were factors associated with supplement intake. After the regression analysis, the consumption of supplements was associated with the male gender (PR: 1.68; 95% CI: 1.01; 2.78; p = 0.044), use of pharmacological substances (PR: 1.77; 95 %: 1.37; 2.27; p &lt; 0.001) and the risk of muscle dysmorphia (PR: 1.75; 95% CI: 1.37; 2.23; p &lt; 0.001). Conclusions: The results of this research clearly demonstrate the importance of professionals working closely with athletes to continuously monitor their use of supplements, since it was an alimentary behavior associated with other risk behavior (pharmacological use) as well as image disorders (muscle dysmorphia) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernandes, Vânia Letícia Souza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nabuco, Hellen Clair Garcêz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodrigues, Vanessa Behrends</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ravagnani, Fabrício César de Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fett, Carlos Alexandre</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espinosa, Mariano Martínez</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ravagnani, Christianne de Faria Coelho</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: muchos factores, tales como edad, sexo, deporte, entre otros, llevan al atleta a consumir suplementos alimenticios. Existen pocos estudios sobre prevalencia y factores asociados en atletas, especialmente en países en desarrollo. Objetivo: el objetivo de este estudio fue determinar la prevalencia y los factores asociados al consumo de suplementos alimenticios entre atletas brasileños. Material y métodos: se trata de un estudio de corte transversal realizado con 182 atletas de ambos sexos. Los atletas respondieron a un cuestionario que contenía información sociodemográfica y deportiva, consumo actual de suplementos, consumo de sustancias farmacológicas, y también sobre distorsión de la imagen corporal (BSQ) y dismorfia muscular (MASS). Resultados: en el análisis bivariado, el sexo masculino, la edad entre 25 a 29 años, ejercer actividad remunerada, el consumo de sustancias farmacológicas, la distorsión de la imagen corporal, el riesgo de dismorfia muscular, la modalidad de fuerza y la ausencia de asistencia médica fueron los factores asociados al consumo de suplementos. Después del análisis de regresión, el consumo de suplementos fue asociado al sexo masculino (RPA: 1,68; IC 95%: 1,01; 2,78; p = 0,044), consumo de sustancias farmacológicas (RPA: 1,77; IC 95%: 1,37; 2,27; p &lt; 0,001) y riesgo de dismorfia muscular (RPA: 1,75; IC 95%: 1,37; 2,23; p &lt; 0,001). Conclusiones: los resultados de este estudio mostraron claramente la importancia de los profesionales que trabajan junto a los atletas para monitorizar continuamente el uso de suplementos, puesto que se trataba de un comportamiento alimentario asociado a otros comportamientos de riesgo (uso farmacológico) o a trastornos de la imagen (dismorfia muscular) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;33(3): 678-684, mayo-jun. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154488</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores asociados con la suplementación de la dieta entre los atletas brasileños</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24382^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33546^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53747^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
