<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86861</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cognitive and neuropsychiatric disorders in Parkinson&#146;s disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. In Parkinson&#146;s disease there are patients with isolated and multiple cognitive impairment, and their cognitive performance ranges from normal to an advanced degree of dementia. Most patients present an executive deficit, either in isolation or combined with other cognitive disorders, which is considered to be the most characteristic aspect of the disease, and 30-40% of those affected will end up with a clinically-defined dementia. Development. The presence of a mild cognitive disorder in patients with Parkinson means that the risk of dementia appearing at some time during the development of the disease is high. The dementia associated with Parkinson&#146;s disease is specifically related with neuropsychiatric signs and symptoms, which may have three possible explanations: disorders affecting the mesolimbic pathways, diffuse limbic and cortical compromise, or associated Alzheimer-type phenomenology.  Psychotic episodes tend to present more often in patients with dopaminergic treatment and the clinical spectrum of Parkinson-related psychosis covers visual illusions, visual-audio-olfactory hallucinations, delirium and severe paranoid hallucinatory psychosis. All the antiparkinsonian drugs can give rise to hallucinations and psychosis, but the dopamine agonists are the ones with the greatest capacity to do so. Conclusions. In managing these problems, it is crucial for prevention as well as diagnosis and treatment to be carried out as soon as they are detected. Doses of antiparkinsonian drugs must be reduced, although this is not usually enough, and so it will be necessary to associate atypical antipsychotics, which act mainly on 5-HT receptors and, in most cases, do not produce D2 blockage (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bellas Lamas, Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cebrián, Ernesto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Constenla, Iria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabo López, Iria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En la enfermedad de Parkinson hay pacientes con déficit cognitivo aislado y múltiple y el rendimiento cognitivo forma un abanico que va desde la normalidad hasta un avanzado grado de demencia. La mayoría de los enfermos presenta un déficit ejecutivo, aislado o combinado con otras alteraciones cognitivas, que se considera lo mas característico de la enfermedad, y un 30-40% de afectados acabara presentando una demencia clínicamente definida. Desarrollo. La presencia de alteración cognitiva leve en los enfermos parkinsonianos significa la existencia de un riesgo elevado de aparición de demencia en el transcurso de la enfermedad. La demencia asociada con enfermedad de Parkinson  esta específicamente relacionada con sintomatología neuropsiquiátrica, que puede tener tres posibles explicaciones: alteración de vías mesolímbicas, alteración cortical y límbica difusa, o fenomenología de tipo Alzheimer asociada. Los episodios psicóticos se presentan preferentemente en los pacientes con tratamiento dopaminérgico y el espectro clínico  de la psicosis parkinsoniana abarca: ilusiones visuales, alucinaciones visuoaudioolfatorias, delirio y psicosis alucinatoria paranoide grave. Todos los fármacos antiparkinsonianos pueden provocar alucinaciones y psicosis, pero los agonistas dopaminérgicos detentan la mayor capacidad. Conclusiones. En el manejo de esta problemática es muy importante la prevención y el diagnóstico y tratamiento tan  pronto hagan aparición. Han de disminuirse las dosis de antiparkinsonianos, aunque ello no suele ser suficiente, por lo que habrá que asociar antipsicóticos atípicos, que actúen preferentemente sobre receptores 5-HT y no produzcan bloqueo D2, la mayoría de las veces (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;50(supl.2): s33-s39, feb. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86861</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos cognitivos y neuropsiquiátricos en la enfermedad de Parkinson</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34224^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2850^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
