<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98973</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Permanent incapacity in a public company from 1995-2009</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: The quantifying relationship between health, working environment and work capacity allows us to unravel important aspects of permanent incapacity (PI). One of the objectives of this study is to describe working population characteristics of the Provincial Council of Cadiz who were granted permanent incapacity from 1995 to 2009.Method: A retrospective descriptive study was carried out amongst all the workers with PI in the period described with the following variables taken into account: gender, age, time working for the company, type of occupation, cause of PI, temporary work incapacity (TWI) days and number of TWI in the last 5 years that have been recorded in the company´s archives. Results: The number of PI granted to workers was 192, 53,1% of which were women; 59,9% officials. The average age of workers who were granted PI was 54,06 years having worked in the company for an average of 24,98 years. Within the company most PIs&#146; were manual labor, 44,8%; the most frequent type of pathology for PI was musculoskeletal (29,7%) followed by neoplasia (23,4%) and mental diseases (18,8%),the last one in particular was associated to gender (p= 0,006), the type of work done (p=0,007), the age of PIacceptance (p&lt;0,001) and the grade assigned (p&lt;0,000).Conclusion: This study shows us signs regarding the frequency and the distribution of socialdemographic factors as well as signs belonging to the PI process. This enables us to see some key aspects to be taken into account from the point of view of prevention (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romero Sánchez, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marchena Aparicio, José Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>O´Ferrall González, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ares Camerino, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Domínguez, M. Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: La cuantificación de las relaciones entre salud, medio laboral y capacidad para el trabajo nos permite descifrar aspectos importantes de la incapacidad permanente. Este trabajo tiene como objetivo describir las características de la población trabajadora de la Diputación Provincial de Cádiz a la que se le concedió una incapacidad permanente en el periodo 1995-2009.Métodos: Se llevó a cabo un estudio descriptivo retrospectivo sobre el total de trabajadores/as con incapacidad permanente en el periodo descrito que considera las siguientes variables: sexo, edad, antigüedad, tipo de ocupación, causa de la incapacidad permanente, días de incapacidad temporal y número de incapacidades temporales concedidas en los 5 años previos, recogidas a través de archivos documentales. Resultados: El número de incapacidades permanentes concedidas ascendió a 192. Un 53,1% fueron mujeres; funcionarios el 59,9%; la edad de concesión fue de 54,06 años de media con 24,98 años de antigüedad en la empresa; el tipo de trabajo en el que más incapacidad permanente se concedieron es el manual, 44,8%; El tipo de patología más frecuente de incapacidad permanente fueron las enfermedades musculo-esqueléticas (29,7%), neoplasias (23,4%) y trastornos mentales (18,8%), asociándose significativamente dicha variable con el sexo (p=0,006), el tipo de trabajo desempeñado (p=0,007), la edad de concesión(p&lt;0,001) y el grado asignado (p&lt;0,000).Conclusiones: Este estudio aporta indicios sobre la frecuencia y distribución de factores sociodemográficos y propios del proceso de incapacidad permanente que permiten ir descifrando algunos aspectos susceptibles de ser abordados desde el punto de vista de la prevención (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;57(224): 256-264, jul.-sept. 2011. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98973</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La incapacidad permanente en una empresa pública en el periodo 1995-2009</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32545^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32193^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33205</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d44</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28397</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
