<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139121</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Design and validation of a clinical simulation method for teaching nurses to use the Emergency Severity Index for triage</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To design and validate a clinical simulation method for training nurses to use the Emergency Severity Index (ESI) for triage. Methods. Descriptive, cross-sectional study carried out in the emergency department of Hospital Clínico Universitario Virgen de la Arrixaca in Murcia, Spain. The educational intervention had 3 phases focused on theory, skills, and application. The participants, who were nurses with at least a year&#146;s experience in the emergency department, numbered 55, 43, and 32 in each phase, respectively. They undertook training in ESI for triage (phase 1), participated in simulations with patient-actors (phase 2), and applied their acquired skills (phase 3). We used Cohen&#146;s K and the intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC) to compare the nurses&#146; triage assignments to gold-standard triage assignments. Results. We had data for 1100, 799, and 410 observations of performance in each phase, respectively. Agreement statistics between the nurses&#146; performance and the gold standard were 0.68, 0.67, and 0.68 (Cohen&#146;s K) and 0.870, 0.836, and 0.811 (ICC) in each phase, respectively. These results reflect good agreement. Conclusions. This study supports the relevance of clinical simulations for training nurses to implement structured triage, and in particular to use the ESI. We can state that this study opens the door to further research into whether the reliability of triage can be improved by using this approach, specifically whether it can facilitate better interobserver agreement (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández Ruipérez, Tomás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Adánez Martínez, María de Gracia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leal Costa, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Agea, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Pérez, Bartolomé</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Diseñar y validar un modelo pedagógico articulado en torno a técnicas de simulación clínica, dirigido a formar al personal de enfermería en el sistema de triaje norteamericano Emergency Severity Index (ESI). Método. Estudio descriptivo, transversal, realizado en el servicio de urgencias del Hospital Clínico Universitario Virgen de la Arrixaca (Murcia). Se ha estructurado en tres fases (conocimiento teórico, adquisición de habilidades y aplicabilidad), con una muestra de 55, 43 y 32 participantes respectivamente (enfermeros con experiencia mínima de 1 año en urgencias) a los que, tras una formación en triaje ESI, participaron en sesiones de simulación de triaje con pacientes-actores y, en la última fase, con pacientes reales en un escenario real. Para analizar el grado de concordancia entre el nivel adjudicado por los enfermeros y el patrón oro se utilizó el índice kappa de Cohen (K) y coeficiente de correlación intraclase (CCI). Resultados. En las tres fases se obtuvieron 1.100, 799 y 410 observaciones con un grado de acuerdo, según el índice K de Cohen, de 0,68, 0,67 y 0,68, y un CCI, de 0,870, 0,836 y 0,811, respectivamente. Los resultados obtenidos expresan un grado de acuerdo y concordancia bueno. Conclusiones. Este trabajo establece la pertinencia de la simulación clínica como herramienta docente en los programas de formación en técnicas de triaje estructurado y, en especial, en el sistema de triaje ESI. A partir de los resultados de fiabilidad obtenidos (concordancia interobservador), podemos afirmar que se abre una nueva vía de investigación para demostrar si esta nueva técnica es capaz de mejorar la fiabilidad en la toma de decisiones de triaje (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);27(3): 155-160, jun. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139121</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diseño y validación de un modelo pedagógico basado en simulación clínica dirigido a la formación de enfermería en el sistema de triaje estadounidense Emergency Severity Index</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54837^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4705^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28838^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28838^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52871</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
