<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159591</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The social construction of homoparentality: academia, media, and expert discourse</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study analysed the discursive strategies used to construct the phenomenon of gay and lesbian parenting in different public settings such as academia, the media, and the law. A qualitative research method was used: specifically, discourse analysis based on Potter and Wetherell&#146;s proposals concerning interpretive repertoires. It was found that defensive normalisation strategies are favoured against the risk of homophobia and attacks on family diversity. There is a risk of overlooking resources and experiences that could contribute to a richer collective construction of the phenomenon, reflecting its progress in the legislative, social, and political fields (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Domínguez de la Rosa, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montalbán Peregrín, Francisco Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo pretende conocer las estrategias discursivas desde las que se está construyendo el fenómeno homoparental en diferentes espacios públicos, como son: el ámbito académico, los medios de comunicación y el ámbito experto profesional-legislativo. El método de investigación que se utiliza es cualitativo, concretamente, el Análisis del Discurso a partir de la propuesta de Potter y Wetherell de los repertorios interpretativos. Así comprobamos que se privilegia el uso de estrategias normalizadoras defensivas frente al riesgo de homofobia y ataque a la diversidad familiar. Se corre el riesgo de difuminar recursos y experiencias que pudieran contribuir a una construcción colectiva del fenómeno más rica, en su reflejo en avances sobre la acción legislativa, política y social (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;33(1): 82-92, ene. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159591</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La construcción social de la homoparentalidad: ámbito académico, medios de comunicación y discurso experto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23910^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8574</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31198</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28084</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
