<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166588</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Photoelicitation: a useful tool to investigate management of the vulnerability of homeless women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims: The proposal of the manuscript is to provide a methodological reflection on the use of photo-elicitation as a data gathering strategy to explore vulnerability management among homeless women. Methods: A grounded theory study was carried out. Photo elicitation was one of the data gathering techniques used between February 2015 and February 2017. Five women were selected through intentional sampling. All of them were over 18 years old and residents in 4 shelters within the Madrid Care for the Homeless network. Participants used disposable cameras or mobile phones to record their experiences living in the shelters or on the street through photographs. An interview was conducted with each participant in order to explore the meaning of the photos after they were developed. Data analysis comprised, firstly, describing the obvious content of the photos and, secondly, comparing it with the latent content provided by participants during the interviews. Results: Only 3 women finished the task. Through data analysis some theoretical proposals were discovered, which contributed to a deeper knowledge of some previously established categories and subcategories such as: &#145;The good professionals&#146;, &#145;The safe places in the street&#146; and &#145;The threats in the street&#146;. Conclusions: Photo-elicitation enabled an approach to participants&#146; experiences with minimal imposition, allowing them much of the control over the data production. However, it is a demanding technique that requires deep reflection before its implementation, on the part of both participants and researchers (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oter Quintana, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Gil, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín García, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcolea Cosín, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El propósito de este artículo es analizar el uso de la foto-elicitación como herramienta para explorar la gestión de la vulnerabilidad de las mujeres sin hogar. Métodos: Estudio cualitativo orientado desde la teoría fundamentada. La foto-elicitación se empleó en la recogida de datos desarrollada de febrero de 2015 a febrero de 2017. Se seleccionaron mediante muestreo intencional 5 mujeres mayores de 18 años residentes en 4 centros de acogida de la red de atención a personas sin hogar de Madrid. Las participantes hicieron uso de cámaras fotográficas o teléfonos móviles para representar con imágenes su experiencia de vivir en la calle y en el centro de acogida. Reveladas las fotografías se exploró cara a cara su significado mediante entrevista. En el análisis de datos se describió el contenido manifiesto de las imágenes para luego su contraste con el contenido latente producido por las informantes durante la entrevista. Resultados: Solo 3 mujeres de las participantes completaron la técnica. En el análisis del material discursivo y visual producido se hallaron construcciones teóricas que sirvieron para profundizar en el conocimiento de categorías/subcategorías previamente construidas, por ejemplo &#145;Los buenos profesionales&#146;, &#145;Los lugares seguros de la calle&#146; y &#145;Los peligros de la calle&#146;. Conclusiones: La foto-elicitación permite aproximarse a la experiencia de las participantes con mínimas imposiciones, cediéndoles buena parte del control sobre la producción de datos. No obstante, es una técnica exigente para participantes e investigadores que requiere de una profunda reflexión antes de su puesta en marcha (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);27(5): 308-313, sept.-oct. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166588</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Foto-elicitación: una herramienta útil para investigar la gestión de la vulnerabilidad de las mujeres sin hogar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34658</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37735</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15329</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23421</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23591^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19640^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
