<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116017</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Current and future competencies for public health professionals</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To identify current and future competencies (managers and technicians) for public health professionals in Catalonia (Spain). Methods: Qualitative research with a phenomenological approach. Between November 2009 and February 2010, 31 semistructured interviews were completed with public health professionals working in Catalonia. We purposely used a theoretical sample to include the maximum multiplicity of discourses. We conducted a thematic content analysis. Results: We obtained a wide range of current professional competencies, as well as those required for the future, classified according to professional profile. The participants highlighted transversal competencies, such as the importance of sharing a general theoretical framework of the discipline and the institution. Among the most frequently reported competencies were knowledge management, communication skills, teamwork, multidisciplinary and intersectoral orientation, legal knowledge, computer skills and languages, particularly English. It was also important for individual professionals to have specific skills in their areas of activity. In terms of differences between managers and technicians, the study showed that technicians prioritize management skills concerning human and material resources, while managers emphasize organizational and professional public health expertise. Conclusions: There is a need for transversal and specific competencies in distinct areas. Public health is a multidisciplinary field, which collaborates with a wide range of professionals and organizations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Dolors</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Capella, Jordina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peray,  Josep Lluís de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berenguera, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roma, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pujol-Ribera, Enriqueta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Identificar las competencias actuales y las necesarias para el futuro de los directivos y técnicos de salud pública de Cataluña. Métodos: Investigación cualitativa de perspectiva fenomenológica. Se realizaron 31 entrevistas individuales semiestructuradas a profesionales de la salud pública de Cataluña, entre noviembre de 2009 y febrero de 2010. La muestra fue teórica, intencionada y razonada para incluir la máxima pluralidad discursiva. Se realizó un análisis de contenido temático. Resultados: Se ha obtenido una amplia variedad de competencias actuales y necesarias para el futuro, clasificadas por perfil profesional. Como competencias transversales destaca la necesidad de compartir un marco teórico general sobre la disciplina y la institución. Las más enfatizadas son la gestión del conocimiento, las habilidades comunicativas, el trabajo en equipo interdisciplinario, la orientación intersectorial, los conocimientos jurídicos, las habilidades informáticas y el inglés. Es importante que cada profesional disponga de competencias específicas en su área de actuación. En las competencias específicas hay más diferencias entre técnicos y directivos. Los técnicos priorizan competencias en gestión de recursos humanos y materiales, por las dificultades que se encuentran diariamente. Los directivos dan más importancia a los valores profesionales y organizativos relacionados con la salud pública. Conclusiones: Se requieren competencias transversales, en consonancia con un profesional versátil, y competencias específicas según el ámbito de actuación. Estos resultados confirman que la salud pública es un área de conocimiento multidisciplinario que trabaja estableciendo alianzas y colaboraciones más allá de disciplinas, profesiones y organizaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;27(5): 388-397, sept.-oct. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116017</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Identificación de las competencias actuales y futuras de los profesionales de la salud pública</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50220</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d490^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30192^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
