<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150782</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Consequences for the caregiver of a child hospitalized at home in Paediatric Palliative Care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The signs and symptoms shown by children who might need palliative care throughout their live are multiple and changeable thus caregivers need the knowledge to be able to satisfy their needs. Objectives: To describe the care and devices that children in Palliative Care receive. To assess the level of stress, anxiety, overburden, and giving up perceived by the caregivers of children in Palliative Care. Methodology: Descriptive and cross-sectional study of main caregivers of patients treated successively in the Paediatric Palliative Care Unit. Results: Most of the caregivers were mothers aged between 25 and 46 years old, who had to provide multiple types of aid to their children such as, handling the catheter, posture change, full hygiene, medicine administration, respiratory therapy, etc, which had an impact on their quality of life by feeling short of breath, tiredness and nervousness, difficulty in expressing emotions or economic changes. Furthermore, they mentioned having had to modify their leisure activities and family life. They showed a moderate-high level of stress and a moderate level of anxiety. Nonetheless, the risk of giving up shown by the survey respondents ranged from moderate-low. Conclusion: Caregivers evaluated in this study were over-burdened overload with an impact on quality of life, which however did not lead to giving up (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Del Rincón Fernández, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martino Alba, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Llorente, Tamara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Gallardo, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los signos y síntomas que presentan los niños susceptibles de recibir cuidados paliativos a lo largo de su vida son múltiples y cambiantes por lo que, las personas que cuidan de ellos necesitan conocimientos para ser capaces de atender sus necesidades en casa. Objetivos: Describir los cuidados y dispositivos que reciben los niños en cuidados paliativos. Analizar los niveles de estrés, ansiedad, sobrecarga y claudicación percibido por el cuidador principal de niños en cuidados paliativos. Metodología: Estudio descriptivo transversal. Se evalúan los cuidados y su repercusión en el cuidador principal de los pacientes atendidos de forma consecutiva en una unidad de cuidados paliativos pediátricos. Resultados: La mayoría de los cuidadores principales son madres entre 25 y 46 años, que realizan múltiples cuidados a sus hijos como el manejo de sonda nasogástrica, cambios posturales, higiene completa, administración de medicación, terapia respiratoria que repercuten en su calidad de vida al presentar sensación de falta de aire, cansancio y nerviosismo, dificultad para la expresión emocional o cambios en el nivel económico. Además refieren haber tenido que modificar sus actividades de ocio y la vida familiar. Manifiestan un nivel de estrés moderado-alto y de ansiedad moderado. A pesar de todo, el riesgo de claudicación que presentaban las encuestadas oscilaba entre moderado-bajo. Conclusión: Los cuidadores evaluados en este estudio presentan sobrecarga y repercusiones en su calidad de vida, pero que, sin embargo, no da lugar a la claudicación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;23(2): 79-92, abr.-jun. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150782</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Repercusiones en el cuidador principal del niño hospitalizado a domicilio en cuidados paliativos pediátricos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32196^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30048^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29745^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
