<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74096</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Chagas disease in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A 49-year old male patient, native of Bolivia, who came tohis Primary Care physician due to a 10-day long picture ofstress dyspnea, dizziness and chest pressure. He was admittedto the cardiology department with atrioventricular block2:1 and developed complete atrioventricular block that requiredplacement of definitive pacemaker. The serology waspositive for Trypanosoma cruzi. Due to the increase of LatinAmerican migratory flow in Spain, it is important to stressthe need to sensitization and training about imported diseasesby the health care professionals for adequate diagnosticand therapeutic management (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aguilar Shea, A. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernardo Fernández, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López García, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coleto Lovera, D. N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Paciente varón de 49 años natural de Bolivia que acude a su médico de Atención Primaria por un cuadro de diez días de evolución de disnea de esfuerzo, mareo y opresión torácica. Ingresado en el servicio de Cardiología con bloqueo auriculoventricular 2:1 desarrolló un bloqueo auriculoventricular completo que requirió la colocación de un marcapasos definitivo. La serología resultó positiva para Trypanosoma cruzi. Ante el aumento del flujo migratorio latinoamericano a España, es importante remarcar la necesidad de sensibilización y formación en patología importada por parte de los profesionales sanitarios para un adecuado manejo diagnóstico y terapéutico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);34(9): 465-466, nov. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74096</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad de Chagas en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51348</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10326</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14752^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14752^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30425^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1863</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200811</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
