<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101079</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Euneresis. A manifestation of regression in infancy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article reflects the work of a study group concerning the relationship between enuresis and regression. Enuresis is considered as a privileged symptom which expresses the regression or the stagnation in the sexual development of the individual and the question arises as to what extent enuresis can be understood as conflict or as a disorder. Three clinical vignettes illustrate three possible interpretations not naturally excluded in this symptoms: expression of hostility towards parents, conflict with the relationship with parents and regressive manifestation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Machón, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Michelena, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrión, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heras, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillén, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lalanne, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo refleja el trabajo de un grupo de estudio sobre la relación entre enuresis y regresión. Se considera a la enuresis como síntoma privilegiado que expresa la regresión o el estancamiento en el desarrollo psicosexual del niño y surge la cuestión de cuándo la enuresis puede ser entendida como síntoma de un conflicto y cuándo como un trastorno. Tres viñetas clínicas ilustran tres posibles interpretaciones, no excluyentes, de este síntoma: expresión de hostilidad hacia las figuras parentales, emergente de un conflicto en la relación con los padres y manifestación regresiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(62): 109-117, jun. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101079</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La enuresis. Una manifestación de la regresión en la infancia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12465</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33534^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10476</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4855^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
