<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120347</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nori- and Sea spaghetti- but not Wakame-restructured pork decrease the hypercholesterolemic and liver proapototic short-term effects of high-dietary cholesterol consumption</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Restructured pork (RP) enriched in Seaweeds are potential functional foods. The ant apoptotic and hypocholesterolemic effects of consuming cholesterol enriched diets containing Wakame-RP (CW), Nori-RP (CN) and Sea Spaghetti (CS) were tested in a 1-wk study. Groups of six rats per group were fed a mix of 85% AIN-93Mrodent-diet containing cholesterol and cholic acid as a cholesterol rising agent plus 15% RP containing alga. These diets were compared to control-RP diets enriched or not in cholesterol (CC and C, respectively). After 1-wk,cholesterol feeding significantly increased liver apoptosis markers which were significantly reduced by CS (cellularcycle DNA, caspase-3, and cytochrome c), CN (caspase-3and cytochrome c) and CW (caspase-3) diets. CN and CSdiets significantly blocked the cholesterolaemic rising effect observed in the CC group but no protective effect was observed in the CW group. Differences in seaweed composition added to RP appear responsible for blocking or not the proapoptotic and hypercholesterolemia effects of high cholesterol-RP consumption; thus, any generalization on seaweed effects or food containing seaweeds must be avoided. Although present results are worthy, future studies are demanded to ascertain the utility of consuming algal-RP as part of usual diets (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Schultz Moreira, Adriana R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Muniz, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bastida, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Reus, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benedi, Juana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La incorporación de algas, ricas en fibra y compuestos asociados, a reestructurados de carne de cerdo (R) resulta en derivados cárnicos potencialmente funcionales. Eneste trabajo se estudian los efectos antiapoptóticos e hipocolesterolemia antes de dietas en las que se incluyen agentes hipercolesterolemiantes y R enriquecidos en diferentes algas, Wakame (RW), Nori-R (RN) y Espagueti de Mar(RE). Durante una semana grupos de seis ratas cada uno recibieron una mezcla constituida por 85% de dieta AIN-93M para roedores suplementada con colesterol y ácido cólico, como agente hipercolesterolemia te, y 15% deRW, RN o RE. Estas dietas fueron comparadas con otrasa las que se incorporó R control y a las que se añadió o no el agente hipercolesterolemiante. Después de 1 semana de tratamiento el incremento de marcadores de apoptosishepática observado en el lote control con colesterol seredujo por el consumo de las dietas RE (DNA ciclo celular,caspasa-3, y citocromo c), RN (caspasa-3, y citocromoc) and RW (caspasa-3). Sólo las dietas con RN and RE bloquearon significativamente la inducción hipercolesterolemiantede la dieta control enriquecida en colesterol. Teniendo en cuenta las diferencias observadas entre los lotes respecto a sus efectos hipocolesterolémicos y antiapoptóticos, debe evitarse cualquier generalización sobre el consumo de algas y en particular de carnes conteniendo algas. Aunque los resultados son relevantes, deben realizarse estudios futuros para determinar la utilidad del consumo de estos R enriquecidos en algas dentro de dietas habituales  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;28(5): 1422-1429, sept.-oct. 2013. ilus, mapas</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120347</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El consumo de carne de cerdo reestructurada conteniendo Nori o, Espaguetti de Mar, pero no el de Wakame, reduce los efectos hipercolesterolemiantes y proapoptóticos hepáticos inducidos por altas cantidades de colesterol en la dieta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50326^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53500^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37800</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d963^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30827</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d931^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8629</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33546^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
