<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157888</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Developments in the medical treatment of overactive bladder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Overactive Bladder (OAB) is a common problem among men and women. Antimuscarinic drugs are a reference treatment for OAB and act by blocking the muscarinic receptors (M2 and M3 subtypes) in the bladder. Adherence to antimuscarinic treatment is usually low, due to the perceived lack of efficacy and adverse effects. Therefore, new treatments with different mechanisms of action and a more acceptable tolerability profile are needed, and that improve the symptoms of OAB. Mirabegron is a new treatment option for all patients with OAB and could solve an unmet need in patients still not satisfied, or where the antimuscarinic therapy is not indicated, is an alternative option for patients with OAB (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alcántara Montero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La vejiga hiperactiva (VH) es un problema frecuente entre hombres y mujeres. Los antimuscarínicos son la referencia de la terapia para la VH y actúan bloqueando los receptores muscarínicos (subtipos M2 y M3) en la vejiga. La persistencia con el tratamiento antimuscarínico suele ser baja, debido a la percepción de falta de eficacia y a los efectos adversos. Por todo ello, se necesitan nuevos tratamientos con mecanismos de acción diferentes, que tengan un perfil de tolerabilidad más aceptable y que mejoren los principales síntomas de la VH. Mirabegrón es una nueva opción terapéutica para todos los pacientes con VH y podría resolver una necesidad aún no cubierta en pacientes no satisfechos o en los que no está indicado el tratamiento antimuscarínico, siendo una opción alternativa para los pacientes con VH (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);42(8): 557-565, nov.-dic. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157888</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Novedades en el tratamiento médico de la vejiga hiperactiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52129^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d321^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32129^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52129^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52129^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52129^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32129^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
