<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054620</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Galanthamine versus donepezil in the treatment of Alzheimer´s disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To use comparative studies on the utilisation of the acetylcholinesterase inhibitors (AchE), galanthamine and    donepezil, to evaluate the effectiveness and tolerance of the two drugs in the treatment of the symptoms of Alzheimer&#146;s disease    (AD). Development. A search was conducted on Medline for papers dealing with galanthamine and donepezil that had been    published up to February 2007. Six comparative studies involving galanthamine and donepezil were found, although there are    other studies that compare them together with other AchE inhibitors. Conclusions. Both drugs are moderately effective in the    treatment of AD. Nevertheless, whereas in the case of donepezil there seems to be a positive relation between the maximum    dosage and response, for galanthamine doses above 24 mg/day do not seem to offer any improvement. In general, treatment    was well tolerated in all the studies. Maximum recommended doses (24 mg/day for galanthamine versus 10 mg/day for    donepezil) were more often reached in patients treated with donepezil. The five most common side effects were, in order of    frequency of presentation: nausea, agitation, vomiting, headache and fainting. In the long term, the most frequent side effects    from anticholinesterases are, generally speaking, muscle cramps, tremors, nightmares, nausea, vomiting, fatigue, vertigo and    loss of weight. The studies analysed show limitations in the design, duration, sample sizes and the titration schemes of the drugs</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Pousa, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garre-Olmo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilalta-Franch, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Evaluar a través de los estudios comparativos sobre la utilización de los inhibidores de la acetilcolinesterasa    (AchE), galantamina y donepecilo, la eficiencia y tolerancia de ambos fármacos en el contexto de los síntomas de la    enfermedad de Alzheimer (EA). Desarrollo. Se realizó una búsqueda en Medline sobre artículos de galantamina y donepecilo    publicados hasta el mes de febrero del año 2007. Se hallaron seis publicaciones comparativas entre galantamina y donepecilo,    aunque existen otros estudios que los comparan conjuntamente con otros fármacos inhibidores de la AchE. Conclusiones.    Ambos fármacos mantienen una eficacia moderada en el tratamiento de la EA. Sin embargo, mientras que en el donepecilo    parece existir una relación positiva entre la dosis máxima y su respuesta, para la galantamina las dosis superiores a 24    mg/día parece que no ofrecen mejoría. En general, el tratamiento fue bien tolerado en todos los estudios. Las dosis máximas    recomendadas (24 mg/día de galantamina frente a 10 mg/día de donepecilo) se alcanzaron más en pacientes tratados con    donepecilo. Por orden de presentación, los cinco efectos secundarios más frecuentes fueron: náuseas, agitación, vómitos,    dolor de cabeza y desmayos. A largo plazo, los efectos secundarios más frecuentes de los anticolinesterásicos, en general,    son: calambres musculares, temblor, pesadillas, náuseas, vómitos, fatiga, vértigo y pérdida de peso. Los trabajos analizados    presentan limitaciones en el diseño, la duración, el tamaño de las muestras y los esquemas de titulación de los fármacos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;44(11): 677-684, jun. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054620</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Galantamina frente a donepecilo en el tratamiento de la enfermedad de Alzheimer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5840^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24852</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5840^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2850^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2850^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
