<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102110</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetives: To show the efforts made from medical and psychological point of view in a case of extraovarian serous papillary carcinoma. We looked for the control of physical and psychological symptoms, as well as the increase of skills and resources in the patient and her family. Psychological problems: The patient showed a process of adaptative denial and some psycho&#150;functional limitations (asthenia, decrease of autonomy, fistula, and pain) which affect her quality of life, in addition of anxiety, low state of mood and repeated thoughts. All of them had a repercussion in her family such as some fears, anxiety and incertitude. Method of intervention: The actions carried out considered patient and her family like a unit of intervention. Teamwork was done, as well as everyday coordination among the professionals from the moment of admission the patient in the hospital to the death. Also some follow&#150;up with relatives were borne with regard to grief working&#150; out. It was applied Counselling and psychological interventions from a cognitive&#150;behavioral model. Results: We achieved to minimize reactions of anxiety, cognitives and affectives, to appreciate the existent resources in the whole family unit, decrease of worries, improve the communication between patient and her family, progressive adaptation to the proximity of denouement (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arango Pujal, Milton Olallo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antón Manzanedo, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acinas Acinas, M Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: El objetivo del presente artículo es mostrar el trabajo que se hizo desde el punto de vista médico y psicológico en un caso de carcinoma seroso papilar primario extraovárico. Se buscó el control de síntomas físicos y psicológicos, así como potenciar las habilidades y recursos de paciente y familiares. Problemas psicológicos: La paciente mostraba un proceso de negación adaptativa y limitaciones psicofuncionales (astenia, disminución de aut onomía personal, fístula, dolor) que afectaban a su calidad de vida, además de ansiedad, bajo estado de ánimo y rumiaciones cognitivas. Todo esto tenía una repercusión en la familia en miedos, ansiedad, incertidumbre. Método de intervención: Las actuaciones se llevaron a cabo considerando al paciente y a la familia como unidad de intervención. Se realizó trabajo en equipo y coordinación diaria entre los profesionales desde el mismo momento del ingreso de la paciente hasta el fallecimiento. Además se llevaron a cabo seguimientos posteriores con la familia en relación a la elaboración del duelo. Se empleó Counselling e intervenciones psicológicas desde el modelo cognitivo conductual. Resultados: Se consiguió minimizar reacciones de ansiedad, cognitivas y afectivas, valorar recursos existentes en toda la unidad familiar, disminución de preocupaciones, mejorar la comunicación paciente y familia, adaptación progresiva a la cercanía de un desenlace (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);9(1): 183-201, jun 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102110</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervención médico-psicológica con paciente y familiares en un caso de cáncer ginecólogico en cuidados paliativos oncológicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3175</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5342</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5969^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31527^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37587</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
