<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163936</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Competence of triage nurses in hospital emergency departments</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To identify associations between sociodemographic characteristics variables and competence levels of triage nurses in hospital emergency departments. Methods. Descriptive, cross-sectional, multicenter study of triage nurses in hospital emergency departments in the southwestern area of Catalonia (Ebre River territory). We used an instrument for evaluating competencies (the COM_VA questionnaire) and recording sociodemographic variables (age, sex, total work experience, emergency department experience, training in critical patient care and triage) and perceived confidence when performing triage. We then analyzed the association between these variables and competency scores. Results. Competency scores on the COM_VA questionnaire were significantly higher in nurses with training in critical patient care (P=.001) and triage (P=0.002) and in those with longer emergency department experience (P&lt;.0001). Perceived confidence when performing triage increased with competency score (P&lt;.0001) and training in critical patient care (P&lt;.0001) and triage (P=.045). Conclusion. The competence of triage nurses and their perception of confidence when performing triage increases with emergency department experience and training (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Segura, Estrella</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>March-Pallarés, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chanovas-Borrás, Manel R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Adell-Lleixà, Mireia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solà-Miravete, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lleixà-Fortuño, Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora-López, Gerard</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvadó-Usach, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Identificar la relación entre las variables sociodemográficas estudiadas y el nivel competencial de los enfermeros que realizan triaje en los servicios de urgencias hospitalarios (SUH). Método. Estudio descriptivo, transversal, multicéntrico realizado a enfermeros que realizan triaje en los SUH de Terres de l&#146;Ebre. Se analiza la relación entre variables del cuestionario evaluativo de competencias COM_VA©, sociodemográficas (edad, sexo, experiencia laboral total y en SUH, formación en paciente crítico y en triaje, seguridad percibida en la realización del triaje) y habilidades profesionales. Resultados. El nivel competencial (COM_VA©) es mayor en enfermeros con formación en paciente crítico (p = 0,001) y triaje (p = 0,002) y con experiencia en el SUH (p &lt; 0,0001). La seguridad percibida al realizar triaje aumenta con el nivel competencial (p &lt; 0,0001) y con la formación en paciente crítico (p &lt; 0,0001) y triaje (p = 0,045). Conclusiones. La formación y experiencia en el SUH aumentan las competencias del enfermero de triaje y la seguridad percibida al realizarlo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);29(3): 173-177, jun. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163936</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfil competencial en los profesionales de triaje de los servicios de urgencias hospitalarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19270^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4711^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28838^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
