<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89268</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cognitive restructuring: a Posttraumatic stress disorder case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This manuscript presents a case of psychological intervention for a 36 year old woman who seeks  treatment after receiving exposure-based psychological treatment for a diagnosed vaginismus without satisfactory results. During the first interview, she is diagnosed with post traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) following sexual assault given the intense reexperienceing symptoms, including nightmares an flash backs continual and increased vigilance, avoidance of every-day activities (work, leave the house, etc) and hyperarousal. She also suffers form major depressive disorder (MDD). The cognitive restructuring treatment employed highlights the role of emotional self-regulation in emotional disorders (Moses &amp; Barlow, 2006) and synthesizes the principal cognitive restructuring models and techniques: (1) explaining the changes and sequelae that arise at a cognitive, physiological and behavioural level after experiencing a traumatic experience, emphasizing the role of emotional learning in the development of the problem; (2) self-monitoring training of thoughts, images, physiological and behavioural responses, associated with traumatic emotional learning, with the aim of interpreting the information in an adaptive way; (3) correctly reinterpreting everyday life cognitive, emotional and behavioural reactions, helping the patient to handle such reactions by using cognitive strategies; (4) reinforcing the patient´s initiative to confront emotional situations; and 85) persuading of the efficacy of the treatment. After 32 sessions (the first 28 on a weekly basis), the therapeutic objective were achieved, having eradicated PTSD, MDD and vaginismus (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dongil Collado, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta un caso de intervención psicológica llevado a cabo con una mujer de 36 años, que acude a consulta diagnosticada de vaginismo tras haber recibido tratamiento psicológico basado en exposición sin resultados satisfactorios. En la primera entrevista se le diagnostica un trastorno por estrés postraumático (TEP) por violación encontrándose síntomas de reexperimentación muy intensos, con pesadillas y flashbacks frecuentes, destacada hipervigilancia, evitación de casi todas las actividades cotidianas (trabajar, salir de casa, etc) así como niveles de activación fisiológica muy elevados, Presenta también un trastorno depresivo mayor (TDM). El tratamiento mediante reestructuración cognitiva que se ha utilizado resalta el papel de la autorregulación emocional en los trastornos emocionales (Moses y Barlow, 2006) y recoge una síntesis de los  principales modelos y técnicas de reestructuración cognitiva: (1) explicación de los cambios y las secuelas que se producen a nivel cognitivo, fisiológico y motor tras haber sido víctima de una experiencia traumática, destacando el papel del aprendizaje emocional en el desarrollo del problema: (2) entrenamiento en observación de pensamientos, imágenes, respuestas fisiológicas y conductas, relacionados con el aprendizaje emocional traumático, tratando de interpretarlos como una reacción adaptativa; (3) reinterpretación correcta de las reacciones cognitivas, emocionales y conductuales que se van desarrollando en su vida cotidiana, dotando así a la paciente de estrategias cognitivas de manejo de esas reacciones; (4) reforzamiento de las iniciativas propias a la hora de volver a exponerse a situaciones emocionales, y (5) persuasión sobre la eficacia del tratamiento. Tras 32 sesiones ( las 28 primeras con periodicidad semanal), se consiguieron los objetivos terapéuticos, destacando eliminación del TEP, el TDM y el vaginismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;14(2/3): 265-288, dic. 2008. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89268</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reestructuración cognitiva: un caso de estrés postraumático</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3885^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50498^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12338^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
