<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-65709</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-2597</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Silver-Russell syndrome is a rare genetic disease characterized by severe intrauterine and post-natal growth retardation, body asymmetry and dysmorphic facial features; is a well recognizable syndrome, but the etiology seems to be heterogeneous. We present a male baby 6 months old, with prenatal and postnatal growth retardation, asymmetry by right side hemihypertrophy and typical facial dysmorphism; the patient shows no sporadic Silver-Russell syndrome but a rare X-linked heredity with maternal inheritance and an affected male sibling (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aviña Fierro, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Aviña, D. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de Silver-Russell es una rara enfermedad genética caracterizada por un retardo de crecimiento intrauterino y postnatal, asimetría corporal y dismorfismo facial peculiar; el cuadro es reconocible clínicamente pero su etiología parece ser heterogénea. Presentamos el caso de un lactante de 6 meses de edad con retardo del crecimiento prenataly postnatal, asimetría de hemihipertrofia del lado derecho, y dismorfia facial característica; paciente con síndrome de Silver-Russell no esporádico con rara herencia ligada aX, tiene transmisión materna y un hermano también afectado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Bol. pediatr;48(203): 56-58, ene.-mar. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-65709</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6280^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32938^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13957</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
