<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161794</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Classification of patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease according to the Latin American Thoracic Association (ALAT) staging systems and the global initiative for chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (GOLD)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Several classification systems use different criteria when assessing COPD stages. The objective of this study was to compare the prevalence and distribution of COPD stagesusing Global initiative for chronic Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD) recommendationsand Latin American Thoracic Association (ALAT) guidelinesin a primary-care population. Methods. Subjects attending routine primary care visits, &amp;#8805;40 years of age, current or former smokers or exposed to biomass, completed a questionnaire and performed spirometry. COPD was defined as post-bronchodilator FEV1/FVC&lt;0.70 and categorised according to GOLD-2013 criteria and ALAT-2014 guideline. The BODEx index was used to assess the prognostic value of the stratification systems. Results. A total of 1743 subjects completed the interview, 1540 performed acceptable spirometry. COPD prevalence according GOLD-2013 was 20.1% and had a U-shaped stage distribution (group A: 9.3%, B: 4.3%, C: 2.0%, D: 4.6%). According to ALAT, prevalence was 19.7% with a bell-shaped stage distribution (mild: 2.9%, moderate: 9%, severe: 5.4%, very-severe: 2.7%). Approximately 73% of patients were stratified as moderate (45.4%) or severe (27.3%) by ALAT guidelines, whereas using GOLD-2013 criteria the majority of subjects (approximately 69%) were in group A (46.3%) or group B (22.7%). BODE index score increased as COPD worsened according to ALAT stratification. This is not observed with GOLD2013 criteria (similar values for B and C groups). Conclusions. Disease stages differ under ALAT and GOLD-2013 criteria. ALAT identified a greater proportion of COPD subjects in the moderate and severe categories compared with GOLD-2013, where the majority were categorised in group A. Future evaluation of the ALAT classification should address its predictive ability in terms of hospitalizations and mortality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montes de Oca, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laucho-Contreras, María Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schiavi, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas, alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Varela, María Victorina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rey, Alejandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva, Alejandra</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En los diferentes sistemas de clasificación de la EPOC se utilizan diversos criterios de estadificación. El objetivo de este estudio fue comparar la prevalencia y la distribución de los estadios de la EPOC con las recomendaciones de la iniciativa global para la enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica (GOLD) y las orientaciones de la Asociación Latinoamericana de Tórax (ALAT) en una población de atención primaria. Métodos. Sujetos &amp;#8805;40 años de edad, fumadores, exfumadores o expuestos a biomasa que acudieron a visitas rutinarias en centros de atención primaria cumplimentaron un cuestionario y se sometieron a una espirometría. Se definió EPOC si el cociente FEV1/FVC era &lt;0,70 tras la administración de un broncodilatador, y se calificó de acuerdo con los criterios GOLD-2013 y ALAT-2014. El valor pronóstico de los sistemas de estratificación se evaluó mediante el índice BODEx. Resultados. Cumplimentaron la entrevista 1.743 pacientes, de los cuales 1.540 obtuvieron espirometrías aceptables. Según los criterios GOLD-2013 la prevalencia de EPOC fue de un 20,1% y la distribución de estadios fue en forma de U (grupo A: 9,3%, B: 4,3%, C: 2,0% y D: 4,6%). Con los criterios de las orientaciones ALAT la prevalencia fue de un 19,7%, con una distribución de estadios en forma de campana (leve: 2,9%, moderada: 9%, grave: 5,4% y muy grave: 2,7%). Al utilizar las orientaciones de la ALAT, aproximadamente un 73% de los pacientes fue adjudicado a los estratos de EPOC moderada (45,4%) o grave (27,3%), mientras que con los criterios GOLD-2013 la mayoría (aproximadamente un 69%) se clasificó en los grupos A (46,3%) y B (22,7%). Con la estratificación ALAT las puntuaciones del índice BODEx aumentaron al empeorar la EPOC, lo que no se observó con los criterios GOLD-2013 (los valores de los grupos B y C fueron similares). Conclusiones. La distribución de pacientes en los estadios de la enfermedad difiere según se usen los criterios de la ALAT o GOLD-2013. Los criterios de la ALAT identificaron una mayor proporción de pacientes en las categorías moderada y grave de EPOC que los criterios GOLD-2013, con los cuales la mayoría de pacientes fueron adjudicados al grupo A. En futuras evaluaciones de la clasificación ALAT se debería analizar su capacidad predictiva de hospitalizaciones y mortalidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;53(3): 98-106, mar. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161794</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Clasificación de los pacientes con enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica según los sistemas de estadificación de la Asociación Latinoamericana de Tórax (ALAT) y la iniciativa global para la enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica (GOLD)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10113^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28433^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28598^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
