<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120278</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Changes in body composition in relation to the stage of dementia in a group of institutionalized elderly</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: To assess the nutritional status of a group of institutionalized elderly with dementia by analysing the changes in the body composition according to their evolutionary state. METHOD: A cross-sectional study was carried out assessing the nutritional status and the body composition (anthropometry, MNA and bioimpedance) in 63 institutionalized elderly with a diagnosis of dementia in evolutionary stages 5, 6 and 7 of the GDS (Global Deterioration Scale) scales and the FAST (Functional Assessment Stating) scale. The fat mass index (FMI) and the fat-free mass index (FFMI) were calculated. The results were analysed by one-factor ANOVA and Kruskal-Wallis factorial ANOVA and Scheffé's a posteriori contrasts. The significance level was set at p &lt; 0.05. RESULTS: Mean age was 80.6 years (95%CI: 78.3-83.0; Range: 51-95). According to MNA, 38.1% of the sample had hyponutrition, 60.3% was at risk for malnourishment; and 1.6% had normal nutrition. The average body mass index was 23.06 (22.01-24.10) kg/m2, without any significant difference by the degree of evolutionary state, except for those on palliative care (mean: 19.85; 95%CI: 78.3-83.0 kg/m2). The patients in the non-palliative stages GDS/FAST 5, 6 and 7 presented a Z-Score of FMI close to a 0 SD, and a Z-Score for the FFMI of approximately -1 DS. These results are compatible with a sarcopenia situation. In patients on palliative care (GDS/FAST =?7c) both indexes were significantly lower. CONCLUSION: The analysis of body composition should always be included in the assessment of the nutritional status. If not, it would not be possible to detect situations of sarcopenic obesity, which is rather prevalent in elderly people with these characteristics (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Camina Martín, M Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carreño Enciso, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz Marcos, Sandra de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miján de la Torre, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateo Silleras, Beatriz de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Redondo del Río, M Paz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Valorar el estado nutricional de un grupo de ancianos institucionalizados con demencia, analizando los cambios en la composición corporal en función de su estadío evolutivo. Método: Se ha realizado un estudio transversal en el que se valoró el estado nutricional y la composición corporal (antropometría, MNA, y bioimpedancia) en 63 ancianos institucionalizados con diagnóstico de demencia en estadíos evolutivos 5, 6 y 7 de las escalas GDS (Global Deterioration Scale) y FAST (Functional Assessment Stating). Se calcularon los índices de masa grasa (IMG) y de masa libre de grasa (IMLG). Los resultados se analizaron mediante el ANOVA de un factor y ANOVA factorial o Kruskal-Wallis, y contrastes a posteriori de Scheffé. La significación se alcanzó con p &lt; 0,05. Resultados: La media de edad fue 80,6 (IC 95%: 78,3- 83,0; Rango: 51-95) años. Según el MNA, el 38,1% de la muestra presentaba malnutrición, el 60,3% riesgo de malnutrición, y el 1,6% normalidad nutricional. La media del índice de masa corporal fue 23,06 (22,01-24,10) kg/m2, sin diferencias significativas en función del estadío evolutivo, salvo en los paliativos (media: 19,85; IC 95%: 78,3-83,0 kg/m2). Los pacientes en estadíos GDS/FAST 5, 6 y 7 no paliativos presentan una Z-Score del IMG próxima a 0 DS, y una Z-Score del IMLG de aproximadamente -1 DS, resultados compatibles con una situación de sarcopenia. En los paliativos (GDS/FAST =?7c) ambos índices son significativamente inferiores. Conclusión: El análisis de la composición corporal debe ser incluido en la valoración del estado nutricional siempre. De lo contrario no sería posible detectar situaciones de obesidad sarcopénica, muy prevalentes en ancianos con estas características (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;28(4): 1093-1101, jul.-ago. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120278</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambios en la composición corporal en función del grado de demencia en un grupo de ancianos institucionalizados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50238</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50320</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
