<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82045</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacy of rituximab versus cyclophosphamide in lupus patients with severe manifestations. A randomized and multicenter study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There are no controlled studies that compare the efficacy of RTX with standard treatment, such as cyclophosphamide, in patients with systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE). Objective. The objective of this study was to compare the efficacy of rituximab to that of cyclophosphamide in patients with severe manifestations of SLE. Materials and method. This is a multicenter, randomized open and controlled trial in adults with a diagnosis of active SLE. Patients were randomized into two groups; group 1: treated with RTX and group 2: cyclophosphamide pulses with the same steroid scheme. We registered MEX-SLEDAI, steroid requirements and adverse events for 12 months. Descriptive and comparative statistic analysis was performed. Results. 19 patients were included, 17 females, mean age 35.7±12.1 years and duration of disease 5.6 years (range 0.35 to 30.8 years). There were no differences at baseline regarding gender, age, duration of disease, previous treatments or disease activity between both groups. MEX-SLEDAI was reduced from 12 to 3 in group 1 and from 9 to 2 in group 2 (p=0.80). Nevertheless, patients treated with RTX had a faster improvement. There was no difference in the cumulative steroid dose. Both groups had significant reduction in antinuclear antibody levels and similar increase in C3 levels. Adverse events were similar in both groups. Conclusion. This comparative clinical study in patients with SLE shows that rituximab can be as useful as cyclophosphamide for severe manifestations, maybe showing a faster response. Adverse events were no different. Rituximab should be considered as an adequate alternative for this group of patients(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Paz, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urenda-Quezada, Adelfia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrade-Ortega, Lilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barragán-Navarro, Yaneth</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Villanueva, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Irazoque-Palazuelos, Fedra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bourget-Pietrasanta, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Ceballos, María de los Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivas-Ruiz, Rodolfo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">No existen a la fecha estudios controlados que evalúen la eficacia de rituximab (RTX) comparando con un tratamiento estándar, como ciclofosfamida, en pacientes con lupus eritematoso generalizado (LEG). Objetivo. Comparar la eficacia de RTX con ciclofosfamida en pacientes con manifestaciones graves de LEG. Material y método. Estudio clínico aleatorizado, multicéntrico, controlado y abierto en adultos con LEG activo. Se administró RTX o bolos de ciclofosfamida, con mismo esquema de esteroides. Se evaluó MEX-SLEDAI, dosis de esteroide y eventos adversos, durante 12 meses. Se empleó estadística descriptiva y comparativa. Resultados. Fueron 19 pacientes, 17 mujeres, con edad de: 35,7 años ±12,1, y tiempo de evolución de 5,6 años (0,35&#150;30,8). No hubo diferencias en género, edad, tiempo de evolución, tratamientos previos o actividad de la enfermedad al inicio entre los grupos. Se observó descenso en el MEX-SLEDAI de 12 a 3 en el grupo 1, y de 9 a 2 en el grupo 2 (p=0,80). El grupo que recibió RTX tuvo mejoría más rápida. La dosis acumulada de esteroide fue similar. En ambos grupos se observó reducción en niveles de anti-DNAds e incremento de C3. Los eventos adversos fueron semejantes. Conclusión. Este ensayo clínico comparativo muestra que RTX puede ser tan eficaz como ciclofosfamida, para el control de manifestaciones graves del LEG, con respuesta más rápida. Los eventos adversos inmediatos y mediatos no fueron diferentes. RTX puede considerarse una opción terapéutica adecuada en este tipo de pacientes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);6(5): 250-255, sep.-oct.2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82045</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia de rituximab comparado con ciclofosfamida en pacientes con manifestaciones graves de lupus eritematoso generalizado. Estudio aleatorizado y multicéntrico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29646</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22443^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8356^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23164^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8356^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28570^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23164^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3540^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7344^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28636^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
