<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133393</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1473</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Selection of medical graduates for residency posts. A comparative study of the methodologies used in different countries</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Medical grade Selection for residency Postgraduate specialization Residency Clinical competence MIR examination Knowledge testing a b s t r a c t Introduction: The design of an appropriate method for the selection of medical graduates for residency posts is extremely important, not only for the efficiency of the method itself (accurate identification of most competent candidates), but also for its influence on the study and teaching methodologies operating in medical schools. Currently, there is a great variation in the criteria used in different countries and there is no definitively appropriate method. The use of isolated or combined criteria, such as the marks obtained by students in medical schools, their performance in tests of theoretical knowledge and evaluations of clinical competence, or personal interviews, have a limited value for identifying those candidates who will perform better during the residency and later on during independent practice. Objectives: To analyse the variability in the methodologies used for the selection of residents employed in different countries, in particular those used in the United Kingdom and USA, where external agencies and medical schools make systematic analyses of curriculum development. The advantages and disadvantages of national or transnational licensing examinations on the process of convergence and harmonization of medical degrees (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lobato, Ramiro D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lagares, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villena, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castaño-Leon, Ana M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Seoane, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Roldán, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alén, José F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Munarriz, Pablo M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción El diseño de una metodología apropiada para la selección de los graduados que acceden a los puestos de residencia tiene gran importancia porque, aparte de su eficiencia en la elección de los candidatos, condiciona decisivamente el funcionamiento curricular en las escuelas de medicina, incluyendo la manera de estudiar y aprender del estudiante y la actitud docente del profesorado y su motivación para perseguir la innovación curricular. En la actualidad existe una gran dispersión en los métodos de selección de los residentes en diferentes países, evidenciando que no hay ninguno perfecto. El uso aislado de criterios tales como el peso del expediente académico, los test de conocimiento teórico, determinadas pruebas prácticas de la competencia clínica, o las entrevistas tienen un valor limitado para predecir qué candidatos van a ser más competentes durante la residencia o la práctica autónoma. Objetivos Describir las metodologías utilizadas para la selección de los residentes en los países de nuestro entorno prestando especial atención a las empleadas en el Reino Unido y los EE. UU. donde se analiza de manera sistemática el funcionamiento de los currícula en las escuelas de medicina. Se comentan las ventajas y desventajas de los exámenes de ámbito nacional para otorgar el grado y/o construir el listado de acceso a la residencia, y su utilidad para favorecer el proceso de convergencia y armonización de los grados y los programas de residencia a nivel transnacional europeo o internacional. El presente análisis se utiliza para establecer una comparación con la metodología de selección aplicada actualmente en España en un intento de diseñar un nuevo  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurocirugia (Astur);26(1): 3-12, ene.-feb. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133393</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La selección de los graduados en Medicina para los puestos de residencia. Estudio comparativo de los métodos usados en diferentes países</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13421</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8671^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
