<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047030</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness of a home care nursing program for patients with severe mental disorder: a controlled clinical trial</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To assess the effectiveness of a home care nursing program in patients with a severe mental disorder. Method. In a year-long controlled clinical trial, 52 patients with severe mental disorder resident in the city of Badalona (Barcelona) were examined pre- and post- intervention. The following instruments were used to assess the program's effectiveness: the Drug Attitude Inventory (DAI), Global Clinical Impression (GCI), Global Assessment of Functioning (GAF), Quality of Life Satisfaction (QLS), and the Degrees of Insight Questionnaire in Schizophrenic Patients I-II. The data were analyzed using non-parametric statistical tests. Results. There were 30 patients in the experimental group and 22 in the control group. In the experimental group, the trial: a) increased patients' adherence to treatment (p = 0.001); b) enhanced the links with the mental health community center (p &lt; 0.001); c) reduced the number of readmissions and length of hospital stay (a mean of 14 days per year in the experimental group versus a mean of 74 days per year in the control group); d) increased patients' quality of life: intrapsychic (p = 0.02), relational (p = 0.02) and everyday activities (p = 0.021); and e) achieved a slight increase in their functional capacity. Conclusions. The results suggest that the home care nursing program has a positive impact on the general health of patients with severe mental disorder</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Márquez-Romero, M. Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Morales, Josefina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Fenollar, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabadell-Gimeno, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Bouza, Tatiana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Checa-Peña, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayllón-Ortega, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rigol-Cuadra, Assumpta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camarena-Pelegrí, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beltrán-Megías, José Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabater-Mateu, M. Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Eguileta, Maite</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lluch-Canut, M. Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer la efectividad de un programa de atención domiciliaria de enfermería (PADE) administrado a pacientes con trastorno mental severo. Método. Se aplicó un ensayo clínico controlado, con grupo experimental y grupo control, y mediciones pre y postintervención. La muestra estuvo compuesta por 52 pacientes afectados por un trastorno mental severo, residentes en la ciudad de Badalona (Barcelona). El PADE (intervención) se llevo a cabo durante 1 año y para evaluar su efectividad se utilizaron los siguientes instrumentos: DAI (Drug Attitude Inventory); juicio clínico global; GAF (Global Assessment of Functioning); QLS (Quality of Life Satisfaction); cuestionario de grados de insight en pacientes esquizofrénicos I-II. Los datos se analizaron mediante pruebas estadísticas no paramétricas. Resultados. Se estudiaron 30 pacientes en el grupo experimental y 22 en el grupo control. En el grupo experimental se consiguió: a) aumentar la adherencia al tratamiento (p = 0,001); b) incrementar el grado de vinculación a los centros de salud mental (p &lt; 0,001); c) reducir el número de reingresos y los días de reingreso (media de 14 días por año en el grupo experimental frente a 74 días por año en el grupo control); d) aumentar el nivel de calidad de vida de los pacientes, en los aspectos intrapsíquicos (p = 0,02), relacionales (p = 0,02) y de actividades cotidianas (p = 0,021), y e) incrementar ligeramente su capacidad funcional. Conclusiones. Los resultados permiten concluir que el PADE incide favorablemente en el nivel general de salud de los pacientes afectados de un trastorno mental severo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);16(4): 198-205, jul. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047030</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad de la atención domiciliaria de enfermería administrada a pacientes con trastorno mental severo: ensayo clínico controlado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23591</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10553^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16735</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32196^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16836</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12005^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
