<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132876</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Promotion of the Primary Care pediatrician&#146;s emotional health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pediatric professionals are faced today with numerous situations in Primary Care, which generate emotional distress: parents who are suspicious of our diagnosis, grandparents who tell us a better treatment, "as in their days was done", lack of understanding with management, workload and difficulty in organizing work, lack of professional recognition by peers and visibility as a group, etc. Identifying and learning processing the emotional discomfort is a fundamental personal ability to handle these situations with the greatest serenity possible and avoid the risk of a continued frustration of the professionals. In short, all of it is going to make a decisive impact on the climate of the relationship established among professionals, and therefore the ability of the professional to influence beliefs, emotions and behavior of the people with whom he/she relates or are under their direction. In this workshop, some basic ideas about how human emotions work will be addressed in the first place, and secondly some strategies to processes and control them will be offered. We will focus exclusively on the operation and handling of unpleasant emotions, as they often have a decisive influence on the ability of the professionals to establish a positive and effective relationship that can stimulate the motivation of the others to follow behavior patterns. Moreover, some verbs that make easier the comprehension, understanding, respect and mutual confidence will be provided (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Navarro Matillas, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Hoy en día los profesionales de Pediatría tienen que afrontar numerosas situaciones en la consulta de Atención Primaria que les generan malestar emocional: padres que desconfían de nuestro diagnóstico; abuelos que nos recomiendan un tratamiento mejor, &#147;como en su época se hacía&#148;; falta de entendimiento con los directivos; presión asistencial y dificultad para organizar el trabajo; falta de reconocimiento profesional por parte de otros compañeros y de visibilidad como colectivo; etc. Identificar y saber procesar las emociones de malestar es una habilidad personal fundamental para poder manejar estas situaciones con la mayor serenidad posible y evitar el riesgo de la constante frustración de los/as profesionales. En definitiva, todo ello va a influir de forma decisiva en el clima de la relación que se establece entre profesionales y, por lo tanto, en la capacidad del/la profesional para influir en las creencias, emociones y comportamientos de las personas con las que se relaciona o que están bajo su dirección. En este taller se van a abordar, en primer lugar, algunas ideas básicas acerca de cómo funcionan las emociones humanas, para, en segundo lugar, ofrecer algunas estrategias dirigidas a procesarlas y controlarlas. Vamos a centrarnos exclusivamente en el funcionamiento y manejo de las emociones desagradables, ya que suelen tener una influencia decisiva en la capacidad de las/os profesionales para establecer una relación positiva y eficaz que pueda estimular la motivación de los/as otros/as a seguir pautas de comportamiento. Además, se aportarán ciertos verbos que en la comunicación con los padres, familiares, jefes y compañeros facilitan la comprensión, el entendimiento, el respeto y la confianza mutua (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;12(supl.19): s255-s262, nov. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132876</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Promoción de la salud emocional del pediatra de Atención Primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23896</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37555^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13099</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33140</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2698^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37614</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201011</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
