<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-67330</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-0095</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Technology advantages in gases analyse and their supply inmost anaesthesia machines have improved halogenated agents monitoring in inhaled anaesthesia. The first discovering about endotracheal monitoring found intratracheal ETCO2 were very similar to alveolar ETCO2 because their values were almost the same to arterial values. Moreover these ones are different to extratracheal values but there were good correlation level. However, intra and extratracheal differences of halogenated gases and N2O were not studied. Lately, it has discovered significant differences in intratracheal gases monitoring during paediatric anaesthesia. This kind of monitoring can be very useful in the future in critical, paediatric patients and offers a good control of Et halogenated vapors when we don&#146;t have hypnosis monitoring. Advantages and disadvantages are studied of this new intratracheal monitoring system with a promised future (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Quesada, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monge Cid, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo Vecino, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gilsanz Rodríguez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abad Gurumeta, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Lapetra, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los avances tecnológicos en el análisis de gases y su incorporación a todas las máquinas actuales de anestesia han permitido la monitorización de los agentes halogenados en la anestesia inhalatoria. El primer descubrimiento de la monitorización intratraqueal encontró que el ETCO2 intratraqueal era muy similar a los valores alveolares de ETCO2 porque sus valores eran casi los mismos que los valores arteriales. Además estos eran diferentes a los valores extratraqueales aunque existía una buena correlación. Sin embargo, las diferencias intra- y extratraqueales de los gases halogenados y el N2O no fueron estudiados. Recientemente se han descubierto diferencias significativas en la monitorización intratraqueal de gases. Este tipo de monitorización puede ser muy útil en el futuro en pacientes críticos, pediátricos y ofrecer un buen control del Et de los vapores halogenados cuando no se dispone de sistemas de monitorización de hipnosis. Son analizadas las ventajas e inconvenientes de este tipo novedoso de monitorización intratraqueal con un prometedor futuro (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actual. anestesiol. reanim;18(2): 41-45, abr.-jun. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-67330</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d781</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d780^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28998^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
