<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048073</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Follow-up survey of the special unit of psychological attention at summa 112 after the terrorist attacks on 11th march in Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Special Unit of Psychological Attention at SUMMA 112 carried out a medium-term follow-up survey with a 350 subjects sample three months after the terrorist attacks on 11th March 2004 in Madrid, and the results are presented in this paper. Method: A protocol designed ad hoc by the Unit, and the TOP-8 and TQ scales were administered by telephone. Results: In our sample of 350 individuals (66 percent were women) 53 percent of respondents were victims, 27 percent direct witnesses, and 19 percent indirect witnesses of the attacks. During the follow up 33 percent of the total sample showed Post-traumatic Stress Disorder (66 percent were victims). 32 percent of people who answered the questionnaire received mental assistance one week after the terrorist attacks. A high number of respondents (82 percent) indicated a reduction of their initial symptoms during the survey, those which urged them to call SUMMA 112 emergency numbers in the first moments after the attacks. Conclusion: These results show the consequences on people of a traumatic event and the relevance of immediate and close assistance in psychological crisis intervention in order to diminish the negative effects</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hillers Rodríguez, Rosalía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rey Bruguera, Mayelin</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se presentan los resultados del seguimiento a medio plazo realizado por el Dispositivo Especial de Atención Psicológica del SUMMA 112, con una muestra de 350 afectados por los atentados de Madrid, iniciado tres meses después del 11 de marzo de 2004. Método: Se administró telefónicamente un protocolo creado especialmente por el Dispositivo y las escalas TOP-8 y TQ. Resultados: De los 350 entrevistados (66% mujeres), el 53% fueron víctimas de los atentados, el 27% testigos directos y el 19% testigos indirectos. El 33% de los encuestados presentó durante el seguimiento síntomas del Trastorno de estrés postraumático (TPET), siendo el 66% víctimas. El 32% de los encuestados recibió atención en los dispositivos de salud mental la semana siguiente a los atentados. El 82% de encuestados manifestó durante el seguimiento una reducción de los síntomas iniciales que originaron la demanda al SUMMA 112. Conclusión: Estos resultados reflejan las consecuencias sobre las personas de un suceso traumático y la importancia de la intervención psicológica en crisis próxima e inmediata para amortiguar sus efectos</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;22(1): 1-10, jun. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048073</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguimiento de los afectados por los atentados del 11-M en Madrid desde el Dispositivo de Atención Psicológica del SUMMA 112</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33199^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3437^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34598</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
