<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102319</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1972</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Satisfaction, attitudes and perceptions of resident physicians toward teaching and research training</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this paper is to analyze the attitudes and perceptions of residents regarding their training in teaching and research skills in our hospital through a structured survey distributed to resident doctors in third, fourth and fifth year in a teaching hospital of fourth level. The results show high level of dissatisfaction of residents with their training and scientific production.  Given the collective interest of this research, it must implement measures to secure their participation in this activity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Boyero González, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Iglesias, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcos Martín, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo es analizar las actitudes y percepciones de los MIR respecto a su formación en habilidades docentes e investigadoras en nuestro hospital a través de una encuesta estructurada distribuida a los médicos residentes de tercer, cuarto y quinto año en un hospital docente de cuarto nivel. Los resultados muestran el alto grado de insatisfacción de los residentes con su  formación y producción científica. Dado el interés de este colectivo por la investigación, se deben implantar medidas que permitan su participación en esta actividad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Todo hosp;(264): 98-102, mar. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102319</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Satisfacción, actitudes y percepciones de los médicos internos residentes hacia su formación docente e investigadora</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24419</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4570^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23897</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
