<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153572</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nursing care for a low-complexity condition in Primary Care. Clinical case about a urinary tract infection</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Institut Català de la Salut (ICS) is the main public provider of services in Catalonia; and since 2008, Nursing professionals have been seeing and managing low-complexity acute conditions in the Primary Care (PC) setting, through protocols by consensus with algorithms of action in specific scenarios. The objective of this article is to create awareness about Nursing care in this process. To this aim, we present the clinical case of a30-year-old woman, who presented with discomfort and a burning sensation when urinating, during a visit managed and solved by the nurse. The objective of this care under a new role is that nursing professionals can be able to manage mild acute conditions, both in the adult and paediatric population, which will provide an additional value with a nursing care plan, by modifying lifestyles, promoting prevention behaviours and risk control, improving autonomy, and even offering alternative options of care to medicalization. Managing low-complexity health problems, such as the clinical case presented here, entails an increase in nurses&#146; responsibility and commitment, beyond healthcare education in the Primary Care setting (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dalfó Pibernat, Artur</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosell Vidal, Jessica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peralta García, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gibert Llorach, Elvira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dalfó Pibernat, Enric</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Institut Català de la Salut (ICS) es el principal proveedor público de servicios sanitarios de Cataluña y desde 2008 los profesionales de Enfermería atienden y gestionan la patología de baja complejidad aguda en el ámbito de la Atención Primaria de Salud (APS) mediante protocolos consensuados con algoritmos de actuación en determinadas situaciones. El objetivo del presente trabajo es dar a conocer la atención de Enfermería en este proceso, y con ese fin se presenta un caso clínico de una mujer de 30 años de edad, que presenta molestias y escozor al orinar en una visita que gestiona y resuelve la enfermera. La finalidad de esta atención bajo un nuevo rol es que los profesionales enfermeros atiendan una patología aguda leve, tanto en la población adulta como infantil, lo que proporciona un valor añadido con un plan de cuidados enfermeros, modificando estilos de vida, promoviendo conductas de prevención y control del riesgo, mejorando la autonomía e incluso dando alternativas de cuidado a la medicalización. La atención de problemas de salud de baja complejidad, como el presente caso clínico, conlleva el incremento de la responsabilidad y el compromiso de las enfermeras más allá de la educación sanitaria en la APS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;19(1): 6-11, feb. 2016. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153572</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Atención enfermera a la patología de baja complejidad en Atención Primaria de Salud. Caso clínico de una infección del tracto urinario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11742^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10541</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9916^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
