<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112495</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">One weekly fluoxetine, tolerability and safety according to use patterns in the psychiatric clinical practice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Treatment with selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRI) has become generalized in all the medical setting although its efficacy and good tolerability may be affected by long term non-compliance. Once weekly fluoxetine could improve compliance due to the comfort of its use. The objective is to evaluate the safety, tolerability and efficacy of one weekly fluoxetine (90 mg) in a sample of out-patients, following naturalistic criteria in the usual clinical practice. Method. A total of 46 patients (age: 41,89± 1,85) who received one weekly fluoxetine for at least 3 months (mean time: 135.24 days) were analyzed retrospectively. Clinical Global Impression of Severity (CGI-S) at the onset and end of the period evaluated, presence of adverse events, drop-out index and impression of patient´s satisfaction with the treatment and use pattern were used. Results. The mean of the final CGI-S was 2,09, compared with the onset 3.09 (p&lt;0.02), indicating significant improvement in the efficacy with one weekly fluoxetine. The most frequent adverse effects were: anxiety (10.87%), headache (8,69%) and restlessness (8.69%) related with once weekly fluoxetine. Compliance was very high at the onset (99%) and at the end (96%). Ten patients dropped-out of the treatment (27.74 %), 6 due to appearance of undesirable effects (anxiety; headache and insomnia), three due to voluntary wish and only one due to lack of efficacy. The CGI of satisfaction of clinical global efficacy on the final visit was 1.43 (satisfied-very satisfied) and the CGI of satisfaction for the treatment pattern was 1.17 (very satisfied). Conclusion. Change to once weekly fluoxetine generally improves satisfaction of treatment efficacy and its use pattern, although some patients return to the initial regime after adverse effects appear (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vega Fernández, F. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varona, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gándara, J de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Majadas Fernández, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montejo González, A. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El tratamiento con inhibidores selectivos de la recaptación de serotonina (ISRS) se ha generalizado a todo el ámbito médico, si bien su eficacia y buena tolerabilidad pueden verse comprometidas por el incumplimiento a largo plazo. La fluoxetina semanal podría mejorar el cumplimento debido a su comodidad de uso. El objetivo es evaluar la seguridad, tolerabilidad y eficiencia de la fluoxetina semanal (90 mg) en una muestra de pacientes ambulatorios siguiendo criterios naturalísticos en la práctica clínica habitual. Método. Se analizaron retrospectivamente 46 pacientes (edad: 41,89 ± 1,85) que recibieron fluoxetina semanal al menos durante 3 meses (tiempo medio: 135,24 días). Se utilizó la Escala de Impresión Clínica Global de Severidad (ICG-S) al inicio y al final del período evaluado, la presencia de acontecimientos adversos, el índice de abandonos y la impresión de satisfacción del paciente con el tratamiento y con el patrón de uso. Resultados La media de la ICG-S final fu edad 2,09 comparada con la inicial 3,09 (p&lt;0,02), indicando mejoría significativa en la eficacia con fluoxetina semanal. Los efectos adversos más frecuentes fueron: ansiedad (10,87%), cefalea (8,69%) e inquietud (8,69%) relacionados con fluoxetina semanal. El cumplimiento fue muy alto al inicio (99%) y al final (96%). Diez pacientes abandonaron el tratamiento (27,74%), seis por aparición de efectos indeseables (ansiedad, cefalea e insomnio), tres por deseo voluntario y sólo uno por falta de eficacia. La ICG de satisfacción por la eficacia clínica global en visita final fue de 1,43 (satisfecho-muy satisfecho)y la ICG de satisfacción por el patrón de tratamiento fue de 1,17 (muy satisfecho). Conclusión. El cambio a fluoxetina semanal por lo general mejora la satisfacción de la eficacia del tratamiento y del patrón de uso del mismo, si bien algunos pacientes regresan a la pauta inicial tras la aparición de efectos adversos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;32(5): 280-286, sept.-oct. 2004. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112495</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fluoxetina semanal. Tolerabilidad y seguridad según patrones de uso en la práctica clínica psiquiátrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28248</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4420</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28248^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28248^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28248^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
