<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135253</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnosis and treatment of familial hypercholesterolemia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Familial hypercholesterolemia is the most frequent monogenetic disease. The mode of transmission is autosomal dominant. This disease is characterized by severe elevations of low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDLc), with the possibility of deposits in different tissues. Unless treated appropriately, this disorder carries a high risk of vascular complications and shortened life expectancy. Therefore, strategies for its early detection in the population should be designed to allow early treatment in affected individuals at young ages. Due to the peculiarities of this disease, vascular risk is estimated by methods that differ from those used in the general population. Drug treatment (mainly statins) is almost mandatory in all affected individuals due to their extremely high LDL-c levels. This type of treatment has been shown to be safe and effective in preventing the vascular complications for which this population is at risk (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Enterría, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Faedo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hipercolesterolemia familiar es la enfermedad hereditaria monogénica más frecuente. Se transmite de forma autosómica dominante y se caracteriza por cifras de colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de baja densidad (cLDL) muy elevadas, con posibilidad de presentar depósitos en distintos tejidos. Su presencia entraña un elevado riesgo vascular y un acortamiento de las expectativas de vida si no se trata adecuadamente. Es necesario, por tanto, diseñar estrategias de detección precoz en la población que nos permitan iniciar el tratamiento en edades tempranas de la vida. El riesgo vascular se estima por métodos distintos de los aceptados para la población general debido a las peculiaridades que presentan. El tratamiento con fármacos (fundamentalmente estatinas) es prácticamente obligado para la totalidad de personas afectadas, a causa de los valores de cLDL tan elevados que suelen presentar. El tratamiento farmacológico se ha mostrado seguro y eficaz para prevenir las complicaciones vasculares que amenazan a este colectivo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;54(supl.2): 11-16, ene. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135253</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico y tratamiento de la hipercolesterolemia familiar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8251^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8252^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33014^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52458^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4074^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50058^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4074^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7118^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7118^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4074^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54030^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7118^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51609^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7118^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
