<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111654</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">On 4 April 2011, as part of the XVIII Conference in Lay and the Human Genome, the offical presentation took place of the first Spanish language Encyclopedia of Biolaw and Bioethics, in an event organised by the Inter-University Chair in Law and the Human Genome held, on this occasion, in the new Auditorium of the University of the Basque Country. The Encyclopdia of Biolaw and Bioethics is a project which was conceived and riven forward by the Inter-University Chair in Law and the Human Genome. It was an ambitious project which was supported by the Roche Institute Foundation. It was therefore a magnum opus which began more than three years ago and which has required the work of more than 200 professionals from various disciplines in Spain, Latin America and Portugal.  The encyclopaedia tries to make up for the lack of a suitable publication in the Spanish language that could be use as a reference and be consulted by different experts who have to tackle controversies and doubts posed in the field of biolaw and bioethics as part of their everyday work. The work makes it possible to ascertain the situation in this field regarding the most controversial issues and emerging conflicts, find out which values, assets or rights are involved or confronted, what solutions have been proposed by bioethics and the social positions that have been established through legal regulations. All in all, the encyclopaedia was the culmination of an ambitious undertaking, a pioneering work in the Spanish speaking countries due to its charateristics and scope. It is essential to have such a resource in today´s cultural environment. The presentation of the Encyclopedia of Biolaw and Bioethis given by Mr. Del Barrio Seoane as Director General of the Roche Institute Foundation during the Conference deservers a special mention. The project has been consolidated through the support of this institution (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barrio Seoane, Jaime del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El pasado 4 de abril de 2011, en el marco de las XVIII Jornadas sobre Derecho y Genoma Humano, tuvo lugar la presentación oficial de la primera Enciclopedia de habla hispana de Bioderecho y Bioética, en un acto organizado por la Cátedra Interuniversitaria de Derecho y Genoma Humano celebrado, en esta ocasión, en el Paraninfo de la Universidad del País Vasco. La Enciclopedia de Bioderecho y Bioética es una oba concebida e impulsada por la Cátedra Interuniversitaria de Derecho y Genoma Humano, un ambicioso empeño al que se ha prestado su apoyo la Fundación Instituto Roche. Se trata, por tanto, de una obra magna, que empezó a gestarse hace más de tres años y que ha precisado la labor de más de 200 profesionales de distintas disciplinas de España, Latinoamérica y Portugal. Con ella, se pretende cubrir la carencia que existía en habla hispana de una obra que pudiese ser fe referencia y consulta para los distintos expertos que se deben enfrentarse en sus tareas cotidianas a controversias y dudas planteadas en el ámbito del bioderecho y de la bioética. La obra, permite verificar la situación en este campo sobre los temas más polémicos y los conflictos emergentes, qué valores, bienes o derechos se han visto implicados o confrontados así como cuáles han sido las soluciones que se han propuesto desde la Bioético y cuáles han sido las posiciones sociales cristalizadas en normas jurídicas. Con todo, la Enciclopedia pretende colmar una empresa ambiciosa, pionera por sus características y dimensiones en los países de habla hispana y necesaria en nuestro ámbito cultural.  Mención Especial merece la presentación que en dichas Jornadas hizo D. Jaime del Barrio Seoane en torno a la Enciclopedia de Bioderecho y Bioética, en calidad de Director General de la Fundación Instituto Roche, institución gracias a la cual este proyecto ha podido consolidarse (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. derecho genoma hum;(34): 13-18, ene.-jun. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111654</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La Enciclopedia de Bioderecho y Bioética</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4771</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1698</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6958</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
