<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80450</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Community nutrition and sustainability: concept and evidence</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In community nutrition, sustainability refers to the ability of the program or intervention to continue over time in line with local and global economic, human and environmental resources. We can differentiate the sustainability into two major conceptual areas: The sustainability of community nutrition programs, understood as autonomy and self-financing or external independence, and the sustainability of agricultural, livestock and nutritional policies with respect to the environment. Food production exerst distinct effects on the geophysical environment, such as the degradation of species, the emission of toxins, air pollution and water consumption. The changes in diet related to reducing animal products and increasing vegetable comsumption not only produce benefits for human health and on the overall utilization of land, but can also play a decisive role in the policies of climate change mitigation. The Mediterranean, being understood not only as a concrete set of foods but also as a cultural incorporating the ways foods are produced and processed, is an example of sustainability, in wich biodiversity is also key. Sustainability should be considered as a fundamental element when planning and defining community nutrition interventions and should constitute a key issue in the agenda for climate change mitigation(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Serra-Majem, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En nutrición comunitaria la sostenibilidad hace alusión a la capacidad del programa o intervención de perdurar en el tiempo en armonía con los recursos económicos, humanos y medioambientales locales y globales. Podemos diferenciar la sostenibilidad en dos grandes áreas conceptuales: sostenibilidad de los programas de nutrición comunitaria, entendido como autonomía y autofinanciamiento o no dependencia exterior y sostenibilidad de las políticas agrícolas, ganaderas y nutricionales con el medio ambiente. La producción de alimentos tiene distintas consecuencias sobre el entorno geofísico, como la degradación de especies, la emisión de tóxicos, la polución atmosférica y el consumo de agua. Los cambios en la dieta, reduciendo los productos animales e incrementando los vegetales, pueden no sólo producir beneficios en la salud humana y en la utilización global de los recursos de la tierra, sino que además pueden desempeñar un papel decisivo en las políticas de mitigación del cambio climático. La dieta mediterránea, entendida no sólo como un conjunto de alimentos, sino además como una cultura sobre las formas de producir y elaborar los alimentos, es un ejemplo de sostenibilidad, en la que la biodiversidad es también un elemento clave. La nutrición comunitaria debe considerar la sostenibilidad como un elemento fundamental en su planificación, y tiene que constituir en sí misma un aspecto prioritario en la agenda para la mitigación del cambio climático(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;16(1): 35-40, ene.-mar.2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80450</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nutrición comunitaria y sostenibilidad: concepto y evidencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16303^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32441^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51686^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4858</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34661^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3184^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4067^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38364</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16276^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51714^s22082</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34661^s22082</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16570</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16303^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
