<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165674</identifier>
<setSpec>1697-641X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dental considerations in patients with idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Coagulation disorders are a major drawback in daily dental practice, more so in the increasingly frequent implant surgical treatments, because of the risk of bleeding. Idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP) or primary immune purpura is part of the heterogeneous group of so-called &#145;rare&#146; diseases and is characterized by a temporary or persistent decrease in platelet counts. A greater number of hemorrhagic events derived from ITP are added the use of drugs with a large and important dental impact, such as cyclosporine, monoclonal antibodies or corticosteroids. The objective of this work is to provide the dentist the main characteristics of the disease and the pharmacological implications related to its treatment in order to provide a correct and individualized care to each patient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz Alonso, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Buesa Bárez,  José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruíz Sáenz, Pedro Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Rodríguez, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez González, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los trastornos de coagulación constituyen un gran inconveniente en la práctica odontológica diaria, especialmente en los cada vez más frecuentes tratamientos quirúrgicos implantológicos, por el riesgo de hemorragia. La púrpura trombocitopénica idiopática (PTI) o púrpura inmune primaria forma parte del grupo heterogéneo de enfermedades denominadas &#145;raras&#146; y está caracterizada por una disminución temporal o persistente del recuento plaquetario. A un mayor número de sucesos hemorrágicos derivados de la PTI se añade el empleo de fármacos con una gran e importante repercusión odontológica como la ciclosporina, los anticuerpos monoclonales o los corticoides. El objetivo de este trabajo es facilitar al odontólogo las principales características de la enfermedad y las implicaciones farmacológicas relacionadas con su tratamiento a fin de dispensar una atención correcta e individualizada a cada paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cient. dent. (Ed. impr.);14(2): 109-113, mayo-ago. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165674</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consideraciones odontológicas en los pacientes con Púrpura Trombocitopénica Idiopática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1805^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24400^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33572^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29857^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28875^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
