<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166455</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cardiovascular risk assessment: relevance and usefulness</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The latest guidelines on the management of dyslipidemia produced by the European Society of Cardiology (ESC) emphasize that preventative treatment should be based on an assessment of the individual&#146;s total cardiovascular risk. The recommended assessment tool is the modified SCORE (Systematic Coronary Risk Evaluation) risk chart, which takes high-density lipoprotein cholesterol into account. The chart classifies asymptomatic patients according to their risk of dying from cardiovascular disease in the next 10 years: very high (&gt;10%), high (5-10%), moderate (1-5%) or low (&lt;1%). The use of additional complementary risk markers or risk factors (e.g. other lipid or laboratory parameters, the results of imaging techniques such as carotid ultrasonography, the coronary calcium score or the ankle-brachial index) are considered useful for refining risk assessment in intermediate-risk patient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alegría Barrero, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alegría Barrero, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alegría Ezquerra, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En las nuevas «Guías para el manejo de las dislipemias» de la Sociedad Europea de Cardiología se destaca la importancia clínica de calcular el riesgo cardiovascular total individual como base de las decisiones de tratamiento preventivo ulteriores. El baremo aconsejado es el SCORE modificado con la inclusión del colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de alta densidad, con el que los sujetos asintomáticos se catalogan en riesgo muy alto (&gt; 10%), alto (5-10%), moderado (1-5%) o bajo (&lt; 1%) de fallecer por una causa cardiovascular en los siguientes 10 años. Algunos marcadores o factores de riesgo complementarios (otros parámetros lipídicos y analíticos, técnicas de imagen como la ecografía carotídea, el calcio coronario o el índice tobillo/ brazo) se consideran útiles para afinar la cuantificación del riesgo de los sujetos en la categoría intermedia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);12(supl.C): 8c-11c, 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166455</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estratificación del riesgo cardiovascular: importancia y aplicaciones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d963^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d931^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50514^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50504^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14679^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201200</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
