<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122418</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patients with advanced Parkinson&#146;s disease with and without freezing of gait: A comparative analysis of vascular lesions using brain MRI</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Freezing of gait (FOG) is one of the most disabling and enigmatic symptoms in Parkinson&#146;s disease. Vascular lesions, observed in magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scans, may produce or exacerbate this symptom. Patients and methods: The study includes 22 patients with Parkinson&#146;s disease subjects, 12 with freezing of gait and 10 without. All patients underwent an MRI scan and any vascular lesions were analysed using the modified Fazekas scale. Results: Patients with FOG scored higher on the modified Fazekas scale than the rest of the group. Although the two groups contained the same percentage of patients with vascular lesions (50% in both groups), lesion load was higher in the group of patients with FOG. Vascular lesions in the periventricular area and deep white matter seem to be the most involved in the development of FOG. Discussion: Vascular lesions may contribute to the onset or worsening of FOG in patients with PD. This study suggests that cerebral vascular disease should be considered in patients with FOG (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vaamonde, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallardo, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabello, J. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibañez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrasco, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastor, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Torrero, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La congelación de la marcha (CDM) es uno de los fenómenos más incapacitantes y menos comprendido de la enfermedad de Parkinson idiopática (EPI). Las lesiones vasculares, objetivadas mediante resonancia magnética nuclear (RMN), podrían contribuir a la aparición o empeoramiento de este síntoma. Pacientes y método: Se estudió un grupo de 22 pacientes con EPI avanzada, 12 con episodios de CDM y 10 sin dichos episodios. Se realizó RMN en todos los pacientes y se analizaron, mediante la escala de Fazekas modificada, las lesiones vasculares existentes. Resultados: Los pacientes con CDM obtuvieron puntuaciones superiores en la escala de Fazekas modificada. Aunque el porcentaje de pacientes que presentaban lesiones vasculares fue el mismo en ambos grupos (50% en los 2 grupos), la carga lesional fue superior en el grupo de pacientes con CDM. Las lesiones vasculares en la región periventricular y en la sustancia blanca profunda son las que parecen estar más implicadas en la aparición de la CDM. Conclusiones: Las lesiones vasculares podrían contribuir a la aparición o al empeoramiento de la CDM en los pacientes con EPI, con este estudio se sugiere que la afección vascular cerebral debe ser considerada en los pacientes con CDM (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;29(4): 218-223, mayo 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122418</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pacientes con enfermedad de Parkinson avanzada con y sin congelación de la marcha. Análisis comparativo de lesiones vasculares en resonancia magnética cerebral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24230^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34319^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15055^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
