<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85150</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Consequences of lawsuits on affected doctors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To determine the consequences of a judicial claim on the private life and professional practice of affected doctors. Material and methods. A cross-sectional, descriptive study was performed on the basis of 169 surveys filled out by physicians subjected to a lawsuit in Spain in the period including 2002-2005. Results. The claim produced a bad or very bad personal experience in 98.8%. A total of 85.1% admitted repercussions on family life, 84% made some change in the way they worked, and 57.4% admitted effects on their vocation. There was an unfavorable court ruling in 6%. Conclusions. There were important repercussions on doctors after a lawsuit, both on their private and family life, as well as the way they approach medical practice(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Sánchez, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Labajo-González, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albarrán-Juan, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santiago-Sáez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perea-Pérez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Determinar las consecuencias que una reclamación judicial tiene para la vida personal y la práctica profesional de los médicos afectados. Material y métodos. Estudio transversal, descriptivo, realizado sobre 169 encuestas cumplimentadas por médicos que han sido objeto de una reclamación judicial en España durante el período 2002-2005. Resultados. La reclamación supuso una vivencia personal mala o muy mala en el 98,8%. Un 85,1% reconoce una repercusión en su vida familiar. El 84% ha variado su forma de trabajar y el 57,4% reconoce repercusión en su vocación. En el 6% hubo resolución judicial desfavorable. Conclusiones. Se evidencian importantes repercusiones en los médicos después de una reclamación judicial, tanto en su vida personal y familiar, como en la forma de afrontar el ejercicio de la medicina(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;211(1): 17-22, ene.2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85150</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consecuencias de las reclamaciones judiciales sobre los médicos afectados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11653^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36419</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36414</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11799^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36311^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201101</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
