<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103912</identifier>
<setSpec>1697-641X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interleukin 1 (IL-1) polymorfims in periOdontitis: rewiew of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The principal aim of the review was to determine the association between interleukin 1(IL-1) and periodontitis, and the possible repercussions of the same for the severity of periodontal disease. Material and method A bibliographic search was conducted, looking for systematic reviews and longitudinal studies published between 1990 and 2011into IL-1 polymorfisms, in the following databases: PubMed, EMBASE and Cochrane. Results Of the articles reviewed that sought to establish a correlation between IL-1polymorphisms and periodontal disease, 24were longitudinal studies and 1 was a retrospective study. Of the 25 studies, 9established a relationship between different clinical variables and the IL-1 polymorphisms. The remaining 16 sought to relate the presence of certain polymorphisms to IL-1 with the presence and/or absence of (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Piñas Caballero, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballín García, Armando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Aguilar, Mariano</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción El objetivo principal de la revisión fue determinar la asociación entre los polimorfismos de la interleukina 1 (IL-1) y la posible repercusión de los mismos en la severidad de la enfermedad periodontal. Material y método Se realizó una búsqueda bibliográfica de revisiones sistemáticas y estudios longitudinales publicados desde 1990 hasta el año2011 sobre los porlimorfismos de la IL-1 en las bases de datos: PubMed, EMBASE y Cochrane. Resultados De los artículos revisados que tratan de establecer correlación entre los polimorfismos de la IL-1 y la enfermedad periodontal,24 fueron estudios longitudinales y 1 un estudio retrospectivo. De los 25 estudios, 9establecen relación entre diferentes variables clínicas y los polimorfismos de la IL-1.Los 16 restantes intentan relacionar la presencia de ciertos polimorfismos de la IL-1con la presencia y/o ausencia de periodontitis. Discusión Existe una relación demostrada entre los polimorfismos de la IL-1 y la severidad de la enfermedad periodontal constada en numerosos estudios por el empeoramiento de las (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cient. dent. (Ed. impr.);9(2): 35-44, mayo-ago. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103912</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Polimorfismos de la interleukina 1 (IL-1) en la Periodontitis: Revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11547</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29487^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10709^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
