<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147496</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Care of the family</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Care of the families of cancer patients should be a central activity of health teams, with similar importance to that of symptom control. Most of the care provided to these patients falls to their families, which can often lead to caregiver overload. The aim of caring for the carers should be to reduce this overload through strengthening their resources and reducing their vulnerability. Key elements are communication skills and adequate emotional support. Few studies have been published on interventions with relatives in the specific setting of the care of advanced cancer patients. Therefore, the disparity between the objectives of palliative medicine, theoretically focused on patients and their families, and the services actually provided to carers, is evident. Well designed studies to evaluate these interventions are required (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso Babarro, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La atención a la familia del paciente oncológico debe ser una actividad central en la asistencia de los equipos sanitarios, con importancia semejante a la de controlar los síntomas del paciente. La mayor parte de los cuidados prestados a estos enfermos recae en sus familiares. En muchas ocasiones esos cuidados conducen a la sobrecarga del cuidador. El objetivo de la atención a los cuidadores debe ser reducir esa sobrecarga mediante la potenciación de sus recursos y la disminución de su vulnerabilidad. Las habilidades de comunicación y un adecuado soporte emocional son los aspectos clave en la atención. Hay pocos trabajos sobre intervenciones con familiares en el ámbito específico de cuidados al enfermo oncológico avanzado. Resulta evidente, por tanto, la disparidad entre los objetivos de la medicina paliativa, teóricamente enfocados a paciente y familia, y la atención prestada realmente a los cuidadores. Sería importante realizar estudios con diseños adecuados para valorar las intervenciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;38(supl.2): 14-20, nov. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147496</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Atención a la familia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29745^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14105^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11797</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
