<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91260</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Muscle catabolism in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives. Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) is accompanied by muscle involvement. Pseudouridine, a catabolite of RNA, has been used in other conditions to assess muscle catabolism. We have examined the excretion of pseudouridine in patients with different stages of COPDs evolution. Subjects and methods. We have defined four population groups: control group (without disease), chronic bronchitis group, emerging COPD group, and advanced COPD group. Pseudouridine was determined by high performance liquid chromatography, Results. Pseudouridine extraction (pseudouridine/creatinine ratio) was (mean + 19.9 (6.6) &amp;#956;mol/mmol in control group and was found to be very increased in all the patients with pulmonary condition: chronic bronchitis, 44.1 (60.75) &amp;#956;mol/mmol, 81.6 (56.8) &amp;#956;mol/mmol in emerging COPD group and 140.1 (68) &amp;#956;mol/mmol in advanced COPD for all the comparisons with normal subjects and among patients with lung disease). Age and gender did not affect pseudouridine excretion. Conclusions. The urinary excretion of pseudouridine is increased in chronic bronchitis and COPD and is related to disease stage. Its excretion is independent of age and gender(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Ortega, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabanes-Mariscal, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez de Terreros, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina Font, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montenegro Álvarez de Tejera, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villa-Corbatón, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes y objetivos. La enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica (EPOC) se acompaña de afectación muscular. La pseudouridina, catabolito del RNA, ha sido empleado en otras afecciones para evaluar el catabolismo muscular. Hemos examinado la excreción de pseudouridina en pacientes con diferentes estadios evolutivos de su EPOC. Sujetos y métodos. En cuatro grupos de sujetos (controles sanos y enfermos con bronquitis crónica, EPOC emergente y EPOC avanzada) determinamos la excreción urinaria de pseudouridina (orina aleatoria) mediante cromatografía líquida de alta resolución (HPLC). Resultados. La excreción de pseudouridina (cociente pseudouridina/creatinina [Psu/Crea]) en la población sana fue de (media ± DE) 19,9±6,6&amp;#956;mol/mmol y se halló muy incrementada en todos los enfermos con afección pulmonar: bronquitis crónica, 44,1±60,7&amp;#956;mol/mmol; EPOC emergente, 81,6±56,8&amp;#956;mol/mmol y EPOC avanzada, 140,1±68,0&amp;#956;mol/mmol (p&lt;0,01 para todas las comparaciones con los sujetos normales y entre los pacientes con afección pulmonar). La edad y el sexo no influyeron en la excreción de pseudouridina. Conclusión. La excreción de pseudouridina está incrementada en pacientes con bronquitis crónica y EPOC. Se relaciona con el estadio de la enfermedad y su excreción es independiente de la edad y del sexo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;211(10): 511-516, nov.2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91260</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Catabolismo muscular en pacientes con enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8837^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2900^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11997^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9327^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2900^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2900^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9327^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201111</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
