<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056607</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Expectations and needs detected among professionals at provincial organizations working in intersectorial action in health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Intersectorial Action in Health has been the    methodology proposed for reducing inequality in health. The    objectives of this study are to ascertain what experiences,    expectations and needs are perceived to exist among the professionals    working at provincial organizations in order to propose    a framework for analyzing and carrying out intersectorial work.    Methods: With a qualitative design, 21 semi-structured    individual surveys were conducted in July 2005 of professionals    from provincial justice, education, health, equality and    welfare organization and from law enforcement officials in    Granada and Seville. An intentional «snowball» sampling was    used, in which it was possible to complete the profile table by    way of two individuals answering the survey.    Results: The professionals identified needs which it    would be necessary to cover with the intersectorial work as    well as the grounds for the same. They highlighted a number    of personal traits and some organization-related ones and identified    factors which have been divided among, political, social    and operative factors.    Conclusions: A consensus exists as to pointing out intersectorial    action as a way of guaranteeing the reduction of    social inequality, given that it prevents doubling resources and    unifies the response being provided. It was thought to be fundamental    for some profound changes to first be made in the    provincial organizations culture in or for the intersectorial    work to comprise part thereof. These changes must go along    with clear-cut guidelines at the upper levels of social movements    which will clearly highlight the need for a certain intersectorial    action in particular</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escudero Espinosa, Cecilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Agudo, Mónica Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Martín, Juan M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sierra Quesada, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: La Acción Intersectorial en Salud (AIS) ha    sido la metodología propuesta para la reducción de la desigualdad    en salud. Los objetivos del presente estudio son conocer las    experiencias, expectativas y necesidades percibidas de los profesionales    que trabajan en organizaciones provinciales, para proponer    un marco de análisis y desarrollo de trabajo intersectorial.    Métodos: Con un diseño cualitativo se realizaron 21 entrevistas    individuales semiestructuradas durante el mes de julio de    2005 a profesionales de organizaciones provinciales de justicia,    educación, salud, igualdad y bienestar social y de fuerzas y    cuerpos de seguridad en Granada y Sevilla. Se utilizó un muestreo    intencional «en bola de nieve» en el que a través de dos    informantes clave se logró completar el cuadro de perfiles.    Resultados: Los profesionales identifican necesidades    que habrían de ser cubiertas con el trabajo intersectorial así    como los fundamentos del mismo. Destacan una serie de    características personales y algunas relacionadas con la organización    e identifican factores que han sido divididos en políticos,    sociales y operativos.    Conclusiones: Hay un consenso en señalar la acción intersectorial    como garante para reducir la desigualdad social, ya    que evita la duplicidad de recursos y unifica la respuesta que    se ofrece. Resulta básico abordar cambios profundos previos    en la cultura de las organizaciones provinciales para que el trabajo    intersectorial forme parte de las mismas. Tales cambios    han de ir acompañados de directrices políticas claras en los    niveles superiores y de movimientos sociales que visibilicen la    necesidad de una determinada acción intersectorial</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;81(1): 43-52, ene.-feb.2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056607</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Expectativas y necesidades detectadas en profesionales de organizaciones provinciales que trabajan en acción intersectorial en salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3222^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29655</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32415</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6448^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33962</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33920^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
