<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165264</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Passion for teaching, transformational leadership and burnout among physical education teachers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of the study was to examine the associations between physical education (PE) teachers&#146; passion and their perception of burnout, testing the mediating role of teachers&#146; transformational teaching behaviours in this relationship as a coping resource. Participants (161 PE teachers; M = 40.59; SD = 8.36) were asked to complete a multi-section questionnaire tapping the variables of interest. Results showed that harmonious passion and transformational teaching were negative predictors of burnout, whereas obsessive passion was a positive predictor of burnout. Results also indicated that teachers&#146; transformational behaviours partially mediated the relationship between harmonious passion and burnout, and they totally mediated the relationship between obsessive passion and burnout. In conclusion, lower levels of burnout in PE teachers appear to be related to whether teachers perform more transformational behaviours in their job, and whether they feel in control of their passion for teaching (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, Octavio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Queralt, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estevan, Isaac</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina-García, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del estudio fue examinar las asociaciones entre la pasión en profesores de educación física (EF) y su percepción de burnout, testando el rol mediador de sus conductas transformacionales de enseñanza como recurso de afrontamiento. 161 profesores de EF (Medad = 40.59; DT = 8.36) respondieron a una batería de cuestionarios que recogía las variables de interés. Los resultados mostraron que la pasión armoniosa y el estilo transformacional de enseñanza predijeron negativamente el burnout; mientras que la pasión obsesiva lo predijo positivamente. Asimismo, las conductas transformacionales de los profesores mediaron parcialmente la relación entre la pasión armoniosa y el burnout, y mediaron totalmente la relación entre la pasión obsesiva y el burnout. En conclusión, en la medida que los profesores de EF sean más transformacionales, y sientan un mayor control sobre su pasión por la enseñanza, sus niveles de burnout serán más bajos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;26(supl.3): 57-61, 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165264</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pasión por la enseñanza, liderazgo transformacional y burnout en profesores de educación física</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8035</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
