<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050504</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5665</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Expression and Purification of GDNF for its microencapsulation in drug delivery systems and application in Parkinson&#146;s disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Parkinson&#146;s disease (PD) is a slowly progressive neurodegenerativedisorder caused by decreased levels of dopamine in thesubstantia nigra, brain region responsible for movement. Thelack of dopamine is believe to be responsible of the symptomsof PD. Parkinson&#146;s affects 200 in 100000 people and 2 inevery 100 persons over 60 years old. In Spain, there areabout 110000 people with PD. There is no cure at this time,and there are no prevention techniques or therapies. Recently,it has been demonstrated that GDNF, a glial-derived neurotrophicfactor is able to protect the dopaminergic neurons of thesubstancia nigra and it can also induce regeneration of injuredneurons in the central nervous system in vivo.The aim of this work was to develop a procedure for theexpression and purification of bioactive GDNF in view of itsmicroencapsulation for the treatment of PD.The cDNA of the GDNF gene was cloned in the expressionvector pDEST26 (Invitrogen) using the Gateway® Technology.Several eukaryotic mammalian cell lines (BHK, COS-7, and293) were stably transfected with the construction with LipofectaminePlus (Invitrogen). In those clones in which the presenceof the mRNA of the GDNF was confirmed by PCR studies,the expression of the recombinant protein in the serumfree medium was analyzed by Western Blot studies. The highestGDNF-producing clone, obtained from the BHK cell line,was cultured in 850 cm2 roller bottles (Corning) alternatingthe presence or the absence of FBS in the medium every 24hours, being collected only the serum free medium for theproduction of the recombinant GDNF. Each cycle protein expression was analyzed by SDS-PAGE and by Western Blot.The secreted protein was purified by several chromatographysteps. After each step of the purification procedure the fractionsobtained were analyzed by SDS-PAGE, Western Blotand silver staining analysis. A neuronal differentiation PC-12cell-based bioassay was also developed to confirm the biologicalactivity of the purified recombinant protein. Previously,the presence of GFRa1 and RET, receptors required forGDNF activity were confirmed by PCR.In conclusion, recombinant GDNF was produced in an eukaryoticmammalian cell line-based system. The protein purificationprocedure developed, allowed to obtain a highly purifiedrecombinant GDNF. Furthermore, the recombinant protein isbioactive</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blanco Prieto, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garbayo Atienza, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lanciego, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aymerich, M. S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad de Parkinosn (EP) es un proceso neurodegenerativodel sistema nervioso central que afecta a las neuronasde dopamina de la sustancia negra, núcleo mesoencefálico delcontrol motor. La perdida en el cerebro de este neurotransmisorvital causa los síntomas de la enfermedad. La EP afectaactualmente a 200 de cada 100.000 personas y a 2 de cada100 entre los mayores de 60 años. En España hay unos110.000 enfermos. Además, hoy por hoy no se conoce nadaque pueda prevenir o curar la enfermedad, ni existe ningunaprueba de laboratorio que permita diagnosticarla. Recentiementese ha demostrado que el GDNF, factor neurotrófico derivadode las células gliales, es capaz de proteger las neuronasdopaminérgicas e incluso inducir la regeneración del tejidodopaminérgico dañado in vivo.El objetivo del trabajo fue diseñar y desarrolar un método deexpresión y purificación de GDNF bioactivo para su posteriormicroencapsulación y aplicación en la enfermedad de Parkison.El sistema escogido para expresar el GDNF fue el sistema decélulas eucariotas de mamífero. El vector utilizado para la produccióndel GDNF en células eucariotas fue el pDEST26 (TecnologíaGateway de Invitrogen). Como sistema de expresión deGDNF se utilizaron las líneas celulares eucariota BHK, 293 yCOS 7. Estas células fueron cultivadas en medio D-MEM (Invitrogen)complementado con un 10% de suero fetal bovino(FBS) y Penicilina/Streptomicina (100u/ml) (Invitrogen). Latransfección se realizó con Lipofectamine Plus (Invitrogen). Seanalizó la expresión de GDNF a nivel de mRNA mediante PCR ya nivel de proteína mediante Western Blot del medio condicionado. Los clones positivos se crecieron en botellas de cultivode 850 cm2 (Corning) y se realizaron ciclos de recolección delmedio. Cada ciclo fue analizado por SDS-PAGE y Western Blot.Para evaluar la actividad de la proteína se ha desarrollado unensayo de actividad en el que se demuestra la diferenciaciónmorfológica de células PC-12 inducida por GDNF. La presenciade los receptores GFRa1 y RET, necesarios para que el GDNFejerza su acción, fue determinada por PCR.Las conclusiones obtenidas de este estudio son la obtenciónde GDNF recombinante a partir de un sistema de expresión encélulas eucariotas, el desarrollo de un protocolo para su posteriorpurificación y la obtención de GDNF recombinante biológicamenteactivo</dc:description>
<dc:source>MAPFRE med;17(3): 166-171, mar. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050504</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Expresión y purificación de GDNF para su microencapsulación y aplicación en la enfermedad de Parkinson</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23987^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29900^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34465^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
