<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141450</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hepatitis C associated with substance abuse: ever closer to a treatment without Interferon</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">With 3-4 million of new infections occurring annually, hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection is a global Public Health problem. In fact, hepatitis  C virus infection is one of the leading causes of liver disease in the world; in Western countries, two thirds of the new HCV infections are associated with injection drug use. The treatment of hepatitis C will change in the coming years with the irruption of new anti-HCV drugs, the so called Direct Antiviral Agents (DAA) that attack key proteins of the HCV life cycle. The new antiviral drugs are effective, safer and better tolerated. The 2014  WHO HCV treatment guidelines include some of them. The new DAA are used in combination and it is expected that Interferon will be not necessary in future treatment regimens against HCV infection.The irruption of new and potent antivirals mandate the review of  the current standards of care in the HCV infected population. More inclusive and proactive treatment policies will be necessary in those  individuals with substance use disorders (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muga, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bolao, Ferrán</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuster, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanvisens, Arantza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zuluaga, Paola</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivas, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La infección por el virus de la hepatitis C (VHC) es un problema de  Salud Pública de primera magnitud; cada año ocurren entre 3 y 4 millones de nuevas infecciones y de hecho, la hepatitis crónica C es una de las principales causas de enfermedad hepática en el mundo. Usar drogas por vía parenteral está en el origen de dos de cada tres nuevas infecciones por VHC en el mundo occidental.El tratamiento de la hepatitis C va a cambiar en los próximos años. El cambio es debido a la aparición de los llamados Antivirales de Acción Directa (AAD), unos fármacos que actúan contra proteínas clave del  ciclo vital del VHC y que serán más eficaces, mejor tolerados y se administrarán durante menos tiempo. En este sentido, la nueva guía de tratamiento de la OMS en 2014 ya incluye alguno de ellos en sus recomendaciones; los nuevos fármacos se utilizarán en combinación y probablemente se podrá prescindir del Interferón. Con la aparición de más y mejores antivirales contra el VHC es probable que debamos revisar el modelo asistencial vigente y orientarlo hacia uno más ágil e integrador, que trate al mayor número posible de pacientes, incluyendo a aquellos con abuso de sustancias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);27(2): 141-149, 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141450</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hepatitis C asociada al abuso de sustancias: nunca tan cerca de un tratamiento sin Interferón</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1002^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1002^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1002^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1002^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31852^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31852^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31852^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31852^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
