<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051776</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Phylephebitis dur to diverticulitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A case of a 52 year-old-male, with past medical history of renoureteral crisis and recurrent episodes of abdominal pain, is presented. The patient presented to the Emergency Department with abdominal pain (similar to previous episodes), fever and abnormal liver function test (marked elevation of gammaglutamyltranspeptidase and alkaline phosphatase). An abdominal ultrasound was performed showing hepatomegaly, and enlarged spleen and an echogenic material that suggested a thrombosis. A CT scan confirmed the thrombosis of the inferior mesenteric vein extending up to the splenic vein and the portal vein. It also showed a large number of diverticulum. Surgery was performed in order to rule out an acute diverticulitis. A phylephlebitis, infective suppurative thrombosis of the portal vein and its branches (inferior mesenteric vein and splenic vein) was found due to an acute diverticulitis with neither perforation nor abscess. A ligature of the inferior mesenteric vein and a Hartmann procedure with resection of the diseased colon, and end colostomy and creation of a rectal stump, were performed. A favourable outcome was obtained with antibiotics and anticoagulation.         Some aspects of the aetiology, symptoms, diagnosis and treatment of this unusual complication of diverticulitis are also presented</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casallo Blanco, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco González, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Ruiz, A. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castañeda Bergamín, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcos Sánchez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matías Salces, L. de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos el caso de un varón de 52 años, con antecedentes de cólicos renoureterales que había consultado por un episodio de similares características, acompañado de fiebre y elevaciones de la GGT y de la fosfatasa alcalina. Una ecografía abdominal mostró hepatoesplenomegalia y un material ecogénico en el eje esplenoportal, sugerente de trombosis. La TAC abdominal demostró trombosis de la vena mesentérica inferior, continuándose por la vena esplénica hasta el origen proximal de la vena porta. También se observaron numerosos divertículos. Se sospechó que el paciente presentaba una diverticulitis aguda complicada con trombosis vascular, por lo que se decidió la realización de cirugía, que confirmó la existencia de diverticulitis sin perforación ni abscesos, flebitis con pileflebitis de la arteria mesentérica inferior hasta su unión con la vena esplénica, con salida de pus al seccionar la vena. Se realizó ligadura de la vena mesentérica inferior e intervención de Hartman con ligadura del muñón rectal y colostomía. Además se indicó tratamiento antibiótico de amplio espectro y anticogulación, siendo la evolución favorable.         Posteriormente comentamos algunos aspectos etiológicos, clínicos, diagnósticos y terapéuticos de esta infrecuente complicación de la diverticulitis</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;23(12): 593-595, dic. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051776</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pileflebitis secundaria a diverticulitis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11611^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8985^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7154^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10883^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10883^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23255^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d683^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10883^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4301^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10883^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7154^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5444^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5444^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11611^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
