<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107864</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Unsuspected malignant struma ovarii: cytological diagnosis on fine needle aspiration of a spinal metastatasis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Malignant struma ovarii is an exceptionally rare tumour which may metastasize, in the same way as other malignant tumours of thyroid origin. We report a case of a 56-year-old woman who presented with a pelvic mass and lung and bone lesions. To our knowledge this is the first case of malignant struma ovarii with bone metastases diagnosed by CT-guided FNA. The aim of this report is to emphasize the usefulness of immunocytochemistry, in particular TTF1 and thyroglobulin, in cytological samples in order to identify the epithelial cells and microfollicles as thyroid tissue. We also describe the correlation between the cytology and histology of this lesion(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Idoate, Miguel A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bondía, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano, María D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Labiano, Tania</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echeveste, José I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El struma ovarii maligno es un tumor excepcional. A pesar de su rareza, puede dar metástasis igual que un tumor maligno de origen tiroideo. Presentamos un caso, en una paciente mujer de 56 años, que se inició con metástasis pulmonares y óseas. Aportamos un caso único de struma ovarii maligno que se manifestó con metástasis óseas y se diagnosticó mediante citología por punción aspirativa con aguja fina guiada por tomografía computarizada. Queremos enfatizar la utilidad de la inmunohistoquímica, especialmente TTF1 y tiroglobulina, en el material de punción, que permite identificar los nidos epiteliales y microfolículos como tejido tiroideo. Describimos, además, la correlación citohistológica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;45(4): 238-242, oct.-dic.2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107864</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Struma ovarii maligno no sospechado: diagnóstico citológico mediante punción aspirativa con aguja fina de lesión vertebral metastásica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d38338^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38338^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38338^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10229^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13509^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38338^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13509^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10229^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
