<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051956</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparison of the REGICOR and SCORE function charts for classifying cardiovascular risk and for selecting patients for hypolipidemic or antihypertensive treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. In Spain, use of the Framingham-REGICOR (Registre Gironí del Cor) and SCORE (Systematic Coronary Risk Evaluation) risk charts is recommended for stratifying cardiovascular disease risk. The aims of the present study were to evaluate the degree of agreement between these charts when used to evaluate cardiovascular disease risk in nondiabetic individuals aged 40-65 years and to estimate the percentage of patients recommended for hypolipidemic or antihypertensive treatment. Methods. The study included 608 nondiabetic patients aged between 40-65 years (mean 52.8 years, 56.7% female) with no evidence of cardiovascular disease who were attending a primary healthcare center between 1990-1994. REGICOR and SCORE equations were used to calculate 10-year cardiovascular disease risks. Patients were classified as high-risk if their risk was &amp;#8805;10% with REGICOR or &amp;#8805;5% with SCORE. Results. Some 7.9% of the population was classified as high-risk with REGICOR and 9.2%, with SCORE (P=.41). Only 2.6% and 2.9% (P=.81) of women were classified as high-risk, compared with 14.8% and 17.5% of men, with REGICOR and SCORE, respectively (P=.40). The kappa coefficient was 0.45. According to European professional society guidelines, 23.8% of patients classified by SCORE and 23.0% classified by REGICOR (P=.73) would be recommended hypolipidemic treatment, while 31.2% and 31.7% (P=.85), respectively, would be recommended antihypertensive treatment. Conclusions. There was moderately good agreement between REGICOR and SCORE charts when used to evaluate nondiabetic individuals aged 40-65 years. They identified similar percentages of patients who would be recommended for hypolipidemic or antihypertensive treatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Herrera, Natalio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruces-Muro, Eloísa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escobar-Fernández, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Buitrago, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañón-Barroso, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano-Arias, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Las funciones de Framingham-REGICOR y SCORE son funciones recomendadas en la estratificación del riesgo cardiovascular en nuestro país. El objetivo del presente estudio fue evaluar la concordancia de estas tablas en la estratificación del riesgo en la población no diabética de 40-65 años y estimar el porcentaje de pacientes candidatos a recibir tratamiento hipolipemiante e hipotensor. Métodos. Se incluyó a un total de 608 pacientes no diabéticos de 40-65 años de edad (media, 52,8 años; 56,7%, mujeres) sin evidencia de enfermedad cardiovascular, atendidos en el centro de salud durante los años 1990-1994. El riesgo cardiovascular a los 10 años se calculó mediante la ecuación de REGICOR y SCORE. Se consideró pacientes de riesgo alto a los que tenían un riesgo &amp;#8805; 10% en REGICOR y &amp;#8805; 5% en SCORE. Resultados. Un 7,9% de la población fue catalogada de riesgo alto en REGICOR y un 9,2% en SCORE (p = 0,41). Solamente el 2,6 y el 2,9% de las mujeres (p = 0,81) se incluyeron en la categoría de riesgo alto, frente al 14,8 y 17,5% de los varones (p = 0,40) en REGICOR y SCORE, respectivamente. El coeficiente kappa fue 0,45. El seguimiento de las recomendaciones de las Sociedades Europeas implicaría que el 23,8% de los pacientes, según SCORE, y el 23,0%, según REGICOR (p = 0,73), serían candidatos a recibir tratamiento hipolipidemiante, y el 31,2 y el 31,7% (p = 0,85), a recibir fármacos antihipertensivos. Conclusiones. Las tablas REGICOR y SCORE presentan una concordancia moderada en la población no diabética de 40-65 años de edad. Su aplicación identifica a un porcentaje similar de pacientes candidatos a recibir tratamiento hipolipemiante o antihipertensivo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;60(2): 139-147, feb. 2007. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051956</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de las tablas REGICOR y SCORE para la clasificación del riesgo cardiovascular y la identificación de pacientes candidatos a tratamiento hipolipemiante o antihipertensivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14679^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d963^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1822</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32048^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
