<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-36819</identifier>
<setSpec>0301-0546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nasal obstruction and its measurement</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Nasal obstruction is an important symptom of rhinitis. The present article presents the inflammatory mechanisms that lead to the clinical presentation of this symptom: conchal vasodilation, infiltration of mainly eosinophilic cells with activation of these cells and release of intracellular mediators. Given the importance of this symptom and its effects both on function and on quality of life, the various methods used to study it are discussed. Active anterior rhinometry (AAR), measurement of nasal peak inspiratory flow (NPIF), and acoustic rhinometry (AR) are discussed. The underlying principles, based on the trajectory of nasal air flow, techniques, and their advantages and disadvantages are presented. In conclusion, any of these methods can be used to evaluate nasal obstruction (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ediciones Doyma, S.L.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La obstrucción nasal es un síntoma importante en las rinitis. En el presente trabajo se exponen los mecanismos inflamatorios que conducen a la presentación clínica de dicho síntoma: dilatación de los vasos de capacitancia de los cornetes, infiltración celular de predominio eosinofílico, con activación de dichas células y liberación de los mediadores intracelulares. Dada la importancia del síntoma, de sus repercusiones tanto a nivel funcional, como en lo referente a la calidad de vida del paciente, se discuten los diferentes métodos para su estudio. Se analizan sucesivamente la rinomanometría anterior activa (AAR), la medición del flujo inspiratorio nasal (NPIF) y la rinometría acústica (AR). Se exponen: a) los fundamentos, basados en el recorrido del flujo aéreo nasal; b) las técnicas, y c) sus ventajas e inconvenientes. Como conclusión, cualquiera de estos métodos puede ser usado en la valoración de la obstrucción nasal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Allergol Immunopathol (Madr);32(6): 361-367, nov. 2004.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La obstrucción nasal y su medida</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Olivé Pérez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-36819</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36272</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36273</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27801</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24794</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200411</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
