<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044395</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bacterial tracheitis: an infectious cause of upper airway obstruction to be considered in children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Bacterial tracheitis is a cause of severe upper respiratory airway obstruction. It has been considered a rare entity whose clinical and epidemiological features are not well known.                Patients and methods: The medical records of children diagnosed with bacterial tracheitis and admitted to our pediatric intensive care unit (PICU) from June 1992 to May 2004 (12 years) were analyzed. The following variables were recorded: age, sex, personal history, need for endotracheal intubation, duration of intubation, isolated bacteria, antibiotic treatment, steroid administration, and length of stay in the PICU.                Results: Twelve patients (six girls and six boys) were included in this study. Age ranged from 1 month to 13 years (median 24 months). Four children had a history of acute laryngotracheitis, one had Down syndrome and another had interauricular communication. All patients needed orotracheal intubation for 2 to 72 hours (median 48 hours). All patients received empirical antibiotic therapy: cephalosporins in 11 children (91 %) (in association with vancomycin or teicoplanin in four of them) and erythromycin in one (9 %). Corticosteroids were administered in nine patients (75 %). Bacterial pathogens were isolated from tracheal secretion culture in seven children (58 %) and the most common was Staphylococcus aureus (42 %). Three children (25 %) developed lobar pneumonia and one developed congestive cardiac insufficiency as a complication of bacterial tracheitis. In all patients, clinical outcome was satisfactory.                Conclusions: Although the absolute frequency of bacterial tracheitis is low, in our environment this entity represents a considerable cause of severe upper respiratory airway obstruction secondary to an infectious process. Therefore, it should be considered in patients who present with stridor and fever. If the correct treatment is provided, the prognosis is generally good</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Núñez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcos Alonso, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molini Menchón, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martinón Sánchez, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martinón Torres, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La traqueítis bacteriana es una causa de obstrucción grave de la vía aérea superior que se considera poco frecuente y cuyas características clínico-epidemiológicas son poco conocidas.                Pacientes y métodos: Se analizaron las historias clínicas de los niños diagnosticados de traqueítis bacteriana que ingresaron en nuestra unidad de cuidados intensivos pediátrica (UCIP) entre junio de 1992 y mayo de 2004 (12 años). Se recogieron las siguientes variables: edad, sexo, antecedentes personales de enfermedad, necesidad de intubación endotraqueal, días de intubación, bacteria aislada, tratamiento antibiótico, corticoterapia y días de estancia en la UCIP.                Resultados: Se incluyeron 12 pacientes (6 niñas y 6 niños). El rango de edad osciló entre 1 mes y 13 años (mediana: 2 años). Tenían historia previa de laringotraqueítis aguda 4 niños, uno tenía un síndrome de Down y otro una comunicación interauricular. Todos los pacientes precisaron intubación orotraqueal, durante un período entre 2 y 72 h (mediana: 48 h). En todos ellos se utilizó antibioterapia empírica: cefalosporinas en 11 niños (91 %) (en cuatro ocasiones asociadas a un glucopéptido) y macrólido en un niño (9 %). Se emplearon corticoides en 9 casos (75 %). El cultivo del aspirado traqueal fue positivo en 7 niños (58 %), siendo Staphylococcus aureus el germen más frecuente (42 %). Tres niños (25 %) desarrollaron neumonía lobular y uno (8,3 %) insuficiencia cardíaca congestiva como complicación de la traqueítis bacteriana. La evolución clínica fue satisfactoria en todos los casos.                Conclusiones: Aunque la incidencia absoluta de la traqueítis bacteriana es baja, en nuestro medio constituye una causa relevante de obstrucción grave de la vía aérea superior secundaria a un proceso infeccioso, por lo que debe tenerse en cuenta en el diagnóstico diferencial del paciente con estridor y fiebre. Si se realiza el tratamiento adecuado, el pronóstico en general es favorable</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);63(2): 164-168, ago. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044395</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Traqueítis bacteriana: una causa infecciosa de obstrucción de la vía aérea que hay que considerar en la infancia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d405^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1447^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14528^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14528^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
