<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93776</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4603</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Linguistic development in a case of prelocutive deafness and attention deficithyperactivity disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article retrospectively describes language development in a prelocutive deaf girl who was enrolled in a long-term longitudinal study. The main aim was to study the effect of the simultaneous use of an early cochlear implant (CI) and cued speech (CS). From 15 months to 6 years old the child underwent rehabilitation in the complemented oral model [COM, Modelo Oral Complementado (MOC) in Spanish]. During this period, 159 sessions of 30-minutes each were videotaped, forming the MOC-CORPUS, available in the CHILDES database. Prelinguistic acquisitions (canonical babbling, phonetic inventory, and first words), and linguistic development (phonology, lexicon, grammar and pragmatics) were explored. As the child's linguistic development did not follow the expected course for a case of deafness with CI+CS, other hypotheses were investigated. After 4 years of CI use, attention-deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) was confirmed and was treated with methylphenidate. The data were reanalyzed from the perspective of deafness plus ADHD, assuming that both disorders were present from the beginning. The differential features in linguistic development in cases of typical deafness versus deafness plus ADHD are contrasted(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santana Hernández, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Monreal, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Casas, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este informe se describe de manera restrospectiva el desarrollo lingüístico de una niña con sordera profunda prelocutiva, que fue admitida para un estudio longitudinal de larga duración. El objetivo principal era evaluar el efecto del uso simultáneo del implante coclear (IC) temprano y la palabra complementada (LPC). Desde los 15 meses hasta los 6 años de edad, fue rehabilitada en el modelo oral complementado (MOC). Durante este periodo se grabaron 159 muestras de habla de 30 min cada una, que forman el CORPUS-MOC, disponible en CHILDES. Fueron objeto de estudio el desarrollo prelingüístico &#151;balbuceo canónico, inventario fonético y primeras palabras&#151; y el lingüístico &#151;fonología, léxico, gramática y pragmática&#151;. Como el desarrollo lingüístico no era el esperado para un caso de sordera con IC+LPC, se indagaron otras hipótesis. A los 4 años de uso del IC se confirmó el TDAH, que fue tratado con metilfenidato, y se reanalizaron los datos desde la perspectiva de sordera+TDAH, en la presunción de que ambas discapacidades estaban presentes desde el principio. Se contraponen los rasgos diferenciales del desarrollo lingüístico entre sordera típica y sordera+TDAH(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. logop. foniatr. audiol. (Ed. impr.);31(4): 183-192, oct.-dic.2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93776</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desarrollo lingüístico de un caso de sordera prelocutiva más trastorno por déficit atencional (TDAH)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7982</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3082^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3655^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33553^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3655^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33553^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29348^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3082^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29348^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8961^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
