<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137505</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-0740</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cervical ripening: natural process acceleration</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The each time more effective methods of prenatal diagnosis, the increase of primigravidas aging more than 35 years, the increase of fertilization processes and the improvement on the knowledge of the fetal physiology, Makes procedures of cervical ripening more frequent. The  aim of this bibliographic review is to show the wide spectrum of methods used to reach a cervical ripening, furthermore a description of the physiology of cervical ripening to understand how do they work or don&#146;t sometimes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-Boubeta, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cid-González, Carla</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los cada vez más eficaces métodos de diagnóstico prenatal, el aumento de gestantes mayores de 35 años, el aumento de los procesos de fecundación y el mejor conocimiento de la fisiología fetal hacen que sean cada día más frecuentes los procesos de maduración e inducción del parto. Esta revisión bibliográfica pretende mostrar el amplio espectro de métodos de maduración cervical; además, se hace una pequeña incursión en la fisiología de la maduración cervical para facilitar la comprensión del éxito o fracaso de los diferentes métodos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Matronas prof;8(1): 24-29, ene.-mar. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137505</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Maduración cervical: aceleración de un proceso natural</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27774</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5208</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7923</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2624^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2624^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33866^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17570</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
