<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154830</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Inhaled anesthesia for ambulatory surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The anesthetic technique chosen for the ambulatory surgery will influence on the postoperative period. The following article discusses the results of several recently published works in this field. The main differences between intravenous and inhalation techniques are based on a lower incidence of postoperative nausea and vomiting and a minimum saving of hospital stay for total intravenous anesthesia. The analysis of the costs associated with each technique is difficult to determine. Regarding to the differences between the two most common inhalation anesthetic, sevoflurane and desflurane, there is less time for awakening with desflurane (between 1.2 and 4.2 minutes), and these differences don't increase in cases of surgeries longer than 2 hours or in obese patients. Minimal differences between the two drugs in relation to the recovery time for the daily activities of the patients are described. There is an increased airway irritability associated with the use of desflurane but it is minimized by adding intravenous opioids. The incidence of PONV and the intensity of postoperative pain are similar between the two agents. The economical matters are extremely relevant, since with the same fresh gas flow the amount of desflurane spent is considerably bigger than sevoflurane. Sevoflurane and desflurane are useful drugs for ambulatory surgery. Both have common features but also specific differences that could influence their use in certain patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bilbao Ares, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La técnica anestésica elegida durante la cirugía mayor ambulatoria tendrá su influencia en el periodo postoperatorio. Las diferencias fundamentales entre la técnica endovenosa y la inhalatoria se basan en una menor incidencia de náuseas y vómitos en el postoperatorio (NVPO) y un mínimo ahorro del tiempo de estancia hospitalaria a favor de la anestesia total endovenosa. El análisis de los costes asociados a cada técnica es difícil de determinar. En relación a las diferencias entre los dos anestésicos inhalatorios de empleo común, el sevoflurano y desflurano, destaca un menor tiempo de despertar con el uso de desflurano (entre 1,2 y 4,2 minutos), sin aumentarse esas diferencias en los casos de cirugías de duración mayor a 2 horas o pacientes obesos. Se describen mínimas diferencias entre ambos fármacos en relación al tiempo de recuperación de las actividades diarias de los pacientes. Existe una mayor irritabilidad de la vía aérea asociada al uso de desflurano que se minimiza añadiendo opioides endovenosos. La incidencia de NVPO es similar entre ambos agentes, así como la intensidad del dolor postoperatorio. De especial relevancia son las consideraciones económicas, ya que con los actuales precios en nuestro país, ante un mismo flujo de gas fresco el gasto en desflurano sería sustancialmente mayor al de sevoflurano. Tanto el sevoflurano como el desflurano son fármacos útiles para su empleo en cirugía mayor ambulatoria. Ambos presentan características comunes pero también diferencias específicas que podrían condicionar su uso en determinados pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;19(3): 109-113, jul.-sept. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154830</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anestesia inhalatoria en cirugía ambulatoria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32367^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d780^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
