<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117577</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Aicardi syndrome: retrospective study of a series of seven case reports</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The Aicardi syndrome is a disorder presumably X-linked dominant, classically defined by the triad of agenesis of the corpus callosum, chorioretinal lacunae and infantile spasms, with lethality in males. Patients and methods. Retrospective descriptive study of patients diagnosed with Aicardi syndrome over a period of 29 years in two tertiary pediatric hospitals. Results. We found seven women that developed infantile spasms before 6 months of age, epileptic spasms persisting beyond infancy in two cases, a refractory symptomatic partial epilepsy in three patients, and well-controlled partial epilepsy in one girl. Six cases presented severe-profound mental retardation and moderate-severe in a girl. Two girls died at 2 and 6 years-old. In all patients neuroimaging studies showed agenesis of the corpus callosum, intracranial cysts and malformations of cortical development. Ophthalmological lesions were chorioretinal lacunae in seven cases, anophthalmia/microphthalmia in four girls and optic nerve coloboma in three patients. Other findings were congenital heart disease, costovertebral abnormalities, cervical lymphangioma and focal hypertrichosis. Conclusions. The Aicardi syndrome should be suspected in girls with infantile spasms and agenesis of the corpus callosum. It is necessary to rule out these ophthalmologic abnormalities, malformations of cortical development and intracranial cysts. The prognosis is poor due to its high mortality and its evolution to refractory epilepsy and profound mental retardation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Camacho Salas, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Laso, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camino León, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerra García, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar Quintero, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez Enamorado, Noemí</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Ramos, Joaquín Alejandró</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Simón de las Heras, Rogelio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El síndrome de Aicardi es un trastorno presumiblemente dominante ligado al cromosoma X, que afecta en exclusiva a mujeres, clásicamente definido por la tríada de agenesia del cuerpo calloso, lagunas coriorretinianas y espasmos infantiles, letal en varones en la vida intrauterina. Pacientes y métodos. Estudio descriptivo retrospectivo de pacientes diagnosticadas y seguidas hasta el final de la edad pediátrica de síndrome de Aicardi en dos hospitales universitarios durante un período de 29 años. Resultados. Encontramos siete niñas, todas desarrollaron espasmos infantiles antes de los 6 meses de edad. La evolución fue a espasmos más allá de la infancia (n = 2), a epilepsia parcial farmacorresistente (n = 3) y a epilepsia parcial bien controlada (n = 1). Seis casos presentaron retraso mental grave-profundo, y uno, moderado-grave. Fallecieron dos niñas a los 2 y 6 años. En todas, los estudios de neuroimagen mostraron agenesia del cuerpo calloso, quistes intracraneales y malformaciones del desarrollo cortical cerebral, además de lesiones oftalmológicas: lagunas coriorretinianas (n = 7), anoftalmia/microftalmia (n = 4) y coloboma del nervio óptico (n = 3). Otros hallazgos fueron cardiopatía  ongénita, anomalías costovertebrales, linfangioma cervical e hipertricosis focal. Conclusiones. El síndrome de Aicardi debe sospecharse en niñas con espasmos infantiles y agenesia del cuerpo calloso. Deben descartarse en estas pacientes las alteraciones oftalmológicas, las anomalías de la migración y organización neuronal y los quistes intracraneales. El pronóstico es grave por su elevada morbimortalidad y por la frecuente evolución a epilepsia refractaria y retraso mental grave (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;57(11): 481-488, dic. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117577</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Aicardi: estudio retrospectivo de una serie de siete casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53965^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54514^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13419^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28268^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
