<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055170</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-734X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Rights and restrictions of the allergic patient in the occupational environment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Allergic processes are rather frequent in the occupational environment, ofter as a consequence of the workplace conditions or of the materials and substances used. The Law for Prevention of Occupational Risks (in Spain, Ley de Prevención de Riesgos Laborales) aims at protecting the labourers&#146; health, by imposing a number of preventive and corrective measures. However, questions arise regarding the individual adequacy for performing a specific occupational task and also regarding the rights protecting that individual who is not apt or adequate for that particular task because of his (her) allergic condition. Health surveys may detect this particular problem, and render indispensable measures for correction of the occupational environment, as well as further ones for individual protection. However, once all this has been carried out and when the allergic disease persists, a number of doubts arise: May anyone be rejected for this cause? Should the worker previously report his &#145;limitations&#146;? Does asking him about this infringe his right to privacy? What should the occupational physician and the employer do? We do consider that the Law gives adequate answer and response to all these questions and guarantees the rights of all those involved, as well as demanding truthfulness on the side of the employee and confidentiality on the side of the examining medical team (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramos Hernández, MP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Martínez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pacheco Guevara, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miralles López, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los procesos alérgicos son frecuentes en el ambiente laboral, a menudo como consecuencia de las condiciones del lugar de trabajo o de los materiales y sustancias empleadas. La Ley de Prevención de Riesgos Laborales persigue la protección de la salud de los trabajadores, imponiendo la realización de una serie de medidas preventivas y correctoras. No obstante, se plantean las cuestiones de la idoneidad individual para la realización de una tarea laboral específica y de los derechos que protegen a quien resulta no apto para ese trabajo, por causa de su alergia. Mediante los exámenes de salud se puede detectar esta problemática, haciéndose imprescindibles medidas correctoras del medio laboral, así como otras de protección individual. Efectuado todo esto, y ante la persistencia de la patología alérgica, surgen dudas: ¿Podría ser alguien rechazado por esa causa?, ¿Debe el trabajador informar sobre sus limitaciones, con carácter previo?, ¿Se atenta contra su privacidad, interrogándole al respecto?, ¿Qué deben hacer el médico del trabajo y el empresario? Entendemos que la Ley otorga adecuada respuesta a esos interrogantes, garantizando los derechos de todos, a la vez que exige veracidad por parte del empleado y confidencialidad por parte del equipo médico que le examina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Alergol. inmunol. clín. (Ed. impr.);20(1): 10-13, feb. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055170</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Derechos y restricciones del enfermo alérgico en el ambiente laboral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29063^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36412</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7145^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36355</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
