<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156193</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The complex interactions to be found in borderline conditions between the psychotic and neurotic parts of the personality imply that these patients use primitive defense mechanisms together with more elaborated psychic mechanisms. In order to carry out an analysis with this kind of patient the analyst needs to perceive, discriminate, and eventually interpret both psychotic and neurotic mechanisms, as well as their linkage. On the other hand, it is difficult for these patients to symbolize, and thus the analyst must be mindful of his own counter-transferencial affects. In this context, the counter-transference function may act as a precise tool in understanding borderline functioning; a counter-transference that is obviously used thoughtfully and meanfully, and not hurriedly or wildly. Another aim of this paper is to show how difficult it is to make an exact, systematic diagnosis of the borderline process as from a list of clinical symptoms, in the course of early interviews. We may, however, attempt anapproximate diagnosis based on the most outstanding features: impulsiveness, intense affects, general malaise, lack of repression, idealization and devaluation of the object. But the most precise tool we posses in order to make a diagnosis is counter-transference, as well as the course of the treatment and its vicissitudes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Crespo, Luis Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las complejas interacciones de las partes psicótica y neurótica de la personalidad que se establecen en los procesos borderline, implican que estos pacientes utilizan mecanismos de defensa primiticos junto a mecanismos psíquicos más elaborados. Para llevar a cabo un psicoanálisis con estos pacientes, el analista necesita percibir, discriminar y, eventualmente, interpretar tanto los mecanismos psicóticos como los neuróticos, así como su articulación. Por otra parte, estos pacientes tienen dificultades para la simbolización; por lo que el psicoanalista tiene que estar atento a sus afectos contratransferenciales. En este contexto, la función de la contratransferencia puede servir como un instrumentom, muy preciso en la compresión del funcionamiento borderline. Contratransferencia utilizada, obviamente, matizada y reflesxivamente, y no de forma precipitada o silvestre. Otro objetivo de este trabajo ha sido mostrarles la dificultad de un diagnóstico preciso y sistemático del proceso borderline en las entrevistas previas basándose en un listado de síntomas clínicos. Podemos, sin embargo, hacer una aproximación diagnóstica por sus características más puntuales: impulsividad, afectos intensos, malestar generalizado, ausencia de represión, idealización y desvalorización del objeto. Pero la herramienta más precisa de que disponemos para el diagnóstico es la de contratransferencia y el curso de la cura y sus vicisitudes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(37): 137-156, 2002.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156193</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Interacciones de las partes psicótica y neurótica de la personalidad en los procesos &#145;borderline&#146;</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1907^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13863</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9686^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200200</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
