<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153030</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The most significant deficiencies in macro and micro nutrients in adolescents living with HIV/AIDS in antiretroviral therapy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate macro and micronutrients intake of adolescents living with HIV/AIDS in use of antiretroviral therapy and compare it to the Dietary Reference Intakes. Methodology: Cross-sectional study conducted with adolescents of both genders with HIV/AIDS, assessing the dietary composition of macro and micronutrients, using the 24h dietary recall. Results: 39 adolescents, average age of 15 years, 51.3% males. The participants intake of total calories, total fiber (g/d), liposoluble vitamins (A, D, E, K), vitamin B5 (mg/d), vitamin B9 (mg/d), vitamin C (mg/d), calcium (mg/d), phosphorus (mg/d), potassium (mg/d), and magnesium (mg/d) was lower than recommended. The percentages of intake lower than recommended were 79.5% for calories, 82.1% for total fibers, 89.7% for vitamin A, 100% for vitamin D, 87.2% for vitamin E, 100% for vitamin K, 71.8% for vitamin B5, 82.1% for vitamin B9, 76.9% for vitamin C, 92.3% for calcium, 61.5% for phosphorus, 97.4% for potassium, and 76.9% for magnesium. The participants ingested more carbohydrates (g), proteins (g), vitamins B2 (mg/d), B3 (mg/d), B8 (mg/d) and sodium (g/d) than recommended, the percentages above the recommendations being 92.3% for carbohydrates, 64.1% for proteins and vitamin B2, 56.4% for vitamin B3, 82.1% for vitamin B8, and 59% for sodium. The remaining nutrients were within the amounts recommended by the DRIs. Conclusion: Food intake was inadequate as compared to the recommendations of the International Nutrition Guidelines (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Silva, Carmem Lúcia Oliveira da</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schmitz, Caroline Barbosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lazzarotto, Alexandre Ramos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miraglia, Fernanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bissigo Pereira, Fernanda</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: identificar la ingestión alimentaria de macro y micronutrientes en adolescentes viviendo con VIH/sida que usan terapia anti-retroviral y compararlos a las Dietary Reference Intakes. Metodología: estudio transversal realizado con adolescentes de ambos sexos con VIH/sida, en el que se evaluó la composición dietética de macro y micronutrientes a través del recordatorio alimentario de 24h. Resultados: 39 adolescentes con una edad promedio de 15 años, un 51,3% del sexo masculino. Los participantes consumieron menos calorías totales en la dieta, fibra total (g/d), vitaminas liposolubles (A, D, E, K), vitamina B5 (mg/d), vitamina B9 (mg/d), vitamina C (mg/d), calcio (mg/d), fósforo (mg/d), potasio (mg/d) y magnesio (mg/d) que lo recomendado. Los porcentajes de ingestión por debajo de lo recomendado representaron el 79,5% para las calorías, el 82,1% para la fibra total, el 89,7% para la vitamina A, el 100% para la vitamina D, el 87,2% para la vitamina E, el 100% para la vitamina K, el 71,8% para la vitamina B5, el 82,1% para la vitamina B9, el 76,9% para la vitamina C, el 92,3% para el calcio, el 61,5% para el fósforo, el 97,4% para el potasio y el 76,9% para el magnesio. Los participantes consumían más carbohidratos (g), proteínas (g), vitaminas B2 (mg/d), B3 (mg/d), B8 (mg/d) y sodio (g/d) de lo recomendado, representando porcentajes por encima de la ingestión del 92,3% para los hidratos de carbono, del 64,1% para las proteínas y la vitamina B2, del 56,4% para la vitamina B3, del 82,1% para la vitamina B8 y del 59% para el sodio. Los demás nutrientes estaban dentro de lo recomendado por las DRIs. Conclusión: el consumo alimentario fue inadecuado en comparación con lo recomendado por las Directrices Internacionales de Nutrición (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;33(1): 21-25, ene.-feb. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153030</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las deficiencias más significativas de macro y micro nutrientes en adolescentes que viven con el VIH/sida en terapia anti-retroviral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38332^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50311</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32687^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
