<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146094</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sixth Jesus Culebras&#146; lecture: glutamine and the critical patient: the end of an age?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the last few years, glutamine has changed its status from a 'non-essential' amino acid to 'almost essential or indispensable' in the critical patient. This has occurred thanks to a series of studies and meta-analysis highlighting the beneficial effects on nosocomial infection, stay in ICU and hospital stay and mortality. After two multicentre studies (REDOXS and MetaPlus) which reviewed the effects of glutamine on critically ill patients, comments changed to: 'we do strongly recommend that glutamine is not used in critically ill patients in shock or multiple organ failure' and: 'there is an important questioning about the safety of this approach (combination of high-dose enteral and parenteral glutamine) which should not be ignored' and, therefore: 'the committee decides to decrease the degree of recommendation for endovenous glutamine'; it currently states that glutamine 'should be considered'. According to another multicentre study with severe trauma patients our group (a group which in theory was much benefitted from glutamine actions), and 143 patients, did not experience any observable benefit at the usual parenteral doses. We do agree with previous studies on the prognostic value of low levels of glutamine at admittance, which was confirmed if those levels were not back to normal after its administration, although there are no readily available analytic trials for this. This divergence about the usefulness of glutamine grows up as more and more multicentre studies in critical patients show there should be a change of attitude, and probably the clinical guidelines that welcomed its use should now be amended (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marsé Milla, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La glutamina es un aminoácido que en pocos años ha pasado de 'no esencial' a 'casi imprescindible en el enfermo crítico', gracias a una serie de estudios y metaanálisis en los que destacaban sus beneficiosos efectos sobre la infección nosocomial, estancias en UCI y hospitalarias y mortalidad, sobre todo tras dos estudios multicéntricos (REDOXS y MetaPlus) que revisaban los efectos de la glutamina en pacientes críticos, los comentarios pasaban a: 'recomendamos fuertemente que la glutamina no sea utilizada en pacientes críticos en shock o fallo multiorgánico' a través de un 'importante cuestionamiento sobre la seguridad de esta estrategia (combinación de altas dosis de glutamina enteral y parenteral) que no debe ser ignorada' y, por tanto, 'el comité decide disminuir el grado de recomendación para la glutamina endovenosa'; y actualmente destaca que la misma 'debería ser considerada'. Nuestro grupo, también según otro estudio multicéntrico en enfermos traumáticos graves, un grupo teóricamente más beneficiado de la acción de la glutamina, y en 143 pacientes, a las dosis parenterales habituales, no observamos ningún beneficio. Sí que coincidimos con anteriores estudios en el valor pronóstico de valores bajos de glutaminemia al ingreso, que se veía confirmado si no se normalizaban tras su administración, aunque su determinación no es una prueba analítica asequible. Esta divergencia sobre la utilidad de la glutamina aparece con la proliferación de estudios multicéntricos en pacientes críticos que obligan a un cambio de actitud y, probablemente también, en las guías clínicas que tan favorablemente acogieron su uso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(6): 2374-2379, dic. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146094</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sexta Lección Jesús Culebras: glutamina y paciente crítico ¿El fin de una era?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6117^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
