<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149154</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Advantages of the presence of the family in pediatric resuscitation or in painful procedures</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The presence of parents or others relatives during the painful procedures to the child, as well as during the pediatric resuscitation has raised discussion among health professionals, both for its advantages and disadvantages. Objective: Considering this subject, the main goal of this investigation consists in identifying scientific studies that are oriented for the advantages of having family members at hand during resuscitation and/or painful procedures. Method: It was performed a systematic review of the literature with the following research question: What are the advantages of having family members in the resuscitation room and/or painful procedures? Results: All the articles identified advantages in having the presence of family members in the resuscitation room and/or during painful procedures. Conclusions: This research reinforces the debate and reflection among the multidisciplinary team about the presence of family members during the painful procedures or resuscitation performed to a child. However, in order for this process to be executable it is necessary to train all the health team, enabling them to explain the procedure to the family and accompany them throughout the process (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vaz, Judite</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alves, Rita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos, Vera</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La presencia de los padres o de otros familiares ante la prestación de procedimientos dolorosos para el niño, así como en la reanimación pediátrica, ha provocado discusión entre profesionales de la salud, por las ventajas y desventajas que presenta. Objetivo: Teniendo en cuenta este problema, el objetivo de esta investigación consiste en identificar estudios científicos orientados a las ventajas de la presencia de los familiares en la sala de reanimación y/o en procedimientos dolorosos. Método: Fue realizada una revisión sistemática de la literatura con la siguiente pregunta de investigación: ¿Cuáles son las ventajas de la presencia de la familia en la sala de reanimación y/o procedimientos dolorosos? Resultados: Todos los artículos identifican ventajas de la presencia de la familia en la sala de reanimación y/o procedimientos dolorosos. Conclusiones: La investigación favorece el debate y la reflexión entre el equipo multidisciplinar sobre la presencia de los familiares de los niños frente a procedimientos dolorosos o reanimación. Sin embargo, a fin de que este proceso sea factible, es necesaria la formación y capacitación de todo el equipo de salud, para que puedan estar disponibles para explicar los procedimientos a los familiares y acompañarlos en todo el proceso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;15(41): 375-386, ene. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149154</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ventajas de la presencia de la familia en la reanimación pediátrica o en procedimientos dolorosos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30894^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30894^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30894^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30894^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
