<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79680</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-2159</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">+ormative ratings on valence, arousal, subjetive familiarity, and its relation with threat, depression and anger of 238 nouns in university students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present normative data of the assessment by university students of nouns on scales of valence, arousal, word frequency or subjective familiarity, and its relation with threat, depression and anger. The reported norm rate can be utmost useful for research on the relationship between cognition and emotion, and in particular to researchers using attention and memory tasks with words stimuli and participants selected according to their emotional characteristics(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Megías, Jesús L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lupiáñez, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acosta, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Dueñas, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presentan los resultados de las evaluaciones que realizaron un grupo de estudiantes universitarios sobre 238 sustantivos en las dimensiones de valencia, activación, frecuencia subjetiva de uso y relevancia para la ansiedad, la depresión y la ira. Los datos normativos que se muestran pueden ser de gran utilidad para aquellos investigadores que estudian las relaciones entre cognición y emoción, particularmente cuando utilizan tareas de atención o de memoria en que se incluyen estímulos verbales y los participantes son seleccionados por sus rasgos afectivos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>PsicolÔogica (Valencia, Ed. impr.);31(2): 241-273, 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79680</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de las dimensiones de valencia, activación, frecuencia subjetiva de uso y relevancia para la ansiedad, la depresión y la ira de 238 sustantivos en una muestra universitaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13723^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33140^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d797^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
