<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-30912</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The serine proteases and their function in neuronal death processes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims. In this review we analyse the role played by the serine proteases in the nervous system and we focus on the role they play in degenerative processes. Development. These proteolytic enzymes, together with the caspases, play a vital role in the processes regulating cell functioning, both in the development stages and following the response to a harmful stimulus. This family of proteases includes the granzymes and thrombin (TR). The former, which are closely related to proteases I and II and cathepsin G, are situated in the cytoplasmic granules of the activated T lymphocytes, together with other proteins such as perforin or cytolysin. Granzymes A and B are linked to degenerative processes. These enter the target cells thanks to the action of perforin and once inside they are translocated to the nucleus. Granzyme A has been isolated and identified as the agent responsible for the immediate and complete retraction of neurites in different models. Its physiological substrates include fibronectin, type IV collagen and the proteoglycans. Granzyme B is characterised by its being a cysteine protease with substrates such as prointerleukin-1&amp;#946;, TR receptor and poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase. The family of TR-type proteases includes proteases such as TR itself, plasmin, kallikrein, urokinase plasminogen activator and tissue plasminogen activator. TR is considered to be an early modulator in damaged tissues which acts as an extracellular signal of death, leading to the activation of intracellular mechanisms that appear to be mediated by calcium. Serine protease activity is regulated by endogenous inhibitors, such as plasminogen activator inhibitor, protease nexin-1 and neuroserpin. Conclusions. Upsets in the proteaseinhibitor balance are crucial in the processes involved in the neuronal plasticity and death induced by ischemia in the brain and by excitotoxins (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. En esta revisión analizamos el papel de las serina proteasas en el sistema nervioso y nos centramos en su participación en los procesos degenerativos. Desarrollo. Estas enzimas proteolíticas, junto a las caspasas, desempeñan un papel esencial en los procesos de regulación de funciones celulares, tanto en etapas del desarrollo como tras la respuesta ante un estímulo dañino. Dentro de esta familia de proteasas se engloban las granzimas y la trombina (TR). Las primeras, altamente relacionadas con las proteasas I y II y la catepsina G, se localizan en los gránulos citoplasmáticos de los linfocitos T activados, junto a otras proteínas como la perforina o citolisina. Las granzimas A y B se relacionan con los procesos degenerativos. Éstas entran en el interior de las células diana gracias a la acción de la perforina, y una vez en su interior se translocan al núcleo. La granzima A se ha aislado e identificado como el agente responsable de la inmediata y completa retracción de las neuritas en diversos modelos, y entre sus sustratos fisiológicos se encuentran la fibronectina, el colágeno de tipo IV y los proteoglicanos. La granzima B se caracteriza por ser una cisteína proteasa con sustratos como la prointerleucina-1Beta, el receptor de TR y la polimerasa poli(ADP-ribosa). La familia de las proteasas del tipo TR engloba proteasas como la propia TR, la plasmina, la kallikreína, el activador del plasminógeno urocinasa, y el activador del plasminógeno tisular. La TR se considera como un modulador temprano en los tejidos dañados, que sirve como señal extracelular de muerte que conduce a la activación de mecanismos intracelulares por un mecanismo que parece mediarse por calcio. La actividad de las serina proteasas se regula por inhibidores endógenos, como el inhibidor de activador del plasminógeno, la proteasa nexina-1 y la neuroserpina. Conclusión. Alteraciones en el equilibrio proteasainhibidor resultan cruciales en los procesos implicados en plasticidad y muerte neuronal inducidos por isquemia en el cerebro y por excitotoxinas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;38(5): 449-457, mar. 2004. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las serina proteasas y su función en los procesos de muerte neuronal</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Galindo, MF</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jordán, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ceña, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuster Lluch, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-30912</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d9666</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30204</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9665</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30438</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2585</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22940</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23025</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23521</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24873</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23473</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13765</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
