<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147887</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-1959</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Results of the smoking habit survey in the Hospital de Alcañiz</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. In the hospital of Alcañiz and within the initiative to control smoking, we have conducted a survey on the prevalence and opinion regarding the smoking habit in all the hospital departments. Material and methods. We have carried out a survey in form of a written questionnaire addressed to all the hospital worker, both health care and non-health care workers. The voluntary and anonymous survey was distributed and collected in the different hospital departments by a responsible person designated by the work group. Results. A total of 283 persons surveyed participated, most, 221 (78.1%) being women. Active smoking prevalence was 78 (27.6%) workers. The most active smoking group present was nursing with 37.4%, the computer technology team being the group having the greatest amount of personnel who had never smoked 75%. A total of 71.7% of the smokers admitted having smoked during the work hour although only 2 (0.3%) did so within the hospital premises. More than 70% of the workers agreed with the utility of the smoke-free Hospital de Alcañiz project and that parents as well as health care and non-health care professionals should lead by example by not smoking. Conclusion. Prevalence of smoking the health care centers is elevated so that work must continue and measures implemented against the smoking habit (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fandos Lorente, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Colas Orós, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gavín Blanco, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alquezar Fernández, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Belenguer Carreras, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En el hospital de Alcañiz y dentro de las iniciativas para el control de consumo de tabaco, hemos realizado una encuesta de prevalencia y opinión de tabaquismo en todos los servicios del hospital. Material y métodos. Hemos realizado una encuesta en formato cuestionario escrito dirigida a todos los trabajadores del hospital, tanto sanitarios como no sanitarios. La encuesta, voluntaria y anónima, fue entregada y recogida en los diferentes servicios del hospital por un responsable designado por el grupo de trabajo. Resultados. Participaron 283 encuestados, la mayoría, 221 (78,1%), mujeres. La prevalencia de tabaquismo activo fue de 78 (27,6%) trabajadores. El colectivo que más fumadores activos presentó fue enfermería, con un 37,4%, siendo el equipo de informática los que contaban con más personal nunca fumador 75%. El 71,7% de los fumadores reconocieron fumar en el horario de trabajo aunque solamente 2 (0,3%) lo hacían dentro del recinto hospitalario. Más de un 70% de los trabajadores estuvieron de acuerdo en la utilidad del proyecto Hospital de Alcañiz sin humo, así como en que tanto padres como profesionales sanitarios y no sanitarios debían dar ejemplo no fumando. Conclusión. La prevalencia de tabaquismo en centros sanitarios es elevada por lo que se debe seguir trabajando e implementando medidas en contra del tabaquismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prev. tab;17(4): 158-162, oct.-dic. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147887</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados de la encuesta de tabaquismo en el Hospital de Alcañiz</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32415^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32415^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9926^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9926^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9926^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9926^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
