<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053806</identifier>
<setSpec>0301-0546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Chronic urticaria: What is new, where are we headed</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Chronic urticaria can be defined as the occurrence of widespread daily or nearly daily wheals for at least 6 weeks, which may be accompanied by angioedema. It is a disease with a considerable impact on patients' quality of life. Furthermore, these patients may undergo extensive laboratory evaluations seeking a cause only to be frustrated when none is found. There is no curative treatment for this disorder and we do not understand the mechanisms that lead to the onset of disease. However, in recent years there have been significant advances in the understanding of some of the molecular mechanisms that cause cutaneous inflammation that is manifest as urticaria and angioedema. In this review we will summarize our recent contributions to this field and try to offer insights regarding future directions for research</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferrer, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kaplan, AP</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La urticaria crónica consiste en la presencia de una erupción habonosa generalizada con o sin angioedema que se presenta de forma diaria o casi diaria durante al menos seis semanas. Es una entidad que tiene un impacto muy importante sobre la calidad de vida. Además, a estos pacientes se les somete a múltiples pruebas y analíticas con el fin de encontrar una causa y para frustración del médico y paciente, están invariablemente dentro de la normalidad. No hay tratamiento curativo para esta enfermedad y desconocemos el mecanismo íntimo que lleva a la aparición de una urticaria crónica así como a su remisión. En los últimos años ha habido adelantos importantes en la comprensión de los mecanismos moleculares que pueden causar la inflamación que desencadenará la urticaria y al angioedema. En esta revisión resumimos nuestras contribuciones más recientes en este campo e intentamos sugerir hacia donde puede dirigirse el futuro de la investigación de esta enfermedad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Allergol Immunopathol (Madr);35(2): 57-61, mar. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053806</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Urticaria crónica: Qué es nuevo, dónde fallamos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1512^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8579^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29460^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32004^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d811^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32005^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14983^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
