<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055172</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-734X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anaphylactic reaction after Hippobosca equina bite</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Anaphylaxis to the sting of insect in Italy is very frequent, especially to    Hymenoptera family1. Anaphylaxis to the bite of Diptera, specifically the bite    of Tabanidae family (horsefly) has been sparsely documented2. In our country    we have many insects that belong to Diptera order, like Tabanus. Particularly,    in our areas, rich of grazing, riding school and wild animals, lives a particular    insect that belongs to Diptera order: Hippobosca equina. Hippobosca equina    (H. e.) is a hematophage two-winged fly. It belongs to the order of Diptera, family    of Hippoboscidae, different from Tabanida3. Similar in shape to the horse    fly from the family of Tabanidae, it has pointed proboscis which sucks blood    from mammals. It&#146;s known with the name of louse-fly because of its behavior.    In fact this insect stays attached to animals after bite. Blood-suckers Diptera,    that belong to Hippoboscoidea superfamily, are well known to be carriers of serious    infective diseases4,5. Both families belong to the sub-order of Brachycera.    To our knowledge, anaphylactic reactions to Hippobosca equina bite have    not yet been reported</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quercia, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Emiliani, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Foschi, FG</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Stefanini, GF</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A 48-year-old female received the bite of an unidentified insect in summer time.    Almost immediately she experienced generalized pruritus. Then she developed    urticaria, abdominal pain, nausea, angioedema on the face, and dyspnoea. Afterwards,    in the out-patient department, she underwent an allergic screening through    skin prick tests to Hymenoptera venom and dosage of specific IgE (Cap System).    They revealed sensitization to Apis m, Vespula sp and Polistes sp. In fact the patient    reported urticaria and angioedema after previous Hymenoptera stings. We    performed a skin prick test with Tabanus extracts and obtained a positive reaction    (wheal 5 mm). Later on, the patient captured the culprit insect and, after having    consulted an entomologist, we were able to identify it as a fly from Hippoboscidae    family: Hippobosca equina (H. e.). However, we cannot fully rely on skin    prick tests and specific IgE, since for the time being the extract for H. e. allergy    is not available. Our case is the first clinical report of an allergic reaction after the    bite of Hippobosca. e in a patient with sensitization to Hymenoptera venom</dc:description>
<dc:source>Alergol. inmunol. clín. (Ed. impr.);20(1): 31-33, feb. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055172</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anaphylactic reaction after Hippobosca equina bite</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7473^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7106</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1187^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d721^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d721^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
