<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86632</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endovascular treatment of cerebral aneurysms: review of a ten year experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. We analyze the immediate and long-term clinical and angiographic results of endovascular treatment of ruptured and unruptured aneurysms in our single-center experience. Method. Between January of 1996 and June of 2005, 145 aneurysms were treated endovascularly in 137 patients. The clinical follow-up was performed during hospitalization and then  for at least one year (mean, 40 months) in the out-patient clinic. The results of the angiographic follow-up that was completed by 64.9% of the patients (mean: 33 months) were analyzed. Results. Initially, complete occlusion was obtained in 64.8% and partial (sac or neck remnant) in 22.1%. There were technique failures in 12 cases. Overall morbidity associated to the procedure was 8.1%. There was no case of direct mortality and only one  case of post-embolization re-bleeding. Rate of complete final occlusion was 78.6 and recanalization 7.5%. Partial occlusion and recanalization rates correlated with aneurysm geometry (simple or complex), neck size and posterior localization. Age, clinical state at admission (Hunt-Hess grade III-V), time of treatment and the concomitant intraventricular hemorrhage correlated with worse clinical outcome (Rankin III-V) at day 90 (p&lt;0.05). Discussion. In our experience, endovascular treatment is an effective and safe technique for cerebral aneurysms. Rate of morbidity and the only case of long recanalization demonstrate the procedure safety and stability of the middle-long term results. The large experience of our radiologists and the incorporation of new technical modalities have allowed us to improve the results, above all, in recent years (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pascual Lozano, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Láinez Andrés, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chamarro Lázaro, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Se analizan los resultados clínicos y angiográficos, inmediatos y a largo plazo, del tratamiento endovascular con Guglielmi datachable coiling de aneurismas cerebrales en nuestro medio. Método. Entre enero de 1996 y junio de 2005 fueron intervenidos endovascularmente 145 aneurismas en 137 pacientes. El seguimiento clínico se realizó durante la hospitalización y luego en consultas  externas un mínimo de 1 año (media: 40 meses). Se analizaron los resultados del seguimiento angiográfico que completaron el 64,9% de los pacientes (media: 33 meses). Resultados. Se obtuvo inicialmente una oclusión completa en el 64,8% e incompleta (saco o cuello remanente) en el 22,1%. La técnica fracasó en 12 casos. La morbilidad permanente asociada al procedimiento fue del 8,1%. No hubo ningún caso de mortalidad directa. Hubo un único caso de resangrado postembolización. La tasa de oclusión  completa definitiva fue del 78,6%. La de recanalización del 7,5%. La oclusión incompleta y la recanalización se relacionaron con la geometría (compleja) y la localización (posterior) del aneurisma. La edad, el estado clínico al ingreso (grado de Hunt-Hess III-V), el tiempo de embolización y la presencia de hemorragia intraventricular se relacionaron con una peor evolución clínica (Rankin III-IV) a los 90 días (p&lt;0,05). Discusión. En nuestra experiencia la terapia endovascular es  una técnica eficaz y segura. Los datos de morbilidad y un único caso de recanalización tardía apoyan la seguridad del procedimiento y la estabilidad de los resultados a medio-largo plazo. La experiencia de los radiólogos y la aplicación de nuevos avances técnicos nos permitieron mejorar los resultados, sobre todo durante los últimos años (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;24(9): 797-803, nov. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86632</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento endovascular de aneurismas cerebrales: revisión de una experiencia a 10 años  (Endovascular treatment of cerebral aneurysms: review of a ten year experience)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23184^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30956^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2569^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4695^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200911</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
