<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107532</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0973</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pharmacological and physiological effects of cannabis use</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Since the discovery of the endocannabinoid system, it is known that the psychoactive effects associated with marijuana use are due to the pharmacological interaction of Delta9-tetrahydrocannabinol present in cannabis derivatives with one of the molecular elements of this system, the CB1 cannabinoid receptor that is preferentially located in the central nervous system. However, today it is not clear how this pharmacological interaction relates to the possibility that the prolonged consumption of this type of substances becomes necessarily in addiction. This article will try to review the different studies conducted to identify whether cannabis has reinforcing effects, as well as to determine whether its prolonged consumption is associated with the occurrence of tolerance, dependence and withdrawal phenomena as happen with other addictive substances (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sagredo, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde que se descubrió el sistema cannabinoide endógeno, se sabe que los efectos psicoactivos asociados al consumo de marihuana se deben a la interacción farmacológica del Delta9-tetrahidrocannabinol presente en los preparados de cannabis con uno de los elementos moleculares de este sistema, los receptores cannabinoides CB1 que están localizados preferentemente en el sistema nervioso central. Sin embargo, a día de hoy, todavía no está claro cómo se relaciona esta interacción farmacológica con la posibilidad de que el consumo prolongado de este tipo de sustancias derive necesariamente en adicción. En este artículo se pretende repasar los diferentes estudios que se han realizado para identificar si el cannabis tiene efectos reforzantes, así como para determinar si su consumo prolongado conlleva la aparición de fenómenos de tolerancia, dependencia y abstinencia como ocurre con las sustancias que resultan adictivas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trastor. adict;13(3): 94-96, jul.-sept. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107532</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos farmacológicos y fisiológicos del consumo de cannabis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d38269^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22937^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13761^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2218</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13761^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13761^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2218^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2220^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22937^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22937^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22937^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22937^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38270^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
