<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040251</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evolution of the epidemiological characteristics of tuberculosis in Navarra (1994-2003)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To describe the changes in the incidence and the epidemiological profile of tuberculosis in Navarra. Methods. The cases of tuberculosis in the 1994-2003 period were analysed. Cases reported to the system of obligatory notifiable diseases, completed with the microbiological diagnoses and the cases collected in other health registers. Results. The incidence of tuberculosis fell from 21 per 100,000 inhabitants in the five-year period 1994-1998 to 16 per 100,000 in 1999-2003. In both periods the number of cases in men doubled that in women, and the maximum incidence occurred in the age groups from 25 to 44 and over 65 years of age. The diagnoses of tuberculosis in persons with HIV infection fell from 15.1% to 6.6% and those in immigrants rose from 2.2% to 21.3%. Somewhat over 3% of the cases had received prior anti-tuberculosis treatment and about 6% showed resistance to some medicine, without significant differences between periods. The proportion of potentially transmissible tuberculosis (73%) underwent no significant changes, nor did that of those with positive sputum bacilloscopy. The number of outbreaks (groupings of two or more cases) rose from 18 to 26 and the percentage of cases secondary to another recent case rose from 3.6% to 10.1% (p&lt;0,001). In the 1999-2003 period, pulmonary localisation occurred in isolated form in 67.7% of the patients, and in combination with other localisations in another 5.1%. The isolated pleural form appeared in 9.9% and the meningeal form in 1.5%. Conclusion. There has been an advance in the control of tuberculosis although its incidence is still high with respect to other European countries. Control of imported cases is one of the challenges to be faced in coming years, without neglecting control measures in the autochthonous population</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Urtiaga, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernaola, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castilla, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sola, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torroba, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Irisarri, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barricarte, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hueto, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dorronsoro, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Describir los cambios en la incidencia y en el perfil epidemiológico de la tuberculosis en Navarra. Métodos. Se analizaron los casos de tuberculosis del período 1994-2003 según el sistema de enfermedades de declaración obligatoria, completado con los diagnósticos microbiológicos y con los casos captados por otros registros sanitarios.Resultados. La incidencia de tuberculosis disminuyó desde 21 por 100.000 habitantes en el quinquenio 1994-1998 hasta 16 por 100.000 en 1999-2003. En ambos períodos los casos en hombres duplicaron a los de mujeres, y la máxima incidencia se produjo en los grupos de 25 a 44 y mayores de 65 años. Los diagnósticos de tuberculosis en personas con infección por el VIH disminuyeron del 15,1 al 6,6% y los realizados en personas inmigrantes aumentaron del 2,2 al 21,3%. Algo más del 3% de los casos había recibido tratamiento antituberculoso previo y en torno al 6% presentaban resistencia a algún fármaco, sin diferencias significativas entre periodos. La proporción de tuberculosis potencialmente transmisibles (73%) no experimentó cambios significativos, ni la de aquellas con baciloscopia de esputo positiva (53%). El número de brotes (agrupaciones de dos o más casos) pasó de 18 a 26 y el porcentaje de casos secundarios a otro reciente aumentó desde 3,6 a 10,1% (p&lt;0,001). En el período 1999-2003, la localización pulmonar se presentó de forma aislada en el 67,7% y combinada con otras localizaciones en otro 5,1%. La forma pleural aislada apareció en el 9,9% y la meníngea en el 1,5% de los pacientes.Conclusión. Se ha avanzado en el control de la tuberculosis aunque todavía la incidencia es alta respecto a otros países europeos. El control de los casos importados es uno de los retos para los próximos años, sin descuidar las medidas de control en la población autóctona</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;28(2): 237-245, mayo-ago. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040251</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución en las características epidemiológicas de la tuberculosis en Navarra (1994-2003)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24560</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28583</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4716</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14797^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14791^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14798^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
