<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151563</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acute respiratory distress: from syndrome to disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) is currently one of the most important critical entities given its high incidence, rate of mortality, long-term sequelae and non-specific pharmacological treatment. The histological hallmark of ARDS is diffuse alveolar damage (DAD). Approximately 50% of ARDS patients present DAD, the rest is made up of a heterogeneous group of histological patterns, many of which correspond to a well-recognized disease. For that reason, if these patterns could be diagnosed, patients could benefit from a treatment. Recently, the effect of DAD in clinical and analytical evolution of ARDS has been demonstrated, so the classical approach to ARDS as an entity defined solely by clinical, radiological and gasometrical variables should be reconsidered. This narrative review aims to examine the need to evolve from the concept of ARDS as a syndrome to ARDS as a specific disease. So we have raised 4 critical questions: a) What is a disease?; b) what is DAD?; c) how is DAD considered according to ARDS definition?, and d) what is the relationship between ARDS and DAD? (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Correger, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rios, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villanueva, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cardinal-Fernández, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de distrés respiratorio agudo (SDRA) constituye una de las entidades más importantes de la medicina crítica dada su elevada incidencia, mortalidad, secuelas a largo plazo y ausencia de un tratamiento farmacológico específico. El patrón histológico característico del SDRA es el daño alveolar difuso (DAD). Aproximadamente el 50% de los pacientes con SDRA tienen DAD; el resto está constituido por un grupo heterogéneo de patrones histológicos, muchos de los cuales constituyen enfermedades bien caracterizadas que, de ser diagnosticadas, podrían beneficiarse de un tratamiento específico. Recientemente se ha demostrado el efecto del DAD en la evolución clínica y analítica del SDRA, por lo cual, el enfoque clásico del SDRA como una entidad definida exclusivamente por variables clínicas, radiológicas y gasométricas podría ser reconsiderado. La presente revisión narrativa procura analizar la necesidad de evolucionar desde el concepto de SDRA como síndrome a SDRA como enfermedad; para ello hemos planteado 4 preguntas que consideramos prioritarias: a) ¿qué es una enfermedad?; b) ¿qué es el DAD?; c) ¿cómo consideran al DAD las distintas definiciones de SDRA?, y d) ¿qué relación existe entre el DAD y el SDRA? (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);40(3): 169-175, abr. 2016. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151563</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Distrés respiratorio agudo: del síndrome a la enfermedad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12549^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12087^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12552^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
