<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61122</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-0740</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The evolution of the episiotomies carried out in the Hospital «Ciudad de Coria» between 1997 and 2005. Anatomical and clinical repercussions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To value the effect of a selective policy of episiotomies ineutocic deliveries taken care of by midwives in the Hospital Ciudad deCoria, initiated in 1997, on the number of episiotomies and its repercussionon perine and the neonatal well-being.People and method: Descriptive study with retrospective data collection,carried out in the «Ciudad de Coria» Hospital in Coria, Cáceres,Spain. All the spontaneous vaginal deliveries supervised by midwivesbetween 1 January 1997 and 31 December 2005 were reviewed, collectingthe data from the unit&#146;s log book and analysing the followingvariables: the episiotomy rate, the situation of the perineum after thedelivery and the neonatal wellbeing.Results: A progressive reduction in the rate of episiotomies was observed,from 75.57% (229) in 1997 to 10.65% (26) in 2005. The firstand second degree perineal tears decreased in the first years. The percentageof women with an intact perineum increased from 11.55% (35)in 1997 to 39.34% (96) in 2005, as did the percentage of women whoshowed minimal perineal lesions, from 19.8% (60) at the start of thestudy to 74.59% (180) in 2005. No repercussions were found in the Apgartest of the newborns.Conclusions: The application of a selective episiotomy policy involvesa significant increase of intact perinea or perinea with minimal lesions,without having a negative impact on the percentage of tears or on neonatalwellbeing. The restricted use of episiotomies has led to their substantialdecrease, down to the levels currently recommended, withoutincreasing the number of complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vidal Bermejo, Máxima</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Valorar el efecto de una política selectiva de episiotomíasen partos eutócicos atendidos por matronas en el Hospital Ciudad deCoria, iniciada en 1997, sobre el número de episiotomías y su repercusiónen el periné y el bienestar neonatal.Personas y método: Estudio descriptivo con recogida retrospectivade los datos, realizado en el Hospital «Ciudad de Coria», en Coria (Cáceres).Se han revisado todos los partos eutócicos atendidos por matronasdesde el 1 de enero de 1997 hasta el 31 de diciembre de 2005, recogiéndoselos datos del libro de registro de la unidad y analizando lassiguientes variables: índice de episiotomías, situación del periné despuésdel parto y bienestar neonatal.Resultados: Se observa una disminución progresiva del índice de episiotomías,desde un 75,57% (229) en 1997 hasta un 10,65% (26) en2005. Los desgarros del periné de grado I y II disminuyeron en los primerosaños. En cambio, se produjo un aumento del porcentaje de mujeresque presentaron un periné intacto, que fue del 11,55% (35) en1997 y del 39,34% (96) en 2005, y también de las mujeres que presentaronperiné con lesión mínima, que pasó del 19,80% (60) al iniciodel estudio al 74,59% (180) en 2005. No se observan repercusiones enel test de Apgar del recién nacido.Conclusiones: La práctica de una política selectiva de episiotomíasconlleva un aumento significativo de periné intacto o con lesión mínima,sin repercutir negativamente en el porcentaje de desgarros ni en elbienestar neonatal. Restringiendo el uso de las episiotomías, se consigueun llamativo descenso, hasta alcanzar los niveles recomendadosactualmente, sin que por ello aumente el número de complicaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Matronas prof;10(1): 5-9, ene.-mar. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61122</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución de las episiotomías realizadasen el Hospital «Ciudad de Coria» entre 1997y 2005. Repercusiones anatómicas y clínicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9514^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4920^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
