<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108641</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Opinion of the pharmacists that work in a group of drugstores which differentiation is the services of medical care in the Pharmaceutical service. Case Pharmacies Trébol</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: It is important to study how a pharmaceutical group which has a service of medical care works in their pharmacies, with the objective of being able to explore how some professionals act when they implement and develop these programs. Method: Twenty semi structured interviews are done to pharmacists of the Trébol group, in the different business and premises in Madrid during the second fortnight of September 2009, in which pharmacists that work in the ZAP and other that work in the counter of the pharmacies that participate. Results: Some of the persons interviewed believe that only the big pharmacies can carry out that kind of service. It is better for the ZAP to be visible from the outside, so it can attract attention. The individual counters favor privacy. To work with numerical objectives, is one of the elements that facilitate the implantation of these services, which at the same time can be seen as economical benefits. The pharmacists that have been interviewed work in the ZAP are satisfied with the work they do. The pharmaceutical attention improves the image of the pharmacy by offering and increasing the sales. Some state that the future is to convert the pharmacy in a health center, with the presence of sanitary professionals of different areas, so that the patient can fi nd all the services related to health in the same place. Conclusions: At the Trébol pharmacies it is understood that the Pharmaceutical attention is a business strategy which allows the difference in respect to other drugstores, it is profitable, and the patients become loyal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gastelurrutia Garralda, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riu Torrens, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pablo, D. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Martínez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Martín, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grande, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Nos pareció importante estudiar los métodos de trabajo de un grupo de farmacéuticos que ya tienen implantados los servicios de atención farmacéutica (AF) en sus farmacias, con el objetivo de explorar cómo actúan algunos profesionales a la hora de implantar y desarrollar dichos servicios. Método: Durante la segunda quincena de septiembre de 2009 se realizaron 20 entrevistas semiestructuradas a farmacéuticos del grupo Trébol en los distintos establecimientos y locales en Madrid, en las que participaron farmacéuticos que trabajan en las zonas de atención personalizada (ZAP) y otros que desarrollan su labor en el mostrador de las farmacias. Resultados: Algunos entrevistados creen que sólo en las farmacias grandes pueden desarrollarse servicios. Es mejor que la ZAP sea visible desde el exterior, para que llame la atención. Los mostradores individuales favorecen la privacidad. Trabajar con objetivos numéricos es uno de los elementos que facilitan la implantación de estos servicios, que a su vez se traducen en beneficios económicos. Los farmacéuticos entrevistados que trabajan en ZAP están satisfechos con el trabajo que realizan. La AF mejora la imagen de la farmacia en la que se ofrece, y aumenta las ventas farmacéuticas. Algunos afirman que el futuro pasa por convertir la farmacia en un centro de salud, con presencia de profesionales sanitarios de distintos campos, para que el paciente encuentre todos los servicios relacionados con la salud en un único establecimiento. Conclusiones: En Farmacias Trébol se entiende que la AF es una estrategia de negocio que permite la diferenciación respecto a las demás farmacias, es rentable y fideliza a los pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;13(2): 48-56, mar.-abr. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108641</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Opiniones de farmacéuticos que trabajan en un grupo de farmacias cuya diferenciación es la prestación de servicios de atención farmacéutica. El caso de Farmacias Trébol</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11016^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11016^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11016^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50249</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
