<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124450</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of knowledge about healthy breakfast and its relation to life style habits and academic performance in compulsory secondary students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives The main objective of the study is to analyze whether students of Compulsory Secondary Education (ESO) of Badajoz city known foods that are part of a healthy breakfast. It also intends to see the relationship of this knowledge with lifestyle habits and academic performance. Materials and methods A representative sample of 1197 secondary students in the city of Badajoz (Spain) (50.1% female) was calculated their Body Mass Index (BMI) and were asked to fill in a questionnaire, previously validated in a pilot study, which included sociodemographic items as well as others related with life style habits. They were also asked to choose among a series of food, which of them were a part of a healthy breakfast.Results49.2% of adolescents know foods which are a part of a healthy breakfast. Very low correlations were obtained between all the variables analyzed and knowledge of foods that make up a healthy breakfast. However, within a few variables are significant differences (p &lt; .05) between subgroups, such as families of students with low cultural level of aided schools, repeaters, without reading habit, passing lot of time with friends, who have been on a diet, make less than 3 meals a day and spend less than 10 min for breakfast and know the amount of fruit that should be consumed daily. Conclusions Life style habits of adolescents are not related to the knowledge about the foods that are part of a healthy breakfast (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Preciado, Ventura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gonzalo Córdoba Caro, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luengo Pérez, Luis Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos El objetivo principal del estudio es analizar si los alumnos de la enseñanza secundaria obligatoria (ESO) de la ciudad de Badajoz conocen los alimentos que forman parte de un desayuno saludable. Además se pretende ver la relación que tiene este conocimiento con los hábitos de estilo de vida y el rendimiento académico. Material y método A una muestra representativa formada por 1.197 alumnos de ESO de la ciudad de Badajoz, 50,1% de mujeres, se les calculó el índice de masa corporal (IMC) y contestaron un cuestionario previamente validado en un estudio piloto que incluía variables sociodemográficas y otras relacionadas con los hábitos de estilo de vida. Además se les pidió que seleccionaran entre una serie de alimentos aquellos que formaban parte de un desayuno saludable. Resultados Un 49,12% de los adolescentes conoce los alimentos que forman parte de un desayuno saludable. Se obtienen correlaciones muy bajas entre todas las variables analizadas y el conocimiento de los alimentos que conforman un desayuno saludable. A pesar de ello, dentro de algunas variables se observan diferencias significativas (p &lt; 0,05) entre los subgrupos, como es el caso de alumnos con familias de nivel cultural bajo, de centros concertados, repetidores, sin hábito de lectura, que pasan mucho tiempo con los amigos, que han hecho dieta, hacen menos de 3 comidas diarias y dedican menos de 10 min al desayuno y desconocen la cantidad de fruta que deben consumir diariamente. Conclusiones Los hábitos de estilo de vida de los adolescentes no tienen correlación con el conocimiento sobre los alimentos que conforman un desayuno saludable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;61(5): 242-251, mayo 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124450</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de los conocimientos sobre el desayuno saludable y su relación con los hábitos de estilo de vida y el rendimiento académico en la enseñanza secundaria obligatoria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52508</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55081</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32738^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
