<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60984</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of motor and non-motor symptoms on the direct costs of Parkinson's disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. We evaluate the health-related economic burdenof patients with Parkinson's disease (PD) and identify theimpact of motor and nonmotor symptoms (NMS) and health-relatedquality of life (HRQL) on the direct costs of PD in Spain.Method. A cross-sectional, multicenter, pilot study coveringconsecutive PD outpatients who were included during the year2004. Cognition (MMSE, SCOPA-Cog), autonomic dysfunction(SCOPA-AUT), motor impairment, severity and complications(SCOPA-motor), depression/anxiety (HADS), sleep (PDSS),psychosis (PPRS), pain, severity/global impairment (HY stagingand CISI-PD) and health-related quality of life (EuroQoL) wereevaluated. PD-related cost data were obtained using a standardizedquestionnaire. Association of clinical variables with directcosts was analyzed using the parametric and nonparametric tests.Results. Seventy-eight consecutive PD outpatients (52%female and 48% male) having a mean age of 68.2 years (SD: 11),median HY stage of 2 (1-5), and mean PD duration of 8.3 years(SD: 5.4) were included in this study. Average 3 month total directcost of PD was &#128; 2,631 (SD: 4507) per person (range: &#128; 71.5-&#128;29,159) and medical treatment was the main cost driver, accountingfor 34 % (mean drug cost per person &#128; 669; SD: 406). PDdirect costs were significantly higher among younger patients,with higher HY stage, PD duration, severity, motor impairmentand motor complications (p&lt;0.05).Conclusions. Disease severity, motor impairment and complicationshad a higher impact on the direct costs of PD than NMS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grupo ELEP</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Se evalúa la carga económica de los pacientes conenfermedad de Parkinson (EP) en España y se identifica el impacto delos síntomas motores y los síntomas no motores (SNM) y la calidad devida relacionada con la salud (CVRS) en los gastos directos de la EP.Método. Estudio piloto transversal, multicéntrico con pacientesambulatorios con EP incluidos durante el 2004. Se evaluó cognición(MMSE, CISI-PD, SCOPA-Cog), disfunción autonómica (SCOPA-AUT),discapacidad, gravedad y complicaciones motoras (SCOPA-Motor),depresión/ansiedad (HADS), sueño (PDSS), psicosis (PPRS), dolor (VA),gravedad global (estadio Hoehn-Yahr [HY], CISI-PD) y CVRS (EuroQoLVA) y gastos (cuestionario estandarizado). Se analizó la asociación devariables clínicas con los costes directos usando tests paramétricos yno paramétricos.Resultados. Se incluyeron 78 pacientes (52% mujeres y 48%hombres); edad media: 68,2 años±11; mediana HY: 2 (1-5); duraciónmedia EP: 8,3 años±5,4. El coste medio trimestral directo fue 2.631 &#128;±4.507 por persona con EP (rango: 71,5-29.159,3 &#128;). El gasto farmacológicomedio fue de 669 &#128;±406, y fue el principal determinantede los gastos directos de la EP (34%). Los costes directos de la EP fueronsignificativamente mayores en las personas más jóvenes, con unestadio de HY mayor, mayor duración y gravedad de la EP, mayor discapacidady mayor gravedad de los signos motores y complicacionesmotoras (p&lt;0,05).Conclusiones. La discapacidad, la gravedad motora y las complicacionesmotoras tienen mayor impacto en los gastos directos de laEP que los SNM (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;24(1): 15-23, ene.-feb. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60984</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de los síntomas motores y no motores en los costes directos de la enfermedad de Parkinson</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10489</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27771</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
