<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82595</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Protocol for action in the event of non-resolving pneumonia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Acute lower respiratory tract infections (LRTIs) are the most common infections in children; approximately 1.5% of those infections are pneumonias. It is difficult to establish the incidence of pneumonia since it is a benign process with no official reporting obligation, but it is estimated that there are 15 to 40cases per thousand children and year according to age. Pneumonias are the main cause of respiratory morbidity worldwide and the third cause of death in developed countries; commonly, resolution is the norm. However, in some cases the clinical and radiological evolution is not favourable in spite of a supposedly appropriate treatment. In those cases, a systematic diagnosis is required in order to clarify the causes of the abnormal evolution and establish a correct treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Cimadevilla, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salcedo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tolín, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Ruiz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las infecciones agudas del tracto respiratorio inferior son las más frecuentes en la edad pediátrica; aproximadamente el 1,5% de ellas son neumonías. La incidencia de la neumonía es difícil de establecer, al tratarse de un proceso benigno sin obligación oficial de declararse, aunque se estima en 15-40/1.000 niños al año, según la edad. Las neumonías son la principal causa de morbilidad respiratoria en el mundo y la tercera causa de muerte en los países  desarrollados. Su resolución es habitual, aunque en ciertas ocasiones la evolución clínica y radiológica no es favorable a pesar de realizar un tratamiento supuestamente adecuado, lo que obliga a llevar a cabo una sistemática diagnóstica para intentar aclarar las causas de esta evolución anormal a fin de realizar un tratamiento correcto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;68(6): 285-291, jun. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82595</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Protocolo de actuación ante una neumonía que no se resuelve</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7335^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
