<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120306</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of a short-term whole body vibration intervention on lean mass in elderly people</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: To clarify whether a short-term whole body vibration (WBV) training has an effect on lean mass (LM) in the elderly. METHOD: 49 non-institutionalized elderly (20 men) participated in the study. Participants who met the inclusion criteria were randomly assigned to the WBV or control group. A total of 24 elderly trained squat positioned on a vibration platform 3 times per week for 11 weeks. LM at the whole body, upper and lower limbs was assessed by dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry. Two-way repeated measures ANOVA was used to determine the effects of the intervention on the studied variables and also to determinate the changes within group throughout the intervention period including age and height as covariates.RESULTS:11 weeks of WBV training led to no changes in none of the LM parameters.CONCLUSION:A short-term WBV therapy is not enough to cause significant changes on LM in non-institutionalized seniors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Cabello, Alba</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Agüero, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casajús, José A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ara, Iganacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente-Rodríguez, Germán</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Comprobar si un programa de entrenamiento vibratorio de corta duración tiene algún efecto sobre la masa magra (MM) en personas mayores. Método: 49 personas mayores no institucionalizadas (20 hombres) participaron en el estudio. Los participantes que reunieron los criterios de inclusión fueron distribuidos al azar en el grupo de entrenamiento o el grupo control. Un total de 24 personas entrenaron sobre una plataforma vibratoria 3 veces por semana durante 11 semanas. Mediante absorciometría fotónica dual de rayos X se evaluó la MM del cuerpo completo, brazos y piernas. Se utilizó ANOVA de medidas repetidas para determinar los efectos de la intervención sobre las variables estudiadas y también para determinar los cambios intra-grupo a lo largo del periodo de intervención, incluyendo la edad y altura como variables de confusión. Resultados: 11 semanas de entrenamiento vibratorio no produjeron ningún cambio sobre la MM en ninguna de las regiones. Conclusión: Un programa de entrenamiento vibratorio de corta duración no es suficiente para producir cambios significativos en la masa magra en personas mayores no institucionalizadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;28(4): 1255-1258, jul.-ago. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120306</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de una intervención de vibración corporal total sobre la masa magra en personas ancianas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15137^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
