<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109983</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recommendations on making decisions and end of life care in neonatology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Healthcare-professionals who work in neonatal units believe that a very important part of their work is the care of sick newborns, and their families if the neonate has an incurable disease or will die. The effort is focused on preventing disproportionate and unnecessary treatments that result in pain and discomfort, and also separate the child from his family. These situations usually occur when the infant has a terminal illness, extreme immaturity with complications, or severe birth defects. The care of the sick neonate care at the end of life, and their families requires a considerable effort, dedication and training of all health personnel. The repeated experience of being close to suffering and death can adversely affect the professionals involved. Finally, there is mention of the legal aspects of limiting treatment, how to perform and document decision process, the withdrawal of life support, assessment of symptoms and pain control and sedation. In this paper, the Ethics Working Group of the Spanish Society of Neonatology reflects on decision making at this time of life. The ethical aspects are reviewed, including, limiting treatment, the basis of decision-making process (that should include adequate information), the relationship of trust, and deliberation between parents and professionals to make the right decision. It highlights the importance of caring for the family in a complex situation and of great suffering, when faced with the recommendation of professionals to limit treatment because their child suffers from a disease with a poor prognosis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López de Heredia Goya, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Rodríguez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejedor Torres, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Munóz, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herranz Rubia, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nicolás Jimenez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los profesionales sanitarios que trabajamos en las unidades de neonatología consideramos que una parte muy importante de nuestro trabajo es el cuidado del recién nacido enfermo y su familia, cuando el neonato presenta una enfermedad incurable o va a morir. El esfuerzo se centra en evitar tratamientos desproporcionados e inútiles, que producen dolor, disconfort y separan al niño de su familia. Estas situaciones suelen ocurrir cuando el neonato tiene una enfermedad incurable, inmadurez extrema con complicaciones o graves malformaciones congénitas. En este documento, el Grupo de Trabajo de Ética de la Sociedad Española de Neonatología realiza una reflexión sobre la toma de decisiones en esta edad de la vida. Se han revisado los aspectos éticos de la limitación de los tratamientos, las bases del proceso de toma de decisiones que deben incluir la información adecuada, la relación de confianza y la deliberación entre padres y profesionales para tomar una decisión correcta. Se destaca la importancia del cuidado de la familia con una situación compleja y de gran sufrimiento, cuando se enfrenta a la recomendación de los profesionales de limitar tratamientos al presentar su hijo una enfermedad de mal pronóstico. La atención al neonato enfermo al final de la vida, y a sus familiares, requiere un considerable esfuerzo, dedicación y formación de todo el personal sanitario. La experiencia cercana de forma reiterada al sufrimiento y a la muerte puede afectar negativamente a los profesionales implicados. Para finalizar, se realiza una reflexión de los aspectos jurídicos de la limitación del tratamiento, la retirada del soporte vital y cómo se deben de realizar y documentar el proceso de decisión, la retirada del soporte vital, la valoración de síntomas y el control del dolor y la sedación(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);78(3): 190-190[e1-e14], mar. 2013. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109983</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recomendaciones sobre toma de decisiones y cuidados al final de la vida en neonatología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7405</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29199</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36358</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1352^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
