<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102855</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Maternal intelligence-mental health and child neuropsychological development at age 14 months</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To examine the relationship between maternal intelligence-mental health and neuropsychological development at age 14 months in a normal population, taking into account maternal occupational social class and education. Methods We prospectively studied a population-based birth cohort, which forms part of the INMA (Environment and Childhood) Project. Cognitive and psychomotor development was assessed at 14 months using Bayley Scales of Infant Development. Maternal intelligence and mental health were assessed by the Cattell and Cattell test and the General Health Questionnaire-12 respectively. Results We observed a crude association between maternal intelligence and cognitive development in children at 14 months but this association disappeared when maternal education was included. The associations were stratified by maternal education and occupational social class. Within the manual maternal occupational social class, there was a significant difference in cognitive development between children whose mothers scored in the highest tertile of maternal IQ and those whose mothers scored in the lowest tertile. In contrast, no differences were observed among children whose mothers were in the non-manual occupational social class. Conclusions The association between maternal intelligence and child cognitive development differed by occupational social class. While this association was not confounded by education or other variables in manual occupational social classes, maternal education explained this association among advantaged occupational social classes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vrijheid, Martine</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sunyer, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guxens, Mònica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer, Muriel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Forns, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Esteban, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grellier, James</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Julvez, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos Este estudio exploró la relación entre inteligencia y salud mental materna y desarrollo neuropsicológico infantil a los 14 meses de edad en población normal, teniendo en cuenta la clase social basada en la ocupación y el nivel educativo maternos. Métodos Estudio prospectivo de cohortes de nacimiento englobado dentro del proyecto INMA (Infancia y Medio Ambiente). El desarrollo cognitivo y psicomotor fue evaluado mediante la escala Bayley de desarrollo infantil. La inteligencia y la salud mental maternas se evaluaron usando el Test de Cattell y Cattell, y el Cuestionario de Salud General de 12 ítems, respectivamente. Resultados Se observó una asociación cruda entre inteligencia materna y desarrollo cognitivo infantil a los 14 meses de edad. Sin embargo, esta asociación desaparecía cuando la educación materna era incluida. Las asociaciones fueron estratificadas por educación y clase social basada en la ocupación materna. En el estrato de clase social manual materna se observó una diferencia significativa en la escala mental de la escala Bayley entre esos niños cuyas madres puntuaron en el tercil más alto de inteligencia materna, comparado con el tercil más bajo. No obstante, no se observaron diferencias entre aquellos niños de clase social no manual materna. Conclusiones Existe un patrón diferente en la asociación entre inteligencia materna y desarrollo cognitivo infantil según la clase social materna. Mientras la asociación no es confundida por la educación ni por otras variables en las clases sociales manuales, el nivel educativo materno explica esta asociación en las clases sociales no manuales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;26(5): 397-404, sep-oct. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102855</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inteligencia y salud mental maternas y desarrollo neuropsicológico infantil a los 14 meses de edad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9227^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4592</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3102</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7528</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13306</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
