<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121127</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Functional and aesthetic results of orthopaedic treatment of midshaft fractures of the clavicle. A 22 years follow-up study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To evaluate the functional results of the orthopaedic treatment of midshaft clavicle fractures with a minimum follow-up of 15 years. Materials and methods: A retrospective study was conducted on 40 patients, mean age 35 years (18&#150;64) with a non-surgically treated clavicle fracture. The mean follow-up was more than 22 years (15&#150;32). The clinical evaluation was performed with the Disability of Arm, Shoulder and Hand score (DASH), Constant Shoulder Score test (CSS), EVA score, and a subjective assessment of the final result. Fractures were classified according to Neer's criteria. The radiological evaluation was performed with an anteroposterior and 45° cephalic anteroposterior oblique X -ray. Results: A mean DASH score 2.17 points (0&#150;20.82), the mean CSS score was 98.2 (79&#150;100), the mean EVA score was 0.42 (0&#150;6), and 100% patients were satisfied, with good or excellent results. The control X -ray showed 39 healed fractures (97.5%) with a mean shortening of 6.4 mm (0&#150;20). Conclusions: The presence of comminution and/or shortening of 15 mm or more had the worst functional and radiographic results. Despite this, non-surgical treatment showed excellent functional and radiographic results, and a high personal satisfaction (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Capdevila-Baulenes, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sirvent-Díaz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calmet-García, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar el resultado funcional del tratamiento ortopédico de las fracturas de tercio medio de clavícula con un seguimiento mínimo de 15 años. Material y métodos: Estudio retrospectivo de 40 pacientes adultos, edad media 35 años (18-64), afectos de fractura de tercio medio clavícula tratadas ortopédicamente con seguimiento medio de 22 años (15-32). La evaluación clínica se realiza con la escala Disabilities of Arm, Shoulder and Hand (DASH), el test de Constant Shoulder Score (CSS), la escala visual analógica (EVA) del dolor y una valoración subjetiva respecto al resultado final. La evaluación radiográfica se realiza mediante proyección anteroposterior (AP) simple y oblicua con 45° de inclinación cefálica. Resultados: Los resultados de la escala DASH muestran un valor medio de 2,17 sobre 100 (0-20,82), el test de CSS medio es de 98,2 sobre 100, la escala EVA 0,42 sobre 10 (0,6) y el 100% de resultados fueron buenos o excelentes de manera subjetiva por parte de los pacientes. En radiología de control se observan 39 fracturas consolidadas (97,5%) con acortamiento medio de 6,4 mm (0-20). Conclusiones: La presencia de conminución y/o acortamiento igual o mayor a 15 mm obtienen peores resultados funcionales de forma estadísticamente significativa. A pesar de ello, el tratamiento ortopédico de las fracturas de tercio medio de clavícula obtiene un buen resultado funcional y radiográfico, y una alta satisfacción subjetiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);58(2): 108-113, mar.-abr. 2014. graf, tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121127</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fracturas de clavícula tratadas conservadoramente tras 22 años de seguimiento: resultados funcionales y estéticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2992^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11981^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13165^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
