<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116150</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A review of evidence-based resilience programs in the Army</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Since the end of the Cold War and the beginning of the asymmetric warfare, some countries are implementing resilience programs for the mental health´s and well being of their military and families, shaped as Defense strategies. This has been possible because of the development of the positive mental health model and the evidence-based practice in psychology. Objectives: To summarize the information about resilience in the military; to review outstanding factors in resilience military programs; to show how resilience programs are already implemented; to analyze resilience evidenced-based main topics in the Comprehensive Soldier and Family Fitness and in the Battlemind Trainig; to help overcome the idiomatic hurdle; to analyze the barriers of resilience programs; and to suggest research topics. Methods: The publications about resilience and military were review in PsycINFO and DTIC. Meta-analysis, systematic reviews and randomized controlled trial with strong or moderate evidence were selected. Results: There is a growing trend in the use of evidence-based practices in military resilience programs. The content of the resilience programs is usually evidence-based. However, some of these programs haven´t been validated yet. comprehensive Soldier and Family Fitness and the Battlemind Training are described because of their good validation; finally, the barriers in the implementation of the programs are discussed. Discussion: The growing evidence-based psychology has been significant in military contexts, throwing positive results in the personnel. However, there are still some barriers to develop these programs in the Army (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Silgo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los riesgos físicos y psicológicos asociados a las operaciones, el desarrollo del modelo positivo de salud mental y el avance en las prácticas basadas en la evidencia en psicología, han determinado que las estrategias de Defensa en determinados países incorporen programas de entrenamiento de la resiliencia para los militares y sus familias. Objetivos: Identificar tendencias en el estudio de la resiliencia en contextos militares; analizar el contenido de los programas de resiliencia en población militar; valorar las evidencias de dichos programas, entre ellos el Comprehensive Soldier and Family Fitness y el Battlemind Trainig; y examinar qué barreras dificultan la implementación de dichos programas en contextos militares. Método: Se emplearon bases de datos civiles y militares para realizar la revisión de publicaciones sobre resiliencia en personal militar. Se seleccionaron aquellas revisiones sistemáticas, metanálisis e investigaciones que hubieran demostrado un grado de evidencia fuerte o moderado. Resultados: Se observa una tendencia creciente a abordar la resiliencia en contextos militares desde las prácticas basadas en la evidencia; se demuestra que los contenidos de los programas militares de resiliencia se basan en evidencias fuertes o moderadas; se expone un resumen de programas militares de resiliencia; se detallan las fuertes evidencias en las que se basan el Battlemind Training y el Comprehensive Soldier and Family Fitness. y se relatan algunas de las barreras que obstaculizan la implementación de dichos programas en los ejércitos. Discusión: El avance de la psicología basada en la evidencia ha sido significativo en los ejércitos, redundando en resultados positivos en el personal militar. Sin embargo, existen todavía algunas barreras que dificultan realizar estos programas en contextos militares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;69(3): 182-194, sept. 2013. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116150</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión de programas de resiliencia basados en la evidencia en los ejércitos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9077^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29210</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53366</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
