<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036951</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Descriptive analysis of chronic pain clinics operating in Spain in 2001</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: To describe the characteristics and care approaches to care of chronic pain clinics operating in Spain in 2001.DESIGN: Cross-sectional mail survey of pain clinics in Spain. SETTING: Chronic pain clinics in Spain. STATISTICAL ANALYSIS: Descriptive statistics of pain clinics responding to the questionnaire. RESULTS: Fifty-six of the 79 pain clinics (70.8%) responded; 57.1% were in public facilities, 55.4% were affiliated with medical schools, and 53.6% were interdisciplinary units. Both acute and chronic pain were treated by 72.4%of the respondents. Anesthesiology departments supervised89.3% of the clinics. Only 57.1% had staff permanently assigned to the pain clinic. A mean 2194 (SD 2041) visits by patients were received annually. The most commonly applied treatments were drugs, blocks, spinal techniques, and transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation. Implantable systems were more frequently used in chronic pain clinics than in mixed pain clinics, and in university-affiliated clinics than in non-teaching facilities (P=0.03 in both comparisons).A psychological approach was used more often in interdisciplinary clinics than in units operated by staff from a single specialty (P&lt;0.01).CONCLUSIONS: Chronic pain clinics were not evenly distributed throughout Spain. The number of patients treated at pain clinics was high. The various characteristics of pain clinics&#151;such as funding source, interdisciplinarity, university affiliation, and specialization in chronic pain&#151;a were factors that affected the use of certain treatments</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rigola, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Zapata, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Català, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Descripción de las características y actividad asistencial de las Unidades de Dolor Crónico (UDC)de España durante el año 2001.DISEÑO: Estudio transversal basado en una encuesta por correo realizada a las UDC españolas. UNIDAD DE ESTUDIO: UDC españolas. ANÁLISIS: Análisis descriptivo de las UDC que cumplimentaron la encuesta. RESULTADOS: De 79 UDC encuestadas, respondieron56 (70,8%), de las cuales el 57,1% eran públicas, el55,4% desarrollaban actividad docente y el 53,6% eran multidisciplinares. El 72,4% de UDC eran mixtas. El89,3% eran dependientes del Servicio de Anestesiología. Sólo un 57,1% de UCD disponían de personal con dedicación exclusiva. La media del número de visitas anual por UDC fue de 2.194 (±2.041). Los recursos terapéuticos más utilizados fueron los fármacos, los bloqueos, las técnicas espinales y las técnicas de estimulación transcutáneas (TENS). Los sistemas implantables también fueron más frecuentes en las unidades de dolor crónico que en las de dolor mixto así como, también fue más frecuente en las universitarias que en las no universitarias (p= 0,03y p= 0,03 respectivamente). El abordaje psicológico se utilizó más en las multidisciplinares que en las unidisciplinarias (p&lt;0,01). CONCLUSIONES: La distribución geográfica de las UDC en España no fue homogénea. La actividad asistencial de dichas UDC fue importante. Diversas características de las UDC como fuente de financiación, multidisciplinariedad, práctica de docencia universitaria y especialización en sólo dolor crónico, condicionaron la utilización de algunos tratamientos para el dolor</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;52(3): 141-148, mar. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036951</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis descriptivo en el año 2001 de las Unidades de Tratamiento del Dolor Crónico en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33118</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28561</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
