<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147032</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Benzodiazepines in aged patients: a case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Benzodiazepines are the most consumed sedative-hypnotic drugs, especially among geriatric population. In this publication, we report the case of a patient who suffered a fall and broked his femur and who was treated with two benzodiazepines at higher doses tan recommended for elderly patients, at the time of suffering the fall. Such drugs were ketazolam and lorazepam, prescribed at 30 mg/ day and 5 mg/day respectively. We emphasize the need of pay special attention to the dosage of these drugs in the elderly and to follow the recommendations of choicing those ones of short or ultrashorthalf-life, at the lowest dose possible and for the shortest time necessary (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz Gutiérrez, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las benzodiazepinas son los fármacos hipnótico-sedantes más consumidos, sobre todo entre la población geriátrica. En la presente publicación se describe el caso clínico de un paciente que ha sufrido una caída con consecuencia de rotura de fémur y que se encontraba en tratamiento con dos benzodiazepinas a dosis mayores a las recomendadas para ancianos, en el momento de sufrir la caída. Dichos fármacos fueron ketazolam y lorazepam, a dosis de 30 mg y 5 mg, respectivamente. Recalcamos la importancia de prestar especial atención a la dosificación de estos fármacos en los ancianos y de seguir las recomendaciones de elegir benzodiazepinas de vida media corta o ultracorta, a la menor dosis posible y durante el menor periodo de tiempo necesario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;17(6): 763-768, 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147032</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Benzodiazepinas en ancianos: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4365</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22065</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5368^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5368^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5368^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5368^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30472</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
