<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040084</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6709</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Microbe - surface interactions in biofouling and biocorrosion processes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The presence of microorganisms on material surfaces can have a profound effect on materials performance. Surface-associated microbial growth, i.e. a biofilm, is known to instigate biofouling. The presence of biofilms may promote interfacial physico-chemical reactions that are not favored under abiotic conditions. In the case of metallic materials, undesirable changes in material properties due to a biofilm (or a biofouling layer) are referred to as biocorrosion or microbially influenced corrosion (MIC). Biofouling and biocorrosion occur in aquatic and terrestrial habitats varying in nutrient content, temperature, pressure and pH. Interfacial chemistry in such systems reflects a wide variety of physiological activities carried out by diverse microbial populations thriving within biofilms. Biocorrosion can be viewed as a consequence of coupled biological and abiotic electron-transfer reactions, i.e. redox reactions of metals, enabled by microbial ecology. Microbially produced extracellular polymeric substances (EPS), which comprise different macromolecules, mediate initial cell adhesion to the material surface and constitute a biofilm matrix. Despite their unquestionable importance in biofilm development, the extent to which EPS contribute to biocorrosion is not well-understood. This review offers a current perspective on material/microbe interactions pertinent to biocorrosion and biofouling, with EPS as a focal point, while emphasizing the role atomic force spectroscopy and mass spectrometry techniques can play in elucidating such interactions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hiraoka, Kenzo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beech, Iwona B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sunner, Jan A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La presencia de microorganismos en las superficies de materiales puede tener un efecto profundo en el funcionamiento de dichos materiales. El crecimiento microbiano asociado a superficies, por ejemplo un biofilm, se sabe que estimula el desarrollo del bioensuciamiento (biofouling). La presencia de biofilms puede promover en las interfaces reacciones fisicoquímicas no favorecidas en condiciones abióticas. En el caso de materiales metálicos, los cambios no deseados en las características del material y debidos a un biofilm (o a una capa de bioensuciamiento) se denominan biocorrosión o corrosión microbiana (MIC, microbially influenced corrosion). El bioensuciamiento y la biocorrosión se producen en hábitat acuáticos y terrestres con diferentes contenidos de nutrientes, temperatura, presión y pH. En dichos sistemas, la química de las interfaces refleja una gran variedad de actividades fisiológicas realizadas por poblaciones microbianas diversas que crecen muy bien en los biofilms. La biocorrosión puede verse como la consecuencia de un conjunto de reacciones biológicas y abióticas de transferencia de electrones de los metales, por ejemplo reacciones redox, favorecidas por la ecología microbiana. Las sustancias poliméricas extracelulares (EPS) producidas por microorganismos, que comprenden diferentes macromoléculas, median la adherencia inicial de la célula a la superficie del material y constituyen la matriz del biofilm. A pesar de su importancia indiscutible en el desarrollo del biofilm, no se sabe muy bien hasta qué punto contribuyen las EPS a la biocorrosión. Esta revisión describe la percepción actual de las interacciones material/microorganismo relativas a la biocorrosión y al bioensuciamiento, centrándose en las EPS, y destacando el papel que las técnicas de espectroscopia de fuerza atómica y de espectrometría de masas pueden desempeñar en la aclaración de tales interacciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int Microbiol;8(3): 157-168, sept. 2005. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040084</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión de las interacciones entre microorganismos y superficies en los procesos de bioensuciamiento y de biocorrosión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11545^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13440^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32342</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3359</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13441^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32433</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
