<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77935</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Subjective experience facing disability, A psychoanalytical approach</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We are all adopted beyond the biological kins-hip that unites us to our progenitors. The appearanc eof a disability or malformation is experienced as something siniter affecting the ideal image projected onto the being  about to be born. Faced with such a reality it is necessary for the progenitor to assume the child as such so as to work through the grief of the experienced loss. At the opposite side to the mourning we find the taboo of what is denied unconsciously. The function of the psycholgist is to accompany the parents in the transitionform the taboo towards mouning, favouring in this way the adoption of the newborb and the updating of all his potentials (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Iglesias, Mario</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Todos somos adoptados más allá del parentesco biológico que nos une a nuestros progenitores. La aparición de una discapacidad o malformación es vivida como algo siniestro que incide en la imagen ideal proyectada enel ser que está por nacer. Ante tal realidad es necesario que el probenitor asuma al hijo como tal para que pueda elaborar el duelo por la pérdida vivida. En el caso opuesto al duelo encontramos el tabú de aquello que se niega inconscientemente. La función del psicólogo es acompañar a lso padres en el tránsito del tabú al delo, favoreciendo así la adopcióndel neonato y la actualización de todas sus potencialidades (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(7): 67-73, ene. -jun.2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77935</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia subjetiva  frente a la discapacidad. Un enfoque psicoanalítico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30935^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10476</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33552^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
