<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131999</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-0740</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Contribution of maternal education to maternal and infant health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Maternal education is the health education programme run during the process of pregnancy, delivery, postpartum and birth. Participation in this programme has often been related exclusively &#150;and wrongly&#150; with reducing the pain of birth. A change is currently coming about in the context of postpartum care. Moreover, women&#146;s participation in this programme is generally low. For these reasons, it was decided to establish the benefits offered by a maternal education programme for both mother and newborn, with a view to promoting the programme with the aid of suitable scientific support. To do this a bibliographical search was conducted in the main national and international databases. Most of the results found indicate benefits from the mother and the newborn (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Galiano, Juan Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Rodríguez, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La educación maternal es el programa de educación para la salud que se desarrolla durante el proceso de embarazo, parto, puerperio y nacimiento. La participación en este programa se ha relacionado a menudo, casi exclusivamente y de forma errónea, con una disminución del dolor en el parto. Actualmente se está produciendo un cambio en el contexto de la atención perinatal y, además, la participación de las mujeres en dicho programa suele ser baja. Por todo ello, se propuso conocer los beneficios que aporta el programa de educación maternal, a la madre y al recién nacido, con el fin de poder promocionar dicho programa con el apoyo científico adecuado. Para conseguir este objetivo, se realizó una búsqueda bibliográfica en las bases de datos nacionales e internacionales más relevantes. La mayoría de los resultados hallados indican beneficios para la madre y el recién nacido (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Matronas prof;15(4): 137-141, oct.-dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131999</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Contribución de la educación maternal a la salud maternoinfantil. Revisión bibliográfica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28488</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37736</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7922^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
