<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119429</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5274</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recommendations for the use of the Spanish adaptation of the Beck Anxiety Inventory (BAI) in clinical practice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In its 25 years of existence, the Beck Anxiety Inventory (BAI) has become the most widely used self-report instrument for assessing the severity of anxiety in the countries with higher research productivity in psychology, although in Spain this instrument is still the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI). This paper presents the basic characteristics of the BAI in comparison with the Trait Anxiety scale of the STAI, describes the process of adaptation of the BAI to the Spanish population, summarizes the psychometric properties of this adaptation, and discusses its use in the clinical practice. To this use, norms and cut-off scores are calculated in order to measure the severity of anxiety, evaluate the clinical significance of therapeutic change, screen for clinical anxiety, and aid in the differential diagnosis of anxiety disorders (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En sus 25 años de existencia, el Inventario de Ansiedad de Beck (BAI) se ha convertido en el cuestionario autoaplicado para evaluar la gravedad de la ansiedad más utilizado en los países con mayor producción científica en psicología, aunque en España dicho instrumento sigue siendo el Cuestionario de Ansiedad Estado-Rasgo (STAI). En este trabajo se presentan las características básicas del BAI en comparación con la escala de Ansiedad Rasgo del STAI, se describe el proceso de adaptación del BAI a la población española, se resumen las propiedades psicométricas de dicha adaptación y se discute su utilización en la práctica clínica, para lo cual se calculan baremos y puntuaciones de corte para la evaluación de la gravedad de la ansiedad, la evaluación de la significación clínica de los cambios terapéuticos, el cribado de personas con ansiedad clínica y la ayuda en el diagnóstico diferencial de los trastornos de ansiedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. salud;25(1): 39-48, mar. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119429</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recomendaciones para la utilización de la adaptación española del Inventario de Ansiedad de Beck (BAI) en la práctica clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8519</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3885^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
