<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75094</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of personality disorders and consumption patterns on the efficacy of a relapse-prevention program for the treatment of alcoholism</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this study is to analyze to efficacy of a cognitive-behavioral treatment program, in individual and group format, for people with alcohol problems, and to determine the role of some personality variables in the process of therapeutic recovery. The sample was made up of 80 patients diagnosed as alcoholics, 83.8 % of whom were men (n = 67) and 16.3 % were women (n = 13). Mean age was 42.73 years, with a standard deviation of 9.63 years. Basically, we found a high incidence of obsessive-compulsive personality disorder and consumption patterns that change as a function of the presence or absence of personality disorders. We also observed that the results varied in relation to physiological variables and environmental situations associated with the presence of craving responses. Treatment of such patients with dual pathology demands greater effort from the therapist to promote treatment adherence, an aspect crucial to completion of treatment programs and to achieve therapeutic success. Cognitive-behavioral intervention for relapse prevention was observed to produce satisfactory results in patients with personality disorders. Neither consumption patterns nor personality disorders predict the type of treatment termination (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez González, José Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trujillo Mendoza, Humberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Graña Gómez, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio tiene como objetivo analizar la eficacia de un programa de tratamiento cognitivo conductual en formato de terapia individual y grupal para personas con un problema de alcoholismo, y determinar el papel que juegan determinadas variables de personalidad en el proceso de recuperación terapéutica. La muestra estaba formada por 80 pacientes diagnosticados con un problema de alcoholismo, siendo el 83.8 % hombres (n = 67) y el 16.3 % mujeres (n =13). La edad media era de 42.73 años y la desviación típica 9.63 años. Se ha encontrado, fundamentalmente, una alta incidencia del trastorno de personalidad obsesivo-compulsivo y patrones de consumo de alcohol que cambian en función de la presencia o ausencia de trastornos de personalidad. También se puso de manifiesto que los resultados variaban en relación a variables fisiológicas y a situaciones ambientales asociadas a la presencia de respuestas de deseo. El tratamiento de estos pacientes con patología dual exige un mayor esfuerzo por parte del terapeuta para potenciar la adherencia al tratamiento, aspecto que es crucial a la hora de completar el programa de tratamiento y alcanzar el éxito terapéutico. Se ha visto que la intervención cognitivo-conductual para la prevención de recaídas muestra resultados satisfactorios en pacientes con trastornos de la personalidad. Ni los patrones de consumo ni los trastornos de la personalidad predicen el tipo de terminación del tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);21(2): 105-112, mar.-jun. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75094</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de los trastornos de la personalidad y patrones de consumo en la eficacia de un programa de prevención de recaídas para el tratamiento del alcoholismo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24570</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33536^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1538</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
