<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119191</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Medication safety in surgery. error risk areas and improvements proposed by the nurses</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This bibliographic study describes the aspects of bonding that a pediatric nurse must know to foster the emotional attachment between a mother and her baby in the maternity hospital setting. It describes the theoretical models of bonding based on a review of the literature and research on this subject. It also discusses the origins of the bonding theory and the characteristics, types, benefits and consequences that this attachment has on the child&#146;s physical, emotional and social development. Finally, it summarizes the nurse&#146;s role in strengthening mother-child duality, assisting with baby care and supporting the family environment. The qualitative protocol of Kitchenham (2005) was used to extract the relevant information. Conclusion: The results of this review highlight the key role of nurses in promoting mother-child bonding despite political structures in maternity and pediatric centres (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín Cebrián, M. Camen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casanova Forner, M. Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano-Caballero Gálvez, M. Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez López, M. Ascensión</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Celma Vicente, Matilde</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano Gómez, Martina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se describe el proceso de implantación de mejoras para la seguridad del paciente en la administración de medicamentos, en quirófano.  Objetivos. Conocer los puntos débiles del quirófano que pueden contribuir a que se produzca un incidente en torno a la medicación y la administración de líquidos intravenosos en aquel, y establecer estrategias de mejora para reducir o prevenir los errores a partir de las experiencias de las enfermeras.  Método. Cualitativo de consenso mediante grupo de enfermeras expertas y cuestionario sobre los niveles de riesgo que estas atribuyen a cada una de las categorías de análisis. Se exploran sus experiencias sobre la seguridad en quirófano y sus propuestas para el control de los errores de medicación.  Resultados. Se identifican como áreas de mayor riesgo los proveedores y la prescripción y el procesamiento, los puntos débiles de la cultura profesional sobre la seguridad del paciente y las propuestas de mejora (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;37(1): 42-50, ene. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119191</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguridad de la medicación en quirófano. Áreas de riesgo de errores y propuestas de mejora de las enfermeras</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52955</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10053^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10055^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201401</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
