<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045471</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Glutamate-related excitoxicity neuroprotection with memantine, an uncompetitive antagonist of nmda-glutamate receptor, in Alzheimer&#146;s disease and vascular dementia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To review the therapeutic efficacy of memantine, an uncompetitive antagonist of N-methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA)-glutamate receptor. Development. Alzheimer&#146;s disease (AD) is the most common neurodegenerative disorder and cause ofdementia with ageing worldwide. The main AD symptoms are a gradual loss of cognitive function and a functional impairment.Glutamatergic excitatory neurotransmission, an important process in learning and memory, is severely disrupted in AD,probably due to the oxidative stress associated with the &amp;#946;-amyloid peptide (1-42) increase. The glutamate-related excitotoxicity,mainly mediated by NMDA subtype of the glutamate receptors, is a common clue of pathogenesis for neurodegenerativedisorders. Conclusions. Memantine, a moderate-affinity, voltage-dependent, uncompetitive antagonist of NMDAreceptor, shows neuroprotective effects in patients with moderate-to-severe AD. Memantine is a drug with neuroprotective andcognition-enhanced properties, which can be combined with other treatments for AD. Thus, memantine does not stop orreverse AD, but its moderating effect in protecting the brain from the toxic levels of calcium, allows normal signaling amongbrain neurons. The efficacy and safety profile of memantine have been reported in several clinical trials for treatment of ADand vascular dementia</dc:description>
<dc:creator>TAnovic, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alfaro, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Realizar una revisión de la eficacia terapéuticade memantina, un antagonista no competitivo del receptor de Nmetil-D-aspartato (NMDA)-glutamato. Desarrollo. La enfermedadde Alzheimer (EA) es el trastorno neurodegenerativo y la causa dedemencia asociada al envejecimiento más frecuente en todo elmundo. Los síntomas principales de la EA son una pérdida gradualde la función cognitiva y el deterioro funcional. La neurotransmisiónexcitatoria glutamatérgica, un proceso importante en elaprendizaje y la memoria, se encuentra gravemente alterada en laEA, debido probablemente al estrés oxidativo asociado con el aumentodel péptido amiloide &amp;#946; (1-42). La excitotoxicidad asociadaal glutamato, mediada principalmente por el subtipo NMDA de losreceptores de glutamato, es un indicio frecuente de patogenia entrastornos neurodegenerativos. Conclusiones. La memantina, unantagonista no competitivo, dependiente de voltaje y con una moderadaafinidad por el receptor de NMDA, induce efectos neuroprotectoresen pacientes con EA entre moderada y grave. La memantinaes un fármaco con propiedades neuroprotectoras y potenciadorasde la cognición que se puede combinar con otros tratamientoscontra la EA. Por tanto, la memantina no detiene ni reviertela EA, pero su efecto moderador al proteger el cerebro de losniveles tóxicos de calcio permite una transmisión normal de señalesentre las neuronas cerebrales. Se describen aquí diferentesensayos clínicos que han detallado la eficacia y la seguridad de lamemantina en el tratamiento de la EA y la demencia vascular</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;42(10): 607-616, mayo. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045471</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neuroprotección con memantina (antagonista no competitivo del receptor NMDA-glutamato) frente a la excitotoxicidad asociada al glutamato en la enfermedad de Alzheimer y en la demencia vascular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23598^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32219^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24240^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9687^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29046^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
