<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119743</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To determine knowledge about pregnancy and contraceptive methods among school adolescent in order to define their lacks, and those aspects to include in programs of health education. Subject and methods. Cross-sectional study. Stratified random sample from Córdoba secondary schools. Anonymous self administered survey. Results. Of the 893 students, 48% was men. The mean age of the sample was 17.16 years (95% CI: 17.05-17.26). 77,7% recognize to be very informed  about pregnancy and contraceptive methods, finding significant differences among public (80%) and private schools (73,5%) p=0,034. About pregnancy, the mean of successes was 3,40 (95% CI: 3.31-3.48); limits 0-5), finding differences among women (p&lt;0,001); older students (p&lt;0,001); public schools (p=0,002), and the students non believers (p=0.002). About contraceptive methods, the mean of successes was of 5.69 (IC95% 5,59-5.78; limits 0-8), with significant differences among older students (p&lt;0.001) and public schools (p&lt;0.001). Conclusions. Level of knowledge shown y adolescents for aspects related to pregnancy and contraceptive methods can be consider as enough, being women those that to present a bigger degree of knowledge. Likewise, the information facilitated by doctors and professors influences in a right way about the final result (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gascón Jiménez, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juralo Porcel, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Gochicoa, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gascón Jiménez, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montes Redondo, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérula de Torras, L. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Determinar el conocimiento sobre embarazo y métodos anticonceptivos en los adolescentes escolarizados a fin de delimitar sus carencias, y aquellas facetas a incluir en los programas de educación sanitaria. Personas y métodos. Estudio transversal. Muestreo aleatorio estratificado de los centros escolares de secundaria de Córdoba. Cuestionario anónimo autocumplimentado. Resultados. De los 893 alumnos, el 48% eran hombres. La media de edad fue de 17,16 años (IC 95%: 17,05-17,26). El 77,7% afirman estar bien informados respecto al embarazo y anticonceptivos, encontrando diferencias significativas entre centros públicos (80%) y privados (73,5%) p=0,034. Respecto al embarazo, la media de aciertos fue de 3,40 (IC 95%: 3,31-3,48; límites 0-5), encontrando diferencias a favor de las mujeres (p&lt;0,001); en los cursos superiores (p&lt;0,001); en los centros públicos (p=0,002) y los alumnos no creyentes (p=0,002). Para los anticonceptivos, la media fue de 5,69 (IC 95%: 5,59-5,78; limites 0-8), con diferencias significativas a favor de los cursos superiores (p&lt;0,001) y en los centros públicos (p&lt;0,001). Conclusiones. El nivel de conocimiento mostrado por los adolescentes para aspectos relacionados con el embarazo y los anticonceptivos se puede considerar como suficiente, siendo las mujeres las que presentan un mayor grado de conocimiento. Asimismo, la información facilitada por médicos y profesores influye de manera favorable en el resultado final (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;59(4): 348-355, jul.-ago. 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119743</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conocimientos sobre embarazos y métodos anticonceptivos entre adolescentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d297</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3287</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3286^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13116^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11709</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
