<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036967</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Stress, hemodynamic and immunological responses to inhaled and intravenous anesthetic techniques for video-assisted laparoscopic cholecystectomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: Given the immunomodulatory effects of anesthesia        and surgery, 2 anesthetic regimens in clinical use were        compared to evaluate hemodynamic, stress, and immunologic        response in patients undergoing laparoscopic cholecystectomy.        PATIENTS AND METHODS: Randomized controlled trial        in patients classified ASA I and scheduled for laparoscopic        cholecystectomy. Patients were randomly assigned to        the inhaled anesthetic group (13 anesthetized with propofol&#150;        fentanyl&#150;isoflurane) or the total intravenous anesthesia        (TIVA) group (14 patients anesthetized with propofol&#150;        remifentanil). Patients in both groups received the        muscle relaxant vecuronium. We assessed hemodynamic        variables, cortisol levels, prolactin, interleukin 6, white        cell and lymphocyte counts before, during (1 hour after        induction) and after (24 hours and 7 days) surgery.        RESULTS: Hemodynamic variables were stable in both        groups. Significant changes in prolactin levels and markers of        immune and inflammatory responses between baseline and        later measurements occurred in both groups. Patients who        received TIVA had no change in cortisol levels at any time        during the study. The TIVA group had lower levels of cortisol        than did the inhaled anesthesia group (TIVA, 207 [SD, 100]        ng/mL; inhaled 293 [97] ng/mL; P&lt;0.05)), higher neutrophil        counts (TIVA, 75 [12.5]%; inhaled: 62 [20]%; P&lt;0.05) and        higher CD4+ T lymphocyte counts (TIVA, 53 [11.6]%; inhaled:        42 [17.6]%; P&lt;0.001).        CONCLUSION: Although both techniques afford hemodynamic        stability, lower cortisol levels were observed with the        application of TIVA with propofol&#150;remifentanil. That would        be the technique of choice for patients with compromised        immune response</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Colucci, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Graziola, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elena, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puig, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gobbo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Dados los efectos inmunomodulatorios de la        anestesia y la cirugía, se compararon dos regímenes anestésicos        en uso clínico, evaluando la respuesta hemodinámica,        de estrés e inmunológica en pacientes de colecistectomía        laparoscópica (CVL).        PACIENTES Y MÉTODOS: Estudio clínico prospectivo randomizado        en pacientes ASA I de CVL electivas. Los        pacientes fueron asignados al azar al grupo Inhalatorio        (13 pacientes anestesiados con propofol-fentanilo-isoflurano)        o al grupo TIVA (14 pacientes, recibieron anestesia        con propofol-remifentanilo). Se administró vecuronio en        ambos grupos como relajante neuromuscular. La evaluación        incluyó variables hemodinámicas, niveles de cortisol,        prolactina e interleucina-6, así como recuentos leucocitarios        y linfocitarios, que fueron registrados antes de la        cirugía, intraoperatorio (1 hora después del comienzo de        la anestesia) y en el postoperatorio (24 horas y 7 días).        RESULTADOS: En ambos grupos se verificó buen control        hemodinámico. En cada grupo, en los diferentes momentos anestésico        quirúrgicos se produjeron cambios significativos con respecto        a los valores basales en cortisol, prolactina y marcadores de        la respuesta inmune-inflamatoria. Los pacientes que recibieron        TIVA no modificaron sus niveles de cortisol a lo largo del estudio.        Al comparar entre las dos técnicas anestésicas se observó en        TIVAmenores niveles de cortisol (207 ± 100 ng/ml), y niveles más        altos de neutrófilos (75 ± 12,5%) y linfocitos TCD4 (53 ± 11,6%)        que en el grupo inhalatorio: cortisol 293 ± 97 ng/ml, p&lt;0,05; neutrófilos        62 ± 20%, p&lt;0,05 y LTCD4 42 ± 17,6%, p&lt;0,001.        CONCLUSIONES: Si bien ambas técnicas brindaron estabilidad        hemodinámica, la técnica intravenosa (propofol-remifentanilo)        mostró menor respuesta de cortisol y sería        de elección en pacientes con compromiso de la respuesta        inmunológica</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;52(4): 208-216, abr. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036967</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio sobre la respuesta de estrés, hemodinámica e inmunológica de dos técnicas anestésicas (inhalatoria e intravenosa) en colecistectomías videolaparoscópicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30788</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d712</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22498</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15343</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13883</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32366^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32367^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d788^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13700</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1794</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7293</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d788^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9489^s32387</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7594</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d788^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
