<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044529</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Priapism following paraneoplastic leukemoid reaction in a patient with bladder cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Priapism associated with solid tumours is usually produced by penile metastasis or direct tumour infiltration of the corpora cavernosa. Neoplasias are responsible for between 3-8% of all cases of priapism,and in 80% of cases the primary tumour has a genito-urinary origin. Leukemoid reaction is an haematological disorder characterised by a leukocytosis of over 50000/microl, which develops reactively with different pathological processes such as severe inflammation, disseminated infections, intoxications and tumours.The pathophysiologic mechanism that explains priapism following leukemoid reaction is an intravascular obstruction due to blood hyperviscosity, leading to a blood stasis in the cavernosa veins, and impeding the drainage of the corpora cavernosa. We present a case of priapism in a patient with locally advanced bladder cancer, which was probably the result of blood hyperviscosity produced by a paraneoplastic leukemoid reaction</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cuerpo Pérez, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Blanco, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez Pascual, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Alonso, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonelli Martín, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto García, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo Franco, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Picos, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El priapismo asociado a tumores sólidos suele producirse por metástasis peneanas o por infiltración tumoral directa de los cuerpos cavernosos. Las neoplasias son responsables del 3-8% de los casos de priapismo, y en el 80% de los casos el tumor primario es de origen génito-urinario.La reacción leucemoide es un trastorno hematológico caracterizado por una leucocitosis superiora 50000/microl, que se desarrolla de forma reactiva ante diversos procesos patológicos como inflamaciones severas, infecciones diseminadas, intoxicaciones y tumores. El mecanismo fisiopatológico que explica el priapismo secundario a reacción leucemoide es una obstrucción intravascular por hiperviscosidad sanguínea, que origina una estasis sanguínea en las venas cavernosas, impidiendo el drenaje de los cuerpos cavernosos. Presentamos un caso de priapismo en un paciente con un cáncer de vejiga localmente avanzado, que se desencadenó por la hiperviscosidad sanguínea producida por una reacción leucemoide paraneoplásica</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;28(7): 539-543, jul.-ago. 2004. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044529</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Priapismo secundario a reacción leucemoide paraneoplásica en paciente con cáncer de vejiga</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11753^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8132^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d325^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8132^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d319^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8132^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8132^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11753^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11753^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
