<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90966</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ogilvie's syndrome, a caesarean complication</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Ogilvie's syndrome is acute colonic pseudo-obstruction without mechanical obstruction, is a tipical complication of caesareas and hips surgery. It is difficult to diagnose, mainly, by having clinic similar to paralytic ileus, but with a much higher gravity. Its complications are ischemia and perforation, which can have when establishing a mortality rate of up to 50%. This is a case with bad evolution after caesarea and that despite the medical treatment is complicated with cecal perforation, finishing in a right hemicolectomy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moliner Renau, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonilla-Musoles, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Aguilar, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camps Selva, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Raga Baixauli, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de Ogilvie es una seudoobstrucción aguda de colón en ausencia de obstrucción mecánica, se trata típicamente de una complicación que aparece tras cirugías, sobretodo de cadera y cesáreas. Es de difícil diagnóstico, sobre todo por tener clínica similar al íleo paralítico, aunque con una gravedad muy superior. Sus complicaciones por excelencia son la isquemia y la perforación, que cuando se establecen pueden tener una mortalidad de hasta el 50%. Se trata de un caso con evolución tórpida poscesárea y que, a pesar del tratamiento médico, se complicó con perforación de ciego, acabando en una hemicolectomía derecha (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);54(10): 537-539, oct. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90966</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Ogilvie: una complicación poscesárea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19127^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23438^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29341^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2625^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19127^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23190^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
