<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119084</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adolescents and self-destructive behaviors: an exploratory analysis of family and individual correlates</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Several studies have shown that as many as 20% of European schooled adolescents report self-destructive thoughts/behaviours. Using multinomial logistic regression analysis, the present study investigated the family and individual variables that predict reports of these behaviours. Three groups, one without reports of self-destructive thoughts/behaviours (NSDTB; n= 998), one with reports of self-destructive thoughts/behaviours (SDTB; n= 268) and a clinical group (CS; n= 42) of adolescents with a mean age of 15.88 (SD= 2.11), participated in the study. Parenting styles, parental attachment, family functioning, satisfaction with family relationships, self-esteem and internalising and externalising symptoms, were analyzed. The findings suggest that increases in mothers&#146; quality of emotional bond, fathers&#146; control and family cohesion and decreases in age and mothers&#146; control lead to a decreased likelihood of belonging to the SDTB group. However, being female, perceiving a high level of mothers&#146; inhibition of exploration and individuality, perceiving a high level of fathers&#146; rejection and having a low satisfaction with family relationships increase the probability of belonging to the CS group</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, Marina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Narciso, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereira, Cícero Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz, Diana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sampaio, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los estudios demuestran que el porcentaje de adolescentes estudiantes que relata pensamientos y conductas autodestructivas es de aproximadamente 20% en toda Europa. Mediante un análisis de regresión logística multinomial, el presente estudio investigó tres grupos de adolescentes (M= 15,88; DT= 2,11), uno sin informe de pensamientos/comportamientos autodestructivos (NSDTB; n= 998), uno con informe de pensamientos/comportamientos autodestructivos (SDTB; n= 268) y un grupo clínico (CS; n= 42). Se evaluaron los estilos parentales, el apego de los padres, el funcionamiento familiar, la satisfacción con las relaciones familiares, autoestima y síntomas interiorizados y exteriorizados. Los hallazgos sugieren que la calidad del vínculo emocional con las madres, el control de los padres, la cohesión familiar y la disminución en la edad llevan a una menor probabilidad de pertenecer al grupo SDTB. Sin embargo, ser mujer, percibir un alto nivel de inhibición de exploración e individualidad de la madre, un alto nivel de rechazo de los padres y una baja satisfacción en las relaciones familiares, aumentan la probabilidad de pertenecer al grupo CS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;21(2): 271-288, mayo-ago. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119084</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los adolescentes y conductas autodestructivas: un análisis exploratorio de los factores individuales y familiares</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29822^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
