<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-18169</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship between coping strategies and psychological well-being in adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Coping strategies used by adolescents may have an effect on their psychological development. This piece of research studied the relationships between coping and psychological well-being and the effect that age and gender had on these variables. The sample was made up of 417 adolescents between 15 and 18 years old. Coping strategies were evaluated by using ACS (Frydenberg &amp; Lewis, 1996a) and well-being by means of the BIEPS (Casullo &amp; Castro, 2000). The results showed that the relationship between age and coping and psychological well-being was not a close one. As to gender, adolescent women used a greater variety of coping strategies and were less skilful in coping with problems than men. Clearer differences with regard to the coping strategies used were established by the level of psychological well-being than by age and gender (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Barrón, Remedios</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casullo, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernabéu Verdú, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montova Castilla, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las estrategias de afrontamiento utilizadas por los adolescentes pueden incidir en su desarrollo psico-lógico. En el presente trabajo se estudió la relación entre el afrontamiento y el bienestar psicológico, así como la incidencia de la edad y el género sobre estas variables. La muestra está formada por 417 adolescentes entre 15 y 18 años. Las estrategias de afrontamiento se evaluaron con el ACS (Frydenberg y Lewis, 1996a) y el bienestar psicológico con el BIEPS (Casullo y Castro, 2000). Los resultados señalan una escasa relación de la edad con el afrontamiento y el bienestar psicológico. En cuanto al género, las mujeres poseen mayor repertorio de estrategias de afrontamiento y menos habilidad para afrontar los problemas que los varones. El nivel de bienestar psicológico establece diferencias más claras respecto a las estrategias de afrontamiento utilizadas que la edad y el género (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);14(2): 363-368, mayo 2002. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-18169</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre estilos y estrategias de afrontamiento y bienestar psicológico en adolescentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23896</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13330^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
