<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138634</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-1959</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Smoking prevalence and smoker profile in the adolescents scholars in the province of Castellon</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to analyze the prevalence of smoking in the adolescents scholars in the province of Castellon. Patients and methods: epidemiologic study carried out in secondary schools, with the help of a questionnaire where in addition to the toxic habits, information on familiar and social environment, global health status and respiratory symptoms; addiction and dependence degree and smoking cessation motivation was collected. Results: 1.088 adolescents with a mean age of 15.94 years participated (46.69% girls and 53.31% boys). The 25.82% were smokers (27.36% girls and 24.48% boys). The mean age of starting smoking was 13.46 years, starting to smoke earlier the girls (13.08 years) than the boys (13.85 years), and earlier between 10-14 years (12.38 years) than between 15-19 years (13.57 years). Higher percentage of familiar and friends smokers was seen within adolescent smokers. As the physic and/or psychic/social/gestural dependence degree to nicotine increases, the motivation degree to stop smoking was smaller and the attitude about cessation was worst. Conclusions: smoking starting is every time at a younger age and earlier in girls than boys, being and association detected between familiar and social environment and the star and maintenance of smoking (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Khalaf-Viciano, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Martínez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Khalaf-Ayash, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fabregat-Agost, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo analizar la prevalencia del tabaquismo en los escolares adolescents de la provincial de Castellón. Pacientes y métodos: estudio epidemiológico realizado en institutos de educación secundaria (curso 2006-2007); se recogió información sobre hábitos tóxicos, entornos familiar y social del adolescente, el estado de salud general y los síntomas respiratorios, el grado de adición y dependencia y la motivación para la cesación tabáquica. Resultados: participaron 1.088 adolescentes de edad media 15,94 años  (46,69% chicas y 53,31% chicos). El 25,82% eran fumadores (27,36% chicas, 24,48% chicos). La edad media de inicio del consumo de tabaco fue de 13,46 años, empezando a fumar antes las chicas (13,08 años) que los chicos (13,85 años), y antes enter 10-14 años (12,38 años) que entre 15-19 años (13,57 años). El porcentaje de familiares y amigos fumadores fue mayor entre los adolescentes fumadores. Al aumentar el grado de dependencia física y/o psíquica/social/gestual a la nicotina, el grado de motivación para dejar de fumar fue menor y la actitud ante el abandono fue peor. Conclusiones: el inicio del consumo de tabaco se da cada vez a edades más tempranas y antes en las chicas que en los chicos, detectándose una asociación entre el entorno familiar y el social y el inicio y mantenimiento del hábito tabáquico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prev. tab;11(1): 10-18, ene.-mar. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138634</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia del tabaquismo y perfil del fumador en los escolares adolescentes de la provincial de Castellón</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51528</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51529</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d301^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
