<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116744</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-3334</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of hope in the social participation of the older adult</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">From a humanist vision, it aims to evaluate the role played by the experience of hope in the social behavior of the older adult. It was used a cross-sectional descriptive correlational design. It were administered a sociodemographic questionnaire, the Test Hope-Hopelessness and the Activities Inventory, to a not probabilistic-accidental sample of150 self-reliance older adults, living in a large urban center of the Argentina Republic. The results from the MANOVA indicated that, with the exception of the cultural-educational activities that involve a higher educational level that was not presented by the majority, the older adults with high levels of hope, compared with those with low-levels, were more involved in other activities, especially in social and spiritual ones. The results are justified in part by the approaches of a positive psychology and the personal strength, and enriches those obtained in other studies on the topic in the field of social psychology of aging (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hermida, Paula Daniela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cófredes, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ofman, Silvia Deborah</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Stefani, Dorina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereyra Girardi, Carolina Iris</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tartaglini, María Florencia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde una visión humanista, se intenta evaluar el papel que cumple la experiencia de esperanza en el comportamiento social del adulto mayor. Se utilizó el diseño descriptivo correlacional, de corte transversal. Un cuestionario sociodemográfico, el Test Esperanza-Desesperanza y el Inventario de Actividades fueron administrados a una muestra no probabilística-accidental de 150 adultos mayores autoválidos, de un gran centro urbano de la República Argentina. Los resultados del MANOVA indicaron que, excepto en las actividades culturales-educacionales, que requieren mayor nivel educativo no presentado por la mayoría, los adultos mayores con alto nivel de esperanza, en comparación con aquellos con bajo nivel, participaron más en otras actividades, destacándose esta diferencia en las sociales y espirituales. Los enfoques de una psicología positiva y de la fortaleza personal justificarían, en parte, los resultados obtenidos, que enriquecerían los de otros estudios sobre el tema en el área de la psicología social de la vejez (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apuntes psicol;31(1): 29-35, ene.-abr. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116744</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de la esperanza en la participación social del adulto mayor</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d20174^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54367^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
