<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053720</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dermoid cyst of the floor of the mouth</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Dermoid cysts are congenital lesions composed of tissues with different origins: ectoblastic, mesoblastic, or endoblastic, caused by a defect in the fusion of the embryonic lateral mesenchymatic mass. A true dermoid cyst is a cavity covered with epithelium showing keratinisation and presenting identifiable dermal appendices.     We present a case of a male patient aged 53 years presenting tumouration on the floor of the mouth with an evolution of about 30 years. A bibliographic revision of this pathology is also presented</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aneiros Fernández, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sainz Quevedo, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo Rojas, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vargas Fernández, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los quistes dermoides son lesiones congénitas constituidas por tejidos de varias procedencias: ectoblástico, mesoblástico o endoblástico. Tienen su origen en un defecto de fusión de las masas mesenquimatosas laterales embrionarias. El quiste dermoide verdadero está recubierto de epitelio que muestra queratinización y tiene apéndices de piel identificables.     Presentamos el caso de un varón de 53 años de edad que presenta una tumoración en suelo de boca de unos 30 años de evolución. Se realiza una revisión bibliográfica de dicha patología</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;58(1): 31-33, ene. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053720</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Quiste dermoide de suelo de boca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22570^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9254^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22570^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3904^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3904^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
