<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122227</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spirometry quality in preschool children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Carrying out quality spirometric maneuvers in preschool children in both the diagnosis and follow-up of respiratory diseases continues to be very scarce. This is due to several reasons, including a lack of consensus on quality criteria and the acceptability of the test. The purpose of this study is therefore to obtain reference norms from a population of healthy preschool children from the Autonomous Community of Navarre (Spain). Method: A total of 114 healthy preschool children aged between 3 and 7 years of age, without prior experience in carrying out lung function tests, were included. Results: A total of 76 were able to realize at least two acceptable spirometric maneuvers, and 60 of them maneuvers that were acceptable and reproducible, according to ATS/ERS criteria. This represents a global success percentage of 59%. The most common failing was premature and brusque termination of the spirometric maneuver, followed by an inadequate peak in breathing. Conclusions: Over half of the preschool children were able to realize quality spirometric maneuvers. Our data make it possible to recommend the proposed quality criteria as being suitable for routine use, and to encourage the use of spirometry in regular clinical practice within the setting of specialized care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Puebla, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olaguíbel Rivera, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esteban Chocarro, B. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cambra Contín, K</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vela Vizcaino, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Uribe San Martín, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: La realización de maniobras espirométricas de calidad en niños preescolares tanto en el diagnóstico como en el seguimiento de enfermedades respiratorias sigue siendo muy escaso, por diversas razones entre las que se encuentran la falta de un consenso en los criterios de calidad y aceptabilidad de la prueba. Por ello, se inició este estudio con el fin de obtener ecuaciones de referencia provenientes de una población de niños preescolares sanos de la Comunidad Foral de Navarra (España). Métodos: Se incluyeron un total de 114 niños preescolares sanos con edades comprendidas entre los 3 y los 7años y sin experiencia previa en la realización de estudios de función pulmonar. Resultados: Un total de 76 fueron capaces de realizar al menos dos maniobras espirométricas de aceptables y de ellos 60 aceptables y reproducibles, de acuerdo a los criterios ATS/ERS, lo cual representa un porcentaje global de éxito de 59%. El fallo más habitual fue la terminación prematura y brusca de la maniobra espirométrica, seguido de un pico espiratorio inadecuado. Conclusiones: Más de la mitad de los preescolares fueron capaces de realizar espirometrías de calidad. Nuestros datos permiten recomendar los criterios de calidad propuestos, como adecuados para su uso rutinario, y fomentar el uso de la espirometría en la práctica clínica habitual, dentro del entorno de la atención especializada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;37(1): 81-89, ene.-abr. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122227</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de la espirometría en preeescolares</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13530^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1969^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12542^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
