<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72880</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-695X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The caregiver burden and its repercussions on quality of life and health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine caregiver burden and its repercussions on quality of life, physical and mentalhealth and social life and the use for healthcare resources (frequency).Design. Observational, analytical, case control study.Setting. Primary Health Care Centre in an urban setting.Participants. The case group was made up of 156 primary caregivers and the control group of 156personas assigned to the Primary Health Care Centre who were not primary care givers. They werepaired by age, gender and number of chronic diseases.Measurements. Clinical and socio-demographic characteristics, caregiver role characteristics (kinship,time performing role of caregiver, etc.), caregiver burden (Zarit scale), frequency, perceived health,subjective quality of life (Nottingham Health Profi le), presence of anxiety and depression symptoms(GADS-18), family functioning (Family APGAR) and perception of family and social support (Duke-UNC questionnaire).Results. According to the Zarit scale, burden was present in 66.4% of caregivers. Compared to31.4% of persons in the control group, 48.1% of caregivers considered their health was poor or verypoor (OR = 2.02; 95% CI: 1.27 &#150; 3.21). The mean frequency in the last year was 8.37 visits/year in thecaregiver group and 7.12 visits/year in the control group (p&lt;0.01). A higher prevalence of anxiety anddepression was observed in the caregiver group, and a greater frequency of possible family dysfunctionand sensation of insuffi cient social support.Conclusions. The results indicate the need for multidisciplinary supportive and preventive interventionsfor caregivers. Such interventions have obtained positive results in several aspects both for thecaregiver and the person cared for person. These interventions need to be adapted to the specifi ccharacteristics and needs of each caregiver(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Gila, M. Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orueta Sánchez, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carmona de la Morena, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Moreno, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Caro, Samuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Oropesa, Arancha</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer la sobrecarga sentida por los cuidadores y las repercusiones que este rol representa sobre su calidad de vida, su salud en las esferas física, psíquica y social y su necesidad deutilización de los recursos sanitarios (frecuentación). Diseño. Estudio observacional y analítico de casos y controles Emplazamiento. Centro de salud de características urbanas.Participantes. El grupo de estudio fue formado por 156 cuidadores principales y el grupo control por 156 personas adscritas al centro de salud que no realizaban funciones de cuidador principal, emparejadas por edad, sexo y número de patologías crónicas padecidas. Mediciones. Características clínicas y sociodemográfi cas, datos relativos al rol de cuidador (parentesco,tiempo de desempeño del rol de cuidador, etc.), sobrecarga del cuidador (escala de Zarit), frecuentación, salud percibida, calidad de vida subjetiva (cuestionario de salud de Nottingham), presencia de sintomatología, ansiedad y depresión (EADG-18), función familiar (APGAR familiar y apoyo social percibido (cuestionario de Duke-UNC).Resultados. El 66,4% de los cuidadores presentaba sobrecarga en el test de Zarit. El 48,1% los cuidadoresrespondió que su salud era mala o muy mala, frente al 31,4% del grupo control (OR = 2,02; IC 95%: 1,27 - 3,21). La frecuentación media en el último año fue de 8,37 visitas/año en el grupo decuidadores y de 7,12 visitas/año en el grupo control (p&lt;0,01). Se observó una mayor prevalencia de ansiedad y depresión en el grupo de cuidadores, así como una mayor frecuencia de posible disfunción familiar y de sensación de apoyo social insufi ciente. Conclusiones. Los resultados indican la necesidad de actuaciones multidisciplinarias encaminadas a apoyar a los cuidadores tanto de forma preventiva como de soporte(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. clín. med. fam;2(7): 332-339, jun.2009. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72880</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El rol de Cuidador de personas dependientes y sus repercusiones sobre su calidad de vida y su salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
