<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056534</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-2597</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Obesity and inflammatory response</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The obesity is the nutrition disturbance more common in developed countries, where it substituted the calorie malnutrition. The effects of calorie malnutrition on immunity were widely studied for many years and it is well-known that contributes to different types of immunodeficiency, enhancing infections and parasitosis. The obesity also impairs the immunity although its effects are less known. Some molecules (adipokines) synthesized in fat tissue participate in inflammation and their plasma levels are modified in obese subjects. Moreover, obesity could increase or disturb the evolution of inflammatory process, including pregnancy, fetal growth or labor. Most available information has been obtained from animal research; nevertheless there are already important data from human clinics suggesting a worse follow-up of chronic inflammation, such as asthma, when it is associated to obesity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blanco Quirós, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La obesidad es la alteración de la nutrición más común en los países desarrollados, donde ha sustituido a la malnutrición calórico-proteica. Los efectos de la malnutrición calórica sobre la inmunidad fueron muy estudiados y se sabe que contribuye a diferentes tipos de inmunodeficiencia, facilitando infecciones y parasitosis. La obesidad también altera la inmunidad, aunque sus efectos son peor conocidos. Algunas moléculas (adipocinas) sintetizadas en el tejido adiposo intervienen en la inflamación y sus niveles se modifican en la obesidad. Por consiguiente, la obesidad podría favorecer o alterar la evolución de procesos inflamatorios, incluyendo el embarazo, parto y el desarrollo fetal. La mayoría de la información disponible procede de la investigación animal, pero ya hay datos clínicos en humanos que sugieren una peor evolución de inflamaciones crónicas, como el asma, cuando se asocian a obesidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Bol. pediatr;47(201): 237-249, jul.-sept. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056534</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Obesidad y respuesta inflamatoria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34404^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34404^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9692^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9692^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
