<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050401</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-3655</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">First program on rational use of antibiotics in Gipuzkoa. Assessment of 1999-2004 period</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Results of the first program on rational use of antibiotics in Gipuzkoa, until the year 2004, are analyzed. This program was set up in 1999 and almost half of the pharmacies in the province have participated in it in a voluntary way. Method: Data were gathered within the pharmacies during one week every three months, and by writing up all the antibiotics, both demanded and dispensed without corresponding prescription, and also some information related to the activity of the pharmacists in the dispensing process. All data were sent to the Gipuzkoa Professional Association. Results: antibiotics&#146; demand without prescription diminished to reach a 3.6% out of the overall antibiotics demand. On the other hand, antibiotics dispensing without the prescription fell until the 1.6% out of the overall antibiotics dispensed. These figures mean that a few antibiotics keep being dispensed without the corresponding prescription. Conclusions: This program achieved a reduction on both the demand and the dispensing of antibiotics without the corresponding prescription. It&#146;s important to keep working on these kind of programs to reinforce the professional role of pharmacists by a more active participation of related organizations, the use of protocols and guidelines, and the possible use of negative incentives (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gastelurrutia, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larrañaga, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: En el presente trabajo se analizan los resultados, hasta el año 2004, del Programa de Uso Racional de Antibióticos que viene realizándose en Gipuzkoa desde el año 1999 y en el que participan de forma voluntaria casi la mitad de las farmacias. Método: La recogida de datos se realiza en las farmacias y consiste en anotar todos los antibióticos solicitados y dispensados sin receta durante una semana cada trimestre, junto a otra información referida a la actuación del farmacéutico. Finalmente se remiten los datos al COF de Gipuzkoa. Resultados: Durante este periodo se ha producido una disminución considerable de la solicitud de antibióticos sin receta, hasta el 3,6% sobre el total de solicitudes de antibióticos. Por su parte, la dispensación de antibióticos sin receta disminuyó de manera significativa, hasta alcanzar el 1,6% del total de dispensaciones de antibióticos. Esto supone que todavía se siguen dispensando antibióticos sin receta. Conclusiones: Este programa ha conseguido disminuir tanto la solicitud como la dispensación de antibióticos sin receta. Es necesario seguir trabajando en este tipo de programas para reforzarla actuación profesional del farmacéutico, mediante la implicación más activa de las instituciones, la utilización de unas guías de actuación y la posible aplicación de incentivos negativos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. pract. (Granada, Internet);4(1): 1-8, ene.-mar. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050401</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Primer programa institucional de uso racional de antibióticos en Gipuzkoa. Evaluación de los años 1999-2004</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4422^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11742^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13037^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
