<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118593</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Multifocal necrotizing fasciitis: presentation of a case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Multifocal necrotizing fasciitis is a condition in which there is more than one non-contiguous body area affected, and it is usually the result of the dissemination of septic emboli. Clinical case. We present a 67 year-old patient, on oral corticosteroid treatment, who was admitted with a septic shock. The previous week he had been operated on due to the perforation of a colon diverticulum. He had signs that suggested necrotizing fasciitis on all four limbs which progressed quickly. Emergency fasciotomies on all limbs were performed, and empirical antibiotic treatment was started. Results. After the surgery the patient improved, and seven days after the debridement, primary closure of the wounds was performed. Tissue cultures were negative. Discussion. Being a rare entity, there is no consensus regarding the management of multifocal necrotizing fasciitis. However, early and aggressive debridement (including fasciotomies and even amputation) and broad-spectrum antibiotics are essential for its treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Noriego-Muñoz, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro-Cano, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La fascitis necrosante multifocal es aquella entidad en la que hay afectada más de un área corporal no contiguas, y que suele ser resultado de la diseminación de émbolos sépticos por vía hematógena. Caso clínico. Paciente de 67 años, en tratamiento corticoideo oral, que presenta un cuadro de shock séptico. La semana anterior había sido sometido a una intervención de urgencia por la perforación de un divertículo colónico. Presentaba signos compatibles con fascitis necrosante en las 4 extremidades que evolucionaron rápidamente. Se decidió la realización urgente de fasciotomías de las 4 extremidades e iniciar tratamiento antibiótico empírico. Resultados. Tras la intervención, el paciente evolucionó favorablemente, y 7 días después del desbridamiento se realizó el cierre primario de las heridas. Los cultivos intraoperatorios fueron negativos. Discusión. Debido a su escasa frecuencia, no existe consenso para el manejo de las fascitis necrotizantes multifocales. Sin embargo, se considera esencial el desbridamiento precoz y la antibioticoterapia de amplio espectro (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);58(1): 60-63, ene.-feb. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118593</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fascitis necrosante multifocal. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32750^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32750^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32750^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13150^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3664^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32750^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13150^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32750^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6590^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
