<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053849</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-1813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Concept maps as a polyvalent educational tool for health sciences. Their application to histology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article analyzes the concept map as a tool for educational strategy applied to health sciences, particularly in the area of histology. After considering the elements that make up these maps, the different types of concept maps and the epistemological basis of maps as instruments to enhance significant learning, the article examines how maps can be used for curriculum development, evaluation, pedagogic design by teachers, and self-learning by students within the context of the Bologna process. With reference to histology, we analyze how different types of maps are used to define and rank concepts, examine the relationship between disciplines and to understand the new paradigm of histology related to tissue engineering (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vicente Crespo, Pascual</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alaminos, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cubero, María Angustias</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Quevedo, María del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente artículo se analiza el mapa conceptual como instrumento de estrategia educativa aplicada a las ciencias de la salud y, especialmente, al ámbito de la histología. Tras considerar los elementos constitutivos y los tipos de mapas conceptuales y el fundamento epistemológico de los mismos para estimular el aprendizaje significativo, se examina la aplicación de los mapas al desarrollo curricular, la evaluación, el diseño pedagógico por parte del profesor y el autoaprendizaje por parte del alumno en el contexto del proceso de Bolonia. En el ámbito de la histología se analiza la utilización de los distintos tipos de mapas para la definición y jerarquización de sus contenidos, su relación con el resto de las disciplinas y su nuevo paradigma vinculado a la Ingeniería tisular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Educ. med. (Ed. impr.);9(2): 51-58, jun. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053849</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El mapa conceptual. Un instrumento educativo polivalente para las ciencias de la salud. Su aplicación en histología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3499</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6812^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
