<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113902</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Betadine® in the care of friction blisters. treatment protocol in primary health care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">First prize in the VII edition of the award winning work Betadine ® for nursing 2012. The dermatitis caused by repeated friction or trauma to the skin are very common in the population, mainly in athletes. The action of shear forces on the skin makes intradermal blisters very painful; being foot the areas more prone to its occurrence and local infection, one of the most common complications during its evolution. The proposed treatment protocol, presents a new technique of cost-effective cure for these injuries from the nursing consultation in Primary Health Care. Currently, there are many techniques in the treatment of these skin changes, but none has established itself as the "gold standard" in its approach. This technique of treatment accelerates regeneration of the injured area, reduces pain, prevents infection and epithelialization time is estimated between four and five days(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Campo, Myriam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González de la Guerra, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Trabajo ganador del primer premio de la VII edición del Premio Betadine® para Enfermería 2012. Trata de cómo las dermatosis producidas por la fricción o traumatismos repetidos sobre la piel son muy frecuentes en la población, principalmente, en los deportistas. La acción de fuerzas de cizallamiento sobre la piel produce ampollas intradérmicas muy dolorosas; siendo los pies las áreas más proclives a su aparición; y la infección local una de las complicaciones más frecuentes durante su evolución. El protocolo de tratamiento planteado expone una nueva técnica basada en el coste-efectividad para estas lesiones, desde la consulta de enfermería en Atención Primaria. En la actualidad existen numerosas técnicas en la cura de estas alteraciones cutáneas, pero ninguna se ha consolidado como el gold standard en su abordaje. Esta técnica de tratamiento acelera la regeneración del área lesionada, disminuye el dolor, previene la infección y el tiempo de epitelización se estima entre cuatro y cinco días(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;36(6): 416-423, jun. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113902</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ampollas por fricción. Tratamiento con betadine® en atención primaria de salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13248^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30722^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1273^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1273^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
