<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115413</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">An experience of mother and daughter in parallel groups</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper presents modality of treatment practiced in the UPPIJ, a public mental health care Ward that provides psychoanalytic psychotherapy for children and adolescents. In this treatment modality children participate in a group whilst their parents participate in another simultaneous group, in the same ward but in a differentiated space. The authors present two complete session transcriptions of each group, and several vignettes, to illustrate how they work and describe the evolution of a little girl and her mother within this specific treatment setting (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sariol, Mercé</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ger, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el marco de la asistencia en salud mental pública y desde la Unidad de Psicoterapia Psicoanalítica Infantil y Juvenil (UPPIJ), presentamos una modalidad de tratamiento en la que los niños se incorporan a un grupo y los padres a otro simultáneo en el mismo lugar y en un espacio diferenciado. Exponemos la trascripción de dos sesiones de cada grupo y varias viñetas que intenta ilustrar la forma de trabajar y la evolución que siguieron una niña y su madre en el dispositivo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(9): 65-77, abr. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115413</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia en grupos paralelos de madre e hija</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12012^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12051^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9227</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
