<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161183</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New tendencies in tissue regeneration: leucocyte-rich platelet-rich fibrin</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Periodontal regeneration is the reproduction or re-enactment of an injured, or lost, part of the periodontium, with the aim of repairing its architecture and main function. The key role of platelets in tissue regeneration has been demonstrated in the last few years. They accelerate healing in both the soft and hard tissues due to the liberation of cytokines and growth factors over a long period. Leucocyte-rich platelet-rich fibrin, used for the first time by Choukroun in 2001, is a second generation platelets extract that is obtained from the patient's own blood, without the need of additives. Its purpose is to attain an autologous fibrin mesh to be used for as a framework for the substances involved in bone regeneration. The purpose of this work is to present a review and an update on the use of this technique (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salgado-García, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arriba-Fuente, Lorenzo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orión Salgado-Peralvo, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La regeneración periodontal es la reproducción o reconstitución de una parte perdida o dañada del periodonto con el fin de restaurar su arquitectura y función. En los últimos años se ha puesto de manifiesto el papel clave que juegan las plaquetas en la regeneración tisular, acelerando la cicatrización tanto de tejidos blandos como duros, mediada por la liberación de citocinas y factores de crecimiento durante un tiempo prolongado. La fibrina rica en plaquetas y leucocitos utilizada por primera vez por Choukroun en el 2001 es un concentrado de plaquetas de segunda generación que se obtiene a partir de la propia sangre del paciente, sin el empleo de aditivos, con el fin de conseguir una malla de fibrina que sirva de andamiaje para las sustancias implicadas en la regeneración. El objetivo de este trabajo es el de realizar una revisión y puesta al día en el uso de esta técnica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;39(2): 91-98, abr.-jun. 2017. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161183</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevas tendencias en regeneración tisular: fibrina rica en plaquetas y leucocitos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1886^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32333^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55011^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1819</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21045^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1696^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22316^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13896^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21045^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8140</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
