<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148480</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnosis and treatment of iron deficiency, with or without anemia, before and after bariatric surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bariatric surgery (BS) is an increasingly used therapeutic option for severe obesity which allows patients to achieve sustained weight loss over time and resolution or improvement in most associated pathological conditions. Major mid- and long-term complications of BS include iron deficiency and iron-deficient anemia, which may occur in up to 50% of cases and significantly impair patient quality of life. These changes may be present before surgery. The aim of this review was to prepare schemes for diagnosis and treatment of iron deficiency and iron-deficient anemia before and after bariatric surgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Ruiz de Gordejuela, Amador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilarrasa, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidal, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bretón, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tinahones, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jericó, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliveira, Ana Carla de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La cirugía bariátrica es una modalidad terapéutica para la obesidad grave que se utiliza cada vez con más frecuencia, y permite que el paciente consiga una pérdida de peso mantenida en el tiempo y una resolución o mejoría de la mayor parte de las enfermedades asociadas. Una de las principales complicaciones a medio y a largo plazo es el déficit de hierro y la anemia ferropénica, que puede afectar hasta al 50% de los casos, y deteriora de manera importante la calidad de vida del paciente. Estas alteraciones pueden estar presentes desde el preoperatorio. El objetivo de la presente revisión es elaborar unos esquemas de diagnóstico y tratamiento del déficit de hierro y la anemia ferropénica en el pre y postoperatorio de la cirugía bariátrica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;63(1): 32-42, ene. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148480</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico y tratamiento del déficit de hierro, con o sin anemia, pre y poscirugía bariátrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32369^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31381^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20180^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16595^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51221^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
