<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79939</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Antifungal activity, cytotoxicity and composition of essential oils from the Asteraceae plant family</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background The plants of the Asteraceae family have been used for medicinal purposes,in traditional Colombian medicine. Aim To evaluate the antifungal activity and the cytotoxic effects of 15 essential oils from plants of the Asteraceae family. Methods Antifungal activity was evaluated against Candida parapsilosis ATCC 22019, Candida krusei ATCC 6258, Aspergillus flavus ATCC 204304 and Aspergillus fumigatus ATCC 204305 following EUCAST and CLSI M38-A standard methods, for yeast and filamentous fungi, respectively. Cytotoxic effect was evaluated on Vero cell line by MTT assay. Results The oils from the plants Achyrocline alata and Baccharis latifolia were the only ones active against A. fumigatus (GM-MIC=78.7 and 157.4mg/ml, respectively). In contrast, there was no evidence of oils active against Candida species. In addition, these oils were not cytotoxic on Vero cells. The oils of A. alata and Baccharis latifolia could be candidates for disinfecting hospital environments and for inhibiting biofilm formation by A. fumigatus Conclusions The oils of A. alata and B. latifolia could be candidates for disinfecting hospital environments and for inhibiting biofilm formation by A. fumigatus(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Stashenko, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zapata, Bibiana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mesa-Arango, Ana Cecilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durán, Camilo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Betancur-Galvis, Liliana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes En la medicina tradicional de Colombia, las plantas de la familia Asteraceae se han utilizado con fines medicinales. Objetivo Evaluar la actividad antimicótica y el efecto citotóxico de 15 aceites esenciales de plantas de la familia Asteraceae. Métodos La actividad antimicótica se evaluó con las cepas Candida parapsilosis ATCC 22019, Candida krusei ATCC 6258, Aspergillus flavus ATCC 204304 y Aspergillus fumigatus ATCC 204305 de acuerdo con las técnicas EUCAST y CLSI M38-A para levaduras y hongos filamentosos, respectivamente. La actividad citotóxica se evaluó mediante la técnica del MTT en la línea celular Vero. Resultados Los aceites de las plantas Achyrocline alata y Baccharis latifolia fueron los únicos activos contra A. fumigatus (media geométrica de la concentración mínima inhibitoria=78,7 y 157,4mg/ml, respectivamente). En contraste, no se evidenció actividad de los aceites contra especies de Candida. Además, estos aceites no fueron citotóxicos en las células Vero. Conclusiones Los aceites de A. alata y B. latifolia podrían ser candidatos para la desinfección de ambientes hospitalarios y para la inhibición de formación de biopelículas por A. fumigatus(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;27(2): 101-103, abr.-jun. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79939</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actividad antimicótica y citotóxica de aceites esenciales de plantas de la familia Asteraceae</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32342^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2207^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3622^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22585^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1237^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33297</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
