<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161261</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Therapeutic aggressiveness and liquid oncology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aggressiveness criteria proposed in the scientific literature a decade ago provide a quality judgment and are a reference in the care of patients with advanced cancer, but their use is not generalized in the evaluation of Oncology Services. In this paper we analyze the therapeutic aggressiveness, according to standard criteria, in 1.001 patients with advanced cancer who died in our Institution between 2010 and 2013. The results seem to show that aggressiveness at the end of life is present more frequently than experts recommend. About 25% of patients fulfill at least one criterion of aggressiveness. This result could be explained by a liquid Oncology which does not prioritize the patient as a moral subject in the clinical appointment. Medical care is oriented to necessities and must be articulated in a model focused on dignity and communication. Its implementation through Advanced Care Planning, consideration of patient&#146;s values and preferences, and Limitation of therapeutic effort are ways to reduce aggressiveness and improve clinical practice at the end of life. We need to encourage synergic and proactive attitudes, adding the best of cancer research with the best clinical care for the benefit of human being, moral subject and main goal of Medicine (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Amor Pan, JR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Calvo, MS</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barón Duarte, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los criterios de agresividad terapéutica publicados hace una década proporcionan un juicio de calidad y son una referencia en la atención de pacientes con cáncer avanzado, pero su utilización no está generalizada en la evaluación de los Servicios de Oncología. En este trabajo analizamos la agresividad terapéutica, según los criterios estándar, en 1.001 pacientes con cáncer avanzado fallecidos en el Complejo Hospitalario Universitario de Santiago de Compostela, entre los años 2010 y 2013. Los resultados parecen demostrar que la agresividad terapéutica al final de la vida en nuestro medio hospitalario está presente con más frecuencia de lo recomendado, ya que el 25% de los pacientes cumple al menos un criterio de agresividad. Este resultado podría explicarse por la presencia de una Oncología líquida que no prioriza al paciente como sujeto moral del encuentro clínico. Los cuidados se dirigen a la atención de las necesidades y deben estar articulados en modelos centrados en la comunicación y en la dignidad. Su aplicación mediante la Planificación Anticipada de los Cuidados, la consideración de los valores y preferencias del paciente y la Limitación del Esfuerzo Terapéutico, son formas de disminuir esta agresividad y mejorar la práctica clínica al final de la vida. Necesitamos plantear actitudes sinérgicas y proactivas, sumando lo mejor de la investigación oncológica con el mejor cuidado y atención clínica en beneficio del ser humano, sujeto moral y finalidad última de la Medicina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad Bioet;28(92): 71-81, ene.-abr. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161261</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La agresividad terapéutica y la oncología líquida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56213^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30048^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14105^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54219^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29924^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1698</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8662^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56213</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4418^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
