<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90221</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Outcomes of a suicide prevention program in the general population. Barcelona dreta eixample district</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective. Suicide and self destructive behaviors are not only health problems but are also related to social and personal aspects. Public health and community action can play an important role in increasing survival among those at risk. We present the results of a program based on health education among the general population and in a specific health care setting to monitor the at risk population. Subjects and Method. The Suicide Behavior Prevention Program (SBPP) developed in the Dreta del&#146;Eixample district in Barcelona city included 219 patients, 148 (67.5%) of whom completed a 12-month follow-up. We selected a comparison group from a neighboring district that did not have a SBPP. This group was made up of 180 patients, 167 of whom completed the 12-monthfollow-up. Results. Main differences between the two groups were that patients who were enrolled in the SBPP consulted more often for suicidal thoughts than those in the comparative group (36% vs 25%), had fewer hospital admissions (6% vs 36%), presented fewer repeated suicide attempts over the 12-month follow-up (11% vs 32%) and showed longer time to repeat attempt. Conclusions. Early detection of suicidal ideation and adherence to post-suicide attempt treatment reduce the risk of recurrent suicide attempts. Further studies with longer follow up may help to reduce suicide mortality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Faus, Gustavo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solà, Ivan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejedor, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: el suicidio y las conductas autodestructivas son en parte un problema sanitario pero también social y personal. En este sentido, la actuación desde la salud pública y comunitaria es importante para aumentar la supervivencia de las personas en riesgo suicida. El objetivo de este trabajo es mostrar algunos resultados de un programa basado en la educación sanitaria de la población general y el establecimiento de circuitos asistenciales específicos para el seguimiento de esta población de riesgo. Material y método: El Programa de Prevención de la Conducta Suicida (PPCS), llevado a cabo en el distrito de la Dretade l&#146;Eixample de Barcelona, incluyó a 219 pacientes de los que 148 (67,5%) completaron el seguimiento al año. Se seleccionó un grupo de comparación de 180 pacientes, procedentes de otros distritos colindantes en los que no se realizaba el PPCS, 167 de los cuales completaron el seguimiento. Resultados: en las comparaciones de ambos grupos las principales diferencias significativas fueron que los pacientes que entran en el PPCS consultaron más frecuentemente por ideas suicidas que el de comparación (36 % vs 25%), presentaron menos ingresos hospitalarios (6% vs 36%), repitieron menos tentativas suicidas al año de seguimiento (11%vs 32%) y el tiempo hasta la repetición fue mayor. Conclusiones: La detección precoz de las ideas suicidas y la adherencia a la terapia post-tentativa, como se observa en los pacientes del PPCS, disminuye las recidivas. Se requieren nuevos estudios más prolongados que reduzcan también la mortalidad suicida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;39(5): 280-287, sept.-oct. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90221</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados del programa de prevención de la conducta suicida. Distrito de la Dreta de l&#146;Eixample de Barcelona</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13792^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13791^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13791^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13792^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13791^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13792^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13791^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
