<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111949</identifier>
<setSpec>1697-641X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Update in endodontic microbiology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Microbiological agents are essential in the progression and perpetuation of periradicular inflammatory pathologies. Within these, bacteria constitute the most prevalent flora. For a canal to become infected, the pulp must be necrotic and the microorganisms must adhere to the tissues and multiply insufficient quantity, with the interaction being important, therefore, between the host and the infectious dose. The specific associations that are implied in the pathogenesis of the periradicular disease are still unknown, but it is accepted that the most frequently isolated species should have a greater contribution in the degree of pathogenicity. The different forms of periradicular disease maybe classified as different microbial aetiologies. The types of endodontic infections (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Flores García, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valencia de Pablo, Oliver</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Algar Pinilla, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estévez Luaña, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Alfayate, Ruth</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cisneros Cabello, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los agentes microbiológicos son esenciales en la progresión y perpetuación de la patología inflamatoria perirradicular. Dentro de éstos, las bacterias constituyen la flora más prevalente. Para que un conducto se infecte, la pulpa debe estar necrótica y los microorganismos deben adherirse a los tejidos y multiplicarse en cantidad suficiente, siendo por tanto importante la interacción entre el hospedador y la dosis de infección. Las asociaciones específicas que están implicadas en la patogénesis de la enfermedad perirradicular aún son desconocidas, pero se acepta que las especies aisladas más frecuentemente deben tener una mayor contribución en el grado de patogenicidad. Las diferentes formas de enfermedad perirradicular pueden tener etiologías microbianas distintas. Los tipos de infección endodóntica (primaria, secundaria y persistente) se asocian con diferentes condiciones clínicas. Las infecciones extrarradiculares pueden catalogarse como cualquiera de las anteriores, y están cobrando mucha importancia, por la resistencia que presentan al (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cient. dent. (Ed. impr.);10(1): 27-39, ene.-abr. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111949</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actualización en microbiología endodóntica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12765^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30421^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10673^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3803^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3801^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
