<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-64865</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">High flow priapism occurs mainly as a result of a posttraumatic arteriocavernous fistula. Treatment aims to seal the fistula without damaging erectile function. Of all the available treatments, supraselective embolization of the lacerated artery achieves optimal sealing of the fistula with minimal damage to the surrounding tissues. There is no consensus regarding the best materials to be used. Although reabsorbable materials have traditionally been the most commonly used, it is also possible to achieve adequate resolution of the priapism with adequate conservation of erectile function using non-reabsorbable materials, especially microcoils. We describe two cases of patients with high flow priapism caused by bilateral arteriocavernous fistulas treated using microcoil embolization (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lloret, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Noguera, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bilbao, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Cuesta, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El priapismo de alto flujo se produce principalmente por una fístula arteriocavernosa postraumática. El objetivo del tratamiento es el sellado de la fístula sin causar daños sobre la función eréctil. De todos los tratamientos disponibles, la embolización supraselectiva de la arteria lacerada consigue un óptimo sellado de la fístula con mínimo daño a los tejidos circundantes. Existe controversia acerca de qué materiales deben ser usados. A pesar de que tradicionalmente han sido los materiales reabsorbibles los más utilizados y recomendables, es posible usar material no reabsorbible, sobre todo microcoils, con una adecuada resolución del priapismo y una adecuada conservación de la función eréctil. Exponemos dos casos de pacientes con priapismo de alto flujo por fístulas arteriocavernosas bilaterales que fueron tratados mediante embolización con microcoils (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);50(2): 163-167, mar. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-64865</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10606^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29321^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4695^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11753^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1696^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
