<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-27882</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Malformations of cortical development and their clinical repercussions in a series of 144 cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To show the disorders of the brain cortical development and the possible origin in base to a large series studied in a Pediatric Neurology service. Patients and methods. A series of 144 children with ages ranging between newborn and 12 years was studied from the clinic, image (MR, 3DMR) and evolutive point of views. Results. The diagnosis was: polymicrogyria in 61 cases, lissencephaly in 22, eschizencephaly in 16, heterotopia in 16, cortical dysplasia in 9, hemimegalencephaly in 8, cobblestone in 7, sublobar dysplasia in 3, and &#145;double cortex&#146; in 2. Mental retardation, motor disorders and epilepsy were the most important anomalies. Conclusions. Actually, the image is the most important study to make the diagnosis of every type of cerebral malformation. However, to know the specific gene that origin every disorder seems to be the most important thing to make the classification of every malformative type and the possible prevention of this pathology (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Hacer una exposición de los trastornos del desarrollo cortical del cerebro y de las posibles causas originarias aprovechando una importante casuística estudiada por un único servicio de Neurología Pediátrica. Pacientes y métodos. Son 144 niños de edades comprendidas entre recién nacidos y 12 años. Se estudiaron desde el punto de vista clínico, de imagen (RM y RM3D) y evolutivo. Resultados. Se diagnosticaron 61 casos de polimicrogiria, 22 lisencefalias, 16 esquisencefalias, 16 heterotopias, nueve displasias corticales, ocho hemimegalencefalias, siete displasias complejas de tipo empedrado (cobblestones), tres displasias sublobares y dos con `doble corteza'. En casi todos los tipos de anomalías, las alteraciones más importantes eran retraso psicomotor, trastornos motores y epilepsia. Conclusiones. Actualmente, la imagen es fundamental para identificar el tipo de marformación cortical, pero el conocimiento del gen específico que da origen a cada trastorno parece que será la clave de las clasificaciones sobre los diferentes tipos de malformación y de la posible prevención de esta patología (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;37(4): 327-344, ago. 2003. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Malformaciones del desarrollo cortical y su repercusión clínica en una serie de 144 casos</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Pascual Pascual, SI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palencia, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual Castroviejo, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viaño, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-27882</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29482</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2579</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1953</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29918</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14121</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
