<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107005</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">IT Program for Use in Methodology Observacional</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">HOISAN tool (Tool Observation Social Interaction in Natural Environments) is a software application that enables the encoding, recording, description and handling of recordings or viewing in real time from one or more cameras. Can work with all data types: sequences of events, states, mixed, time intervals and multimodal events. The observational record metrics and measures used parameters derived from primary or secondary. It has the ability to analyze verbal output and calculate different types of agreement and correlation indexes. The program supports data exchange with specific programs for use in observational methodology (SDIS-GSEQ,OBSERVER, THEME and MOTS), other general programs (spread sheets, statistical packages, word processors), and programs for the analysis qualitative(Atlas.ti) and export of data to PDF. In this paper we present also the results of quality analysis of the data belonging to an observation tool for football 7 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López López, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Sánchez, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Mendo, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castellano Paulis, Julen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastrana Brincones, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La herramienta HOISAN (Herramienta de Observación de las Interacciones Sociales en Ambientes Naturales) es una aplicación informática que permite la codificación, registro, descripción y manipulación de grabaciones o del visionado en tiempo real desde una o varias cámaras. Permite trabajar con todos los tipos de datos: secuencias de eventos, de estados, mixtas, de intervalos de tiempo y de eventos multimodales. La métrica del registro observacional utiliza parámetros primarios y medidas derivadas o secundarias. Tiene la capacidad de analizar la producción verbal, así como de calcular distintos tipos de acuerdo e índices de correlación. El programa admite el intercambio de datos con programas específicos de uso en Metodología Observacional (SDIS-GSEQ, OBSERVER, THEME y MOTS),otros programas de carácter general (hojas de cálculo, paquetes estadísticos, procesadores de textos), y programas para el análisis cualitativo (Atlas.ti)y la exportación de los datos a PDF. En este trabajo se presentan, además, los resultados de un análisis de calidad del dato pertenecientes a una herramienta de observación para el fútbol 7 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;12(1): 55-78, ene.-jun. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107005</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">HOISAN 1.2: Programa informático para uso en Metodología Observaciona</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33183</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19402</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
