<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165350</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Body composition of patients with autism spectrum disorder through bioelectrical impedance</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Autism spectrum disorder (ASD) is a neurodevelopmental disorder characterized by deficits in sociability, communication, and limited repertoire of interests and behaviors. Objectives: We aimed to investigate the nutritional status through bioelectrical impedance analysis (BIA) and antrophometrics variables in 63 ASD children and adolescents (10.5 ± 4.1 years; 81% male). Materials and methods: Anthropometric variables were weight, height, and waist circumference (WC); body composition (fat mass, fat free mass) and phase angle (PA) were obtained through BIA. Results: The body mass index showed a prevalence of overweight, obesity and underweight of 38.9, 36.5 and 15.8%, respectively. According to the body fat percentual, obesity prevalence was 49.2%, and 49.2% showed WC &gt; 80th percentile for age. Eleven patients presented lower PA values than references. Conclusion: According to the these parameters, a large percentual of ASD children and adolescents in this sample had total overweight and obesity and truncal adiposity, which causes concern, as well as the percentage of underweight participants (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Slongo Faccioli, Larissa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schweigert Perry, Ingrid</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro, Kamila</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baronio, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riesgo, Rudimar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gottfried, Carmem</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: el trastorno del espectro autista (TEA) es un trastorno neurológico caracterizado por deficiencias en la sociabilidad y la comunicación, y un repertorio limitado de intereses y comportamientos. Objetivos: investigar el estado nutricional por medio del análisis de impedancia bioeléctrica (BIA) y variables antropométricas en 63 niños y adolescentes con TEA (10,5 ± 4,1 años, 81% hombres). Material y métodos: las variables antropométricas fueron el peso, la altura y la circunferencia de la cintura (CC); la composición corporal (masa grasa, masa magra) y el ángulo de fase (PA) se obtuvieron por medio de BIA. Resultados: el índice de masa corporal mostró una prevalencia del sobrepeso, la obesidad y el bajo peso de 38,9, 36,5 y 15,8%, respectivamente. De acuerdo con el porcentaje de grasa corporal, la prevalencia de obesidad fue del 49,2%, y el 49,2% mostró CC &gt; percentil 80 para la edad. Once pacientes presentaron valores de PA inferiores a las referencias. Conclusión: de acuerdo con estos parámetros, un gran porcentaje de niños y adolescentes TEA en esta muestra presentaba adiposidad total de sobrepeso y obesidad y del tronco, lo que causa preocupación, así como el porcentaje de participantes con bajo peso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;34(4): 875-879, jul.-ago. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165350</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Composición corporal por medio de la impedancia bioeléctrica de los pacientes con trastorno del espectro autista</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16508^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56096^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50314</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56096^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
