<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142520</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Association between childhood obesity and oral hygiene status</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The purpose of this study was to evaluate the oral hygiene status in pediatric obese patients. Methods: A cross-sectional study was conducted from 2011 to 2012, which evaluated 180 Brazilian pediatric patients, 6-14 years old, girls and boys, recruited according to two Body Mass Index (BMI) categories: obese and non-obese (healthy weight). For the evaluation the oral hygiene status, the study used Oral Hygiene Index (OHI) and Gingival Bleeding Index (GBI). Results: According to the total sample, 5/60 obese (8.3%) and 57/120 non-obese (47.5%) had good OHI, while 23/60 obese (38.4%) and 3/120 non-obese (2.5%) were classified in a low level of OHI, with a significance between the groups (p &lt; 0.001), even after sorting by age. According to the classification of GBI, 60/60 obese (100.0%) and 89/120 non-obese (74.2%) had GBI 1 (bleeding gingiva), and 0/60 obese and 31/120 non-obese (25.8%) were classified as GBI 0 (healthy gingiva), with a significance between the groups (p &lt; 0.001), even after sorting by age. Conclusions: This study indicated that OHI and GBI were significantly higher in the obese children group (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oliveira, Thaís Feitosa Leitão de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarmento, Viviane Almeida</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferraz, Eduardo Gomes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Magalhães, Juliana Cunha</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paraguassú, Gardênia Matos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos, Elisângela de Jesus</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boa-Sorte, Ney</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva, Luciana Rodrigues</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El propósito de este estudio fue evaluar el estado de higiene oral en pacientes pediátrica con obesidad. Métodos: Un estudio transversal realizado en Brasil en el período 2011-2012, que evaluó 180 pacientes pediátricos de 6 a 14 años, niños y niñas, reclutados en el Índice de Masa Corporal (IMC) y separados en dos categorías: obesos y no obesos (peso saludable). Para evaluar el estado de la higiene oral, el estudio utilizó Índice de Higiene Oral (OHI) y índice de sangrado gingival (GBI). Resultados: De acuerdo con la muestra total, 5/60 obesos (8,3%) y 57/120 no obesos (47,5%) tuvieron buena OHI, mientras que 23/60 obesos (38,4%) y 3/120 no obesos (2,5%) fueron clasificado en un nivel bajo de OHI, con una significación entre los grupos (p &lt; 0,001), incluso después de la clasificación por edades. De acuerdo con la clasificación de GBI, 60/60 obesos (100,0%) y 89/120 no obesos (74,2%) tenían GBI 1 (gingiva sangrante), y 0/60 obesos y 31/120 no obesos (25,8%) fueron clasificados como GBI 0 (gingiva sana), con una significación entre los grupos (p &lt; 0,001), incluso después de la clasificación por edades. Conclusiones: Este estudio indicó que OHI y GBI fueron significativamente mayores en el grupo de niños obesos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;30(2): 253-259, ago. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142520</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asociación entre la obesidad infantil y el estado de higiene oral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55220^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27736</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
