<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161345</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Advances research in the treatment and diagnosis of smoking</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">At the present time, the tobacco abstinence rates increase up to 50% with the therapeutic arsenal available, in the best-case scenario. That is why we are in the need for new treatments that achieve higher abstinence rates per year, given that smokers who remain are those with greater dependence. Also, we must give a thorough look into new possibilities for varenicline. There are on-going investigations searching for new therapeutic targets such as agonists and antagonists of GABA and glutamate, acetylcholine receptors, serotonin agonists, selective inhibitors of monoamine oxidase, and noradrenergic agonists. Moreover, the electronic cigarette requires a position at the present time as a treatment for smoking cessation, and other therapeutic approaches like magnetic intracranial stimulation, mindfulness or nicotine vaccine should be explored as well, added to seeking biomarkers in order to obtain higher abstinence with all these combined (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Segrelles-Calvo, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solano-Reina, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>De Granda-Beltrán, AM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Ruiz, CA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>De Granda-Orive, JI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Padilla, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el momento actual con el arsenal terapéutico disponible para ayudar a dejar de fumar las tasas de abstinencia se elevan hasta el 50% en el mejor de los casos. Es por ello que estamos en la necesidad de buscar nuevos tratamientos que consigan mejorar las tasas de abstinencia al año, teniendo en cuenta que los fumadores que van quedando son aquellos con una mayor dependencia. Debemos ahondar en el análisis de nuevas posibilidades con la vareniclina. Disponemos de investigación activa en la búsqueda de nuevas dianas terapéuticas como son los agonistas y antagonistas del GABA y del glutamato, receptores de acetilcolina, agonistas serotoninérgicos, inhibidores selectivos de la monoaminooxidasa, y agonistas noradrenérgicos. Por otra parte, el cigarrillo electrónico requiere posicionarse en el momento actual como tratamiento para dejar de fumar, debiendo profundizar en la investigación de las posibilidades de la estimulación intracraneal magnética, el mindfullness y la vacuna antinicotina, además de buscar biomarcadores que consigan unidos una mayor abstinencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;73(1): 57-65, ene.-mar. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161345</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Avances y líneas de investigación en el tratamiento y diagnóstico del tabaquismo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30151^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29815^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29291^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29537^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
