<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73124</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Children are the population group who most need photo protection. They are very sensitiveto the negative consequences of an excessive sun exposure, and they aren&#146;t aware of therisk. Children have much more open air activity than adults, and the exposure to ultravioletradiation and sun burns in childhood are a risk factor of the utmost importance in the developmentof skin cancer in adulthood.It is therefore of vital relevance to protect the child from the deleterious effects of ultravioletradiation.The photo protection measures include sun avoidance, protection with cloths, caps andsolar glasses, and the use of photo protection ointments.Sun education campaigns should be implemented in hospitals, schools and communicationmedia, and with dermatologists, pediatricians, teachers and political referents altogether(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Balbín Carrero, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernanz Hermosa, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chavarría Mur, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mauleón Fernández, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cueva Dobao, P de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valdivielso Ramos, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los niños son el grupo poblacional en el que más debe extremarse la fotoprotección. Sonmuy sensibles a los efectos negativos derivados de una exposición solar excesiva, y no sonconscientes de este riesgo. Los niños desarrollan una actividad al aire libre mucho más importanteque los adultos, y la exposición a la radiación ultravioleta y las quemaduras durantela infancia son un factor de riesgo fundamental para el desarrollo de cáncer cutáneo en laedad adulta.Es por tanto de vital importancia proteger al niño de los efectos nocivos de la radiación ultravioleta.Las medidas de fotoprotección incluyen las conductas de evitación solar, la proteccióncon ropa, gorros y gafas solares, y el uso de cremas fotoprotectoras.Las campañas de educación solar deben desarrollarse en los hospitales, en los colegios, yen los medios de comunicación, de forma conjunta entre dermatólogos, pediatras, profesoresy responsables gubernamentales(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;11(42): 313-324, abr.-jun. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73124</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fotoprotección en la infancia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32513</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13860^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13859^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14865^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4862^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34640^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34640^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
