<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166347</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of The FIFA 11(R) training program on stamina strength, flexibility and balance in female soccer players aged 14 -18 years</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the impact of The FIFA 11(R) training programme on stamina strength, flexibility and balance in female soccer players aged 14-18years. Material and method: A quasi-experimental study design was conducted with female soccer players aged 14-18years from two sports training clubs in the city of Manizales (Colombia). Both, the control group (Club A) and the experimental group (Club B) had 20 participants. The control group underwent a conventional training program, whereas the experimental group additionally underwent The FIFA 11(R) training programme. The impact of these programmes was determined on physical capacity variables such as muscle strength, flexibility and balance. This was done through 1-minute paravertebral testing, 1-minute abdominals testing, and Wells and Flamenco tests. Homogeneity tests for related and independent samples were conducted as well. Results: Pre-post intervention measures of change were higher in the experimental group in all functional tests. However, 1-minute abdominals test and Wells test (P&lt;.05) exhibited a significant difference between both groups. Conclusions: The FIFA 11(R) training programme, combined with a conventional training programme, proved more effective in improving flexibility and abdominal strength-resistance in female soccer players aged 14-18years, in contrast to a conventional training programme (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Solano, KB</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montealegre-Mesa, LM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Parra, JE</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar los efectos del programa de entrenamiento Los 11 FIFA(R) sobre la fuerza resistencia, la flexibilidad y el equilibrio en mujeres futbolistas de 14 a 18años. Material y método: Se realizó un estudio cuasi-experimental con mujeres futbolistas de 14 a 18años de dos clubes de formación deportiva de la ciudad de Manizales (Colombia). Tanto el grupo control (Club A) como el grupo experimental (Club B) contaban con 20 participantes. Al grupo control se le realizó un programa de entrenamiento convencional, mientras que al grupo experimental adicionalmente se le realizó el programa de entrenamiento Los 11 FIFA(R). Se determinó el efecto de estos programas sobre variables de capacidad física como la fuerza resistencia, la flexibilidad y el equilibrio mediante las pruebas de paravertebrales en un minuto, abdominales en un minuto, test de Wells y Flamenco. Se realizaron pruebas de homogeneidad para muestras relacionadas e independientes. Resultados: En todas las pruebas funcionales, las medidas de cambio pretest y postest fueron superiores en el grupo experimental. Sin embargo, la diferencia entre grupos resultó significativa solamente en las pruebas de abdominales en un minuto y en el test de Wells (p&lt;0,05). Conclusiones: El programa de entrenamiento Los 11 FIFA(R), combinado con un programa de entrenamiento convencional, mostró ser más efectivo para mejorar la flexibilidad y la fuerza resistencia de abdominales en mujeres futbolistas de 14 a 18años respecto a un programa de entrenamiento convencional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);39(5): 202-208, sept.-oct. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166347</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos del programa de entrenamiento Los 11 FIFA(R) sobre la fuerza resistencia, la flexibilidad y el equilibrio en mujeres futbolistas de 14 a 18 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30732^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29097^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4936^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28453^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
