<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167310</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-654X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cost-effectiveness of using recombinant human thyroid-stimulating hormone before radioiodine ablation for thyroid cancer treatment in Spanish hospitals</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. In thyroid cancer treatment, the thyroid-stimulating hormone (TSH) must be elevated before radioiodine ablation, either by exogenous (with recombinant human thyrotropin [rhTSH]) or endogenous stimulation by thyroid hormone withdrawal (THW). The use of rhTSH avoids hypothyroidism and favours the subsequent elimination of radioiodine, but involves the cost of the product. For this reason, a cost-effectiveness analysis was performed, taking into account all costs involved and the benefits associated with the use of this therapy. Material and methods. Using a Markov modelling with two analysis arms (rhTSH and THW), stratified into high (100mCi/3700 MBq) and low (30mCi/1110 MBq) radioiodine doses, and using 17 weekly cycles, the incremental cost per quality-adjusted life-year (QALY) related to the use of rhTSH was determined. The clinical inputs included in the model were based on published studies and in a treatment survey conducted in Spain. Results. Radioablation preparation with rhTSH is superior to THW, showing additional benefits (0.048 AVAC), as well as cost savings (&#150;&#128;614.16), with an incremental cost-effectiveness rate (ICER) of &#150;&#128;12,795/QALY. The univariate and multivariate sensitivity analyses showed the result to be robust. Conclusions. The use of rhTSH previous to radioablation in Spain has cost savings, as well as a series of health benefits for the patient, making it highly cost-effective (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vallejo, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muros, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Previo a la ablación con radioyodo en el tratamiento del cáncer de tiroides, se necesita aumentar los niveles de tirotropina (TSH) mediante estimulación exógena (con tirotropina humana recombinante [rhTSH]) o endógena, retirando la terapia con hormona tiroidea (THW). La utilización de rhTSH evita el hipotiroidismo y favorece la eliminación posterior de radioyodo pero supone un coste del producto. Por tanto, era necesario realizar un análisis de coste-efectividad que tuviera en cuenta todos los costes y los beneficios de la utilización de esta terapia. Material y métodos. Mediante un modelo de Markov con 2 brazos de análisis (rhTSH y THW), estratificado en dosis altas (100mCi/3.700 MBq) y bajas (30mCi/1.110 MBq) de radioyodo, y utilizando 17 ciclos semanales se determinó el coste incremental por años de vida ajustados por calidad (AVAC) asociados a la utilización de rhTSH. Los parámetros clínicos incluidos en el modelo se basan en estudios publicados y en una encuesta realizada en España. Resultados. La preparación con rhTSH para la radioablación es superior a la THW, presentando beneficios adicionales (0,048AVAC) a la vez que un ahorro en costes (&#150;614,16&#128;), con un ratio de coste-efectividad incremental (ICER) de &#150;12.795&#128;/AVAC. Los análisis de sensibilidad univariantes y multivariantes demuestran que el resultado es consistente. Conclusiones. La utilización de rhTSH previa a la radioablación en España supone un ahorro de costes a la vez que una serie de beneficios de salud para el paciente, por lo que es altamente coste-efectiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. med. nucl. imagen mol. (Ed. impr.);36(6): 362-370, nov.-dic. 2017. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167310</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Coste-efectividad de la utilización de la tirotropina recombinante humana previa a la ablación con radioyodo en el tratamiento del cáncer de tiroides en hospitales españoles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22696^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7217^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22696^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33090^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28629</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7217^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50303</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22696^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22697^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30313^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
