<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82157</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ethnocultural identity at the multiplying agents training/education on maternal and child health and nutrition in an indians group of the Wixarika ethnia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: This is a research article about culture on maternal and child health and nutrition in an Indian group of the Wixarika ethnia Methods: Based on action-oriented participant research methodology, qualitative research techniques, like deep interviews and ethnographic observation were used to construct a proposal of ethnocultural education of indegenous multiplying agents and establish an intercultural program of surveillance and self health care at this vulnerable group. The educational process it is sustained on the conscience pedagogy. Results: Due to the prolonged breast-feeding, pregnancy is detected late. Pregnant women do not have particular feeding practices other than non-pregnant. Few women are handled in prenatal care. Breastfeeding is by spontaneous demand and long-lasting, usually determined with the birth of another brother. From the retrieved data and discussion with community leaders, an ethno-cultural model for training multipliers in maternal and child health care, food safety and nutrition. Conclusions: We concluded that this model of investigation is useful to create programs on maternal and child health and nutrition based on Wixarika group cosmovision, strengthening their ethnical identity(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Crocker-Sagástume, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Serrano, V. G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez-Castellanos, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Se investiga la cultura en nutrición y cuidado de la salud maternoinfantil de la etnia wixárika. Métodos: Basándonos en la metodología de investigación acción participativa se han utilizado técnicas cualitativas de entrevistas en profundidad y observación etnográfica, con el propósito de construir una propuesta de formación etnocultural de multiplicadores indígenas y establecer un programa intercultural de vigilancia y autocuidado de la salud de este grupo vulnerable. El proceso educativo está sustentado en la pedagogía concientizadora. Resultados: Debido a la lactancia materna prolongada el embarazo es detectado tardíamente. Las mujeres embarazadas no tienen una alimentación especial diferente a la de las no embarazadas. Pocas mujeres son atendidas en su control prenatal. La lactancia materna es por demanda espontánea y de larga duración, determinada generalmente con el nacimiento de otro hermano. A partir de los datos recuperados y su discusión con los líderes comunitarios, se desarrolla un modelo etnocultural para la formación de multiplicadores en el cuidado de la salud maternoinfantil y seguridad alimentaria y nutricional. Conclusiones: Se concluye que este modelo de investigación es útil para generar programas de salud y nutrición maternoinfantil basado la cosmovisión del pueblo wixárika, fortaleciendo su identidad étnica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;16(2): 105-110, abr.-jun.2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82157</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La identidad etnocultural en la formación de multiplicadores en salud y nutrición maternoinfantil con el pueblo wixárika</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28488</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16570^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5663</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52507^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52507^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16573</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3490</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52507^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
