<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047442</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diode laser therapy in retinopathy of prematurity: More than a decade of experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Retinopathy of prematurity (ROP) is one of the most important causes of blindness in childhood. The introduction of diode laser has represented a significant advance in its treatment. The aim of the present study was to evaluate our results in the treatment of this entity after more than a decade of experience.                 Patients and methods: One hundred eighty-two eyes in 92 premature infants with ROP treated with diode laser in the Hospital Universitario Miguel Servet from 1992 to 2003 were studied. The characteristics of the population (gestational age, birth weight, sex, stage and affected zone) and treatment outcomes were analyzed. The change in the criteria indicating this treatment was also analyzed.                 Results: In the treated population, mean gestational age (27.9 weeks) and birth weight (1015.9 g) were similar to those in other published studies. A favorable outcome was achieved in 169 of the 182 cases (92.8 %). The change in criteria increased the proportion of favorable outcomes to 96.1 %.                 Discussion: Diode laser therapy is currently the treatment of choice in ROP. This treatment, based on guidelines for earlier intervention, provide greater efficacy without increasing morbidity</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferrer Novella, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rebaje Moisés, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayoral Masana, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marco Tello, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Viejo,  I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pueyo Royo, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: La retinopatía del prematuro (ROP) constituye una de las causas más importantes de ceguera en la infancia. La introducción del láser diodo ha constituido un avance significativo en su tratamiento. El presente estudio pretende evaluar nuestros resultados en el tratamiento de esta patología, con más de una década de experiencia.                 Pacientes y métodos: Se han estudiado 182 ojos de 92 prematuros con ROP tratados con láser diodo en el Hospital Universitario Miguel Servet desde 1992 hasta 2003. Se analizan las características de la población (edad gestacional, peso al nacimiento, sexo, estadio y zona de la enfermedad) y el resultado del tratamiento. Se evalúa además el cambio en los criterios de indicación del mismo.                 Resultado: La población tratada tiene una media de edad gestacional (27,9 semanas) y peso al nacimiento (1.015,9 g) similares a las de otros autores. Se ha logrado evolución favorable en 169 de 182 casos (92,8 %). Con el cambio en los criterios ha aumentado la proporción de evoluciones favorables al 96,1 %.                 Discusión: Actualmente el láser diodo es el tratamiento de elección en la ROP. El tratamiento, basándose en pautas de actuación más precoces, proporciona mayor eficacia sin aumentar la morbilidad</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);64(4): 336-340, abr. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047442</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento con láser diodo en la retinopatía del prematuro: más de una década de experiencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12581^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30674</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22228</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
