<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165279</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The integration of research and practice in sport psychology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">From the consolidation of the psychology of sport as an independent scientific discipline at an international level, a great advance was developed that also favored the consolidation of the applied field and the intervention, into two distinct political-geographic areas: the Eastern countris and the Western block. In both the performances began with the elite sport, and the figure of the psychologist as a member of the sports teams. In 1979 the publication of Rainer Martens' article On Jackets and Jocks (Martens, 1979) mobilized the reflection of both researchers and applied psychologists. From its publication to the present day, this text became a reference text, especially when it came to direct interventions with athletes, and led to a reflection on the methodological difference between research and direct intervention. However, previously, in 1987, Martens himself had recommended and warned of the need to establish links between both spheres, academic and applied, to strengthen and give consistency to the psychology of sport (Garcia-Ucha and Martinez, 2014) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Fernández, Jerónimo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llames Lavandera, Rosana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Gavira, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Villalba, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A partir de la consolidación de la Psicología del Deporte como disciplina científica independiente a nivel internacional, se desarrolló un gran avance que favoreció también la consolidación del ámbito aplicado y de intervención, con dos áreas político-geográficas diferenciadas: los países del Este y el bloque occidental. En ambos se iniciaron actuaciones directas con el deporte de élite, y la figura del psicólogo como miembro del staff en los equipos deportivos fue estabilizándose. En 1979 la publicación del artículo de Rainer Martens, About smocks and jocks (Martens, 1979), movilizó la reflexión tanto de investigadores como de psicólogos aplicados. Desde su publicación hasta la actualidad, este texto se convirtió en un texto de referencia, especialmente a la hora de plantear intervenciones directas con deportistas, y propició que se estableciera una reflexión sobre la diferencia metodológica que debía darse entre investigación e intervención directa. Sin embargo ya anteriormente, en 1987, el propio Martens había recomendado y alertado de la necesidad de establecer nexos entre ambos ámbitos, académico y aplicado, para fortalecer y otorgar consistencia a la psicología del deporte (García-Ucha, y Martínez, 2014) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;26(supl.4): 1-4, 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165279</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La integración de la investigación y la práctica en psicolgía del deporte</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13421^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11799^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36312</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56106^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
