<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163909</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Selective arterial embolization as a therapeutic alternative in the management of puerperal dissecting haematoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Most puerperal haematomas are produced by lacerations or tears as a result of birth trauma and rarely have significant maternal consequences. These hematomas can sometimes expand and dissect surrounding tissues, becoming a potentially serious obstetric complication. Although early diagnosis and treatment is necessary, the management of these entities remains controversial and there is no conclusive evidence on the benefits of surgery compared with non-surgical treatment. The present case report illustrates the importance of imaging techniques in identifying the site of bleeding and the possibility of selective arterial embolization as an effective alternative for bleeding control (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Veiras Fernández, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallardo Arozena, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez Mora, Domingo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Contreras González, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernaldo de Quirós Huguet, Iván</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arozena Abad, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Hernández, Leticia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Regal, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La mayoría de los hematomas puerperales son secundarios a laceraciones o desgarros producidos como consecuencia del traumatismo del parto, y rara vez tienen consecuencias maternas importantes. En ocasiones, estos hematomas pueden expandirse y disecar el tejido circundante suponiendo una complicación obstétrica potencialmente grave. Aunque es necesario un diagnóstico y tratamiento precoz, su manejo no está estandarizado y es causa de controversia ya que la literatura no es concluyente en cuanto a los beneficios del tratamiento conservador respecto al quirúrgico. El propósito de presentar este caso es demostrar la importancia de las técnicas de imagen para la identificación del lugar de la hemorragia y la posibilidad de realizar una embolización arterial selectiva como alternativa eficaz para el control de la misma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);59(4): 243-246, jul.-ago. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163909</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La embolización arterial selectiva como alternativa terapéutica en el manejo del hematoma puerperal disecante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53231^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6556^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6556^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8986^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8986^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6625^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4920^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53231^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5219^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
