<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165397</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Arrhythmias and Cardiac Electrophysiology: Topics of Interest in 2004</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Arrhythmias and cardiac electrophysiology are some of the fastest developing fields in cardiology. New data from the AFFIRM and RACE trials, which compared atrial fibrillation management with rate control or rhythm control strategies, have been published during the last year. New antiarrhythmic drugs, such as azimilide or drodenarone are being evaluated also in other trials. At the same time, the results of the SPORTIF III trial have been published and showed similar tromboembolic risk reduction and less haemorrhagic risk with ximelagatran than with classical anticoagulants in patients with non-valvular atrial fibrillation. Research in the field of atrial fibrillation ablation remains highly active and several important contributions improving the technique or the knowledge about the mechanism of this arrhythmia have been published during the last year. There is continuous interest on new tools for ablation, such as new non-fluoroscopic navigation systems or remote magnetic navigation. Finally, sudden death primary prevention by defibrillator implantation in patients with ventricular dysfunction and non sustained spontaneous ventricular arrhythmias is at present the field with greatest interest about these devices. This has been shown by the publication and presentation of the results of the COMPANION, DEFINITE, SCD-HeFT, and DINAMIT trials (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Merino, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las arritmias y la electrofisiología cardíacas representan una de las disciplinas de la cardiología de más rápido desarrollo, con avances que se producen tanto en los aspectos del tratamiento farmacológico como en los técnicos, de tan rápida evolución. Durante el último año, se han seguido publicando datos de los estudios AFFIRM y RACE, sobre el manejo de la fibrilación auricular (FA) con control de la frecuencia cardíaca o del ritmo cardíaco. También se están desarrollando estudios con antiarrítmicos, como la azimilida o la drodenarona. Al mismo tiempo, se han publicado los resultados del estudio SPORTIF III, que muestran una reducción equivalente de riesgo embólico con un menor riesgo hemorrágico del ximelagatran frente a los anticoagulantes orales clásicos en la FA no valvular. La investigación en la ablación de la FA sigue estando muy activa y se han publicado importantes referencias que depuran la técnica y aportan información sobre los mecanismos de esta arritmia. También se mantiene un gran interés en facilitar los procedimientos de ablación, con la aparición de nuevos sistemas de navegación intracardíaca no fluoroscópica o de navegación magnética remota. Por último, la prevención primaria de la muerte súbita con desfibriladores implantables en pacientes con disfunción ventricular sin arritmias ventriculares sostenidas espontáneas sigue siendo el campo de mayor interés actual con estos dispositivos, como muestra la publicación y presentación de los resultados de los estudios COMPANION, DEFINITE, SCD-HeFT y DINAMIT (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);5(supl.A): 55a-65a, 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165397</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Arritmias y electrofisiología cardíaca: temas de actualidad en 2004</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1150^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30797^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30797^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1150^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4667^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30763^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52886^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4667^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d902^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
