<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159274</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Determining factors for the use of anxiolytic and hypnotic drugs in the elderly</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. To estimate the prevalence of self-reported anxiety/hypnotics use in adults 65 years and older and identify potential factors that determine the use of these drugs. Material and Methods. Cross-sectional study conducted on a study population of 1,161 non-institutionalised adults 65 years old and older with enough ability to conduct a personal interview. Participants were randomly selected from health care registers. The main outcomes of interest included consumption of anxiolytics, hypnotics and other drugs (filed by ATC classification system), mood (based on the Yesavage geriatric depression scale), cognitive status (Pfeiffer questionnaire), physical-functional assessment of basic activities of daily living (Katz index), health problems (ICPC-2 classification WONCA), and sociodemographic variables. Results. The prevalence of self-reported anxiety/hypnotics consumption was 16.6% (95% CI: 14.5 - 18.7), of which 90.5% were benzodiazepines (BZD), mainly lorazepam (39.4% of BZD). Long half-life BZD accounted for 24.7% of BZD. Hypnotics accounted for 27.5% of anxiolytics/hypnotics. The use of sedatives/hypnotics was independently associated with other drugs (non-psychotropics) consumption (OR 6.8, 95% CI: 2.1-22.0), presence of established depression (OR: 2.5; 95% CI: 1.0 -5.9), presence of 4 or more comorbidities (OR: 2.0; 95% CI: 1.4-2.9), being female (OR 2.1, 95% CI: 1.5-3.1) and being dependent for basic activities of daily living (OR: 1.8, 95% CI: 1.1-2.9). Conclusions. The prevalence of sedatives/hypnotics use in the elderly from Albacete is high. Several factors were identified as potential determinants of sedatives/hypnotics use in our study population. It will be important to evaluate the misuse of these drugs in order to develop effective, efficient and safe prescription strategies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Torres Hidalgo, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Ruiz, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Téllez-Lapeira, Juan M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Párraga-Martínez, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gálvez-Alcaraz, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boix-Gras, Clotilde</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Estimar la prevalencia del consumo de ansiolíticos e hipnóticos referido por los mayores de 65 años e identificar posibles factores condicionantes del citado uso. Material y métodos. Estudio transversal. La población de estudio fue de 1.161 sujetos de &amp;#8805;65 años no institucionalizados con suficiente capacidad para llevar a cabo una entrevista personal. Selección mediante muestreo aleatorizado simple del listado de tarjeta sanitaria. Las principales variables evaluadas incluyeron: consumo referido de ansiolíticos/hipnóticos y otros fármacos (según el sistema de clasificación ATC), estado anímico (GDS-VE), estado cognitivo (cuestionario Pfeiffer), valoración física-funcional sobre actividades básicas de la vida diaria (índice de Katz), problemas de salud (clasificación CIAP-2 de la WONCA) y variables sociodemográficas. Resultados. La prevalencia de uso referido de ansiolíticos/hipnóticos fue del 16,6% (IC 95%: 14,5-18,7). El 90,5% fueron benzodiacepinas (BZD), fundamentalmente lorazepam (39,4% de las BZD). Las BZD de vida media prolongada supusieron el 24,7% de todas. Los hipnóticos representaron el 27,5% de los ansiolíticos/hipnóticos. El uso de ansiolíticos/hipnóticos se asoció independientemente con consumir otros fármacos no psicotrópicos (OR: 6,8; IC 95%: 2,1-22,0), presentar depresión establecida (OR: 2,5; IC 95%: 1,0-5,9), presentar 4 o más problemas de salud (OR: 2,0; IC 95%: 1,4-2,9), ser mujer (OR: 2,1; IC 95%: 1,5-3,1) y ser dependiente para las actividades básicas de la vida diaria (OR: 1,8; IC 95%: 1,1-2,9). Conclusiones. La prevalencia de uso de ansiolíticos/hipnóticos es elevada en mayores de Albacete. Diversos factores han sido identificados como potenciales condicionantes de su utilización. Sería importante mejorar el conocimiento sobre el mal uso de estos fármacos con el fin de desarrollar estrategias de prescripción efectivas y seguras (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);52(1): 31-34, ene.-feb. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159274</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consumo de ansiolíticos e hipnóticos y factores asociados en las personas mayores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1593^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14543^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28410</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8316^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56131^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14543^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28598^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
