<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101249</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-6581</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Absolute reliability of conventional and functional ratios and peak isokinetic torque of knee flexion and extension</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Isokinetic strength tests are probably the most common measurement tools for estimating muscle function in sport setting. However, there is little scientific evidence justifying their use as accurate tools. For that reason, the main purpose of this study was to examine the absolute reliability of isokinetic functional and conventional strength ratios as well as concentric and eccentric isokinetic knee flexion and extension peak torque (PT) of the knee in recreational active young adults. Material and methods: Fifty two participants performed 3 measurement sessions to record the functional and conventional strength ratios and concentric and eccentric knee flexion and extension PTs with a 72-96hours rest interval between consecutive sessions. The inter-session absolute reliability was measured through change in the mean between measures (expressed as percentage value [CM]), typical percentage error (% within-subjects variation [CVTE]), and intraclass correlations (ICC).Results: Poor absolute reliability scores were found for conventional (CM=0.2%-0.4%; CVTE=16%-18%; ICC=0.6-0.7) and functional (CM=&amp;#8722;2.1%-0.2%; CVTE=18%-20%; ICC=0.3-0.7) knee strength ratios. Likewise, moderate absolute reliability scores were observed for PT values independently of the knee movement (flexion and extension), type of muscle contraction (concentric and eccentric) and angular velocity (60°/s and 180°/s). Conclusions: An observed change greater than = 12% and = 17% for PT scores (independently of knee movement and muscle contraction) and isokinetic ratios (conventional and functional), respectively, from baseline scores would suggest that a real change in strength balance was likely and not because a measurement error. These absolute reliability scores could be sensitive enough to detect large changes, as showed after completing rehabilitation programs for subjects injured(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ayala, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ste Croix, Mark de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sainz de Baranda, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarobe, Lorea</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Conclusiones: Una modificación mayor de =12 y de =17% en los valores iníciales de la variable PFM (independientemente del tipo de contracción y movimiento articular) e índices isocinéticos (convencional y funcional), respectivamente, podrían ser considerados como reales y no simplemente debidos al error de la medida. Estos valores de fiabilidad absoluta podrían ser lo suficientemente sensibles como para detectar cambios de gran magnitud, como los acontecidos tras la aplicación de programas de rehabilitación en personas lesionadas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apunts, Med. esport (Internet);47(174): 55-64, abr.-jun. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101249</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fiabilidad absoluta de los índices convencional y funcional y momento máximo de fuerza isocinética de la flexión y extensión de rodilla</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24807</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7892^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1721^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
