<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152223</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characterization of &#145;Knockout&#146; in Boxing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of this work is to identify the last four motor actions (punches) made by heavyweight world champion boxers, in an attempt to characterize how &#145;Knock out&#146; is achieved in this sport. An observation tool consisting of four criteria and 35 categories was devised. The two requirements for sampling are: that the subject was the world heavyweight champion sometime between 1921-2007 (Jack Dempsey to Ruslan Chagaev) and that digital images are available for analysis. Data were obtained about the motor actions preceding the end of the fight, studying the last four punches delivered by the winner. The results show that the &#145;Knock out&#146; in boxing is in most cases due to certain types of punches being used by the contenders, with significant differences being recorded (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blanco-Villaseñor, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-López, CR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pic-Aguilar, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo es identificar las cuatro últimas acciones motrices emitidas (golpes) por boxeadores campeones del mundo de los pesos pesados y así poder caracterizar el &#145;Knock out&#146; en boxeo. Para ello, hemos desarrollado una herramienta de observación que consta de cuatro criterios y 35 categorías. Para la selección de la muestra se tuvo en cuenta dos requisitos: haberse proclamado campeón del mundo del peso pesado durante el período que comprende 1921-2007 (desde Jack Dempsey hasta Ruslan Chagaev) y la disponibilidad digital de las imágenes para su análisis. Se obtuvieron datos relativos a la secuencia de acciones motrices que anteceden a la finalización de los combates en boxeo, medido a través de los últimos cuatro golpes lanzados por el ganador. Los resultados del estudio muestran que el &#145;Knock out&#146; en boxeo suele darse haciendo un uso mayoritario de ciertos golpes entre los contendientes, presentando diferencias significativas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;16(1): 85-94, ene. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152223</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Caracterización del &#145;Knock out&#146; en Boxeo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d55468</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8300</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1939^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3194</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
