<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96220</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A review of questionnaires exploring driver&#146;s exposure and risk factors in road crashes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Given the diversity of questionnaires currently being used in the study of the analytic epidemiology of traffic injuries, we made a review of studies on this question published between 1989 and 2011 in order toidentify their advantages and disadvantages. We wereable to observe that most of the questionnaires were focused on the human factor regarding the risk of road crashes, but very few of them included intensity of exposure and its association with other risk factors in road crashes. Many questionnaires have a high number of items and complex rating scales. Further more, in Spain there are few validated questionnaires which contain complete information about exposure and road crashes. In Spain we should work on the design and validation of questionnaires containing questions aimedat obtaining complete and easy information about the epidemiology of traffic injuries. In this way we would be able to increase our awareness of traffic injuries and how to prevent them (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Mejías, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amezcua, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lardelli, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Moleón, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Dada la diversidad de cuestionarios empleados en el estudio de la epidemiología analítica de las lesiones por tráfico, realizamos una revisión de los estudios publicados al respecto entre 1989 a 2011, con objeto de identificar sus fortalezas y debilidades. Dicha revisión puso de relieve que la mayor parte de los cuestionarios se centran en el factor humano sobre el riesgo de accidente, pero son muy pocos los que incluyen la intensidad de exposición y la asociación de ésta con otros factores de riesgo de la accidentalidad. Muchos cuestionarios poseen un elevado número de ítems y complejas escalas de valoración. Además, en España son escasos los cuestionarios validados sobre la exposición y la accidentalidad por tráfico. Por todo ello, es necesario trabajar en el diseño y la validación de cuestionarios que recojan de forma sencilla información integral sobre la epidemiología de las lesiones por tráfico de cara a su mayor conocimiento y prevención (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;34(3): 443-452, sept.-dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96220</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuestionarios sobre factores de riesgo de la exposición y la accidentalidad por tráfico en conductores. Una revisión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1340^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
