<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146135</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of a beverage made from cactus pear (nopalea cochenillifera (l) salm-dyck) in a rural population of hidalgo, Mexico; a pilot clinical trial</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: cactus pear has been used in Mexican traditional medicine. However, clinical studies are limited to demonstrate the effectiveness as anti-diabetic. Objective: to evaluate the effect of a fresh beverage made from Nopalea cochenillifera (l.) Salm-dyck on glucose levels, glycosylated hemoglobin, weight, waist circumference and blood pressure. Methods: the beverage (50 g/250 mL) was daily administered in twenty patients for 30 days. Results and discussion: differences statistically significant were found in some time of the supplementation for all measured variables excepting for glucose levels, this suggests that values might be significant to a longer administration or bigger doses. Conclusions: although preliminary data, the results demonstrated that cactus pear used in this study may be an alternative for the management of patients with diabetes type 2. Nevertheless, further trials must be conducted with a bigger sample size and more control groups so that the effectiveness can be fully evaluated (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Betanzos-Cabrera, Gabriel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Pacheco, Alejandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ariza Ortega, José Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ávila-Domínguez, Rosángela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fabela-Illescas, Héctor Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: el nopal ha sido usado en la medicina tradicional mexicana. Sin embargo, los estudios clínicos para demostrar la eficacia como antidiabético son limitados. Objetivo: evaluar el efecto de una bebida fresca a base de nopal (Nopalea cochenillifera (l.) Salm-dyck), sobre los niveles de glucosa, hemoglobina glicosilada, peso corporal, circunferencia de cintura y presión sanguínea. Métodos: la bebida (50 g/250 mL) se administró diariamente a 20 pacientes durante 30 días. Resultados y discusión: se encontraron diferencias estadísticamente significativas en algún momento de la suplementación, excepto para la glucosa, sugiriendo que los valores podrían ser significativos en un tiempo mayor de administración a dosis mayores. Conclusiones: aunque preliminares, los resultados demostraron que el nopal usado en este estudio podría ser útil en el manejo de pacientes con diabetes tipo 2. No obstante, deben efectuarse futuros ensayos con un tamaño de muestra más grande y más grupos control, para que la efectividad pueda ser totalmente evaluada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(6): 2710-2714, dic. 2015. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146135</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de una bebida a base de nopal (Nopalea cochenillifera (l) Salm-dyck) en pacientes de una población rural de Hidalgo, México; ensayo clínico piloto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7124^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35730</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23138^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51396</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
