<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60770</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of severe diabetic neuropathy through spinal cord stimulation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Diabetes mellitus (DM) is a widespread disease among the generalpopulation which, because of the damaging effect of hyperglycemiaon the nervous or vascular structures, may lead to complicationswhich in many cases are difficult to treat. In general, neurologicaldisorders secondary to DM cause severe, painful processes. A greatmany clinical practice guidelines are available providing recommendationsabout different drugs to be used as a monotherapy or incombination, with varying degrees of evidence. Nevertheless, certainclinical situations show no response to pharmacological therapiesand, therefore, other resources have to be found and implementedto achieve analgesia. We present a case that was resistant to traditionalpharmacological treatments, in which analgesic control wasachieved through spinal cord stimulation systems (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Silva Cedeño, M. V.</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquer Quiles, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villanueva Pérez, V. L.</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrés Ibáñez, J. A. de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La diabetes mellitus (DM) es una patología ampliamente extendidaen la población general que, por el efecto perjudicial que ejerce lahiperglucemia sobre estructuras nerviosas o vasculares, puede generarcomplicaciones, en muchas ocasiones difíciles de tratar. Laalteración nerviosa secundaria a la DM ocasiona, por lo general, procesosdolorosos graves. Existen multitud de guías de práctica clínicaque realizan recomendaciones sobre el uso de diferentes fármacosen monoterapia o combinados, con distintos grados de evidencia.Sin embargo, hay situaciones clínicas en las que no se produce respuestaa las terapias farmacológicas, por lo que se buscan otrosrecursos para obtener la analgesia. Presentamos un caso resistenteal tratamiento convencional farmacológico, en el que se obtiene elcontrol analgésico mediante sistemas de estimulación medular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;25(2): 139-141, mar.-abr. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60770</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de la neuropatía diabética grave medianteestimulación medular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13499</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28247^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3952^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d714^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
