<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147731</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Consensus-based approach for severe paediatric asthma in routine clinical practice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Accurate identification of paediatric patients with severe asthma is essential for an adequate management of the disease. However, criteria for defining severe asthma and recommendations for control vary among different guidelines. Material and methods: An online survey was conducted to explore expert opinions about the definition and management of severe paediatric asthma. To reach a consensus agreement, a modified Delphi technique was used, and practice guidelines were prepared after the analysis of the results. Results: Eleven paediatric chest disease physicians and allergy specialists with wide expertise in severe asthma responded to the survey. Consensus was reached in 50 out of 65 questions (76.92%). It was considered that a patient has severe asthma if during the previous year they have required 2 or more cycles of oral steroids, required daily treatment with medium doses of inhaled corticosteroids (with other controller medication) or high doses (with or without other controller medication), did not respond to optimised conventional treatment, or if the disease threatened the life of the patient or seriously impairs their quality of life. The definition of severe asthma may also include patients who justifiably use health resources on a regular basis, or have psychosocial or environmental factors impeding control. For monitoring, the use of questionnaires designed specifically for paediatric population, such as CAN or ACT, is recommended. As regards treatment, the use of omalizumab should be considered prior to the use of oral corticosteroids. Conclusions: This paper provides consensus recommendations that may be useful in the management of severe paediatric asthma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Corzo, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hoz, B de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabero, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Korta-Murua, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bosque-García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Salguero, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tortajada-Girbés, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zapatero, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez, MDP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Plaza, AM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valverde-Molina, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Hernández, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres-Borrego, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Solís, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La identificación adecuada del paciente pediátrico con asma grave es esencial para su correcto manejo. Sin embargo, los criterios para definir el asma grave y las recomendaciones para su control varían mucho entre las distintas guías. Material y métodos: Se elaboró una encuesta telemática para analizar las opiniones relativas a la definición y control del asma grave pediátrica. Para lograr un consenso se siguió una metodología Delphi modificada. Con los resultados se elaboraron recomendaciones prácticas. Resultados: El cuestionario fue respondido por 11 neumólogos y alergólogos pediátricos expertos en asma grave. Hubo consenso en 50 de los 65 ítems planteados (76,92%). Se consideró que un paciente tiene asma grave si en el último año ha requerido 2 o más ciclos de corticoides orales, si requiere tratamiento diario con corticoides inhalados a dosis medias (con otra medicación controladora) o dosis altas (con o sin otra medicación controladora), si no responde a un tratamiento convencional optimizado, o si la enfermedad pone en riesgo su vida o deteriora gravemente su calidad de vida. La definición de asma grave también podría incluir a los pacientes que consumen recursos sanitarios de manera regular y justificada, o tienen factores psicosociales o ambientales que impiden su control. Para la monitorización, se recomienda usar cuestionarios específicos de población pediátrica (CAN o ACT). Respecto al tratamiento, se debería considerar el uso de omalizumab en un escalón anterior al de los corticoides orales. Conclusiones: El presente trabajo ofrece recomendaciones consensuadas que pueden ser de utilidad en el manejo del asma grave pediátrica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);84(2): 122.e1-122.e11, feb. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147731</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consenso para el abordaje del asma grave pediátrica en la práctica clínica habitual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22870</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32137^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28379^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
