<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73782</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interspinous arthrosis (Baastrup syndrome): a case report imaging diagnosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Interspinous osteoarthritis is not rare butit is often an unrecognised cause of lumbar pain producedby pseudoarthrosis between lumbar spinous apophysis. Degenerationand/or rupture of interspinous ligament is thekey problem of this degenerative process that may promotedevelopment of adventitial bursas. We present the case of a72 years-old woman with history of breast cancer since4 years that presented with chronic low back pain andmarkedly increased activity at L4 and L5 spinous processesat bone scintigraphy. A radiological diagnosis of interspinousosteoarthritis (Baastrup syndrome) with severely degeneratedinterspinous ligament was made. The back ache hasbeen relieved partially with conservative treatment untilthis moment(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Soriano Guillén, A. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vela Marín, A. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayayo Sinués, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La artrosis interespinosa es una causa pococonocida, aunque no excesivamente rara, de dolor lumbarproducida por el desarrollo de una pseudoarticulación entrelas apófisis espinosas lumbares. La degeneración o roturadel ligamento interespinoso parece ser un proceso claveen el desarrollo de estos fenómenos degenerativos quepueden acompañarse de la formación de bursas adventiciales.Presentamos el caso de una mujer de 72 años, con antecedentesde cáncer mamario, que presentaba un dolorlumbar crónico y captación en la gammagrafía ósea en lazona de las apófisis espinosas de L4-L5. Las pruebas radiológicasefectuadas demostraron una artrosis interespinosa(síndrome de Baastrup) asociada a una degeneración avanzadadel ligamento interespinoso, efectuándose tratamientoconservador con control del dolor lumbar hasta el momento(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);43(5): 236-239, sept.-oct. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73782</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Artrosis interespinosa (síndrome de Baastrup): presentación de un caso y diagnóstico por imagen</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14538^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8334^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d86^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8334^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
