<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77246</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Parotidectomy and facial vein</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Benign parotid tumor surgery is related to fundamentalnervous structures, defined simply: that when damaged cause greatpsychosomatic problems. In order to make peripheral facial nervesurgery easy to handle for the surgeon this article emphasizes theimportance of the facial vein in the dissection and conservation ofthe nerve. Its dissection can be compromised if the caudal branchesare damaged. The study that we develop should be seen as praisefor the vein structures in the follow up and control of the peripheralfacial nerve, and the main auricular nerve that is often undervaluedwhen it is no longer the protagonist in the face(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández Montero, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Altemir, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Montero, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La cirugía de los tumores benignos de la parótida, es una cirugíade relaciones con estructuras fundamentalmente nerviosas cuyo daño, representaun gravísimo problema psicosomático por definirlo de una maneragenérica. Para ayudar al manejo quirúrgico del nervio facial periférico, es porlo que en el presente artículo tratamos de enfatizar la importancia de la venafacial en la disección y conservación del nervio, precisamente donde su disecciónsuele ser más comprometida, esto es en las ramas más caudales. Eltrabajo que vamos a desarrollar hay que verlo pues, como un ensalzamientode las estructuras venosas en el seguimiento y control del nervio facial periféricoy de porqué no, el nervio auricular mayor no siempre suficientementevalorado en la cirugía de la parótida al perder protagonismo con el facial(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;31(5): 319-327, sept.-oct. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77246</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Parotidectomía y vena facial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10496^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22602^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15080^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5255^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12844^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10496^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
