<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-70834</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-0559</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In order to analyse the relationship between volunteerism and life satisfaction, 401 volunteers have filled the Life Satisfaction Scale (SWLS), the previous time that they have been like volunteers and the probability of going to like volunteers. The results show that there are some differences in the satisfaction according to the type of volunteerism. The socioassistance volunteers show more life satisfaction then environmental volunteers. The life satisfaction is related to the previous time that they have been like volunteers and only with socioassistance volunteers is related to the probability of going on two years</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dávila de León, M. Celeste</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Morales, Juan Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Con el objetivo de analizar la relación existente entre el voluntariado y la satisfacción vital, 401 voluntarios cumplimentaron un cuestionario donde se les solicitaba información sobre su satisfacción vital, el tiempo previo que llevaban como voluntarios y la probabilidad de que siguiesen como tales en el futuro. Los resultados encontrados muestran que existen diferencias significativas en los niveles de satisfacción experimentada en función del tipo de voluntariado estudiado: los voluntarios socioasistenciales manifiestan una mayor satisfacción vital que los voluntarios ambientales. La satisfacción vital está asociada al tiempo previo como voluntario y únicamente en el coso de los voluntarios socioasistenciales se relaciona con la probabilidad de continuar a los dos años</dc:description>
<dc:source>Interv. psicosoc;14(1): 81-94, ene.-abr. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-70834</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37744^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15240^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
