<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75329</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Primary renal lymphoma: Report of three new cases and literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: We report the cases of three patients with primary renal lymphoma. Diagnosis and subsequent treatment are discussed.METHODS: The literature on the origin, epidemiology, clinical presentation, diagnosis, treatment and prognosis of primary renal lymphoma was reviewed.RESULTS: The first patient was diagnosed after radical nephrectomy and subsequently was given six cycles of CVP (cyclophosphamide, vincristine, prednisone). The diagnosis of the second patient was established by renal biopsy, and the patient received six cycles of CHOP (cyclophosphamide, adriamycin, vincristine and prednisone). The last patient had a lymphoma, secondary to immunosuppression, in a transplanted kidney. In this case transplant nephrectomy sufficed to cure the patient&#146;s lymphoma. All patients had B-cell non-Hodgkin lymphoma (an extrarenal origin was ruled out by bone marrow biopsy), and were disease-free 15 months, 7 months, and 6.5 years after diagnosis, respectively.CONCLUSIONS: Primary renal lymphoma is rare. Diagnosis is established by renal biopsy, although it often presents as a mass simulating renal cell cancer and diagnosis is obtained after radical nephrectomy. Treatment consists of chemotherapy (CHOP) associated with rituximab(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cózar Olmo, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tallada Buñuel, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Carazo, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Funes Padilla, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Becerra Massare, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Herrera, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Alonso, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Ramos, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual Geler, Manrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente Prados, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVOS: Se presentan tres casos clínicos de pacientes con linfoma renal primario, su diagnóstico y posterior tratamiento.MÉTODOS: Se realiza una revisión bibliográfica del origen, epidemiología, características clínicas, diagnóstico, tratamiento y pronóstico de esta enfermedad.RESULTADOS: En nuestro primer caso la paciente es diagnosticada tras una nefrectomía radical y tratada posteriormente con seis ciclos de CVP (ciclofosfamida, vincristina, prednisona). En el segundo paciente el diagnóstico se llevó a cabo mediante biopsia renal, administrándose seis ciclos de CHOP (ciclofosfamida, adriamicina, vincristina y prednisona). El último caso se trata de un linfoma secundario a la inmunosupresión en un riñón trasplantado en la que la realización de una trasplantectomía fue suficiente. Todos los casos fueron linfomas no-Hodgkin de células B descartándose el origen extrarrenal con biopsia de médula ósea, estando libres de enfermedad tras 15, 7 meses y 6.5 años del diagnóstico respectivamente.CONCLUSIONES: El linfoma renal primario es muy raro. El diagnóstico se realiza mediante biopsia renal aunque con frecuencia se presenta como una masa simulando un cáncer renal y es diagnosticado tras nefrectomía radical. El tratamiento consiste en quimioterapia (CHOP) asociada a rituximab(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;62(6): 461-465, jul.-ago. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75329</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Linfoma renal primario: Aportación de tres nuevos casos y Revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8398</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7855</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7855^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7855^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7855^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7855^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9585^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9585</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50345</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
