<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155972</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Burnout in nursing professionals performing overtime workdays in emergency and critical care departments. Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Burnout syndrome is a disorder that seriously affects people who suffer it, the institutions in which they work and the quality of healthcare. It is of great interest to advance in burnout research for its possible prevention. The aim of this work was to study the levels of burnout syndrome in nurses of emergency department with overtime workdays and to know the relationship between burnout and personality characteristics. Methods: Multicenter cross-sectional study with a sample of 1225 emergency nurses from the Andalusian Health Service. Demographic, social and occupational variables were recorded. Burnout was assessed with Maslach Burnout Inventory and personality factors with NEO-Five Factor Inventory. Descriptive analysis of the variables, independent means hypothesis contrast and bayesian analysis were done. Results: 44.1% of nurses who perform overtime workdays had high burnout versus a 38% for those without such overload. These differences have been also found in burnout dimensions, especially in emotional exhaustion (15.3% versus 10.8%) and depersonalization (17.9% versus 11.8%). Conclusions: Overtime workdays performed by emergency nurses seems to have a negative on them and it could also influence the development of burnout syndrome (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Urquiza, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañadas, Gustavo Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañadas-De la Fuente, Guillermos Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albendín-García, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuente, Emilia Inmaculada de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Luis, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: El síndrome de burnout es un trastorno que afecta a las personas que lo padecen, a las instituciones en las que éstas prestan servicio y a la calidad de los cuidados a los pacientes. El objetivo fue estudiar los niveles de síndrome de burnout en los profesionales de enfermería de urgencias con jornada física complementaria y conocer su relación con características de personalidad y realización de jornada física complementaria y conocer su relación con características de personalidad de los profesionales de enfermería. Métodos: Estudio transversal multicéntrico con una muestra de 1.225 profesionales de enfermería de urgencias del Servicio Andaluz de Salud. Se recogieron variables sociodemográficas, psicológicas y laborales. El síndrome de burnout fue evaluado mediante el Maslach Burnout Inventory y los factores de personalidad a través del NEO-Five Factor Inventory. Se realizaron análisis descriptivos de las variables, contrastes de hipótesis de dos medias independientes y análisis bayesianos. Resultados: El 44,1% de los profesionales de enfermería que realizaban jornada física complementaria presentaban síndrome de burnout alto frente a un 38% de los que no tenían dicha sobrecarga. Respecto a las dimensiones del burnout se mantenían estas diferencias, especialmente en las dimensiones cansancio emocional (15,3% frente a 10,8%) y despersonalización (17,9% frente a 11,8%). Conclusiones: La realización de jornada física complementaria parece afectar negativamente a los profesionales de enfermería de urgencias y podría favorecer en ellos el desarrollo del síndrome de burnout (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;90: 0-0, 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155972</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Burnout en profesionales de enfermería que realizan jornada física complementaria en servicios de cuidados críticos y urgencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d55418^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16370</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30140^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9927^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
