<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105431</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-1959</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of COPD among the smoker population of Colloto (Asturias)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To know the total and unknown prevalence of COPD in the smoker and ex-smoker population of 40 to 75 years in the urban -rural area of Colloto, Asturias, and the differences according to the different sociodemographic variables. Patients and method. A descriptive cross-sectional study on 364 smokers and ex-smokers of both genders,  40 to 75 years old, who came to the medical facility of Colloto. A detailed clinical history on the habit and physical examination was obtained, as well as a complete spirometric study for the diagnosis and staging. Results. COPD prevalence was 15.1% (95% CI 11.7- 19.4), without differences between genders. Associated factors were age (going from 8.1 to 24.8% from  its first to third terciles of age) and the smoking habit index (going from 8.4 to 24.8% from its first to the third terciles) and as protective factor, the body mass index. The current smoking consumption habit showed no differences. A total of 48% of those diagnosed by spirometry were new diagnoses. Of those previously diagnosed of COPD, the diagnosis was not confirmed in the spirometry  in 52% and 14.8% of the COPD were classified as severe or very severe. Conclusions. The prevalence obtained is similar to that of other studies, half of the cases being unknown.  All smokers should undergo routine spirometric studies, at least those smoking from 15 packs a year after the age of 40 and in all of those patients who have been smokers after the age of 65 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso Cortina, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García García, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castaño Pérez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias García, Mª T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Fernández, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez García, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz González, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Conocer la prevalencia total y no conocida de EPOC en la población fumadora y ex-fumadora de 40 a 75 años en el área urbano-rural de Colloto, Asturias, y las diferencias según las distintas variables sociodemográficas. Pacientes y método. Estudio descriptivo transversal  sobre 364 fumadores y ex-fumadores de ambos sexos de 40 a 75 años que acudían al consultorio de Colloto. Se realizó una historia clínica del hábito y examen físico detallados, y un estudio espirométrico completo para el diagnóstico y estadiaje.  Resultados. La prevalencia de EPOC fue del 15,1% (IC 95% 11,7-19,4), sin diferencias entre sexos. Los factores asociados fueron la edad (pasando del 8,1 al 24,8% del primer al tercer terciles de edad) y el índice tabáquico (pasando del 8,4 al 24,8% del primer al tercer terciles del mismo), y como factor protector el índice de masa corporal. El hábito actual de consumo  de tabaco no presentaba diferencias. El 48% de los diagnosticados por espirometría fueron nuevos diagnósticos. De los diagnosticados previamente de EPOC, en el 52% no se confirma el diagnóstico en la espirometría. El 14,8% de los EPOC se clasificaron como grave o muy grave. Conclusiones. La prevalencia obtenida es similar a la de otros estudios, siendo la mitad de los casos desconocidos.  Deben estudiarse espirométricamente de rutina todos los fumadores, al menos desde 15 paquetesaño a partir de los 40 años, y en todos los pacientes que hayan sido fumadores a partir de los 65 años (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prev. tab;14(2): 61-68, abr.-jun. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105431</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de EPOC entre la población fumadora de Colloto (Asturias)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
