<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153346</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-1342</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perceptions of acceptable conducts by university students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine perceptions of acceptable conducts amongst under and postgraduate optometry students and to compare them with students from other disciplines. Methods: Students (under/postgraduate) of optometry (n=156) and other courses (n=54) from University of Minho participated in a voluntary online questionnaire about perception of conducts, classifying as acceptable or unacceptable 15 academic or professional scenarios. Results: 210 questionnaires were analyzed. Differences in perceptions were found between optometry under and postgraduates in scenario 5, Chi-square(2,156)=4.3, p=0.038, and scenario 7, Chi-square(2,156)=7.0, p=0.008 (both with cheating more acceptable for postgrads). Differences between under and postgraduates from other courses were found in scenario 9 (taking supplies from classroom more acceptable for undergrads), Chi-square(1,54)=5.0, p=0.025, and scenario 14 (forging a signature more acceptable for postgrads), Chi-square(1,54)=3.9, p=0.046. Differences between optometry and other courses undergraduates were observed in scenario 2 (plagiarism more acceptable for optometry undergrads), Chi-square(1,154)=8.3, p=0.004 and scenario 9 (taking supplies from classroom more acceptable for other undergrads), chi-square(1,54)=7.8, p=0.005. Differences between optometry and other courses postgraduates were observed in scenario 7, Chi-square(1,56)=5.8, p=0.016, scenario 10 (both with cheating more acceptable for optometry postgrads), chi-square(1,54)=8.1, p=0.004 and scenario 14 (forging a signature more acceptable for other postgrads), Chi-square(1,54)=6.1, p=0.026. Conclusion: Academic misconducts were mainly considered more acceptable than professional misconducts. Our results show that perceptions of acceptable conducts amongst optometry students are not very different from other students, and, against our initial prediction, do not show a general change in misconduct perception when students become more mature. Universities should pay more attention to this problem and take action (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marques, Dora Nazaré</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macedo, António Filipe</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar las percepciones sobre las conductas aceptables entre los estudiantes universitarios y los postgraduados en optometría, y compararlas con los estudiantes de otras disciplinas. Métodos: Los estudiantes (universitarios/y postgraduados) de optometría (n=156) y de otras carreras (n=54) de la Universidad de Minho participaron en un cuestionario online voluntario acerca de la percepción de las conductas, calificando de aceptables o inaceptables a 15 escenarios académicos o profesionales. Resultados: Se analizaron 210 cuestionarios. Se encontraron diferencias en las percepciones entre los estudiantes y los postgraduados en optometría en el escenario 5, &amp;#967;2(2,156)=4,3,p=0,038, y el escenario 7, &amp;#967;2(2,156)=7,0,p=0,008 (en ambos, hacer trampas es más aceptable para los postgraduados). Se encontraron diferencias entre los estudiantes y los postgraduados de otras carreras en el escenario 9 (coger suministros de la clase es más aceptable para los estudiantes), &amp;#967;2(1,54)=5,0,p=0,025, y el escenario 14 (falsificar una firma es más aceptable para los postgraduados), &amp;#967;2(1,54)=3,9,p=0,046. Se encontraron diferencias entre los estudiantes de optometría y de otras carreras en el escenario 2 (el plagio es más aceptable para los estudiantes de optometría), &amp;#967;2(1,154)=8,3,p=0,004 y el escenario 9 (coger suministros de la clase es más aceptable para los estudiantes de otras carreras), &amp;#967;2(1,54)=7,8,p=0,005. Se encontraron diferencias entre los postgraduados de optometría y de otras carreras en el escenario 7, &amp;#967;2(1,56)=5,8,p=0,016, y el escenario 10 (en ambos, hacer trampas es más aceptable para los postgraduados en optometría), &amp;#967;2(1,54)=8,1,p=0,004 y el escenario 14 (falsificar una firma es más aceptable para los postgraduados en otras carreras), &amp;#967;2(1,54)=6,1,p=0,026. Conclusión: Las malas conductas académicas se consideraron mucho más aceptables que las malas conductas profesionales. Nuestros resultados muestran que las percepciones sobre las conductas aceptables entre los estudiantes de optometría no son muy diferentes a las de otros estudiantes y, en contra de nuestra predicción inicial, no reflejan un cambio general de la percepción de mala conducta cuando los estudiantes son más maduros. Las universidades deberían prestar más atención a este problema, y tomar medidas al respecto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>J. optom. (Internet);9(3): 166-174, jul.-sept. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153346</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Percepciones sobre las conductas aceptables por los estudiantes universitarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10087^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32415^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32415^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8491^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10087^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32415^s22082</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10087^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32415^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8491^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10087^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
