<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79449</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-1375</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sexual behaviour in haemodialysis patients in Melilla</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Sexual dysfunction disorders are not infrequent in people with Terminal Chronic Renal Insufficiency undergoing dialysis. Our aim was to find out the sexual behaviour inhaemodialysis patients in Melilla, and determine whether they suffered any sexual alteration or dysfunction. This is a transversal descriptive study carried out on a sample of 38 patients. The data were compiled on  questionnaire prepared for this purpose which was submitted to the opinion of experts and was translated into Arabic due to the language barrier. The results show that 57.89% are women and 42.10% are men. The average age is around 40 in men and 70 in women. Sex drive has fallen in 56.25% of the men and 31.8%of the women since they have been on haemodialysis. The reduction in libido affects women more than men.75% of the men would be willing to treat the sexual dysfunction and 37.5% list the psychological factor as the cause (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vaca Ruíz, Ana María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz García, Victoria Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Criado, Juana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bagdad Abselam, Aziza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mohamed Maanan, Nayet</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Estudillo, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los trastornos de la disfunción sexual no son infrecuentes en las personas con Insuficiencia Renal Crónica Terminal en diálisis. Nuestro objetivo fue conocer el comportamiento sexual en los pacientes de Hemodiálisis en Melilla, y saber si padecen alguna alteración o disfunción sexual. Se trata de estudio descriptivo transversal en una muestra de 38 pacientes. Se recogen los datos en un cuestionario confeccionado para tal fi n que se sometió a un juicio de expertos y se tradujo al árabe por la barrera idiomática. Los resultados muestran que el 57.89% son mujeres y el 42.10% varones. La edad media oscila entre los 40 en varones y los 70años en mujeres. En el 56.25% de lo varones y el31.8% de las mujeres han disminuido el deseo sexual desde que están en Hemodiálisis. La disminución dela libido afecta más a las mujeres que a los varones. Estarían dispuestos a tratar la disfunción sexual el75% de los hombres y el 37.5% relacionan el factor psicológico como causante (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Enferm. Nefrol;13(2): 113-118, abr.-jun. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79449</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comportamiento sexual en los pacientes de hemodiálisis en Melilla</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13115^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13104</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8165^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13115^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
