<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042725</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bruising of the esophagus as a cause of gastrointestinal a case of heatstroke</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Alterations in blood clotting are a frequent complication ofserious heatstroke and may result in gastrointestinal bleeding.We report the case of a 26-year-old man who was admitted toour hospital with symptoms of hyperthermia associated with encephalopathyand disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC)after prolonged exposure to sunlight. He presented hematemesis,after which he was diagnosed with having a bruising of theesophagus that took up the upper and lower thirds, there beingno other lesions in the stomach or duodenum. After supportivetreatment and following the resolution of the underlying pathology,the endoscopy-revealed injuries healed with a completenormalization of the esophageal mucosa. Esophageal submucosalbruising is an exceptional cause of hematemesis in seriousheatstroke not previously described in the literature</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carrión Alonso, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manceñido Marcos, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rey Sanz, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pajares Villarroya, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lucendo Villarín, A. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kassem, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las alteraciones de la coagulación son una complicación frecuenteen el golpe de calor grave, y pueden ser causa de hemorragiadigestiva. Presentamos el caso de un varón de 26 años quefue admitido en nuestro hospital por un cuadro de hipertermia,asociado con encefalopatía y coagulación intravascular diseminadatras exposición solar prolongada. Presentó hematemesis por laque fue diagnosticado de múltiples hematomas esofágicos queocupaban los tercios superior e inferior del órgano, en ausenciade otras lesiones en estómago y duodeno. Tras el tratamiento desoporte y la resolución de la patología subyacente, desaparecieronlas lesiones endoscópicas, normalizándose la mucosa esofágica</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;97(8): 596-599, ago. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042725</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hematomas esofágicos como causa de hemorragia digestiva en un caso de golpe de calor</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34727</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5025^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6556^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6623^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
