<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97634</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Incontinentia pigmenti. Four patients with different clinical manifestations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Incontinentia pigmenti (IP) is a rare neurocutaneous disorder with a frequency of 1 in 50,000 newborn, and is associated with mutations in IKBKG gene (NEMO) in Xq28, inherited as an X-linked dominant trait. Clinical manifestations detected since the newborn period are highly variable, with 3 well established sequential or overlapped states and each with a characteristic differential diagnosis. With PCR+RFLPs, we analyzed the IKBKG gene in 4 patients with different clinical manifestations and characteristic skin biopsy. In all 4 patients the same deletion of exons 4 to 10 was identified. In female patients in whom the dermatological lesions lead to the suspicion of an IP diagnosis, it is important to have the complete, multidisciplinary and molecular analysis of their first level female relatives. This should give us a clear diagnosis, which is the first step to complete genetic counselling(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llano-Rivas, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soler-Sánchez, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Toral, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Málaga-Diéguez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La incontinencia pigmenti (IP) es un trastorno neurocutáneo raro, con una frecuencia de 1 en 50.000 recién nacidos, de etiología genética asociada a mutaciones en el gen IKBKG (NEMO) en Xq28, con herencia dominante ligada al X. Tiene una presentación clínica de manifestaciones muy variables detectadas desde la etapa neonatal, con 3 estadios bien definidos en forma secuencial, solapada o salteada, y cada una de estos con un diagnóstico diferencial distinto. Mediante la técnica molecular de PCR+RFLP se analizó el gen IKBKG en cuatro pacientes diferentes con manifestaciones sospechosas de IP además de la biopsia de piel confirmatoria; en todas se detectó la deleción de los exones 4 al 10. Destacamos que ante la sospecha clínica de IP es importante el estudio familiar y el multidisciplinario (complicaciones neurológicas, oculares&#133;), y el necesario asesoramiento genético(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);76(3): 156-160, mar. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97634</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incontinencia pigmenti. Cuatro pacientes con diferentes manifestaciones clínicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19206^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24666^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34313^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
