<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120589</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of obesity and altered lipid profile in university students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Obesity is a serious public health problem because its association with the risk to develop various chronic diseases. Atherogenic dyslipidemia that often accompany obesity is also associated to the metabolic syndrome and to cardiovascular diseases. The transition from adolescence to young adulthood appears to be a period where major changes occur in the lifestyle which contributes to the development of obesity, however, little attention has been given to this transition stage. The inclination to adopt unhealthy behaviors which occurs during early adulthood may be increased on university students because their lifestyle, which is characterized by lack of time to eat a healthy diet, which can make them susceptible to obesity. Objective: To determine the prevalence of obesity and lipid levels abnormalities and their relationship in a group of university students. Methods: Transversal study of university students aged between 18 and 24 years. Body mass index, waist circumference and blood lipid profile where evaluated. Results: Of the 620 students surveyed about one-third have either overweight or obesity. 86% of students had at least one alteration in the evaluated parameters. Lipid profile results show a high prevalence of minor alterations in levels, particularly in cholesterol linked to low density lipoproteins levels. Conclusions: University young students have a high prevalence of overweight and plasma lipid levels above the norm, but most are in the low-risk categories. It is necessary to establish early preventive measures aimed at promoting in the university student good eating habits and increased physical activity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Medina Díaz, Eunice</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Sandoval, Claudia Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Burke, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendizabal-Ruiz, Adriana Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales, José Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La obesidad constituye un grave problema de salud pública por su asociación con los riesgos a desarrollar enfermedades crónicas. La dislipidemia aterogénica que acompaña con frecuencia a la obesidad también está asociada al síndrome metabólico y a las enfermedades cardiovasculares. La transición entre la adolescencia y el adulto es un periodo con modificaciones importantes en el estilo de vida que contribuyen al desarrollo de la obesidad, sin embargo es poca la atención brindada a esta etapa. La tendencia a adoptar comportamientos poco saludables durante esta transición puede incrementarse en los universitarios que llevan un estilo de vida caracterizado por la falta de tiempo para llevar una dieta saludable, haciéndolos susceptibles a desarrollar obesidad. Objetivo: Determinar la prevalencia de la obesidad y de las anormalidades en los niveles de lípidos y su relación en un grupo de universitarios. Métodos: Estudio transversal que evalúa Índice de Masa Corporal, diámetro de cintura y perfil de lípidos en universitarios con un rango de edad de 18 a 24 años. Resultados: De los 620 jóvenes estudiados, aproximadamente un tercio tienen sobrepeso u obesidad. El 86% presentó al menos una alteración en los parámetros evaluados. Los resultados del perfil lipídico muestran alta prevalencia de alteraciones leves, particularmente en los niveles de colesterol ligado a lipoproteínas de baja densidad. Conclusiones: Los jóvenes Universitarios presentan alta prevalencia de lípidos plasmáticos por encima de la norma y exceso de peso. Es necesario establecer medidas preventivas dirigidas a promover en los universitarios buenos hábitos alimenticios y mayor actividad física (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;29(2): 315-321, 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120589</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de obesidad y perfil lipídico alterado en jóvenes universitarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50514^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32738^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51243</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
