<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165677</identifier>
<setSpec>1697-641X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Osteneocrosis of the jaw for Denosumab: Report of a case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Osteonecrosis of the jaw (ONJ) induced by antiresorptive drugs, mainly bisphosphonates (BF), is widely described in the scientific literature. In recent years, there have been reports of ONJ induced by other antiresorptive drugs such as Denosumab, Bevacizumab and Sunitinib used in cancer patients. Denosumab is a monoclonal antibody that is used in the treatment of osteoporosis and in the prevention of fractures following the treatment of some types of cancer. In this article, we present the case of a patient who developed ONJ. The patient had periodontal disease and osteoporosis, which had been treated for years with Alendronate (oral bisphosphonate) and currently with Denosumab. In addition, she had a poorly adapted removable prosthesis. This work discusses the risk of ONJ associated with these drugs, and the possible influence on their occurrence of certain factors at the local level, as well as the preventive and therapeutic measures that should be adopted in these cases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rubio Ramírez, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>De Arriba de la Fuente, Lorenzo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Sánchez-Rey, M Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Pintor Muñoz, Rosa M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La osteonecrosis de los maxilares (ONM) inducida por fármacos antirresortivos, principalmente los bifosfonatos (BF), está ampliamente descrita en la literatura científica. En los últimos años se han publicado algunos casos de ONM inducidas por otros medicamentos antirresortivos como Denosumab, Bevacizumab y Sunitinib utilizados en pacientes oncológicos. Denosumab es un anticuerpo monoclonal que se utiliza en el tratamiento de la osteoporosis y en la prevención de fracturas tras el tratamiento de algunos tipos cáncer. En este artículo, presentamos el caso de una paciente que desarrolló ONM. La paciente tenía enfermedad periodontal y osteoporosis, que había sido tratada durante años con Alendronato (bifosfonato oral) y actualmente con Denosumab. Además, era portadora de una prótesis removible mal adaptada. En el presente trabajo se discute el riesgo de ONM asociada a estos fármacos, y la posible influencia en su aparición de ciertos factores a nivel local, así como las medidas preventivas y terapéuticas que se deberán adoptar en estos casos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cient. dent. (Ed. impr.);14(2): 129-134, mayo-ago. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165677</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Osteonecrosis maxilar por Denosumab: A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32988^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4220^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10701^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55976^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54489^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
