<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107328</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Experience Using Doxorubicin-Loaded DC Beads ® During Hepatic Chemoembolisation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction Hepatocellular carcinoma is the most common and aggressive liver and biliary tumour. Hepatic chemoembolisation with doxorubicin-loaded DC Beads® is a local therapy for patients with localised nodes, which are not suitable for surgery. The objective of this study is to describe the clinical situations in which this procedure has been used and its early toxicity. Methods Retrospective descriptive study of patients treated with doxorubicin-loaded DC Beads® undergoing hepatic chemoembolisation from October 2006 until July 2009. Data were taken from the Farhos Oncología® programme and clinical histories. Results Twenty-two patients were treated during the study period, 15 men and 6 women, with an average age of 66 years. This technique was used for patients diagnosed with unresectable liver cancer. Out of the patient total, 6 were on the liver transplant waiting list. Patients were assessed using the Child&#150;Pugh score: 15 patients in group A, 5 in group B and 1 in group C; and according to Okuda staging system: 14 were in group I, 6 in group II and 1 in group III. The most common toxicity was post-chemoembolisation in 16 patients, who were treated with symptomatic medication. Discussion Using doxorubicin-loaded microspherical DC Beads® during transarterial chemoembolisation has been adapted to use with scientific evidence and tolerated by all patients. Incidences during administration were mild and were resolved with symptomatic medication (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Carrasco, M. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Capel Alemán, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muros-Ortega, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vila-Clérigues, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendoza-Otero, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubia, A. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción El carcinoma hepatocelular es el más común y agresivo del grupo de tumores hepatobiliares. La quimioembolización hepática con partículas DC Bead® cargadas de doxorrubicina es un tipo de terapia local para pacientes con nódulos localizados, no susceptibles de cirugía. El objetivo de este estudio es describir las situaciones clínicas en las que se ha utilizado este procedimiento y su toxicidad temprana. Métodos Estudio descriptivo retrospectivo de los pacientes tratados con partículas DC Bead® cargadas de doxorrubicina en quimioembolización hepática desde octubre de 2006 hasta julio de 2009. Los datos se obtuvieron del programa Farhos Oncología® y las historias clínicas. Resultados Durante el periodo de estudio fueron tratados 21 pacientes, 15 hombres y 6 mujeres con una mediana de edad de 66 años. El diagnóstico que motivó la utilización de la técnica fue hepatocarcinoma no resecable. Del total de pacientes, 6 se encontraban en lista de espera para trasplante hepático. Los pacientes fueron clasificados según el sistema Child-Pugh: 15 pacientes en el grupo A, 5 en el grupo B y uno en el C, y según el Sistema Okuda: 14 pertenecían al grupo I, 6 al grupo II y uno al grupo III. La toxicidad más frecuente fue la aparición de síndrome posquimioembolización en 16 pacientes, que se resolvió con medicación sintomática. Discusión La utilización de doxorrubicina cargada en microesferas DC Bead® en quimioembolización transarterial se ha ajustado a usos con evidencias científicas y ha sido bien tolerado en todos los pacientes. Las incidencias durante la administración fueron leves y se resolvieron con medicación sintomática (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;35(4): 172-179, Jul. -Ago. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107328</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia de uso de partículas DC Bead ® cargadas con doxorrubicina en quimioembolización hepática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24023^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4420</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8287^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30194^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31855^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9051</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
