<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109117</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Opening of an Acute Orthogeriatric Unit in a general hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Patients with hip fracture (HF), due to their characteristics, require a specific support. The Acute Orthogeriatric Unit (OGU) has been shown to be one of the most beneficial. Objective. To evaluate the main variables of HF patients treated at an OGU and compare them with the previous referral model (RC). Material and methods. A prospective observational study with retrospective control was conducted on 169 patients, split into two groups. In the RC group, patients were admitted to conventional trauma ward. In the OGU group, an early geriatric assessment was performed, and patients were simultaneously attended daily by the orthopaedic surgeon, nurse and geriatrician, and the surgery times, work load, discharge and destination, were planned in a weekly meeting with the rest of professionals. Results. A total of 71 patients were included in the RC group and 96 in the OGU group. The preoperative characteristics were similar, except for a slightly higher comorbidity in the OGU group. The OGU patients were operated on earlier (3.82±2.08 vs 4.61±2.5 days; P&lt;.32), and overall hospital stay was reduced by 28% (11.84±4.04 vs 16.46±8.4 days; P&lt;.001). The functional efficiency (Barthel Index at discharge-Barthel Index at admission/overall stay - stay before surgery) was higher in the OGU group (1.56±0.7 vs 2.61±1.1; P&lt;.05). There were no differences in functional status, mortality or discharge location. Conclusions. The OGU is a level of care that provides effective medical care in HF patients in general hospitals(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escalera Alonso, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velasco Guzmán de Lázaro, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bielza Galindo, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tapia Salinas, Blanca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Martín, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora Casado, Asunción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Cerezo, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Espada, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias Muñana, Estefanía</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los pacientes con fractura de cadera (FC), precisan por sus características una asistencia específica. Una de las que más beneficios han demostrado es la Unidad Ortogeriátrica de Agudos (UOG). Objetivos. Evaluar las principales variables, de los pacientes con FC atendidos en una UOG de nueva creación y compararlas con el modelo interconsultor previo (IC). Material y métodos. Estudio prospectivo observacional con control retrospectivo. Se distribuyen en 2 grupos, 169 pacientes. En el grupo IC, los pacientes ingresan en planta convencional de Traumatología y en el grupo UOG, se realiza una valoración geriátrica precoz, son atendidos a diario por el traumatólogo, la enfermera y el geriatra simultáneamente, y semanalmente en una reunión con el resto de profesionales se planifican los tiempos de cirugía, de carga, de alta y el destino. Resultados. Se incluyen 71 pacientes en el grupo de IC y 96 en el grupo de UOG. Las características previas son homogéneas, salvo una comorbilidad discretamente superior en el grupo de UOG. Los pacientes de UOG se intervinieron antes (3,82±2,08 vs 4,61±2,5 días; p&lt;0,32) y la estancia hospitalaria global se redujo un 28% (11,84±4,04 vs 16,46±8,4 días; p&lt;0,001). La eficiencia funcional (índice de Barthel al alta-índice de Barthel al ingreso/estancia global-estancia precirugía) fue superior en el grupo de UOG (1,56±0,7 vs 2,61±1,1; p&lt;0,05). No hubo diferencias en la situación funcional, la mortalidad o la ubicación al alta. Conclusiones. La UOG es un nivel asistencial que aporta una atención más eficaz de los pacientes con FC en hospitales de segundo nivel(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);48(1): 26-29, ene.-feb.2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109117</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implantación de una Unidad de Ortogeriatría de Agudos en un hospital de segundo nivel</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6778^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6778^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6778^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6778^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6913^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
