<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95263</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-9476</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Since September 2007 until June 2009 a total of 72 interventions of Robotic Radical Prostatectomy Radical Robótica (RRP) have been carried out in our Unit of Clinical Management. The results have been very satisfactory: decrease of the postsurgical bleeding; significant descent of the hospital average stay (2,5 days); a faster recovery of the patient and better rates of erectile function. The surgical technique is executed witha robot Da Vinci, series S, of four arms.Starting from a clinical case, a patient diagnosed in our Service of cancer of prostate, the cares that the staff of nursery in a case ofRRP are exposed once he arrives to the medical ward up to his hospital discharge, as well as the evolution followed by the patient.The model of cares that is followed is based on the eleven functional patterns of Majori Gordon. Finally, domiciliary nursing and Primary Care are highlighted for roles that they play (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Romana, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montes Nieto, I. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Mora, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Martínez, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Suárez, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde septiembre de 2007 hasta junio de 2009 se ha realizado en nuestra Unidad de Gestión Clínica un total de 72 intervenciones de prostatectomía radical robótica (PRR). Los resultados han sido muy satisfactorios: disminución del sangrado posquirúrgico; bajada significativa de la estancia media hospitalaria (2,5 días); una más rápida recuperación del paciente y mejores tasas de función eréctil. La técnica quirúrgica se ejecuta con un robot Da Vinci, serie S, de cuatro brazos. Partiendo de un caso clínico, un paciente diagnosticado en nuestro Servicio de cáncer de próstata, se exponen los cuidados que presta el personal de enfermería en un caso de PRR una vez que llega a la planta hasta su alta hospitalaria, así como la evolución seguida por el paciente.El modelo de cuidados que se sigue se basa en los once patrones funcionales de Majori Gordon. Por último, se resalta el papel que juega en este tipo de cirugía tanto enfermería domiciliaria como de Atención Primaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>ENFURO: Rev. Asoc. Esp. A.T.S. Urol;(113): 9-14, ene.-mar. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95263</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuidados de enfermería en un paciente intervenido de prostatectomía radical asistida por robot</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19270^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19341^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
