<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74672</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Desmoplastic fibroma of the jaw associated with tuberous sclerosis. Literature review and case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Tuberous sclerosis is a congenital anomaly of embryonicdevelopment with an autosomal dominant inheritance. It ischaracterized by the presence of neurologic and dermatologicdisorders and mental retardation. It can affect other organs andsystems and produce orofacial manifestations. Dental enamel defectsare the most frequent intraoral lesion. Bone lesions rarely occur inthe upper jaw. Desmoplastic fibroma is an infrequent, slow-growing,locally aggressive intraosseous fibrous tumor that rarely is associatedwith tuberous sclerosis. We report the clinical case of a 33-year-oldman with tuberous sclerosis and a jaw lesion diagnosed asdesmoplastic fibroma. The diagnostic methods, clinical presentation,and treatment are discussed(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Infante Cossío, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acosta Feria, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Pérez, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Vaquero, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carranza Carranza, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La esclerosis tuberosa es una anomalía congénita del desarrolloembrionario que se transmite de forma autosómica dominante caracterizadapor la presencia por trastornos neurológicos, cutáneos o dermatológicos,y retraso mental. Se pueden afectar otros órganos y sistemas, ydar manifestaciones orofaciales. La lesión a nivel del esmalte dental constituyela lesión intraoral más frecuente. Rara vez se pueden encontrar lesionesóseas en los maxilares. El fibroma desmoplásico es un infrecuente tumorfibroso intraóseo localmente agresivo de lento crecimiento, que se asociamuy rara vez a la esclerosis tuberosa. Presentamos el caso clínico de unpaciente de 33 años afecto de esclerosis tuberosa con una lesión en la mandíbuladiagnosticada como fibroma desmoplásico. Se discuten los métodosdiagnósticos, presentación clínica y tratamiento(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;30(2): 107-114, mar.-abr. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74672</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fibroma desmoplásico de mandíbula asociado a esclerosis tuberosa. Revisión de la literatura y presentación de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31472^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14804^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24235^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
