<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90360</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cardiovascular risk profile of young Spanish people in the province of Cáceres</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The identification and characterisation of cardiovascular risk factors in the youth population helps to determine those individuals who may be predisposed to cardiovascular disease and in designing prevention strategies. Objectives. To determine the anthropometric characteristics, clinical data and cardiovascular risk factors in a sample of young men and women aged 14 to 24 years in the Spanish province of Caceres. Material and methods. Cross-sectional study on a sample of 172 randomly selected young men and women using three-stage sampling: health area, health district, and medical quota. They completed a health questionnaire, physical examination, and their intravenous blood glucose, triglycerides and HDL-cholesterol levels were determined. Results. The cardiovascular risk factor most prevalent among young people in the Spanish province of Caceres is smoking, with a prevalence of 27.9%, with 17.9% males and 36.2% females (P=.01) . Overweight was observed 12.2% of young people (BMI &amp;#8805; 25 kg/m2), and 2.3% were obese (BMI &amp;#8805; 30 kg/m2), with no differences seen between gender. Other risk factors, such as hyper-tension, dyslipidaemia and diabetes are very prevalent in young people. The anthropometric parameters studied significantly correlated with blood pressure levels. Conclusions. The results of our work confirm a high prevalence of cardiovascular risk factors in the Spanish youth population, including smoking and excess weight, and our findings stress the importance of establishing measures, including interventions to promote a healthy lifestyle from an early age(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Martino, Juan Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Barrado, José Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Polo, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barquilla, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Turégano, Soledad</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La identificación y la caracterización de los factores de riesgo cardiovascular en la población juvenil permite identificar a los individuos predispuestos a presentar enfermedad cardiovascular y contribuye a diseñar estrategias de prevención. Objetivos. Conocer las características antropométricas, los datos clínicos y los factores de riesgo cardiovascular de una muestra de jóvenes de ambos sexos de entre 14 y 24 años de la provincia española de Cáceres. Material y métodos. Estudio transversal sobre una muestra de 172 jóvenes de ambos sexos elegidos al azar mediante muestreo trietápico: área de salud, zona de salud y cupo médico. Se les realizó una encuesta de salud, un examen físico y una determinación en sangre venosa de glucemia, triglicéridos y colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de alta densidad. Resultados. El factor de riesgo cardiovascular más prevalente entre los jóvenes españoles de la provincia de Cáceres es el tabaquismo, cuya prevalencia es del 27,9%, el 17,9% de varones y el 36,2% de mujeres (p = 0,01). El 12,2% de los jóvenes presentaba exceso de peso (índice de masa corporal [IMC] &amp;#8805; 25 kg/m2), y el 2,3% eran obesos (IMC &amp;#8805; 30 kg/m2), sin diferencias entre sexos. Otros factores de riesgo como hipertensión arterial, dislipemia y diabetes mellitus son muy poco prevalentes en jóvenes. Los parámetros antropométricos estudiados se correlacionan de forma significativa con las cifras de presión arterial. Conclusiones. Los resultados de nuestro trabajo confirman una prevalencia elevada de factores de riesgo cardiovascular en la población juvenil española, como el tabaquismo y el exceso de peso, y destacan la importancia de establecer, entre otras medidas, intervenciones de promoción de estilos de vida saludable desde etapas tempranas de la vida(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;27(1): 9-14, ene.-feb. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90360</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfil de riesgo cardiovascular de los jóvenes españoles de la provincia de Cáceres</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
