<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113923</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Incidence of cervical spine injuries associated with isolated mandibular fractures caused by physical aggression</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Supraclavicular trauma associated with fractures of the mandible may lead to cervical spine injuries if they are not diagnosed in the comprehensive evaluation of the multiple trauma patient, and may cause subclinical or unnoticed neurological and muscular complications, and even death. Objective: To determine the presentation and incidence of cervical spine injuries associated with mandibular fractures. Material and methods: A prospective, longitudinal and observational study was performed on a 25 patient cohort diagnosed with isolated mandibular fracture during the period from May 2010 to February 2011, and who were seen in the &#147;Dr. Ignacio Morones Prieto&#148; hospital in San Luis Potosi (Mexico) Results: The majority of the 25 patients were students with a mean age of 26.4 years of whom 24 were male and 1 was female. The most frequent type of physical aggression was a violent interpersonal violence. The effects of alcohol on their assailants were identified by 44% of the patients. None of the patients showed any changes in sensitivity and had normal muscle strength. The type of cervical spine lesion was predominantly anterolisthesis. The prevertebral soft tissue was radiographically within normal limits and the, the dimension of the corresponded to the average figures for normal tissue, maximum cervical instability was 3mm. The mean diameters of the air column were, C1: 13.28mm, C3: 11.52mm, and C6: 22.04mm. Conclusions: Cervical spine lesions in patients with mandibular fractures caused by physical assault are common and often have subclinical course, so a clinical and radiographic evaluation is very importan(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jesús Pozos Guillén, Amaury de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toranzo Fernández, José Martín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Valdez, Laura Gabriela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Noyola Frías, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los traumatismos suprclaviculares que se asocian a las fracturas de la mandíbula pueden ser generadores de lesiones cervicales, si estas no son diagnosticadas en la evaluación integral del paciente policontundido pueden pasar desapercibidas causando complicaciones neurológicas, musculares o la muerte. Objetivo. Determinar la presentación e incidencia de las lesiones cervicales asociadas a las fracturas mandibulares. Material y métodos. Estudio tipo cohorte, observacional, prospectivo-longitudinal, donde se incluyeron 25 pacientes con diagnóstico de fractura mandibular aislada durante el periodo de mayo de 2010 a febrero de 2011, que acudieron al servicio de cirugía maxilofacial del Hospital Central «Dr. Ignacio Morones Prieto» en San Luís Potosí. Resultados. De los 25 pacientes, fueron 24 hombres y una mujer, con una edad media de 26,4 años. Los estudiantes fueron los más involucrados. El tipo de agresión física que destacó fue la violencia interpersonal por riña. El 44% de los pacientes identificó los efectos del uso de alcohol en sus agresores. Ninguno de los pacientes presentó alteraciones de sensibilidad y tuvieron una fuerza muscular normal. El tipo de lesión cervical predominante fue la anterolistesis. Radiográficamente, la dimensión de los tejidos blandos prevertebrales correspondió a las cifras promedio de los tejidos sanos, la inestabilidad cervical máxima fue de 3 mm. El diámetro de la columna de aire, fue en promedio de C1:13,28 mm, C3:11,52 mm y C6:22,04 mm. Conclusiones. Las lesiones cervicales en pacientes con fractura mandibular causada por agresión física son comunes pero suelen cursar de manera subclínica por lo que es muy importante la inspección clínica y radiográfica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;35(3): 101-106, jul.-sept. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113923</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incidencia de lesiones cervicales asociadas a fracturas mandibulares aisladas causadas por agresión física</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8509^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33366^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8509^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33366^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33366^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33366^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8509^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8509^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
