<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047921</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The hourly accumulated patient density as an indicator of Emergency Clinic saturation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To define and study the behaviour of a sensitive indicator or patient accumulation in the Outpatient Emergency Clinic, the &#147;hourly accumulated patient density&#148; (HAPD), which indicates the number of patients who, within a given hour, are still pending discharge. Method: Considering the hour of admission and the hour of discharge, the contribution to the HAPD of all paediatric patients attending the Outpatient Emergency Clinic during the last four months in the year 2002 has been calculated. A retrospective descriptive study was carried out differentiating the september-october period, considered as a &#147;normal demand&#148; one, and the novemeber-december one, considered as an &#147;epidemic demand&#148; period. Results: The 80-visit level was nott achieved in any single day of the non-epidemic-demand period, but was exceeded in 18% of the days in the epidemic demand one. The HAPD on arrival of a patient was highest among those who decided to leave without consultation (median, 12). With the HAPD &gt;= 12 criterion, ten days with saturations (16.4%) were detected in the non-epidemic-demand period, versus 39 days (63.9%) in the epidemic-demand one. Conclusions: This indicator detects discrete accumulation periods which are not evidenced by the &#147;number of emergency attendances&#148; analysis, and may help in the improvement of resources assignation and general quality improvement (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Allué Martínez, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jariod Pamias, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Closa Monasterolo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carretero Bellón, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Definir y estudiar el comportamiento de un indicador sensible a la acumulación de pacientes en Urgencias, la densidad horaria de pacientes acumulados (DHPA), que indica el número de pacientes que en una hora determinada están pendientes de alta. Método: Con la hora de admisión y de alta, se ha cuantificando la contribución a la (DHPA) de todos los pacientes pediátricos que transitaron por urgencias en el último cuatrimestre del 2002. Se ha realizado un estudio descriptivo retrospectivo, diferenciando entre septiembre-octubre, período con demanda considerada habitual, y noviembre-diciembre con demanda epidémica. Resultados: En el periodo no epidémico no se llegó ningún día a la cifra de referencia de 80 visitas, mientras que en el periodo epidémico se superó esta cifra el 18% de los días. La DHPA a la llegada de un paciente fue superior en los que decidieron marcharse sin ser visitados (mediana 12). Con el criterio de una DHPA 12, se detectaron 10 días (16,4%) con saturaciones del período no epidémico y, 39 días (63,9%) del epidémico. Conclusiones: Este indicador detecta periodos puntuales de acumulación no evidenciados por el análisis del número de urgencias y puede ayudar en la mejora de la asignación de recursos y la mejora de la calidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);18(4): 215-218, jul. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047921</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La densidad horaria de pacientes acumulados como indicador de saturación en urgencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4705^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28416^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16665^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6453^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6453^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28416^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28416^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28416^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12223</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28416^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16665^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
