<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124189</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of somatostatin receptor scintigraphy in the detection of recurrences and follow-up of carotid paragangliomas</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Octreotide is an active synthetic analogue of Indium-111-labelled somatostatin. It has the ability to bind to their receptors, especially present in neuroendocrine cells. The objective is to evaluate the usefulness of somatostatin receptor scintigraphy (GRS) for the detection of recurrences or residual tumours of carotid paragangliomas. Material and methods: A total of 29 cases in 26 patients treated between January 1996 and December 2010 were considered for analysis. GRS studies were compared with CT angiography and the clinical and pathological findings. We recorded demographic, therapeutic techniques and monitoring data. Results: Mean age 68 years (r-27-82), 76.9% female, complete resection of glomus tumour with vascular reconstruction in 2 cases, CEA in 3 patients, and preoperative embolization in three cases. There was no perioperative mortality. After a mean of 5.8±3.9 years, neurological injury was the most common complication (hypoglossal nerve injury in one case, dysphonia in two cases, and glossopharyngeal injury in another). The GRS study was possible in 17 patients (19.2% mortality, 15.4% lost to follow-up). One of the patients showed abnormal findings in GRS study that were not detected in CT; confirmed surgically as a local recurrence. Conclusions: The GRS is a useful technique for the detection of primary and metastatic neuroendocrine tumours. This technique helps to distinguish between carotid paragangliomas and other head and neck tumours, and is valid for the monitoring and detection of postoperative recurrence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carpintero Mediavilla, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Talavera San Miguel, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brizuela Sanz, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero Puerta, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Fajardo, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino Díaz, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El octreótido es un análogo sintético activo de la somatostatina que marcado con indio-111 tiene la capacidad de unirse a sus receptores, especialmente presentes en células neuroendocrinas. El objetivo es evaluar la utilidad de la gammagrafía de receptores de somatostatina (GRS) para la detección de recurrencias o restos tumorales de paragangliomas carotídeos. Material y métodos: Fueron considerados para análisis 29 casos tratados en 26 pacientes entre enero de 1996 y diciembre de 2010. Los estudios de GRS fueron comparados con angio-TC, así como los hallazgos clínicos y patológicos. Se registraron las variables demográficas, técnicas terapéuticas y los datos de seguimiento. Resultados: Mediana de edad de 68 años (r-27-82), 76,9% mujeres, resección completa del tumor glómico con reconstrucción vascular en 2 casos, endarterectomía carotídea en 3 y embolización preoperatoria en 3 casos. No se registró mortalidad perioperatoria. Tras una mediana de seguimiento de 5,8 ± 3,9 años, la lesión neurológica fue la complicación más frecuente (un nervio hipogloso, disfonía en 2 casos y glosofaríngeo en otro). El estudio GRS fue posible en 17 pacientes (mortalidad 19,2% [5], pérdida de seguimiento 15,4% [4]). Uno de los pacientes mostró hallazgos anormales en el estudio que no fueron detectados con angio-TC, confirmándose quirúrgicamente una recidiva local. Conclusiones: La GRS es una técnica útil para la detección de tumores neuroendocrinos primarios y metastásicos. Esta técnica permite la distinción entre paragangliomas carotídeos y otros tumores de cabeza y cuello, siendo válida para el seguimiento postoperatorio y la detección de recurrencias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;65(5): 169-174, sept.-oct. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124189</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de la gammagrafía de receptores de somatostatina en la detección de recurrencias y seguimiento de paragangliomas carotídeos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22696^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24373^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24338^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2380^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9557^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10421^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30544^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
