<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84416</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical and radiographic assessment of meniscectomy and repair of the anterior cruciate ligament rupture ten years after surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the functional and radiographic status of patients operated upon for meniscectomy and/or ligamentoplasty of the anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) 10 years after surgery. Material and method: We reviewed 35 patients operated upon in 1997 for partial meniscectomy, ligamentoplasty with goosefoot tendons for rupture of the ACL, or both techniques in combination. We evaluated the satisfaction index (1-10 scale), KOOS questionnaire (Knee Osteoarthritis Outcome Score) and the degree of gonarthrosis in antero-posterior and lateral weight-bearing radiography, following the Kellgren-Lawrence scale. The data obtained from each group were analyzed and subjected to descriptive study. Results: Meniscectomy was a risk factor for the development of osteoarthritis. We have not shown reconstruction of the ACL with goosefoot tendons to enhance gonarthrosis over the middle term; almost 70% of all patients had no degenerative signs, and those who did were rated as grade I. Likewise, no relationship was established between the presence of signs of radiographic osteoarthritis and patient perceived quality of life. In our cases, both surgical interventions offer middle term clinical results affording patients a good quality of life and normal working activity, though ACL ligamentoplasty alone obtains better scores according to the KOOS questionnaire, with a lesser incidence of osteoarthritis as determined by imaging techniques (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Forriol Campos, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Serrano, P. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García de las Heras, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Capilla Ramírez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Oliva, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: valorar la situación funcional y radiográfica de los pacientes que fueron intervenidos de meniscectomía, ligamentoplastia de LCA o ambas 10 años después de las cirugías. Material y Método: revisamos 35 pacientes intervenidos de meniscectomía parcial, ligamentoplastia con tendones de la pata de ganso por rotura del LCA, o ambas técnicas conjuntas, en 1997. Evaluamos el índice de satisfacción (escala 1-10), cuestionario KOOS (Knee Osteoarthritis Outcome Score) y el grado de gonartrosis en radiografía antero- posterior y lateral en carga, siguiendo la escala de Kellgren-Lawrence. Se efectuó un análisis de los datos obtenidos en cada grupo para efectuar un estudio descriptivo de los mismos. Resultados: la meniscectomía fue un factor de riesgo para el desarrollo de artrosis, no hemos demostrado que la reconstrucción del LCA con tendones de pata de ganso favorezca la gonartrosis a medio plazo, casi el 70% de los pacientes no tenía signos degenerativos y los que los presentaron se encuadraron en un grado I. Tampoco establecimos una relación entre la presencia de signos de artrosis radiográfica y la percepción de calidad de vida. En nuestros casos, ambas cirugías tienen una evolución clínica a medio plazo que permite al paciente una buena calidad de vida y una actividad laboral normal, si bien la ligamentoplastia aislada de LCA obtiene mejores puntuaciones en el cuestionario KOOS con menor incidencia de artrosis en la imagen (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);19(supl.1): 76-81, 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84416</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración clínica y radiográfica de la meniscectomía y reparación de la rotura del ligamento cruzado anterior con 10 años de evolución</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33556^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28861^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33759^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19395^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33759^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33759^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33759^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28861^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33759^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28861^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33556^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19395^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200800</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
