<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108390</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Induced changes by chronic kidney disease in patients with diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Diabetic nephropathy affects about 25-40% of diabetic patients and is a markerof morbimortality. Complications related to kidney failure in these patientsbecome even more relevant with decreasing glomerular filtration rate.Cardiovascular disease is the most relevant complication, which include coronarydisease, arterial hypertension, left ventricular hypertrophy, congestive cardiacinsufficiency, arrhythmias and pericarditis. Other related renal complicationswill influence the prognosis and evolution of diabetic patients such asanemia, hemorrhagic complications, thrombotic phenomena, alterations of immune response and susceptibility to infections. All these complications, which are present in the patient with diabetic nephropathy, force towards a multifactor approach, which includes firstly the prevention of the appearance/progression of the complications through a control of the risk factors for macro and microangiopathyas glycemic and blood pressure control, proteinuria reduction,avoiding nicotine abuse, keeping closed to the ideal weight, salt intake reduction,antiaggregant treatment and statins therapy, as well as preventing additional renal toxicity(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Górriz Teruel, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beltrán Catalán, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La nefropatía diabética afecta al 25-40% de los pacientes diabéticos y es unmarcador de morbimortalidad. Las complicaciones relacionadas con la insuficienciarenal presentes en estos pacientes se hacen más relevantes a medidaque disminuye el filtrado glomerular. La enfermedad cardiovascular es la complicacióncon más relevancia pronóstica. Ésta incluye la enfermedad coronaria,la hipertensión arterial, la hipertrofia ventricular izquierda, la insuficiencia cardiaca,las arritmias y la pericarditis. Otras complicaciones derivadas de la afectaciónrenal influirán en el pronóstico y evolución del paciente con diabetes,como la anemia, las complicaciones hemorrágicas, los fenómenos trombóticos,las alteraciones en la respuesta inmunitaria y la susceptibilidad a las infecciones.Todas las complicaciones presentes en el paciente con nefropatía diabéticaobligan a un abordaje multifactorial que incluye, en primer lugar, laprevención de la aparición/progresión de las complicaciones mediante el controlde los factores de riesgo de desarrollo de macroangiopatía y microangiopatía:control de la glucemia y de la hipertensión arterial, reducción de la proteinuria,evitación del tabaquismo, mantenimiento del peso ideal, reducción dela ingestión de sal y tratamiento con antiagregantes y estatinas, así como prevenirla nefrotoxicidad(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;26(4): 235-241, jul.-ago. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108390</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambios inducidos por la enfermedad renal crónica en los pacientes con diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33014^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22965^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3948^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3951^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
