<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125693</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Detection of the PMP22 gene duplication in peripheral neuropathy patients: a study in Mexican population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease (CMT) is a neuropathy that affects sensory and motor nerves. The most common CMT subtype is CMT1A due to a PMP22 duplication of a 1.5 Mb fragment on the 17p11.2-p12. The development of a specific molecular technique that detects the PMP22 duplication is necessary for the diagnosis of CMT1A. Aim. To establish a routinary test for detection of the PMP22 gene duplication in Mexican population and to estimate the CMT1A frequency in patients clinically diagnosed as CMT. Patients and methods. A cohort of 157 individuals clinically diagnosed as CMT were analyzed. The detection of the PMP22 gene duplication was performed using the comparative 2&#150;&amp;#916;&amp;#916;CT qPCR method. Results. The comparative 2&#150;&amp;#916;&amp;#916;CT method was sensitive and reliable for the detection of the PMP22 duplication. In order to validate the testing, data was compared with FISH results. Duplication of PMP22 was detected in 79 patients (50.3%). Although CMT1A frequency is different among populations, in Mexican patients it was similar with other populations such  as United States, Australia, Finland, Sweden and Spain. Conclusions. The qPCR technique is an accurate and inexpensive method for the diagnosis of CMT1A. This method can be routinely used in México where CMT1A represents &amp;#8776; 50% of CMT cases. Molecular diagnosis of CMT1A is essential for the genetic counseling and treatment of patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bautista Tirado, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leyva García, Norberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortés, Hernán</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Hernández, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Magaña, Jonathan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escobar Cedillo, Rosa Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La enfermedad de Charcot-Marie-Tooth (CMT) es una neuropatía que afecta los nervios motores y sensitivos, y la CMT1A es el subtipo más frecuente en el mundo. La CMT1A se produce por una duplicación de 1,5 Mb en el locus 17p11.2-p12, donde se localiza el gen PMP22. Para el diagnóstico de CMT1A es importante contar con técnicas moleculares específicas para la determinación de esta mutación. Objetivos. Establecer un método de uso rutinario para detectar la duplicación de PMP22 en la población mexicana y estimar su frecuencia en pacientes con características clínicas para la CMT. Pacientes y métodos. Se analizaron 157 pacientes mexicanos no relacionados entre sí, diagnosticados de CMT por valoración clínica. La determinación de la duplicación de PMP22 se realizó a través de reacción en cadena de la polimerasa en tiempo real mediante el método comparativo 2&amp;#150;&amp;#916;&amp;#916;CT. Resultados. El método 2&#150;&amp;#916;&amp;#916;CT para detectar la duplicación del gen PMP22 mostró ser sensible y fiable. Los resultados fueron consistentes con los obtenidos mediante la técnica de hibridación in situ fluorescente. Se detectó la duplicación de PMP22 en 79 pacientes (50,3%), con un comportamiento similar a lo comunicado en Estados Unidos, Australia, Finlandia, Suecia y España. Sin embargo, se observó que existen diferencias con otras poblaciones. Conclusiones. La técnica de reacción en cadena de la polimerasa cuantitativa se implementó como un diagnóstico molecular de CMT1A eficaz y de bajo coste, por lo que puede utilizarse rutinariamente en México. Esto es esencial para el asesoramiento genético y el tratamiento oportuno de los pacientes con CMT. La frecuencia de la duplicación del gen PMP22 varía entre regiones geográficas, por lo que es importante estimarla en diferentes poblaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;59(3): 111-117, ago. 2014. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125693</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Detección de la duplicación del gen PMP22 en pacientes con neuropatía periférica: estudio en la población mexicana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33897^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24021^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5950^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31887^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53777^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
