<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150462</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Awareness and detection of abuse in the elderly. Towards primary care adapted to the elderly</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The elder abuse has become a reality that increasingly health professionals are faced with greater frequency. This fact creates the need for health professionals work in a multidisciplinary team and based on a care as close as possible to the humanization of care; possess the necessary skills required by this health claim with the objective of ensuring the well-being and quality of life of our elders.  Primary care professionals have a unique opportunity to identify and report abuse to elderly people, therefore it is necessary to train them to help detect, assess and intervene1.  Currently there are no valid, sufficiently sensitive and specific instruments for the detection of child abuse in the elderly1. After reviewing the different used references we have aimed at the elaboration of a «Questionnaire to help professional nursing for early detection of abuse in older people» (table 1) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Estrella González, Isabel M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Prados, M Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El maltrato en el anciano se ha convertido en una realidad a la que cada vez se enfrentan con mayor frecuencia los profesionales sanitarios. Este hecho crea la necesidad de que los profesionales sanitarios, de forma multidisciplinar y basándose en una atención lo más cercana posible a la humanización de los cuidados, posean las competencias necesarias que esta demanda sanitaria requiere con el objetivo de garantizar el bienestar y calidad de vida de nuestros mayores.  Los profesionales de atención primaria tienen una oportunidad única para identificar e informar del maltrato a personas mayores; por ello es necesario formarlos para ayudarles a detectar, evaluar e intervenir1.  En la actualidad no hay instrumentos válidos lo suficientemente sensibles y específicos para la detección de los malos tratos en personas mayores1. Tras revisar las diferentes referencias bibliográficas empleadas nos planteamos como objetivo la elaboración de un «Cuestionario de Ayuda al Profesional de Enfermería de Atención Primaria para la Detección Precoz del Maltrato en las Personas Mayores» (tabla 1) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);26(3): 79-83, sept. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150462</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sensibilización y detección del maltrato en el anciano. Hacia una atención primaria adaptada a los mayores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4626^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23897</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3222^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12075</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
