<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151224</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-5151</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Large increases in learning that result with the active teaching methods in Microbiology in Podiatry Degree</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Our focus here is to improve teaching methods in University microbiology classes and the development of educational practices that explicit engage students while enhacing how they learn Microbiology. These practices including inquiry-based learning (IBL) in which students are actively engaged in the learning process for improving the skills to be acquired as part of their effective learning . This study included 55 Microbiology students of Second Year Degree in Podiatry (Academic Year 2014-2015), and calculated the percentage of students who used these resources 3 IBL, 2IBL, 1IBL, and that did not participate in any and subsequently related to the student performance in Microbiology exam. The IBL questions that were done in class ,were included in the virtual campus , but not including the correction. Students who prepared IBL scored higher en exam questions designed to test synthesis of knowledge and analysis of data. In order to assess the perceived impact of the active learning, the students were asked to fill out a questionnaire evaluating IBL positively considering that this activity can measure learning and improve exam preparation. We believe that the benefits of active learning methods over lecture instruction are consistent and can increases student performance in Microbiology (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramos, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alou, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bas, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Lus, María Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se ha planteado como objetivo la mejora de la calidad de la docencia de la Microbiología mediante la actualización de la metodología docente, introduciendo como actividad docente el aprendizaje activo basado en preguntas (inquirybased learning:IBL) para conseguir mejorar las competencias que deberán adquirir los estudiantes como parte de su formación integral. En este estudio han participado 55 alumnos de Segundo Curso del Grado de Podología (Curso 2014-2015), y se ha calculado el porcentaje de alumnos que participaron en las 3 pruebas (3 IBL), en 2 (2 IBL), en 1 (1 IBL), y los que no participaron en ninguna y posteriormente se relacionó con las calificaciones obtenidas en la asignatura de Microbiología. Se incluyeron las preguntas IBL que se realizaron en clase en el campus virtual de la asignatura, pero sin incluir la corrección de las mismas. En los alumnos que realizaron alguna prueba IBL se obtuvieron calificaciones mejores en las preguntas diseñadas para analizar la síntesis de conocimientos y el análisis de datos que en aquellos que no habían participado en ninguna. Al finalizar la actividad se realizó un estudio transversal a través de un cuestionario autocumplimentado en el que se valoraba la opinión de los alumnos sobre el aprendizaje activo mediante IBL valorando positivamente esta actividad para medir el aprendizaje y mejorar la preparación del examen. Consideramos que el uso del campus virtual unido a la actualización en la metodología docente puede mejorar el rendimiento académico de los estudiantes de Microbiología (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. int. cienc. podol. (Internet);10(2): 85-94, 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151224</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El aprendizaje activo de la microbiología en el Grado de Podología incrementa el rendimiento académico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11462^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9018^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19371</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3499</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
