<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126222</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7113</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Toxicology of perfluorooctane sulfonate (PFOS) such as a polyfluorinated compound model</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Fluorinated organic compounds (FOCs) or perfluorinated chemicals are a group of chemicals widely used at industrial level. Perfluorooctane sulfonate (PFOS) belongs to this group of compounds and it is also the product of degradation of many FOCs. This xenobiotic is extremely persistent in the environment. For the general population, the major routes of exposure to PFOS are the dietary intake, inhalation and dermal contact. PFOS is mainly absorbed orally, it is transported in blood bound to albumin and it is able to cross the placenta and the blood brain barrier. The liver is the main target organ. Besides hepatotoxic and metabolic effects observed after this xenobiotic exposure, different receptors such as peroxisome proliferator activators or PPAR are also involved in their toxicity mechanisms. In addition, PFOS is immunotoxic, by modifying cytokine secretion, cell differentiation of monocytes, lymphocytes, etc. and the activity of natural killer cells. Furthermore, PFOS is neurotoxic at both central and peripheral levels, and it induces significant neuroendocrinological alterations in several organs and tissues of the hypothalamic-pituitary-gonadal and hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axes. (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pereiro, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lafuente, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los compuestos orgánicos fluorados (FOCs) o productos químicos perfluorados constituyen un grupo de sustancias utilizadas ampliamente a nivel industrial. El sulfonato de perfluorooctano (PFOS) pertenece a este grupo de compuestos y es además el producto de degradación de numerosos FOCs. Este xenobiótico es extremadamente persistente en el medioambiente. Para la población general, las principales vías de exposición a PFOS son: la ingesta alimentaria, la vía inhalatoria y el contacto dérmico. El PFOS se absorbe principalmente por vía oral, se transporta en sangre unido a la albúmina, es capaz de atravesar la placenta y la barrera hematoencefálica y se elimina por vía renal. El principal órgano diana del PFOS es el hígado. Además de los efectos hepatotóxicos y metabólicos observados tras la exposición a este xenobiótico, también están involucrados en sus mecanismos de acción tóxica diversos receptores como son los activadores de proliferación de peroxisomas o PPAR. Al mismo tiempo, presenta inmunotoxicidad, alterando la secreción de citoquinas, la diferenciación celular de monocitos, linfocitos, etc. así como la actividad de las células natural killer. Además, el PFOS es neurotóxico, tanto a nivel central como periférico, e induce importantes alteraciones neuroendocrinológicas en distintos órganos y tejidos que constituyen los ejes hipotalámico-hipofisario-gonadal e hipotalámico-hipofisario-adrenal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. toxicol;29(2): 107-116, jul.-dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126222</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Toxicología del sulfonato de perfluorooctano (PFOS) como modelo de compuesto orgánico fluorado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25099</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32392^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4867^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23865</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4867^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4867^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10108^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
