<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123913</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-7546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Electromyographic activities of trunk muscles during stability exercises from Pilates method</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The purpose of this study was to compare the electromyographic (EMG) activity of trunk muscles during stability exercises from Pilates method. Method. Participants were 10 healthy undergraduate students (20.9 ± 2.4 years,162.7 ± 6.7 cm in height; 61.7 ± 6.4 kg body weight and 13.2 ± 5.2 % body fat) with previous Pilates experience. The Pilates exercises: superman (SU), swimming (SW), breaststroke (BS), hip extension (HE) and quadruped arm and lower extremity lift (QA) were performed using maximum isometric effort. The EMG signal of multifidus (MD), dorsal longissimus (DL) and iliocostalis (IC) were recorded. The normalization of the EMG signal was performed using maximum voluntary contraction (% MVC). In statistics treatment, were applied the  Shapiro-Wilk test followed by one-way ANOVA and Bonferroni post hoc (p &lt; 0.05). Results. The exercises SU, SW, BS, and HE showed higher levels of muscle activation (&gt; 40 % MVC) for DL and IC, however, during the QA was observed a significant reduction on muscle activation for all monitored muscles compared to other exercises. Conclusion. Therefore, the above exercises can be performed looking for improve the trunk muscle activation and spine stability, as well as the results found in the current study can be a reference to select exercises during training programs for low back muscles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Paz, G. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lima, V. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miranda, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliveira, C. G de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dantas, E. H. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El propósito de este estudio fue valorar la electromiografía (EMG) de los músculos del tronco durante ejercicios de estabilidad del método Pilates. Método. Los participantes fueron 15 estudiantes universitarios (20,9 ± 2,4 años, 162,7 ± 6,7 cm de altura; 61,7 ± 6,4 kg de peso y 13,2 ± 5,2 % de grasa corporal) con experiencia previa en Pilates. Los ejercicios de Pilates: superman (SU), swimming (SW), breaststroke (BS), hip exension (HE) y el quadruped arm and lower extremity lift (QA) se realizaron con esfuerzo isométrico máximo. Se registró la señal de EMG de multifidus (MD), dorsal longissimus (DL) e iliocostalis (IC). La normalización de la señal EMG se realizó mediante la contracción voluntaria máxima (% CVM). En el análisis estadístico se aplicó el test de Shapiro-Wilk seguido por ANOVA de una vía y de Bonferroni post hoc (p &lt; 0,05). Resultados. Los ejercicios del SU, SW, BS y HE mostraron mayores niveles de activación muscular (&gt; 40 % CVM) para DL y IC, sin embargo, durante el control de calidad se observó una reducción significativa en la activación muscular para todos los músculos controlados en comparación con otros ejercicios. Conclusión. Por lo tanto, los ejercicios anteriores se pueden realizar buscando mejorar la activación de los músculos del tronco y la estabilidad de la columna vertebral. Asimismo, los resultados encontrados en el estudio actual pueden ser una referencia para seleccionar los ejercicios durante los programas de entrenamiento para los músculos de la espalda lumbar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. andal. med. deporte;7(2): 72-77, jun. 2014. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123913</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actividad electromiográfica de los músculos extensores del tronco durante la estabilización física del método Pilates</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7704^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4648^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32124^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
