<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050856</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: analyze the scientific production of Spanish primary care paediatricians (PAP)in order to a better knowledge of their researching profile.Methods: descriptive study of biomedical publications during 1999-2005, in five steps:1) review article by article of Spanish paediatric journals and primary care journals; 2) combinedMedline-Embase search; 3) search by author; 4) personal contact with authors, and 5)contact with key persons. Papers from PAP and signed from Primary Care were identified andauthor, institution, journal, type of publication, topics and funds were described.Results: papers identified were 565, signed by 286 authors (first PAP who signed), from14,955 evaluated articles. Most of them (84.9%) had the PAP as first author. The 48.8% of papersand 70% of original articles were indexed by Medline or Embase and 24 (4.2%) were publishedin English language journals. Four out of ten papers were signed in collaboration withother institutions. A total of 240 papers (42.5%) were original articles, observational studies ingeneral. Three journals gathered more than half papers (Rev Pediatr Aten Primaria, An Pediatrand Aten Primaria). Asturias, La Rioja, Cantabria and Navarra were the regions with better ratioof indexed publications by paediatrician and year. Overall, the regions with more number ofpublications were Madrid, Catalonia and Valencia. Papers were classified in 45 topics and werefound 16 papers supported with external funds.Conclusions: Spanish primary care paediatricians publish 80 papers per year (34 originals).&#150; Only half oft he papers are indexed by Medline or Embase.&#150; There is a trend to publish original papers in indexed journals.&#150; Publication in English language journals is anecdotic</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Suárez Gutiérrez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez Suárez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vigón Fernández,  J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Vázquez, C. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Velascoc, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernardo Trapiello, R. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez García, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peláez Ardura, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Gutiérrez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego García, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: analizar la producción científica de los pediatras de Atención Primaria (PAP)como un medio de aproximación a su perfil investigador.Diseño: estudio descriptivo transversal.Fuentes de información: la información se recuperó en cinco etapas: 1) revisión, artículopor artículo, de revistas pediátricas y de Atención Primaria; 2) búsqueda de artículos combinadaMedline-Embase; 3) búsqueda por autor; 4) contacto personal con autores, y 5) contactocon informadores clave.Mediciones principales: se identificaron trabajos publicados por PAP y firmados desdeAtención Primaria. Para cada trabajo se valoró: autor, filiación, revista, tipo de publicación,temática y financiación.Resultados: en el período 1999-2005 se hallaron 565 trabajos firmados por 286 autores(primeros PAP firmantes), sobre 14.955 artículos evaluados. El 84,9% de los trabajos tenía alpropio PAP como primer autor.El 48,8% del conjunto de trabajos y el 70% de los originales estaban indexados por Medlineo Embase. Un total de 24 trabajos (4,2%) habían sido publicados en revistas de lengua inglesa.El 47,4% de los trabajos fue firmado de forma colaborativa. El 42,5% fueron originales,en general observacionales. Tres revistas (Pediatría de Atención Primaria, Anales de Pediatría yAtención Primaria) acumularon el 56% de los artículos. Asturias, La Rioja, Cantabria y Navarrason las comunidades con mayor tasa de publicaciones indexadas por 100 pediatras y año. Entérminos absolutos, las autonomías con más publicaciones son Madrid, Cataluña y Valencia.Los trabajos fueron catalogados en 45 áreas temáticas. Se identificaron 16 trabajos financiadospor agencias externas.Conclusiones:&#150; Los pediatras españoles de Atención Primaria publican una media de 80 trabajos poraño (34 originales). &#150; Sólo la mitad de los trabajos aparece indexada en Medline y/o Embase.&#150; Hay una mayor tendencia a publicar los trabajos originales en revistas indexadas.&#150; La presencia internacional es anecdótica</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;8(30): 43-58, abr.-jun. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050856</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Publicaciones de los pediatras de Atención Primaria españoles en revistas científicas. 1999-2005</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2710^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
