<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-68195</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Cancer and its oncological treatment cause symptoms which increase the patients risk to suffer from malnutrition. This affects the patients health status negatively by increasing the number of complications, reducing the tolerance to the oncology treatment and a decrease of the patients quality of life. Motivated by this, a group of health professionals from several spanish regions met with the backing of the Sociedad Española de Nutrición Básica y Aplicada (SENBA) to address strategies to improve the quality of nutritional intervention in cancer patients. Methods: This multidisciplinary group developed a protocol describing nutritional assessment and intervention in form of algorithms based on literature and personal experience. The patients are classified in a three step process: 1. type of their oncology treatment (curative or palliative); 2. nutritional risk of the antineoplastic therapy (low, medium or high risk) and 3. depending on the Subjective Global Assessment patient-generated (SGApg). The patients are classified as: A. patients with adequate nutritional state, B. patients with malnutrition or risk of malnutrition and C. patients suffering from severe malnutrition. During one year, the protocol has been used for 226 randomly chosen female and male patients older than 18 years. They were treated by the Medical and Radiotherapy Oncology outpatient clinic. Results: More than a half of the patients were suffering from malnutrition (64%) increasing up to 81% for patients undergoing palliative treatment. Most of them were treated curatively (83%) and received oncology treatment with moderate or high nutritional risk (69%). 68% of patients were affected by some feeding difficulty. The mean percentage of weight loss has been 6.64% ± 0.87 (min 0%, max 33%). Albumin values of 32% of the patients were between 3 and 3.5 g/dl and negatively correlated with feeding difficulties (p = 0.001). The body mass index (BMI) has not found to be a significant parameter for detecting malnutrition (only in 10% of the patients, the value was below 19.9 kg/m2). But a significant linear tendency when compared to feeding problems could be shown, such that in patients with less feeding problems a higher BMI has been found (p = 0.001). More than a half of the patients required nutritional counselling to control symptoms which made food intake difficult. One third of the patients needed oral nutritional supplementation. Following the nutritional intervention the weight of about 60% of the patients could be maintained and of one sixth it could be increased. Conclusion: The application of this protocol is useful, easy and could help detecting malnutrition in oncology patients. It provides the possibility to select those patients who can benefit from a specific nutritional intervention. If possible, the application of the protocol should be started immediatly after cancer is diagnosed. Nutritional support proves efficient for most of the patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marín Caro, MM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zamora Auñón, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villarino Sanz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López- Portabella, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Celaya Pérez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Robledo Sáenz, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lourenço Nogueira, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nogués Boqueras, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo Masferrer, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo Rabaneda, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Loria Kohen, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zarazaga Monzón, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Huerta, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espinosa Rojas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Candela, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luengo Pérez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Suárez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El cáncer, los tratamientos que lo acompañan y los síntomas consecuentes que a su vez generan, aumentan en los pacientes el riesgo de sufrir malnutrición. La cual produce un gran deterioro del estado de salud, con el consecuente aumento de complicaciones, disminución de la tolerancia al tratamiento oncológico y una disminución de la calidad de vida del paciente. Por este motivo, un grupo de profesionales sanitarios de diferentes puntos de España se reunieron con el objetivo de mejorar la intervención nutricional en pacientes oncológicos, con el apoyo de la Sociedad Española de Nutrición Básica y Aplicada (SENBA). Metodología: Este grupo multidisciplinar de profesionales elaboró un documento de consenso basado en la literatura y en la experiencia personal, creando un protocolo de evaluación y de intervención nutricional en forma de algoritmos. Se clasifican los pacientes en tres pasos: 1. según el tipo de tratamiento oncológico que reciben, ya sea de tipo curativo o paliativo; 2. riesgo nutricional de la terapia antineoplásica (bajo, mediano, o alto riesgo), y 3. de acuerdo a la Valoración Global Subjetiva-Generada por el paciente (VGS-gp), que clasifica a los pacientes en: A. pacientes con adecuado estado nutricional, B. pacientes con malnutrición o a riesgo de malnutrición y C. pacientes con malnutrición severa. Durante un año el protocolo se puso en marcha en 226 pacientes mayores de 18 años de ambos sexos, escogidos al azar en las consultas externas de Radioterapia Oncológica y Oncología Médica. Resultados: Más de la mitad sufren malnutrición (64%), y este valor se incrementa llegando hasta un 81% en pacientes con tratamiento paliativo. La mayoría de los pacientes tienen tratamiento de intención curativa (83%) y reciben tratamiento oncológico de intensidad moderada o de alto riesgo nutricional (69%). Un 68% de los pacientes tienen algún tipo de dificultad en la alimentación. La media en el porcentaje de pérdida de peso es del 6,64% ± 0,87 (min 0, máx 33%). El 32% de la población presenta cifras de albúmina entre 3 y 3,5 g/dl, existiendo una correlación negativa entre ésta y las dificultades con la alimentación p = 0,001. El IMC no mostró ser un parámetro significativo para detectar malnutrición (sólo un 10% se encontraba por debajo de 19,9 kg/m2), pero tiene una tendencia lineal significativa con las dificultades en la alimentación, de forma tal que a medida que disminuye el IMC aumentan las dificultades p = 0,001. Más de la mitad de la población, requirió recomendaciones dietéticas específicas para el control de los síntomas que dificultaban la ingesta y una tercera parte de la población necesitó la indicación de suplementos nutricionales. Tras la intervención nutricional más de la mitad (60%) mantuvo su peso y una sexta parte lo aumentó. Conclusión: La aplicación de este protocolo es útil, sencillo y podría facilitar la detección de malnutrición en los pacientes oncológicos. Seleccionando a los pacientes que realmente se podrían beneficiar de una intervención nutricional específica, pero debería aplicarse al inicio coincidiendo si fuera posible con el diagnóstico de la enfermedad. El soporte nutricional resulta eficaz en la mayoría de los pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;23(5): 458-468, sept.-oct. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-68195</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32108^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16556^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
