<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91747</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A Project of evaluation of results in child and adolescent psychoanalytic psychotherapy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper presents a Project of evaluation of child psychoanalytical psychotherapy treatments. The data analysis of the population studied revealed that psychotherapies obtaining the best results were those psychotherapies whose length came closest to the pre-established length, those undertaken with the youngest population groups and those with patients where anxiety had a predominant role amongst clinical symptoms (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miquel, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chancho, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ger, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Noguero, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sala, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montserrat, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ríos, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La evaluación de los tratamientos de psicoterapia psicoanalítica infantil es el objetivo principal de este trabajo. Del análisis de las variables de la población en tratamiento se destaca que aquellas psicoterapias que obtienen mejores resultados son las que su duración se acerca más a la preestablecida, las que se realizan en población de menor edad y en paciente con trastornos en que la ansiedad ocupa en papel predominante en la sintomatología clínica que presentan (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(14): 81-85, nov. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91747</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Un proyecto de evaluación de resultados en psicoterapia psicoanalítica infanto-juvenil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28380^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56095^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33540</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200911</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
