<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151774</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">HSP-90 expression as a predictor of response to radiotherapy in head and neck cancer patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: HSP-90 is an intracellular protein that protects the cell from environmental stress situations. The overexpression of HSP-90 isoforms could serve as a mechanism of resistance to radiotherapy for tumour cells. We studied this effect in a sample of head and neck tumours. Methods: We included 87 patients diagnosed with oral cavity, oropharynx, larynx and hypopharynx tumours. We studied the expression of the HSP-90 isoforms by real-time PCR on pre-treatment biopsy samples. We analysed the relationship between HSP-90 expression levels and local relapse of the tumour with CRT decision trees.  Results: The expression levels of the inducible citosolic isoform (HSP90AA) allowed the definition of 2 groups of patients with different rates of local relapse. The group with a low expression level showed a 2.9% local relapse rate, while the group with a high expression level showed a 38.2% rate. Survival curves showed differences in time to local relapse for both groups of patients. These differences did not reach statistical significance. Conclusions: Radiotherapy response was related to expression levels of HSP-90 in a sample of head and neck cancer patients. This result could prove useful in the selection of treatments for this group of patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Camacho Pérez de Madrid, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Lorenzo, Jacinto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León Vintró, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: La HSP-90 es una proteína intracelular que protege la célula en situaciones de estrés ambiental. El objetivo de este estudio es valorar si la sobreexpresión de alguna de las isoformas de HSP-90 confiere resistencia a la radioterapia en una muestra de tumores de cabeza y cuello. Métodos: Se incluyeron en el estudio 87 pacientes con tumores de cavidad oral, orofaringe, laringe e hipofaringe. En muestras de biopsia pretratamiento se analizaron mediante PCR en tiempo real la expresión de las isoformas de HSP-90. Se utilizaron árboles de decisión para estudiar la relación entre el nivel de expresión de HSP-90 y la recidiva local del tumor. Resultados: La expresión de la isoforma citosólica inducible (HSP90AA) permitió definir 2 grupos con diferentes índices de recidiva local. El grupo con expresión baja presentó un 21,9% de recidivas frente al 38,2% del grupo con expresión alta. Las curvas de supervivencia muestran diferencias en el tiempo libre de recidiva local entre ambos grupos, aunque estas diferencias no alcanzaron significación estadística. Conclusiones: La respuesta de los tumores de cabeza y cuello a la radioterapia parece relacionada con la expresión de HSP-90. Este resultado podría ser de utilidad en la selección de tratamientos en este grupo de pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;67(3): 130-134, mayo-jun. 2016. tab, graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151774</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Expresión de Heat Shock Protein-90 (HSP-90) como factor predictor de la respuesta a radioterapia en pacientes con tumores de cabeza y cuello</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54677^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6409^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12314^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13915</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32204^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6409^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6409^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22877</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9557^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32204^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32204^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
