<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055288</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Staphylococcus aureus prostatic abscess and subdural empyema: a case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: To report one case of prostatic abscess and subdural empyema by    Staphylococcus aureus.    Methods: We describe the case of a 51 year old male patient who was diagnosed of prostatic abscess and    subdural empyema by Staphilococcus aureus. We use clinical presentation and physical exploration based    on rectal digital examination, as diagnostic approach method. And computerized axial tomography and    transrectal ultrasonography, which allows the guided needle drainage of the abscess, as diagnostic confirmation    methods.    Results: The clinical picture resolved with the transrectal ultrasonography guided needle aspiration of    the abscess and conservative treatment with antibiotics and urinary diversion.    Conclusions: Prostatic abscess is an uncommon entity nowadays. Provided the great variety of symptoms,    a great degree of clinical suspicion is needed for the diagnosis, and once it is got it, immediate aggressive    treatment must be initiated. Transrectal ultrasonography allows not only the diagnosis, but also the    drainage of the abscess. The culture of the obtained material identifies the etiological agent and the most    specific antibiotic therapy</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Duque Ruiz, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanchís Bonet, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Carballo, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leiva Galvis, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Parada, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrera Meirás, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo: Presentamos el caso de un paciente con absceso prostático y empiema subdural    por Staphilococo aureus.    Material y método: Descripción de un caso de un paciente de 51 años de edad diagnosticado de absceso    prostático y empiema subdural por Staphilococo aureus. Utilizamos como método de aproximación diagnóstica    la sospecha clínica y la exploración física mediante tacto rectal. Como métodos de confirmación    diagnóstica, pruebas de imagen, como la tomografía axial computerizada y la ecografía transrectal, que permite    además el drenaje del material purulento.    Resultados: El cuadro se resolvió con ecografía transrectal y punción-drenaje de la colección y con tratamiento    conservador en base a antibioterapia y derivación urinaria.    Conclusiones: El absceso prostático es en la actualidad una patología poco frecuente. Dada la gran variedad    de presentación de esta entidad, hay que tener un alto grado de sospecha para su diagnóstico y una    vez realizado comenzar un tratamiento inmediato agresivo. La ecografía transrectal permite, no sólo el diagnóstico,    sino también la punción-drenaje del contenido purulento. El cultivo de las muestras obtenidas    identifica el agente causante y la antibioterapia más adecuada</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;31(5): 548-552, mayo 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055288</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Absceso prostático por Sthapilococo aureus y empiema subdural: presentación de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13596^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37562^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32383^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13742^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11912^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13590^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
