<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61677</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Unilateral pulmonary edema</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Unilateral pulmonary edema has been reported in the literature, but it is a very rare condition that can easily be confused with other diagnoses. Acute unilateral pulmonary edema can be either ipsilateral or contra lateral to the causative process. An understanding of the underlying pathophysiologic mechanism is essential if we are to diagnose this condition correctly and prescribe appropriate treatment. We report a case of left-sided pulmonary edema in a 57-yearoldman who had been diagnosed 4 days earlier with right basilar pneumonia. The absence of any signs of sepsis or left ventricular failure plus the asymmetric presentation of edema led us to suspect unilateral pulmonary embolism in the leftlung. The diagnosis was confirmed by spiral computed tomography (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lezama García de Cortázar, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Caudevilla, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí Cabané, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berruete Cilveti, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lores Domínguez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El edema de pulmón unilateral está descrito en la literatura médica, pero es una situación muy poco frecuente y de fácil confusión en su diagnóstico. El edema agudo de pulmón unilateral puede ser ipsilateral al proceso que lo produce o contralateral al mismo. Es importante comprender el mecanismo fisiopatológico que lo produce para llegara un correcto diagnóstico y adecuado tratamiento. A este respecto presentamos un caso de edema pulmonar izquierdo en un paciente de 57 años, diagnosticado de neumonía basal derecha 4 días antes, que reacude por empeoramiento de su situación clínica. La ausencia de signos de sepsis, de fallo ventricular izquierdo y la asimetría del edema permitió sospechar de tromboembolismo pulmonar unilateral izquierdo, que se confirmó con tomografía computarizada helicoidal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);21(4): 309-311, jul.-ago. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61677</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Edema pulmonar unilateral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30693^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37549^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12091^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12092^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
