<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81265</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-2399</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Improving the case of critical patient family members: Agreed on strategies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">IntroductionWithin the context of participatory action research (PAR), a 4-stage process was established with the general aim of promoting improvements in the care offered to families of patients in the Intensive Care Unit (ICU). The 4 stages consisted of a situational diagnosis, proposals for change, the design and implementation of the proposals, and an evaluation. This paper presents the first 2 stages.ObjectivesTo define the attention given to families of patients in the Intensive Care Unit. To reach a consensus on areas for action/intervention in the unit.Materials and methodA qualitative methodology. Design: PAR. Data-collection technique: 4 focus groups made up of 10 professionals, and consensus with support groups made up of 30 members. Content analysis was performed. The theoretical saturation point was reached.ResultsTwo documents were drawn up: 1) A situational diagnosis, describing the current situation of the attention given to families and 2) 10 proposals for change, 5 of which were given priority. They were: a session to familiarize professionals with evidence concerning families of patients in the ICU and the handing out of informative leaflets, the improvement of (nurse-family and intra-team) informative procedures, more privacy for patients and a reduction in environmental noise, a training plan for professionals, and change in the visiting policy.ConclusionBy using consensus-based methodologies, strategies for change can be prioritized and designed, adapted to the context in which they will be applied(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno Mulet, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Val Pérez, J. V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zaforteza Lallemand, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina Santiago, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz López, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto González, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canet Ferrer, T. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto González, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Martín, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">IntroducciónEn el contexto de una investigación-acción participativa (IAP), con el objetivo general de promover un cambio para mejorar los cuidados que se ofertan a los familiares del paciente ingresado en la unidad de cuidados intensivos (UCI), se estableció un proceso en 4 fases: diagnóstico de situación, propuestas de cambio, diseño e implementación de las propuestas y evaluación. Este trabajo presenta las 2 primeras fases.ObjetivosConocer las características de la atención a los familiares en la unidad. Alcanzar el consenso sobre las áreas de acción-intervención en esta unidad.Material y métodoMetodología cualitativa. Diseño: IAP. Técnica de recogida de datos: 4 grupos focales y consenso con grupos de apoyo. Participaron 10 profesionales en los grupos focales y 30 en los grupos de apoyo. Se realizó análisis de contenido. Se alcanzó el punto de saturación teórica.ResultadosSe elaboraron 2 documentos: 1) diagnóstico de situación en el que se describe la situación actual de la atención de los familiares y 2) 10 propuestas de cambio, de las que se priorizaron 5, que eran: difusión entre los profesionales de la evidencia sobre familiares en la UCI a través de una sesión y la entrega de trípticos informativos, mejora de los procesos de información (enfermera-familia e intraequipo), protección de la intimidad de los pacientes y disminución del ruido ambiental, plan de formación para los profesionales y cambio en la política de visitas.ConclusiónEl uso de metodologías de consenso permiten priorizar y diseñar estrategias de cambio adecuadas al contexto en el que se van a aplicar(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Intensiva;21(1): 11-19, ene. -marz. 2010. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81265</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mejorando el cuidado a los familiares del paciente crítico: estrategias consensuadas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23905</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37619</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9152</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23905^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
