<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050053</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adult progeria (Werner syndrome). Follow-up of 2 cases from primary care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Crohn's disease is a chronic and recurrent inflammatory disorder of the gastrointestinal tract mainly affecting the terminal ileum and colon. Its etiology is unknown and it has a systemic character, that follows a recurrent and remittent course. From the clinical point of view, it is characterized by a non-specific and chronic picture of diarrhea and abdominal pain that are frequently associated to extraintestinal manifestations. Diagnosis is based on the combination of clinical, radiological, endoscopic and pathology data. In order to choose the best treatment, the fact that it is an acute episode, its intensity and extension must be verified. Management of the corticoresistant and corticorefractory forms have special importance</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Sánchez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Vellido, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Perera, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nicolás Blanco, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad de Crohn es un trastorno inflamatorio crónico y recurrente del tubo digestivo con afectación preferente del íleon terminal y el colon. De etiología desconocida y carácter sistémico, sigue un curso recurrente y remitente. Desde el punto de vista clínico, se caracteriza por un cuadro inespecífico y crónico de diarrea y dolor abdominal frecuentemente asociado a manifestaciones extraintestinales. El diagnóstico se basa en la combinación de datos clínicos, radiológicos, endoscópicos y anatomopatológicos. Para seleccionar el tratamiento adecuado es necesario confirmar que se trata de un brote agudo, la intensidad del mismo y el grado de extensión. Teniendo especial importancia el manejo de las formas corticorresistentes y corticorrefractarias</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);32(8): 415-417, oct. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050053</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Varón de 29 años con síndrome constitucional y fiebre</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3994^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5444^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
