<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88597</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Contact Dermatitis Caused by Acrylates Among 8 Workers in an Elevator Factory</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Acrylates are widely used low-molecular-weight substances, initially introduced in industry in the 1930s and subsequently applied also in medicine and the home. One of their main features is the ability to undergo polymerization. The most commonly used acrylic compounds are cyanoacrylates, methacrylates, and acrylates. Objective: To confirm suspicion of occupational disease in a group of workers in an elevator factory. Material and methods: We studied 8 patients with dermatitis of the hands and finger pads. In their work, the patients came into contact with acrylates. Patch testing was applied with an acrylate panel (BIAL-Aristegui, Bilbao, Spain). Results: Seven of the patients (87.5%) had a positive result with 1% ethylene glycol dimethacrylate. Positive results were also observed for 2% hydroxyethyl methacrylate (5 patients, 62.5%), 1% triethylene glycol dimethacrylate (4 patients, 50%), 10% ethyl methacrylate monomer (3 patients, 37.5%), 10% methyl methacrylate monomer (2 patients, 25%), 1% ethyl acrylate (1 patient, 12.5%), and 0.1% acrylic acid (1 patient, 12.5%). Conclusions: We highlight the strong sensitizing capacity of acrylates and the importance of taking all necessary preventive measures in industries where these substances are used. Such measures should include avoidance of contact with the product in cases where sensitization has been confirmed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Formoso, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maraví-Cecilia, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Anca-Fernández, J. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Torres, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los acrilatos son sustancias químicas de bajo peso molecular, con una amplia utilización en la industria (desde su introducción en los años treinta), la medicina y el medio doméstico, que destacan por sus propiedades de polimerización. Los compuestos acrílicos más utilizados son los cianoacrilatos, los metacrilatos y los acrilatos. Objetivo: Establecer el diagnóstico de sospecha de enfermedad profesional en un grupo de trabajadores de una fábrica de ascensores. Material y métodos: Se estudian un total de 8 pacientes que presentan clínica de dermatitis en las manos, así como pulpitis en los dedos, y que trabajan en contacto con acrilatos. Se realizaron pruebas epicutáneas con batería de acrilatos (BIAL-Aristegui, Bilbao, España). Resultados: El 87,5% mostró positividad frente al dimetacrilato de etilenglicol al 1%. También mostraron positividad el hidroxietilmetacrilato al 2% (62,5%), el dimetacrilato de trietilenglicol al 1% (50%), el monómero de metil metacrilato al 10% (25%) y el monómero de etil metacrilato al 10% (37,5%), el acrilato de etilo al 1% (12,5%) y el ácido acrílico al 0,1% (12,5%). Conclusiones: Destacamos el alto poder sensibilizante de los acrilatos y la importancia de extremar las medidas preventivas en las distintas industrias, así como la evitación del contacto con el producto en los casos de sensibilización demostrada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;101(4): 336-340, mayo 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88597</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dermatitis de contacto a acrilatos en una industria de fabricación de ascensores. A propósito de 8 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3894^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d185^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d185^s22025</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12107^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d185^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12107^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12107^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3894^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3894^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11545^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11545^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30756^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30756^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11545^s22025</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30756^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
