<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-68369</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: VEIA study is an evolutional registry of acute poisonings (AP) attended in the Emergency Room of the Doce de Octubre Hospitalin Madrid (Spain) in a whole year (1979, 1985, 1990, 1994,1997 and 2000). We present the 2004 study and compare the results with the previous years. Methods and results: Methodology has been identical across VEIA STUDY. Of 1508 AP, 610 are suicide attempts (IAVIS), 319 ethylic, (IAVE), and 218 by illicit drugs (IAVD). Of the 2,259 toxics involved,48% are medications (50% benzodiacepines) alcohol 25% and illicit drugs 13%. Conclusions: There is an important increase (34%) of cases and the incidence surpasses all published in our country. There are no gender differences nor in the whole neither the Health Area Census, but there are differences in IAVIS, IAVE and IAVD. IAVIS increase in 35%. Benzodiacepines poisoning increases two-fold as well as antidepressive drugs do in women. In men also increase, but in a minor extent. Acetaminophen remains the same in 23%. NSAID&#146;s, adjuvants and myorelaxants increase in women as do also alcohol and other poisons that almost equal men&#146;s. There are 13 cases of IAVIS in patients with alimentary disorders. Among men, a quarter are illicit drug abusers. In IAVE, the group without alcoholism grows and the total decreases. Illicit drugs duplicate the number of the former year. Cocaine supposes already 2/3 of the cases, MDMA ascends to 22 cases and they appear new substancesas glue, without doubt as an effect of immigration and ketamine. Finally 205 household accidents and 57 industrial injuries complete the series</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz Brasero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Pacho, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Gil, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero Vallés, P. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dorado Pombo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cantero Bengoechea, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yubero Salgado, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibero Esparza, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: VEIA es un registro evolutivo de las intoxicaciones agudas (IA) atendidas en Urgencias del Hospital Doce de Octubre de Madrid en un año completo (1979 [2], 1985 [3], 1990 [4], 1994 [5], 1997 [6] y 2000 [7]) presentamos el estudio del año 2004 y comparamos los resultados con los de años anteriores (1-7). Métodos y resultados: el método es idéntico. De las 1.508 IA, 610 son intentos de suicidio (IBAIS) 319 etílicas (IAVE) y 219 drogas (IAVD). De los 2.259 tóxicos implicados el 48% son medicamentos (50% diazepóxidos) alcohol 25% y drogas el 13%. Conclusiones: este año ha supuesto un importante aumento (34%) del número de casos y la incidencia supera a todas las publicadas en nuestro país (25,31,40). Aunque en el conjunto no hay diferencia significativa de género con el Censo de Área, la hay en IBAIS, IAVE y IAVD. Las IBAIS crecen un 35%; Se duplica el uso de benzodiacepinas y antidepresivos en los IS de mujeres y crecen también en hombres pero menos; El paracetamol se mantiene en el 23% AINE, adyuvantes y míorelajantes aumentan en mujeres y también el uso de alcohol y otros no fármacos en los is de mujeres casi igualándose con los hombres. La cuarta parte de los hombres con IS eran adictos y aparecen 13 casos de trastornos alimentarios. En las IAVE crecen el grupo sin etilismo y baja eltotal. Las drogas se duplican con respecto al año anterior: la cocaína supone los 2/3 también suben la MDMA (22 casos) y aparecen nuevas drogas, como el pegamento, sin duda efecto de la inmigración, y ketamina; incluso cuatro casos no pudieron ser etiquetados por la falta de medios diagnósticos en la urgencia</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;25(6): 262-268, jun. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-68369</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d13792^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5656^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11471^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30931^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d439^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11471^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d439^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d439^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8866^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13792^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
