<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106005</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of a questionnaire to evaluate patient safety in clinical laboratories</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: The aim of this study was to prepare, pilot and validate a questionnaire to evaluate patientsafety in the speci&amp;#64257;c context of clinical laboratories.Methods: Aspeci&amp;#64257;c questionnaire on patient safety in the laboratory,with 62 items grouped into six areas,was developed, taking into consideration the diverse human and laboratory contextual factors whichmay contribute to producing errors. A pilot study of 30 interviews was carried out, including validityand reliability analyses using principal components factor analysis and Cronbach&#146;s alpha. Subsequently,240 questionnaires were sent to 21 hospitals, followed by a test-retest of 41 questionnaires with thede&amp;#64257;nitive version.Results: The sample analyzedwas composed of 225 questionnaires (anoverall response rate of 80%). Ofthe62 items initially assessed, 17were eliminated due to non-compliancewith the criteria established beforethe principal components factor analysis was performed. For the 45 remaining items, 12 componentswere identi&amp;#64257;ed, with an cumulative variance of 69.5%. In seven of the 10 components with two or moreitems, Cronbach&#146;s alpha was higher than 0.7. The questionnaire items assessed in the test-retest werefound to be stable.Conclusions: We present the &amp;#64257;rst questionnaire with suf&amp;#64257;ciently proven validity and reliability for evaluating patient safety in the speci&amp;#64257;c context of clinical laboratories. This questionnaire provides a usefulinstrument to perform a subsequent macrostudy of hospital clinical laboratories in Spain. The questionnaire can also be used to monitor and promote commitment to patient safety within the search forcontinuous quality improvement (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grupo de la Comisión de Gestión del Laboratorio Clínico de la SEQC</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivosEs objeto de este trabajo elaborar, pilotar y validar un cuestionario para evaluar la seguridad del paciente en el ámbito específico de los laboratorios clínicos.MétodosSe elaboró un cuestionario específico sobre seguridad del paciente en el laboratorio, con 62 ítems agrupados en 6 áreas, partiendo de los diferentes factores humanos y del entorno de los laboratorios, que contribuyen a que se generen errores. Se realizó un pilotaje de 30 cuestionarios, análisis de validez y fiabilidad mediante análisis factorial de componentes principales y alfa de Cronbach con envío de 240 cuestionarios a 21 hospitales, y test-retest con 41 cuestionarios con la versión definitiva.ResultadosLa muestra la formaron 225 cuestionarios (tasa de respuesta del 80%). De los 62 ítems inicialmente valorados, se descartaron 17 por no cumplir los criterios previos a la realización del análisis factorial de componentes principales. Para los 45 ítems restantes se identificaron 12 componentes, con una varianza acumulada del 69,5%. En 7 de los 10 componentes con dos o más ítems, el alfa de Cronbach fue superior a 0,7. Los ítems valorados del cuestionario para el test-retest resultaron estables.ConclusionesSe presenta el primer cuestionario con garantías de validez y fiabilidad para evaluar la seguridad del paciente en el ámbito específico de los laboratorios clínicos. El cuestionario resulta una herramienta de utilidad para realizar tanto un posterior macroestudio de los laboratorios clínicos hospitalarios en España como, a nivel particular, para monitorizar y fomentar el compromiso y la responsabilidad con la seguridad del paciente en un entorno de mejora continua (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;26(6): 560-565, Nov. -Dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106005</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación de un cuestionario para evaluar la seguridad del paciente en los laboratorios clínicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22929^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31061^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17193^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
