<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108173</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness and safety of a blood glucose control protocol in hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the effectiveness and safety of a glucose control protocol designed to manage patients with diabetes in hospital. Material and methods: An interventional, prospective and open study was designed for patients with diabetes admitted in a conventional hospital setting. Patients were randomized to an intervention group (glucose control protocol) or to a control group (conventional treatment for diabetes). Blood glucose was performed every 48hours. The primary endpoint was to obtain a pre-prandial blood glucose between 80 and 180mg/dl, and the secondary endpoint was the absence of hypoglycemia. Results: The study included a total of 104 patients (51.0% male), with a mean age of 67.8±9.2 years old, 13.7±10.2 years since onset of diabetes, and mean HbA1c of 7.8±1.5%. The patients in the intervention group showed a significant improvement in glucose control before all meals as well as in the 24hour mean compared to day 0 and with the control group. In the first week, patients achieved a mean blood glucose of 148.2±30.3mg/dl. The percentage of patients with blood glucose between 80 and 180mg/dl gradually increased, exceeding 50% of patients from day 4 for fasting blood glucose, day 5 for blood glucose before lunch, and day 7 for blood glucose before dinner. Seven patients (13.4%) had mild hypoglycemia in the intervention group, and nine (17.3%) in the control group (P=0.817). Conclusions: The use of a blood glucose control protocol in hospital settings is effective for improving metabolic control and to achieve the targets, with a low rate of associated hypoglycemia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Baena Nieto, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar Diosdado, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Tinoco, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carral-San Laureano, Florentino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Barea, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cayón Blanco, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la efectividad y seguridad de un protocolo de control glucémico para pacientes con diabetes mellitus (DM) en el medio hospitalario. Material y métodos: Estudio de intervención, prospectivo y abierto realizado en pacientes con DM ingresados en planta de hospitalización convencional. Los pacientes fueron asignados a un grupo de intervención (protocolo de control glucémico), o a un grupo control (tratamiento para la diabetes según práctica habitual) con evaluaciones cada 48 h, estableciéndose como objetivo primario la obtención de glucemias preprandiales entre 80 y 180mg/dl, siendo el objetivo secundario la ausencia de hipoglucemias. Resultados: Se incluyó a 104 pacientes de 67,8±9,2 años de edad, 13,7±10,2 años de evolución de diabetes y HbA1c media de 7,8±1,5%. En el grupo de intervención se observó una mejoría significativa en las glucemias capilares antes del desayuno, almuerzo, cena y media de 24 h tanto con respecto al día 0 como comparativamente con el grupo control, alcanzando el 7.° día de seguimiento una glucemia media de 148,2±30,3mg/dl. El porcentaje de pacientes con glucemia entre 80 y 180mg/dl superó el 50% desde el día 4 para la glucemia en ayunas, desde el día 5 para la glucemia antes del almuerzo y desde el día 7 para la glucemia antes de la cena. Siete pacientes (13,4%) presentaron hipoglucemias leves en el grupo de intervención y 9 (17,3%) en el grupo control (p=0,817). Conclusiones: La aplicación de un protocolo de control glucémico en el medio hospitalario es efectiva para mejorar el control metabólico y alcanzar los objetivos establecidos, con un bajo número de hipoglucemias asociadas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;28(6): 136-143, nov.-dic. 2012. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108173</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad y seguridad de un modelo protocolizado de control glucémico en el medio hospitalario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7181^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
