<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142775</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4603</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this paper it is explained the evolution of the intervention during two years of a Language Delayed child of 3 years old. The theoretical frame of the interventions emphasieces the social and cognitive dimensions in the langauge acquisition. At the beginng a psycholinguistic profile of the child competence was established and accordig to it were defined the goals of his rehabilitation in communication and language. The presentation of the evolution of the intervention has been divided in 6 time points, and in each of them the language state is described and illustrated with typical exemples together with the goals, methodology and strategies for improving language production. The evolution is presented with the final profile of the child. It is concluded that early diagnosisi is a real need as well as early profiles for evaluation and intervention in order to avoid a consolidation of the early difficulties in more severe impairments (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Pérez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giró Murtró, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se resume la intervención logopédica realizada durante dos cursos escolares a un niño que a los 3 años presentaba un retraso del lenguaje. La reeducación programada, que enfatiza las dimensiones social y cognitiva de la adquisición del lenguaje, se inició con la elaboración del perfil psicolingüístico que determinó tanto la situación lingüística inicial del niño como los objetivos a trabajar, en este caso, referidos a la comunicación y el lenguaje. La presentación de la intervención se ha estructurado en 6 momentos, en cada uno de los cuales se citan los objetivos planteados para ese momento (el qué trabajar), la metodología y las estrategias utilizadas (el cómo trabajar), los avances logrados por el niño y ejemplos de su producción. La evolución queda reflejada en el artículo con la presentación del perfil final de comunicación y lenguaje. Del artículo se concluye la necesidad de realizar un diagnóstico y una intervención precoz para que dificultades iniciales no se consoliden en un trastorno, de disponer de perfiles para su evaluación y de tener un marco teórico que guíe nuestra intervención (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. logop. foniatr. audiol. (Ed. impr.);22(2): 111-117, abr.-jun. 2002. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142775</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervención en un caso con dificultades del lenguaje (4-6 años)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7986^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7983^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7985</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12015^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
