<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051689</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The acute pseudobstruction of the colon or Ogilvie´s syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The acute pseudobstruction of the colon or Ogilvie&#146;s syndrome is a infrecuent pathology of acute or subacute evolution, that is associated to different clinical or surgical pathologies, and whose pathophysilogy continues being not known. The treatment begins with general measures and if these are not effective, with the surgical decompression of colon to avoid the most serious complication and it frequents that it is the perforation of the ceacum. We present a case of an acute and idiopathic dilatation of colon in an adult man who entered by an episode of acute respiratory insufficiency, and that was solved with preservative medical treatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gordillo Morera, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hormeño Bermejo, R. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montero Leal, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Moreno, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La pseudobstrucción aguda del colon o síndrome de Ogilvie es una entidad clínica rara de curso agudo o subagudo que se asocia a diferentes patologías clínicas o quirúrgicas, y cuya etiopatogenia sigue siendo desconocida. El tratamiento se inicia con medidas generales y si estas no son efectivas, con la descompresión quirúrgica del colón para evitar la complicación más grave y frecuente que es la perforación cecal. Presentamos el caso de una dilatación aguda e idiopática del colón en un varón adulto que ingresó por un episodio de insuficiencia respiratoria aguda, y que se resolvió con tratamiento médico conservador</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;23(9): 435-437, sept. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051689</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Ogilvie o pseudobstrucción aguda del colon: una causa rara de abdomen agudo, de elevada mortalidad y asociada a patologías frecuentes en un Servicio de Medicina Interna</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23324^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19127^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2021^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10625^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19127^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
