<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049114</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hepatitis C and insulin resistance: steatosis, fibrosis and non-response</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Insulin resistance is more often seen in hepatitis C than in otherliver diseases, including non-alcoholic steatohepatitis. TheHomeostasis Model for Assessment [HOMA= fasting insulin(mUI/ml) * fasting glucose (mmol/L) / 22.5] has proved useful inthe measurement of insulin sensitivity in euglycemic patients.Cross-sectional and case-cohort studies support a role for hepatitisC as a factor implied in the development of type-2 diabetes inhigh-risk patients (male patients, older than 40 years, and overweight).In transgenic mice models the HCV core protein hasbeen found to induce insulin resistance via TNF production. Insulinresistance has been associated with steatosis developmentand fibrosis progression in a genotype-dependent manner. Ingenotype-1 patients, the mechanisms by which insulin resistancepromotes fibrosis progression include: a) steatosis; b) hyperleptinemia;c) increased TNF production; and d) impaired expressionof PPAR&amp;#947; receptors. Indeed, insulin resistance has beenfound as a common denominator to the majority of features associatedwith difficult-to-treat patients. Patients with cirrhosis, obesity,coinfected with HIV, and Afro-American, all of them showedinsulin resistance. Insulin resistance strongly influences sustainedresponse rates, at least in genotype-1 patients. Insulin resistancedecreases during and after treatment in patients that achievedvirus C clearance. Moreover, the incidence of type-2 diabetesseems to be lower in responders than in non-responders. In summary,hepatitis C promotes insulin resistance and insulin resistanceinduces steatosis, fibrosis, and interferon resistance. Thetreatment of insulin resistance by decreasing hyperinsulinemiacould improve sustained response rates in patients with chronichepatitis C treated with peginterferon plus ribavirin</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romero Gómez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La resistencia a la insulina se ha observado con más frecuenciaen la hepatitis C que en otras enfermedades del hígado incluida laesteatohepatitis no alcohólica. Se ha demostrado que el HomeostasisModel for Assesment (HOMA= insulina en ayunas(mUI/ml)* glucosa en ayunas (mmol/L)/ 22,5) es útil para medirla sensibilidad a la insulina en pacientes euglucémicos. Los estudiosde corte transversal y caso-cohorte apoyan el papel de la hepatitisC como factor implicado en el desarrollo de diabetes tipo 2en pacientes de alto riesgo (pacientes masculinos, mayores de 40y con sobrepeso). Se ha encontrado en modelos con ratonestransgénicos que la proteína del core del VHC es capaz de inducirla resistencia a la insulina por la producción de TNF. La resistenciaa la insulina se ha asociado con el desarrollo de esteatosis y laprogresión a la fibrosis de forma genotipo dependiente. En pacientescon genotipo 1, el mecanismo por el cual la resistencia ala insulina promueve la progresión a la fibrosis incluye: a) esteatosis;b) hiperleptinemia; c) aumento de la producción de TNF; y d)expresión dañada de receptores PPAR&amp;#947;. De hecho, la resistenciaa la insulina se ha encontrado como denominador común en lamayoría de los pacientes difíciles de curar. Los pacientes con cirrosis,obesidad, coinfectados con VIH y Afro-Americanos, todosellos presentaban resistencia a la insulina. La resistencia a la insulinainfluye en la tasa de respuesta sostenida, al menos en los pacientescon genotipo 1. La resistencia a la insulina disminuye durantey después del tratamiento en pacientes que erradicaron elvirus C. La incidencia de diabetes tipo 2 parece ser menor en respondedoresque en no respondedores. En resumen, la hepatitis Cpromueve la resistencia a la insulina y la resistencia a la insulinainduce esteatosis, fibrosis y resistencia al interferón. El tratamientode la resistencia a la insulina, disminuyendo la hiperinsulinemiapodría mejorar la tasa de respuesta sostenida en pacientes con hepatitiscrónica C tratados con peginterferón más ribavirina</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;98(8): 605-615, ago. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049114</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hepatitis C y resistencia a la insulina: esteatosis, fibrosis y no respuesta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5337^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33344^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33344^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5337^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
