<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151355</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Maggot therapy: case study in home care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Maggot therapy is a wound bed preparation method of ancestral use. Its use was relegated with the emergence of antibiotics, until today, where is reemerging as an option in the treatment of chronic wounds. Methodology. We report a case study where a six months wound in diabetic foot with torpid evolution and with several changes of ineffective treatment, improved in 3-4 days after the use of maggot therapy at home; leaving the wound bed prepared for the process of granulation. Results. As could see, after four days from the application of maggot therapy, the wound bed was free of slough, also decreasing exudation and edema. Leaving the optimal conditions for wound healing. It was assessed by the VAS scale decreased pain after dressing changes. It was demonstrated that maggot therapy can be used in home or community care without inconvenience. Conclusion. The maggot therapy is a method of debridement fast, effective and safe, this method can be used in home care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Faura, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco Romero, Maite</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordoño Martínez, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Mallo, Mónica E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La terapia larval es un método de preparación del lecho de la herida de utilización ancestral. Su uso quedó relegado con la aparición de los antibióticos, hasta nuestros días, donde está resurgiendo como opción en el tratamiento de heridas crónicas. Metodología. Presentamos un caso clínico, donde una herida en pie diabético de seis meses de evolución tórpida y con varios cambios de tratamiento poco efectivos mejora en 3-4 días tras la utilización de terapia larval en el domicilio. El lecho de la herida queda preparado para el proceso de granulación. Resultados. Se puede apreciar cómo, tras cuatro días de tratamiento con la terapia larval, el lecho de la herida queda libre de esfacelos y disminuye también el exudado y el edema. Se consigue una herida en óptimas condiciones para la cicatrización. Se objetivó, aplicando la escala EVA, una clara disminución del dolor tras la terapia. Se demostró que la terapia larval puede utilizarse en atención domiciliaria o comunitaria sin inconvenientes. Conclusión. La terapia larval es un método de desbridamiento rápido, efectivo y seguro, que se puede aplicar en el domicilio del usuario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;39(4): 258-261, abr. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151355</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Terapia larval. Caso clínico en atención domiciliaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3664^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55416^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19283^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3664^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19283^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55416^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3664^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55416^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6248^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6856^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31512^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31512^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
