<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59422</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Aneurysm of the gastroduodenal artery associated with stenosis of the celiac trunk</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Aneurysms of the gastroduodenal artery constitute a rare condition, although their associationwith an occlusion or with stenosis of the celiac trunk is well known. Case report. A 43-year-old female who was referredto our service after the results of abdominal ultrasonography performed following a 6-month history of lower abdominalpain included images that were consistent with vascular abnormalities related to the head of the pancreas. CT-angiographyshowed two aneurysms in the gastroduodenal artery associated with an occlusion of the origin of the celiac trunk. Theshortage of blood flow produced by this stenosis was compensated by an elongated, dilated gastroduodenal artery.Through midline laparotomy, the gastroduodenal artery both proximal and distal to the aneurysms was ligated andsectioned and it was re-implanted in the abdominal aorta. The patient was discharged following remission of hersymptoms and with thrombosis of the aneurysms proven by CT-angiography. Conclusions. Surgical treatment by meansof resection is still a valid approach for this kind of condition. Although some authors recommend concomitant treatment ofthe stenosis of the celiac trunk, failing to treat it has not proved to lead to a higher rate of relapses(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hípola-Ulecia, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santaolalla-García, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fonseca-Legrand, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrero-Bernabé, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los aneurismas de la arteria gastroduodenal son una rara entidad, aunque su asociación conuna oclusión o con una estenosis del tronco celíaco es bien conocida. Caso clínico. Mujer de 43 años de edad remitida anuestro servicio por encontrarse, en una ecografía abdominal realizada en el contexto de una epigastralgia de 6 mesesde evolución, hallazgos compatibles con anomalías vasculares relacionadas con la cabeza del páncreas. En la angiotomografíase observaron dos aneurismas de la arteria gastroduodenal asociados con una oclusión del origen del troncocelíaco. La falta de riego que producía esta estenosis era compensada por una arteria gastroduodenal elongada y dilatada.Mediante laparotomía media se procedió a la ligadura y a la sección de la arteria gastroduodenal proximal y distala los aneurismas y a su reimplantación en la aorta abdominal. La paciente fue dada de alta en remisión de su sintomatologíay con trombosis de los aneurismas demostrada mediante una angiotomografía. Conclusión. El tratamientoquirúrgico mediante resección sigue siendo un abordaje válido para este tipo de afección. Aunque algunos autores recomiendanel tratamiento concomitante de la estenosis del tronco celíaco, no tratarlo no ha demostrado que se produzca unmayor índice de recurrencias(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;61(1): 41-45, ene.-feb. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59422</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aneurisma de la arteria gastroduodenal asociada con estenosis del tronco celíaco</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2480^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7991</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d794</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37754^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3270</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2480^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
