<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-MFM2-10854</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neurological manifestations of excessive alcohol consumption</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article reviews the different acute and chronic neurological manifestations of excessive alcohol consumption that affect the central or peripheral nervous system. Several mechanisms can be implicated depending on the disorder, ranging from nutritional factors, alcohol-related toxicity, metabolic changes and immune-mediated mechanisms. Recognition and early treatment of these manifestations is essential given their association with high morbidity and significantly increased mortality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Planas-Ballvé, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grau-López, Laia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morillas, Rosa María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Planas, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se revisan las distintas manifestaciones neurológicas del consumo excesivo de alcohol, que pueden ser agudas o crónicas y afectar al sistema nervioso central o periférico. El mecanismo por el cual se producen varía de un grupo de trastornos a otro. Destacan factores nutricionales, efectos tóxicos del alcohol, factores metabólicos e incluso inmunológicos. Estas manifestaciones pueden conllevar una gran morbilidad y un aumento significativo de la mortalidad, por lo que es importante reconocerlas y tratarlas precozmente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;40(10): 709-717, dic. 2017. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-MFM2-10854</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manifestaciones neurológicas del alcoholism</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
