<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122049</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The Effect of Hyperactive Bladder Severity on Healthcare Utilization and Labor Productivity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To explore the relationship between the severity of urinary urge incontinence (UUI) on healthcare resources utilization (HRU) and loss of labor productivity of subjects with overactive bladder (OAB) in the general population in Spain. Methods: Secondary analysis of a cross-sectional web-based study conducted in the general population &gt;18 years, through a battery of HRU questions asked using an online method. Probable OAB subjects were identified using a previously validated algorithm and a score &gt; 8 in the OAB-V8 questionnaire. HRU questions included an assessment of concomitant medication used as a consequence of OAB/UUI, pad utilization, and medical office visits. Patients were grouped according to the number of UUI episodes into 0, 1, 2-3 or 4 + episodes. Results: Of a total of 2,035 subjects participating from the general population, 396 patients [52.5% women, mean age: 55.3 (11.1) years, OAB-V8 mean score: 14.5 (7.9)] were analyzed; 203 (51.3%) with 0 episodes, 119 (30.1%) with 1, 52 (13.1%) with 2 or 3, and 22 (5.6%) with 4 or more episodes. A linear and significant adjusted association was observed between the number of UUI episodes and HRU; the higher the number of daily episodes the higher the HRU. Subjects with more episodes had medical visits more frequently at the primary care (P = 0.001) and specialist (P = 0.009) level as well. Consumption of day (P &lt; 0.001) and night (P &lt; 0.001) urinary absorbents, anxiolytic medicines (P = 0.021) and antibiotics (P = 0.05) was higher in patients with more UUI episodes. Conclusion: The severity of OAB in terms of frequency of daily urge incontinence episodes was significantly and linearly associated with higher healthcare resources utilization and a decrease in labor productivity in subjects with probable OAB in Spain (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Trillo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ochayta, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Angulo, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arumí, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brenes, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lizarraga, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rejas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Explorar la relación entre la severidad de la incontinencia urinaria de urgencia (IUU) y la utilización de recursos sanitarios o la pérdida de productividad laboral en pacientes con vejiga hiperactiva (VH) en la población general española. Métodos: Análisis secundario de un estudio transversal realizado por vía telemática (Internet) en la población general, &gt; 18 años, mediante una batería de preguntas relacionadas con el uso de recursos sanitarios y la productividad laboral. Los sujetos con probable VH fueron identificados mediante un algoritmo previamente validado. Las preguntas sobre el uso de recursos sanitarios abarcaron la medicación concomitante, el empleo de absorbentes y las visitas médicas. Los pacientes se agruparon según el número de episodios de IUU en: 0, 1, 2-3 o 4 +. Resultados: De un total de 2.035 sujetos participantes de la población general se identificaron 396 pacientes (52,5% mujeres, edad media [DE] 55,3 [11,1] años, puntuación media en OAB-V8: 14,5 [7,9]), con probable VH: 203 (51,3%) con 0 episodios, 119 (30,1%) con uno, 52 (13,1%) con 2-3 y 22 (5,6%) con 4 +. Se observó una relación lineal significativa, de manera que a mayor número de episodios de IUU mayor uso de recursos sanitarios. Los sujetos con más episodios realizaron con mayor frecuencia visitas médicas, tanto de asistencia primaria (p &lt; 0,001) como al especialista (p = 0,009) y emplearon mayor cantidad de absorbentes tanto en horario diurno (p &lt; 0,001) como nocturno (p &lt; 0,001) de ansiolíticos (p = 0,021) y de antibióticos (p = 0,05). Conclusión: La severidad de la incontinencia urinaria de urgencia, según el número diario de episodios de incontinencia de urgencia, mostró una relación lineal significativa con un uso más frecuente de recursos sanitarios y una disminución en la productividad laboral en pacientes con probable VH en España (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;38(4): 249-256, Mayo 2014. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122049</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La severidad de la vejiga hiperactiva modifica la carga asistencial y la productividad laboral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52129^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d44</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52132^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
