<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145520</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of low carbohydrate diets on weight loss and glycosilated hemoglobin in people with type 2 diabetes: systematic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: some experts have suggested out that low carbohydrate diets (LCD) are more effective for weight loss and glycemic control. However, long term results are controversial. Objective: to review and analyze randomized control studies that evaluate the effect of LCD on weight and metabolic control in individuals with type 2 diabetes for a period equal to or greater than 10 months. Methods: a systematic review was conducted on randomized trials registered in PubMed, EBSCOhost and Scielo to May 15th 2015, published in English and Spanish, with the following search data: 'diabetes mellitus' AND 'carbohydrate restricted diet' OR 'restricted carbohydrate diet' OR 'low carbohydrate diet' AND 'weight loss'. Results: four studies met the inclusion criteria. There were 444 participants between 18-70yo. Follow-up time ranged between 10 to 24 months. Three out of the four studies reported weight reduction with LCD. However, when LCD were compared with other diets no significant differences in weight loss or A1C levels were observed. Conclusions: this review showed that three of four studies on the LCD were effective for weight loss over a period of 10 to 24 months. However, there was no evidence showing better results than those observed with other diets. Nor, difference in A1C (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Cruz, Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Alcántara, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bacardí Gascón, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: algunos expertos señalan que las dietas bajas en carbohidratos (DBC) son más efectivas para la reducción de peso y el control glucémico. Sin embargo, los resultados a largo plazo son controversiales. Objetivo: realizar una revisión y análisis de estudios aleatorizados que estudien el efecto de la DBC sobre el control metabólico en individuos con diabetes tipo 2 en un periodo igual o superior a 10 meses. Métodos: se realizó una revisión de estudios aleatorizados controlados publicados en PubMed, EBSCOhost y Scielo hasta el 15 de mayo del 2015. Se buscaron estudios publicados en inglés y español, utilizando los términos de búsqueda: 'diabetes mellitus' AND 'carbohydrate restricted diet' OR 'restricted carbohydrate diet' OR 'low carbohydrate diet' AND 'weight loss'. Resultados: cuatro estudios cumplieron con los criterios de inclusión. El número de participantes fue de 444 individuos, el rango de edad fue de 18 a 70 años. El tiempo de seguimiento osciló entre los 10 y 24 meses. Tres de los cuatro estudios reportaron una reducción de peso con la DBC. Al compararlos con otras dietas no se observaron diferencias significativas en la pérdida de peso ni en los niveles de A1C. Conclusiones: esta revisión muestra que en tres de los cuatro estudios las DBC son efectivas para la pérdida de peso en un período de 10 a 24 meses. Sin embargo, no existen evidencias que demuestren mayor efectividad para la pérdida de peso o la reducción de AIC, cuando se comparan con otras dietas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(5): 1960-1966, nov. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145520</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de las dietas bajas en carbohidratos sobre la pérdida de peso y hemoglobina glucosilada en personas con diabetes tipo 2: revisión sistemática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22190^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23862^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51218^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
