<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80463</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Utility of combined therapy in the prevention and treatment of the cardiovascular disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Although blood pressure control is crucial in patients with hypertension, current clinical practice guidelines recommend that the goal of treatment should be aimed at not only reducing blood pressure values but decreasing global cardiovascular risk. Available data suggest that blood pressure and LDL-cholesterol control rates, two of the most common cardiovascular risk factors, are low, not only in the primary care setting but also in specialists setting. Clinical trials, such as the Anglo-Scandanavian Cardiac Outcomes Trial (ASCOT), have demonstrated that the integration of a multifactorial approach through the treatment of different risk factors effectively reduces the risk of cardiovascular morbidity and mortality.AbstractThe aim of this review was to update the current knowledge about the combined therapy of different risk factors in the hypertensive population(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escobar Cervantes, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrios Alonso, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ResumenAunque el control de la presión arterial es crucial en los pacientes con HTA, las actuales gruías de práctica clínica recomiendan que el objetivo del tratamiento en esta población no se debería limitar a reducir las cifras de presión arterial, sino que debería ir encaminado además a reducir el riesgo cardiovascular global. Los datos actuales sugieren que las tasas de control tanto de la presión arterial como del colesterol LDL, 2 de los principales factores de riesgo cardiovascular, son bajos, tanto en atención primaria como en las consultas del especialista. Ensayos clínicos como el Anglo-Scandanavian Cardiac Outcomes Trial, han demostrado que el tratamiento basado en un abordaje multifactorial de los diferentes factores de riesgo cardiovascular, reduce eficazmente la morbimortalidad cardiovascular.ResumenEl objetivo de esta revisión fue realizar una actualización de los conocimientos existentes sobre el tratamiento combinado de los distintos factores de riesgo en la población hipertensa(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;210(5): 230-236, mayo 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80463</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de la terapia combinada en la prevención y tratamiento de la enfermedad cardiovascular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
