<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78490</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Initial evaluation, diagnosis, staging, treatment, and follow-up of patients with primary cutaneous malignant melanoma. Consensus statement of the network of Catalan and Balearic Melanoma Centers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The consensus statement on the management of primary cutaneous melanoma that we present here was based on selection, discussion, review, and comparison of recent literature (including national and international guidelines). The protocols for the diagnosis, treatment, and follow-up used in the hospital centers throughout Catalonia and the Balearic Isles belonging to the Network of Catalan and Balearic Melanoma Centers were also considered. The main objective of this statement was to present the overall management of melanoma patients typically used in our region at the present time. As such, the statement was not designed to be an obligatory protocol for health professionals caring for this group of patients, and neither can it nor should it be used for this purpose. Professionals reading the statement should not therefore consider it binding on their practice, and in no case can this text be used to guarantee or seek responsibility for a given medical opinion. The group of dermatologists who have signed this statement was created 3 years ago with the aim of making our authorities aware of the importance of this complex tumor, which, in comparison with other types of cancer, we believe does not receive sufficient attention in Spain. In addition, the regular meetings of the group have produced interesting proposals for collaboration in various epidemiological, clinical, and basic applied research projects on the subject of malignant melanoma in our society (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gallardo, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedragosa, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paradelo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rocamora, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrándiz, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pozo, LJ del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Curcó, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcoval, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Formigón, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llambrich, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nogués, ME</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Azon, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bigatà, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí, RM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dalmau, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puig, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sàbat, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salleras, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Malvehy, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mangas, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Just, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bel, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llistosella, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bartralot, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El documento de consenso respecto al manejo del melanoma primario de la piel, que detallamos a continuación, nace de la puesta en común, aceptación, revisión y confrontación con la literatura reciente (incluyendo guías clínicas nacionales e internacionales), así como de los protocolos de diagnóstico, seguimiento y tratamiento consensuados en los diferentes centros hospitalarios de toda Cataluña y Balerares pertenencientes a la Xarxa de Centres de Melanoma de Catalunya i Balears. El objetivo principal de este documento es exponer de forma conjunta el manejo habitual del paciente con melanoma que actualmente se realiza en nuestro medio. Sin embargo, este documento no pretende, ni puede, por lo que tampoco debiera ser usado como un protocolo de obligado cumplimiento por los profesionales que atendemos a este grupo de enfermos. En este sentido, cabe mencionar que la consulta de este documento por parte del profesional no es vinculante para su acción, y en ningún caso este texto podrá ser utilizado para garantizar o buscar responsabilidades del juicio médico concreto. El grupo de dermatólogos que firman dicho documento se formó hace ahora tres años, con la intención de dar a conocer a nuestras autoridades la importancia de este complejo tumor, que en nuestro país creemos que se encuentra erróneamente infravalorada con respecto a otros tipo de cáncer. Además, fruto de las reuniones periódicas del grupo, han surgido también interesantes propuestas de colaboración en distintos proyectos de investigación epidemiológica, clínica y básica aplicada en torno al melanoma maligno en nuestra sociedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;101(2): 129-142, mar. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78490</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración inicial, diagnóstico, estadificación, tratamiento y seguimiento de los pacientes con melanoma maligno primario de la piel. Documento de consenso de la 'Xarxa de Centres de Melanoma de Catalunya i Balears'</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8374^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8374^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32054^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31057^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8714^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29469^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31057^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30193^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8714^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
