<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044013</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-7973</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gestational diabetes mellitus: prevalence and risk factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To investigate the gestational diabetes mellitusprevalence in our region. To evaluate the usefulness of the doubleand the selective screening and the relationship betweenthe presence of gestational diabetes mellitus and age, bodymass index and maternal familiar history of diabetes mellitus.Material and methods: Retrospective study of the results ofa screening test with 278 mmol of glucose to 2088 womenbetween the 24th and 28th gestational week.591 of these women were subjected to a previous screeningtest with 278 mmol of glucose between the 12th and 14thgestational week.Results: The gestational diabetes mellitus prevalence in Burgosand its province was 4.5%. Gestational diabetes mellituswas independently related to maternal age (p&lt;0.001) andfamiliar maternal history of diabetes mellitus (p&lt;0.05).Conclusions: If we had not made the O´Sullivan test to lowrisk women we would have had diagnosed correctly all thepatients with gestational diabetes mellitus</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calmarza, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vazquez, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cordero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Investigar la prevalencia de diabetes mellitus gestacionalen nuestro medio. Evaluar la utilidad del doble screeningy del screening selectivo, así como la relación existenteentre diabetes mellitus gestacional y edad, índice de masa corporalo antecedentes familiares maternos de diabetes mellitus.Material y métodos: Estudio retrospectivo de los resultadosobtenidos al realizar una prueba de cribado con 278 mmol deglucosa a 2088 mujeres entre las semanas 24 y 28 de gestación,de las cuales 591 fueron sometidas a un cribado previoentre las semanas 12 y 14 de embarazo.Resultados: La prevalenciade diabetes gestacional en nuestro medio fue de 4.5%.La presencia de diabetes mellitus gestacional se relacionaba deforma independiente con la edad materna (p&lt;0.001) así comocon la presencia de antecedentes familiares maternos de diabetesmellitus (p&lt;0.05). Conclusiones: Excluyendo del screeninguniversal a las mujeres que poseen bajo riesgo, se habríandiagnosticado correctamente todas las pacientes queacabaron desarrollando diabetes mellitus gestacional</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. diagn. biol;54(4): 337-342, oct.-dic. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044013</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diabetes mellitus gestacional: prevalencia y factores de riesgo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6096^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30157^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30157^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
