<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152994</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Drug abuse in nursing students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the patterns of substance abuse of students attending the Lugo School of Nursing. Method: Observational, descriptive and cross-sectional study in the classroom carried out by survey research in April 2015. Results: 61.5% of students participated (185), 83.2% of whom were females. The first addictive substance consumed by participants was tobacco (at 15 years old). In the last month cigarettes were consumed by 36.2% of students, while alcohol was consumed by 89.9% (58.4% of the total got drunk). 2.2% were consuming tranquilizers/hypnotics in the same time period. The most widely used illegal drug was cannabis (17.8%) and then cocaine (2.2%). There is a significant correlation between illegal drug consumption and being male, smoking cigarettes or drinking alcohol, living alone or with friends (not family), have poor academic performance and public drinking (botellón). There were no association between illegal drugs and sports or reading. Polydrug use was also studied: a 16.2% declared to have consumed alcohol and cannabis simultaneously, and a 4.9% alcohol and cocaine. Conclusions: Consumption patterns are similar compared to the general population in that age group, with some of them being higher. Therefore, it is necessary to take measures in order to prevent substance abuse at the university level (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garrido-González, Iria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Machín-Fernández, Antonio Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bugarín-González, Rosendo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer los patrones de consumo de sustancias adictivas de los estudiantes de la Escuela Universitaria de Enfermería de Lugo. Método: Estudio observacional, descriptivo y transversal realizado en las aulas a través de un cuestionario en el mes de abril de 2015. Resultados: La participación del alumnado fue del 61,5% (185), de los que el 83,2% correspondían al sexo femenino. La sustancia adictiva de consumo más precoz fue el tabaco (15 años). Consumieron cigarrillos en el último mes un 36,2% de los estudiantes y alcohol el 89,9% (un 58,4% del total se emborracharon). Un 2,2% utilizaron, en ese período, tranquilizantes/hipnóticos. La droga ilegal de mayor uso fue el cannabis (17,8%) y a continuación la cocaína (2,2%). Existe una asociación significativa entre el consumo de drogas ilegales y ser varón, fumar tabaco o beber alcohol, vivir solo o con amigos (no con la familia), tener un mal rendimiento académico y practicar botellón. No hubo diferencias con la práctica deportiva ni con la lectura. Se estudió también el policonsumo: el 16,2% manifestó haber utilizado simultáneamente alcohol y cannabis y un 4,9% alcohol y cocaína. Conclusiones: Los patrones de consumo son similares, y algunos incluso mayores, que los de la población general en ese grupo de edad. De ahí que se consideren necesarias, en el ámbito universitario, medidas específicas para prevenir la adicción a sustancias en este colectivo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);26(3): 174-180, mayo-jun. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152994</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consumo de drogas en estudiantes de enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28587</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13725^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
