<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113483</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Non safety costs in the Spanish Health Care System</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: In the context of budgetary difficulties, the estimation of non safety costs is an additional tool that may be useful in the decision making process of the health systemas well as to improve the health caremanagement. Until now there is no study that has estimated the costs of non safety in Spain in an integral way. The objective of this article is to show a first approach to the calculation of the costs of non safety referred to the year 2011. Method: The study updated from the year 2005 an estimation of the costs of non safety affecting inpatients. Those costs referred to medication errors, to nosocomial infections and to surgical complications. The costs derived from the non safety related to outpatients are estimated from data obtained from the National Health Survey combined with other information of medication errors and their treatment costs that other authors calculated. Results: Non safety costs were 2,474 million euros and 960 million euros for hospitalized and non hospitalized patients respectively. Conclusions: This first estimation shows that non safety costs are about 6% of total public health expenditure(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Antoñanzas Villar, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: En un contexto de dificultades presupuestarias, la cuantificación de los costes de la no seguridad constituye un instrumento adicional que puede ayudar en la adopción de decisiones y en la mejor gestión del sistema sanitario. Hasta el presente no se ha llegado a estimar los costes de la no seguridad en nuestro país de una forma integral. Este artículo tiene por objetivo presentar una primera aproximación al cálculo de los costes de la no seguridad referidos al año 2011. Métodos: Para efectuar los cálculos se partió de una estimación de los costes de los pacientes hospitalizados para el año 2005 referentes a los errores de medicación, infecciones nosocomiales y complicaciones quirúrgicas, que se actualizaron al año de referencia. Para los costes de los pacientes no hospitalizados se tuvo en cuenta la Encuesta Nacional de Salud y las estimaciones de la tasa de errores de medicación y de los costes de los tratamientos procedentes de otros autores. Resultados: El coste de la no seguridad en los pacientes hospitalizados fue de 2.474 millones de euros y de 960 millones de euros para los pacientes no hospitalizados. Conclusiones: Esta estimación indica que los costes de la no seguridad se sitúan en el entorno del 6% del gasto sanitario público(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;87(3): 282-293, mayo-jun.2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113483</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aproximación los costes de la no seguridad en el sistema nacional de salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51280</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17140</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3376^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3380^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
