<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154118</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">How management teams use information and control systems to manage hospitals</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze the relationship between the characteristics of top management teams and the different use of management information and control systems (MICS) to implement policies that encourage cooperation and activity coordination in public hospitals. Methods: Data were collected through a questionnaire sent to each member of the top management teams of 231 Spanish public hospitals (chief executive director, medical director, nursing director and director for financial and social issues). A total of 457 valid questionnaires were returned, composing 86 full top management teams (37.23%). Results: Top management team diversity was positively related to the interactive use of MICS. Management teams composed of younger members and members with longer service used MICS interactively. Top management teams with a predominantly clinical education and experience used MICS interactively, while top teams with a predominantly administrative education and experience used MICS diagnostically. The results also showed that cooperation and coordination in hospitals were positively related to the interactive use of MICS and were negatively related to the diagnostic use of MICS. Conclusions: The interactive use of MICS is an important mediator in the relationship between top team diversity and policies focused on hospital decentralization. Top management teams with diverse characteristics (e.g. age, length of service, education and experience) use management information interactively to enhance activity coordination and resource allocation in hospitals (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Naranjo-Gil, David</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar la relación entre las características de los equipos de dirección y el uso diferenciado de los sistemas de información y control de la gestión (SICG), así como el efecto de tales sistemas en la cooperación y la coordinación de actividades en los hospitales públicos. Métodos: Los datos se recogieron mediante un cuestionario enviado individualmente a los miembros del equipo de dirección de 231 hospitales públicos españoles (director/a gerente, director/a médico, director/a de enfermería y director/a de asuntos sociales y económicos). Se recibieron 457 respuestas válidas, con las cuales se formaron 86 equipos de dirección completos (37,23%). Resultados: Un equipo de dirección con diversidad de características está relacionado positivamente con un uso interactivo de los SICG. Los equipos directivos más jóvenes y de mayor antigüedad usaron interactivamente los SICG. Los equipos de dirección con formación y experiencia clínica también usaron los SICG interactivamente; sin embargo, los equipos con formación y experiencia predominantemente administrativas usaron los SICG de forma diagnóstica. Los resultados también muestran que la cooperación y la coordinación en los hospitales se relacionan positivamente con un uso interactivo de los SICG y negativamente con un uso diagnóstico de los SICG. Conclusión: El uso interactivo de los SICG es un mediador importante de la relación entre la diversidad del equipo de dirección y el fomento de políticas de cooperación y coordinación en los hospitales. Los equipos con diversidad de características (p. ej., edad, antigüedad, educación y experiencia) tienden a usar los sistemas de información de la gestión de forma interactiva para mejorar la coordinación de actividades y la asignación de recursos en los hospitales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;30(4): 287-292, jul.-ago. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154118</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cómo los equipos de dirección usan los sistemas de información y control en la gestión hospitalaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6437^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50216</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6904^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17099</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55139^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
