<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77199</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Renal lithiasis in patients with primary hyperparathyroidism. Evolution and treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: The relationship between hyperparathyroidism and lithiasis is quite known, so the study of parathyroid glands is especially mandatory in the face of relapses. Our objective is to analyze both primary hyperparathyroidism (PHPT) associated with renallithiasis and the evolution of this condition after parathyroidectomy,as well as to study factors associated with the presence of lithiasis or bone pathology, and carry out a review on bibliography.METHODS: We describe a retrospective study of a series comprising 287 cases of hyperparathyroidism: 237 of them were primary and the remaining 50, secondary.We have included: sex, age, evolution time and symptoms, diagnostic tests (biochemical, radiologicaland histological). Factors such as number of episodesprior to diagnosis and treatments were analyzed in patients with symptomatic lithiasis to know whether patients exhibited residual lithiasis after the management of calculi or whether patients underwent episodes after parathyroidectomy, or whether or not they were treated. Statistical analysis was carried out through SPSS 15.0 for Windows.RESULTS: Forty five percent of the patients had suffered lithiasis episodes; 50%, osteopenia/osteoporosis; 23%, musculoskeletal pain; 23%, asthenia and/or depressive syndrome. In 13.5% of cases, diagnosis was supported by the presence of hypercalcemia; no other symptoms were detected.We have analyzed factors that favor or inhibit renal lithiasisformation and compared biochemical parameters from the group of primary hyperthyroidism that exhibited lithiasis (41 patients) with those patients who did not (49). We noted that lithiasis patients showed higher valuesof calcium, alkaline phosphatase, intact PTH, mean PTH, osteocalcin, and chlorine/phosphate, calciuria and phosphaturia indexes. Student&#146;s t test on two independentsamples revealed significant statistical differencesin calcium levels (p&lt;0.05), intact PTH (&lt;0.05) and osteocalcin...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miján Ortiz, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valle Díaz de la Guardia, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zuluaga Gómez, Armando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arrabal Martín, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arrabal Polo, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quirosa Flores, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: La relación hiperparatiroidismo-litiasis renal es bien conocida y el estudio de paratiroideses obligado en paciente con litiasis, sobre todo si hay recidivas. Nuestro objetivo es analizar los casos de HPTP con litiasis renal y su evolución tras paratiroidectomía;estudiar los factores que se asocian a la presencia de litiasis o patología ósea y revisión bibliográfica.MÉTODOS: Estudio descriptivo retrospectivo de una serie de 287 casos de hiperparatiroidismo: 237 primarios,50 hiperparatiroidismos secundarios. Hemos analizado: sexo, edad, tiempo de evolución, clínica, pruebas diagnósticas (bioquímicas, radiológicas e histológicas).En pacientes con clínica de litiasis se ha analizado el número de episodios previos al diagnóstico y su tratamiento,si presentaban litiasis residual tras el tratamiento del cálculo, si sufrieron episodios posteriores a la paratiroidectomíay si fueron tratados o no. Análisis estadísticocon SPSS 15.0 para Windows.RESULTADOS: El 45% de pacientes había presentado episodios de litiasis, 50% osteopenia/osteoporosis, 23% algias osteomusculares, astenia y/o síndrome depresivoel 23%; en el 13,5% de los casos el diagnóstico se realiza tras el hallazgo de hipercalcemia sin otros síntomas.Analizamos factores favorecedores o inhibidores de formaciónde litiasis renal, hemos comparado parámetros bioquímicos del grupo de hiperparatiroidismos primarioscon litiasis (41 pacientes) con grupo sin litiasis (49). Observamos que enfermos con litiasis presentan cifras más elevadas de calcio, fosfatasa alcalina, PTHi, PTHm, osteocalcina, índice cloro/fosfato, calciuria y fosfaturia. Al aplicar el test &#147;t&#148; Student para dos muestras independientesse encontraron diferencias estadísticamente significativasen niveles de calcio (p&lt;0,05), PTHi (p&lt;0,05) y osteocalcina...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;63(1): 32-40, ene.-feb. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77199</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Litiasis renal en pacientes con hiperparatiroidismo primario. Evolución y tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29078^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24820^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52124^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10494^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10494^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7140^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7140^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52124^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52124^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7114^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7114^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
