<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76816</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to analyze the degree of accomplishment with gastroprotection-related guidelines in a sample of patients seen in an oncological ward and a palliative care unit at HUAV, Lleida. Material and methods: a descriptive and prospective study where were view the clinical records of patients consecutively admitted to an oncological ward and a palliative care unit between January and March, 2008. We studied the following data: age, gender, main diagnosis, previous ulcer disease, and treatment with NSAIDs, steroids, antiaggregants and anticoagulants.Treatment with gastroprotective drugs (active principle, dose and route of administration). Results: 106 patients were included in the study (57 male and 49 female). Mean age was 65 years. The main diagnosis was breast cancer, head and neck cancer (17.4% each), and lung cancer (15%). Regarding the association of risk factors we found the following data: NSAIDs + ulcer: 5(3 patients treated); NSAIDs + age &gt; 65 years: 17 (16 treated); NSAIDs +AAS: 1 (1 treated); NSAIDs + steroids: 13 (13 treated); NSAIDs + anticoagulants:5 (5 treated). Conclusion: 40 patients received NSAIDs (47.7%); 69 patients (65%) received PPIs. Regarding the association of risk factors, guidelines were complied with in 38/41 cases (92.7%). Among patients who did not receive PPIs and had no risk factors, guidelines were complied with in 35/37 cases (94.57%). Finally, 23/69 patients were on PPIs and had no risk factors (66%) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Canal, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nabal, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Justes, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: analizar el grado de cumplimiento de las guías de gastroprotección en función en una muestra de enfermos oncológicos avanzados ingresados en una unidad de oncología médica y cuidados paliativos en el HUAV de Lleida. Material y métodos: estudio descriptivo y prospectivo observacional en el que mediante la revisión de las historias clínicas de los pacientes ingresados de manera consecutiva, entre enero y marzo de 2008, se determinaron las siguientes variables: edad, género, diagnóstico principal, historia de enfermedad ulcerosa, uso de los siguientes fármacos: AINE, antiagregantes plaquetarios, corticoides y anticoagulantes. Tratamiento con fármacos gastroprotectores (principio activo, dosis y vía de administración). Resultados: se incluyen 106 pacientes (57 varones y 49 mujeres), con una edad media de la muestra de 65 años. Los tumores más frecuentes fueron mama (17,4%), cabeza y cuello (17,4%) y pulmón (15%). En cuanto a la asociación de factores de riesgo estudiados, encontramos los siguientes resultados: AINE + Hª ulcus: 5 (tratados 3); AINE + edad &gt; 65años: 17 (tratados 16); AINE + AAS: 1 (tratado 1); AINE + corticoides: 13; (tratados 13), AINE + anticoagulantes: 5 (tratados 5). Conclusión: cuarenta pacientes recibieron tratamiento con AINE(47,7%). Sesenta y nueve pacientes (65%) recibieron IBP. En cuanto a laasociación de factores de riesgo se cumplieron las guías en 38/41 casos (92,7%). En referencia a los pacientes que no recibieron IBP y no presentaron factores de riesgo, las guías se cumplieron en 35/37 casos (94,57%). De los pacientes que recibieron IBP y no presentaron factores de riesgo, 23/69 cumplieron con las guías (66%) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;16(4): 218-221, jul.-ago. 2009. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76816</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad en la prescripción de fármacosgastroprotectores en una cohorte de enfermos oncológicos y paliativos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19405^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
