<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96511</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Meniscus-ligament instability due to muscle weakness. A case report of a femoral nerve injury</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present a case of femoral nerve injury that caused knee instability, initially attributed to a meniscopathy and a partial patellar tendon tear. A review is made of the etiology and clinical findings of femoral nerve injuries. In addition, a series of concepts regarding the differences between true instability due to meniscal or ligamentous injury and muscular atrophy are explained. Correctly labeling the cause of knee instability is an important factor to orient towards either conservative or surgical treatment(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Candau Pérez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta un caso de lesión del nervio femoral, que ocasionó una clínica de claudicación mecánica de miembro inferior, atribuida en un principio a una inestabilidad por meniscopatía y rotura parcial del tendón rotuliano. Se hace una revisión de la etiología y clínica de las lesiones del nervio femoral, y se explican una serie de conceptos que permiten diferenciar la inestabilidad verdadera por lesión meniscal o ligamentosa y la claudicación por atrofia muscular. El etiquetar correctamente la causa de una inestabilidad de la rodilla es un factor clave para orientar el tratamiento de forma conservadora o quirúrgica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);46(1): 79-81, ene.-mar. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96511</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inestabilidad menisco-ligamentosa e inestabilidad por debilidad muscular. A propósito de una lesión del nervio femoral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10480^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10522^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37294^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7547^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10480^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7547^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32676^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5371^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5371^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10480^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32676^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32676^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
