<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99496</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Drug plant collection of The museum of History of Pharmacy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The collection of drug plants is composed of a series of 663 large glass jars containing both herbal drugs from the former Department of Pharmacognosy, Faculty of Pharmacy, Granada. Cataloged in the Museum's "Professor José Mª Suñé Abrussà" as teaching material it self Faculty of Pharmacy, is an interesting collection from the scientific point of view, high-value pharmaceutical estético. El paper aims to present this important collection, systematize the different contents and proceed to their classification in the Museum(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cabezas López, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Martín, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galdeano Fernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Andújar, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La colección de drogas vegetales está compuesta por una serie de 663 botes grandes de vidrio y conteniendo ambos drogas vegetales procedentes de la antigua Cátedra de Farmacognosia de la Facultad de Farmacia de Granada. Catalogado dentro de los fondos del Museo &#147;Profesor José Mª Suñé Abrussà&#148; como material docente de la propia Facultad de Farmacia, forma una colección interesante desde el punto de vista científico-farmacéutico y de alto valor estético. El objetivo del trabajo es dar a conocer esta importante colección, sistematizar el diverso contenido y proceder a su catalogación en el Museo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;51(supl.3): 361-374, jul. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99496</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La colección de drogas vegetales del Museo de Historia de la Farmacia &#147;Prof. José Mª Suñé Arbussá&#148; de Granada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9336</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4582^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4582^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4582^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10789^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10789^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10789^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10789^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10794^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10794^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10789^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50137</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201007</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
