<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75724</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mesenteric ischemia. Review and update</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Although recent advances have improved outcomes in most surgical diseases over the last several decades, mesenteric ischemiaremains a highly morbid condition. High clinical suspicious and knowledge of the differential diagnostic possibilities inthis clinical setting are essential for the correct management of this patients. The type of the treatment depends largely on the clinical presentation, with time being the most important factor determining viability before irreversible damage occurs to the bowel. Transluminal angioplasty and stenting of the visceral arteries is a viable alternative for treatment of chronic mesentericischemia. We review the pathophysiology, the clinical presentation and the current state of the art in diagnosis and treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez, V. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>De Marino, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carpintero, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Fajardo, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Del Río, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mengíbar, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Pedrosa, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Norberto, E. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvador, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Del Blanco, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrera, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brizuela, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Revilla, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A pesar de los recientes avances que han mejorado los resultados de la mayoría de las patologías quirúrgicas en las últimas décadas, la isquemia mesentérica continúa constituyendo una enfermedad con una elevada morbilidad. Una elevada sospecha clínica, así como el conocimiento de las diferentes posibilidades diagnósticas son esenciales para el correcto tratamiento de estos pacientes. El tipo de tratamiento depende en gran medida de la presentación clínica así como del tiempo de evolución puesto que representa el factor de mayor importancia para determinar la viabilidad intestinal. La angioplastia transluminaly el stent de las arteria viscerales son unas alternativas viables en el tratamiento de la isquemia mesentérica crónica. Revisamos la fisiopatología, la presentación clínica y el estado actual de las técnicas diagnósticas y terapéuticas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;11(2): 81-85, abr.-jun. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75724</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Isquema mesentérica. Revisión y puesta al día</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8818^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30956^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8818^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7678^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
