<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163855</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness and safety of nifedipine solution vs. nifedipine capsules in threatened preterm labor. A retrospective study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objecti ve: To analyze the effectiveness and safety of nifedipine oral solution compared with nifedipine oral capsules as tocolytic agent in pregnant women with threatened preterm labor (TPL). Methods: Single-center retrospective study was performed in women with TPL treated with nifedipine as a tocolytic of first choice, between January 2012 and December 2015. There were two cohorts: patients who received nifedipine capsules and patients who received nifedipine oral solution. Results: Obstetric characteristics, total tocolytic doses administered prolongati on of pregnancy and adverse reacti ons were analyzed. There were no significant differences for the prolongation of pregnancy to 48 hours and to 7 days. The total tocolytic dose used was lower for nifedipine oral soluti on than for nifedipine capsules (median 75 mg; IQR: 125 vs. 120 mg; IQR: 140) respectively. The incidence of adverse events was significantly lower on nifedipine solution group than on nifedipine capsules group (12.1% vs. 37.3%; p = 0.010). Conclusions: Nifedipine solution showed similar effectiveness to nifedipine capsules but with less secondary effects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salazar, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palacio, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guirior, Cristian de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: analizar la efectividad y seguridad de nifedipino solución comparado con nifedipino cápsulas en el tratamiento de la amenaza de parto prematuro (APP). Métodos: estudio retrospectivo, unicéntrico, en mujeres con APP, tratadas con nifedipino como tocolítico de primera elección, entre enero de 2012 y diciembre de 2015. Se distribuyeron en dos cohortes, según recibieron nifedipino cápsulas o nifedipino solución. Se analizaron las características obstétricas al ingreso, dosis de tocolítico administrado, prolongación de parto y reacciones adversas. Resultados: no hubo diferencias significativas en cuanto a la prolongación de parto de 48 horas y 7 días. La dosis total utilizada de nifedipino fue menor en solución que en cápsulas (mediana 75 mg; IQR: 125 vs. 120 mg; IQR: 140), respectivamente. Un menor número de mujeres presentó uno o más efectos adversos en nifedipino solución frente a cápsulas (12,1% vs. 37,3 %; p = 0,010). Conclusiones: nifedipino solución mostró eficacia similar a nifedipino cápsulas, pero con un menor número de efectos secundarios (tales como hipotensión y taquicardia) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);59(3): 151-155, mayo-jun. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163855</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad y seguridad de nifedipino solución vs. nifedipino cápsulas para la amenaza de parto pretérmino. Estudio retrospectivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4421</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7925^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13993^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7202^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7925^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23848^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23848^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
