<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050530</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-5981</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Management and laboral repercussion of Kienböck´s disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The management of the Kienböck´s disease in the workingplace presents a high risk of partial or total disabilitywith all the medical / legal conflicts that this involveswhen determining the origin of the disease as a commondisease, from employment injury or occupationaldisease.Surgery is possible and it improves the functional outcome.Its results are conditional by the radiological status,hand&#146;s activity, evolution and worker attitude.We establish four stages depending on symptomatology,radiological status, working activity and most adequatetreatment for each group.We review the clinical, radiological results, working andprofessional repercussion and social/laboral and economicrepercussion of these processes</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Delgado Serrano, P. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abad Morenilla, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Mora, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuentes Sanz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El manejo de la enfermedad de Kienböck en el medio laboralpresenta un alto riesgo de incapacidad (parcial o total)con todos los conflictos médico-legales que esto supone ala hora de determinar su origen como enfermedad común,accidente de trabajo o enfermedad profesional.La cirugía es posible y mejora el cuadro clínico. Sus resultadosse encuentran condicionados por el estadio radiológico,la actividad manual, el tiempo de evolución y la actituddel trabajador.Establecemos cuatro estadios en función de la sintomatología,radiología y actividad laboral y se establecen los tratamientosmás adecuados para cada grupo.Revisamos los resultados clínicos, radiológicos y la repercusiónlaboral y profesional de la enfermedad de Kienböck yuna medición de la repercusión socio-laboral y económicade estos procesos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Patol. apar. locomot. Fund. Mapfre Med;4(supl.1): 39-44, dic. 2006. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050530</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo y repercusión laboral de la enfermedad de Kienböck</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9967</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10200^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d44</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23892</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
