<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78829</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mortality following cardiac surgery in the national health service hospitals of the Community of Valencia in 2007: a descriptive analysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJETIVE: To analyze clinical records of cardiacsurgery patients in an attempt to identify factorsassociated with mortality in the postoperative criticalcare units of the public health service hospitals in theCommunity of Valencia, Spain, in 2007.METHODS: Retrospective study of cases from January1, 2007 to December 31, 2007. The charts of all patientswho underwent cardiac surgery with or without miocárdiextracorporealcirculation were reviewed. A datacollection protocol was followed to obtain informationon age, sex, body mass index (BMI), presurgical riskfactors, type of surgery, duration of extracorporealcirculation, duration of ischemia, cause of death, andlength of stay in the postoperative critical care unit.RESULTS: The study population consisted of 2113patients at 5 public hospitals; 124 patients (70 men, 54women) died. The mean (SD) age was 70 (9.43) years(range, 36-91 years). The mean BMI was 28.19 kg/m2(maximum, 42 kg/m2). The mean Euroscore was 21.92(maximum, 94.29). Hypertension was present as apreoperative risk factor in most patients (74.2%);dyslipidemia was present in 51.6%, diabetes mellitus in38.7%, stroke in 7.3%, and renal failure in 2.4%. It wasnoteworthy was that the group who underwent coronaryrevascularization had the highest mortality rate (nearly35% of the 124 patients). The next highest mortality rate(19.4%) was in patients who had combined procedures(valve repair or substitution plus coronaryrevascularization). Mortality was 18.5% in the groupundergoing aortic valve surgery and 11.3% in thoseundergoing mitral valve surgery. The mean duration ofextracorporeal circulation was 148.63 minutes...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tur, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrandis, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pajares, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marqués, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reina, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muedra, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aparicio, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Loro, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuente, C. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soria, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguar, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llagunes, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llopis, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cantó, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ripoll, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Porta, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Osseyran, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillén, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Analizar los datos clínicos y tratar de identificarlos factores asociados que pudieran haber influidoen la mortalidad postoperatoria de los pacientes decirugía cardiaca durante su permanencia en la Unidadde Cuidados Críticos de los hospitales de la sanidadpública de la Comunidad Valenciana durante el 2007.MÉTODO: Estudio retrospectivo desde 1 enero de 2007hasta 31 diciembre del 2007. Se revisaron todas las historiasclínicas de los pacientes operados de cirugía cardiacacon y sin circulación extracorpórea y se aplicó unformulario de recogida de datos que permitió obtener lainformación necesaria para determinar edad, sexo, índicede masa corporal, factores de riesgo prequirúrgicos,tipo de intervención quirúrgica realizada, tiempo de circulaciónextracorpórea, tiempo de isquemia, causa demortalidad y tiempo de estancia en la Unidad de CuidadosCríticos.RESULTADOS: En los 5 centros públicos donde se realizacirugía cardiaca la población estudiada fue de 2.113pacientes. El número de pacientes fallecidos fue de 124,de ellos 70 fueron hombres y 54 mujeres. La media deedad fue 70 años (DE 9,43) oscilando entre 36 y 91 años.El valor medio del índice de masa corporal fue de 28,19kg/m2 con un máximo de 42 kg/m2. El valor medio delEuroscore fue de 21,92 con un máximo de 94,29. Entrelos factores de riesgo estudiados la hipertensión arterialestaba presente en la mayoría de los pacientes (74,2%),dislipemia en el 51,6% de los casos, diabetes mellitus enel 38,7%, accidentes cerebrovasculares previos en el7,3% e insuficiencia renal previa a la cirugía en el 2,4%...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;57(2): 79-85, feb. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78829</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis descriptivo de mortalidad en cirugía cardiaca en los hospitales públicos de la Comunidad Valenciana en el año 2007</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14290^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13148^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6935^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6935^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6935^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13148^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14290^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
