<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136598</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hydatid disease in Department of Health two of the Valencian Community (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hydatidosis is one of the most important zoonotic parasitic diseases of Mediterranean and South American countries where they constitute a significant health problem. Its diagnosis is realized essentially by image techniques and its treatment continues being eminently surgical. During the period 2000-2005, we reviewed clinical records of diagnosed and treated cases of hydatidosis carried out at the Department of Health 2 of the Valencia Community, Spain. Thirty three cases were evaluated of which we describe demographic, radiological, clinical, analytic, therapeutical and evolutionary data. We discuss the peculiarities found in them: thirty two cases were of hepatic location, essentially right, 48.5% unique cysts, five casual finding, 88.87% were diagnosed by ultrasonographic technique and in 2/3 of the cases the serology was positive. In addition, 52.17% of the twenty three cases treated surgically cured without recurrence and a 15.15 % recurred without subsequent healing. Studies will require long term monitoring of patients evolution (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Téllez, C. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hidatidosis es una de las más importantes parasitosis zoonóticas de los países mediterráneos y del cono sur de América en los que constituye un importante problema de salud. Su diagnóstico se realiza fundamentalmente por técnicas de imagen y su tratamiento sigue siendo eminentemente quirúrgico. Durante el período 2000-2005 revisamos las historias clínicas de los casos de hidatidosis diagnosticados y tratados en el Departamento de Salud 2 de la Comunidad Valenciana. Se evaluaron 33 casos de los que describimos datos demográficos, radiológicos, clínicos, analíticos, terapéuticos y evolutivos. Se discuten las particularidades encontradas en ellos; 32 eran de localización hepática, fundamentalmente derecha, un 48,5% quistes únicos, 5 hallazgo casual, el 88,87% se diagnosticaron por ecografía y en 2/3 de los casos la serología fue positiva. Un 52,17% de los 23 casos tratados quirúrgicamente curó sin recidivas y un 15,15% recidivó sin curación posterior. Se requieren estudios que a largo plazo controlen la evolución de los pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;22(2): 62-67, jun. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136598</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Casos de hidatidosis en el Departamento de Salud 2 de la Comunidad Valenciana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22491</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4510^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38512^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4509^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22835^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4509^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4510^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d886^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4510^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24511^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4509^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4510^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4509^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
