<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046274</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endovascular surgery of thoracic aortic aneurysms</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims and development. In this article we review the problems involved in the endovascular treatment of    thoracic aortic aneurysms with an atherosclerotic origin. Thus, we analyse the features involved in this therapeutic    alternative that are conditioned by a number of aspects including those based on age, the patient&#146;s general state, any    associated pathologies and general to other more specific risk factors, according to the morphology of the lesions as    regards characteristics such as their diameter, extension, the involvement of collateral or visceral branches, and the    existence of mural thrombus or kinking or folds. Treatment is also conditioned by the possibility of placing different    types of stents, which, together with the biological aspects involved, have a greater or lesser effect on ensuring the short    and long-term outcomes of the therapy. The article includes a discussion on the evidence obtained from the results of    conventional open surgery and future prospects with regard to the contributions made by the latest diagnostic techniques    and the appearance of new devices for endovascular applications</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vaquero-Puerta, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Alonso, V. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco-Alonso, I. del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrera, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mengíbar- Fuentes, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Fajardo, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Norberto-García, E. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cenizo, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez-Maraña, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brizuela-Sanz, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Río-Solá, M. L del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo y desarrollo. Se realiza una revisión de la problemática que plantea el tratamiento endovascular de    los aneurismas de aorta torácica de origen ateroscleroso. Para ello, se analizan los aspectos implicados en esta opción    terapéutica que condicionan múltiples aspectos: desde los basados en la edad, estado general del paciente, patología    asociada, los factores de riesgo desde un punto de vista general hasta otros más específicos, según la morfología de las    lesiones en los aspectos de diámetro, extensión, afectación de ramas colaterales o viscerales, existencia de trombo mural    o angulaciones o plicaturas. El tratamiento también está condicionado por la posibilidad de colocación de diferentes    tipos de endoprótesis, las cuales aseguraran en mayor o menor grado, junto con la implicación de aspectos biológicos,    los resultados del tratamiento a corto y largo plazo. Se discute la evidencia de los resultados de la cirugía abierta convencional    y las posibilidades futuras en comparación con las aportaciones de nuevas técnicas diagnósticas y la aparición    de nuevos dispositivos de aplicación endovascular</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;58(supl.1): S25-S35, 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046274</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cirugía endovascular de los aneurismas de aorta torácica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7678^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7678^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30828^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30828^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15058^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
