<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129498</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-5434</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sellar and parasellar syndrome: a novel bilateral multiple mononeuropathy in dogs and cats</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The sellar and parasellar region (SPS) contains bone structures, vascular structures, somatic and autonomous nerves, the pituitary gland and meningeal structures related that predisposes to various neurological, ophthalmologic or endocrine diseases The aim of this work is to describe the anatomy of the SPS region and communicate a clinical picture observed in a dog and 2 cats consisting of a multiple mononeuropathy involving various cranial nerves on their way in relation to this region and, by its nature, is particularly syndrome. To our knowledge this is the first description of a syndrome affecting dogs and cats and can simultaneously engage one or more of the II, III, IV, V (ophthalmic, maxillary and mandibular nerves) and VI cranial nerves, the pituitary gland and its meningeal coverings, and the brain and brain stem (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pellegrino, F. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vazzoler, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pacheco, E. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La región selar y paraselar (SPS) contiene formaciones óseas, vasculares, nervios somáticos y autónomos, la hipófisis y las estructuras meníngeas relacionadas que la convierte en asiento de diversas patologías neurológicas, oftalmológicas o endocrinológicas. El objetivo de este trabajo es describir la anatomía de la región SPS y comunicar un cuadro clínico observado en un perro y en 2 gatos consistente en una mononeuropatía múltiple que involucra diversos NC en su recorrido en relación a esta región que, por sus características, constituye un síndrome particular. En nuestro conocimiento esta es la primera descripción de un síndrome que afecte a perros y gatos y que pueda comprometer simultáneamente uno o más de los NC II, III, IV, los 3 nervios que forman el V (oftálmico, maxilar y mandibular) y VI, a la glándula hipófisis y sus cubiertas meníngeas, y al tronco encefálico (diencéfalo) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. vet. Murcia;29: 93-110, ene.-dic. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129498</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome selar y paraselar: una nueva mononeuropatía múltiple bilateral en perros y gatos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3407^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9726^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2454</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9726^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13040^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24792^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34339^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28275^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34339^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14515^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31887^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31887^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34339^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10444^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
