<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73514</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A two-phase population study: relationships between overweight, body composition and risk of eating disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Overweight and eating disorder (ED) are major public health problems in adolescents. Aims: To assess the association of overweight, body composition and anthropometric characteristics with the probability being at risk of ED. Methods: A two-phase study was used. 329 girls and 96 boys (aged 12-18 years) from an initial sample of 2967 adolescents were studied. The BMI, percentage of fat mass estimated by bioimpedance (FM(BIA)), waist circumference, waist-to-height ratio, and waist-to-hip ratio (WHipr) were calculated. The Eating Attitudes Test, Youth's Inventory-4 and a questionnaire to evaluate social influences were administered. Results: A total of 34.7% of girls and 53.6% of boys at risk of ED were overweight (including obesity). For girls, overweight frequency was significantly higher in risk ED group than in control group. Increases of one point in the BMI or FM(BIA) increased the probability of being at risk of ED by 12% (3.0-19.0) and 4% (0.0-8.0), respectively. An increase in Whipr was negatively associated with ED risk. Smoking and symptoms of dysthymia and the genralized anxiety disorder also increase the probability of being at risk of ED in adolescent girls. In adolescent boys, these relations were not observed. Conclusions: The higher BMI and the percentage of FM(BIA) are associated with greater risk of ED in adolescent girls, when psychological factors are present. Increases in the WHipr, characteristic of childhood body is negatively associated with that risk (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arija, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pietrobelli, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canals, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Babio, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El sobrepeso y los Trastornos de la Conducta Alimentaria (TCA) son problemas importantes de salud pública entre los adolescentes. Objetivos: Valorar la asociación del sobrepeso, la composición corporal y otras características antropométricas con la probabilidad de estar en riesgo de desarrollar un TCA.  Métodos: Se realizó un estudio con un diseño en doble fase. Se estudiaron 329 chicas y 96 chicos (de 12-18 años) procedentes de una muestra inicial de 2967 adolescentes. Se calcularon el índice de masa corporal (IMC), el porcentaje de masa grasa (% MG(BIA)), la circunferencia de la cintura, los cocientes cintura-talla y cintura-cadera. Se administraron el Eating Attitudes Test, el Youth's Inventory-4 y un cuestionario para evaluar influencia sociocultural. Resultados: El 34,7% de las chicas y el 53,6% de los chicos con riesgo de TCA presentan sobrepeso (incluyendo obesidad). La frecuencia de sobrepeso es significativamente más alta en las chicas del grupo de riesgo de TCA que las del grupo control. En las adolescentes, el aumento de un punto en el IMC o en el % MG(BIA) incrementa el riesgo de estar en riesgo de TCA en 12% (3,0-19,0) y 4% (0,0-8,0), respectivamente; un incremento en el cociente cintura-cadera se asocia negativamente con el riesgo de TCA. Fumar, presentar síntomas de distimia y de trastornos de ansiedad generalizada también se asociaron con la probabilidad de estar en riesgo de TCA, en las adolescentes. En los varones, no se han observado esas relaciones. Conclusiones: El mayor IMC y de % MG(BIA) se asocian con mayor riesgo de TCA en las adolescentes cuando los factores psicológicos están presentes. Un aumento en el cociente cintura-cadera, característico de un cuerpo infantil, se asocia negativamente con el riesgo de TCA (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;24(4): 485-491, jul.-ago. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73514</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio a doble fase: relación entre el sobrepeso, la composición corporal y el riesgo de trastorno de la conducta alimentaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24382^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24382^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
