<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72990</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidemiological study on the demand for rehabilitation in hospitalized patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Specialists in Physical Medicineand Rehabilitation (FM&amp;R) attend to patients who have losttheir autonomy. A large number of hospitalized patients whohad acquired a disability need to be attended by rehabilitationtherapists. We have developed this descriptive study toanalyze demand for rehabilitation in patients admitted to ourhospital.Materials and methods. A prospective observational studywas performed for all the patients admitted during themonths of February, March and April 2008 who were evaluatedby our department.Results. In our FM&amp;R Department from February to April2008 (60 days), there were 464 consultations made by345 patients. Average daily consultations to our departmentwas 7.73 and average number of consultations per patientwas 1.36 (SD 0.70, range 1-7). Of the 354 patients evaluatedduring the study, 55 were not included in therapy as they didnot meet the criteria. Thus 84 % of the hospitalized patientshas required rehabilitation.Conclusion. This study has revealed that a considerablenumber of inpatients need assessment and treatment fromFM&amp;R Department. Traumatology and Internal Medicine Departmentsare those who demand our care the most. Only aminority of patients required outpatient physical therapytreatment(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Balsa-Mosquera, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Vázquez, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villamayor-Blanco, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Fraga, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los especialistas en Medicina Físicay Rehabilitación (MFyR) damos asistencia a pacientes que hanperdido su autonomía. Hay un porcentaje considerable de pacienteshospitalizados que adquieren una discapacidad y precisanser asistidos por terapeutas de Rehabilitación. Hemos desarrolladoel presente estudio descriptivo para analizar la demandade rehabilitación en pacientes ingresados en nuestro hospital.Material y métodos. Se realizó un estudio observacionalprospectivo, que incluyó a todos los pacientes ingresados yque fueron valorados por nuestro servicio durante los mesesde febrero, marzo y abril de 2008.Resultados. El número de interconsultas realizadas por elServicio de MFyR durante los meses de febrero-abril de 2008(60 días laborales) ha sido de 464 para atender a 345 pacientes.La media de interconsultas diaria a nuestro servicio hasido de 7,73 y el número medio de interconsultas por pacienteha sido de 1,36 (desviación estándar [DE] 0,70; rango1-7). De los 354 pacientes valorados durante el estudio,55 no fueron incluidos en terapia por no cumplir los criterios,lo que significa que un 84 % de los pacientes hospitalizadosha precisado tratamiento rehabilitador.Conclusión. El presente estudio nos ha permitido conocerque un porcentaje considerable de pacientes hospitalizadosnecesita valoración y tratamiento por parte de los serviciosde MFyR. Los servicios de Traumatología y Medicina Internason los que demandan más nuestra asistencia. Solo un grupominoritario de pacientes precisa continuar tratamiento deforma ambulatoria(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);43(4): 167-175, jul.-ago.2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72990</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio epidemiológico sobre la demanda de rehabilitación en pacientes hospitalizados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12467^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12467^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33576^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6453^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1185^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6453^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33577^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
