<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87402</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Case-working history at risk management units: An update</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A case-working history is a document which contains all the information about workers&#146; surveillanceand health control, so it should take in account not only those data which are often collected in a casehistory, but also the posts and risks the worker could have been exposed to during their working life in orderto establish a relationship between cause and effect with the pathology they may present at a given time.It has a multiple usability: epidemiologic analysis, health surveillance and teaching.It should defend no discrimination in general, and particularly to immigrant workers following theguidelines given for health surveillance. The access to the data in a case-working history is established bylaw. It is not only a confidential document, which should be under the control of health staff, but it is alsoconsidered to be a file which should be kept for five years after the worker has resigned, except for thosesituations in which workers are exposed to special risks (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mallada Rivero, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espina Álvarez, Carlota</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canga Alonso,  Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La historia clínico-laboral es el documento que recoge toda la información y documentación relativa ala vigilancia y control de la salud de los trabajadores; por lo que debe contemplar no solo los datos quehabitualmente recoge la historia médica; sino también los distintos puestos y riesgos a que haya podido estarexpuesto el trabajador a lo largo de su vida laboral, tratando de establecer la posible relación causa-efectocon la patología que en un momento dado presente.Su utilidad es múltiple: análisis epidemiológico, pericia médica, docencia.Debe hacer suya la no discriminación en general y particularmente de los trabajadores emigrantes, ensintonía con los principios generales de la vigilancia de la salud.El acceso a la historia clínico-laboral está establecido en la normativa vigente. Es un documentoconfidencial que debe permanecer bajo la custodia del personal sanitario y tiene la consideración de fichero;debiendo conservarse, con carácter general, hasta cinco años después que el trabajador haya causado bajaen la empresa por finalización de la relación laboral, salvo en casos reglamentados por riesgos especiales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;55(217): 57-64, oct.-dic. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87402</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La historia clínico-laboral en los servicios de prevención de riesgos laborales: Actualizacion</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51562</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
