<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054930</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Compliance with the document of the Spanish society of nephrology 2002 document for the control of diabetic nephropathy in Catalonia. (ECODIAB)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the level of compliance with the 2002 consensus document (Spanish        Society of Nephrology) on guidelines for the detection, prevention and treatment of        diabetic nephropathy in Catalonia.        Subjects and methods: Multicenter (23 hospitals), observational, cross-sectional, descriptive        study conducted in 413 diabetic patients (61.7% men, 38.3% women) with a median        age of 66.2 ± 11.5 years (26-93 years). The ANOVA test (post-hoc analysis; p value         30 kg/m2: 48.7%) and waist circumference        104.1 ± 14 cm (48.6% men &gt; 102 cm and 78.9% women &gt; 88 cm). Serum creatinine        1.9 ± 1.3 mg/dl and simplified MDRD equation 45.3 ± 25.0 ml/min/1.73 m2 [65.8%        with CKD stages 3 and 4]. 80% of patients had ophthalmologic examination and 52.8%        antiplatelet treatment. Hb A1c was 7.3 ± 1.3%, but the percentage of patients with glycated        hemoglobin &gt; 7% and 8% was 54.9 and 28.6% [only 50.2% had been seen by an        endocrinologist in the last 6 months]. 52.8% of patients were treated with insulin and 44.1%        with anti-diabetic drugs, although only 19.6% used the new anti-diabetic drugs. 61% of        patients had an LDLc &gt; 100 mg/dl (61% treated) and 44% had triglycerides (TG) &gt; 150        mg/dl (72% treated). 95% of patients presented with hypertension (BP &gt;= 130/80 mmHg),        91% were undergoing antihypertensive treatment (79.7% with angiotensin-converting enzyme        inhibitors and / or angiotensin receptor blockers). 81% with microalbuminuria and 78%        with established proteinuria were receiving antiproteinuric treatment. Of the patients considered        to be refractory to BP (&gt;3 drugs), only 28.9% underwent ambulatory BP monitoring.        Significant differences were observed between stages of diabetic nephropathy and glycated        hemoglobin (HBA1c; p = 0.048), systolic blood pressure (SBP; p = 0.024), lipidic        control (HDLc; p = 0.015 and TG; p = 0.034), anemia (Hb; p = 0.010) and CKD (creatinine        and sMDRD; p = 0.000). The levels of compliance with the therapeutic objectives        regarding lipid control (LDL &lt;= 100 mg/dl and TG &lt;= 150 mg/dl), BP &lt;= 130/80 mmHg and        HbA1c &lt;= 7% were 1 objective: 68%, 2 objectives: 21.8% and 3 objectives: only 4% of        patients.        Conclusions: According to the results of our study, only a reduced proportion of patients        fulfilled the different therapeutic end-points indicated. Future measures will be directed at        improving physician-patient relationships with the main aim of intensifying the therapeutic        measures to attain better metabolic and blood pressure control, nephroprotection and prevention        in the appearance of cardiovascular events</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torres, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuevas, X. de las</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fort, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonal, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fontseré, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar el grado de cumplimiento del documento de consenso 2002 (SEN)        sobre pautas de detección, prevención y tratamiento de la nefropatía diabética en Cataluña.        Pacientes y métodos: Estudio multicéntrico de corte transversal (23 centros hospitalarios),        observacional y descriptivo, realizado sobre un total de 413 pacientes diabéticos (61,7%        hombres y 38,3% mujeres) con una edad media de 66,2 ± 11,5 años (26-93 años). Para        el análisis estadístico entre los diferentes grados de nefropatía diabética y las variables del        estudio, se utilizó un test de ANOVA con valoración post-hoc (p  30 kg/m2: 48,7%) y perímetro de cintura 104,1        ± 14 cm (48,6% hombres &gt; 102 cm y 78,9% mujeres &gt; 88 cm). El valor de la creatinina        sérica 1,9 ± 1,3 mg/dl y el GFR estimado con la ecuación MDRD simplificada (MDRDs)        45,3 ± 25,0 ml/min/1,73 m2 [65,8% con ERC estadios 3 y 4]. El 80% de los pacientes        tenían examen oftalmológico y el 52,8% recibía tratamiento antiagregante. La Hb A1c fue        7,3 ± 1,3%, pero el porcentaje de pacientes con glicadas &gt; 7% y 8% resultó del 54,9 y        28,6% respectivamente [tan sólo el 50,2% había sido visitado por el endocrinólogo en los        últimos 6 meses]. El 52,8% de los pacientes se encontraban en tratamiento con insulina y        el 44,1% con ADOs, pero tan sólo un 19,6% con antidiabéticos de metabolización hepática.        El 61% de la muestra tenia un LDLc &gt; 100 mg/dl (61% tratados) y el 44% triglicéridos        (TG) &gt; 150 mg/dl (72% tratados). El 95% de los pacientes presentaban antecedentes        de hipertensión arterial (&gt;= 130/80 mmHg) y de estos el 91% se encontraban con tratamiento        hipotensor (79,7% con IECAS y/o ARA tipo II). El 81% de los microalbuminúricos y el        78% de los macroalbuminúricos recibía algún tipo de tratamiento antiproteinúrico. Entre        el grupo de pacientes considerados con HTA refractaria (&gt;3 fármacos), tan sólo el 29%        tenía un MAPA. Se obtuvieron relaciones significativas entre los diferentes estadios de nefropatía        diabética y el control glucémico (HBA1c; p = 0,048), tensión arterial sistólica (TAS; p = 0,024), perfil lipídico (HDLc; p = 0,015 y TG; p = 0,034), anemia (Hb; p = 0,010)        y grado de ERC (creatinina sérica y MDRDs; p = 0,000). El grado de cumplimiento terapéutico        sobre el control lipídico (LDL &lt;= 100 mg/dl y TG &lt;= 150 mg/dl), TA &lt;= 130/80 mmHg        y HbA1c &lt;= 7%; fue 1 objetivo: 68%, 2 objetivos: 21,8% y 3 objetivos: sólo el 4% de la        muestra.        Conclusiones: Según los resultados obtenidos en nuestro estudio, tan sólo un reducido        porcentaje de pacientes cumplieron los diferentes «end points» terapéuticos marcados. Futuras        acciones deberán ir encaminadas a potenciar la relación entre médico-paciente, con        el principal objetivo de intensificar aquellas medidas terapéuticas encaminadas a un mejor        control metabólico y tensional, nefroprotector y prevención de los eventos cardiovasculares</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;26(6): 679-687, nov.-dic. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054930</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio sobre el grado de cumplimiento ambulatorio del documento de consenso 2002 para el control de la nefropatía diabética en Cataluña (ECCODIAB)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3421^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28634</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3421</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22965^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22190^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3951^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10223^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3951^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3951^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
