<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054846</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of an intensity of interprofessional collaboration questionnaire translated into Spanish</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To assess the validity and reliability of the Spanish version of the Intensity of Interprofessional Collaboration questionnaire (Sicotte et al). Method. In the first phase, the questionnaire was translated and adapted to Spanish. The questionnaire was then distributed to a sample of 123 nurses in a Spanish University hospital. In the second phase, the construct validity, convergent validity, and internal consistency of the Spanish version of the questionnaire were determined. Results. A principal components analysis with Promax rotation suggested the existence of 4 factors that accounted for 61.47% of the total variance. Pearson's correlation coefficient between the Spanish instrument and another instrument measuring the same phenomenon was 0.718. Analysis of the internal consistency of the instrument showed a Cronbach's * coefficient of 0.907. Conclusion. We can conclude that the intensity of interprofessional collaboration scale shows good validity and reliability in the measurement of the intensity of collaboration among professionals in healthcare teams</dc:description>
<dc:creator>D'Amour, Danielle</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leduc, Nicole</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Martín-Rodríguez, Leticia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Establecer la fiabilidad y validez de una versión española del cuestionario Intensité de la Collaboration Interprofessionnelle de Sicotte et al. Método. Tras una primera etapa de traducción al español y de adaptación, el instrumento se ha distribuido a una muestra de 123 enfermeras de un hospital universitario español. La segunda etapa ha consistido en la determinación de: 1) la validez estructural; 2) la validez convergente, y 3) la consistencia interna de la versión española del instrumento. Resultados. El análisis factorial en componentes principales y con rotación Promax sugiere la existencia de 4 factores que explican el 61,47% de la varianza total. Por otro lado, el coeficiente de correlación de Pearson entre el instrumento a estudio y otro instrumento que mide el mismo fenómeno es de 0,718. Por último, el análisis de la coherencia interna del instrumento ha mostrado un * de Cronbach de 0,907. Conclusión. Se puede concluir que la escala Intensidad de la colaboración entre los profesionales de la salud (ICPS) posee un buen grado de validez y fiabilidad para medir la colaboración que hay entre los profesionales de la salud en los equipos interprofesionales</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);17(1): 24-31, ene. 2007. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054846</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación de un instrumento de medida de la intensidad de la colaboración entre los profesionales de la salud traducido al español</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6276</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3320</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10542^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
