<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100833</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Descriptive study of intrapartum antibiotic prophilaxis of neonatal infection by group b streptococcus in Txagorritxu</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. GBS is one of the most important causes of neonatal sepsis of vertical transmission (1-2% of the carriers). The infection may involve newborn´s death or severe complications.  The culture of vaginal and rectal GBS is a screening test and it is performed to all pregnant women between 35-37 weeks of gestation. If it is positive, intrapartum penicillin is prescribed. If it is negative or unknown, the antibiotic per protocol is given according to risk factors: rupture of membranes more than 18 hours, intrapartum temperature, or prematurity.  The aim of this study is to quantify women who receive intrapartum antibiotic in relation to the positive culture and achievement with the SEGO´s recommendation.  Material and methods. It describes a sample of 261 women of the Txagorritxu Hospital who have given birth during the work shift of researchers, excluding cesarean sections.  Variables: results of culture, antibiotic administration. Data were collected by reviewing and analyzed medical records using SPSS 17.0.  Results. From 261 women, 69 (26.4%) received antibiotic administration. From 69, 46 (66.67%) had a positive culture. 26 (37.68%) received antibiotics according to risk factors, although their cultures were negative or unknown.  Discussion. The results suggest there is a correct application of the SEGO´s recommendation. Carrier women with no risk factors would not have received antibiotic therapy without screening(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calzada Hernández, M. Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordax García, Leire</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Terrades Milla, Claudia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El SGB (Streptococcus grupo B) es una de las causas más importantes de sepsis neonatal por transmisión vertical (1-2% de las portadoras). La infección puede comportar la muerte del recién nacido o complicaciones severas. El cultivo vagino-rectal del SGB es una prueba de detección que se realiza a todas las embarazadas entre las semanas 35-37 de gestación. Si es positivo se prescribe penicilina intraparto. Si es negativo o desconocido, el antibiótico se protocoliza según factores de riesgo: rotura de membranas mayor de 18 horas, fiebre intraparto o prematuridad. El objetivo del estudio es cuantificar las mujeres que reciben antibiótico intraparto en relación con el cultivo positivo y el cumplimiento de la recomendación de la SEGO (Sociedad Española de Ginecología y Obstetricia). Material y métodos. Se describe una muestra de 261 mujeres del hospital de Txagorritxu, que han parido durante el turno de trabajo de los investigadores, excluyendo las cesáreas.  Variables: resultado de cultivo, administración de antibiótico. Los datos fueron recogidos por revisión de historia clínica y analizados con el programa SPSS 17.0. Resultados. De las 261 mujeres, 69 (26,4%) recibieron la administración antibiótico. De las 69, 46 (66,67%) tenían un cultivo positivo. Recibieron antibioterapia según factores de riesgo 26 (37,68%), aunque sus cultivos fueran negativo o desconocido. Discusión. Los resultados apuntan a una aplicación correcta de la recomendación de la SEGO. Las mujeres portadoras sin factores de riesgo no habrían recibido antibioterapia sin screening(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;35(2): 135-138, feb. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100833</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio descriptivo de profilaxis antibiótica. Infección neonatal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2710^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30642^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30642^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30642^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11437^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
