<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61451</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Management of hypertension in pregnancy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hypertensive states of pregnancy are a set of disordersthat occur during gestation whose common nexusis hypertension. They must be given special emphasisdue to their implication in maternal and neonatal morbidityand mortality.A classification is made of the different hypertensivestates, with special emphasis placed on preeclampsia.This article defines the symptoms and signs of thedisease and a differential diagnosis is made amongstdiseases that must be ruled out. It is important to identifyexpectant mothers with preeclampsia, and it is ofeven greater importance in such cases to rule out somecriterion of seriousness, as this will enable a differentmanagement to be carried out.The article includes the indications and the momentwhen the pregnancy finalises. Similarly, it detailsthe controls that must be made if an expectant managementis chosen for the benefit of the premature baby.The different anti-hypertensive therapeutical optionsare detailed, as well as the prophylactic treatment ofeclampsia with magnesium sulphate.Because of their intrinsic interest, we draw specialattention to the HELLP syndrome and to eclampsia ascomplications. The treatment and conduct that must befollowed in gestation is described(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Modroño, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Huarte, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larrañaga, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los estados hipertensivos del embarazo son unconjunto de desórdenes que acontecen durante la gestacióncuyo nexo común es la hipertensión. Deben serdestacados dada su implicación en la morbimortalidadmaterna y neonatal.Se realiza una clasificación de los diferentes estadoshipertensivos poniendo especial interés en la preeclampsia.En el texto se definen los síntomas y signosde la enfermedad y se realiza un diagnóstico diferencialentre enfermedades que debemos descartar. Es de interésidentificar las gestantes con preeclampsia y todavíaresulta de mayor interés descartar en ellas algún criteriode gravedad ya que esto nos obligará a realizar unmanejo diferente.A lo largo del texto, se adjuntan las indicacionesy el momento de finalización de la gestación. De igualforma se detallan los controles que deben realizarse sise opta por una conducta expectante en beneficio delprematuro. Se detallan las diferentes opciones terapeúticasantihipertensivas así como el tratamiento profilácticode la eclampsia con sulfato de magnesio.Destacamos por su interés el Síndrome de HELLPy la eclampsia como complicaciones. Se describe eltratamiento y la conducta que se debe tomar en la gestación(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;32(supl.1): 91-103, ene.-jun. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61451</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conducta ante los estados hipertensivos del embarazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11689^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38639^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30704^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11662^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4529^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
