<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129429</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-6581</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Morphological characteristics of the triathlete according to sex, category and competitive level</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The triathlon combines three resistance sport disciplines and requires physical characteristics to optimize the performance of each segment. The aim of this study was to determine the morphological profile of the triathlete. A retrospective analysis was performed on 153 protocols including: weight, height, perimeters, diameters, lengths, and skin folds. The male and female samples were divided into senior and junior, and senior into first and second ranking levels. The somatotype was ecto-mesomorph, except for junior females, for which it was central. The senior category had a fat percentage (Withers, 1987) lower than the junior, men 7.4 vs.8.5; females 13.9 vs. 16.8; and level 1 compared to level 2 in females, 11.8 vs. 16.2. Muscle mass (Lee, 2000) for the senior was higher than for the junior, in males in kilograms (32.1 vs.30.9), and females in percentage (42.8 vs. 41); level 1 female compared to 2 (44.2 vs. 41.2).Muscle cross-section areas (Heysmfield, 1982) in arm and thigh were higher in senior male than in junior male; and for senior female in the thigh it was higher in level 1 than in level 2. The indices were in the middle range, the senior male having a brachial index greater than the junior male. Males only reached the senior phase in the upper body musculoskeletal development; while females reach it in the junior phase. The performance in the senior females is marked by greater age and lower fat levels. Triathletes should have a weight with low percentage of body fat and a musculoskeletal component in the medium range (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Canda, Alicia Sofía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nekane Toro, Ainhoa Nekane</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Higueras, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castiblanco, Luis Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amestoy, Javier Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El triatlón combina 3 modalidades deportivas de resistencia y necesita unas características físicas para optimizar el rendimiento de cada segmento. El objetivo fue determinar el perfil morfológico del triatleta. Se analizaron retrospectivamente 153 protocolos incluyendo: peso, talla, perímetros, diámetros, longitudes y pliegues cutáneos. Se dividieron las muestras masculina y femenina en sénior y junior, y los sénior en primer y segundo nivel competitivo. El somatotipo fue ecto-mesomórfico, excepto en mujeres junior, que fue central. Los sénior tuvieron menor porcentaje graso (Whiters, 1987) que los junior (varones 7,4 vs 8,5; mujeres 13,9 vs 16,8), y las mujeres de nivel 1 respecto al 2 (11,8 vs 16,2). La masa muscular (Lee, 2000) fue mayor en sénior respecto a los junior, en varones en kilos (32,1 vs 30,9) y en mujeres en porcentaje (42,8 vs 41); las mujeres de nivel 1 respecto al 2 (44,2 vs 41,2). Las áreas musculares transversales (Heysmfield, 1982) fueron mayores en sénior varones en brazo y muslo respecto al junior, y mujeres sénior de nivel 1 mayor en muslo en relación al 2. Los índices se situaron en rango medio, teniendo los sénior varones un mayor índice braquial que los junior. Los varones hasta la etapa sénior no alcanzan el desarrollo musculoesquelético del tren superior; mientras que las mujeres lo alcanzan en la etapa junior. En las mujeres sénior su nivel de rendimiento lo marca una mayor edad y niveles de grasa más bajos. Los triatletas deberán tener un peso con bajo porcentaje graso y un componente musculoesquelético en rango medio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apunts, Med. esport (Internet);49(183): 75-84, jul.-sept. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129429</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características morfológicas del triatleta según sexo, categoría y nivel competitivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d26146</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36345^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1860^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13391^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1852^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
