<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143622</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-3334</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Teachers interaction style in the classroom, and cognitive development: The Cognitive Mobilizing Patterns</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Data presented here has been carried obtained within a broader study related to the thinking skills programme Comprehending and Transforming (C&amp;T). Three groups of school-age children that participated in this intervention with differing positive pretest-postst gains were included. We hypothesized that it is the teachers different interaction style in the classroom that explains the different results of each group. In order to confirm this, an observation instrument was developed and 26 programme videotaped sessions were analysed. Results are in agreement with the idea that certain aspects of interaction (which we call Cognitive Mobilizing Patterns) are relevant for the stimulation of thinking skills. Conclusions point to the need to incorporate these patterns in the training of persons responsible for the implementation of C&amp;T (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Agullera Jiménez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora Roche, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo se ha realizado en el contexto de otra investigación más amplia en torno al programa de estimulación de habilidades de pensamiento Comprender y Transformar (CyT). Hemos partido de tres grupos de escolares que han seguido el citado programa con ganancias distintas en un estudio pretest-postest. Tomamos dichos grupos como sujetos de nuestra investigación y propusimos la hipótesis de que es el distinto estilo de interacción en el aula que mantiene cada aplicador el que explica la diferencia de resultados. Con objeto de comprobada procedimos a la construcción de instrumentos de observación y al análisis de 26 sesiones de aplicación del citado programa grabadas en vídeo. Los resultados confirman la hipótesis destacando algunos aspectos de la interacción (a los que denominamos Patrones de Movilización Cognitiva) como relevantes para la estimulación del pensamiento. Como consecuencia, la formación de los aplicadores de CyT debe incorporar el entrenamiento para la activación de dichas pautas de interacción (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apuntes psicol;21(1): 5-27, 2003. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143622</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pautas de interacción en el aula y desarrollo cognitivo: los Patrones de Movilización Cognitiva (PMC)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29986</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8776</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3102^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14230</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200300</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
