<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038751</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Emergency department activity during the 2003 summer heat wave</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Several thousands deaths were attributed to a heatwave during the summer of 2003 in Europe. The aim of this study was to analyze its consequences in an emergency department. Patients and method: We performed a descriptive observational study of the patients admitted to our emergency unit between 15 July and 31 August, 2003. We also carried out a comparative study of these patients with those admitted during the same period of 2002. Results: A total of 5197 patients were admitted in our unit during the summer of 2003, in comparison with 4672 in the same interval in 2002. An increase in rates of total fever (17% versus 12%; p &lt; 0.001), non-infectious fever (29% versus 26%; p &lt; 0.001), decompensation of a chronic cardiovascular or respiratory disease (14% versus 11%; p &lt; 0.001), admission (28% versus 22%; p &lt; 0.001), and mortality (2% versus 1%; p &lt; 0.001) were registered during the summer of 2003, in comparison with the previous year. A multivariate study showed a higher risk of death in patients older than 70 years (p &lt; 0.01), in fragile dependent people (p &lt; 0.05), and upon the presence of abnormal blood levels of creatinine (p &lt; 0.05) on arrival at the emergency department. We also found an association between daily maxim temperature and number of daily emergency visits (R2 = 0.15; p &lt; 0.001), total percentage of patients with fever (R2 = 0.26; p &lt; 0.001), percentage of patients with non-infectious fever (R2 = 0.07; p = 0.01), percentage of deceases (R2 = 0.04; p &lt; 0.05), and percentage of hospital admissions (R2 = 0.15; p &lt; 0.001). Conclusions: The summer 2003 heatwave resulted in an elevation of the total number of emergency visits and hospital admissions, and higher mortality and morbility rates, especially in old people. In the future, preventive measures must be taken to limit the health consequences of any heatwaves to come</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miró, Òscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Collvinent, Blanca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Red, Gloria de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salmerón, Joan M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trejo, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bragulat, Ernest</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Asenjo, Miguel A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>sánchez, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Durante la ola de calor del verano de 2003 se registraron varios miles de fallecimientos en Europa. Se analizan las consecuencias de esta ola de calor en una sección de urgencias de medicina de un servicio de urgencias hospitalario. Pacientes y método: Estudio descriptivo de las características de los pacientes visitados en una sección de urgencias de medicina entre el 15 de julio y el 31 de agosto de 2003, y se compara con las de los que fueron atendidos durante el mismo intervalo en 2002. Resultados: El número total de pacientes atendidos en el verano de 2003 fue de 5.197, frente a los 4.672 del año anterior. Durante 2003 aumentó, con respecto al año 2002, el porcentaje total de pacientes con fiebre (el 17 frente al 12%; p &lt; 0,001), fiebre de causa no infecciosa (el 29 frente al 26%; p &lt; 0,001), descompensación de enfermedad crónica (el 14 frente al 11%; p &lt; 0,001), ingresados (el 28 frente al 22%; p &lt; 0,001) y fallecidos (el 2 frente al 1%; p &lt; 0,001). Los factores predictivos independientes de mortalidad para los pacientes con fiebre visitados durante la ola de calor de 2003 fueron la edad superior a 70 años (p &lt; 0,01), la dependencia para las actividades de la vida diaria (p &lt; 0,05) y la alteración de las concentraciones de creatinina a su llegada a urgencias (p &lt; 0,05). Además, encontramos una asociación lineal con significación estadística entre la temperatura máxima diaria y el número de visitas diarias a urgencias (R2 = 0,15; p &lt; 0,001), así como con el porcentaje total de pacientes que se visitaron por fiebre (R2 = 0,26; p &lt; 0,001), fiebre de causa no infecciosa (R2 = 0,07; p = 0,01), fallecidos (R2 = 0,04; p &lt; 0,05) e ingresados (R2 = 0,15; p &lt; 0,001). Conclusiones: Durante la ola de calor del verano de 2003 se produjo un aumento del número de visitas a urgencias y de ingresos hospitalarios, así como una mayor tasa de morbimortalidad, especialmente en las personas de edad avanzada. Las autoridades sanitarias deberían llevar a cabo medidas preventivas para limitar las consecuencias sobre la salud pública que pudieran derivarse de futuras olas de calor</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);125(6): 205-209, jul. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038751</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de la ola de calor del verano de 2003 en la actividad de un servicio de urgencias hospitalario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34727</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6509^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
