<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113442</identifier>
<setSpec>2013-6889</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Charles Bonnet syndrome is characterized by the presence of complex visual hallucinations, elaborate and persistent, which the patient recognizes as unreal, in the absence of other psychiatric symptoms. We interviewed a total of eighteen patients from the ophthalmology service with the possible diagnosis of Charles Bonnet syndrome in order to rule out psychiatric disorders. We performed a descriptive analysis of the sample. The mean age was 78.99 years (standard deviation of 9.12) with 83.33% female and 16.67 % male. Most patients (72 %) had no secondary anxiety nor cardiological pathology (78 %) or neurological pathology (78 %). All of them had ophthalmologic pathology, being the most frequent macular degeneration (50%). The most frequent hallucinations were about objects and figures (67 %), manifested continuously up to 28 % of patients. 17 % of the patients had psychiatric disorders, but none justified the presence of visual hallucinations. The Charles Bonnet syndrome is an underdiagnosed disease and difficult to manage, as it requires various evaluations by different specialists(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Quiroga, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saiz González, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos Bueso, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Marsá, Marina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de Charles Bonnet se caracteriza por la presencia de alucinaciones visuales complejas, elaboradas y persistentes, que el paciente reconoce como irreales, en ausencia de otros síntomas psiquiátricos. Se entrevistaron a un total de 18 pacientes derivados del Servicio de Oftal - mología con posible diagnóstico de síndrome de Charles Bonnet, con el fin de descartar patología psiquiátrica. Se realizó un análisis descriptivo de la muestra. La edad media fue de 78,99 años (desviación típica de 9,12), con un 83,33% de mujeres y un 16,67 % de varones. En la mayor parte de los pacientes (72 %) no había ansiedad secundaria, así como tampoco patología somática cardiológica (78 %) ni neurológica (78 %). Todos presentaban patología oftalmológica, siendo la más frecuente la degeneración macular (50 %). Las alucinaciones más frecuentes fueron sobre objetos y figuras (67 %), manifestándose de manera continua hasta en un 28 % de los pacientes. El 17 % de los pacientes presentaba patología psiquiátrica, pero ninguna justificaba la presencia de alucinaciones visuales. El síndrome de Charles Bonnet es una enfermedad infradiagnosticada y de difícil manejo, ya que exige diversas valoraciones por distintos especialistas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Alzheimer (Barc., Internet);(54): 28-34, mayo-ago. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113442</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Charles Bonnet: la alucinación visual en el anciano</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24230^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54195^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6365^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6365^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6365^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15197^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
