<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143989</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-0618</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Regulatory framework for human medicinal products</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A complete review of the regulations applicable to blood derived medicines is made, including European legislation and its transposition into national legislation. This complex and comprehensive regulation is updated and commented to facilitate appropriate guidance to healthcare professionals for its consultation and use. Blood derived products, as chronic medication and susceptible of transmitting diseases, are very important in the pharmaceutical industry, they have a large social and mediatic impact and their manufacturing is based on the use of human plasma as raw material. The discussion on donating plasma altruistically or in remunerated manner and its effect on self-sufficiency for the availability of blood products is also addressed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso Verduras, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frutos Cabanillas, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Collazo López, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se hace una revisión integral de la regulación aplicable a los medicamentos hemoderivados, incluyendo la normativa europea así como su transposición a la normativa nacional. Esta regulación compleja y extensa se actualiza y comenta de forma que facilite a los profesionales sanitarios su consulta y aplicación. Los hemoderivados, medicamentos de administración crónica y susceptibles de transmitir enfermedades, tienen gran impacto social y mediático, y su elaboración, de suma importancia en la industria farmacéutica, se basa en la utilización de plasma humano. Se aborda también el debate de la donación de plasma de forma altruista o remunerada y sus consecuencias en la autosuficiencia de un país para la disponibilidad de hemoderivados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Real Acad Farm;81(2): 103-115, 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143989</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Marco regulatorio de los medicamentos hemoderivados de uso humano</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4398^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51443</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4398^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4398^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10792^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10792^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10792^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
