<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83893</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Trends in leisure time and occupational physical activity in the Madrid region, 1995-2008</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: Information on trends in physical activity is very scarce in Mediterranean countries, which have the highest sedentariness in Europe. This study describes recent trends in leisure time physical activity (LTPA) and at work in the Madrid region. Methods: The data were taken from representative annual surveys of population aged 18-64 years, between 1995-2008, 28,084 people participated. We calculated total energy, quantified in metabolic equivalent (MET-1 h per week), spent on LTPA and on light LTPA (&lt;3 MET), moderate LTPA (3-6 MET) and vigorous LTPA (&gt;6 MET). The annual change in LTPA was estimated by linear regression, and occupational activity by logistic regression, adjusting for age, gender and educational level. Results: The total amount of LTPA in MET-1 h per week declined by 19.8% (P &lt; .001) between 1995-2008; for both genders, all age groups and educational levels, except for those with the lowest level of education. The adjusted annual change in MET-1 h per week was: &#150;0.21 (P &lt; .001) for total LTPA; &#150;0.1 (P &lt; .001) for light; &#150;0.08 (P &lt; .001) for moderate; and &#150;0.03 (P = .192) for vigorous. This decline is reflected by a shift to the left of the LTPA distribution in the population. Occupational physical inactivity has increased in the general population (odds ratio for annual change = 1.01; 95% confidence interval, 1-1.02); specially in women, young and middle aged, and intermediate educational level. Conclusions: There has been a decline in LTPA, mainly in light and moderate activities, accompanied by greater occupational physical inactivity. This could have contributed to the increase in obesity in the Community of Madrid between 1995-2008 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Meseguer, Carmen M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galán, Iñaki</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herruzo, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Artalejo, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. La información sobre tendencias en actividad física es muy escasa en países mediterráneos, los de mayor sedentarismo en Europa. Se presentan tendencias recientes en actividad física en tiempo libre (AFTL) y laboral en la región de Madrid. Métodos. Datos procedentes de encuestas anuales representativas de población de 18-64 años entre 1995 y 2008, con la participación de 28.084 personas. Se calculó el consumo de energía en equivalentes metabólicos (MET-1 h/semana) en AFTL total y en ligeras (&lt; 3 MET), moderadas (3-6 MET) y vigorosas (&gt; 6 MET). El cambio anual en AFTL se estimó mediante regresión lineal y en la actividad laboral, mediante regresión logística, ajustando por edad, sexo y nivel de estudios. Resultados. El consumo de MET-1 h/semana en AFTL descendió un 19,8% (p&lt;0,001) entre 1995 y 2008 en ambos sexos, todas las edades y niveles educativos, excepto en personas con estudios más bajos. El cambio anual ajustado en MET-1 h/semana fue &#150;0,21 (p&lt;0,001) para AFTL total, &#150;0,1 (p&lt;0,001) para ligeras, &#150;0,08 (p&lt;0,001) para moderadas y &#150;0,03 (p=0,192) para vigorosas. Este descenso se manifiesta en un desplazamiento a la izquierda de la distribución de AFTL en la población. La inactividad física laboral aumentó en población general (odds ratio de cambio anual=1,01; intervalo de confianza del 95%, 1-1,02), especialmente en mujeres, edades jóvenes e intermedias y con nivel medio de estudios. Conclusiones. Se ha producido un descenso en AFTL, principalmente en actividades ligeras y moderadas, acompañado de una mayor inactividad laboral. Ello puede haber contribuido al aumento de obesidad en la Comunidad de Madrid de 1995 a 2008 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;64(1): 21-27, ene. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83893</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tendencias de actividad física en tiempo libre y en el trabajo en la Comunidad de Madrid, 1995-2008</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3186^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3184^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24419</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4813^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24811</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201101</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
