<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053858</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-1813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The new technologies and the distance continuing medical education</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The advantages and disadvantages of the distance CME are considered, analyzing the three fundamental typologies: contents' offer (traditional approach,),contents' management (traditional approach plus new technologies) and &#147;on-line&#148; offer (learning processes and communication).Among the elements related to the quality of the distance CME programmers one can identify the following three essentials: technology, methodology and evaluation. Technology&#146;s elements include the platforms, standards and programmer&#146;s structure. The tutors, contents' design, communication systems and tools to generate activities are the fundamental elements of the methodologies. Finally, among the evaluation one can identify the different procedures aimed to assess the contents, the learning and the practice (performance) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Segura Badia, Helena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Tras analizar las ventajas e inconvenientes de las FMC a distancia, se contemplan las tres tipologías básicas: provisión de contenidos (enfoque tradicional), gestión de contenidos (enfoque tradicional con las nuevas tecnologías) y &#147;on-line&#148; (procesos de aprendizaje y comunicación).Entre los elementos que definen la calidad de los programas formativos a distancia se destacan los tecnológicos, metodológicos y evaluativos. Éntrelos primeros se incluyen las plataformas, los estándares la estructura del programa; entre los segundos, los tutores, el diseño de los contenidos , los sistemas de comunicación y las herramientas para crear actividades; y, finalmente, entre los evaluativos, destacan las tipologías destinadas a la evaluación de contenidos, de aprendizaje y de práctica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Educ. med. (Ed. impr.);9(3): 118-126, sept. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053858</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las nuevas tecnologías y la formación médica continuada a distancia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33919^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24459^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32764^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
