<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111527</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical significance of congestive heart failure in prosthetic valve endocarditis. A multicenter study with 257 patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. There have been no studies conducted in the past that focus on the significance of congestive heart failure in patients with prosthetic valve endocarditis. We studied the incidence of congestive heart failure in patients with prosthetic valve endocarditis and analyzed its profile. In this study, we addressed the prognostic significance of heart failure in patients with prosthetic valve endocarditis and analyzed its outcome based on chosen therapeutic strategies. Methods. A total of 639 episodes of definite left-sided endocarditis were prospectively enrolled. Of them, 257 were prosthetic. Of the 257 episodes, 145 (56%) were diagnosed with heart failure. We compared the profiles of patients with prosthetic valve endocarditis based on the presence of heart failure, and performed a multivariate logistic regression model to establish the prognostic significance of heart failure in patients with prosthetic valve endocarditis and identified the prognostic factors of in-hospital mortality in these patients. Results. Persistent infection (odds ratio=3.6; 95% confidence interval, 1.9-6.9) and heart failure (odds ratio=3; 95% confidence interval, 1.5-5.8) are the strongest predictive factors of in-hospital mortality in patients with prosthetic valve endocarditis. The short-term determinants of prognosis in patients with prosthetic valve endocarditis and heart failure are persistent infection (odds ratio=2.8; 95% confidence interval, 1.2-6.5), aortic involvement (odds ratio=2.5; 95% confidence interval, 1.1-5.8), abscess (odds ratio=3.6; 95% confidence interval, 1.4-9.5), diabetes mellitus (odds ratio=2.9; 95% confidence interval, 1.1-7.7), and cardiac surgery (odds ratio=0.2; 95% confidence interval, 0.1-0.5). Conclusions. The incidence of heart failure in patients with prosthetic valve endocarditis is very high. Heart failure increases the risk of in-hospital mortality by threefold in patients with prosthetic valve endocarditis. Persistent infection, aortic involvement, abscess, and diabetes mellitus are the independent risk factors associated with mortality in patients with prosthetic valve endocarditis and heart failure; however, cardiac surgery is shown to decrease mortality in these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sevilla, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Héctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, Itziar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva, Jacobo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varvaro, Grétel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Román, José Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarriá, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Revilla, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilacosta, Isidre</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pozo, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palacio, María del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Hasta el momento no se han realizado estudios centrados en determinar la importancia de la insuficiencia cardiaca congestiva en los pacientes con endocarditis protésica. En este trabajo se ha estudiado la incidencia de la insuficiencia cardiaca congestiva en pacientes con endocarditis protésica y se ha analizado su perfil. Se aborda la importancia pronóstica de la insuficiencia cardiaca en los pacientes con endocarditis protésica y se analiza su evolución en función de las estrategias terapéuticas elegidas. Métodos. Se incluyeron prospectivamente en el estudio 639 episodios de endocarditis izquierda con diagnóstico definitivo. De ellos, 257 eran casos de endocarditis protésica. De los 257 episodios, en 145 (56%) se estableció diagnóstico de insuficiencia cardiaca. Se compararon los perfiles de los pacientes con endocarditis protésica según tuvieran o no insuficiencia cardiaca, se desarrolló un modelo de regresión logística multivariable para establecer la importancia pronóstica de la insuficiencia cardiaca en pacientes con endocarditis protésica y se identificaron los factores pronósticos de la mortalidad hospitalaria de esos pacientes. Resultados. La infección persistente (odds ratio=3,6; intervalo de confianza del 95%, 1,9-6,9) y la insuficiencia cardiaca (odds ratio=3; intervalo de confianza del 95%, 1,5-5,8) son los más potentes factores predictivos de la mortalidad hospitalaria de los pacientes con endocarditis protésica. Los factores determinantes del pronóstico a corto plazo en los pacientes con endocarditis protésica e insuficiencia cardiaca son la infección persistente (odds ratio=2,8; intervalo de confianza del 95%, 1,2-6,5), la afección aórtica (odds ratio=2,5; intervalo de confianza del 95%, 1,1-5,8), los abscesos (odds ratio=3,6; intervalo de confianza del 95%, 1,4-9,5), la diabetes mellitus (odds ratio=2,9; intervalo de confianza del 95%, 1,1-7,7) y la cirugía cardiaca (odds ratio=0,2; intervalo de confianza del 95%, 0,1-0,5). Conclusiones. La incidencia de insuficiencia cardiaca entre los pacientes con endocarditis protésica es muy alta. La insuficiencia cardiaca aumenta al triple el riesgo de mortalidad intrahospitalaria de los pacientes con endocarditis protésica. La infección persistente, la afección aórtica, el absceso y la diabetes mellitus son los factores de riesgo independientes asociados a la mortalidad de los pacientes con endocarditis protésica e insuficiencia cardiaca. Sin embargo, se demuestra que la cirugía cardiaca reduce la mortalidad de esos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;66(5): 384-390, mayo 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111527</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Importancia clínica de la insuficiencia cardiaca congestiva en la endocarditis protésica. Estudio multicéntrico de 257 pacientes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4778^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30047^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24811</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201305</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
