<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114504</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-7347</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of comorbidity in patients with COPD</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To Study the prevalence of comorbidity in patients with stable COPD, in Andalusia and Extremadura and to analyze its relationship with the consumption of healthcare resources, degree of airway obstruction and quality of life. Material and methods: Two phase study: the first was a transversal, multi-center, prospective study, concurrent with stable COPD patients, recruited from six hospitals in the regions of Andalusia and Extremadura (Spain). Demographic data was collected, as well as respiratory function, Charlson comorbidity index, BODE index, hospital scale for anxiety and depression and specific quality of life questionnaire). The existence of comorbidity was assessed through patient clinical history and detailed interview. The second phase was a longitudinal, one year prospective study to review the use of healthcare resources. Results: 164 patients were included, of which 83.5% were males with an average age of 65.7 years, and an average FEV1 of 48.1%. The most frequent prevalence of comorbidity in our patients was ischemic heart disease 9.8%, cardiac insufficiency 6.1%, peripheral vascular disease 6.1%, cerebrovascular disease 4.9%, diabetes mellitus 12.8%, neoplasm 10.9%, hepatopathy 10.4%, anxiety 15.2% and depression 14%. No significant association was observed between the prevalence of comorbidities or Charlson comorbidity Index and the need for healthcare, the quality of living or pulmonary function. Conclusions: the prevalence of comorbidities in patients with stable COPD in the regions of Andalusia and Extremadura is high. The existence of comorbidity was independent on the deterioration of pulmonary function, the need for emergency healthcare or admittance to hospital and deterioration of living quality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alfageme Michavilla, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas Maldonado, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcazar Navarrete, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cordero Montero, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arnedillo Muñoz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lopez-Campos, J. L.</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudiar la prevalencia de comorbilidades en pacientes con EPOC estables, en Andalucía y Extremadura, y analizar su relación con el consumo de recursos sanitarios, grado de obstrucción al flujo aéreo y calidad de vida. Material y métodos: Estudio con dos fases, una primera prospectiva transversal multicéntrica concurrente de pacientes con EPOC estables, reclutados en seis hospitales de Andalucía y Extremadura. Se recogieron datos demográficos, funcionales respiratorios, índice de comorbilidad de Charlson, índice BODE, escala hospitalaria de ansiedad y depresión y cuestionario específico de calidad de vida (SGRQ). Se recogió la existencia de comorbilidad a través de la historia clínica del paciente y entrevista detallada. Una segunda fase prospectiva longitudinal de un año para estudiar el consumo de recursos sanitarios. Resultados: Se incluyeron 164 pacientes, el 83,5% varones, con edad media de 65,7 años, y FEV1 medio de 48,1%. Las prevalencias de comorbilidades mas frecuentes en nuestros pacientes fueron de cardiopatía isquémica 9,8%, insuficiencia cardiaca 6,1%, enfermedad vascular periférica 6,1%, enfermedad cerebrovascular 4,9%, diabetes mellitus 12,8%, neoplasias 10,9%, hepatopatía 10,4%, ansiedad 15,2% y depresión 14%. No se observó asociación significativa entre la prevalencia de comorbilidades o el índice de comorbilidad de Charlson y la necesidad de asistencia sanitaria, calidad de vida o función pulmonar. Conclusiones: la prevalencia de comorbilidades en pacientes con EPOC estable en Andalucía y Extremadura es elevada. La existencia de comorbilidad fue independiente del deterioro de la función pulmonar, de la necesidad de asistencia a urgencias o ingresos hospitalarios y del deterioro de la calidad de vida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol. torac;25(2): 117-124, abr.-jun. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114504</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de comorbilidades en pacientes con EPOC</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
