<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123925</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: Morbimortality and healthcare burden</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) is an enormous public health problem and of growing importance due to its high prevalence, elevated morbimortality, and socioeconomic costs. Many Spanish epidemiological studies report a prevalence of 10% of the adult population, with its growth appearing to have stabilised. Nevertheless, over 75% of cases are still underdiagnosed.  The diagnosis of mild and moderate obstruction is associated with a higher survival and lower costs (14 years and D 9,730) compared to 10 years survival and D 43,785 of patients diagnosed in the severe obstruction phase. COPD was the fourth cause of death in Spain in 2011, although the adjusted mortality rates have decreased more than 20% in the last decade, particularly in males. Patients with advanced  COPD die from it, but patients with mild or moderate COPD die due to cardiovascular diseases or cancer (mainly of the lung). It is estimated that the annual cost of the disease is around 3,000 million Euros. These increase with the spirometric severity, and is mainly associated with exacerbations (almost 60% of the  direct costs). Comorbidity, that is the presence of diseases that coexist with the studied disease, is higher in patients with COPD than in the general population and affects health results. © 2013 Sociedad Española de Médicos de Atención Primaria (SEMERGEN). Published by Elsevier España, S.L. All rights reserved (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno Vilaseca, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gérez Callejas, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zangróniz Uruñuela, M. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hidalgo Requena, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintano Jiménez, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández García, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Sáenz, J. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Béjar, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica (EPOC) constituye un problema de salud pública de enorme y creciente importancia por su alta prevalencia, elevada morbimortalidad y costes socioeconómicos. Diversos estudios epidemiológicos españoles cifran la prevalencia en un 10% de la población adulta, pareciendo haberse estabilizado su crecimiento. Con todo, el infradiagnóstico sigue superando el 75%. El diagnóstico en fases de obstrucción leve y moderada se asocia a mayor supervivencia y menores costes (14 años y 9.730 D ), frente a los 10 años de supervivencia y 43.785 D  de los pacientes diagnosticados en fases de obstrucción grave. La EPOC constituyó la cuarta causa de mortalidad en España en 2011, si bien las tasas de mortalidad ajustadas han disminuido en la última década más de un 20%, sobre todo en varones. Los pacientes con EPOC avanzada fallecen de la misma, pero los pacientes con EPOC leve o moderada lo hacen por enfermedades cardiovasculares o cáncer (sobre todo de pulmón). Se estima que el coste anual de la enfermedad alcanza los 3.000 millones de euros al año. Estos aumentan con la gravedad espirométrica y se asocian fundamentalmente con las agudizaciones (casi un 60% de los costes directos). La comorbilidad, entendida como la presencia de dolencias que coexisten con la enfermedad de estudio, es mayor en los pacientes con EPOC que en la población general, y condiciona resultados en salud (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);40(4): 198-204, mayo-jun. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123925</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica: morbimortalidad e impacto sanitario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
