<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112363</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The routine use of the Pneumonia Severity Index in the emergency department: Effect on process-of-care indicators and results in community acquired pneumonia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To evaluate process-of-care indicators (inappropriate hospitalisation, suitability and early antibiotic treatment) and outcome indicators (length of hospital stay, hospital readmission, ICU admission, and mortality) in the management of community-acquired pneumonia (CAP) when the SEPAR/IDSA guidelines were applied. Patients and methods An observational retrospective study conducted on patients diagnosed with CAP during the first semester of 2007 and 2008 (186 and 161 patients, respectively) in the emergency unit of a general hospital. Differences in the process-of-care and outcome indicators between 2007 and 2008 (with and without the Pneumonia Severity Index [PSI]) were evaluated. Moreover, the indicators were compared with those obtained in 2006 (110 patients), when the current guidelines were those of SEQ/ATS. Results The SEPAR/IDSA guidelines improved the following process-of-care indicators: appropriateness of treatment, unjustified hospital readmission (39.4% in 2006 vs. 8.5% in 2007 [P&lt;.001], and 17,2% in 2008 [P=.005]), and early treatment. However, outcome indicators did not change. In 2008, a decrease in the mortality of the patients of risk classes IV-V in which the PSI had been estimated was observed in comparison with the patients in which the PSI was not estimated (2.3% vs. 28.3%; P&lt;.001). Moreover, the mortality rate of the patients of risk classes IV-V in which the PSI had been estimated was lower than those measured using the SEQ/ATS guidelines (22.7%; P=.003).Conclusion SEPAR/IDSA guidelines decreased the unjustified hospital readmission. In the second year of its application an increase in the number of patients who received early treatment, and a decrease of the mortality rate of the patients of risk classes IV-V in which the PSI had been estimated, were also observed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, M. Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Velasco, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrascosa, Inés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado, Miriam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrios, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canut, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos Evaluación de indicadores de proceso (hospitalización inadecuada, adecuación y precocidad de antibioterapia) y resultado (estancia hospitalaria, reingresos, ingresos UCI y mortalidad) de neumonía adquirida en la comunidad (NAC) al aplicar la guía SEPAR/IDSA. Pacientes y métodos Estudio observacional retrospectivo de pacientes consecutivos con diagnóstico al alta de NAC en los primeros semestres de 2007 y 2008 (186 y 161 pacientes, respectivamente) atendidos en urgencias de hospital general. Se han analizado las diferencias en los indicadores entre los grupos de pacientes con/sin Pneumonia Severity Index (PSI) calculado, según el año de implantación de la guía, y se compararon con los de 110 pacientes de 2006 según la guía SEQ/ATS. Resultados La guía SEPAR/IDSA ha mejorado los indicadores de proceso: mayor adecuación del ámbito de tratamiento, disminución de ingresos injustificados (del 39,4% en 2006 al 8,5% en 2007 [p&lt;0,001] y al 17,2% en 2008 [p=0,005]) y mayor precocidad de antibioterapia. No se han modificado los indicadores de resultado. En 2008 se observó una reducción de la mortalidad en el subgrupo de pacientes con PSI IV-V en los que se calculó el PSI (2,3%), respecto a los que no se calculó (28,3%; p&lt;0,001), y esta tasa fue inferior a la de los pacientes con criterios de hospitalización según la guía SEQ/ATS (22,7%; p=0,003).Conclusión La guía SEPAR/IDSA ha reducido los ingresos injustificados y en el segundo año de aplicación se ha observado mayor precocidad de la antibioterapia junto a una reducción de la mortalidad en los pacientes con riesgo moderado-alto en los que se calculó el PSI (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;31(5): 289-297, mayo 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112363</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso rutinario del Pneumonia Severity Index en el servicio de urgencias: efecto sobre los indicadores de proceso y resultado en neumonía adquirida en la comunidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31549^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3981^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201305</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
