<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118847</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8799</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acuracy of different equation to predict maximal heart rate in cycle ergometer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: Comparing equations to predict the maximum heart rate (MHR) in cycle ergometer in young people. Material and Methods: The sample was composed by 51 male (22.2 ± 2.7 years) and 17 female (21.9 ± 1.9 years). After a10 min warm&#150;up period, the subjects performed a maximum speed test during 1 minute, applying as resistance a load of 3watts per Kg body weight. A total of 53 equations were considered to contrast their results with the MHR obtained during the maximum test at cycle ergometer. Paired Student&#146;s t-test was used to compare the mean values between the groups (MHR prev and MHR obt) in order to determinate the similarity between the data. Results: The MHR mean values were 183.5 ± 8.1 bpm (male) and 175.6 ± 8.5 bpm (female). Among the MHR prediction equations for cycle exercise, only six of them showed a p &gt; 0.05 for men, meanwhile only two equations were accepted for women. The equation (MHR = 220 &#150; age) systematically overestimated the predicted MHR both in men and women. Conclusions: The most suitable equation to predict MHR in cycle ergometer exercise for men was (MHR = 202 - 0,72 * age),while for women (MHR = 189 &#150; 0.56 * age) or (MHR = 196 &#150; 0.9 * age) were the most adequate. We suggest no to use the equation (MHR = 220 &#150; age) to predict MHR in young people (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bouzas Marins, João Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Fernández, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benito Peinado, Pedro J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Comparar la precisión de ecuaciones para estimar la frecuencia cardiaca máxima (FCM) en cicloergómetro para jóvenes. Material y Métodos: La muestra estuvo compuesta por 51 hombres (22,2 ± 2,7 años) y 17 mujeres (21,9 ± 1,9 años). La prueba consistió en realizar, tras un período de calentamiento de 10 minutos, una fase de ejercicio a la máxima velocidad durante un minuto en cicloergómetro, aplicándole al evaluado como resistencia una carga de 3 vatios por cada Kg de peso corporal. Fueron consideradas un total de 53 ecuaciones para contrastar la FCM obtenida durante la prueba máxima en cicloergómetro. Se empleó la t de Student para muestras relacionadas, para comparar los valores medios entre los dos grupos(FCM predicha vs FCM obtenida) con el fi n de determinar la similitud entre los datos. Resultados: Se obtuvo una FCM durante la prueba en ciclo de 183,5 ± 8,1 lpm (hombres) y 175,6 ± 8,5 lpm (mujeres). Entre las 53 fórmulas de predicción de FCM evaluadas para el ejercicio en cicloergómetro, entre los hombres solamente seis fórmulas presentaron un P &gt; 0.05, sin embargo entre las mujeres fueron aceptadas solamente dos ecuaciones. La ecuación (FCM =220 - edad) ha sobrevalorado sistemáticamente la FCM predicha tanto en hombres como en mujeres. Conclusiones: La mayor parte de las ecuaciones evaluadas no son precisas para estimar la FCM en cicloergómetro. Para predecir la FCM en ejercicio de cicloergometría en hombres se recomienda la ecuación (FCM = 202 &#150; 0,72 * edad) y para mujeres (CM = 189 - 0,56 * edad) o (FCM = 196 &#150; 0,9 * edad). No se sugiere emplear la ecuación (FCM = 220 &#150; edad) para predecir la FCM para una población de jóvenes adultos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. med. deporte;30(153): 14-20, ene.-feb. 2013. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118847</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Precisión de las ecuaciones para estimar la frecuencia cardiaca máxima en cicloergómetro</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5178^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30118^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6493</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
