<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115183</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9572</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Chronic insomnia is a highly prevalent disorder. Its pathophysiology shows multiple factors: both homeostatic and circadian control factors, together with cognitive-behavioural factors, intervene. Pharmacological treatment has drawbacks due to undesirable effects of prescribed drugs (benzodiazepines, sedative antidepressants, atypical neuroleptics). Melatonin is an alternative, but its efficacy is controversial. One of main melatonin handicaps is its short average life. To solve this, use of prolonged release drugs and melatonin agonists (Ramelteon, Agomelatine) has been proposed. USA&#146;s FDA has approved Ramelteon to treat primary insomnia, and CircadinR is the only melatonin that has been approved for clinical use in the EU as monotherapy short-term treatment of primary insomnia in patients over 55 years old. Agomelatine is also authorized and sold as an antidepressant. Studies up to date prove these drugs&#146; efficacy to reduce sleep onset latency (in lower parameters than hypnosedatives) and to improve daytime alertness. No rebound or withdrawal symptoms were observed after discontinuing the treatment. Moreover, they seem to be safe drugs that show no significant adverse events. Recent data on melatonin&#146;s hypotensor and modulator effect on glucose metabolism open a new research field for the potential clinical use or melatonin and its agonists in insomnia linked with CV risk diseases(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Benetó, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soler Algarra, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El insomnio crónico es un trastorno muy prevalente y su fisiopatología es multifactorial, interviniendo factores homeostáticos y de control circadiano, además de cognitivo-conductuales. Su tratamiento farmacológico tiene inconvenientes por los efectos indeseables de los fármacos utilizados (Benzodiacepinas, antidepresivos sedantes, neurolépticos atípicos). La melatonina es una alternativa, pero su eficacia es controvertida. Un handicap importante es su corta vida media, por lo que se ha propuesto el uso de compuestos de liberación prolongada (CircadinR) y agonistas melatoninérgicos (Ramelteon, Agomelatina). Ramelteon está aprobado por la FDA en USA para el tratamiento del insomnio primario y CircadinR es la única melatonina aprobada para su uso clínico en la Unión Europea como monoterapia para el tratamiento a corto plazo del insomnio primario en sujetos de 55 años o más de edad; Agomelatina está también autorizada y se comercializa como antidepresivo. Los estudios realizados hasta la fecha avalan la eficacia para reducir la latencia de inicio al sueño (en parámetros menores que los hipnosedantes) y para mejorar la alerta diurna, sin observarse síntomas de rebote o de retirada con la interrupción del tratamiento. Parecen además fármacos seguros y sin efectos adversos relevantes. Los recientes datos sobre el efecto hipotensor y modulador del metabolismo de la glucosa por parte de la melatonina abren un campo a la investigación de la posible utilidad clínica de la melatonina y sus agonistas en el insomnio asociado a enfermedades con riesgo cardiovascular(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Vigilia sueño;25(2): 24-37, jun. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115183</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Insomnio. Posibilidades terapéuticas de la melatonina y sus agonistas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8718^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8718^s32387</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
