<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052342</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">IGF-I, VEGF and b-FGF as predictive factors for the onset of retinopathy of prematurity (ROP)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine if IGF-I, VEGF and    bFGF, present in the serum of premature infants, are    independent risk factors of the development of    ROP. It was also our objective to design a multivariate    model that included these three cytokines as    indicator parameters in the ROP screening, in addition    to the other parameters already in existence.    Methods: 74 patients were recruited with a birth    weight below 1500g or gestational age below 32    weeks. These were classified into those who developed    ROP (N = 37) and those without ROP (N =    37). We obtained serum from each infant at the time    of the first examination at 4-6 postnatal weeks. These    samples were frozen until the time of analysis.    The roles of gestational age and birth weight were    also evaluated.    Results: There were significant differences in the    amount of the cytokines IGF-I and VEGF between    the groups with or without ROP, but there were no    significant differences for bFGF. The differences    enabled us to establish a multivariate model including IGF-I and VEGF for the prediction of risk of    ROP.    Conclusions: Cytokine serum levels in premature    infants can be useful as an indicator in ROP screening,    as well as being used to predict the probability    of suffering the illness</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-Fernández, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perula-Torres, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallardo-Galera, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villegas-Becerril, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Identificar en suero de prematuros a IGF,    VEGF y bFGF, como factores de riesgo independientes    en el desarrollo de la ROP. Es también nuestro    objetivo el diseño de un modelo multivariante    que englobe a las tres citokinas y que este pueda ser    usado como parámetro indicador del examen de la    ROP, además de los ya existentes.    Métodos: 74 pacientes prematuros fueron reclutados    con un peso al nacer menor de 1500 grs o edad    gestacional menor de 32 semanas, y fueron divididos    en pacientes enfermos de ROP (N=37) y    pacientes no enfermos de ROP (N=37). Se tomaron    muestras de sangre de cada paciente, coincidiendo    con el primer examen, entre la 4 a 6 primeras semanas    de vida y estas fueron congeladas en espera de    su determinación. La edad gestacional y el peso al    nacer fueron evaluados.    Resultados: Encontramos diferencias significativas    entre grupos en función de los valores de IGF-I y    VEGF, pero no encontramos diferencias en función    de la bFGF. Establecimos un modelo multivariante incluyendo a la IGF-I y VEGF, para la predicción    del riesgo de padecer ROP en función de estas dos    citokinas.    Conclusiones: Los niveles en sangre de prematuros    de estas citokinas pueden ser usados como factores    indicadores del examen de la ROP, así como para    predecir la probabilidad de sufrir la enfermedad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;81(11): 641-646, nov. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052342</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">IGF-I, VEGF y b-FGF, como factores pronósticos de la aparición de la retinopatía de la prematuridad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38244^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32715^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19399^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28903^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28936^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
