<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112015</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hysteroscopic approach to residual endometrial tissue in the cervical stump</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The main difference between subtotal and total hysterectomy lies in the persistence of the cervical stump and the possible associated problems. One of these problems is cyclical bleeding after a subtotal hysterectomy, which, depending on the series, occurs in 0% to 25% of cases. We describe resolution of cyclical bleeding after a subtotal hysterectomy by means of hysteroscopic treatment. To our knowledge, this is the first published case in which ablation of the remnant tissue was performed with a monopolar loop in order to treat cyclical bleeding. We believe this surgical treatment could be a valid alternative to resolve cyclical bleeding associated with persistence of endometrial tissue in the cervical stump(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gonzalez de Gor Crooke, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larracoechea Barrionuevo, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodrigo Olmedo, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Pacheco, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La principal diferencia entre la histerectomía total y la subtotal reside en la persistencia del muñón cervical y en los posibles problemas asociados a este. Uno de estos problemas es la existencia de un cuadro de sangrado cíclico persistente tras la cirugía; esta posibilidad acontece entre un 0 y 25% de los casos según las distintas series. Presentamos en este trabajo la resolución por vía histeroscópica de un cuadro de sangrado cíclico posquirúrgico en una paciente sometida a histerectomý´a subtotal por cuadro de metrorragia. Hasta donde sabemos, es el primer caso publicado con realizacio´n de una ablación del tejido endometrial restante con asa monopolar, para corregir el cuadro de sangrado. Pensamos que puede tratarse de una alternativa válida a la traquelectomía en estos casos de sangrado asociado a la persistencia de endometrio residual en el muñón cervical(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);56(5): 274-277, mayo 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112015</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abordaje histeroscópico del endometrio residual en muñón cervical</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24738^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8986^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d571^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4636^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7225^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4636^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4636^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d571^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24738^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7225^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8986^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8986^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7225^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4636^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201305</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
