<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139832</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To study the relationship between cost-effectiveness and budgetary impact the application of a neoadjuvant chemo-hyperthermia treatment on 15 patients with NMI multi-recurrent bladder cancer and/or whose risk of recurrence and progression is medium-high, compared with the standard neoadjuvant BCG treatment, has had on the Hospital Comarcal de Monforte de Lemos (Lugo). Methods: A model was designed from an SNS perspective with a temporary horizon of three years to compare the costs of applying neoadjuvant chemohyperthermia on the patients of the clinical test (8 instillations weekly of 80 mg Mitomycin C recirculating at 43° C for an hour prior to carrying out a transurethral resection of the bladder tumor) with the costs of treating 15 patients with the same risk profile with the standard adjuvant treatment of BCG (control group). The effective available costs corresponding to drugs, disposables and those relative to TURBT, cold biopsy and tumor relapse were included. The costs of diagnostic tests and followup were discarded from the model because they did not vary between groups. Results: The model built with effective and published cost data establishes a favourable difference in favour of the neoadjuvant treatment with chemo hyperthermia in terms of 3 year costs with a minimum global savings of 10,300&#128; and 687&#128; per patient, together with an improvement in the effectiveness of the treatment. These values could reach a minimum savings of 25,960&#128; and 1,731&#128; per patient, if a change in protocol is made after the neoadjuvant treatment, which uses the cold biopsy to check the results. Of the 15 patients pre-treated with chemo-hyperthermia, 11 high-risk and 4 medium-risk, 9 have responded completely (absence of residual tumor) and 6 partially (shrinking of the tumor). The number of expected relapses has been reduced from 8 to 2 and progression from 3 to 0. Conclusions: The neoadjuvant treatment with chemo hyperthermia constitutes a cost-effective therapeutic strategy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aparici, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monserrat, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Uribarri, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Neira, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piñeiro, Idelfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sousa, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudiar la relación de coste-efectividad e impacto presupuestario de una pauta de quimiohipertermia (QHT) neoadyuvante en pacientes con cáncer vesical no musculo invasivo (NMI) comparándolo con un tratamiento estándar de BCG y aplicando valores de recidiva y progresión basadas en tablas de riesgo internacionalmente aceptadas. Métodos: Para ello, se diseñó un modelo desde la perspectiva de un sistema público de salud tras un seguimiento de 3 años para comparar los costes de aplicar quimiohipertermia neoadyuvante a los pacientes del ensayo clínico (8 instilaciones semanales de 80 mg Mitomicina C recirculando a 43 ºC durante 1 hora previas a la realización de una resección transuretral del tumor vesical) con los costes de tratar a 15 pacientes con el mismo perfil de riesgo con el tratamiento estándar adyuvante de BCG (grupo control). Se incluyeron los costes reales disponibles correspondientes a fármacos y desechables y los publicados relativos a la resección transuretral (RTU) de vejiga, biopsia fría y riesgo de recidiva tumoral. Se descartaron del modelo los costes de pruebas diagnósticas y de seguimiento por no variar entre ambos grupos. Resultados: El modelo construido con datos de costes reales y publicados establece una diferencia favorable para el tratamiento neoadyuvante con quimiohipertermia en términos de coste a 3 años con un ahorro mínimo global de 10.300&#128; y de 687&#128; por paciente, todo ello con una mejora de la efectividad del tratamiento. Estos valores pueden pasar a 25.960&#128; de ahorro mínimo y 1.731&#128; de ahorro por paciente, si se asume un cambio de protocolo después de la neoadyuvancia que utilice la biopsia fría para comprobar el resultado. De los 15 pacientes pretratados con quimiohipertermia, 11 de riesgo alto y 4 de riesgo medio, 9 han respondido de forma completa (ausencia de tumor residual) y 6 de forma parcial (reducción del tumor). El número de recurrencias esperadas se ha reducido de 8 a 2 y de progresiones de 3 a 0. Conclusiones: El tratamiento neoadyuvante con quimiohipertermia constituye una estrategia terapéutica coste-efectiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;68(5): 482-492, jun. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139832</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis del Impacto Presupuestario del tratamiento mediante quimiohipertermia neoadyuvante en el cáncer vesical no músculo invasivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31403^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31403^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
