<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92872</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Poverty, nutritional status and child enteropasitoses: a cross-sectional</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The study of the growth and nutritionalstatus of the individuals is considered an importantsign of the population health, as well as the action ofsocio-economic and environmental factors. Objectives: To analyze the relationship among thenutritional status, enteroparasitoses and socio-environmentalconditions in children from Aristóbulo del Valle,Misiones.Methods: A cross-sectional anthropometrical andparasitological study was made in children from bothsexes between 6 to 11 years old of public school fromMunicipality of Aristóbulo del Valle. NCHS was emplo -yed as reference in the analysis of undernutrition, andIOTF for the excess of weight. The parasitologicalanalysis was realized by faecal samples and anal brushes.Socio-environmental conditions were evaluatedthrough structured interviews (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oyhenart Evelia, Edith</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garraza, Mariela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zonta María, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navone Graciela, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El estado nutricional de los individuos es considerado un valioso indicador del estado desalud de la población, así como también del accionarde factores socio-económicos y ambientales.Objetivos: Analizar la relación entre el estado nutricional,las enteroparasitosis y las condiciones socioambientalesen niños de Aristóbulo del Valle, Misiones.Métodos. Estudio antropométrico transversal y parasitológicoen niños de ambos sexos y entre 6 a 11 añosde escuelas públicas del Municipio de Aristóbulo delValle. Para el análisis de desnutrición se utilizó comoreferencia CDC/NCHS y para exceso de peso IOTF. Elanálisis parasitológico se realizó mediante la toma demuestras seriadas de materia fecal y escobillado anal.El relevamiento de las condiciones socio-ambientalesse realizó mediante encuestas estructuradas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;31(2): 48-57, mayo-ago. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92872</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pobreza, estado nutricional y enteropasitosis infantil: un estudio transversal en Aristóbulo del Valle, Misiones,Argentina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24471</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23583^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7574^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13306</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10459^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
