<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94478</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Definition and sequencing of learning outcomes of the Nursing Practicum</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: to describe the process by means of which learning out comes have been defined by nursing practicum years and present these outcomes. Material and method: the sample consists of 50 people including: nurses , instructors, 3rd year students and teaching-tutor staff. There have been two group discussion working sessions. Results: Practicum learning outcomes have been defined by year, andorganized in four competence fields: relationship with users, family membersand groups; team work; application of the Nursing process; and professional development.Conclusions: collaborative work between the teaching, health care delivery and management areas is essential in order for the desired integration of theory and practice to become a reality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lasa Labaca, Garbiñe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina, Pilar Gil</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Uranga Iturrioz, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: describir el proceso mediante el cual se han definido los resultados de aprendizaje por cursos del Practicum de Enfermería y presentar dichos resultados.Material y método: la muestra está compuesta por 50 personas entre las que se encuentran: enfermeras asistenciales, instructoras, alumnado de 3º y profesorado-tutor. Se ha trabajado durante dos sesiones en grupos de discusión.Resultados: se han definido por cursos los resultados de aprendizaje del Practicum, ordenándose en cuatro ámbitos competenciales: relación con usuarios, familiares y grupos, trabajo en equipo, aplicación del proceso de Enfermería y desarrollo profesional.Conclusiones: el trabajo colaborativo de los ámbitos docente, asistencial y de gestión es esencial para que la deseada integración de la teoría y la práctica sea una realidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;14(1): 51-57, feb. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94478</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Definición y secuenciación de los resultados de aprendizaje del Practicum de Enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32065^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4577^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17571^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
