<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132600</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of physical stability of all in one parenteral admixtures for pediatric home care with high electrolytes concentrations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The aim of the study was to evaluate stability of 48 total parenteral admixtures for pediatric patients who require home parenteral nutrition. Admixtures contain high amounts of electrolytes. In a clinical practice electrolytes-enrichment of the parenteral nutrition admixtures is a usual demand, especially on the neonatal/pediatric wards. The supplementation of parenteral nutrition with high concentration of electrolytes is a living problem due to decreased stability of lipid emulsions in nutrition admixtures caused by bivalent cations. Methods: Preliminary admixtures were prepared in two-chamber ethylene vinyl acetate bags: amino acids, glucose and electrolytes were combined in one chamber and 20% (w/w) lipid emulsions (SMOFlipid®, Intralipid ® or ClinOleic®) were placed separately in the second chamber. Organic salts of calcium and phosphates were used. Pre-admixtures were stored at +4ºC for up to 21 days after preparation. Each composition of admixtures was prepared twice, because contents of the two chambers were combined at t=0 or after 21 days of storage at +4ºC. Visual observations, globule size distribution (using optical microscopy, laser diffraction and photon correlation spectroscopy methods), pH analyses, zeta potential and surface tension were performed after combining all components together with vitamins. Results: Among 48 of investigated admixtures only two were problematic and other may be stored for at least 21 days at 4°C and completed admixtures demonstrated stability for at least 24 h at room temperature. Conclusion: It was possible to obtain stable admixtures despite of the high concentration of electrolytes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dorota, Watrobska-Swietlikowska</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agnieszka, Szlagatys-Sidorkiewicz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luszkiewicz, Katarzyna</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El objetivo del estudio fue evaluar la estabilidad de un total de 48 preparados o mezclas parenterales para pacientes pediátricos con necesidad de nutrición parenteral domiciliaria. Los preparados contienen cantidades elevadas de electrolitos. En la práctica clínica, el enriquecimiento con electrolitos de los preparados de nutrición parenteral es una demanda habitual, especialmente en las unidades neonatales/pediátricas. El complemento de la nutrición parenteral con altas concentraciones de electrolitos es un problema corrriente debido a la menor estabilidad de las emulsiones lipídicas en preparados de nutrición provocada por cationes bivalentes. Métodos: Se prepararon mezclas preliminares en bolsas de etilenvinilacetato de dos cámaras: se combinó amino ácidos, glucosa y electrolitos en una cámara y en la  segunda cámara se puso por separado emulsiones lipídicas 20% (w/w) (SMOFlipid®, Intralipid® o ClinOleic®). Se utilizaron sales orgánicas de calcio y fosfatos. Se almacenaron pre-mezclas a +4ºC durante 21 días después de la preparación. Cada composición de mezcla fue preparada dos veces, dado que el contentido de las dos cámaras se combinó en t=0 o después de 21 días después del almacenamiento a +4ºC. Se realizaron observaciones visuales, distribución del tamaño globular (empleando métodos de microscopía óptica, difracción por láser y espectroscopía de correlación fotónica), análisis de pH, potencial zeta y tensión superficial después de combinar todos los componentes a la vez con vitaminas. Resultados: De los 48 preparados investigados solo dos resultaron problemáticos y el resto se pudo almacenar durante al menos 21 días a 4°C y las mezclas completadas presentaron estabilidad durante al menos 24 h a temperatura ambiente. Conclusión: Fue posible obtener preparados estables a pesar de la alta concentración de electrolitos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(1): 236-243, ene. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132600</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la estabilidad física de preparados parenterales «todo en uno» para atención pediátrica domiciliaria con altas concentraciones de electrolitos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4645^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30376^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4416</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4415</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5321^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54124^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19352</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19295</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
