<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042500</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sexuality and reproduction, an important field in endocrinology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Gender Dysphoria Working Group was created in response to an increasing need for the medical care of transsexualism. After several years, the Group decided to extend its activity to the field of sexuality and reproduction because insufficient attention is paid to this topic by Spanish endocrinologists. Factors contributing to the lack of endocrinologists interested in this field include the burden of medical care produced by other, more prevalent diseases, the secondary role assigned to endocrinologists by public and private institutions, and the diagnostic and therapeutic difficulties associated with this field. Therefore, our Working Group aims to deal with clinic pictures whose origins or consequences are directly or undirectly related to alterations in gonadal function (male or female). These alterations, which are mainly hormonal, precipitate diverse disorders in many organs and systems. Because the clinical pictures are so varied, other disciplines (gynecology, urology, internal medicine, cardiology, traumatology, dermatology, geriatrics, etc.) have taken on the leading role in the clinical and research settings. We believe that the field of endocrinology should play a role in the clinical, teaching and research activity performed as a result of diseases with a hormonal substratum (and specifically gonadal), a task which is the raison d'être for the activities of our Group</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Becerra-Fernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Grupo de Trabajo sobre Trastornos de Identidad de Género fue creado como respuesta a la, cada vez más frecuente, necesidad de asistencia médica del transexualismo. Después de algunos años, el grupo decidió extenderse hacia el campo de la sexualidad y la reproducción, porque este tema no está suficientemente desarrollado por los endocrinólogos españoles. La sobrecarga asistencial provocada por otras enfermedades más prevalentes, el papel secundario adjudicado a los endocrinólogos por instituciones públicas y privadas, o las dificultades diagnósticas y terapéuticas, pueden haber contribuido a la falta de endocrinólogos interesados en este campo. Por ello, nuestro grupo de trabajo intenta abordar cuadros clínicos cuyo origen o consecuencia están, directa o indirectamente, relacionados con alteraciones de la función gonadal (masculina o femenina). Estas alteraciones, principalmente hormonales, precipitarán diversos trastornos en múltiples órganos y sistemas. Estos diferentes cuadros han propiciado que otras disciplinas (ginecología, urología, medicina interna, cardiología, traumatología, dermatología, geriatría, etc.) asuman el protagonismo, tanto a escala asistencial como en el terreno de la investigación. Así, nosotros creemos que el desarrollo asistencial, docente e investigador de enfermedades con un sustrato hormonal (y específicamente gonadal) tiene que contar con un punto de vista endocrinológico, y esta tarea es la razón de ser de las actividades de nuestro grupo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;53(1): 34-41, ene. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042500</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sexualidad y reproducción, un campo importante de la endocrinología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7184^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7184^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31397^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22243</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33533^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6205^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33533^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31397^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6205^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
