<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98538</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Lipid profile and cardiovascular risk factors among first-year Brazilian university students in São Paulo</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background/aims: The surveillance of cardiovascular risk factors has been recommended world wide. The current study is aimed to estimate the prevalence of cardiovascular risk factors among first-year students from a public university in the city of Sao Paulo, Brazil. Methods: A cross-sectional study of 56 first-year students, of both genders, was performed. Information about demographic characteristics, family history of chronic diseases, smoking, and physical activity was obtained by means of a standardised questionnaire. Anthropometrical parameters (BMI, waist circumference, body fat percentage), metabolic parameters (glycaemia, serum lipid profile), and dietary data (total energy intake, percentage of total energy from macronutrients, cholesterol and dietary fiber) were assessed. Results: The risk of cardiovascular diseases was characterised by family history of cardiovascular diseases(44.6%), smoking (10.7%), physical inactivity (35.7%), borderline high total cholesterol and LDL-c levels (16.1%and 5.4, respectively), decreased HDL-c levels (8.9%), increased triglyceride levels (8.9%), and overweight and obesity (17.8% and 7.1%, respectively). The diet of the students was inadequate: it was high in fat and protein, and low in carbohydrate and dietary fibre. Conclusions: The prevalence of risk factors for cardiovascular diseases in young adults draws attention to the need to adopt preventive plans in the university setting</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sachs, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barreto Corsi, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro Coelho, L de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toyomi Hirai, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Duarte Pimentel, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Costa Silva Zemdegs, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecendentes /objetivos: la vigilancia de los factores de riesgo se ha recomendado mundialmente. El presente estudio pretendía estimar la prevalencia de los factores de riesgo cardiovascular en estudiantes de primer año de una universidad pública de la ciudad de Sao Paulo, Brasil. Métodos: Se realizó un estudio transversal de 56 estudiantes de primer año, de ambos sexos. Se obtuvo información a cerca de las características demográficas, antecedentes familiares de enfermedades crónicas, hábito de fumar y actividad física mediante un cuestionario estandarizado. Se evaluaron parámetros antropométricos (IMC, circunferencia de la cintura, porcentaje de grasa corporal) y bioquímicos (glucemia, perfil lipídico en suero). La información relativa a la ingestión de la dieta se evaluó mediante un registro de alimentación de tres días. Resultados: el riesgo de enfermedades cardiovasculares se caracterizó por los antecedentes familiares de enfermedades cardiovasculares (44,6%), hábito tabáquico (10,7%), actividad física (35,7%), colesterol y concentración de LDL-c en el límite superior (16,1% y 5,4,respectivamente), disminución de las concentraciones de HDL-c (8,9%), aumento de las concentraciones de triglicéridos(8,9%) u sobrepeso y obesidad (17,8% y 7,1%,respectivamente). La dieta de los estudiantes fue inapropiada: su contenido era elevado en grasas y proteínas y bajo en hidratos de carbono y fibra de la dieta. Conclusiones: la prevalencia de factores de riesgo para enfermedades cardiovasculares en adultos jóvenes reclama la atención hacia la necesidad de planes preventivos en el ámbito universitario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;26(3): 553-559, mayo-jun. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98538</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfil lipídico y factores de riesgo cardiovascular en estudiantes universitarios brasileños de primer año de Sao Paulo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8230^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1963^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
