<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140838</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Depression and somatic symptoms in middle-aged women seen in Primary Care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction:. This study has aimed to describe the prevalence of depression and physical symptoms and the potential impact of the menstrual cycle in female middle aged patients seen in Primary Care in Spain. Material y methods: An observational and cross sectional study conducted in march-july 2005. A total of 1019 doctors included 1019 female outpatients (863 of whom were evaluable for the study) whose ages ranged from 40 to 55 years who came to Primary Care for any reason. HDSR-6 and PHQ-15 scales were used, respectively for the evaluation of depression and somatic symptoms. A cutoff was established at HDRS-6 &gt; 4 (meaning presence of depression symptoms) and PHQ-15 &gt; 4 (meaning presence of somatic symptoms). Results. It was found that 75.6% of the patients had depression symptoms (n = 625), and 85.4% physical symptoms (n = 656). A total of 68.6% of the patients (n = 514) simultaneously suffered depression and physical symptoms. A greater proportion of patients with physical symptoms was observed among the patients with depression (n = 514, 92.3%) than among the patients without depression (n = 126, 65.6%) (Chisquare test, p-value &lt; 0.05). Nevertheless, no statistically significant differences in the presence of physical symptoms were found between the groups of patients with regular menstruation (n = 260, 83.1%), irregular (n = 141, 86.5%), and without menstruation (n = 228, 86.0%) (Chi-square test, p = 0.4933). Conclusion. The results show a high prevalence of depression and physical symptoms and a clear association among them in middle-aged women seen in Primary Care. No association between menstrual cycle and presence of physical symptoms was confirmed, except for an association between menstrual status and menstrual pain symptoms (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ros Montalbán, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Comas Vives, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introduccion: El objetivo de este trabajo es describir la prevalencia de síntomas de depresión y físicos y el posible impacto del ciclo menstrual en pacientes mujeres de mediana edad, atendidas en consultas de Atención Primaria en España. Material y métodos:. Estudio observacional y transversal, realizado entre marzo-julio de 2005. Un total de 1.019 médicos incluyeron 1.019 pacientes ambulatorias (863 fueron valorables para el estudio), mujeres, con edad comprendida entre 40 y 55 años, que acudían a consulta de Atención Primaria por cualquier motivo. Para la evaluación de síntomas de depresión y somáticos se emplearon la escala HDSR-6 y el cuestionario PHQ-15, respectivamente, estableciendo como puntos de corte HDRS-6 &gt; 4 (depresión) y PHQ-15 &gt; 4 (síntomas somáticos). Resultados: Un 75,6% de las pacientes presentaba síntomas de depresión (n = 625), y un 85,4% síntomas físicos (n = 656), por encima de los puntos de corte definidos. Un 68,6% de las pacientes (n = 514) presentaba simultáneamente síntomas de depresión y físicos. Se observó una mayor proporción de pacientes con síntomas físicos entre las pacientes con depresión (n = 514, 92,3%), que sin depresión (n = 126, 65,6%). Sin embargo, no se hallaron diferencias estadísticamente significativas en la presencia de síntomas físicos entre pacientes con menstruación regular (n = 260, 83,1%), irregular (n = 141, 86,5%) y sin menstruación (n = 228, 86,0%). Conclusión: Los resultados muestran una elevada prevalencia de síntomas de depresión y físicos, y una clara asociación entre ellos en mujeres de mediana edad que acuden a Atención Primaria. No se confirma asociación entre ciclo menstrual y síntomas físicos, excepto entre estatus menstrual y los dolores menstruales en sí (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);35(4): 165-172, abr. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140838</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síntomas depresivos y somáticos en mujeres de mediana edad atendidas en Atención Primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55468</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22243^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22243^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22243^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22243^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
