<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165405</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cardiac Resynchronization Therapy: An Economic Perspective</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Today, heart failure is an important public health problem in developed countries. It affects an estimated 1-2% of the general population. This fact coupled to the frequent hospitalization of affected patients means that the disease accounts for as much as 2% of total healthcare expenditure. On the other hand, heart failure is still associated with high mortality and hospital admission rates and poor quality of life. Recently, cardiac resynchronization therapy (CRT) has emerged as an effective treatment for patients with advanced heart failure, conduction abnormalities, and a poor ejection fraction. This technique improves patients&#146; quality of life and functional class, reduces the number of hospital admissions, and decreases mortality. Recent studies have shown that CRT is also beneficial economically as it reduces health costs in patients receiving treatment. Only a few studies have compared the cost-effectiveness of CRT with that of standard medical therapy. Nevertheless, the results show that the incremental cost per additional quality-adjusted life year (QALY) with CRT is similar to that with other common medical interventions for heart failure (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Granell, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macías-Gallego, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Actualmente, la insuficiencia cardíaca es un importante problema sanitario en los países desarrollados y se estima que afecta a un 1-2% de la población general. Este hecho, unido a los ingresos hospitalarios frecuentes, hacen que esta enfermedad consuma cerca del 2% de todos los recursos sanitarios. Por otro lado, la insuficiencia cardíaca permanece como una enfermedad con altas tasas de mortalidad e ingresos hospitalarios y afecta de una manera importante a la calidad de vida de estos enfermos. Hace pocos años, la terapia de resincronización cardíaca (TRC) ha emergido como un tratamiento eficaz en pacientes con insuficiencia cardíaca avanzada, trastornos de la conducción y baja fracción de eyección. Así, esta técnica mejora la calidad de vida y la clase funcional, disminuye los ingresos hospitalarios y reduce la mortalidad de estos pacientes. En estudios recientes se ha demostrado también que la TRC es beneficiosa desde un punto de vista económico, produciendo una reducción de los costes sanitarios en los pacientes tratados. Hay pocos análisis de la relación coste-eficacia de la TRC comparada con el tratamiento médico convencional. Sin embargo, los resultados muestran que el coste adicional por calidad de vida ajustada por año ganado con la TRC es similar al de otros tratamientos empleados en la insuficiencia cardíaca (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);5(supl.B): 18b-23b, 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165405</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Terapia de resincronización cardíaca: el punto de vista económico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16645</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54223^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54283^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
