<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164175</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Frequent users in Pediatric Emergency Departments, it is all the parents' fault?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: there is little information regarding the abuse of consultations in the Pediatric Emergency Departments (PED). The aims of the study are to determine the characteristics of frequent users in a public general hospital, and to estimate the concerns of parents guided by responses to a telephone survey. Patients and methods: a descriptive, cross-sectional, unicentric and local study was conducted from January to December 2015. All children &amp;#8804; 14 years visiting Pediatric Emergency Departments &amp;#8805; 10 times were included. Through a telephone interview, parents were asked whether or not they would go to the Emergency Room for 25 supposed clinical cases. SPSS v22.0(R) was used for statistical analysis. Results: 21 children (52.2% males) visited PED &amp;#8805; 10 times, involving 246 clinical cases (1.17% of total emergencies). Median age was 1.5 years. The ratio of the number of visits at Primary Care vs. PED' was &lt; 1 in 38%. Admission was required only in 9 of 246 (3.65%) children. Visits that could not be solved at Primary Care were observed only in 74 cases (30.1%). Reasons for a pediatric visit and personal history were related. Conclusions: to determine which patients are frequent users is an easy task. To contact the parents of these children and to provide health education could be a feasible and efficient chance, which would be accepted by the population, it also would improve the perceived quality and could save costs to the National Health System. This kind of visits promoting health education are part of a project which will be implemented in our hospital in 2017 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Piñeiro Pérez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora Sitjà, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Martín, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carabaño Aguado, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Archidona, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casado Verrier, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>de la Parte Cancho, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: existe poca información sobre el abuso de las Urgencias Pediátricas. El objetivo principal es determinar el perfil de los padres hiperfrecuentadores en un hospital de media complejidad y estimar el grado de preocupación de los padres según respuestas a una encuesta telefónica. Pacientes y métodos: estudio descriptivo, transversal y unicéntrico. Se realiza un análisis retrospectivo de los informes de alta en niños &amp;#8804; 14 años con &amp;#8805; 10 consultas en Urgencias Pediátricas en el periodo desde el 1 de enero al 31 de diciembre de 2015. A través de entrevista telefónica, se preguntó a los padres si acudirían o no a Urgencias ante 25 supuestos clínicos. Análisis de datos mediante SPSS(R) v22.0. Resultados: 21 niños realizaron &amp;#8805; 10 consultas, que suponen 246 episodios (1,17% del total de Urgencias). Edad mediana de 1,5 años; 52,2% varones. La relación entre el número de consultas en el centro de salud frente a Urgencias Pediátricas fue &lt; 1 en el 38%. Solo nueve de 246 (3,65%) precisaron ingreso. Solo en 74 (30,1%) fue necesaria una atención que no hubiera podido ser solucionada en Atención Primaria. Se observa una relación entre los motivos de consulta y los antecedentes personales. Conclusiones: determinar qué pacientes son hiperfrecuentadores es una tarea fácil. Contactar con los padres de estos niños y ofrecer consultas de educación sanitaria constituye una opción plausible y eficiente, que contaría con aceptación por parte de la población, mejoraría la calidad percibida y podría ahorrar costes al Sistema Nacional de Salud. Este tipo de consultas informativas constituyen parte de un proyecto que se implementará en nuestro hospital en 2017 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;19(74): 137-145, abr.-jun. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164175</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hiperfrecuentadores en Urgencias Pediátricas: ¿es toda la culpa de los padres?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23662^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6452^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6452^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6452^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
