<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124237</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nodular regenerative hyperplasia of the liver and cutaneous T-cell lymphoma: an unreported association</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Nodular regenerative hyperplasia of the liver &#150;a type of noncirrhotic portal hypertension&#150; is a rare condition of unknown etiopathogenesis that has been associated with multiple disorders, including diverse types of hematologic disease. We report the case of a 36-year-old female patient diagnosed with cutaneous T-cell lymphoma of the mycosis fungoides variety, staged as T2N0M0B0, where a transjugular liver biopsy demonstrated the presence of nodular regenerative hyperplasia with a hepatic venous pressure gradient of 15 mm Hg. The study was triggered by the incidental radiologic finding of hepatomegaly with indirect evidence of portal hypertension. We are not aware of any previous reports on the association of nodular regenerative hyperplasia with mycosis fungoides in the medical literature (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pascual-Vaca Gómez, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zulueta Dorado, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giráldez Gallego, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ciria Bru, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nacarino Mejías, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hiperplasia nodular regenerativa hepática &#150;una modalidad de hipertensión portal no cirrótica&#150; es una enfermedad poco frecuente de etiopatogenia desconocida que se ha asociado a multitud de trastornos diversos, incluyendo enfermedades hematológicas de distinta índole. Presentamos el caso de una paciente de 36 años diagnosticada de linfoma cutáneo de células T, tipo micosis fungoide, estadio T2N0M0B0, en la que una biopsia por vía transyugular demostró la existencia de una hiperplasia nodular regenerativa con gradiente de presión venosa hepática de 15 mm Hg; el detonante del estudio fue la aparición radiológica de una hepatomegalia incidental con datos indirectos de hipertensión portal. No nos consta que la asociación entre hiperplasia nodular regenerativa y micosis fungoide esté descrita en la literatura médica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;106(4): 289-292, abr. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124237</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hiperplasia nodular regenerativa hepática y linfoma cutáneo de células T: una asociación no descrita</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15202^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29459^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34199^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29031^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7154^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6686^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
