<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109052</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Denosumab for the treatment of osteoporosis: a systematic literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To determine the efficacy and safety of denosumab in osteoporosis. Methods: A systematic search was performed in MEDLINE, EMBASE, and The Cochrane Central Register of Controlled Trials (1950 to July 2010), meeting abstracts (2009&#150;2010), trial registries, and reference lists. The selection criteria were as follows: (population) osteoporosis patients of any age; (intervention) treatment with denosumab; (outcome) efficacy and safety; (study design) randomized clinical trials (RCTs); no language restrictions. Two reviewers independently screened titles and abstracts and subsequently extracted data from the selected studies including quality items, and on outcomes of interest. A meta-analysis was performed for safety issues. Results: A total of 25 studies were included. Denosumab reduces the risk of new radiographic vertebral fracture in a 68% compared with placebo (p &lt; 0.001) and increases bone mineral density (BMD) at lumbar spine, total hip, and one-third radius more than alendronate and placebo. A single subcutaneous dose of denosumab resulted in a dose-dependent, rapid, profound, and sustained decrease bone turnover markers (BTMs). Denosumab was in general well tolerated. A meta-analysis has shown an increase in the incidence of urinary infections (p = 0.012) and eczema (p &lt; 0.001) in the patients treated with denosumab. Meta-analysis of efficacy was complicated due to the study features. Conclusions: Denosumab given subcutaneously twice yearly is associated with a reduction in the risk of vertebral, nonvertebral, and hip fractures in women with osteoporosis. Denosumab is associated with greater and sustained increases in BMD and reductions in BTMs compared with placebo and/or alendronate and with a risk of urinary infections and eczema (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Piedad Rosario, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carmonad, Loreto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Loza, Estibaliz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-López, Juan Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva-Fernández, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar la eficacia y la seguridad de denosumab en la osteoporosis. Métodos. Se realizó una búsqueda sistemática en MEDLINE, EMBASE y el Registro Central Cochrane de ensayos controlados (de 1950 a Julio de 2010), resúmenes de congresos (2009-2010), registros de ensayos y listas de referencias. Los criterios de selección fueron los siguientes: (población) pacientes con osteoporosis de cualquier edad; (intervención) tratamiento con denosumab; (desenlace) eficacia y seguridad; (diseño del estudio) ensayos clínicos con selección aleatoria; sin restricciones de idioma. Dos revisores independientes revisaron títulos y resúmenes y posteriormente extrajeron los datos de los estudios seleccionados, incluyendo elementos de calidad y desenlaces de interés. Se realizó un metanaálisis con los datos de seguridad. Resultados. Se incluyeron 25 estudios. El denosumab reduce el riesgo de fracturas radiográficas nuevas en un 68% en comparación con el placebo (p&lt;0,001); incrementa la de densidad mineral ósea (DMO) en la columna lumbar, la cadera total y el tercio distal del radio, más que el alendronato y el placebo. Una dosis subcutánea única de denosumab provocó una disminución rápida, profunda, sostenida y dosis-dependiente de los marcadores de remodelado óseo (MRO). El denosumab fue bien tolerado en general. El metananálisis mostró un aumento en la incidencia de infecciones urinarias (p=0,012) y eczema (p&lt;0,001) en los pacientes tratados con denosumab. No se pudo realizar metaanálisis de eficacia debido a la heterogeneidad de los estudios. Conclusiones. El denosumab administrado por vía subcutánea, 2 veces al año, se asocia con una reducción en el riesgo de fracturas vertebrales, no vertebrales y de cadera, en mujeres con osteoporosis. El denosumab se asocia con un incremento mayor y sostenido en la DMO, y una reducción en los MRO, en comparación con el placebo y el alendronato, así como con un riesgo aumentado de infecciones urinarias y eczema (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);9(1): 42-52, ene.-mar.2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109052</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Denosumab para el tratamiento de la osteoporosis: revision sistemática de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24543^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
