<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-AOT-2400</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Performance of the KAtex test in screening and diagnosis for visceral leishmaniasis in a reference hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Performing of diagnostic test simple using samples not invasive in the diagnosis of visceral leishmaniasis (VL) may be very beneficial, being necessary comparing to traditional methods. The objective of this study was to know the reliability of test KAtex in the urine of patients with suspicion of VL. Material and methods. Retrospectively were reviewed the medical histories of patients with suspected of VL to which are performed the test between 2009 and 2015. For its analysis were selected the patients to which is them had made study of the parasite in bone marrow. Results. A total of 110 patients were studied, and bone marrow biopsy for research of Leishmania was performed in 44 (40%). In these patients the sensitivity of the test was 50%, the specificity of 96.7%, positive predictive value of 87.5% and negative predictive value of 80.5%. Conclusions. KAtex antigenuria sensitivity is too low recommending it as a unique method in the detection of VL in our medium (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Roldán, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Ruz, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Javier Martínez, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro-Marí, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Grangér, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Fernández, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La utilización de pruebas diagnósticas simples empleando muestras no invasivas en el diagnóstico de la leishmaniasis visceral (LV) en nuestro entorno puede resultar muy útil, siendo necesario compararlas con los métodos tradicionales. El objetivo de este trabajo fue conocer la utilidad diagnóstica de la prueba KAtex en la orina de pacientes con sospecha de LV en nuestro medio. Material y métodos. De forma retrospectiva se revisaron las historias clínicas de los pacientes con sospecha de LV a los que se les realizó la prueba KAtex entre 2009 y 2015. Para la evaluación de su capacidad diagnóstica se seleccionaron los pacientes a los que se les había investigado la presencia del parásito en médula ósea. Resultados. De los 110 pacientes estudiados, en 44 (40%) se realizó biopsia de médula ósea para la investigación de Leishmania. En estos pacientes la sensibilidad de la prueba KAtex fue del 50%, la especificidad del 96,7%, el valor predictivo positivo del 87,5% y el valor predictivo negativo del 80,5%. Conclusiones. La sensibilidad de la antigenuria KAtex es demasiado baja para recomendarla como único método en la detección de LV en nuestro medio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;30(6): 464-467, dic. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-AOT-2400</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comportamiento de la prueba KAtex en el cribado y diagnóstico de la leishmaniasis visceral en un hospital de referencia</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
