<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044487</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion in pediatric patients with type 1 diabetes mellitus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction                 To determine the efficacy and safety of continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion therapy in a group of children and adolescents with type 1 diabetes mellitus.                 Patients and methods                 Data from 17 patients were collected during the first year of continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion treatment. All patients were followed-up at our diabetic pediatric clinic. HbA1c, body mass index, insulin dose, severe hypoglycemic episodes, and diabetic ketoacidosis events before and after initiation of pump therapy were compared.                 Results                 The mean age was 14.02 ± 3.70 years and the mean diabetes duration was 5.81 ± 3.31 years. HbA1c decreased from 8.12 ± 1.46 to 7.52 ± 0.87 % after 2 months of therapy and this decrease was maintained throughout the first year of continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion treatment. Insulin dose decreased from 0.99 ± 0.24 to 0.84 ± 0.18 U/kg/day after 1 year of treatment. Body mass index remained unchanged. There were fewer severe hypoglycemic events after the start of insulin pump therapy (0.47 ± 1.23 events/patient in the 6 months before continuous insulin infusion, 0.29 ± 1.20 episodes in the first 6 months of insulin pump therapy and 0.06 ± 0.24 in the period from 6 to 12 months of the treatment). There were 3 ketoacidosis episodes, all in the same patient.                 Conclusions                 Continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion is a safe and effective alternative in the treatment of children and adolescents with type 1 diabetes mellitus. It improves metabolic control and decreases the number of severe hypoglycemic episodes</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Capapé, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Colino Alcol, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Gómez, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Frías, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrio Castellanos, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Blanco, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción                 El propósito del estudio es determinar la eficacia y la seguridad del tratamiento con bombas de infusión subcutánea continua de insulina en un grupo de niños y adolescentes con diabetes mellitus tipo 1.                 Pacientes y métodos                 Se analizan los datos de 17 pacientes diabéticos tratados en nuestra Unidad de Diabetes Pediátrica durante el primer año de terapia con bomba de infusión subcutánea continua de insulina. Comparamos la HbA1c, índice de masa corporal, dosis de insulina, episodios de hipoglucemia grave y episodios de cetoacidosis antes y después del inicio de la terapia con bomba de insulina.                 Resultados                 La media de edad fue de 14,02 ± 3,70 años y el tiempo medio de evolución de la diabetes de 5,81 ± 3,31 años. Se objetiva una disminución de HbA1c de 8,12 ± 1,46 a 7,52 ± 0,87 % a los 2 meses de tratamiento que se mantiene en estas concentraciones durante todo el año. La dosis de insulina disminuye de 0,99 ± 0,24 a 0,84 ± 0,18 U/kg/día al año de tratamiento. El índice de masa corporal permanece estable. También se observa una disminución del número de episodios de hipoglucemia grave (0,47 ± 1,23 episodios/paciente en los 6 meses previos al inicio del tratamiento con bomba, 0,29 ± 1,20 durante los primeros 6 meses de la nueva terapia y 0,06 ± 0,24 de los 6 a 12 meses). Hubo tres episodios de cetoacidosis, todos ellos en el mismo paciente.                 Conclusiones                 La terapia con bomba de infusión subcutánea continua de insulina es una alternativa eficaz y segura para tratar niños y adolescentes con diabetes mellitus tipo 1, ya que permite mejorar el control metabólico con disminución del riesgo de hipoglucemia grave</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);64(1): 21-27, ene. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044487</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento con infusión subcutánea continua de insulina en pacientes pediátricos con diabetes mellitus tipo 1</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22523</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
