<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91987</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Concerning the pervese struture</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The field of perversions appears to be vast and varied on the phenomenic level; the use of the term perversion has become too loose in psychoanalysis, while the theoretical approaches have multiplied in this respect. The problem is, then, to find out whether, within that  multiplicity, there is something that we may call a perverse structure. By contrasting &lt;true perversions&gt; and transient perverse manifestations in neurotic or psychotic patients, some common elements are brought our which make out the perverse structure the specific relationship between the perverse acting out and confusional anxiety and, more precisely, the attempt to ritualize a confuse fantasy of the primary scene (M. Klein); the rebellion against the father and the profanation of the mother; bisexual and confused identifications; playing with the idea of incest and the denial of castration; the prevalence of narcissistic elements. The authors stress the existence of a &lt;perverse discourse&gt;  by means of which the perverse structure finds expression in the analytic dialogue and which is characterized by the different forms of lying, which ranges from statements made in bad faith to cynical lies. They set forth the hypothesis that the perverse structure cannot be approached only from the point of view of fetishism (where castration anxiety and denial prevail), or form the point out that it requires the combinations of these three determinants, a combinations which is in itself variable according to the various forms of perversion, form the fetishism to extreme sadism or necrophilia. As to the genesis of perversion, the authors stress the role of a &lt;corrupting&gt; family. This role is usually played by the mother, but the corrupting agent may also be the father or both parents. In these families there is a high degree of ambiguity concerning the formulation and enforcement of the paternal  law.  Anyway, in our view &lt;true perversion&gt; is an alternative structured by the subject in his attempt to avoid psychotic disintegration and cope with the death instinct (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>R. De Bisi, Nora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Goldstein, Néstor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Goldstein, Raquel Z. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baranger, Willy</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosenthal, Gela</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El campo de las perversiones aparece como excesivamente vasto y variado en lo fenoménico; el uso de la palabra perversión se ha vuelto demasiado laxo en psicoanálisis, al mismo tiempo, los enfoques teóricos para encarar este campo se han multiplicado. Se plantea el problema de saber si existe algo, dentro de esta multiplicidad, que podamos llamar estructura perversa. Al oponer la &lt;perversión verdadera&gt; a las manifestaciones perversas episódicas de pacientes neuróticos o psicóticos, se muestran grandes constantes que configuran la estructura perversa: la relación específica del acting perverso con las angustias confusionales y más precisamente con el intento de ritualización de una fantasía confusa de la escena primaria (M. Klein); el desafía al padre y la profanación de la madre; las identificaciones bisexuales y confusas; el juego con la idea del incesto y la desmentida de la castración; la predominancia de elementos narcisistas. Los autores recalcan la existencia de un &lt;discurso perverso&gt; mediante el cual la estructura perversa se expresa en el diálogo analítico, y que se caracteriza por las distintas formas de la mentira, desde el juego de la mala fe hasta la mentira cínica. Desarrollan la hipótesis de que la estructura perversa no se puede enfocar tan sólo desde el ángulo del fetichismo (donde predominan angustia de castración y desmentida) ni desde el narcisismo como perversión manifiesta, ni desde el sadismo, sino que requiere la articulación de estos tres factores determinantes, articulación variable ella misma según las diversas formas de la perversión, desde el extremo del fetichismo hasta el del gran sadismo o de la necrofilia. Subrayamos en la génesis de la perversión el papel de una familia &lt;corruptora&gt;. Lo más frecuente es que se la madre quien desempeñe  el papel corruptor, pero también pueden desempeñarlo el padre o ambos padres. En esas familias reina un alto grado de ambigüedad acerca de la formulación y el cumplimiento de la ley paterna. De todos modos, la &lt;perversión verdadera&gt; no parece ser una opción estructurada por el sujeto en el intento  de evitar la desintegración psicótica y de lidiar con la pulsión de muerte (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(57): 13-30, oct. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91987</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acerca de la estructura perversa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8369</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10451^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
