<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117050</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New Treatments for Human Papillomavirus Infection</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Human papillomavirus infection is very common. In this article, we review the latest developments in the treatment of lesions caused by this virus, with a particular focus on anogenital warts. Sinecatechins and new imiquimod formulations are among the most significant new developments. Others include photodynamic therapy and intralesional immunotherapy, but there is insufficient evidence to recommend their routine use. Finally, while therapeutic vaccines and inhibitory molecules appear to hold great promise, they are still in the early phases of investigation. More studies are needed, and these should have similar designs, larger samples, and sufficiently long follow-up periods to enable the direct comparison of the short-term and long-term effectiveness of different treatment options (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alsina, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pigem, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Santos, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La infección por el virus del papiloma humano es una afección muy prevalente. Se revisan los aspectos más novedosos del tratamiento de las lesiones producidas por este virus, especialmente las verrugas anogenitales. Las sinecatequinas y las nuevas formulaciones de imiquimod destacan como novedades, mientras que la terapia fotodinámica y la inmunoterapia intralesional carecen de evidencia científica suficiente para recomendar su uso rutinario. Las vacunas terapéuticas y las moléculas inhibidoras parecen poseer un gran potencial, aun cuando se encuentran en fases iniciales de investigación. Sería deseable disponer de estudios más homogéneos, con muestras más grandes y con seguimientos suficientemente prolongados que permitiesen comparar directamente la efectividad entre las diferentes modalidades terapéuticas a corto y largo plazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;104(10): 883-889, dic. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117050</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevos tratamientos en la infección por virus del papiloma humano</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24015^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52407^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1002^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35997^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
