<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105109</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Genital tuberculosis. Differential diagnosis with ovarian cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In women with an adnexal mass, ascites and elevated serum markers, ovarian carcinoma must be excluded. However, several other entities, including genital tuberculosis, may produce similar symptoms. A 38-year-old woman with no personal or familial history of interest presented with abdominal pain, ascites, constitutional syndrome, high fever and elevated Ca125 and Ca15.3 levels. Computed tomography revealed severe septated ascites and an adnexal mass. A skin tuberculin test was negative for tuberculosis.At exploratory laparotomy, miliary spread over abdominal organs was observed, with adhesions and partial pelvic block. Intraoperative biopsy was negative for malignancy but a double adnexectomy was performed and adhesions were released. Postoperative histologic examination revealed typical features of genital tuberculosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-García, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido Sánchez,  M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Lopera, E. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ocón Hernández, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En mujeres con masa anexial, ascitis y marcadores tumorales elevados, el cáncer de ovario debe ser excluido. Pero existen otras condiciones, incluida la tuberculosis genital, que pueden presentar clínica similar. Una mujer de 38 años, sin antecedentes personales ni familiares de interés, ingresa en nuestro servicio con un cuadro de dolor hipogástrico, ascitis, síndrome constitucional y fiebre elevada. Presentaba niveles séricos elevados de Ca125 y Ca15.3 y la TAC reveló ascitis severa y una masa anexial derecha. El Mantoux fue negativo. En la laparotomía exploradora se aprecia siembra miliar abdominal, cuadro adherencial y bloqueo parcial de la pelvis. La biopsia intraoperatoria fue negativa para malignidad, sin embargo se realiza doble anexectomía y liberación de adherencias. El examen histológico postoperatorio da el diagnóstico de tuberculosis genital (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);39(3): 121-124, may. -jun.2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105109</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tuberculosis genital. Diagnóstico diferencial con cáncer de ovario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1208^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10229^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14784^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7991^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
