<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130328</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">DRESS syndrome secondary to ibuprofen as a cause of hyperacute liver failure</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Acute liver failure has a high mortality and its most frequent cause in Spain is viral infection. In this article, we present a case of fulminant liver failure. The failure is secondary to an idiosyncratic reaction to ibuprofen, an entity included in the DRESS syndrome. This syndrome plays a key role in the differential diagnosis of acute liver failure, since its unfortunate course often requires liver transplantation as the only useful therapeutic weapon. This case illustrates the need for an efficient coordination between hospitals as a key factor for improving the prognosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casabona-Francés, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vanaclocha, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roales-Gómez, Valentín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Amarilla, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Colina, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molero, Aída Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Catalán, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rey Díaz-Rubio, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El fallo hepático agudo presenta alta mortalidad, siendo su primera etiología en España la viral. Presentamos un caso de fallo fulminante secundario a una reacción idiosincrásica a ibuprofeno, englobado en el síndrome de DRESS (Drug Rash with Eosinophilia and Systemic Symptoms). Dicho síndrome constituye un diagnóstico clave en el diagnóstico diferencial del fracaso hepático agudo, ya que su curso infausto obliga en muchas ocasiones a la realización de trasplante hepático como única terapéutica útil. Este caso es un buen ejemplo de la necesidad de la rapidez y la eficiencia en la coordinación a nivel intrahospitalario y entre centros sanitarios como factor clave en la mejoría del pronóstico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;106(7): 482-486, jul.-ago. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130328</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome DRESS secundario a ibuprofeno como causa de fallo hepático hiperagudo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4404^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4404^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1676^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4404^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5175^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30668^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2829^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30667^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28145^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30667^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30668^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30667^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
