<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159578</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sexuality risk factors among people with suspect of sexuality transmitted disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Describing determinants factors in Sexually Transmitted Diseases is necessary to evaluate and design effective measures for prevention and treatment. The aim of this research was to determine the sexual risk factors of people who are treated at Sexually Transmitted Diseases Centre and to analyze differences based on gender. Method: Cross-sectional study on 496 clinical reports, period of time 2010 to 2014, of people who come to the Sexually Transmitted Diseases and Sexual Orientation Centre of Granada, for suspected of Sexually Transmitted Diseases. Sociodemographic, clinical and sexual patterns data were collected. Calculation of descriptive statistics and Chi-square test to compare proportions were performed Results: 56% men and 44% women. The mean age was 29,01 years (SD=9,07). Most of the sample were single (85,9%). 54,2% had a higher education level. The most prevalent infections were the Human Papillomavirus (18,8%), followed Molluscum contagiosum (5,6%) and Candidiasis (3,8%). Significant differences were found by sex with sexual behavior, there are more gay men (n=89) and bisexual (n=22) than women (n=4, n=7, respectively) (p&lt;0,001); differences between sex and sexual life were also found, finding higher prevalence of men with 10-20 couples (n=23) and more than 20 couples (n=20) than women (n=10, n=4, respectively) (p&lt;0,001). Conclusions: The user profile is a young, single, with higher education. The most prevalent infection is the Human Papillomavirus. Men are a vulnerable population for contracting sexually transmitted diseases because of their sexual practices (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castro-López, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Morente, María Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Ocón, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Bautista, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hueso-Montoro, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano-Romero, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: Conocer los factores determinantes en Infecciones de Transmisión sexual (ITS) es necesario para evaluar y diseñar medidas efectivas para su prevención y tratamiento. El objetivo de este estudio fue determinar los factores de riesgo relacionados con la sexualidad de sujetos atendidos en un centro de control de Infecciones de Transmisión Sexual y analizar si hubo diferencias en función del sexo. Método: Estudio transversal utilizando como fuente de información 496 historias clínicas correspondientes al periodo 2010-2014, de sujetos que acudieron al Centro de Enfermedades de Transmisión Sexual y Orientación Sexual de la provincia de Granada por sospecha de ITS. Se recogieron datos sociodemográficos, clínicos y relacionados con pautas sexuales. Se realizó análisis descriptivo y análisis bivariante mediante comparación de proporciones con test de la chi-cuadrado. Resultados: El 56% de los sujetos eran hombres y el 44% mujeres. La edad media fue de 29,01 años (DT=9,07). El 85,9% estaban solteros. El 54,2% presentaba un nivel de estudios superior. Las infecciones más prevalentes fueron el virus del papiloma humano (18,8%), Molluscum contagioso (5,6%) y candidiasis (3,8%). Se hallaron diferencias estadísticamente significativas por sexo con la variable conducta sexual, hallando 89 hombres homosexuales y 4 mujeres, así como 22 hombres bisexuales frente a 7 mujeres(p&lt;0,001).También se hallaron diferencias entre sexo y vida sexual, encontrando mayor prevalencia de hombres con entre 10-20 parejas (n=23) y más de 20 parejas (n=20) que mujeres (n=10, n= 4, respectivamente) (p&lt;0,001). Conclusiones: El perfil es el de una persona joven, soltera, con estudios superiores. La infección más prevalente es el virus del papiloma humano. Los hombres siguen constituyendo la población más vulnerable para contraer infecciones de transmisión sexual debido a sus prácticas sexuales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;91: 0-0, 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159578</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores de riesgo relacionados con las infecciones de transmisión sexual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24326^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24326^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
