<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102303</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-7606</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dysembryoplastic neuroepithelial tumor: a case of sudden death in a young epileptic patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Sudden deaths due to intracranial tumors that have not been diagnosed in life are very rare. In this paper we present the case of a young patient who died during sleep. The only medical antecedent was drug-resistant epilepsy suffered since childhood. Neuroimage techniques did not show any alteration prior to death. The autopsy showed in the cerebral cortex of the left parietal lobe the presence of a tumor of 0.5 x 1 cm without mass effect. In view of the findings of histopathological and immunohistochemical studies a diagnosis of dysembryoplastic neuroepithelial tumor (DNT) simple was made. The cause of sudden death was attributed to an organic seizure disorder secondary to the tumor. DNT is very infrequent (0.2-1% of brain tumors) and it is usually associated with drug-resistant seizures. This case demonstrates that in the investigation of sudden unexplained death associated to epilepsy is crucial to perform a medico-legal autopsy in order to confirm the cause and the risk factors related to epilepsy and death (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Biritxinaga, J. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Querejeta, L. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morentin, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arnaiz, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las muertes súbitas por tumores intracraneales no diagnosticados en vida son muy raras. En el presente artículo se presenta el caso de un paciente joven que es hallado muerto durante el sueño. Como único antecedente de interés destaca la presencia desde la infancia de crisis epilépticas de difícil control medicamentoso. Las pruebas de imagen no habían mostrado en vida alteraciones reseñables. En la autopsia se evidencia un tumor de 0,5 x 1 cm en la corteza cerebral del lóbulo parietal izquierdo, sin efecto masa. A la vista de los hallazgos del estudio histopatológico e inmunohistoquímico se realiza el diagnóstico de tumor disembrioplástico neuroepitelial (TDN) simple. Se establece como causa de la muerte el trastorno epiléptico orgánico secundario al tumor. El TDN es un tumor cerebral de muy baja frecuencia (0,2-1% de los tumores cerebrales) y normalmente se asocia a crisis epilépticas fármaco-resistentes. Este caso demuestra que ante una muerte súbita e inexplicada asociada a epilepsia es fundamental la realización de una autopsia médico-legal a fin de reconocer la causa y los factores de riesgo relacionados con la epilepsia y la muerte (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. med. forense;16(4): 231-233, oct.-dic. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102303</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumor disembrioplástico neuroepitelial: un caso de muerte súbita en un paciente joven epiléptico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14102^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31265^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3662</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28637</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1352^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
