<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118030</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The use of the ketogenic diet as treatment for refractory epilepsy in the paediatric age</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Between 23% and 25% of epileptic children are refractory to antiepileptic drugs. In recent times there has been a renewed interest in the ketogenic diet as treatment in these patients who are not candidates for other therapeutic options. Aims. To evaluate the effectiveness and safety of treatment with the ketogenic diet in an important number of paediatric patients with refractory epilepsy in our centre and to determine whether the results obtained are consistent with others recently reported in the literature. Patients and methods. A retrospective review was conducted of the medical records of 41 children with refractory epilepsy treated with the ketogenic diet, mostly the Radcliffe II-type diet, between 1998 and 2011. Their median age on starting the diet was 3.92 years old. Results. At six months after beginning the diet, the number of crises was reduced by at least 50% in 36.84% of the sample (10.53% of the children reached a 90% reduction and 5.26% no longer suffered crises). Around 50% of those in the youngest age group responded positively. Some tolerable, transient side effects were experienced by 58.54% of the patients, consisting mainly in high levels of cholesterol and constipation; no variations in the anthropomorphic parameters were observed. Conclusions. The ketogenic diet is a good therapeutic alternative in cases of refractory epilepsy in the paediatric age. Moreover, the younger the child is on starting on the diet, the more likely he or she is to gain benefits from it. In general it is well tolerated. Regular check-ups with supervision of these patients&#146; nutrition are of great importance (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Camacho Salas, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Villares, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pablos Sánchez, Tamara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliveros Leal, Liliana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nuñez Enamorado, Noemí</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Simón de las Heras, Rogelio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El 23-25% de los niños epilépticos son refractarios a fármacos antiepilépticos. El interés por la dieta cetogénica como tratamiento en estos pacientes no candidatos a otras opciones terapéuticas ha resurgido últimamente. Objetivo. Valorar la eficacia y seguridad del tratamiento con dieta cetogénica en un importante número de pacientes pediátricos con epilepsia refractaria en nuestro centro y determinar si los resultados obtenidos corroboran otros de publicación reciente. Pacientes y métodos. Se revisaron retrospectivamente las historias clínicas de 41 niños con epilepsia refractaria que fueron tratados con dieta cetogénica entre 1998 y 2011, la mayoría con dieta tipo Radcliffe II. La mediana de edad al inicio de la dieta fue de 3,92 años. Resultados. A los seis meses del inicio de la dieta se redujeron las crisis en al menos un 50% en un 36,84% de la muestra (el 10,53% de los niños alcanzó más de un 90% de reducción y un 5,26% quedó sin crisis). Aproximadamente un 50% por grupo de edad en los más pequeños respondió de manera positiva. Un 58,54% de los pacientes presentó algún efecto secundario, tolerable y transitorio, principalmente elevación de los niveles de colesterol y estreñimiento, sin observarse variación en los parámetros antropométricos. Conclusiones. La dieta cetogénica supone una buena alternativa terapéutica en los casos de epilepsia refractaria en la edad pediátrica, con mayor probabilidad de beneficio cuanto menor sea la edad del niño al inicio de la dieta. En general, es bien tolerada. Son de gran importancia en estos pacientes las revisiones periódicas con control nutricional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;58(2): 55-62, ene. 2014. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118030</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia en el tratamiento con dieta  etogénica de la epilepsia refractaria en la edad pediátrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53233^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52504</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32108^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201401</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
