<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154301</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-695X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Eosinophilic Esophagitis causing dysphagia in an adolescent</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Eosinophilic esophagitis (EE) is a rare, but emerging entity that we must consider in children and young patients with food impaction or persistent dysphagia and atopic disease, or in cases of refractory gastroesophageal reflux disease. Diagnosis must be made by mucosal biopsies of the esophagus obtained by esophagogastroduodenoscopy and the histological finding of at least 20 eosinophils per high-power field.  This disease is a chronic inflammation of the esophagus with increasing prevalence, requiring early diagnosis and treatment with consistent follow-up, since long-term consequences are currently unknown.  We present the case of an adolescent with dysphagia and food impaction of many years´ duration (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Orgaz Gallego, M Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solera Martínez, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tricio Armero, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Esofagitis Eosinofílica (EE) es una entidad rara, aunque emergente, que debemos sospechar en niños y jóvenes con impactación del bolo alimenticio o disfagia persistente y enfermedad atópica, o en casos de reflujo gastroesofágico refractario a la terapia. El diagnóstico precisa la realización de endoscopia digestiva alta con biopsias y el hallazgo histológico de más de 20 eosinófilos por campo de gran aumento. Es una inflamación crónica del esófago con una prevalencia en aumento, que requiere un diagnóstico y tratamiento precoces y un seguimiento en el tiempo, pues por el momento se desconocen las consecuencias a largo plazo. Presentamos el caso de un adolescente con disfagia e impactación alimentaria de años de evolución (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. clín. med. fam;5(1): 63-68, feb. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154301</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Disfagia en un adolescente como manifestación de la esofagitis eosinofílica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23977^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23977^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29396^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23977^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53957^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22562^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33421^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23994^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53957^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
