<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-168661</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Choice of fluids in the perioperative period of kidney transplantation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Normal saline has traditionally been the resuscitation fluid of choice in the perioperative period of kidney transplantation over balanced potassium solutions. However, the problems arising from hyperchloraemia triggered by the infusion of normal saline have led to studies being conducted that compare this solution with balanced solutions. From this narrative review it can be concluded that the use of balanced crystalloids containing potassium in the perioperative period of kidney transplantation can be considered safe. These solutions do not affect serum potassium levels any more than normal saline, whilst maintaining a better acid-base balance in these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortiz-Lasa, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, Camilo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gonzalez-Castro, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peñasco, Yhivian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodriguez-Borregan, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El suero salino normal (SSN) ha sido clásicamente el fluido de resucitación elegido en el periodo perioperatorio del trasplante renal frente a aquellas soluciones balanceadas con potasio. Sin embargo, los problemas derivados de la hipercloremia desencadenada por la infusión de SSN han llevado a la realización de estudios que comparaban esta solución con los fluidos equilibrados. Mediante la presente revisión narrativa se deduce que el uso de cristaloides balanceados con contenido de potasio en su formulación, en el perioperatorio de trasplante renal, puede considerarse seguro. Estas soluciones no provocan una alteración del potasio sérico mayor que la provocada por el SSN y mantienen mejor el equilibrio ácido-base en estos enfermos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;37(6): 572-578, nov.-dic. 2017. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-168661</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Elección de fluidos en el periodo perioperatorio del trasplante renal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54247^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7128^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d147^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12837^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28261^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
