<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128978</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4603</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Syllable frequency effects in Spanish handwriting production</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study was concerned with the nature of the sublexical units that are functional during the process of writing words in normal adults. Specifically, we focused on the role of syllables in Spanish handwriting. Participants were asked to write down trisyllabic words. In the experiment, a graphic tablet was used and the frequency of the second syllable was manipulated in the stimuli while controlling for bigram frequency. The latencies, letter durations and temporal intervals between letters were measured. The results showed an effect of syllable frequency on the interval between the first and second letter of the second syllable: the interval was shorter for high-frequency than for low-frequency syllables. An opposite effect was observed for the duration of the first letter of the critic syllable. No effect was found on the interval previous to the second syllable. These results confirm recent findings supporting the claim that syllables are involved during the handwriting production process and provide new information on the mechanisms underlying these syllabic effects(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Afonso, Olivia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, Carlos J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Esta investigación se ocupa de la naturaleza de las unidades subléxicas funcionales durante el proceso de escritura en adultos normales. En concreto, se centra en el papel de las sílabas en el español escrito. Se pidió a los participantes que escribieran palabras trisilábicas a mano. Mediante una tableta gráfica, se manipuló la frecuencia de la segunda sílaba en los estímulos, mientras se controlaba por la frecuencia de bigramas. Se midieron las latencias, la duración de las letras y los intervalos temporales entre letras. Los resultados mostraron un efecto de frecuencia silábica en el intervalo entre la primera y la segunda letra de la segunda sílaba: fue más corto para las sílabas de frecuencia alta que para las de frecuencia baja. Se observó el efecto opuesto para la duración de la primera letra de la sílaba crítica. No se observó ningún efecto en el intervalo anterior a la segunda sílaba. Estos resultados confirman hallazgos recientes que respaldan la postura de que las sílabas están implicadas en el proceso de producción escrita y proporcionan nueva información acerca de los mecanismos que subyacen en estos efectos silábicos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. logop. foniatr. audiol. (Ed. impr.);31(1): 33-38, ene.-mar.2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128978</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de la frecuencia silábica en la producción escrita del español</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1307^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15354</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52965^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29323^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29323^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1307^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1191^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52965^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52965^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
