<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73455</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnosis and treatment guidelines for difficult-to-control asthma in children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Children suffering from difficult-to-control asthma (DCA) require frequent appointments with their physician, complex treatment regimes and often admissions to hospital. Less than 5% of the asthmatic population suffer this condition. DCA must be correctly characterised to rule out false causes of DCA and requires making a differential diagnosis from pathologies that mimic asthma, comorbidity, environmental and psychological factors, and analysing the factors to determine poor treatment compliance. In true DCA cases, inflammation studies (exhaled nitric oxide, induced sputum, broncho-alveolar lavage and bronchial biopsy), pulmonary function and other clinical aspects can classify DCA into different phenotypes which could make therapeutic decision-making easier (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Asensio de la Cruz, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Merino, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Liñán Cortes, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García García, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villa Asensi, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrés Martín, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los niños con asma de control difícil (ACD) requieren frecuentes consultas, reciben complejos regímenes de tratamiento y, a menudo, requieren ingresos en el hospital. Su frecuencia es escasa, y abarca no más del 5% de la población asmática. El ACD requiere un diagnóstico de certeza, por lo que se tendrán que descartar causas de falso ACD, y es necesario hacer un diagnóstico diferencial con factores de enfermedad sobreañadida, medioambientales, psicológicos, y analizar causas que determinen una baja adherencia al tratamiento. Ante un verdadero ACD, el estudio de la inflamación (óxido nítrico exhalado, esputo inducido, lavado broncoalveolar y biopsia bronquial), la función pulmonar y la clínica nos pueden permitir clasificar el ACD en diversos fenotipos que nos facilitarán la toma de decisiones terapéuticas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);71(6): 548-567, dic. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73455</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Guía de diagnóstico y tratamiento del asma de control difícil en el niño</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29636</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1969^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32858^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
