<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102763</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Maturational changes in the human envelope-following responses</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The auditory ability to discriminate rapid changes in the envelope of language sounds is essential for speech comprehension. Human envelope-following responses (EFRs) are useful for objective measurement of temporal auditory processing in subjects who are unable to give accurate behavioural responses (e.g., young children). Objective: To evaluate age-dependent changes in EFRs during the first 2 years of life. Methods: The EFRs were recorded in a sample of 16 well babies distributed into 2 age groups (G1: 12 newborns; G2: 4 babies of 2 years). The EFRs were evoked by white noise carrier stimuli with a sweep of modulation frequencies from 20 to 200Hz presented at 50dB HL. Results: The age-related changes affected both morphology and EFR detectability. The main morphological differences were at the expense of frequencies below 50Hz, where the first component P1 was not well defined in either of the 2 age groups. For all modulation frequencies, age significantly affected EFR amplitude and detectability. Conclusions: The present study provides the first evidence on EFR maturation. Some understanding of normal EFR development would facilitate a better use of this technique in clinically-objective measurement of auditory temporal processing in infants who cannot provide reliable behavioural responses(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Abalo, María C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mijares Nodarse, Eleina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lage Castellanos, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega Hernández, Mayrim</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Fortuny, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La capacidad de detectar cambios temporales en la amplitud de modulación de los sonidos del habla es esencial para el adecuado desarrollo y comprensión del lenguaje. El potencial evocado auditivo de seguimiento a la envolvente (PEA-SE) permite estudiar objetivamente la respuesta auditiva a los cambios en la modulación del estímulo acústico en sujetos que no cooperan con exámenes conductuales. Objetivo: Evaluar posibles cambios maduracionales en los parámetros del PEA-SE durante los 2 primeros años de vida. Métodos: se estudiaron 16 bebés normooyentes (12 recién nacidos y 4 bebés de 2 años de edad). Se registró el PEA-SE obtenido con un ruido blanco al que se le realizó un barrido continuo de modulación entre 20-200Hz a 50dB HL. Resultados: Las principales diferencias con respecto al patrón morfológico descrito en los adultos estuvieron a expensas de las frecuencias inferiores a 50Hz, donde el componente P1, a diferencia del P2, no se registró de forma definida y estable en ninguno de los grupos. Con la edad existe, además, un incremento significativo en la amplitud y detectabilidad del potencial en todas las frecuencias de modulación estudiadas. Conclusiones: Se caracterizan por primera vez las modificaciones del PEA-SE con la maduración del sistema auditivo en seres humanos. Los resultados sugieren que el PEA-SE obtenido entre 80-200Hz podría ser útil para estudiar los cambios maduracionales del procesamiento auditivo temporal en la población infantil(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;63(4): 258-264, jul.-ago. 2012. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102763</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambios con la edad en la respuesta electrofisiológica de seguimiento a la modulación del estímulo acústico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4641^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4641^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9672^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1312^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5169^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13444</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d165^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
