<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89948</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Continuous infusion of local anesthetic at the site of  the abdominal surgical wound for postoperative analgesia: a systematic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: We present a systematic review of clinical trials to evaluate the efficacy of infusing local anesthetic through a catheter placed in the abdominal surgical wound. Methods: The Jadad (Oxford) scoring system was used to select trials. The variables considered in relation to each trial selected were as follows: type of intervention and incision; type, dose, and concentration of local anesthetic; site where the catheter was placed; rescue analgesia required; opioid use; and incidence of adverse events. Results: Fifteen clinical trials with a mean Jadad score of 4.6 were selected. The 1139 patients enrolled in the trials were grouped according to catheter placement: subfascial (6 trials), subcutaneous (8 trials), and both (1 trial). Six additional unpublished trials registered at ClinicalTrials.gov were also located. Conclusions: Surgical wound analgesia is a safe technique whose effectiveness has been observed in cesarean sections and hysterectomies performed with Pfannenstiel incisions. Outcomes for other types of surgery are inconsistent. There is a lack of studies of the optimal site for catheter placement as well as of adequate anesthetic concentration and volume(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sabaté Pes, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fustran Guerrero, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dalmau Llitjós, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Presentamos una revisión sistemática de los ensayos clínicos que tuvieron como objetivo valorar la eficacia de la administración de anestésico local con catéter en la incisión quirúrgica, en pacientes sometidos a cirugía abdominal. Método: Selección de los estudios siguiendo los criterios de Jadad. Las variables evaluadas en cada estudio fueron: tipo de intervención y de incisión, tipo, dosis y concentración del anestésico local, sitio de ubicación o localización del catéter, analgesia de rescate, consumo de opioides y la aparición de efectos adversos. Resultados: Se han incluido 15 ensayos con puntuación media de Jadad de 4,6 que incluyen 1.139 pacientes agrupados según la ubicación del catéter: subfascial (6 estudios), subcutánea (8 estudios) y en ambas (1 estudio), y 6 estudios adicionales que están en fase de realización registrados en ClinicalTrials.gov. Discusión: La analgesia incisional es una técnica segura, cuya eficacia se ha observado en cesáreas e histerectomías realizadas mediante incisiones de Pfannenstiel. Los resultados son contradictorios en otras técnicas quirúrgicas. Faltan estudios para conocer la localización óptima del catéter así como la concentración y volumen adecuado(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;58(6): 337-344, jun.-jul. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89948</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Analgesia postoperatoria mediante infusión continua de anestésico local en la incisión quirúrgica tras cirugía abdominal. Revisión sistemática de la bibliografía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7225^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d783^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d783^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d715^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2625^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d783^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d790^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201107</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
