<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042942</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acute cholestatic hepatitis after atorvastatin reintroduction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Consumption of 3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl coenzyme A reductase (HMG-CoA) inhibitors, known as statins, has been associated with elevated transaminase levels but rarely with acute hepatitis. Recently, several cases of acute hepatitis secondary to atorvastatin therapy have been published. We report the case of a 72-year-old man who developed acute cholestatic hepatitis after reinitiating treatment with atorvastatin at a higher dose than that previously prescribed. After treatment discontinuation, the patient made a full recovery, with normalization of clinical and laboratory findings</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hermo, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luaces, C. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Clofent, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro, M. L de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El consumo de los inhibidores de la 3-hidroxi-3-metilglutaril-coenzima A (HMG-CoA) reductasa, conocidos como estatinas, se ha asociado a la elevación de transaminasas y, menos frecuentemente, con cuadros de hepatotoxicidad. Recientemente se han comunicado varios casos de toxicidad hepática aguda por atorvastatina. Presentamos el caso de un varón de 72 años que desarrolló una hepatitis colestásica aguda tras la reintroducción de atorvastatina a una dosis superior a la previamente prescrita. La suspensión del fármaco permitió una total recuperación clínica y analítica</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;29(1): 21-24, ene. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042942</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hepatitis colestásica aguda tras la reintroducción de atorvastatina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33014^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12195^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33014^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12195^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6694^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28561</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6694^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2829^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53500^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
