<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105107</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">External cephalic version in breech presentation: An old but very current technique</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Breech presentation occurs in 3-4% of pregnancies and is a routine indication for cesarean section. The external version is a maneuver that has been performed since Hippocrates&#146; time. Nevertheless, despite decreasing the cesarean section rate, this technique is only offered to a small percentage of patients due to lack of awareness and the shortage of experienced obstetricians. The success rate ranges from 40-74%. Factors that can influence the success of the maneuver are gestational age, the amniotic fluid index, presentation, and the location of the placenta. The use of tocolytics and effective analgesia can facilitate the maneuver and improve the success rate. When a standardized protocol is followed and the technique is performed by an experienced gynecologist, the external cephalic version has an excellent safety profile and is an effective option that avoids surgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guerra, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echevarria, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lopez-Picado, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lete, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Munoz, H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La presentación podálica representa el 3-4% de los embarazos y es una indicación habitual de cesárea. La versión externa se ha realizado en nuestro medio desde tiempo de Hipócrates, sin embargo, pese a la importante opción que representa en el descenso de la tasa de cesáreas, solo se ofrece a un pequeño porcentaje de pacientes debido al desconocimiento y a la carencia de obstetras experimentados. El éxito oscila entre el 40-74%. La edad gestacional, el índice de líquido amniótico, la presentación y la situación de la placenta son factores que pueden influir en el éxito de la maniobra. La utilización de tocolíticos y una buena analgesia pueden facilitar la maniobra y mejorar su porcentaje de éxito. Un protocolo estandarizado de la técnica realizado por un ginecólogo experimentado, logra convertirla en una maniobra con un perfil de seguridad excelente que ofrece a las gestantes una interesante opción para evitar una cirugía (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);39(3): 113-117, mayo-jun. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105107</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Versión cefálica externa en presentación de nalgas: una técnica ancestral muy actual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1971</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23849^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28857^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7922</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15114^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
