<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104160</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Candidemia and invasive candidiasis in the adult: Clinical forms and treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Invasive candidiasis is progressively increasing in frequency as a complication of the hospitalised adultpatient. The availability of new antifungal drugs with lower toxicity and high ef&amp;#64257;cacy has increased thecomplexity of managing of these infections. In parallel, the costs of the treatment of invasive fungal infections have considerably increased. Finding of a balance between the best bene&amp;#64257;t for the patient with theless costs is, nowadays, one of the main objectives of the current recommendations for the management of invasive candidiasis. In this review, the recommendations for the management of candidemiaand other forms of invasive candidiasis (esophagitis, peritonitis, ocular, cardiovascular and osteoarticularcandidiasis, central nervous system and urinary tract candidiasis, and chronic disseminated candidiasis)are analysed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cervera, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La infección invasiva por Candida es una complicación cada vez más frecuente en el paciente adulto hospitalizado. La disponibilidad de nuevos antifúngicos con menor toxicidad y gran eficacia ha añadido gran complejidad al tratamiento de la infección fúngica. De forma paralela, los costes derivados de dicho tratamiento se han incrementado de forma considerable. Encontrar el equilibrio entre el mayor beneficio para el paciente con el menor coste es en la actualidad uno de los objetivos de las recomendaciones en el tratamiento de la candidiasis invasiva. En esta revisión se analizan dichas recomendaciones para el tratamiento de la candidemia y otras como la esofagitis, peritonitis, candidiasis ocular, osteoarticular, cardiovascular, del sistema nervioso central, infección urinaria y candidiasis crónica diseminada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;30(8): 483-491, oct. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104160</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Candidemia y candidiasis invasora en el adulto. Formas clínicas y tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53932^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2207^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2209^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53932^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
