<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91513</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0620</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of health benefits from a nutrition program aimed at inmates with cardiovascular risk factors at Huelva prison</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Diet and lifestyle are important factors in improving cardiovascular health and preventing chronic diseases. Objectives: Assessment of changes brought about in cardiovascular risk (CVR) and metabolic syndrome (MS) after inclusion in a nutritional program. Materials and methods: Intervention, nonrandomized prospective cohort study carried out at Huelva prison in a one year period. Information about quarterly and bi-annual anthropometric and blood biochemical variables was obtained to assess changes in diet. A descriptive analysis with LC 95% and pre-post study was also completed, using T-Student quantitative variables and Wilcoxon test averages. Qualitative testing was performed using the Chi-square test. Results: The sample consisted of 139 subjects, 44 patients were lost in the follow-up study and 95 completed the program. Diet modification took place in 86.3% of the cases. We obtained significant improvements in weight, body mass, fat mass, abdominal perimeter and diastolic blood pressure rate index variables (Table 3). We see a reduction in high and low CVR vs. medium CVR according to features of Framingham and REGICOR (without significance), remaining stable in the SCORE model (Table 4). Conclusions: Health education and proper diet improved anthropometric and biochemical parameters in these patients. This may imply a new tool in the health care repertoire that can be applied to other centres(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Sánchez-Suárez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil-Delgado, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez-Zamorano, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: Es fundamental una alimentación y estilo de vida adecuados para mejorar la salud cardiovascular y prevenir múltiples enfermedades crónicas. Objetivo: Evaluar cambios en riesgo cardiovascular (RCV) y síndrome metabólico (SM) tras inclusión en un programa nutricional. Material y método: Estudio de intervención, prospectivo de cohorte no aleatorizado y realizado en el centro penitenciario de Huelva, durante un año. Se estudió a 139 pacientes, completándose el estudio en 95 internos. Se recoge información sobre variables antropométricas y variables bioquímicas en sangre de forma trimestral y semestral para valorar el cambio de dieta. Se realizó análisis descriptivo de variables, así como estudio pre-post, utilizando en variables cuantitativas la T de Student y medianas con la prueba de Wilcoxon. Cualitativas con el test de X2. Resultados: Se incluyó en el programa nutricional a 139 pacientes. Se modificó la dieta en el 86,3% de los casos. Mejoró significativamente las variables de peso, IMC, porcentaje de masa grasa, perímetro abdominal y presión arterial diastólica Disminuyó el Disminuye el RCV alto y bajo vs RCV medio según las funciones de Framingham y REGICOR, permaneciendo estable en SCORE. Conclusión: La educación para la salud y una dieta adecuada mejora los parámetros antropométricos y bioquímicos de estos pacientes. Además supone una herramienta más para el equipo sanitario que puede ser extrapolable a otros centros(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. sanid. penit;13(3): 75-83, 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91513</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración de los beneficios para la salud conseguidos mediante un programa nutricional dirigido a internos con factores de riesgo cardiovascular del Centro Penitenciario de Huelva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11765^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11765^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16569^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11765^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16573</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201100</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
