<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81343</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of a new diabetic foot risk score in Quito (Equator)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the prevalence of diabetic foot and validate a newulcer risk score. Methods: Using a diagnostic accuracy model design, onehundredpatients were examined to assess the presence of diabetic foot ulcersfollowed by the application of an ulcer risk score designed by SIGN. Each parameterwas given a value to construct a new scale. After an 8-month followupperiod, the presence of new diabetic foot ulcers was recorded to validatethe new risk score. Results: The prevalence of diabetic foot was 11%. Theincidence of foot ulcers was 2%. For the new risk score, the sensitivity was50% and specificity was 97%; the positive and negative predictive values were25% and 99%, respectively; the positive likelihood ratio was 16 and the negativewas 0.52, determining a post-test probability of 55% and 4% for apositive and negative result. Conclusions: The new risk score accuratelyclassifies patients into low or high risk group to develop diabetic foot diseaseand is a simple test to be used in primary health care(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cueva Recalde, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar la prevalencia de pie diabético y validar una nueva puntuaciónde riesgo para úlcera. Metodología: Un modelo de validación deprueba diagnóstica. Se tomaron 100 pacientes para examinar la presencia depie diabético y aplicar la escala de riesgo desarrollado por la SIGN. Posteriormente,se asignaron valores a cada variable del mismo para construir un nuevopuntaje numérico. Se realizó un seguimiento de 8 meses para comprobarel desarrollo de úlcera y validar el nuevo puntaje. Resultados: La prevalenciade pie diabético obtenida al inicio del estudio fue del 11%, y la incidencia deúlceras a los 8 meses de seguimiento fue del 2%. Para la nueva puntuaciónde riesgo, la sensibilidad fue del 50% y la especificidad del 97%, los valorespronóstico positivo y negativo fueron del 25 y el 99%, respectivamente, y elíndice de máxima verosimilitud positivo fue 16 y el negativo 0,52, lo que determinóuna probabilidad postest positiva del 55% y negativa del 4%. Conclusiones:El puntaje de riesgo desarrollado clasifica los pacientes diabéticoscomo de alto o bajo riesgo de desarrollar úlceras en el pie, y constituye uninstrumento sencillo para ser aplicado en atención primaria(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;25(6): 486-490, nov.-dic. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81343</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación de una nueva puntuación de riesgo para el pie diabético en Quito (Ecuador)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3952^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31512^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31512^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
