<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156731</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors related to lack of autonomous mobility during out-of-hospital emergency care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To explore the frequency of lack of autonomous mobility and factors related to it in patients requiring prehospital emergency services. Methods. Cross-sectional, observational, retrospective analysis. We identified a stratified random sample of patients attended by the public health emergency service of Andalusia in 2011. Results. The sample included 280 patients with a mean age of 56 years; 63.9% were men. The majority were attended in homes and streets or other public spaces. Most were transported to a hospital in a mobile intensive care unit. The reasons for calling the service were most often related to chest pain or injuries. Loss of autonomous mobility was seen more often in men, when care was required in a public area, when there were injuries or altered vital signs, and when the patient required transport in a mobile intensive care unit. Dependence on others was significantly associated with the presence of a prior condition before the patient required transport (odds ratio [OR], 3.27; 95% CI, 1.60&#150;6.33), the use of immobilization strategies (OR, 7.71; 95% CI, 1.7&#150;34.96], and the use of ambulance transport (OR, 4.35; 95% CI, 1.63&#150;11.60]. The following 2 variables were at the limit of significance: pain during the care process (OR, 1.13; 95% CI, 0.99&#150;1.29) and age (OR, 0.46; 95% CI, 0.97&#150;1.01). Conclusions. The profile we identified for patients and situations in which patients cannot move autonomously during prehospital emergency care can be used to plan preventive strategies to ensure patient safety (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Trujillo Illescas, Juan Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí, Celia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montero García, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Asencio, José Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Conocer la frecuencia y factores asociados a la pérdida de autonomía para la movilización en pacientes atendidos en emergencias prehospitalarias. Método. Estudio observacional transversal analítico retrospectivo. Se realizó muestreo aleatorio estratificado de pacientes atendidos durante el año 2011 por la Empresa Pública de Emergencias Sanitarias de Andalucía. Resultados. Se incluyeron 280 pacientes con una edad media de 57 años (63,9% hombres). Los lugares de asistencia más comunes fueron domicilios, espacios públicos y la calle. La mayoría de pacientes fueron trasladados al hospital, en unidad de vigilancia intensiva (UVI) móvil. Los motivos de llamada más frecuentes fueron dolor torácico y traumatismos. La pérdida de nivel de autonomía se encontró más en hombres, cuando la atención tenía lugar en lugares públicos, se trataba de traumatismos, había una alteración de los signos vitales o cuando el paciente requería traslado en UVI Móvil. El nivel de autonomía se modificaba significativamente en los casos en los que ya existía una alteración previa de la necesidad de movilidad, con una odss ratio (OR): 3,27 [intervalo de confianza (IC) 95%: 1,60-6,33], cuando se requerían intervenciones de inmovilización [OR: 7,71 (IC 95%: 1,70-34,96)] o de transporte [OR: 4.35 (IC 95%: 1.63-11.60)]. Y en el límite de significación, se relacionó con la presencia de dolor durante la asistencia [OR: 1,13 (IC 95%: 0,99-1,29) y la edad [OR: 0,46; (IC 95%: 0,97-1,01)]. Conclusiones. El perfil identificado de pacientes y situaciones con pérdida de autonomía en la movilización en contexto prehospitalario puede ser empleado como sistema de activación de acciones preventivas que garanticen la seguridad del paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);28(5): 340-344, oct. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156731</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores relacionados con la pérdida de autonomía durante la atención prestada por los servicios de emergencias extrahospitalarias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28845^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50246^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36316</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
