<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049617</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Giant intracranial aneurysms</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. Terminology, concept, pathology and phisiopathology, clinical presentation, imaging diagnosis and treatmentof the giant intracranial aneurysms are reviewed. Development. Saccular, fusiform, dissecting and serpentine giant aneurysmsare discussed. Giant saccular aneurysms are developed from small regular congenital lesions growing far away of theircritical rupture size due to the reinforcement of their wall. Fusiform and dissecting aneurysms are formed after a wide ruptureof some of their wall layers and, therefore, both of them are considered to have some similarities. Finally, serpentineaneurysms are rare lesions and their growing mechanism is still under discussion. Conclusion. Any type of giant aneurysmrepresents a great deal for the neurosurgical management</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-Darder, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pesudo-Martínez, J. V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Wiedermann, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Se revisa la terminología, conceptos, fisiopatología,anatomía patológica, clínica, diagnóstico por imagen ytratamiento de los aneurismas cerebrales gigantes. Desarrollo. Seconsideran separadamente los aneurismas saculares, fusiformes,disecantes y serpentinos. Los aneurismas saculares gigantes seconsideran aneurismas saculares congénitos que crecen mas alláde su diámetro de ruptura habitual gracias a mecanismos querefuerzan su pared. Los aneurismas fusiformes y disecantes se formanpor la rotura amplia de alguna de las capas de su pared y, poresta causa, en la actualidad se consideran conjuntamente. Finalmente,los aneurismas serpentinos son excepcionales y su mecanismofisiopatológico es controvertido. Conclusión. Cualquier tipo deaneurisma gigante constituye un gran reto para su manejo neuroquirúrgico</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;43(6): 357-365, sept. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049617</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aneurismas cerebrales gigantes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23184</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2569^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2569^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2569^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32158</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2569^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2569^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2569^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
