<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128706</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Severe and reversible optic neuropathy by aethambutol and isoniazid</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Ethambutol and isoniazid are antimicrobial agents used to treat multi-drug-resistant tuberculosis. The most commonly recognized toxic effect of these drugs is optic neuropathy, usually manifesting as a decrease in visual acuity, deficits in colour vision and cecocentral scotomas. This study presents the case of a 59-year-old Nigerian woman diagnosed of multi-drug-resistant tuberculosis who developed a severe bilateral optic neuropathy induced by ethambutol and isoniazid. Ophthalmologic examination revealed normal intraocular pressure, normal funduscopic examination and normal biomicroscopy. Automated visual field revealed 360º peripheral constriction and central scotoma. Magnetic resonance images of the brain and orbits were normal. Ten months after suspending treatment, the patient recovered complete visual function. Visual loss is a rare complication that can be related to ethambutol and isoniazid toxicity. Both eyes are usually symmetrically affected with deficits in colour vision and cecocentral scotoma. For successful treatment of visual loss, it is important to make a differential diagnosis between infection and adverse effects of anti-TB drugs. Ophthalmological examination is thus important before and after treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Solanas-Álava, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Martínez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andonegui-Navarro, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Marco, N. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio-Obanos, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ascaso, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El etambutol e isoniacida son tuberculostáticos para la tuberculosis multirresistente cuyo efecto adverso es la neuropatía óptica, con pérdida de visión, alteración de percepción de los colores y escotomas cecocentrales. Se presenta el caso de una mujer nigeriana de 59 años con antecedentes de tuberculosis miliar que desarrolló neuropatía óptica bilateral severa secundaria aetambutol e isoniacida. La presión intraocular, fondo de ojo y polo anterior eran normales. La campimetría mostraba constricción periférica de 360º y escotoma central. La resonancia magnética craneal y orbitaria fue normal. Diez meses tras suspender el tratamiento recuperó la visión con mejoría del campo visual. La toxicidad de los antituberculosos se puede asociar en raras ocasiones a la pérdida de visión. Ambos ojos se suelen afectar de forma simétrica mostrando déficits en la percepción de colores y escotomas cecocentrales. Para establecer el tratamiento de esta pérdida de visión hay que hacer diagnóstico diferencial entre infección tuberculosa y efecto adverso de los fármacos. Por ello es fundamental la exploración oftalmológica antes y durante el tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;37(2): 287-291, mayo-ago. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128706</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neuropatía óptica severa y reversible por etambutol e isoniazida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5069^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5069^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15187^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7705^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27728^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7705^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27728^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27728^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27728^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27728^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12987^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7591</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3270</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
