<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163326</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">More than three hours, less than three years. Safety of anesthetic procedures in children under three years, subject to surgeries of more than three hours</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Food and Drug Administration (USA) warning (December 2016) on the safety of general anesthesia and sedation in patients younger that 3 years and pregnant women has raised many questions about the attitude that should be taken by professionals involved in the treatment of these patients. In view of this situation, the following Medical Scientific Societies: SEDAR, SECP, SECIP and SENeo have constituted a working group to analyze and clarify the safety of these techniques. In the present article, we conclude that at present both general anesthesia and deep sedation should continue to be considered safe techniques because there is no sufficient opposing evidence in clinical studies with humans. Despite this, we should not ignore the problem which must be followed carefully mainly in patients under three years of age undergoing anesthetic procedures longer than three hours or prolonged sedation in Neonatal or Pediatric Intensive Care Units (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Paredes, RM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agustín, JC de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cambra, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vento, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moral, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La alerta de la FDA de diciembre 2016, sobre la seguridad de la anestesia general y las sedaciones en pacientes menores de 3 años y en mujeres embarazadas, ha suscitado numerosas dudas sobre la actitud que deben tomar los profesionales implicados en el tratamiento de estos pacientes. Ante esta situación, las siguientes Sociedades Científicas Médicas: SEDAR (Sociedad Española de Anestesia y Reanimación), SECP (Sociedad Española de Cirugía Pediátrica), SECIP (Sociedad Española de Cuidados Intensivos Pediátricos) y SENeo (Sociedad Española de Neonatología), han constituido un grupo de trabajo para analizar y clarificar la seguridad de estas técnicas. En este artículo concluimos que en el momento actual tanto la anestesia general como la sedación profunda deben seguir siendo consideradas como técnicas seguras, porque no existen evidencias de lo contrario en estudios con seres humanos. Esta seguridad no nos permite ignorar el problema, que debe ser seguido con atención, fundamentalmente en pacientes de menos de tres años, sometidos a procedimientos anestésicos de más de tres horas o a sedaciones prolongadas en las Unidades de Cuidados Intensivos Neonatales o Pediátricos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;30(1): 3-8, ene. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163326</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Más de tres horas y menos de tres años. Seguridad de procedimientos anestésicos en niños menores de tres años, sometidos a cirugías de más de tres horas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13895^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7593^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d788^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9687^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
