<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81410</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of diabetic retinopathy in the city of Badajoz 2002 (Extremadura project to prevent blindness)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To establish the prevalence of diabeticretinopathy (DR), types and risk factors in a diabeticpopulation in the city of Badajoz.Methods: A cross-sectional study, with prospectivedata collection, was performed in 2002 on 762 randomlyselected diabetic patients belonging to twoPrimary Care Centers. We evaluated age, gender,type, treatment, duration of diabetes and bloodpressure levels. Two color fundus photographs weretaken and ophthalmoscopy performed on both eyes.Data were analyzed using SPSS (11.5).Results: The mean age of the patients was 66.2 (DS11.4) years, 4.7% were type 1 diabetics, 29% wereinsulin-treated and 52.8% had elevated blood pressure.Prevalence of DR was 29.8%, macular edema1.4% and proliferative DR 4.8%. Multivariateanalysis showed that patients with an evolution ofbetween 5 and 10 years had a frequency 1.13 timeshigher (ORaj 1.13; IC 95% 0.68-1.88; p=0.648)than those of less than 5 years evolution, while thosewith more than 15 years evolution had a frequency 3.12 times higher (ORaj 3.12; IC 95% 1.85-5.26; p&lt;0.001). Patients receiving treatment withoral antidiabetic agents had an RD prevalence 2.39times higher (ORaj 2.39; IC 95% 1.21-4.74;p=0,012) than those treated with diet only. Patientstreated with insulin had a 10.32 higher frequency(ORaj 10.32; IC 95% 5.07-21.00; p&lt;0.001) thanthose treated with diet.Conclusions: 29.8% of the diabetic population inthe city of Badajoz is affected by DR. Although thisprevalence is lower than that observed in previousstudies performed by the same team, further studiesshould be carried out to detect risk sub-groups toallow us to act to decrease such a high prevalence(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santos-Bueso, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macarro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Vigo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Pérez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer la prevalencia de retinopatíadiabética (RD), de sus tipos y factores relacionadosen una población diabética de la ciudad de Badajoz.Métodos: Estudio transversal sobre 762 diabéticosprocedentes de dos centros de atención primaria,realizado de forma prospectiva en 2002. Se valoraron:edad, sexo, tipo, tratamiento y tiempo de evoluciónde la diabetes y diagnóstico de hipertensiónarterial. Se realizaron dos retinografías por ojo ademásdel estudio oftalmoscópico. Los datos fueronanalizados mediante el SPSS (11.5).Resultados: La edad media fue 66,2 (DE 11,4)años, eran diabéticos tipo 1 el 4,7%, insulin-tratadosel 29% e hipertensos el 52,8%. La prevalenciade RD fue de 29,8%, edema macular: 1,4% y RDproliferante: 4,8%. El análisis multivariable mostróque los pacientes con un tiempo de evolución entre5-10 años tienen una frecuencia 1,13 veces superior(ORaj 1,13; IC 95% 0,68-1,88; p=0,648) y los demás de 15 años 3,12 veces superior (ORaj 3,12; IC95% 1,85-5,26; p&lt;0,001) que los de menos de 5 dilataaños.Los pacientes tratados con antidiabéticos oralestienen una frecuencia de RD 2,39 veces superior(ORaj 2,39; IC 95% 1,21-4,74; p=0,012) que lostratados con dieta. Los tratados con insulina tienenuna frecuencia 10,32 veces superior (ORaj 10,32;IC 95% 5,07-21,00; p&lt;0,001) que los tratados condieta.Conclusiones: La prevalencia de RD en la poblacióndiabética de Badajoz es de 29,8%. Aunque laprevalencia es menor que en trabajos previos realizadospor el mismo equipo de investigación, sonnecesarios nuevos análisis en la población paradetectar la existencia de subgrupos de riesgo quenos permitan actuar para reducir estas elevadas prevalencias(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;82(3): 153-158, mar. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81410</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de retinopatía diabética en la ciudad de Badajoz 2002 (Proyecto Extremadura para prevención de la ceguera)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3954^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
