<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039938</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5187</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Batman dermatitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We describe a case of contact dermatitis to antioxidant amines in an actor who played the rale of Batmen in an adventure park. The lesions coincided with the site of direct contact with the mask of his costume, which resolved when he left his job.    On patch testing he presented a positive reaction to various antioxidant amines (lPPO, CPPO and OPPO) as well as a strong positive reaction to a piece of the mask. The company (Scott Gamble) which had manufactured the mask refused to facilitate its composition. The piece of the mask provided by the patient was insufficient to perform thin-Iayer chromatography which could have confirmed the presence of the allergens to which he was sentisized.    In conclusion we present a new type of allergic occupational contact dermatitis in artists</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gatica, María Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conde-Salazar, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valks, Ruud</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta el caso de una sensibilización a aminas antioxidantes en un actor especialista que utiliza una máscara representado a Batman en su trabajo. Las lesiones cutáneas que coincidían con la zona de contacto directo con la máscara, desaparecían al no trabajar.    En el estudio realizado se observa una sensibilización a diversas aminas antioxidantes (IPPD; CPPD, DPPD) así como una positividad marcada a un trozo de la propia máscara. La casa comercial responsable de la fabricación de la máscara (Scott Gamble) se negó a dar su composición. La parte aportada por el enfermo no fue suficiente para poder realizar una cromatografía capa fina (CCF) y demostrar la existencia de los alergenos a los que estaba sensibilizado.    Se trata de un caso original de eczema alérgico de contacto profesional con una nueva sensibilidad en artistas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. cután. ibero-lat-am;33(3): 109-112, mayo-jun. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039938</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Batman dermatitis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d979^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d592^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30757^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30757^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8569^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
