<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152489</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Behçet's syndrome: literature review and clinical case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Behçet's disease (BD) is a multi-systemic vascular disorder characterized by oral and genital ulcers, as well as cutaneous, ocular, arthritic, vascular, central nervous system and gastrointestinal involvement. It usually affects young adults, and its pathological origin is unknown. The case of a 47-year-old woman with recurrent ulcers in the oral cavity is presented. She linked the pain with sitting and during the sexual act, with vaginal and oral cavity pain, due to the lesions present at those sites, as well as swelling and pain in the knees, making walk painful. The patient was kept under observation and underwent multidisciplinary treatment with prescription of topical and systemic drugs to improve quality of life. Dentists should be aware of BD and the need of multidisciplinary treatment to increase the patient's quality of life (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vieira Caputo, Bruno</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tarquinio Marinho, Kelly Cristine</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Magdalena Giovani, Elcio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Araujo Noro-Filho, Gilberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Enfermedad de Behçet (EB) es un trastorno vascular multi-sistémico caracterizado por úlceras orales y genitales, cutáneas, oculares, artritis, y afectación vascular, sistema nervioso central y gastrointestinal. Por lo general afecta a los adultos jóvenes y la etiopatogenia es desconocida. Se presenta un caso de mujer de 47 años de edad que presenta úlceras recorrentes en la cavidad oral. Ella ha relacionado com el dolor al sentarse, durante el acto sexual, dolor vaginal y oral, cavidad, debido a las lesiones presentes en los lugares mencionados, hinchazón y dolor em las rodillas causando dificultad para caminar. El paciente se mantuvo em observación y se sometió a través de untratamientomultidisciplinariocon la prescripción de produtos farmacéuticos tópicos y sistémicos para mejorar la calidad de vida. El conocimiento del clínico sobre EB ayuda en el tratamento multidisciplinario de promoción de la calidad de vida para el paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;38(2): 105-110, abr.-jun. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152489</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Behçet: revisión de la literatura y presentación de Caso Clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28255^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32942^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32942^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32942^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28255^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28255^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5967^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d904^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
