<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037872</identifier>
<setSpec>0303-8874</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Presentation of a case of cervical actinomycosis versus Hodgkin lymphoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Actinomycosis is an unfrequent bacterian infection, that affects 50% of the cases in the cervical facial region. The evolution and clinical, anatomopathologic radiologic characteristic, and its presentation bring us to suspect another type of more frequent pathology: the neoplastic, that make very difficult its diagnosis. We present the case of a young patient affected by a cervical tumoration initially oriented as Hodgkin lymphoma that finally was diagnosed as cervical actinomycosis and treated with penicillin</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Viscasillas Pallás, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruellas Taischik, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cisa Lluís, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dicenta Sousa, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Doménech Juan, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La actinomicosis es una infección bacteriana crónica poco frecuente que afecta en un 50% de los casos a la región cervicofacial. Tanto su evolución como las características clínicas, anatomopatológicas y radiológicas con que se presenta nos llevan a sospechar otro tipo de patología más frecuente como la neoplásica por lo que su diagnótico suele ser difícil. Presentamos el caso de una paciente joven con una tumoración cervical orientada inicialmente como linfoma de Hodkin que fue diagnosticada finalmente de actinomicosis cervical tratada con penicilina</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Otorrinolaringol Ibero Am;32(1): 23-28, ene.-feb. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037872</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actinomicos cervical versus linfoma de Hodgkin. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2614^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d204^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d204^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2614^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2614^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d204^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11856^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22497^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
