<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74992</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The role of voriconazole in the treatment of emerging mycoses</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Voriconazole is a broad-spectrum antifungal drug belonging to triazoles class.Recently, it has been recommended for the treatment of invasive candidiasis innon neutropenic patients. In addition, this drug has showed clinical efficacyin the treatment of fungal infections caused by Candida species other thanCandida albicans, and also in several other infections caused by less commonfungi, such as Aspergillus terreus, Fusarium and Scedosporium(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guarro, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastor, F. Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El voriconazol es un antifúngico de amplio espectro perteneciente al grupode los triazoles. Recientemente recomendado en el tratamiento de lacandidiasis invasiva en pacientes no neutropénicos, ha demostrado poseeruna buena eficacia clínica en infecciones causadas por especies de Candidadiferentes de Candida albicans, y sobre hongos filamentosos oportunistasemergentes tales como Aspergillus terreus, Fusarium, y Scedosporium, asícomo frente a especies fúngicas de menor incidencia clínica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;24(3): 228-232, 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74992</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El papel del voriconazol en el tratamiento de las micosis emergentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5807^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2207^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35306^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1414^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1237^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
