<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129956</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-6221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acute retinal necrosis syphilitic origin as teh first manifestation of HIV</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Syphilis is a chronic systemic disease sexually transmitted disease caused by Treponema pallidum. It can affect any structure and is known, among others, as "the great imitator". Clinical case. A 29 year old presents with decreased visual acuity (VA) of left eye (LE) of 10 days duration. The fundus (FO) right, presents papilla with congestive blurry edges and OI, yellowish-white chorioretinal lesion in upper hemiretina subrretinianos foci. Acute retinal necrosis suspect OI and started treatment with acyclovir intravenously (IV). Pending results, we appreciate a progression of necrosis and decreased AV. With positive serodiagnosis for syphilis and HIV, she was treated with penicillin G sodium for 14 days, showing improvement in subsequent checks the box (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nevado, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Salvador, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dueñas, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heras, M. E de las</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La sífilis es una enfermedad sistémica crónica de transmisión sexual causada por el Treponema pallidum. Puede afectar a cualquier estructura y se la conoce, entre otras, como &#147;la gran simuladora&#148;. Caso clínico. Varón de 29 años acude por disminución de agudeza visual (AV) de ojo izquierdo (OI) de 10 días de evolución. El fondo de ojo (FO) derecho, presenta papila con bordes borrosos congestivos y en OI, lesión coriorretiniana blanco-amarillenta en hemirretina superior con focos subrretinianos. Sospechamos necrosis retiniana aguda en OI e iniciamos tratamiento con aciclovir vía intravenosa (IV). A la espera de resultados, apreciamos una progresión de la necrosis y disminución de AV. Con diagnóstico serológico positivo para sífilis y VIH, se inició tratamiento con penicilina G sódica durante 14 días, observándose en controles posteriores la mejoría del cuadro (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. oftalmol;4(2): 101-104, abr.-jun. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129956</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Necrosis retiniana aguda de origen sifilítico como primera manifestación de VIH</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24865^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9683^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10592^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24320^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
