<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85246</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Beer and health: benefits for sleep</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In our society, beer is recognized to be a component of the Mediterranean diet and moderate intake of this beverage provides numerous beneficial nutrients. However, in the last few decades, beer has been considered not only from a purely nutritional point of view but also in the context of health promotion. Multiple components contribute to the preventive potential of beer against bone and circulatory diseases and cancer. The present article discusses the possible benefits of moderate beer intake from a new perspective: that of regulating sleep due to the sedative action of hops, one of the components of beer(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rubio, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barriga, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, A. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, C. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cubero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bravo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La cerveza goza, en nuestra sociedad, de una reconocida estima dentro de la dieta mediterránea, su ingesta moderada es fuente de numerosos y beneficiosos nutrientes. Pero desde estas últimas décadas se estudia la cerveza no desde un punto de vista puramente nutricional, sino como herramienta promotora de la salud. Sus posibilidades preventivas, gracias a ciertos componentes, son innumerables contra enfermedades óseas y circulatorias y cáncer. Desde este trabajo y siempre con una ingesta moderada, se quiere abordar el posible beneficio de la cerveza desde una nueva perspectiva: de regular el sueño, gracias a la acción sedante principalmente del lúpulo que posee esta bebida(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;16(3): 160-163, jul.-sep.2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85246</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cerveza y salud, beneficios en el sueño</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13272^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25401^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1534^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32692^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37653</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
