<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147214</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of the tester level of experience on the criterion-related validity and intersession reliability of five different ankle dorsal flexion range of motion measures</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this study was to analyse the effect of the different degree of tester´s experience on the criterion-related validity and the inter-session reliability of the ankle dorsiflexion range of motion measures (ROMADF) obtained from the following tests: passive non weight-bearing test (ADFPAS), weight-bearing lunge test using an inclinometer (ADFLUNINC) and a tape measure (ADFLUN-TAP), modified-weight bearing test with a moveable datum (ADFLUN-DAT) and modified weight bearing test with a box (ADFLUN-BOX). A total of 17 recreational athletes completed this study. Each participant was assessed by 2 testers with different level of experience in the clinical setting (expert and novel) of the ROMADF using 5 assessment tests in two different sessions, with a rest-interval of 72-96 hours. The results showed low validity scores for the novel tester in all the assessment tests except for the ADFLUN-INC test (standardized typical error of the estimate = 0.5 [small] and Pearson coefficient = 0.85 [moderate]; Kappa = 0.74 [good]). The expert tester showed high reliability scores for the ADFLUN-INC, ADFLUN-TAP and ADFLUN-BOX tests and acceptable scores for the ADFPAS and ADFLUN-DAT. The novel tester presented acceptable reliability scores for all the assessment tests except for the ADFPAS, which were considered as nonacceptable. Therefore, we recommend that both the expert and novel testers use the ADFLUN-INC test to: (a) identify subjects with restrained or normal ROMADF and (b) monitor the efficacy of the intervention treatments applied in case of being necessary (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ayala, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cejudo, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santonja, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sainz de Baranda, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Jiménez, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio fue analizar el efecto que el diferente grado de experiencia del examinador tiene sobre la validez de criterio y fiabilidad inter-sesión de las medidas de rango de movimiento de la flexión dorsal del tobillo (ROMFDT) obtenidas en las pruebas: flexión dorsal del tobillo pasiva en decúbito prono y rodilla flexionada (FDPAS), zancada con inclinómetro (FDZAN-INC) y cinta métrica (FDZAN-MET), zancada modificada con taburete (FDZAN-TAB) y zancada modificada con cajón (FDZAN-CAJ). Un total de 17 deportistas recreativos completaron este estudio. Cada participante fue evaluado por dos examinadores con distinto nivel de experiencia (experto y novel) del ROMFDT empleando 5 pruebas exploratorias diferentes en dos sesiones distintas. Los resultados muestran bajos valores de validez para el examinador novel en todas las pruebas de valoración del ROMFDT excepto en la prueba FDZAN-INC (error típico de la estimación estandarizado = 0,5 [pequeño]; Pearson = 0,85 [moderado]; kappa = 0,74 [buena]). El examinador experto presentó niveles altos de fiabilidad inter-sesión en las pruebas FDZAN-INC, FDZAN-MET y FDZAN-CAJ y valores aceptables en las pruebas FDPAS y FDZAN-TAB. El examinador novel obtuvo valores aceptables de fiabilidad en toda las pruebas de valoración excepto en la prueba FDPAS, que fueron considerados como no aceptables. Por lo tanto, se recomienda que tanto los examinadores expertos como noveles utilicen la prueba FDZAN-INC para: (a) identificar a personas con restringida o normal movilidad de la flexión dorsal del tobillo; y (b) monitorizar la eficacia de los programas de intervención aplicados en caso de ser necesarios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;15(3): 123-134, oct. 2015. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147214</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto del nivel de experiencia clínica del examinador sobre la validez de criterio y fiabilidad inter-sesión de cinco medidas del rango de movimiento de la flexión dorsal del tobillo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32075^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29097^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1273^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1721^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d856^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51780^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
