<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74687</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Study of vulvar pathology in menopausal women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Study the pathology of the vulva found in menopausal patients referred to a lower genital tract unit (LGTU).Materials and methods: An observational and descriptive study of menopausal patients with vulvar pathology from the LGTU of Hospital General Universitario de Alicante (Spain), between January 2000 and December 2007. We assessed the more common diseases, lesion type, location, diagnosis and treatment. Results: We evaluated 189 patients (that were older than 55 years). Of these, 68 had vulvar pathology (36%), and lichen sclerosus (46%) the most frequent disease. The treatment most often established was with high-powered steroids (64%),which was also the most effective. Conclusions: The most common vulvar pathology in postmenopausal patients of our LGTU is the lichen sclerosus. Pruritus was the main symptom. High-powered steroids were the most effective treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Escoriza, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saco López, Aránzazu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Fernández, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcos Sanmartín, Josefa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Candela Hidalgo, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esteve Fuster, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diéguez de Benito, Francisco José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudiar la patología vulvar de las pacientes en edad menopáusica remitidas a una unidad del tracto genital inferior (UCTI). Material y métodos: Estudio observacional y descriptivo de las pacientes menopáusicas con patología vulvar remitidas a la UTGI del Hospital General Universitario de Alicante entre enero de 2000 y diciembre de 2007. Se evaluaron las patologías más frecuentes, el tipo de lesión, la localización, el diagnóstico y el tratamiento. Resultados: Se estudió a 189 pacientes mayores de 55 años; 68 (36%) presentaban patología vulvar. El liquen escleroso fue la más frecuente (46%), con prurito como síntoma principal (64%) y localizado principalmente en los labios mayores. El tratamiento instaurado con más frecuencia fueron los corticoides de alta potencia (64%).Conclusiones: La patología vulvar más frecuente en las pacientes menopáusicas de nuestra UTGI es el liquen escleroso, que se presenta habitualmente como prurito. Los corticoides de alta potencia fueron el tratamiento más efectivo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);52(11): 622-626, nov. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74687</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de patología vulvar en pacientes menopáusicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11978^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15246^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22243</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32164^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200911</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
