<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131707</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of genital anomalies in young football players</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of genital examination (GE) during the Pre-participation Physical Examination (PPE) is to identify the state of maturity, and rule out any genital pathology. To describe genital anomalies (GA) and estimate the awareness of GE in young football players. A descriptive, cross-sectional study was conducted in 280 elite football players from the results of PPE over two seasons. There was a detection rate of 5.4% GA, with varicocele being 3.2%, and of which only 13% were aware of their condition. Although this study shows a low incidence  of genital abnormality in the study population, only 13% were aware of the GE priorto assessment. These findings demonstrate a low incidence of GA in this population. While GE is recommended during PPE, it is not a routine practice performed by family doctors or sports medicine specialists. This article attempts to raise awareness of the importance of GE in PPE as a preventive health strategy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Verdugo, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Drobnic, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Avendaño, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Til, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mónaco, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bodell, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El propósito de la exploración genital (EG) durante el examen previo a la participación (EPP) deportiva es identificar el estado madurativo y descartar cualquier enfermedad genital. Este examen, si bien está recomendado, no se hace de forma rutinaria. Describir la prevalencia de anomalías genitales (AG) y la utilidad de la EG en deportistas jóvenes en este ámbito. Se realizó un estudio descriptivo, transversal, durante 2 temporadas, en 280 jugadores del fútbol formativo de elite. Se detectó el 5,4% de AG, siendo el varicocele un 3,2% y de los que solo el 13% era consciente de su enfermedad antes de la evaluación. Se demuestra una baja prevalencia de AG, si bien, los datos dan fuerza a la recomendación de practicar la EG durante el EPP como una estrategia más de salud preventiva, dado que no es una práctica habitual por el especialista en estos exámenes médicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);82(1): e181-e183, ene. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131707</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de anomalías genitales en futbolistas jóvenes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5973^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28588^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50219</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5973^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5973^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5973^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
