<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101461</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish adaptation of the &#147;Mobile Phone Problem Use Scale&#148; for adolescent population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Problematic use of the mobile telephone is an emerging phenomenon in our society, and one which particularly affects the teenage population. Knowledge from research on the problematic use of this technology is necessary, since such use can give rise to a behavioural pattern with addictive characteristics. There are hardly any scales for measuring possible problematic use of mobile phones, and none at all adapted exclusively for the Spanish adolescent population. The scale most widely used internationally is the Mobile Phone Problem Use Scale (MPPUS). The aim of the present study is to adapt the MPPUS for use with Spanish adolescents. The Spanish version of the questionnaire was administered to a sample of 1132 adolescents aged 12 to 18. Reliability and factorial validity were comparable to those obtained in adult population, so that the measure of problematic mobile phone use in Spanish teenagers is one-dimensional. A prevalence of 14.8% of problematic users was detected(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Honrubia-Serrano, M. Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Fernández, Olatz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Freixa-Blanxart, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El uso problemático del teléfono móvil es un fenómeno emergente en nuestra sociedad, que parece afectar especialmente a la población adolescente. El conocimiento acerca del uso problemático de esta tecnología resulta necesario, dado que puede desarrollarse un patrón comportamental con características adictivas. Apenas existen escalas que midan el posible uso problemático del móvil y ninguna adaptada exclusivamente a población adolescente española. La escala más utilizada internacionalmente es la Mobile Phone Problem Use Scale (MPPUS). El objetivo de este estudio es adaptar el MPPUS a la población adolescente española. Se administró la versión española del cuestionario a una muestra de 1132 de 12 a 18 años. La fiabilidad y la validez factorial eran comparables a las obtenidas en población adulta, por lo que la medida del uso problemático del móvil en los adolescentes españoles es unidimensional. Se detectó una prevalencia del 14.8% de usuarios problemáticos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);24(2): 123-130, abr.-jun. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101461</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación española del &#147;Mobile Phone Problem Use Scale&#148; para población adolescente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37717^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37717^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37717^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37717^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37717^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37717^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
