<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77478</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0952</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diterpenes in inflammation: Labiatae as paradigm</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This review is devoted to the antiinflammatory diterpenoids obtained from species of Labiatae. Basically, we study the post-2002 publications concerning the four major structural types in the family: labdane, abietane, pimarane and kaurane. Certain interesting diterpenes derived from plants of different taxonomic origin are also reported. Among the mechanisms involved in the pharmacological effect, we should highlight the inhibition of arachidonic acid metabolism through cyclo-oxygenases and lipoxygenases, and the decrease in the production of NO or cytokines. Additionally, some principles are described as enhancers of the expression of heme oxygenase 1. Some of the botanical genera best represented are Lavandula, Isodon, Rosmarinus or Sideritis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tomàs, Mireia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Máñez, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Esta revisión trata esencialmente sobre los diterpenos antiinflamatorios procedentes de especies de Labiadas. Se estudian las publicaciones posteriores a 2002 referentes a los cuatro tipos estructurales más importantes en esa familia: labdano, abietano, pimarano y kaurano. Además se incluyen algunas moléculas interesantes obtenidas de especies de diferente origen taxonómico. De entre los mecanismos implicados destaca la inhibición del metabolismo del ácido araquidónico a través de ciclooxigenasas y lipoxigenasas, así como el freno a la producción de NO o citocinas. Adicionalmente se ha descrito para algunos principios el aumento de la expresión de hemo-oxigenasa 1. Algunos de los géneros botánicos mejor representados son Lavandula, Isodon, Rosmarinus y Sideritis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. fitoter;9(2): 147-155, dic.2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77478</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diterpenos en infl amación: las Labiadas como paradigma</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35854^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30250^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30250^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35858^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38076^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38078^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36880^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4285^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30165^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35858^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38078^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36880^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4285^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38076^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35854^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
