<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041660</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-1285</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of study to asses the prevalence of caries and related factors in the infant population of Móstoles. We conducted a crossover descriptive in 363 six years old schoolchildren in Schools included in the San Fernando Health Center influence area We conducted a dental exploration using the World Health Organization criteria. Variables such as dental state teeth brushing habits, and social-demographic aspects were collected. Results for year 1997 were compared to those obtained in the same schools in year 1988.The prevalence of caries in 1997 for deciduous dentition is 24.6% and for permanent dentition 1.1%. The non adjusted analysis shows that the schoolchildren revised in 1988 have an OR for suffering caries of 3.48 compared to those studied in 1997. Low social class is also a risk factor for caries OR=1.61(IC95% 1.19-2.17) with respect to median-high class. In conclusion, the prevalence of caries in the infant population of Mostoles has decreased between 1988 y 1997. This reduction is related to an improvement in the social class of the scholars. The frequency of teeth brushing has also improved during this period but is not associated to the decrease in the prevalence of caries in this work (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-García, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tapias-Ledesma, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lamas, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrasco-Garrido, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil de Miguel, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del estudio es conocer la prevalencia de caries en una población infantil de Móstoles y los factores asociados. Hemos realizado un estudio descriptivo transversal en 363 escolares de 6 años de edad, en los colegios de la zona de influencia del Centro de Salud San Fernando (Móstoles). Se realizó una revisión odontológica en 1997 según los criterios de la Organización Mundial de la Salud. Se recogieron variables de estado dental, sociodemográficas y de frecuencia de cepillado. Se compararon los resultados con los obtenidos en la revisión del año 1988 en esos mismos centros escolares. Resultados. La prevalencia de caries en dentición temporal es del 24,6% y en dentición permanente del 1,1%. En el análisis univariante los escolares revisados en el año 1988 tienen un OR de sufrir caries de 3,48 respecto a los revisados en 1997 y los escolares de clase social baja tienen OR de 1,61 (IC95% 1,19-2,17) respecto a los de clase media-alta. Conclusión. La prevalencia de caries ha disminuido en la población infantil de Móstoles entre 1988 y 1997. El declinar de la caries se asocia a un mejor nivel socioeconómico. La frecuencia de cepillado ha aumentado en este periodo pero en nuestro estudio no se asocia con la disminución de la prevalencia de caries (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av Odontoestomatol;21(6): 333-339, nov.-dic. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041660</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución de la prevalencia de caries en una población infantil de Móstoles entre 1988 y 1997</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14489^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9247^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3745^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14489^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3745^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14489^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14489^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3745^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
