<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137950</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">HIV prevalence among individuals having had serology performed in eight spanish cities following heterosexual exposure, 1992-2003</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) epidemic in Spain was characterized throughout the first few years by the predominance of infections among injected drug users (IDU's), but everything currently points to a progressive predominance of sexual transmission. This study is aimed at describing the trend in HIV infection among several heterosexual populations groups and at characterizing the situations in which the infections occurred. Methods: Descriptive study of the individuals who had the test conducted for the first time at nine HIV diagnosis centres within the 1992-2003 period due to high-risk heterosexual exposures, not including injected drug users. Results: A total of 47,870 individuals had serology performed during the period under study. The HIV prevalence among the population under study dropped from 3.2% to 1.0% (p&lt; 0.001). Among the individuals with an HIV infected partners, the prevalence remained at around 10%, the male users of prostitution having dropped from 1.9% to 1.0% (p=0.049); among women involved in prostitution, from 1.4% to 0.7% (p=0.008); and among all other heterosexuals, having dropped from 1.6% to 1.0% among males (p=0.014) and from 1.1% to 0.7% among women (p=0.012). Conclusions: The results indicate advances in the control of heterosexual human immunodeficiency virus transmission, mainly among women, although it is necessary to still continue stressing prevention (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Balaguer, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordoñana, Juan Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pueyo, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, Jorge del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ureña, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáez de Vicuña, Luis María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armas, Carlos de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varela, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castilla, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrasa, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bru, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: La epidemia de infecciones por el virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana (VIH) en España se caracterizó durante los primeros años por el predominio de casos en personas usuarias de drogas inyectadas, pero en la actualidad todo parece apuntar a un progresivo predominio de la transmisión sexual. El objetivo de este trabajo es describir la evolución en la prevalencia de VIH en varios grupos de población heterosexual y caracterizar las situaciones en las que se produjeron las infecciones. Métodos: Estudio descriptivo de las personas que se realizaron la prueba por primera vez en nueve centros de diagnóstico de VIH entre 1992 y 2003 por exposiciones heterosexuales de riesgo, excluyéndose a los usuarios de drogas inyectadas. Resultados: El número de personas en las que se determinó la serología fue de 47.870. La prevalencia de VIH en la población estudiada descendió del 3,2% al 1,0% (p&lt;0,001). En las personas con pareja con diagnóstico de infección por VIH la prevalencia se mantuvo en torno al 10%, en hombres usuarios de prostitución descendió del 1,9% al 1,0% (p=0,049), en las mujeres que ejercen la prostitución del 1,4% al 0,7% (p=0,008), y en el resto de heterosexuales disminuyó del 1,6% al 1,0% en hombres (p=0,014) y del 1,1% al 0,7% en mujeres (p=0,012). Conclusiones: Los resultados indican avances en el control de la transmisión heterosexual del VIH, principalmente en mujeres, aunque todavía se requiere insistir en la prevención (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;78(6): 669-677, nov.-dic. 2004. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137950</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de VIH entre las personas de ocho ciudades españolas que se realizan la serología tras exposiciones heterosexuales, 1992-2003</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23555^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33520</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14904</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
