<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055616</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Organ-confined prostate cancer: treatment with high doses of radioterapy. (Intensity modulated radiotherapy)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To report toxicity and local control in patients with localized prostate cancer, treated with high dose radiotherapy. Materials and methods: The records of 100 consecutive patients with clinically localized prostate cancer treated between june 2003 and may 2006 were reviewed. They received 80 Gy to the target volume with a biphasic technique (3DCRT + IMRT). The median pretreatment PSA was 9. The median follow-up time was 12 months.        Results: Eighteen (18%) developed acute Grade 2 rectal toxicity, and no patient experienced acute grade 3 or higher rectal symptoms. Forty-four (44%) developed acute Grade 2 urinary symptoms while 34% of the patients experienced no GU symptoms (Grade 0) during treatment. Three patients (3%) developed late rectal toxicity grade 2 and eight patients (8%) experienced late urinary toxicity grade 2; any patients experienced more severe symptoms. We recorded biochemical relapse in two patients, both had poor prognostic factors at initial diagnosis of        prostate cancer. Conclusions: The data demonstrate the feasibility and safety of high dose radiotherapy for patients with localized prostate cancer and provide a proof that this method allow safe dose escalation with low severe toxicities to the normal tissues</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Biti, G. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meattini, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, L. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Detti, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Livi, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar la toxicidad local así como la supervivencia de los pacientes con cáncer de próstata tratados con altas dosis de radioterapia. Material y métodos: Entre junio de 2003 y mayo de 2006 100 pacientes fueron sometidos a tratamiento radioterápico por cáncer de prostáta localizado. Se administró una dosis de 80 Gy al target con una técnica de        dos fases (CRT+IMRT). El parámetro medio de PSA fue de 9. La media del seguimiento ha sido de 12 meses. Resultados: Dieciocho (18%) de los pacientes desarrollaron toxicidad GI aguda grado 2 y ningún tipo de toxicidad grado 3 o mayor. El 44% de los paciente experimentaron toxicidad GU grado 2 mientras que el 34% de ellos no experimentaron síntomas GU durante el tratamiento. El 3% de los pacientes desarrollaron        toxicidad GI grado 2 y el 8% toxicidad GU tardías. Ningun paciente experimentó síntomas mas severos. Se registró recaída bioquímica en dos pacientes. Ambos tenían factores pronósticos de alto riesgo en el momento del diagnóstico de cáncer de próstata. Conclusión: Los datos demuestran la seguridad y eficacia de las altas dosis de radioterapia en los pacientes con cáncer de próstata localizado utilizando una escalada de dosis en el tratamiento con bajos        niveles de toxicidad en tejidos normales</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;31(6): 611-616, jun. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055616</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cancer de próstata órgano-confinado: Tratamiento con altas dosis de radioterapia (radioterapia de intensidad modulada)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12279</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30596^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
