<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147725</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of the Spanish version of Parent's Postoperative Pain Management pain scale</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Assessment of postoperative pain is a fundamental aspect of post-surgical care. When surgery is performed as an outpatient, the parents are mainly responsible for the assessment of pain, but they may not always correctly evaluate their children's pain. This makes it necessary to have tools that help them to assess postoperative pain reliably. The Parent's Postoperative Pain Measurement (PPPM) is a behavioral measurement tool of post-operative pain developed to help parents to assess their children's post-operative pain. The purpose of this work was to translate this scale into Spanish, and validate the psychometric properties of the Spanish version of the scale. Method: Participants were 111 children aged 2 to 12 years, who had undergone surgery, and one of their parents. After the operation, the children's level of pain was assessed, and the parents completed the PPPM scale in Spanish. Results: The PPPM items in Spanish showed good internal consistency (Cronbach alpha between 0.784 and 0.900) and the scale scores were closely related to the global pain assessment (Spearman's rho correlation between 0.626 and 0.431). The score on the scale decreased between the day of the operation and the next day, and discriminated well between children undergoing surgery qualified as low/moderate pain and high pain. Conclusions: We conclude that the Spanish version of the PPPM scale evaluated in this study, has good psychometric properties to assess postoperative pain by parents at home (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ullan, AM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perelló, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Planas, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrallonga, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jerez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La evaluación del dolor postoperatorio es un aspecto fundamental de los cuidados posquirúrgicos. Cuando la cirugía es ambulatoria, los principales responsables de la evaluación del dolor son los padres, pero los padres no siempre pueden evaluar correctamente el dolor de los niños. Esto hace necesario disponer de instrumentos que les ayuden a valorar el dolor postoperatorio de manera fiable. La Parent's Postoperative Pain Measurement (PPPM) es una medida conductual de dolor postoperatorio desarrollada para ayudar a los padres a evaluar el dolor postoperatorio de los niños. El propósito de este trabajo fue traducir al español esta escala y validar las propiedades psicométricas de esta versión en español. Método: Participaron 111 niños de entre 2 y 12 años sometidos a cirugía y uno de sus padres. Tras la operación, se valoró el nivel de dolor de los niños y los padres completaron la escala PPPM en español. Resultados: Los ítems de la escala PPPM en español mostraron buena consistencia interna (alfa de Cronbach entre 0,784 y 0,900) y las puntuaciones en la escala estuvieron fuertemente relacionadas con la evaluación global del dolor (correlación Rho de Spearman entre 0,626 y 0,431). La puntuación en la escala disminuyó entre el día de la operación y el día siguiente, y discriminó bien entre los niños sometidos a cirugías calificadas como de dolor bajo/moderado y de alto dolor. Conclusiones: Concluimos que la versión española de la escala PPPM que se incluye en este trabajo tiene buenas propiedades psicométricas para evaluar el dolor postoperatorio en el domicilio por parte de los padres (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);84(2): 106-113, feb. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147725</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación de la versión española de la escala de evaluación del dolor postoperatorio Parent's Postoperative Pain Managament</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10479^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19283^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
