<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041509</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Summary of results in research papers of behavioural sciences</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The main aim of this paper is the application of recent methodological developments in order to write adequately the results section of research papers, particularly in the field of Psychology and other behavioural sciences. Thus, we illustrate some general issues about how the in-formation should be summarized, emphasizing the need to explain in detail the choice of the error measure. The second part of the paper introduces more specific issues, as the adaptation of the error variability with reference to two parameters: the research design and the degree of generalization of the research hypothesis. This paper concludes with an applied example of the above issues, including some brief remarks about the way to add error bars to figures and graphics using a spread sheet program (i.e. Microsoft Excel©)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Catena Martínez, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos-Álvarez, Manuel Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo principal será la aplicación de desarrollos metodológicos recientes de cara a la adecuada elaboración del apartado de resultados propio de los artículos de investigación, atendiendo especialmente al campo de la Psicología y disciplinas comportamentales afines. Para ello, se exponen las generalidades sobre el resumen de información, resaltando especialmente la explicación detallada sobre la elección de la medida de error. En una segunda parte se presentan aspectos más específicos, discutiendo con detenimiento la adaptación de la medida de variabilidad error en función de dos parámetros básicos: el tipo de diseño de investigación y el grado de generalidad de la hipótesis de investigación. El trabajo se cierra con un ejemplo de aplicación de los conceptos expuestos con unos breves apuntes sobre la forma de agregar barras de error a los gráficos a partir de un programa de Hoja de Cálculo, como Microsoft Excel©</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;21(2): 328-338, dic. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041509</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El resumen de los resultados en los artículos de investigación de Ciencias Comportamentales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2488^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2488^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13306</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16136</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32101</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9157^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9157^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
