<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155717</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0952</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Aging skin: the role of herbal medicine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">As a results of the increase of the life expectancy, the impact of aging has assumed an increasingly growing interest. The skin plays a central role, reflecting the first signs of aging such as wrinkles, dry skin, blemishes, loss of luminosity and firmness. To preserve a good appearance, the demand of products with action in their prevention and treatment has increased. In turn, the dermocosmetic has increasingly included in their formulations herbal ingredients that have demonstrated various properties with great interest in this area. This article aims to make an approach to the skin aging subjects as well as to review the benefits of plants algae and their metabolites, including Aloa Barbadensis, Argania spinose, Calendula officinalis, Camelia sinensis, Fucus vesiculosus, Glycine max and Vitis vinifera (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salgueiro, Lígia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alves, Andreia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>pt</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Como resultado del aumento de la esperanza de vida, el impacto del envejecimiento como las arrugas, deshidratació, pérdida de luminosidad y firmeza. A fin de mantener una buena apariencia, ha aumentado la demanda de productos con acción en la prevención y el tratamiento de envejecimiento de la piel. A su vez, la dermocosmética ha incluido cada vez ás en sus formulaciones ingredientes vegetales que han demostrado tener propiedades de interés en esta área. Este artículo pretende abordar no sólo la piel tema de envejecimiento, sino también revisar los beneficios de algunas plantas, algas y sus metabolitos, en particular: Aloe barbadensis, Argania spinosa, Caléndula officinalis, Camelia sinensis, Fucus vesiculosus, Glycine max y Vitis vinífera (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. fitoter;16(1): 33-46, jun. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155717</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Envejecimiento de la piel: el papel de la Fitoterapia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8682^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35969</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24879^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24879^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8682^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35959^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13406</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24879^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26588^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26215^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d507^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3694^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13248^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28628^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
