<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76485</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-5962</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Performance evaluations in the Spanish Public Administration</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper shows the need, not only technical but also legal (Act 7/2007), of carrying outperformance evaluations as a normal human resources practice in the Spanish Public Administration. The article identifies the advantages of not doing this kind of evaluations systematically in the Spanish public administration, as some kind of performance evaluation is somewhat made. Three categories in the performance domain are described &#150;task performance, contextual performance and counter- productive behaviors. Some criteria are also offered with respect to how to proceed with performance evaluation and how to overcome typical measurement errors &#150;both from literature and from the task analysis process. Finally, the paper shows recent meta-analysis outcomes about reliability and construct validity of performance evaluations &#150;an evidence for the existence of criteria, contents and techniques to guarantee good performance evaluations in the Spanish public administrations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gorriti Bontigui, Mikel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo demuestra la necesidad, no sólo técnica sino ya legal (Ley 7/2007, de 12 de abril), de acometer la evaluación de desempeño como práctica común de las actividades de Recursos Humanos en las Administraciones Públicas españolas. Identifica las ventajas de no hacer evaluación de desempeño de forma sistemática ya que, su premisa es que alguna forma de evaluación de desempeño se realiza siempre en las AAPP. También justifica y describe las tres categorías de este tipo de evaluaciones: Evaluación de Tarea, Desempeño Contextual y Contra-productividad, y aporta los criterios para escoger cómo hacerlo, solventarlos errores clásicos de estas medidas, tanto desde el punto de vista de la literatura como desde un proceso más exhaustivo de análisis de trabajo. Por último aporta los resultados más recientes de la investigación meta-analítica que permiten afirmar, con evidencias,que existen criterios, contenidos y técnicas para hacer buenas Evaluaciones de Desempeño en las Administraciones Públicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. trab. organ. (1999);23(3): 367-387, 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76485</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La evaluación del desempeño en las Administraciones Públicas Españolas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10751^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4726^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16701</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31493</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
