<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151205</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Correlates and program completion of family only and generally violent perpetrators of intimate partner violence</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present study examined correlates and program completion rates of Family only violent (FO) versus Generally violent (GV) male perpetrators of intimate partner violence mandated to batterer intervention programs. Probation records of 456 men sentenced to probation in Lake County, Illinois between 2006 and 2008 were examined, and the men were categorized as FO (n= 269) or GV (n= 187) by graduate student raters. GV men were younger, had more extensive criminal histories, greater substance use, and greater demographic risk factors related to education and employment. GV men were less likely to complete a mandated partner abuse intervention program and were deemed by probation officers to be at higher risk to reoffend as compared to FO men, even after controlling for racial differences. These findings highlight the utility of a reliable, easy to administer dichotomous categorization system for probation officers to use to differentiate between FO vs. GV men that had differential correlates and was associated with differential program completion rates. Implications for treatment of partner violent men are discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Goldstein, Daniel A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>O´Leary, K Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cantos, Arthur L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Veborg, Rober</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brenner, Lauren</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se examinaron los correlatos y nivel de adherencia al tratamiento de agresores masculinos de violencia contra su pareja, clasificados como generalmente agresivos (GV) y agresivos sólo dentro de la familia (FO), sentenciados a completar programas de intervención. Se examinaron los archivos de 456 hombres en libertad condicionada en Lake County, Illinois, entre los años 2006 y 2008, y fueron categorizados como FO (n= 269) o GV (n= 187). Los hombres GV eran más  jóvenes, con historiales criminales más extensos, mayor consumo de sustancias y factores demográficos de mayor riesgo relacionados con la educación y el empleo. Mostraron menos probabilidad de completar un programa de intervención obligatorio y mayor riesgo de reincidir en comparación a los hombres FO, aun cuando se controlaron diferencias de raza. Se resalta la utilidad de un sistema de categorización dicotómico, fiable y de uso sencillo para que oficiales de libertad condicionada distingan entre hombres FO y GV con correlatos diferenciados y asociados a distintos niveles de adherencia al tratamiento. Se discuten las implicaciones para la intervención con agresores de su pareja intima (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;23(3): 549-569, 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151205</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Correlatos y adherencia al tratamiento de maltratadores de pareja: agresores generalizados vs. sólo dentro de la familia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53387^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28214</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31499^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53262^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56155^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56155^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56155^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55429^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31499^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31499^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
