<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129689</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Healthy heart: Results of a community education program on cardiovascular health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To improve the knowledge of the population about heart-healthy habits through a training program supplemented by a web site and community activities. Design: A controlled clinical trial with intervention done through participation in the Cardiovascular Health Training Classroom (CHTC) Location: A town of 80,000 inhabitants. Participants: Patients: both sexes, aged 55 to 70 years, with at  least one cardiovascular risk factor (CVRF). Intervention: The intervention group (IG) consisted of patients who participated in the CHTC. Intervention was carried out through a 20-hour presential group course in which a support web site was offered and complementary activities were organized. Classes were taught by three Primary Care nurses. Main measurements: The primary endpoint was knowledge of CVRF. The secondary variables were age, sex, CVRF, lifestyle, visits to health centers, pharmaceutical use adherence, and satisfaction with the program. Results: Data from patients in the first 10 courses (n = 150) were evaluated. A statistically significant improvement was observed in overall knowledge of CVRF in the IG (87.3% to 100%) compared with control group (GC) (84.5% to 92.7%), p&lt;.001, as well as an improvement in physical activity is (IG: 71.2% to 83.1% versus CG: 72.6% to 78.2%), p=.05. The total number of Primary Care visits (medical and nursing) decreased in the IG more than in the CG. The satisfaction rate of the course was very high. Conclusions: This experience is effective in improving  cardiovascular health knowledge and promoting some healthy habits (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llobet Traveset, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz Latorre, Inma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Madridejos Mora, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arce Casas, Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pañart Sánchez, Dani</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Majem Fabres, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Morilla,  Dolors</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puig Acebal, Helena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mercadal Dalmau, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Mejorar los conocimientos de la población sobre hábitos cardiosaludables mediante un programa de formación complementado por una Web y actividades comunitarias. Diseño: Ensayo clínico controlado donde la intervención es la participación en el Aula de Formación en Salud Cardiovascular (AFSC). Emplazamiento: Población de 80.000 habitantes. Participantes: Pacientes, ambos sexos, 55-70  años, con al menos un factor de riesgo cardiovascular (RCV). Intervención: El grupo intervención estaba formado por los pacientes que participaron en el AFSC. La intervención constaba de un curso presencial de 20 h en el que se ofrecía una Web de apoyo y se organizaban actividades complementarias. Las clases fueron impartidas por 3 enfermeras de atención primaria. Mediciones principales: La variable principal fue el conocimiento sobre el RCV. Variables secundarias: edad, sexo, factores de RCV, estilos de vida, visitas a los centros, consumo farmacéutico, adherencia terapéutica y satisfacción con el programa. Resultados: Se evaluaron los datos de los pacientes de los 10 primeros cursos (n = 150). Se observa una mejora estadísticamente significativa en el conocimiento general sobre el RCV en el GI (de 87,3 al 100%) respecto al GC (84,5 al 92,7%), p &lt; 0,001 y una mejora en la actividad física (GI: del 71,2 al 83,1% frente GC: del 72,6 al 78,2%), p = 0,05. El número de visitas totales en  atención primaria (medicina y enfermería) disminuyó más en el GI que en el GC. La valoración del curso ha sido elevada. Conclusiones: Se demuestra la efectividad de esta experiencia para mejorar conocimientos sobre salud cardiovascular y algunos hábitos de vida saludable  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;46(9): 457-463, nov. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129689</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Salut al cor/salud en el corazón»: resultados del programa de educación sanitaria en salud cardiovascular de Mútua Terrassa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52939^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201411</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
