<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84409</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Subachromial syndrome secondary to solitary clavicular osteochondroma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: To comment on the rare causes of a diagnosis as common as subachromial syndrome. Material and method: A young patient presented with several months of pain in the left arm. Subachromial syndrome was diagnosed following the history and physical examination with passive, active and counter-resistance locomotion maneuvers. The study was subsequently completed with plain X-rays, computed axial tomography and magnetic resonance imaging. Results: After the sequential clinical diagnosis of subachromial syndrome, a bone-density image was noted at distal and mid-clavicular level, compatible with an osteophytic bar and/or osteochondral tumor. Following magnetic resonance imaging, images with different signal intensities were observed at posterodistal clavicular level. Conclusions: Subachromial syndrome is too often diagnosed, and although the most common cause of the disorder is mechanical condition of the rotator cuff, more unusual disorders such as osteochondroma may simulate it. This possibility must be taken into account in young patients with scant functional demand and a painful shoulder (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Chaparro Recio, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viana López, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir una causa rara del síndrome subacromial. Material y método: Paciente joven con clínica hombro doloroso izquierdo de varios meses de evolución. Tras anamnesis y exploración física con maniobras de exploración pasivas, activas y contrarresistencia, se diagnosticó de síndrome subacromial que fue confirmado mediante radiografía simple, TAC y RNM. Resultados: Se apreció una imagen de densidad ósea en la clavícula compatible con barra osteofitaria o tumoración osteocondral. En la RNM se apreciaron imágenes con diferente señal en la porción posterior y lateral de la clavícula. Conclusiones: El diagnóstico de síndrome subacromial es frecuente y su causa más habitual es una alteración mecánica del manguito rotador. Sin embargo hay que considerar otras causas más raras como es el osteocondroma, especialmente en pacientes jóvenes con escasa demanda funcional y hombro doloroso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);19(4): 260-263, oct.-dic. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84409</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome subacromial por osteocondroma solitario de la clavícula</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d906^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24821^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32937^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32937^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2992^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24821^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24821^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33758^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33758^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32937^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32937^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33758^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2992^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2992^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2992^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32937^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24821^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24821^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
