<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78310</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-695X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Five key questions on flu: a review of the guidelines</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Flu is an acute infectious disease caused by the viruses A, B and C. It mainly affects the respiratory system and is easily transmitted by secretions and contaminated objects. It has a potential risk of complications, especially in susceptible groups, and is one of the most common causes of work absenteeism. With the aim of updating flu management and collecting information that will help the doctor in decision making, we reviewed the recommendations given in different clinical practice guidelines. We searched the bibliographical databases commonly used internationally and chose those guidelines that based their recommendations on levels of evidence and that had been updated in the last three years. We decided to include other guidelines that do not mention levels of evidence but that are endorsed by internationally renowned scientific societies or institutions. We compared the recommendations given according to five key elements: diagnosis, management in health centres, treatment, advice and information to the general public and vaccination(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Ramírez, Miriam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Téllez Lapeira, Juan Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ponce García, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morena Rayo, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villena Ferrer, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayuso Raya, M. Candelaria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La gripe es una enfermedad infecciosa aguda provocada por el virus de la influenza A, B y C, que afecta principalmente al aparato respiratorio, se transmite con gran facilidad por secreciones y objetos contaminados, presenta riesgo potencial de complicaciones, especialmente en grupos susceptibles, y es una de las causas más frecuentes de absentismo laboral. Con el objetivo de actualizar el abordaje del síndrome gripal y recopilar información que ayude al clínico en la toma de decisiones, revisamos las recomendaciones presentadas en diferentes guías de práctica clínica. Realizamos una búsqueda en las bases bibliográficas habitualmente utilizadas en el ámbito internacional seleccionando las que sustentan sus recomendaciones en niveles de evidencia y han sido actualizadas en los tres últimos años. Decidimos incluir otras guías que no mencionan niveles de evidencia pero están avaladas por sociedades científicas o instituciones de prestigio internacional. Comparamos las recomendaciones presentadas en cinco aspectos clave: diagnóstico, manejo en los centros sanitarios, tratamiento, consejos e información a la población y vacunación(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. clín. med. fam;2(8): 412-425, oct.2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78310</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cinco preguntas clave en la gripe: una revisión de guías</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23109^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10155^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29636</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10155^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23109^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19523^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10159^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10155^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
