<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164202</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-3334</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Families headed by a woman who has actively decided to be a solo mother are increasing in our society. Adoption and assisted reproduction techniques are the ways that majority of women use to get access to lone motherhood, both with a common purpose: to realize their desire for motherhood. The objectives of this study are: (1) to know the social support networks of women who have decided to be lone mothers through international adoption; (2) to explore their vital satisfaction; and (3) to analyze the relationship between social support and life satisfaction. Thirty-eight lone adoptive mothers from Andalusia (Spain) were interviewed. Results show that adoptive lone mothers have a wide social support network with which they feel very satisfied and to which they also admit to need. They have a high life satisfaction. Moreover, it is especially interesting that lone adoptive mothers who are more satisfied with their social support network are also the ones who are more satisfied with their lives. These results are discussed in the light of scientific literature (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morgado, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, M Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las familias encabezadas por una mujer que ha decidido activamente ser madre sin pareja constituyen un nuevo modelo familiar y un fenómeno creciente en la sociedad. La adopción y las técnicas de reproducción asistida son las vías que usan cada vez más mujeres para acceder a la maternidad en solitario, ambas con un propósito común: hacer realidad su deseo de maternidad. Los objetivos de este trabajo son: (1) conocer las redes de apoyo social de las mujeres que han decidido ser madres sin pareja a través de la adopción internacional; (2) explorar su satisfacción vital; y (3) analizar la relación entre el apoyo social y la satisfacción vital. Se entrevistaron a 38 madres adoptivas solas de Andalucía. Los resultados muestran que las madres adoptivas solas tienen una amplia red de apoyo social con la que se sienten muy satisfechas y a la que, además, admiten necesitar mucho. Tienen, por otro lado, una alta percepción de satisfacción vital. Además, y especialmente interesante, resulta que las madres adoptivas solas más satisfechas con su red de apoyo son también las que más satisfechas están con sus vidas. Estos resultados se discuten a la luz de la literatura científica existente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apuntes psicol;34(2/3): 139-149, 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164202</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El apoyo social y la satisfacción vital, factores clave en el caso de las madres adoptivas solas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34568^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9227^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23894^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
