<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152463</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Periareolar reduction mammoplasty: anatomy and clinic of the central pedicle</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and Objectives. Periareolar reduction mammoplasty is a minimally invasive technique. Its main feature is to provide a hidden scar in the areolar margin. We present a study of the central pedicle anatomy, surgical technique, a series of operated patients, and a review of the related literature. Patients and Methods. We used 24 breast, in 12 female fresh cadavers, for anatomical study based on irrigation from branches of the internal mammary artery, which irrigates the mammillary complex and its skin case. The technique involves de-epithelization of a cutaneous segment previously marked around the areola, telescope of the gland from the skin case, resection of the desired breast tissue suturing the remaining wedges, and close of the incision around the areola, obtaining a breast circumference diameter smaller than the initial one. We present first author´s experience in 35 patients operated with this technique. Results. A branch of the fifth intercostal artery was identified in 80% of anatomical cadaveric dissections injected with Microfil®, and a branch of the fourth intercostal artery in 20% specimens, ensuring irrigation of the areolo-mammillary complex and skin case. We identified 35 patients operated with the periareolar technique using the central pedicle, 5 of them (14%) had minor complications without requiring reoperation or hospitalization. The results were adequate. Conclusions. We consider that the technique is safe, with good results if there is an adequate patients selection and if it´s performed by a qualified professional. Our recommendation is in young patients, with elastic skin, nipple-clavicle distance up to 25 cm, and a breast tissue resection of no more than 500 gr (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calderón Ortega, Wilfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lombardi Azócar, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calderón Merino, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Poblete Saavedra, Ángela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camacho Martino, Juan Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes y Objetivos. La mamoplastia de reducción periareolar es una técnica poco invasiva. Su característica principal es el dejar una cicatriz camuflada en el margen areolar. El objetivo del presente artículo es presentar la anatomía del pedículo central en mamoplastia de reducción con incisión periareolar, la técnica quirúrgica, una serie de pacientes operadas, y revisar la literatura al respecto. Pacientes y Método. Empleamos para el estudio anatómico 24 mamas de 12 cadáveres frescos femeninos, basándonos en la irrigación mediante ramas de la arteria mamaria interna, que irriga el complejo areolo-mamilar y su estuche cutáneo. La técnica consiste en desepitelizar un segmento cutáneo, previamente demarcado alrededor de la areola, telescopar la glándula desde su estuche cutáneo, resecar el tejido mamario deseado mediante cuñas que posteriormente se suturan, y cerrar la incisión alrededor de la areola pasando de una circunferencia mamaria mayor a una de menor diámetro. Presentamos además la experiencia del primer autor en 35 pacientes operadas con la técnica descrita. Resultados. Identificamos una rama de la quinta arteria intercostal en el 80% de las disecciones anatómicas realizadas en cadáveres inyectados con Microfil®, y una rama de la cuarta arteria intercostal en el 20% de los especímenes, que asegura la irrigación del complejo areolo-mamilar y del estuche cutáneo. En las 35 pacientes operadas con la técnica periareolar usando el pedículo central, 5 ellas (14%) presentaron complicaciones menores, sin requerir reintervenciones ni hospitalización. Los resultados fueron adecuados. Conclusiones. Consideramos que la técnica de reducción mamaria con incisión periareolar es segura y proporciona buenos resultados si se hace una adecuada selección de pacientes y la realiza un profesional calificado. Se recomienda para pacientes jóvenes, con piel elástica, distancia clavícula-pezón de hasta 25 cm, y con un peso mamario a resecar no superior a 500 gr (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;42(1): 21-28, ene.-mar. 2016. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152463</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mamoplastia de reducción con incisión periareolar: anatomía y clínica del pedículo central</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29995^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9743^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4271^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1965^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8496^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
