<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047785</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-6266</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Platelet aggregation inhibitors and bronchoscopic bleeding</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bleeding during bronchoscopy is a fearsome complication thatcan lead to serious complications during the procedure. Nonetheless,when a review of the literature is performed, bleeding afterbronchoscopic sampling is a relatively infrequent complicationand with few clinical implications in most cases. Recently, somecontroversy has aroused regarding the need for suspending plateletaggregation inhibitors therapy before the performance of thebronchoscopy in order to minimize bleeding risk. In this sense,several publications have been published with diverse and in somecases contradictory information. In this review the main factorsrelated to this complication, the magnitude of the problem, themechanism of action of these drugs and their relationship withbronchoscopic bleeding are documented</dc:description>
<dc:creator>León Jiménez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Polo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Campos Bodineau, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El sangrado en broncoscopia es una complicación temida quepuede llevar a complicaciones serias durante la realización de latécnica. Sin embargo, a pesar del potencial peligro para elpaciente, si se realiza una revisión de la literatura, el sangrado trasla toma de muestras broncoscópicas es una complicación relativamenteinfrecuente y, en la mayoría de los casos, con pocas repercusionesclínicas. Desde hace varios años existe cierta incertidumbresobre la necesidad de suspender o no la toma de fármacos inhibidoresde la agregación plaquetaria antes de realizar una broncoscopiacon objeto de minimizar el riesgo de sangrado. En este sentido,existen diversas publicaciones al respecto con informacióndiversa y, en ocasiones, contradictoria. En esta revisión se recogenlos principales factores relacionados con esta complicación, lamagnitud del problema, el mecanismo de acción de estos fármacosy su relación con el sangrado tras la toma de muestras broncoscópicas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neumosur (Sevilla);18(2): 94-101, jun. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047785</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fármacos inhibidores de la agregación plaquetaria y sangrado en broncoscopia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27769^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2026^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22965^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
