<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-16080</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of median fronto-naso-orbital flap in order to decrease the incidence of complications in patients undergoing craneofacial resection</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND: Resection of malignant neoplasms invading the anterior cranial base is performed with craniofacial resection (CFR) with acceptable results in complication rates and oncologic outcomes. However, still there are series with major morbidity in up to 40% of patients, and mortality of 5%. A retrospective study was performed to evaluate the results in terms of morbidity, mortality, function and aesthetics using a median fronto orbital flap (MFOF). METHODS: The MFOF was used in 28 consecutive patients who presented to the Head and Neck Service from 1992 to 1999, in the Instituto Nacional de Cancerología, Mexico City, and was combined with a superior rhinotomy for en bloc resection of the ethmoid complex in the last 12 cases. 89% of patients had malignant neoplasms. RESULTS: 1 death occurred in this series (3%) and the global morbidity was 35%. Aesthetics and function were good to excellent. Percentages of tumor-free survival for malignant lesions was 76% and 41% at 2 and 5 years follow up, respectively. CONCLUSION: CFR is a safe approach for treatment of neoplasms of the anterior skull base. MFOF mobilization decreases complication rates and gives superb exposure for en bloc resection of tumors invading the ethmoidomaxillary complex specially when combined with a superior rhinotomy. A positive impact on quality of life was obtained (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sanidad y Ediciones (SANED, S.L.)</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedente: La resección de neoplasias malignas que invaden la base de cráneo anterior se realiza mediante resección craneofacial (RCF), con resultados aceptables tanto en tasas de complicaciones, como de resultados oncológicos. Sin embargo, todavía existen series cuya morbilidad se eleva hasta un 40% y en que las defunciones llegan al 5%. Se ha realizado un estudio retrospectivo para evaluar los resultados, en términos de morbilidad, mortalidad, estética y función resultantes de un colgajo óseo frontonasoorbitario (FNO). Métodos: El colgajo FNO fue usado en 28 pacientes consecutivos, que se presentaron al servicio de Cabeza y Cuello de 1992 a 1999, en el Instituto Nacional de Cancerología de la Ciudad de México y se combinó con una rinotomía superior para la resección en bloque del complejo etmoidal en los últimos 12 casos. El 89% de estos pacientes presentaban neoplasias malignas. Resultados: En esta serie hubo una defunción (3%) y la morbilidad global fue de 35%. Funcional y estéticamente, los resultados fueron de buenos a excelentes. Un 76% presentó sobrevida libre de enfermedad a los 2 años, y 41% la mantuvo por 5 años. Conclusión: La RCF constituye un método seguro para el tratamiento de las neoplasias que afectan el piso anterior de la base del cráneo; la movilización de un colgajo FNO hace disminuir las cifras de complicaciones y promete una óptima exposición para las resecciones en bloque de los tumores que invaden el complejo etmoidomaxilar, sobre todo cuando se combinan con una rinotomía superior. El resultado obtenido tuvo un impacto positivo en la calidad de vida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;53(8): 585-596, oct. 2002. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso del colgajo frontonasoorbitario para disminuir la frecuencia de complicaciones en pacientes sometidos a resección craneofacial</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Rivas León, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrillo, JF</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrera, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Celis, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano, AM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-16080</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32935^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5096^s22070</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10095^s22070</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32281</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
