<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102078</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of the apical conformation of root Canals with Mtwo and ProTaper systems</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To assess the ability to preserve the centricity at apical level of the ProTaper and Mtwo rotatory systems in mesial canals of mandibular molars. Methodology: A total of twenty mesial roots from freshly mandibular first molars with two canals for each one and curvatures higher than 20º according to Schneider method were used. The specimens were place in gypsum muffle and then were covered with acrylic. Two cross-sections were perfomerd, the first one at 1 mm and the second one at 3 mm form the end of the radicular canal. The root were divided in two groups of 20 canals each one: Group 1(G1) was instrumented with ProTaper System and group 2 (G2) was instrumented with Mtwo System. The ability to maintain the centrality of each system was determined by the centricity ratio calculus. Results: The centricity ratio was evaluated through an analysis of variance that in absolute values showed significant defferences between the two methods in both cross-sections, being Mtwo system more efficient than Pro Taper system (p&lt;0,01). Conclusions: Because the two instrumentation systems compared are manufactured by a similar alloy, the behavioral differences between each system can be attributed to the instrumentation technique used and/or to differences in the design of each one of them. Under the conditions of this study none of the two systems scrupulously respected the centricity of the canal showing Mtwo a better performance than ProTaper (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Coaguila Llerena, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balandrano Pinal, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hilú, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la capacidad de conservar la centricidad a nivel apical de los sistemas rotatorios ProTaper y Mtwo en conductos mesiales de molares inferiores. Metodología: Se emplearon 20 primeros molares inferiores recientemente extraídos con curvaturas superiores a los 20º de acuerdo al método de Schneider. Los especímenes fueron colocados individualmente en muflas de yeso y cubiertos con acrílico de autocurado y se realizaron dos cortes transversales a 1 mm del final del conducto radicular, corte 1 y el otro a 3 mm, corte 2. Un grupo de 20 conductos (G1) se instrumentó con el sistema ProTaper y el otro grupo de 20 conductos (G2) se instrumentó con el sistema Mtwo. La calidad de cada sistema para permanecer centrado en el conducto radicular fue determinada mediante el cálculo del cociente de centricidad. Resultados: Se evaluó el cociente de centricidad, mediante un análisis de varianza, que en valores absolutos, mostró diferencias significativas entre ambos métodos para ambos cortes, siendo el sistema Mtwo más eficiente en ambos casos que el Protaper (p&lt;0,01). Conclusiones: Debido a que los dos sistemas se pueden atribuir a la técnica de instrumentación empleada y/o a las diferencias en el diseño de cada uno de ellos. Bajo las condiciones de este estudio ninguno de los dos sistemas respetó escrupulosamente la centricidad del conducto radicular mostrando Mtwo un mejor comportamiento que ProTaper (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);28(4): 220-227, oct.-dic. 2010. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102078</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la conformación apical de los conductos radiculares con los Sistemas Mtwo y Protaper</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3776^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8602^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32617^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
