<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96178</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4466</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Social-sanitary situation in Marañon&#146;s work in the context of the fight against infectious diseases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Gregorio Marañón y Posadillo (1887-1960), played a leading role in the birth of Endocrinologyin Spain as is well known. However, his medical work included other important and significant fields.Thus, it was specially in the 1910s and 1920s, when Marañón dealt with the social-sanitary situationin Madrid probably due to his professional attachement to the treatment of several infectious diseasesand epidemic outbreaks. Actually, since 1911 onwards, he was in charge of the wards of infectiousdiseases in the Hospital General de Madrid where he had the opportunity of treating an importantnumber of patients suffering from this type of pathology and, as a consequence, in the following yearshe published several articles in medical journals and presented, in the Royal Academy of Medicine inSpain, some reports on infectious diseases and the Spanish health and social conditions at the time.This paper try to analyze this field of Marañón&#146;s social and scientific activity(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Vega, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Como es conocido, Gregorio Marañón y Posadillo (1887-1960), jugó un papel fundamental enel nacimiento de la Endocrinología en España. Sin embargo, su trabajo médico también se centróen otros importantes campos. Fue, sobre todo, en la década de 1910 y 1920, cuando Marañón centrósu atención en la situación sociosanitaria de Madrid, probablemente relacionada con su vinculaciónprofesional al tratamiento de las enfermedades infecciosas puesto que desde 1911 se hizocargo de la Sala de Enfermedades Infecciosas del Hospital General del Madrid, donde tuvo laoportunidad de tratar a este tipo de enfermos. Como consecuencia de su preocupación por la etiologíasocial de enfermedades de prevalencia excesiva o de los brotes epidémicos, en los años siguientes,publicó diversos artículos especializados y presentó comunicaciones en la Real AcademiaNacional de Medicina acerca de estas cuestiones vinculadas a la situación sociosanitaria del país.Este trabajo trata de estudiar este aspecto menos conocido de la obra de Gregorio Marañón(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Asclepio;63(2): 477-506, jul.-dic. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96178</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La cuestión sociosanitaria en la obra de Marañón en el contexto de la lucha contra las enfermedades infecciosas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13319^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28582^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4782^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6935^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
