<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056998</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-5981</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Wearing away of hip arthroplasties</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Revision of a prosthesis may be due to different causes    requiring specific treatments. The fundamental factor is    the type of implant fixation involved. The cement and its    method of use influence the good results presently    obtained.    A classification is required of femoral radiographic loosening    - the best known being the classification proposed by    Harris and Johnston for cemented stems, and the Engh    classification for non-cemented stems. There is no general    technique for application to all cases with the same possibilities    of good results. Acetabular and femoral reconstruction    surgery should be indicated by the surgeon according    to the observed periprosthetic osteolysis and patient    symptoms</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Murcia Asensio, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murcia Mazón, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez Suárez, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrero Manzanal, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La revisión de una prótesis puede sere debida a diferentes    causas que requieren tratamientos específicos. El factor    fundamental es el tipo de fijación del implante. El cemento    y su forma de utilización influyen en los buenos resultados    actuales.    Es necesario adoptar una clasificación de los aflojamientos    radiográficos femorales, siendo las más conocidas las    propuestas por Harris y Johnston para los vástagos    cementados y la de Engh para los no cementados.    No hay una técnica general que pueda aplicarse a todos    los casos con las mismas posibilidades de buenos resultados.    La cirugía de reconstrucción acetabular y femoral, la    debe indicar el cirujano según la osteolisis periprotésica y    los síntomas del enfermo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Patol. apar. locomot. Fund. Mapfre Med;5(supl.1): 12-21, 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056998</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aflojamiento de las artroplastias de cadera</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33577^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28996</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5373^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d81^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19574</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6780^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
