<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055210</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Improvement of metabolic control after resolution of chronic periodontitis in a woman with type 2 diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In general, infectious diseases are more frequent in diabetic patients    than in the general population. This increased risk is related    among other factors with a bad metabolic control. Chronic periodontitis,    the most common variety of periodontal disease, is more    frequent in diabetic patients than in non-diabetic subjects and its    clinical presentation and progression is more severe. The current    clinical case describes a woman with type 2 diabetes and poor    chronic metabolic control, although different insulin regimes were    used and even high insulin doses were employed. The patient was    referred to a maxillo-facial surgeon to evaluate a chronic periodontal    disease. The resolution of this was crucial for the improvement    of metabolic control. Periodontal disease induces a low-grade inflammation    with possible systemic consequences. Deficient metabolic    control in diabetic patients may accelerate the progression of    a current periodontitis. Additionally, as shown with the reported    case, periodontitis may contribute to a sustained poor metabolic    control, which in itself may also deteriorate the progression of the    periodontal disease</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pascual, J. V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferri, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ampudia-Blasco, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carmen, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las infecciones, en general, ocurren con mayor frecuencia en los    pacientes con diabetes que en la población general. Este exceso de    riesgo se relaciona, entre otros factores, con el mal control metabólico.    La periodontitis crónica -la forma más habitual de enfermedad periodontal- es más frecuente en pacientes diabéticos que en sujetos    no diabéticos, y tiene una presentación y una evolución más    graves cuando se asocia a dicha patología. El caso clínico que presentamos    corresponde al de una paciente con diabetes tipo 2 y mal    control metabólico crónico a pesar de la utilización de diversas pautas    de tratamiento insulínico y del empleo de dosis altas de insulina.    La paciente fue remitida al cirujano maxilofacial para la evaluación    de un cuadro de enfermedad periodontal crónica cuya resolución    fue clave para conseguir la mejora del control metabólico. La enfermedad    periodontal induce una situación de inflamación de bajo grado    con posibles repercusiones sistémicas. El mal control glucémico    en pacientes con diabetes puede acelerar la progresión de una periodontitis    ya existente. Adicionalmente, y tal como demuestra el caso    presentado, la periodontitis puede contribuir al mantenimiento de    un control metabólico deficiente, situación que, a su vez, puede    agravar también la progresión de la enfermedad periodontal</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;23(2): 141-144, mar.-abr. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055210</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mejora del control metabólico tras la resolución de un cuadro de periodontitis crónica en una mujer con diabetes tipo 2</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8862^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30157^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10709^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
