<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143039</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Percutaneous electric neurostimulation of dermatome T7 improves glycemic profile in obese and type 2 diabetic patients. A randomized clinical study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Endocrine pancreatic segregation is regulated by the autonomic nervous system. The parasympathetic system stimulates insulin production by the beta cells and inhibits the adrenergic discharge by the sympathetic nervous system. The aim of this study was to evaluate the effect of percutaneous neurostimulation (PENS) of dermatome T7, generating a somato-autonomic reflex, whose efferent pathway are the vagal branches that specifically stimulate the pancreas. The effect of this treatment on glycemia, insulin secretion and insulin resistance was investigated. Methods: A prospective randomized clinical trial was performed. Patients with Body Mass Index &amp;#8805; 30 kg/m2 and diagnosis of diabetes mellitus treated with Metformin were included. Patients were divided into 2 groups: Patients undergoing PENS of dermatome T7 (12 sessions of 30 minutes weekly) associated with a 1,200 Kcal/day diet (Group 1) and patients following only a 1,200 Kcal/day diet (Group 2). All the patients underwent a blood sample extraction before the treatment and 7 days after finishing it. Results: 60 patients were included: 30 in each group. After finishing the treatment, in Group 1 a significant decrease in glycemia (Mean decrease of 62,1 mg/dl; P = .024) and HOMA (Mean decrease 1.37;P = .014) was observed. In Group 2, no significant differences between pre and post-treatment values were observed. Conclusion: PENS of dermatome T7 associated with a 1,200 Kcal/day diet achieves a greater reduction in glycemia and insulin resistance than with diet exclusively after 3 months of treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calpena, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diez, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llavero , Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zubiaga, Lorea</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Tovar, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La secreción endocrina pancreática está regulada por el sistema nervioso autónomo. El sistema parasimpático estimula la producción de insulina por las células beta e inhibe la liberación adrenérgica por el sistema nervioso simpático. El objetivo del presente estudio es evaluar el efecto de la neuroestimulación percutánea (PENS) del dermatoma T7, creándose un reflejo somato-autonómico, cuya vía eferente serán las ramas del nervio vago que estimulan específicamente el páncreas. Se analizará el efecto de este tratamiento sobre la glucemia, la secreción de insulina y la resistencia a la acción de la insulina. Métodos: Estudio prospectivo aleatorizado en el que se incluyeron pacientes con Índice Masa Corporal &amp;#8805; 30 kg/m2 y diagnóstico de diabetes mellitus en tratamiento con metformina. Los pacientes fueron aleatorizados en 2 grupos: pacientes sometidos a PENS del dermatoma T7 (12 sesiones de 30 min semanales) asociado a dieta de 1.200 Kcal/día (grupo 1) y pacientes que seguían una dieta de 1.200 Kcal/día exclusivamente (grupo 2). A todos los pacientes se les realizó una analítica sanguínea en ayunas antes de empezar el tratamiento y a los 7 días de finalizarlo. Resultados: Se incluyeron 60 pacientes: 30 pacientes en cada grupo. Al finalizar el tratamiento en el grupo 1 se observa un descenso significativo en la glucemia (descenso medio de 62,1 mg/dl; p = 0,024) y en el HOMA (descenso medio 1,37; p = 0,014). En el grupo 2 no se observan diferencias significativas en los valores pre y postratamiento. Conclusión: La PENS del dermatoma T7 asociada a dieta de 1.200 Kcal/día produce una mayor reducción de la glucemia y de la resistencia insulínica que la obtenida solo mediante dieta tras 3 meses de tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);93(7): 460-465, ago.-sept. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143039</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La neuroestimulación eléctrica percutánea del dermatoma T7 mejora el perfil glucémico en pacientes obesos y diabéticos tipo 2. Estudio clínico aleatorizado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28246^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29646</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37656</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
