<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90457</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The evolving concept of treatment-resistant schizophrenia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Schizophrenia is a chronic disease of body and mind that affects 1% of the population. The existence of the person with schizophrenia should be understood, at least, with two perspectives: one considering the integration of the individual into the social community, another which includes the understanding that there is a patient with a medical problem treatable with medications and psychotherapies. There is a large group of patients with &#145;treatment-resistant schizophrenia,&#148; that is, cases in which a minimum degree of remission with conventional treatments is not obtained. These cases have pointed to the fact that even today we still lack an integrative treatment model obtained through the assembling of specific interventions with verifiable effectiveness. The concept of treatment-resistant schizophrenia should have evolved in accordance with the advancing of the currently available knowledge and therapeutic resources. Why hasn&#146;t this happened? This article reviews the history of the concept of &#147;resistance&#148; to account for such failure and proposes a methodological approach to overcome this stagnation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barbudo del Cura, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Ibor, María I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Ibor, Juan J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintero, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La esquizofrenia es una enfermedad crónica del cuerpo y de la mente que afecta al 1% de la población. La existencia de la persona con esquizofrenia debe ser entendida, por lo menos, con dos perspectivas: una, la que contempla su integración en la comunidad social; otra, la que entiende que hay un paciente con un problema de salud tratable con medicinas y con psicoterapias. Hay un grupo numeroso de pacientes con presentaciones &#145;resistentes&#146; de la esquizofrenia, es decir: casos en los que no se obtiene un grado mínimo de remisión con los tratamientos convencionales. Estos casos dejan en evidencia el hecho de que todavía hoy carecemos de un modelo de tratamiento integrador que esté armado a partir de intervenciones específicas cuya eficacia sea verificable. El concepto de &#145;esquizofrenia resistente&#146; debería haber evolucionado a la par que los conocimientos y los recursos terapéuticos que hoy tenemos. ¿Por qué no ha ocurrido? Este artículo revisa la historia del concepto de &#145;resistencia&#146; para dar cuenta de tal fracaso y proponer perspectivas metodológicas que nos saquen del estancamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;39(4): 236-250, jul.-ago. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90457</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La evolución del concepto de Esquizofrenia Resistente al Tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10546^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10788</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22164</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
