<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103029</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Respiratory and hemodynamic changes during lung recruitment maneuvering through progressive increases and decreases in PEEP level</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the respiratory and hemodynamic changes during lung recruitment maneuvering (LRM) through stepwise increases and decreases in PEEP level. Design and setting: A retrospective study in a 17-bed ICU was carried out. Patients: Twenty-one patients with acute respiratory failure and bilateral pulmonary infiltration. Intervention: LRM was carried out, consisting of stepwise increases in PEEP (4cmH2O every 3minutes), with fixed ventilation pressure, until reaching a maximal value of 36cmH2O PEEP (ascending branch), followed by progressive decreases in PEEP (2cmH2O every 3minutes) until establishing the open-lung PEEP at the value associated to maximum respiratory compliance (Crs) (descending branch). Continuous hemodynamic monitoring was performed using an esophageal echodoppler probe. Results: Crs gradually decreased in the ascending branch of the LRM, and progressively increased surpassing the initial value after establish the open-lung PEEP in the descending branch, reducing the ventilation pressure and increasing the SpO2/FiO2 ratio. Hemodynamic changes primarily consisted of a fall in cardiac output and left ventricular preload, together with an increased heart rate and cardiac contractility. At comparable levels of PEEP and mean airway pressure, these changes were more pronounced during the descending branch of the LRM. Conclusions: 1) LRM increased Crs, improving oxygenation and decreasing ventilation pressure; 2) the main hemodynamic consequence was the drop in cardiac output and left ventricular preload; and 3) the unequal hemodynamic derangement in both branches, at the same level of PEEP and mean airway pressure, showed that, along with intrathoracic pressure, other factor such as Crs and hypercapnia may have influenced the hemodynamic consequences of this type of LRM (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gil Cano, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gracia Romero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monge García, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Monrové, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudiar los cambios respiratorios y hemodinámicos durante una maniobra de reclutamiento pulmonar (MRP) mediante incrementos y decrementos progresivos de PEEP. Diseño y ámbito: Estudio retrospectivo en una UCI de 17 camas. Pacientes: Un total de 21 pacientes con insuficiencia respiratoria aguda e infiltrados pulmonares bilaterales. Intervención: MRP consistente en incrementos progresivos de PEEP (4cmH2O cada 3 minutos), con presión de ventilación fija, hasta alcanzar un valor máximo de 36cmH2O de PEEP (rama ascendente), seguida de decrementos progresivos (2cmH2O cada 3 minutos) hasta establecer la PEEP de apertura en el valor asociado a la máxima distensibilidad del sistema respiratorio (Dsr) (rama descendente). La monitorización hemodinámica se realizó de forma continua con una sonda ecodoppler esofágica. Resultados: La Dsr disminuyó gradualmente en la rama ascendente de la MRP y aumentó de forma progresiva superando el valor inicial al establecer la PEEP de apertura en la rama descendente, reduciéndose la presión de ventilación y aumentando la relación SpO2/FiO2. Los cambios hemodinámicos consistieron fundamentalmente en una disminución del gasto cardiaco y de la precarga del ventrículo izquierdo, junto con un aumento de la frecuencia y de la contractilidad cardiaca. A niveles equiparables de PEEP y presión media en vía aérea, estos cambios fueron más intensos durante la rama descendente. Conclusiones: 1) La realización de la MRP incrementó la Dsr mejorando la oxigenación y disminuyendo la presión de ventilación; 2) la principal consecuencia hemodinámica fue la disminución del gasto cardiaco y de la precarga ventricular izquierda; 3) la afectación hemodinámica desigual en ambas ramas, a niveles equiparables de PEEP y presión media en vía aérea, puso de manifiesto que, junto a la presión intratorácica, otros factores como la Dsr y la hipercapnia pudieron influir en las consecuencias hemodinámicas en este tipo de MRP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);36(2): 77-88, mar. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103029</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambios respiratorios y hemodinámicos durante una maniobra de reclutamiento pulmonar mediante incrementos y decrementos progresivos de PEEP</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2346^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12563</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53505^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6590^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38345^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9183^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
