<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163640</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychometric properties of Goldberg&#146;s General Health Questionnaire  - GHQ-28 - in informal primary caregivers of cancer patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine the psychometric properties of Goldberg&#146;s General Health Questionnaire -GHQ-28- in a sample of Mexican primary caregivers of cancer patients. Method: Two hundred and seventy six caregivers participated in this protocol, 205 of which were women (74.3%) and 71 were men (25.7%). Participants answered the GHQ-28 and the Beck Depression Inventory (BDI) concurrently. Results. The internal consistency of the overall scale showed a satisfactory index (&amp;#945; =0.91). The Cronbach alphas of the subscale had a value of &amp;#945; =.86, &amp;#945; =.76, explaining the 53.42% of the variance. The correlation validity by BDI showed significant outcomes (Pearson r=0.723 - 0.427, p&lt;0.05). Conclusions. The relevance of the outcomes is that this is a population that can show damages in the overall health throughout the process of care for cancer patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rivera-Fong, Liliana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera Gómez, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meneses García, Abelardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suchil Bernal, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar Ponce, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrera Galeana, Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galindo Vázquez, Oscar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar las propiedades psicométricas del Cuestionario de Salud General de Goldberg -GHQ-28-, en una muestra de cuidadores primarios informales mexicanos de pacientes con cáncer. Método. Participaron 276 cuidadores de los cuales 205 fueron mujeres (74,3%) y 71 hombres (25,7%). Los participantes contestaron concurrentemente el GHQ-28 y el Inventario de Depresión de Beck BDI. Resultados. La consistencia interna de la escala global mostró un índice satisfactorio (&amp;#945;= 0,91). Las alfas de Cronbach de las sub-escalas tuvieron un valor de &amp;#945;=0,86, a &amp;#945;=0,76 que explicaron el 53,42% de la varianza. La validez concurrente con el BDI mostró resultados significativos (r de Pearson de 0,72 a 0,427, p&lt;0,05). Conclusiones. La relevancia de los resultados obtenidos radica en que se trata de una población que puede llegar a presentar afectaciones en la salud en general a lo largo del proceso de cuidado de los pacientes oncológicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);14(1): 71-81, ene.-jun. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163640</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Propiedades psicométricas del cuestionario general del salud de Goldberd - QHQ-28 - en cuidadores primarios informales de pacientes con cáncer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32195^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6858^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
