<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138140</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Uterine intravenous leiomyomatosis. Report of a case with fallopian tube and ovarian affectation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Intravenous leiomyomatosis is a rare variant of leiomyoma characterized by the growth of smooth muscle cells inside the lumen of either uterine venous or lymphatic vessels. Its histogenesis is not clarified. In spite of being a benign tumor, its behaviour could be considered as malignant because it can extend by intracava and intracardiac way, although the prognosis is favourable. Patients and methods: A case of a 39 years old female with an abdominal mass clinically depending of right adnexa is reported. An abdominal hysterectomy with bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy was performed. Results: Grossly, an adnexal mass including a bulky surface ovarian tumor and a nodular fallopian tube wall together with a deformed uterus by the presence of multiple nodules were found. Histologically, adnexal tumor consisted of interlacing bundles of spindle-shaped cells and numerous vessels within intraluminal tumor. Discussion and conclusions: Most of the reported cases showed uterine involvement expanding to the cava and intracardiac cavities. Eventually, lung metastases were reported. Fallopian tube and ovarian involvement found in this case are quite unusual. Immunohistochemical analyses demonstrated the vascular nature of the lumina containing tumor extensions. Positivity for estrogen and progesterone receptors also supports the hypothesis about its origin from uterine smooth muscle instead of vascular walls (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Atienza Cuevas, Lidia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palomo González, M. a Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerrero Cauqui, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Añón Requena, M. a José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La leiomiomatosis intravenosa es una variante rara del leiomioma que se caracteriza por un crecimiento intraluminal de células musculares lisas en las venas o vasos linfáticos uterinos. Su histogénesis no está aclarada. A pesar de ser un tumor benigno, su comportamiento podría ser considerado como maligno debido a que puede extenderse por vía intracava e intracardíaca, aunque el pronóstico es bueno. Pacientes y métodos: Presentamos un caso en una paciente de 39 años con una masa abdominal dependiente del anejo derecho. Se realizó una histerectomía con doble anexectomía. Resultados: Macroscópicamente la masa ovárica se correspondía con una tumoración de superficie abollonada, con nódulos paratubáricos y útero deformado por la presencia de varios nódulos uterinos. Microscópicamente correspondía a un tumor constituido por células fusiformes dispuestas en haces entrecruzados y numerosos vasos en los cuales se introducía el tumor. Discusión y conclusiones: La mayoría de los casos descritos presentan afectación uterina con extensión a la vena cava e intracardíaca y eventualmente metástasis pulmonares, siendo muy rara la afectación paratubárica y ovárica que presentamos en nuestro caso. Las técnicas de inmunohistoquímica demuestran la naturaleza vascular de las luces en las cuales se introduce el tumor, y su positividad a los estrógenos y progesterona apoya la hipótesis de su origen en el músculo liso uterino, y no en la pared de los vasos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;38(4): 238-241, oct.-dic. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138140</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Leiomiomatosis intravenosa uterina. Presentación de un caso con afectación paratubárica y ovárica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8069^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31364^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8069^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7225^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7991^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37781^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24352^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31364^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15000^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10229^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10230^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24352^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
