<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87462</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-2597</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Right aortic arch associated to Kommerell's diverticulm and aberrant left subclavian artery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The vascular rings represent less than 1% of all congenital cardiovascular malformations and only between 1% and2% of children with another type of cardiac malformation will have an associated vascular ring. In spite of its rareness, knowledge about it is very interesting since they may be the cause of recurrent digestive or respiratory symptoms associated to aberrant left subclavian artery that are resistant to conventional treatments. We present two new cases of rightaortic arch associated to left aberrant artery arising from Kommerell's diverticulum, one of the rarest variants of vascular ring whose anatomic and clinical characteristics give special interest to this type of vascular malformation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Ramos, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lapeña López de Armentía, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Fernández, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrero de la Mano, LJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Sánchez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los anillos vasculares representan menos del 1% de todas las malformaciones congénitas cardiovasculares y solamente entre un 1-2% de niños con otro tipo de malformaciones cardiacas tendrá asociado un anillo vascular. A pesar de su rareza su conocimiento resulta de gran interés ya que pueden ser causa de síntomas digestivos o respiratorios de repetición rebeldes a tratamientos convencionales. Presentamos dos nuevos casos de arco aórtico derecho asociado a arteria subclavia izquierda aberrante originada del divertículo de Kommerell, una de las variantes más infrecuentes de anillo vascular cuyas peculiaridades anatómicas y clínicas dotan de especial de interés a este tipo de malformación vascular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Bol. pediatr;49(209): 266-268, jul.-sept. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87462</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Arco aórtico derecho asociado a arteria subclavia izquierda aberrante y divertículo de Kommerell</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1018^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1018^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30319^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13736^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
