<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59311</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Annual review of Archives in Interventional Pneumology, Interstitial Diseases and Lung Transplantation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A review has been made of original articles on invasive pneumology techniques, interstitial diseases andlung transplantation, published in the ARCHIVOS DE BRONCONEUMOLOGÍA during the year 2008. We have selectedthe publication by Martínez-Olondrins et al on the mediastinal staging of bronchogenic carcinoma by«blind» transbronchial needle aspiration to highlight the role of this simple, safe and cost-effectivetechnique at a time when aspiration by ultrasound-guided bronchoscopy is profiled as an alternative tostaging by mediastinoscopy. Besides its usefulness in the study of lymph nodes, transbronchial needleaspiration increases the overall performance of bronchoscopy by 20%, which means that it should beconsidered as a basic tool in the study of lung cancer. We also comment on the work by Galvis-Caravajal etal, who describe percutaneous radiofrequency as an alternative to radiotherapy in small lung or metastasictumours.In diffuse interstitial disease, Morell et al analysed the diagnostic methods in 500 patients with this clinicalradiologicalpresentation in which a definitive diagnosis was achieved in 85%, with 25% of them beingobtained by non-invasively. Baloira et al analysed the characteristics of 19 patients with desquamativeinterstitial pneumonia and respiratory bronchiolitis associated-interstitial lung disease obtained from theNational register of Interstitial DiseasesAs regards lung transplantation, González Castro et al, in a retrospective study in one centre, analysed theincidence and risk factors associated with renal dysfunction and acute renal failure in 138 transplantedpatients.Finally, we would like to mention the work published by Laporta et al, who analysed the clinical andfunctional characteristics of 100 patients selected for transplantations in their centre</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bollo, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Disdier, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montero, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se ha realizado una revisión de los originales publicados en la revista ARCHIVOS DE BRONCONEUMOLOGÍA duranteel año 2008 sobre técnicas invasivas neumológicas, enfermedades intersticiales y trasplante pulmonar. Hemosseleccionado la publicación de Martínez-Olondrins et al sobre estadificación mediastínica del carcinomabroncogénico por punción transbronquial «a ciegas» para destacar el papel de esta técnica sencilla, seguray económica en un momento en el que la punción dirigida por ecobroncoscopia se perfila como unaalternativa a la estadificación por mediastinoscopia. Además de su utilidad en el estudio de adenopatías, lapunción transbronquial incrementa en un 20% la rentabilidad global de la broncoscopia, lo que obliga aconsiderarla como una herramienta básica en el estudio del cáncer de pulmón. Comentamos también eltrabajo de Galvis-Caravajal et al, que describen la técnica de radiofrecuencia percutánea como alternativa ala radioterapia en pequeños tumores pulmonares o metastásicos.En la patología intersticial difusa, Morell et al analizan los métodos diagnósticos en 500 enfermos con estapresentación clínico-radiológica, en los que se alcanzó el diagnóstico definitivo en el 85%, lográndose deforma no invasiva en el 25% de los casos. Baloira et al analizaron las características de 19 pacientes conneumonía intersticial descamativa y bronquiolitis respiratoria asociada a enfermedad pulmonar intersticial,obtenidos a partir del Registro Nacional de Enfermedades Intersticiales.En trasplante pulmonar, González Castro et al, en un trabajo restrospectivo de un centro, analizan la incidenciay los factores de riesgo asociados para la disfunción renal y fallo renal agudo en 138 pacientes trasplantados.Finalmente, nos referiremos al trabajo publicado por Laporta et al, que analizan las característicasclínicas y funcionales de 100 pacientes seleccionados para trasplante en su centro(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;45(supl.1): 39-42, feb. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59311</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revista del año de Archivos de Neumología en neumología intervencionista, enfermedades intersticiales y trasplante pulmonar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30797</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31333^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29477</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
