<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83057</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Longitudinal research on treated alcoholism: Systematic review of long-term follow-ups</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims: To analyze the methodological design of long-term longitudinal studies of alcoholics who have undergone treatment. Methods: Systematic review of prospective longitudinal studies of treated alcoholics with follow-up periods of at least 8 years, and published in English, during the period 1983-2009. The review includes 9studies which analyzed: follow-up evaluations, information sources, the period of reference in the final assessment, the measurement of alcohol use, the operationalization of drinking patterns, and data analysis. Results: 2434 patients (ranging between 57 and 850 per study) were studied on average for a period of 15.3 (D.T. = 3.2) years (range 8-20 years).Studies differ in the number of intermediate evaluations (0, 1, 3, 4) and the length of the period considered for the final evaluation (the whole period, the last 3 years, the last year, last 6 months, last month or present situation). Drinking patterns tend to be used as the main outcome variable, but they are operationalized in non-equivalent forms and the analysis is performed using classical cross-sectional statistical techniques. Alcoholism evolution is studied by analyzing the evolution of drinking patterns and patients&#146; life situation during the period under study. Conclusions: The scarce amount of data available on the evolution of treated alcoholism cannot be compared across studies due to considerable methodological differences. There is a need to promote common methodological criteria in relation to follow-up strategies. New statistical methods that permit longitudinal analysis for non-balanced and correlated data should also be incorporated (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Benito, Juana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gual, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bravo, Fabián</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar el diseño metodológico de los estudios longitudinales a largo plazo en el campo del alcoholismo tratado. Método: Revisión sistemática de los estudios longitudinales prospectivos de pacientes alcohólicos con seguimiento de al menos 8 años y publicados en inglés entre 1983-2009. La revisión incluye 9 estudios en los que se analizan: Las evaluaciones de seguimiento, las fuentes de información, el periodo de referencia en la evaluación final, la medición del consumo de alcohol, la categorización del patrón de consumo y el análisis de los datos. Resultados: 2.434 pacientes (rango 57 &#150; 850 por estudio) tratados por alcoholismo fueron seguidos en promedio 15.3 (D.T. =. 3.2) años (rango 8 &#150; 20 años). Los estudios se diferencian en el número de evaluaciones intermedias (0, 1, 3 y 4) y en el periodo de referencia usado en la evaluación final (todo el seguimiento, últimos 3 años, último año, últimos6 meses, último mes y actual). Los patrones de consumo (principal resultado de tratamiento) se definen de manera no equivalente y los datos se analizan principalmente de manera transversal usando técnicas estadísticas clásicas. La evolución del alcoholismo se estudia analizando la trayectoria de los patrones de consumo y del estado vital de los pacientes durante los seguimientos. Conclusiones: Los escasos datos disponibles respecto al curso del alcoholismo tratado no pueden ser comparados debido a importantes diferencias metodológicas. Es necesario promover criterios metodológicos comunes respecto a las estrategias de seguimiento e incorporar nuevos métodos estadísticos para el análisis longitudinal de datos no balanceados y correlacionados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);22(3): 267-274, jul.-sept. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83057</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Investigación longitudinal del alcoholismo tratado: Una revisión sistemática de los seguimientos a largo plazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
