<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133764</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical study of the effectiveness of the «water of the 3 sulfates» on balanitis and balanoposthitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: Despite scientific literature mentions the application of 'water of the 3 sulfates' (copper sulphate, zinc sulphate and alum) as a treatment for acute balanitis and balanoposthitis, no clinical trials evaluating its efficacy have been found. In our study we evaluate the efficacy of this solution in acute balanitis and balanoposthitis. Material and methods: A double-blind randomized study was designed to compare the efficacy of 'water of the 3 sulfates' (intervention) with saline solution (control) in 50 patients (30 patients and 20 patients, respectively) who suffer from acute balanitis or balanoposthitis. Exudate, erythema, oedema, burning, and itching were the clinical parameters assessed. Results: for all clinical parameters assessed, the outcomes obtained with 'water of the 3 sulfates' are higher than control, although significant differences only have been found for exudate. Conclusions: in our study, the 'water of the 3 sulfates' is significantly more effective than saline solution for removing exudates in acute balanitis and balanoposthitis. Tolerability was excellent in both treatments (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peyri, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Polo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gonzalvo, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrallach, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: La utilización del «agua de 3 sulfatos» (sulfato de cinc, cobre y alumínico-potásico) se cita en la literatura como un posible tratamiento para la balanitis y balanopostitis; ahora bien, no existen trabajos prospectivos que documenten su eficacia clínica. Pretendemos estudiar dicha eficacia. Material y método: Presentamos un estudio aleatorizado doble ciego sobre 50 pacientes con balanitis o balanopostitis en el que se comparan los resultados clínicos del «agua de 3 sulfatos» (30 pacientes) frente a una solución salina (20 pacientes). Los parámetros clínicos estudiados han sido: exudado, eritema, edema, escozor y prurito. Resultados: Una vez aplicados los test estadísticos, hemos observado que el «agua de 3 sulfatos» ha sido superior al suero salino en todos los parámetros clínicos estudiados, aunque las diferencias solo han sido significativas para el parámetro exudado. Conclusiones: El «agua de 3 sulfatos» se ha mostrado significativamente más eficaz que el suero fisiológico en la eliminación del exudado de las balanitis y balanopostitis agudas de nuestro estudio. La tolerabilidad de los tratamientos ha sido excelente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;39(2): 118-121, mar. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133764</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio clínico de la eficacia del «agua de 3 sulfatos» en la balanitis y la balanopostitis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7674</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d287</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1469^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d534^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32968^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32969^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28387</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
