<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158781</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recommendations for the management of emergencies in patients with diabetes, acute metabolic complications of diabetes, and steroid-related hyperglycemia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Persons with diabetes make up a large percentage of patients attended in the emergency department. Most will be discharged, but patients who remain under observation in wards managed by the emergency department or who wait are waiting to be admitted to a conventional ward must receive appropriate, protocol-guided treatment for their diabetes. Situations of hyper- or hypoglycemia must be avoided because both worsen prognosis. Emergency physicians must correctly and efficiently prevent, diagnose, and manage acute metabolic complications of diabetes such as simple hyperglycemia, diabetic ketoacidosis, and hyperosmolar hyperglycemic state. They must also be ready to prescribe and properly administer intravenous insulin to critically ill patients. Hyperglycemia induced by treatment with steroids deserves special mention. If this complication develops, the hyperglycemia is intense, influenced by increased insulin resistance and gluconeogenesis in the liver. Thus, it usually appears after meals and is dependent on steroid dose, duration of treatment, and individual predisposition. The recommendations in this paper elaborated by consensus of the Spanish Society of Emergency Medicine (SEMES) experts, are the first to be written specifically for use in emergency departments in Spain. They give a detailed, in-depth overview of emergencies related to diabetes and diabetic complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Rodríguez, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio Casas, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáenz Abad, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caurel Sastre, Zaida</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agud Fernández, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego Mínguez, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuervo Pinto, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juan Arribas, Artur</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carballo Cardona, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piñero Panadero, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Un alto porcentaje de los pacientes atendidos en urgencias son diabéticos. La mayoría serán dados de alta. Sin embargo, los que se quedan en observación, ingresados en unidades dependientes de urgencias o los que quedan pendientes de ingreso en hospitalización convencional deben recibir un tratamiento correcto y protocolizado en cuanto a su diabetes, que evite tanto la hiper como la hipoglucemia, ya que ambas son situaciones que empeorarán el pronóstico del paciente. Por otro lado, los urgenciólogos deben prevenir, diagnosticar y manejar de una manera correcta y eficiente las complicaciones metabólicas agudas de la diabetes como son la hiperglucemia simple, la cetoacidosis diabética, la situación hiperosmolar y la hipoglucemia, así como las indicaciones y la forma de administración de insulina intravenosa en los pacientes críticos. Una mención aparte requiere también la hiperglucemia reactiva al tratamiento corticoideo. Esta hiperglucemia, en el caso de aparecer, es intensa y está influenciada por el aumento de la resistencia a la insulina y de la neoglucegénesis hepática que provocan los corticoides, por lo que será de predominio postprandial. Depende de la dosis y duración del tratamiento corticoideo además de una predisposición individual. Las recomendaciones que aquí se exponen, procedentes del consenso alcanzado por el grupo de expertos de la Sociedad Española de Medicina de Urgencias y Emergencias (SEMES), son las primeras redactadas en España dirigidas exclusivamente a los servicios de urgencias y que hacen una revisión pormenorizada y profunda sobre todas las situaciones que pueden encontrarse en cuanto a la diabetes y sus complicaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);28(6): 400-417, dic. 2016. graf, tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158781</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recomendaciones de manejo de la diabetes, de sus complicaciones metabólicas agudas y de la hiperglucemia relacionada con corticoides en los servicios de urgencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7181^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4711^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7124^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
