<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109010</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-5962</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Attachment, Relationship Quality and Stressful Life Events: A Theoretical Meta-Perspective and Some Preliminary Results</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Attachment theory has inspired an explosion of research on personality development, close relationships, and the complex interplay between individual and relationship processes in all phases of the lifespan. In recent years, the theory has been extended to organizational settings. Over three decades of attachment research has been applied to people&#146;s attitudes, performance, and social relationships within large organizations, such as the workplace, the army, and community groups. The present paper aims to advance an integrative perspective that would bridge the psychological and sociological aspects of attachment(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rubinstein, Gidi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tziner, Aaron</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bilig, Miria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La teoría del apego ha inspirado una explosión de investigación sobre el desarrollo de la personalidad, las relaciones íntimas y el complejo interjuego entre los procesos individuales y de relaciones en todas la fases de la vida. In los últimos años, la teoría ha sido ampliada al ámbito organizacional. A lo largo de tres décadas, la investigación sobre apego ha sido aplicada a las actitudes personales, el desempeño y las relaciones sociales en grandes organizaciones laborales, el ejército y grupos comunitarios. El presente articulo propone una perspectiva integrativa que uniría los aspectos psicológicos y sociológicos del apego(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. trab. organ. (1999);28(3): 151-156, 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109010</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Apego, calidad de la relación y sucesos vitales estresantes: una meta-perspectiva teórica y algunos resultados preliminares</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10742^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9954</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30184^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34023</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201200</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
