<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139805</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Angular gyrus connectivity model for language: a functional neuroimaging meta-analysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Modern functional neuroimaging techniques permit the analysis of the simultaneous activation of diverse brain areas to suggest cognitive connectivity models related to specific cognitive functions. Aim. To analyze the functional networks of the angular gyrus (Brodmann area 39) related to language functions. Materials and methods. The database of BrainMap was used to analyze the activation coordinates of the angular gyrus and brain related areas while performing different language tasks. Eight articles were selected that included 13 experiments, 155 participants and 265 loci. Results. Sixteen activation clusters made a network that included the activation of the two angular gyri, the superior right parietal lobe and right supramarginal gyri; the superior left temporal lobe (middle lateral and medial inferior), and the frontal lobe (bilateral premotor and left prefrontal). Conclusions. Our findings are in agreement with previous findings using structural connectivity techniques and support the integrative role of the angular gyrus in language functions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bernal, Byron</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosselli, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ardila, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las técnicas modernas de neuroimagen funcional permiten analizar la activación simultánea de diversas áreas cerebrales y sugerir modelos de conectividad para funciones cognitivas específicas. Objetivo. Realizar un metaanálisis de las redes funcionales de la región angular (área de Brodmann 39) con relación al lenguaje. Materiales y métodos. Partiendo de la base de datos BrainMap, se analizaron las coordenadas de activación en estudios de resonancia magnética funcional que mostraban una activación del área de Brodmann 39 durante la realización de tareas lingüísticas. Se seleccionaron ocho artículos con 13 experimentos, que incluían un total de 155 sujetos, y 265 localizaciones. Resultados. Los resultados mostraron 16 conglomerados de activación significativos que conformaban una red de coactivación, la cual incluía las dos regiones angulares, el lóbulo parietal superior y la circunvolución supramarginal derechos, el lóbulo temporal izquierdo (cara lateral medial y cara medial inferior) y el lóbulo frontal (premotor bilateral y prefrontal izquierdo). Conclusiones. Estos resultados coinciden con los hallazgos obtenidos con técnicas de conectividad estructural y apoyan el papel integrador de la región angular en funciones lingüísticas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;60(11): 495-503, 1 jun., 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139805</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Modelo de conectividad de la circunvolución angular en el lenguaje: metaanálisis de neuroimágenes funcionales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6330^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6330^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6330^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30967</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14080^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7980^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14080^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14080^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14080^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6330^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
