<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80388</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Telemedicine: Improving the quality of care for critical patients from the pre-hospital phase to the intensive care unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Health System is in crisis and critical care (from transport systems to the ICU) cannot escape from that. Lack of integration between ambulances and reference Hospitals, a deep shortage of critical care specialists and assigned economical resources that increase less than critical care demand are the cornerstones of the problem. Moreover, the analysis of the situation anticipated that the problem will be worse in the future.&#147;Closed&#148; ICUs in which critical care specialists direct patient care outperform &#147;open&#148; ones in which primary admitting physicians direct patient care in consultation with critical care specialists. However, the current paradigm in which a critical care specialist is close to the patient is in the edge of the trouble so, only a new paradigm could help to increase the number of patients under intensivist care. Current information technology and networking capabilities should be fully exploited to improve both the extent and quality of intensivist coverage. Far to be a replacement of the existing model Telemedicine might be a complimentary tool. In fact, to centralize medical data into servers has many additional advantages that could even improve the way in which critical care physicians take care of their patients under the traditional system(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blanch,  L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murias, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sales, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Esquirol, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El sistema asistencial sanitario está en crisis, y los cuidados críticos (desde los sistemas de transporte hasta la unidad de cuidados intensivos [UCI]) no se libran de esta circunstancia. La falta de integración entre la Medicina prehospitalaria y los hospitales receptores, una limitación profunda en el número de especialistas en cuidados críticos y unos recursos económicos que no aumentan a la par del incremento en la demanda de cuidados intensivos son las piedras angulares del problema. Es más, las previsiones de futuro no son alentadoras.Varios estudios demuestran que las UCI &#147;cerradas&#148;, en las que un especialista en cuidados intensivos dirige la atención del paciente, tienen mejores resultados que las UCI &#147;abiertas&#148;, en las que la atención sigue a cargo de los médicos de atención primaria. Sin embargo, que un especialista en cuidados intensivos se encuentre al lado del paciente es cada vez más complicado; sólo un cambio en la manera de trabajar podría ayudar a incrementar el número de pacientes cuidados por un intensivista. La tecnología de la información y la capacidad de comunicación (transmisión de datos en línea) deberían explotarse al máximo para aumentar tanto la cobertura como la calidad de los cuidados intensivos. Lejos de ser un reemplazo del modelo existente, la telemedicina podría ser la herramienta complementaria que ayudara a mejorar la manera en la que los médicos intensivistas atienden a sus pacientes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);34(1): 46-55, ene.-feb. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80388</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Telemedicina: mejora de la calidad en la atención de los pacientes críticos desde la fase prehospitalaria hasta el servicio de medicina intensiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30481^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9183^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30481^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9183^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30481</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30481^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
