<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60747</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: the purpose of this study was to assess the conditions thatinfluence the death of oncological patients in their homes.Method: we carried out a retrospective study of patients recruited in apalliative care program in Huesca province who died in 2006. We selectedoncological patients older than 18 years, with a main carer, and more thantree days in the program. After reviewing the literature, we selected severalfactors that were highly related to place of death. We designed a questionnaireincluding thirteen of these factors: &#147;place of death&#148;, &#147;age&#148;, &#147;sex&#148;,&#147;Pfeiffer&#148;, &#147;Barthel&#148;, &#147;type of cancer&#148;, &#147;social class&#148;, &#147;place of residence&#148;,&#147;main carer&#148;, &#147;number of homecare visits&#148;, &#147;number of days as inpatient&#148;,and &#147;number of days in program&#148;. Statistical analyses for categorical andnon-categorical variables were made with the SPSS 14 program.Results: 108 patients were selected: 61% of them were men and 39%women; 57.4% died at home and 42.6% died in an acute hospital; 75%lived in urban areas and 25% in rural areas, with a median of 74.6 days inthe palliative care program. Median age was 78 years. The condition was asolid tumour in 91.7% of cases, while the remaining 8.3% had other typesof tumour. Social status was grouped into eight categories. Median of daysin the program was 41.5, and median disease duration was 235 days. Norelations were found between: functional status, mental status, sex, socialclass, main carer, days in program, intensity of home care, and long diseaseduration or tumour type. Variables associated with death at homewere: living in a rural area (p = 0.013), and extended family support (p =0.009). The relation between death at home and age is questionable (p =0.049)Conclusions: Death at home is more frequent in patients living in ruralareas, and having more than one caregiver (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Andrés Esteban, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bescós Orós, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coria Balanzat, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bordonoba Bosque, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parra Moncasi, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: averiguar qué condicionantes socio-ambientales puedeninfluir en el hecho de que la muerte de un enfermo oncológico terminaltenga lugar en el domicilio.Método: se realizó un estudio retrospectivo de los pacientes controladospor el equipo de soporte de atención domiciliaria (ESAD) de la provinciade Huesca durante el año 2006, y se seleccionaron aquellos que habíanfallecido por causa oncológica en domicilio u hospital, eran mayores de 18años, tenían un cuidador principal definido y llevaban más de 3 días en elprograma del ESAD. Las variables a estudio fueron seleccionadas en base auna revisión de la literatura, lo que permitió la elaboración de una hoja derecogida de datos con las siguientes: &#147;lugar de defunción&#148;, &#147;edad&#148;, &#147;sexo&#148;,&#147;Peiffer&#148;, &#147;Barthel&#148;, &#147;tipo de tumor&#148;, &#147;clase social&#148;, &#147;residencia&#148;, &#147;cuidadorprincipal&#148;, &#147;más de un cuidador&#148;, &#147;número de visitas por parte del ESAD&#148;,&#147;días en programa&#148; y &#147;días de enfermedad desde el momento del diagnóstico&#148;.El estudio estadístico se realizó con el paquete estadístico SPSS 14con análisis de variables categóricas y cuantitativas.Resultados: durante el periodo del estudio se incluyeron 108 pacientes,con una media de edad de 75,75 y mediana de 78 años, 61% eran hombresy 39% mujeres, el 57,4% fallecieron en domicilio y un 42,6% en hospitalde agudos. Respecto a la enfermedad de base: el 91,7% presentabantumores sólidos y 8,3% tumores de origen hematológico. Un 75% residíanen zonas urbanas y 25% en rurales. Su estatus social se agrupó en ochocategorías. La mediana de permanencia en programa ESAD fue de 41,5días, y la mediana de los días de enfermedad fue de 235 días. No encontramosrelación entre el lugar de defunción y las variables: Barthel, Peiffer,sexo, clase social, cuidador principal, días en programa, número de visitasy días de enfermedad y no podemos asegurar que haya independenciaentre las variables lugar de defunción y tipo de tumor. (...) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;16(2): 89-94, mar. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60747</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Condicionantes del lugar de defunción de pacientescon enfermedad oncológica terminal,adscritos al ESAD, en la provincia de Huesca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3660</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30047^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6858^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33200^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
