<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73949</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Acupuncture is an important therapy from traditional Chinese medicine that has been used for more than 3,000years. Recently, the popularity of this technique has been increasing among patients and physicians in Western countries. Basic-science research has clarified the physiological mechanisms of acupuncture. It has been shown in many investigations that acupuncture precipitates a neuroendocrine response that activates cascades of endogenous opiates. Numerous randomized, controlled trials and systematic reviews have evaluated the clinical efficacy of acupuncture. The evidence obtained from these works have demonstrated that acupuncture is an effective treatment for dental pain, postoperative nausea and vomiting and chemotherapy-related nausea and vomiting. Evidence is non-conclusive for other conditions since clinical research in acupuncture poses methodological challenges that must still be overcome. Acupuncture is relatively safe when performed by experts. Health care providers are changing their view on the use of acupunture as a non-drug treatment that is complementary to the conventional medical approach. More studies are needed in order to help us clarify the doubts and to serve as a link between this ancient healing art and modern medicine (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ospina-Díaz, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La acupuntura es una terapéutica de la medicina tradicional china utilizada desde hace más de 3.000 años. Recientemente ha ido ganando popularidad entre pacientes y médicos en el mundo occidental. Investigaciones en ciencias básicas aclaran los mecanismos fisiológicos de la acupuntura. Múltiples investigaciones muestran que la acupuntura desencadena una respuesta neuroendocrina que activa cascadas de opioides endógenos. Numerosos estudios clínicos controlados y aleatorizados, y revisiones sistemáticas han intentado evaluar la eficacia clínica de la acupuntura. La evidencia derivada de estos trabajos avala la acupuntura como un tratamiento eficaz para el dolor dental, las náuseas y vómitos de los posoperatorios y de la quimioterapia. Para otras condiciones, los resultados todavía no son concluyentes dado que la investigación clínica en acupuntura plantea retos metodológicos que están en proceso de ser superados. La acupuntura es una terapéutica segura en manos entrenadas. La comunidad médica se está abriendo a la utilización de la acupuntura como una terapéutica no farmacológica complementaria a la práctica médica habitual. Son necesarios más estudios que nos permitan ir esclareciendo las dudas y que sirvan de puente entre este antiguo arte de curar y los sistemas modernos de salud (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);35(8): 380-384, oct. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73949</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Introducción a la acupuntura. Fundamentos e interés para el médico de Atención Primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36318^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19609^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26402</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
