<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108818</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Qualitative approach to coping with the death in intensive care professionals</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the factors that interrelate with professional stress associated with the continued care of pain and death among nursing staff of the Intensive Care Unit of the Virgen del Rocío University Hospital (Seville). Material and method: Descriptive study with quantitative and qualitative techniques. We use a self-administered anonymous survey consisting of: socio-demographic questionnaire, Maslach Burnout Inventory (MBI) and extensive account of a situation perceived as stressful in relation to the care of pain and death. A total of 18 professionals were included (13 nurses and five nursing assistants). A statistical descriptive analysis of the MBI was carried out on the different sociodemographic variables. From the extensive accounts of a situation perceived as stressful, a qualitative analysis was made by coding the text into meaningful units, followed by a statistical descriptive analysis of these units. Results: Only 20% of ICU professionals identified care of pain and death as the main factor of stress. Over 50% of the professionals scored low on the three subscales of the MBI. The factors that interact with stress in the accounts were: 44.4% with a significant concern for family care, 38.9% identified an interpersonal conflict, 22.2% as regards the futility of their work. In 16.7% of cases there was no stress associated with any other factor other than the pain and death for themselves. Colleague support was seen by 5.6% as a protective factor against professional stress. Conclusions: Looking after the family of a terminally ill patient is the main concern of critical care professionals, always difficult due to the restricted visiting times. The quality of interpersonal relationships influences the perceived level of stress in any specific situations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molina Venegas, Cesárea</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cumplido Corbacho, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Valorar los factores que se interrelacionan con el estrés profesional asociado a la atención continuada del dolor y la muerte entre el personal de enfermería de intensivos del Hospital Universitario Virgen del Rocío (Sevilla). Material y método: Estudio descriptivo transversal, con técnicas cuantitativas y cualitativas. Utilizamos una encuesta autoadministrada y anónima compuesta por: cuestionario de datos sociodemográficos, Maslach Burnout Inventory (MBI) y relato extenso de una situación percibida como estresante en relación a la atención del dolor y la muerte. Muestra: 18 profesionales (13 enfermeras/os y 5 auxiliares de enfermería). Se hizo un análisis estadístico descriptivo del MBI en relación a las diferentes variables sociodemográficas. De los relatos extensos se hizo un análisis cualitativo mediante la codificación del texto en unidades de significado y un posterior análisis estadístico descriptivo de estas unidades. Resultados: El 20% de los profesionales de UCI identifican la atención al dolor y la muerte como principal factor de estrés. Más del 50% de los profesionales puntúan bajo en la tres subescalas del MBI. Los factores que se interrelacionan con el estrés en los relatos son: el 44,4% de los relatos muestran una importante preocupación por la atención a la familia, el 38,9% identifica un conflicto interpersonal, el 22,2% se refiere a la inutilidad del trabajo realizado. Un 16,7% no asocia el estrés a ningún otro factor más que al dolor y la muerte por sí mismos. El 5,6% aprecia el apoyo de los compañeros como factor de protección frente al estrés profesional.  Conclusiones: La principal preocupación de los profesionales de UCI es la atención a la familia del paciente en situación terminal, siempre difícil por el régimen de visitas restringido. La calidad de las relaciones interpersonales influye en la percepción del nivel de estrés de situaciones concretas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;18(4): 141-148, oct.-dic. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108818</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aproximación cualitativa al afrontamiento de la muerte en profesionales de cuidados intensivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
