<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055194</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Benefits of exercise in patients with diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Physical exercise has important health benefi ts. Physical inactivity is associated    with an increased risk of chronic diseases like type 2 diabetes    mellitus. In contrast, moderate levels of physical exercise produce considerable    benefi ts in diabetic patients, especially in those with type 2 diabetes    mellitus. At the onset of the disease, modifi cation of lifestyle, with    improvements in diet and exercise, may restore good metabolic control,    postponing, for the time being, the need for pharmacological treatment.    When the disease progresses and metabolic control deteriorates, despite    treatment with oral hypoglycemic agents, exercise may also contribute to    enhance glycemic control. Physical exercise improves fi tness status and    a number of anthropometric parameters, such as weight and fat distribution,    and contributes to the prevention of chronic complications. There is    also evidence of the benefi ts of exercise in terms of cardiovascular risk    factors, reducing the incidence of hypertension and dyslipidemia, which    contributes overall to lowering the risk of cardiovascular disease. Moreover,    regular exercise produces important psychological benefi ts, which    can contribute to increase the adherence to treatment and improve the    quality of life of people with diabetes. However, adherence to physical    exercise programs among diabetic patients is very low. Factors that contribute    to this circumstance include the diffi culties associated with the    introduction of changes in lifestyle and the limited interest in the promotion    and prescription of exercise on the part of health care professionals,    who lack both the training and the time necessary for proper prescription.    Therefore, the need to inform, recommend and prescribe the most    appropriate physical exercise for people with diabetes should be promoted    among clinicians</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero Figueroa, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El ejercicio físico tiene importantes beneficios sobre la salud. En    efecto, mientras los hábitos de vida sedentarios se asocian con un    mayor riesgo de enfermedades crónicas como la diabetes mellitus    tipo 2, niveles moderados de ejercicio físico producen beneficios    considerables en los pacientes con esta enfermedad. Al inicio, la    modificación del estilo de vida, con cambios dietéticos y ejercicio,    puede mejorar el control metabólico y obviar, por un tiempo, el tratamiento    farmacológico. Cuando la enfermedad progresa y el control    metabólico se deteriora a pesar del tratamiento con hipoglucemiantes    orales, el ejercicio puede contribuir a la mejora del control glucémico.    El ejercicio mejora la condición física y diversos parámetros    antropométricos como el peso y la distribución de la grasa corporal,    además de participar en la prevención de complicaciones crónicas.    Existen evidencias claras acerca del beneficio de la actividad física    sobre los factores de riesgo cardiovascular, reduciendo la incidencia    de hipertensión arterial y de dislipemia, lo que se asocia globalmente    a la reducción del riesgo de enfermedad cardiovascular. Además,    el ejercicio presenta importantes beneficios psicológicos que pueden    contribuir a mejorar la adherencia terapéutica y la calidad de    vida del paciente con diabetes. Sin embargo, la adhesión a programas    de ejercicio físico es muy baja en la población con esta enfermedad.    Ello se debe, en parte, a las dificultades en la implementación    de los cambios en el estilo de vida, a la escasa dedicación del    personal sanitario a la promoción del ejercicio, y a la falta de formación    y de tiempo para su adecuada prescripción. En consecuencia,    debe incentivarse en la práctica clínica la necesidad de informar,    aconsejar y prescribir el ejercicio físico de forma adecuada a los pacientes    con diabetes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;23(1): 22-27, ene.-feb. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055194</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Beneficios del ejercicio físico en los pacientes con diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5179</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
