<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149146</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Knowledge and attitudes about adolescent sexuality in first course to degree in Early Childhood and Primary Education at the University of Jaén</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Both teen pregnancy and the prevalence of sexually transmitted infections in this population is a health problem of great importance. Framing adolescent and sexuality, studies indicate high frequencies in risky behaviours and poor knowledge about contraception and sexually transmitted diseases. Objective: To describe the knowledge and attitudes about adolescent sexuality of First Degree in Education at University of Jaén. Method: The information was collected through an anonymous, voluntary, self-administered questionnaire, which was applied to a non-random convenience sample of 151 subjects First Degree in Early Childhood and Primary at the University of Jaén. Results: 118 reported having had sex with penetration, being these significant differences between girls and boys (p = .034), as well as for masturbation regarding sex (96% men vs. 19% women). They are the women who practice more fellatio (p = .031), but these sexual practices are carried out with partner (p = .01), boys are who have higher alcohol consumption prior to intercourse (p =. 021) and higher number of sexual partners (p = .026). They are still women who identify, greater proportion, the papilloma as STD (p = .02). And 27.7% is who known dual method of contraception. Conclusions: Three quarters of the sample had sex, and most have sex in the currently, using contraception to prevent pregnancy. Rating this together with a deficit of knowledge of the dual method contraceptive (a quarter of the total) and sexually transmitted infections, leads us to think that is necessary sex education for these teens (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Muñoz, Inés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Mármol, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Cruz, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer los conocimientos y actitudes sobre sexualidad en los adolescentes de primero de Grado en Educación de la Universidad de Jaén. Material y Método: Los datos se recogieron a través de un cuestionario anónimo, voluntario y autocumplimentado, el cual se aplicó a una muestra no probabilística por conveniencia de 151 sujetos estudiantes de primer curso de Grado en Educación Infantil y Primaria de la Universidad de Jaén. Resultados: 118 manifiestan haber mantenido relaciones sexuales con penetración, siendo estas diferencias significativas entre chicas y chicos (p=.034), al igual que para la masturbación en cuanto al sexo (96% de los hombres frente a 19% de las mujeres). También son las mujeres las que practican más el fellatio (p=.031), pero estas prácticas sexuales las realizan con la pareja (p=.01), siendo los chicos los que presentan mayor consumo de alcohol previo al coito (p=.021) y mayor número de parejas sexuales (p=.026). Siguen siendo ellas las que identifican en mayor proporción el papiloma como ITS (p=.02). Y el 27,7% del total conocen el doble método anticonceptivo. Conclusión: Tres cuartas partes de la muestra han mantenido relaciones coitales haciendo uso de anticonceptivos para evitar el embarazo. Valorando esto junto con un escaso conocimiento del doble método (una cuarta parte del total) y de las infecciones de transmisión sexual, nos lleva a pensar como materia necesaria la educación sexual para estos adolescentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;15(41): 164-173, ene. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149146</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conocimientos y actitudes sobre sexualidad en adolescentes de primer curso de Grado en Educación Infantil y Primaria de la Universidad de Jaén</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11709^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11709^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35173</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13116^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3289^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3289^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13116^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50448^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50448^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
