<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107495</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Malignant eccrine spiradenoma of the nasolabial fold. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Malignant eccrine spiradenoma (MES) is a rare malignancy of the eccrine sweat glands. It usually presents as a small, firm, reddish painful and small solitary nodule. Head and neck are rare locations. Etiology is unknown although previous trauma is believed to be an implicated factor. MES arises over a prior benign spiradenoma. Clinical behavior is aggressive with a high rate of recurrences and distant metastases. Prognosis is poor. Diagnosis is based on histological findings and treatment must be aggressive from the beginning to achieve the best results. Since Kersting and Helwig first described the case in 1956, and Beekley et al., reported its malignant transformation in 1971, only a few cases can be found in the literature. Based on these particular features we report a case of a 75-year-old man diagnosed on a MES that arises in a very unusual location, with a peculiar histopathology and behavior(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín Sastre, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Oliveira, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carro Rey, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Alba, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El espiradenoma ecrino maligno (EEM) es un tumor maligno poco frecuente de las glándulas sudoríparas ecrinas. Suele presentarse como un pequeño nódulo eritematoso, firme, solitario y doloroso. La cabeza y el cuello son una localización excepcional. Se desconoce la etiología aunque se considera que un traumatismo previo es un factor implicado. El EEM se origina sobre un espiradenoma benigno previo. La conducta clínica es agresiva con una elevada tasa de recidivas y metástasis a distancia. El pronóstico es infausto. El diagnóstico se basa en los hallazgos histológicos y el tratamiento ha de ser agresivo desde el principio para obtener los mejores resultados. Desde que, en 1956, Kersting y Helwig describieran el primer caso, y, en 1971, Beekley y cols. documentaran su transformación maligna, sólo se han publicado unos pocos casos. En función de estas características específicas, describimos a un hombre de 75 años de edad, en el que se estableció el diagnóstico de este tumor, originado en una localización poco habitual, con una histopatología y conducta peculiares(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;34(4): 180-184, oct.-dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107495</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Espiradenoma ecrino maligno en el surco nasolabial. Caso clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53489^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54410^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53489^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54410^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54410^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
