<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112171</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">High increments of overweight along with low length-for-age growth during the first 24 months of life</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: It has been reported that children nursed in orphanages loose one month of lineal growth for every three months they spend in the orphanage. Objective: The purpose of this study was to evaluate the daily variation of weight- for- length and length-for-age among infants under 24 months of age, living in a temporary public orphanage in Mexico. Methods: Ninety children from 0 to 24 months of age, who were institutionalized at an orphanage, were assessed during a three month period. Upon arrival their height and weight were measured daily, Monday through Friday. Daily growth velocity for weight and length was calculated. Length-for age (LAZ) and weight-for-length (WHZ) age z- scores were calculated based on WHO criteria. Risk of overweight (ROW) and overweight (OW) were classified using the WHO criteria. Results: The increments of daily weight were lower than the normal range (9 g daily), but the ROW and OW increased from 10% and 3% at the beginning of the study to 14% and 11% at the end. At the end of the follow-up, WHZ was inversely associated to length (cm/day) velocity (r = -302, p &lt; 0.01). Although a significant increase in ROW and OW was observed, at the end of the study, 31% of the children showed signs of stunting (-2 SD in length-age) and 5% remained emaciated (-2 SD in weight-length). Conclusions: Children living in an orphanage showed reduced increments of weight and length-for-age, as well as a reduced length velocity and an increased ROW and OW (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Morán, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Cruz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santillana-Marín, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bacardí-Gascón,  M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: Se ha descrito que los niños de orfanatorios pierden un mes lineal por cada tres meses que residen en un orfanatorio. Objetivo: El propósito de este estudio fue evaluar la variación diaria de peso-para-talla y talla-para edad, entre infantes de menos de 24 meses de edad, que residen en un orfanatorio público temporal de México Métodos: Se valoraron durante un período de tres meses, noventa niños de 0 a 24 meses de edad, institucionalizados en un orfanatorio. Desde su ingreso se midieron diariamente la estatura y el peso de manera estandarizada, del lunes al viernes. Se calculó la velocidad de crecimiento diario del peso y la estatura. Las puntuaciones del z-score de la talla-para-edad y del peso-para-talla (zPT), se calcularon basados en los criterios de la OMS. El riesgo de sobrepeso (RSP) y el sobrepeso (SP) se clasificó de acuerdo a los criterios recomendados por la OMS. Resultados: Los aumentos diarios de peso fueron menores que el rango normal para la edad (9 g diarios), pero el RSP y el SP aumentó de 10 a 3% al inicio del estudio, a 14 y 11% al final del estudio. Al final del seguimiento, el zPT estuvo inversamente asociado a la velocidad de crecimiento (cm/dia) lineal (r = -302, p &lt; 0,01). Aunque se observó un aumento significativo de RSP y SP, al final del estudio 31% de los niños presentaban signos de retraso de crecimiento (-2 SD de talla-para-edad) y 5% seguían emaciados (-2 SD de peso-para-edad). Conclusiones: Los niños que viven en orfanatos presentan aumentos reducidos de peso y talla para la edad, reducción de la velocidad de crecimiento lineal y un aumento de RSP y SP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;27(6): 1894-1899, nov.-dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112171</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aumento de sobrepeso con bajo crecimiento de talla-para-edad durante los primeros 24 meses de vida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24212^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6280^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16508</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2712^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23861^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33204^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
