<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166177</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Natriuretic peptides in heart failure</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The fact that the heart is able to secrete hormones, which are released in significant amounts in advance of certain cardiac conditions, has resulted in a wide range of opportunities and raised a multitude of questions. These hormones, named natriuretic peptides, possess diuretic, natriuretic and vasodilatory properties. The ones used in daily clinical practice are atrial natriuretic peptide (ANP), brain natriuretic peptide (BNP), and their N-terminal fragments NT-proANP and NT-proBNP, respectively. Although most studies currently involve the use of BNP, the number involving NT-proBNP is expected to increase substantially in coming years because its level is less variable and its half-life longer. Nevertheless, at present there appears to be sufficient evidence to suggest that the plasma levels of these hormones will be extremely useful for the diagnosis, prognosis, screening, pharmacological monitoring, and treatment of patients with heart failure (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Dolz, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almenar Bonet, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El hecho de que el corazón sea capaz de segregar hormonas, y que éstas se liberen en cantidades importantes ante determinadas situaciones cardiacas, ha abierto un horizonte lleno de esperanzas e incertidumbres. Estas hormonas, denominadas péptidos natriuréticos, poseen propiedades diuréticas, natriuréticas y vasodilatadoras. Las utilizadas en clínica son el ANP, BNP y sus porciones terminales (NT-proANP y NT-proBNP). Actualmente, la mayoría de estudios están realizados con el BNP, pero debido a su menor variabilidad y mayor vida media es esperable que en los próximos años se incrementen en gran medida el número de trabajos con NT-proBNP. De cualquier forma, parece con suficiente evidencia en la actualidad que el nivel plasmático de estas hormonas será de gran ayuda en el diagnóstico, pronóstico, despistaje, control farmacológico y tratamiento de la insuficiencia cardiaca (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);6(supl.F): 15f-26f, 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166177</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Péptidos natriuréticos en insuficiencia cardiaca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4479^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4479^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8348^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52611^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52611^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38110^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38110^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
