<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150472</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Internal organizational barriers to implement the role of the advanced nurse practitioner</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Bajo Buenestado, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pueyo Garrigues, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introduction. Nowadays the socio-sanitary context is experiencing a transformation process. These changes provoke the emergence  of  innovative nurses&#146; roles, such as the advanced nurse practitioner, with specific preparation and attributes adequate to give answers to a more complex society. Objective. We study the main internal organizational barriers that hinder the implementation process of the advanced nurse practitioner. We identify three of them: «ambiguity of the role», «organizational barriers» and «human factor». A better understanding of these barriers is essential to prevent them as well as to encourage an appropriate implementation of the new role in the health organization. Conclusions. The evolution of the hospital setting requires innovative nurses&#146;roles, such as the advanced nurse practitioner. In its implementation process we identify three internal organizational barriers that hinder such process. A nursing education reform as well as a labor reform at the workplace level should include the advanced practice. The implementation of this new role will be achieved once the profession can articulate and describe its core and features (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;39(3): 176-180, mar. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150472</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Barreras internas de la organización en la implementación de la figura de la enfermera de práctia avanzada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3175</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17227^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23591^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17227^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36313^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17227^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23591^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23591^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
