<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115282</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adherence to physical activity recommendations in a hypertensive primary care population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the prevalence of adherence to physical activity recommendations in the hypertensive population of Lerida (Spain) attended in primary care and to identify related factors. Methods: A cross sectional study was carried out in hypertensive adults. The dependent variable was adherence to physical activity recommendations measured with the Minnesota Questionnaire. The independent variables were sociodemographic factors, the information received, and attitudes to physical activity. Results: A total of 786 hypertensive patients participated in this study; 53.9% were women and the mean age was 66.0±10.2 years. Adherence to recommendations was found in 64.3% (95% CI: 60.9-67.6); this percentage was 65.2% in men (95% CI: 60.2-70.0) and 63.4% in women (95% CI: 58.8-67.9). Greater adherence was associated with age in men and with residence in a rural area in women. In both genders, greater adherence was associated with unpaid work and with having a favorable attitude to physical activity. No association was observed with the number of recommendations received in the last 6 months. Conclusions: More than half the hypertensive population adhered to physical activity recommendations. To improve physical activity levels, recommendations can be tailored to the attitudes of individual patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guitard Sein-Echaluce, M. Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Farreny Justribó, Divina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Artigues Barberá, Eva M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Puig-gros, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Orduna, Miguela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Vilaplana, Josep M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar la prevalencia de cumplimiento de las recomendaciones de actividad física en la población hipertensa del Área de Salud de Lleida y los factores asociados. Métodos: Estudio transversal en personas hipertensas adultas. La variable dependiente fue el cumplimiento de las recomendaciones medido con el cuestionario Minnesota; las independientes fueron las características sociodemográficas, la información recibida y las actitudes frente a la actividad física. Resultados: Participaron 786 personas hipertensas de 66,0±10,2 años; el 53,9% eran mujeres. Cumplieron las recomendaciones el 64,3% (intervalo de confianza del 95% [IC95%]: 60,9-67,6): el 65,2% (IC95%: 60,2-70,0) de los hombres y el 63,4% (IC95%: 58,8-67,9) de las mujeres. Un mayor cumplimiento se asoció con la edad en los hombres y con residir en el ámbito rural en las mujeres. Tener ocupación no remunerada y buena actitud hacia la realización de actividad física se asociaron con mayor cumplimiento en ambos sexos. No se observó asociación con el número de consejos recibidos los últimos 6 meses. Conclusiones: Más de la mitad de la población hipertensa cumple las recomendaciones. Para mejorar el nivel de actividad física puede recomendarse una prescripción individualizada según la actitud hacia ésta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;27(4): 365-368, jul.-ago. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115282</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cumplimiento de las recomendaciones sobre actividad física en personas hipertensas asistidas en atención primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37738^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23899</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
