<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88262</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Lung sparing surgery by means of extended broncho-angioplastic (sleeve) lobectomies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveTo determine the morbidity, mortality and survival of sleeve lobectomy procedures compared to simple broncho-angioplasty procedures.Patients and methodsA total of 535 patients diagnosed with bronchogenic cancer between September 2005 and May 2010 who fulfilled the criteria of clinical, oncological and functional operability were treated in our unit. Unresectable central tumours (n=95) using simple lobectomy were scheduled for broncho-angioplasty techniques and a pneumonectomy in those where this was impossible.ResultsA total of 58 (11%) were performed, 46 simple broncho-angioplastic lobectomies (SBAL) and 12 extended broncho-angioplastic lobectomies (EBAL). In the SBAL group there were 32 bronchial (70%) and 7 (15%) bronchovascular reconstructions and only vascular (15%). In the EBAL group, 8 (66.7%) were bronchial and 4 (33.3%) were bronchovascular reconstructions. The most common type of resection was the right upper lobe (RUL)+segment 6 in five (41%) cases, followed by RUL+middle lobe. There were 2 (3%) deaths in the SBAL group. There was 34% morbidity in the SBAL and 33% in the EBAL group (P&gt;0.05). Fifteen patients received neoadjuvant chemo-radiotherapy treatment, due to histologically confirmed cN2; however, the number of complications was not significantly higher. No risk factors were detected in any variable studied that would affect EBAL compared to the SBAL group (P&gt;0.05). The patients in both groups with a higher morbidity were pN1, located in the left upper lobe and associated with vascular reconstruction (P&lt;0.05). The overall survival at 5 years was 61.6%, SBAL (61%) and EBAL (68.9%) with no differences between groups (P&gt;0.05).ConclusionsEBALs are technically more demanding procedures, but do not increase the morbidity or mortality compared to simple broncho-angioplasty techniques, and with a similar survival(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Caro, Abel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molins, Laurenao</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matute, Purificación</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Samuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gimferrer, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoDeterminar la morbimortalidad y supervivencia de los procedimientos broncoangioplásticos extendidos a más de un lóbulo en comparación con las técnicas broncoangioplásticas simples.Pacientes y métodosEntre septiembre de 2005 y mayo de 2010, 535 pacientes diagnosticados de carcinoma broncogénico que cumplían criterios de operabilidad clínica, oncológica y funcional fueron tratados en nuestra unidad. Los tumores centrales(n=95) no resecables mediante lobectomía simple fueron programados para técnicas broncoangioplásticas y en caso de imposibilidad, neumonectomía.ResultadosSe realizaron 58 (11%) procedimientos, 46 lobectomías broncoangioplásticas simple (LBS) y 12 extendidas (LBE). En el grupo de LBS (bronquiales 32 [70%], reconstrucción broncovascular 7 [15%] y vascular sola 7 [15%]). En el grupo de LBE, 8 (66,7%) fueron reconstrucciones bronquiales y 4 (33,3%) broncovasculares. El tipo de resección más frecuente es el lóbulo superior derecho (LSD)+segmento 6 en 5 (41%) casos, seguido del LSD+lóbulo medio. La mortalidad fue de en 2 (3%) casos en el grupo LBS. La morbilidad ocurrió en el 34% LSB y en el 33% LBE (p&gt;0,05). Quince pacientes recibieron tratamiento quimiorradioterápico neoadjuvante, por cN2 confirmado histológicamente, sin embargo no se detectó mayor número de complicaciones significativamente (p&gt;0,05). No se detectaron factores de riesgo respecto a ninguna variable estudiada que afectaran a las LBE respecto a las LBS (p&gt;0,05). En ambos grupos, los pacientes con mayor morbilidad fueron pN1, localización en lóbulo superior izquierdo y con reconstrucción vascular asociada (p&lt;0,05). La supervivencia global a los 5 años fue 61,6% LBS (61%) y LBE (68,9%) sin diferencia entre ambos grupos (p&gt;0,05).ConclusionesLas LBE son procedimientos técnicamente más demandantes pero no aumentan la morbimortalidad respecto a las técnicas broncoangioplásticas simples con una supervivencia similar(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;47(2): 66-72, feb. 2011. tab, graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88262</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cirugía de preservación pulmonar mediante reconstrucciones broncoangioplásticas extendidas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2326^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11442^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30853^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
