<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046462</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Does nutrition play a role in the quality of life of patients under chronic haemodialysis?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: In patients with chronic renal failure under haemodialysis, we investigated the inter-relationships and relative contributions of disease, haemodialysis and of nutrition related factors on the patients' Quality of Life.  Methods: Collected data in 60 adult patients comprised: co-morbidities (multiple medicines, other chronic diseases), duration of renal failure and of haemodialysis (in months), % weight loss since haemodialysis, nutrient intake derived from diet history analysis (DIETPLAN5 2003, UK). The EuroQoL instrument that includes 5 dimensions, mobility, self-care, activities, pain/discomfort, anxiety/depression, and an overall health visual analogue scale evaluated QoL.  Results: Estimates of effect size attributed to each variable included in the general linear model revealed that 47% of patients' mobility/self-care scores were worsened by deficient protein/energy intake and 30% by weight loss=10%. Poor performance of usual activities was attributed in 45% to duration of haemodialysis and of disease, 70% to protein/energy/vitamin B12/zinc/iron deficits, and 20% to weight loss =10%. Pain/discomfort were worsened in 45% by the duration of haemodialysis and of disease,and in 15% by co-morbidities. Higher anxiety/depression were related in 43% to protein/energy/selenium &amp; vitamin C deficits, in 40% to the duration of haemodialysis and of disease, in 10% to weight loss =10%, and in 3% to co-morbidities. Likewise, 47% of poor overall health was determined by protein/energy/vitamin B12/zinc/selenium &amp; vitamin C deficits, 25% by weight loss=10%, 10% by disease duration, and 7% by co-morbidities.  Conclusion: Protein, antioxidants and key micronutrients involved in protein metabolism, did exert a major effect on patients' Quality of Life. Given the prevalence of nutrient deficits, the ensuing impaired functional capacity is likely to compromise QoL, timely nutrition is thus warranted (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Camilo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ravasco, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Raimundo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Proença, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: en pacientes con insuficiencia renal crónica y en hemodiálisis, investigamos las relaciones y contribuciones relativas de la enfermedad, hemodiálisis y factores nutricionales del paciente sobre la calidad de vida (QOL).  Métodos: los datos recogidos de 60 pacientes adultos incluían: comorbilidades (múltiples fármacos, otras enfermedades crónicas), duración de la insuficiencia renal y hemodiálisis (en meses), % pérdida de peso desde la hemodiálisis, ingestión de nutrientes derivada del análisis de la historia dietética (DIETPLAN5, 2003, RU). La escala EuroQOL que incluye 5 dimensiones de movilidad, autocuidado, actividades, dolor / malestar, ansiedad/depresión, y una escala analógica visual sobre salud global, evaluó la QOL.  Resultados: las estimaciones del efecto del tamaño atribuido a cada variable incluida en el modelo linear general mostraron que el 47% de las puntuaciones de los pacientes sobre movilidad/pérdida de peso empeoraban con una ingestión de deficiente de proteínas / energía y el 30% por una pérdida de peso &amp;#8805; 10%. El bajo rendimiento en las actividades habituales se atribuyó en un 45% a la duración de la hemodiálisis y de la enfermedad, el 70% a deficiencias de proteínas/energía/vitamina B12/cinc/hierro, y el 20% a una pérdida de peso &amp;#8805; 10%. El dolor/ansiedad empeoraban en un 45% por la duración de la hemodialysis y de la enfermedad, y en un 15% por comorbilidades. La mayor ansiedad/depresión se relacionó en un 43% con deficiencias de proteínas / energía/selenio y vitamina C, en un 40% por la duración de la hemodialysis y la enfermedad, en un 10% por una pérdida de peso &amp;#8805; 10%, y en un 3% a las comorbilidades. Asimismo, el 47% de la salud global mala vino determinado por deficiencias de proteína/energía/vitamina B12/cinc/selenio y vitamina C, 25% por pérdida de peso &amp;#8805; 10%, el 10% por la duración de la enfermedad, y el 7% por las comorbilidades.  Conclusiones: las proteínas, los antioxidantes y los micronutrientes clave implicados en el metabolismo proteico ejercieron un efecto principal sobre la calidad de vida de los pacientes. Dada la prevalencia de las deficiencias nutricionales, la alteración resultante de la capacidad funcional probablemente comprometa la calidad de vida, por lo que se debe garantizar una nutrición adecuada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;21(2): 139-144, mar.-abr. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046462</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Desempeña la nutrición un papel en la calidad de vida de los pacientes con hemodiálisis crónica?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
