<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106826</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Do we adequately prescribe antiplatelet treatment to type 2 diabetic patients?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To estimate how many type 2 diabetic patients receive antiplatelet therapy according to the American Diabetes Association (ADA) guidelines on primary and secondary prevention. Design. A descriptive, cross-sectional study based on information in medical records. A random sample of 170 type 2 diabetics seen in an urban Health Centre was studied. Measurements. The data collected including, age, sex, antiplatelet therapy according to the ADA, antiplatelet therapy indicated, cardiovascular risk factors, cardiovascular disease, and other clinical parameters. Results. Of the subjects analysed, 56.9% were males, and the mean age was 67.8 years. The majority of patients (71.2%) were on primary prevention, and 44.4% of the diabetics were receiving adequate antiplatelet therapy according to the ADA. Among the subjects on secondary prevention, 90.9% received adequate antiplatelet therapy, while only 25.7% of those on primary prevention received it, which was significant. The most used antiplatelet drug was acetylsalicylic acid (ASA). Conclusions. A large proportion of diabetes on primary prevention does not receive adequate antiplatelet therapy, according to the ADA. However, patients on secondary prevention receive sufficient antiplatelet treatment. The benefits of ASA in reducing cardiovascular disease are well documented in patients with cardiovascular disease. On the other hand, the role of antiplatelet therapy in diabetics on primary prevention is not clear and is the subject of discussion. From 2006 to 2011, the ADA has modified the recommendation level of primary prevention antiplatelet therapy, thus decreasing the percentage of patients that may be given antiplatelet therapy with ASA, to the extent that it increases the cardiovascular risk calculation required for its indication (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Salvanés, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego Arenas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Díaz, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Novella Arribas, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sierra García, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Estimar cuántos pacientes diabéticos tipo 2 deberían recibir tratamiento antiagregante, según las directrices de la Asociación Americana de Diabetes (ADA) en prevención primaria y secundaria. Diseño. Estudio descriptivo transversal, basado en información de historias clínicas. Muestra aleatoria de 170 diabéticos tipo 2 atendidos en el año 2006, en un centro de salud urbano. Mediciones. Edad, sexo, antiagregación según ADA, antiagregante indicado, factores de riesgo cardiovascular, eventos cardiovasculares, parámetros clínicos. Resultados. De los sujetos analizados, 56,9% eran varones, con edad media de 67,8 años. El 71,2% de los pacientes estaban en prevención primaria. El 44,4% de los diabéticos estaban adecuadamente antiagregados, según la ADA. Entre los sujetos en prevención secundaria están adecuadamente antiagregados el 90,9%, mientras que solamente lo están el 25,7% de los de prevención primaria, lo que es significativo. Cuando se antiagrega, el ácido acetilsalicílico (AAS) es el fármaco más usado. Conclusiones. Una gran proporción de diabéticos en prevención primaria no está adecuadamente antiagregada, según la ADA. Sin embargo existe una correcta antiagregación en los pacientes de prevención secundaria. El beneficio del AAS en la reducción de eventos cardiovasculares está correctamente documentado en pacientes con enfermedad cardiovascular. En cambio, el papel de la antiagregación en diabéticos de prevención primaria es poco conciso y objeto de discusión. Desde 2006 a 2011, la ADA ha modificado el grado de recomendación de antiagregación en prevención primaria, disminuyendo el porcentaje de pacientes susceptibles de recibir tratamiento antiagregante con AAS a medida que aumenta el cálculo del riesgo cardiovascular necesario para la indicación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);38(6): 360-365, sept. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106826</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Antiagregamos adecuadamente a los pacientes diabéticos tipo 2?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22965^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53393^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53393^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
