<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053765</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Yield diagnosis of the peripheral cores in 10 needle extended prostate biopsy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To value if the increase in the number of cylinders in the prostate´s biopsy raise the diagnostic performance        of this test.        Material and Method: In March 2005 we initiate this prospective study with patients who are subject to a first        prostate Biopsy by a PSA between 4 and 10 ng/ml and negative rectal touch. Transrectal, echodirected prostatic        biopsies with ten punctures are carried out according to the following programme as follows: 6 Biopsies according        to classic sextant technique, to what we add 4 cylinders from the most lateral zones of the prostate (lateral horns).        The variables are analyzed: Age, Total PSA, Free PSA/Total PSA, prostatic volume and PSA density.        Results: We value 90 patients consecutively. Prostatic adenocarcinoma was diagnosed to 37 of the 90 patients,        which means that the diagnostic rate of the extended Biopsy reached a 41 %. Nevertheless, the rate for the classic        sextant Biopsy was 32.3 %. These differences are statistically significant (Mcnemar test 0,008); besides, this        supposes a 27% increase in the diagnostic rentability. The 'extra' cylinders in the lateral horns detected 8        tumours which were not detected in the cylinders of the the sextant, and 5 of them presented a Gleason higher        or equal to 6.        Conclusions: In our centre we think that the Biopsy extended to 10 cylinders is an adequate strategy for potential        prostatic adenocarcinoma patients who are going to be subject to their first Biopsy. Realizing the clinic relevance        of the tumours diagnosed thanks to 'extra' cylinders, we do not think that this modality implies an overdiagnosis        and consequently an overtreatment of the prostate cancer</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bosquet Sanz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pontones Moreno, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Backhaus, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trassierra Villa, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arlandis Guzmán, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Cruz, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Valorar si el aumento del número de cilindros en la biopsia de próstata incrementa el rendimiento diagnóstico        de esta prueba.        Material y método: En marzo del 2005 iniciamos este estudio prospectivo pacientes que son sometidos a una primera        biopsia de próstata por un PSA entre 4 y 10 ng/ml y tacto rectal negativo. Se les lleva a cabo una biopsia        prostática transrectal ecodirigida con 10 punciones según el siguiente esquema: 6 biopsias según la técnica sextante        clásica, a los que añadimos 4 cilindros de las zonas más laterales de la próstata (cuernos laterales). Se analizan        las variables: Edad, PSA total, PSA libre/PSA total, volumen prostático y PSA densidad.        Resultados: Valoramos 90 pacientes consecutivos. Se diagnosticó adenocarcinoma prostático a 37 de los 90        pacientes, es decir, la tasa diagnóstica de la biopsia ampliada alcanzó el 41%. Sin embargo, la de la sextante clásica        fue del 32,2%. Estas diferencias fueron estadísticamente significativas (test de Mcnemar 0,008); además esto        supone un aumento en la rentabilidad diagnóstica del 27%. Los cilindros 'extra' en los cuernos laterales detectaron        8 tumores que no eran objetivados en los cilindros de la sextante, y 5 de ellos presentaban un Gleason        mayor o igual a 6.        Conclusiones: En nuestro centro, pensamos que la biopsia ampliada a 10 cilindros es una estrategia adecuada        para los pacientes con sospecha de adenocarcinoma prostático que van a ser sometidos a su primera biopsia.        Teniendo en cuenta la relevancia clínica de tumores dianosticados gracias a los cilindros 'extra'. No creemos que        esta modalidad implique un sobrediagnóstico y consecuente sobretratamiento del cáncer de próstata</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;31(1): 11-16, ene. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053765</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rentabilidad diagnóstica de los cilindros de los cuernos laterales en las biopsias prostáticas ampliadas a 10 muestras</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30596^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
