<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167344</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Change of care model in natural childbirth: implementation in La Ribera delivery room</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To assess knowledge, wish for inclusion and implementation of normal childbirth care protocols at La Ribera University Hospital, the reason why they are not applied, and to assess the attendance at antepartum training activities. Material and method. Cross-sectional descriptive study. They were carried out 186 surveys by convenience sampling to pregnant women attending fetal well-being control at hospital between 2014 and 2015. They were collected data about knowledge, wish for inclusion, compliance of protocols and reasons for non-compliance, and attendance at antepartum training activities. Percentages and confidence intervals were calculated. Chi-square test was used to compare categorical variables. Results. They were collected percentages of knowledge (77%, CI95%: 75,5-78,5) and wish for inclusion (84,6%, CI95%: 82,5-86,7). Protocol compliance ranged from 6% (nitrous oxide administration) to 91% (skin-to-skin contact). The main reasons for non-compliance were due to circumstances of childbirth process (56,3%, CI95%: 51,1-61,5). Attendance at maternal education classes was 62%, mainly primiparous women (p=0,0001) with medium or high education level (p=0,001). Conclusions. Pregnant women have a high knowledge and wish for inclusion of normal childbirth care protocols. Attendance at antepartum training activities could by improved and the main reason for non-attendance is lack of information. Compliance is good enough in most protocols; when they are not applied is due to childbirth circumstances. Remaining tasks include the introduction of additional protocols and to involve pregnant women in decision-making (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romero-Martín, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camacho-Morell, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Valorar el conocimiento, el deseo de inclusión y la aplicación, en el Hospital Universitario de La Ribera, de los protocolos de atención al parto normal, valorando los motivos por los que no se aplican y el cumplimiento de la asistencia a actividades formativas preparto. Material y método. Estudio descriptivo transversal. Realización de 186 encuestas mediante muestreo de conveniencia a gestantes que acudieron a control de bienestar fetal en el hospital entre 2014 y 2015. Se recogieron datos sobre conocimiento, deseo de inclusión y cumplimiento de protocolos, motivos de no cumplimiento y asistencia a actividades formativas. Se calcularon porcentajes e intervalos de confianza. Se utilizó test de la Chi-cuadrado para comparación de variables categóricas. Resultados. Se recogieron porcentajes de conocimiento del 77% (IC95%: 75,5-78,5) y de deseo de inclusión del 84,6% (IC95%: 82,5-86,7) de los protocolos. El cumplimiento varió desde el 6% (administración de óxido nitroso) hasta el 91% (contacto piel con piel). El principal motivo de no cumplimiento fue el relacionado con las circunstancias del parto (56,3%, IC95%: 51,1-61,5). La asistencia a la preparación al parto fue del 62%, con mayor cumplimiento en primíparas (p=0,0001) con nivel de estudios medio-alto (p=0,001). Conclusiones. Las gestantes tienen un elevado conocimiento y deseo de inclusión de los protocolos de atención al parto normal. La asistencia a actividades formativas preparto es mejorable y el principal motivo de no asistencia es la falta de información. El cumplimiento es bueno en la mayoría de los protocolos; cuando no se aplican es debido a las circunstancias del parto. Queda pendiente introducir protocolos aún sin implantar e implicar a las gestantes en la toma de decisiones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;32(5): 255-261, sept.-oct. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167344</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambio de modelo asistencial en la atención al parto normal: aplicación en el paritorio de La Ribera</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7926</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23920</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
