<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77583</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Obtain best usage of meropenem dose in severe infections. Results of an observational multicenter study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To describe the effectiveness and tolerabilityof the dose adjustment of meropenem in empiricaltreatment of nosocomial infections in critically-ill patientsadmitted to intensive care medicine services.Methods. Prospective, observational and multicenterstudy in patients admitted to 17 intensive care medicineservices with nosocomial infection, who were initiallytreated with meropenem, 1 g every 8 h, were eligible.The initial dose was adjusted to 0.5 g every 8 h if therewere: a) a favorable clinical course, and b) microbiologicalisolation of meropenem-susceptible pathogens or absenceof pathogens in cultures.Results. Ninety-two patients in whom meropenemdoses were adjusted to 0.5 g every 8 h were included.Ventilator-associated pneumonia followed by bacteremiawas the most frequently treated infections. Microbiologicalstudies were positive in 53 patients, with apredominance of gram-positive bacteria (53.7%), especiallymethicillin-susceptible Staphylococcus aureus,followed by gram-negative bacteria (42.7 %). A total of18 patients were not evaluable at the end of treatmentSixty-seven (90.5 %) of the 74 evaluable patients had afavorable clinical course (54 patients cured and 13 improved).In 50 out of 53 microbiologically evaluable cases,eradication or apparent eradication of initial microorganismswas achieved. In 3 cases, the initial pathogenpersisted: Acinetobacter baumannii (2 cases) and Pseudomonasaeruginosa (1 case). On three occasions, new pathogensdeveloped during treatment: A. baumannii (2cases) and methicillin-resistant S. aureus (1 case). Adverseevents occurred in 3 patients (4%), none of whichwas considered severe, and withdrawal of meropenemwas not necessary. A total of 25 (27.2 %) patients died,three of them in relation to the infectious process(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Quero, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Sánchez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Lerma, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sancho Ruiz, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Ferrón, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Describir la efectividad y tolerabilidad delajuste de dosis de meropenem en el tratamiento empíricode infecciones nosocomiales en pacientes críticos ingresadosen Servicios de Medicina Intensiva (SMI).Método. Estudio prospectivo, observacional y multicéntricode pacientes ingresados en 17 SMI con infecciones nosocomialesy tratamiento inicial con meropenem a dosis de1 g cada 8 h. Se ajustó la dosis inicial a 0,5 g cada 8 h cuandocumplían las siguientes condiciones: a) evolución clínicafavorable y b) un aislamiento microbiológico sensible a meropenemo ausencia de microorganismos en los cultivos realizados.Resultados. Se incluyeron 92 pacientes en los que seajustó la dosis de meropenem a 0,5 g cada 8 h. La infeccióntratada más frecuentemente fue la neumonía relacionadacon ventilación mecánica, seguido de las bacteriemias. Losestudios microbiológicos fueron positivos en 53 pacientesen los que predominaron bacterias grampositivas (53,7 %),en especial Staphylococcus aureus sensible a la meticilina,seguido de bacterias gramnegativas (42,7%).En 18 casos los pacientes no fueron evaluables al finaldel tratamiento. De los 74 casos evaluables, 67 (90,5%) presentaronuna evolución favorable (curación: 54 pacientes;mejoría: 13). En 50 de los 53 casos evaluables por Microbiologíase logró la erradicación o supuesta erradicación de losmicroorganismos iniciales y en 3 persistió el patógeno inicial:Acinetobacter baumannii (2 casos) y Pseudomonasaeruginosa (1 caso). Se detectó la aparición de nuevos microorganismosdurante el tratamiento en tres ocasiones: A. baumannii(2 casos) y 1 de S. aureus resistente a la meticilina.Aparecieron efectos adversos en 3 pacientes (4%), ninguno valorado como grave, que no precisaron la retirada del tratamiento.Fallecieron 25 (27,2%) pacientes, 3 de ellos en relacióncon la infección (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;21(3): 143-148, sep. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77583</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Optimización de la dosis de meropenem en infecciones graves. Resultados de un estudio multicéntrico observacional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30071^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30071^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30071^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30071^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24550^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24550^s22065</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24550^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32073^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24550^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32073^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30071^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200809</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
