<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161520</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Preemptive hemodynamic intervention restricting the administration of fluids attenuates lung edema progression in oleic acid-induced lung injury</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: A study is made of the influence of preemptive hemodynamic intervention restricting fluid administration upon the development of oleic acid-induced lung injury. Design: A randomized in vivo study in rabbits was carried out. Setting: University research laboratory. Subjects: Sixteen anesthetized, mechanically ventilated rabbits. Variables: Hemodynamic measurements obtained by transesophageal Doppler signal. Respiratory mechanics computed by a least square fitting method. Lung edema assessed by the ratio of wet weight to dry weight of the right lung. Histological examination of the left lung. Interventions: Animals were randomly assigned to either the early protective lung strategy (EPLS) (n=8) or the early protective hemodynamic strategy (EPHS) (n=8). In both groups, lung injury was induced by the intravenous infusion of oleic acid (OA) (0.133mlkg&amp;#8722;1h&amp;#8722;1 for 2h). At the same time, the EPLS group received 15mlkg&amp;#8722;1h&amp;#8722;1 of Ringer lactate solution, while the EPHS group received 30mlkg&amp;#8722;1h&amp;#8722;1. Measurements were obtained at baseline and 1 and 2h after starting OA infusion. Results: After 2h, the cardiac index decreased in the EPLS group (p&lt;0.05), whereas in the EPHS group it remained unchanged. Lung compliance decreased significantly only in the EPHS group (p&lt;0.05). Lung edema was greater in the EPHS group (p&lt;0.05). Histological damage proved similar in both groups (p=0.4). Conclusions: In this experimental model of early lung injury, lung edema progression was attenuated by preemptively restricting the administration of fluids (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guijo González, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Cano, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monge García, MI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Campos, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gracia Romero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo:  Conocer cómo influye una intervención hemodinámica preventiva basada en la restricción de fluidos sobre el desarrollo de la lesión pulmonar inducida por la administración de ácido oleico. Diseño: Estudio aleatorizado en animales vivos. Lugar: Laboratorio universitario de investigación experimental. Variables: Mecánica respiratoria (método de los mínimos cuadrados), medidas hemodinámicas (doppler esofágico), estimación del edema pulmonar (relación peso húmedo/seco del pulmón derecho) y daño histológico del pulmón izquierdo. Intervenciones: Ocho animales fueron asignados a un grupo con una estrategia protectora pulmonar (EPP), y otros 8 a otro grupo con una estrategia protectora hemodinámica (EPH). En ambos grupos la lesión pulmonar se desencadenó mediante la administración intravenosa de ácido oleico (0,133mL/kg&amp;#8722;1/h&amp;#8722;1 durante 2h), recibiendo simultáneamente los animales del grupo EPP 15mL/kg&amp;#8722;1/h&amp;#8722;1 de Ringer Lactato y los del grupo EPH 30mLKg&amp;#8722;1h&amp;#8722;1. Se obtuvieron medidas basales, a la hora y a las 2h. Resultados: Transcurridas las 2h de experimento el índice cardiaco permaneció estable en el grupo EPH, pero disminuyó en el grupo EPP (p&lt;0,05). Por el contrario, la distensibilidad pulmonar disminuyó significativamente solo en el grupo EPH (p&lt;0,05), en el cual el edema pulmonar estimado mediante la relación peso húmedo/seco del pulmón derecho fue mayor (p&lt;0,05). El daño histológico fue similar en ambos grupos (p=0,4). Conclusiones: En este modelo experimental de lesión pulmonar aguda en fase inicial, la formación del edema pulmonar fue atenuada por la restricción preventiva en la administración de fluidos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);41(3): 135-142, abr. 2017. tab, graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161520</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La restricción preventiva en la administración de fluidos disminuye la formación del edema en la lesión pulmonar inducida por ácido oleico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12549^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53086^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4255</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1652^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32388</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4387^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32976^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12091^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
