<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106368</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Glucagon-like peptide 1 and cardiac cell survival</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">During myocardial infarction (MI), a variety of mechanisms contribute to activation of cell death processes in cardiomyocytes, which determines the &amp;#64257;nal MI size, subsequent mortality, and post-MI remodeling. The deleterious mechanisms activated during the ischemia and reperfusion phases in MI include oxygen deprival, decreased availability of nutrients and survivalfactors, accumulation of waste products, generation of oxygen free radicals, calcium overload, neutrophil in&amp;#64257;ltration in the ischemic area, depletion of energy stores, and opening of themitochondrial permeability transition pore, all of them contributing to activation of apoptosis and necrosis in cardiomyocytes. Glucagon-like peptide-1 [GLP-1 (7-36) amide] has gained relevance in recent years for metabolic treatment of patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus. Cytoprotection of different cell types, including cardiomyocytes, is among the pleiotropicactions reported for GLP-1. This paper reviews the most relevant experimental studies that have contributed to a better understanding of the molecular mechanisms and intracellular pathways involved in cardioprotection induced by GLP-1 and analyzes in depth its potential role as a therapeutic target both in the ischemic and reperfused myocardium and in other conditions that are associated with myocardial remodeling and heart failure (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díez, Javiera</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ravassa, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zudaire, Amaia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La activación de diferentes procesos de muerte celular en los cardiomiocitos tras un infarto de miocardio (IM) contribuye al tamaño final del infarto, a la mortalidad subsecuente y al remodelado postinfarto en los supervivientes. Los diversos mecanismos deletéreos activados durante las fases de isquemia y reperfusión en el IM incluyen la privación de oxígeno, la disponibilidad reducida de nutrientes y factores de supervivencia, la acumulación de residuos, la generación de especies reactivas del oxígeno, la sobrecarga de calcio, la infiltración por neutrófilos en el área isquémica, la depleción energética, y la apertura del poro de transición de permeabilidad mitocondrial, todos ellos mecanismos de activación de apoptosis y necrosis en los cardiomiocitos. En los últimos años, las terapias basadas en el péptido similar al glucagón tipo 1 [GLP-1 (7-36) amida] han adquirido mayor relevancia como tratamiento metabólico de la diabetes mellitus tipo 2. Entre las acciones atribuidas a GLP-1 destaca la preservación de la viabilidad en diferentes tipos celulares, entre ellos los cardiomiocitos. Este artículo revisa los principales estudios experimentales que han contribuido a una mayor comprensión de la citoprotección inducida por GLP-1 en el miocardio y de sus efectos en la función cardiaca, ahondando en el estudio de su papel como diana terapéutica, no solo en el contexto de la diabetes mellitus sino también en otras patologías que cursan con remodelado cardiaco (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;59(9): 561-569, nov. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106368</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Péptido similar al glucagón tipo 1 y supervivencia de la célula cardiaca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50567^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30827</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2357^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201211</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
