<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100870</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The pre-school feeding, health education from 2 to 6 years</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The infant feeding and nutrition is one of the most important areas regarding the Health Education (HE). This health-promoting action must start at the early stage of the development and learning, such as the pre-school period. A valuable tool to initiate successfully the HE could be infant nutrition, which can and must be also approached in the educational area. Our objective of the investigation was to gather, from the main Spanish manuals of nutrition, the basic and nutritional characteristics of the stage from 2 to 6 years, in order to be used by educational personnel instead of health personnel in the school area. By the analysis of bibliographical documented review, related to the nutritional characteristics at this stage of growth. The results indicate that the Recommendations Dietary Allowance (RDA) from 2 years are very different with regard to the breast-fed stage, the contribution moves towards the carbohydrates in 50 %, in decline of fats &lt;30 % and proteins. In addition, the preparation and incorporation of new ingredients to the daily foods is already regular, obtaining, in this way, a balanced and healthy diet. For that, we will follow a guideline of 3 daily foods, with 2 intermediate of minor quantity, and the breakfast will have a well-deserved importance. To conclude, we must indicate that the educator has to inculcate healthy habits of feeding in pre-school stage by means of the Health Education. The mentioned infant diet will be the base for a healthy adulthood, since during the infant stage, future pathologies may emerge such as diabetes, cancer of colon and hypertension (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Padez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, A. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calderón, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Costillo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañada, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cubero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La alimentación y nutrición infantil constituye una de las áreas de mayor importancia dentro de la Educación para la Salud (EpS). Esta acción promotora de la salud debe iniciarse en la fase temprana del desarrollo y aprendizaje, como es la etapa preescolar. Una valiosa herramienta para iniciar la EpS es la alimentación infantil, la cual puede y debe ser abordada en el ámbito educativo. Por ello, nuestro objetivo de investigación fue recoger, de los principales manuales de nutrición españoles, las características básicas, nutricionales, de la etapa de 2 a 6 años, para ser utilizado por personal docente no sanitario en el ámbito escolar. Mediante análisis de revisión bibliográfica documentada, referente a las características nutricionales de esta etapa de crecimiento. Los resultados indican que las Recomendaciones Diarias Alimenticias (RDA) a partir de los 2 años son muy diferentes respecto a la etapa de lactante, el aporte se balancea hacía los carbohidratos en un 50%, en decremento de grasas &lt;30% y proteínas. Además, la preparación e incorporación de nuevos ingredientes a los platos diarios es ya una constante, obteniendo nuevas y atractivas características organolépticas para conseguir una dieta equilibrada y saludable. Para ello, se seguirá una pauta de 3 comidas, con 2 intermedias de menor cantidad, y donde el desayuno ya tendrá una merecida importancia. Para concluir, además debemos indicar que el educador a través de la EpS debe trasmitir e inculcar, desde esta temprana edad, hábitos de vida saludable a través de la alimentación infantil. Ya que esta dieta infantil será la base de una etapa adulta saludable, pues es en la etapa infantil donde se fraguan futuras patologías como diabetes, cáncer de colon e hipertensión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;11(27): 337-345, jul. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100870</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La alimentación preescolar, educación para la salud de los 2 a los 6 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5350^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33527^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16566^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52507^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32109^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33527^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52507^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201207</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
