<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149114</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The neuropaediatrci and pathogenic clinical bases of autistic spectrum disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The dimension of the autistic spectrum embraces a considerable degree of clinical complexity which is, in turn, an expression of the numerous systems involved in the functioning of the central nervous system. Every day different biological factors are revealed which put in doubt other factors that, in a more objective way, appear to be involved in a particular aetiology. Conclusions. It is clear that exactly what causes autistic spectrum disorder is still unknown and it may be useful to analyse cases with a known aetiology and correlate them with other similar cases, as it is likely to be this association between findings and studies in the future that will probably enable us to better define the bases and the underlying causes of the complex and manifold origin of the autistic spectrum. This will enable a more efficient therapeutic approach to be developed, which, when all is said and done, is what is primarily sought in the management of children with autistic spectrum disorder (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Etchepareborda, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mulas, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Muela, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abad Mas, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La dimensión del espectro autista abarca una complejidad clínica considerable que es, a su vez, expresión de la multitud de sistemas implicados en el funcionamiento del sistema nervioso central; cada día se evidencian distintos factores biológicos que ponen en discusión los factores que, de una forma más objetiva, parecen implicados en una etiología definida. Conclusiones. Es evidente que todavía no se conocen con precisión las causas determinantes del espectro autista y posiblemente sea útil analizar los casos con una etiología conocida y correlacionarlos con otros similares, siendo esta asociación de hallazgos y los estudios futuros los que probablemente permitan definir mejor las bases y el substrato del origen complejo y múltiple del espectro autista. Ello posibilitará un acercamiento terapéutico mas eficaz, que, en definitiva, es el anhelo primordial para el abordaje de los niños con espectro autista (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;38(supl.1): s9-s14, feb. 2004.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149114</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bases clínicas neuropediátricas y patogénicas del trastorno del espectro autista</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7980</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8738^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3102^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
