<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112100</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perineal pain effect on the activities of women who had an episiotomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: This manuscript discusses the influence of the perineal pain after normal birth on daily activities of women who had an episiotomy. Methods: Descriptive study with data collected through interviews performed from 20 to 48 hours after delivery, with 52 women, applying the pain numeric scale (0-10). Results: Perineal pain was present in 86.5% and 82.7% of women, at 20 and 48 hours after delivery, respectively. There was a predominance of mild pain (64.4% to 72.1%), followed by moderate pain (28.9% to 18.6%). The restriction of the activities varied between 92.3% and 86.5% women, from 20 to 48 hours after delivery, respectively. Conclusions: Although most women had reported mild pain, it was noted that this morbidity limits the essential activities (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gonzalez Riesco, María Luiza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vasconcellos de Oliveira, Sonia María Junqueira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amorim Francisco, Adriana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leister, Nathalie</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barbosa da Silva, Flora María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliveira Santos, Jaqueline de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo principal: Este artículo discute la influencia del dolor perineal después del parto normal en las actividades diarias de las mujeres con episiotomía. Metodología: Estudio descriptivo con recolección de datos a través de entrevistas con 52 mujeres entre 20 y 48 horas después del parto, con aplicación de la escala numérica de dolor (0-10). Resultados principales: El dolor perineal estuvo presente entre 86,5% y 82,7% de las mujeres, a las 20 y 48 horas, respectivamente. Hubo un predominio del dolor leve (64,4% a 72,1%), seguido de moderado (28,9% a 18,6%). La restricción de las actividades varió entre 92,3% y 86,5% de las mujeres, 20 y 48 horas después del parto, respectivamente. Conclusión principal: Aunque de la mayoría de las mujeres después del parto atribuye nota de intensidad leve, se señaló que esto limita las actividades esenciales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;21(3): 150-154, jul.-sept. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112100</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto del dolor perineal en las actividades de mujeres sometidas a episiotomía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4920^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3708^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10693</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
