<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166413</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Heart failure in women: sex differences in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Few studies have been carried out on the specific characteristics of heart failure in women. The proportion of women included in major clinical trials on heart failure is under 20%, while women account for almost half of all hospital admissions for heart failure. Consequently, increased understanding of the actual status of heart failure in women is needed. The aim of this study was to investigate possible sex differences in the prevalence, clinical characteristics, diagnostic assessment, treatment and short- and long-term prognosis of heart failure in Spain. We analyzed data from clinical and observational studies organized by the Section of Heart Failure, Heart Transplantation and Associated Therapies of the Spanish Society of Cardiology during the last 10 years in Spain (i.e., the PRICE, BADAPIC, RAIC and ATIICA studies). The prevalence of heart failure was similar in men and women (6.5% and 7%, respectively). Among patients admitted with acute heart failure (RAIC study), women were older than man, were more likely to have a history of hypertension or diabetes mellitus, were less likely to have a history of coronary heart disease, and were more likely to have heart failure with preserved systolic function. Cardiac catheterization was performed in a smaller proportion of women and they received beta-blockers less frequently. In-hospital mortality and mortality 3 months after discharge were similar in men and women. The demographic, pathophysiological and clinical characteristics found in outpatients with chronic heart failure (BADAPIC study) were similar to those observed in the RAIC study: a smaller proportion of women than men received beta-blockers, angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors and angiotensin-II receptor antagonists, and lower doses were given. Long-term survival was similar in men and women, though women were more frequently admitted for decompensated heart failure. In the ATIICA study, female sex was found to be an independent predictor of low ACE-inhibitor, but not beta-blocker, use (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Anguita-Sánchez, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Navarro, Manuel F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las características específicas de la insuficiencia cardiaca en la mujer han sido poco estudiadas. La proporción de mujeres incluidas en los grandes ensayos clínicos sobre insuficiencia cardiaca es inferior al 20%, mientras que casi la mitad de los ingresos hospitalarios por este problema son de mujeres. Por ello, es importante conocer cuál es la realidad de la insuficiencia cardiaca en mujeres en nuestro entorno. El objetivo de este trabajo es evaluar las posibles diferencias por sexo en la prevalencia, las características clínicas, las medidas diagnósticas, el tratamiento y el pronóstico a corto y largo plazo de la insuficiencia cardiaca en España. Para ello, hemos analizado los estudios y registros de la Sección de Insuficiencia Cardiaca, Trasplante Cardiaco y otras alternativas terapéuticas de la Sociedad Española de Cardiología realizados en los últimos 10 años en nuestro país (estudios PRICE, BADAPIC, RAIC y ATIICA). Las prevalencias de insuficiencia cardiaca en mujeres y varones fueron similares (el 7 y el 6,5%, respectivamente). Entre los pacientes ingresados por insuficiencia cardiaca (estudio RAIC), las mujeres tienen mayor edad, más antecedentes de hipertensión arterial y diabetes y menos de cardiopatía isquémica, y mayor proporción de casos con función sistólica conservada. Se realizan en ellas menos cateterismos cardiacos que en los varones y se utilizan con menor frecuencia fármacos como los bloqueadores beta. La mortalidad durante el ingreso y a los 3 meses del alta fue similar en mujeres y varones. En pacientes seguidos ambulatoriamente (estudio BADAPIC), las características demográficas, clínicas y fisiopatológicas son similares a las encontradas en el estudio RAIC; las mujeres con insuficiencia cardiaca recibieron bloqueadores beta, inhibidores de la enzima de conversión de angiotensina y antagonistas del receptor de la angiotensina II en menor proporción que los varones y a dosis más bajas. La supervivencia a largo plazo fue similar en mujeres y varones, aunque las mujeres tuvieron una mayor incidencia de ingresos por descompensación de la insuficiencia cardiaca. En el estudio ATIICA, el sexo femenino fue predictor independiente de un menor uso de inhibidores de la enzima de conversión de angiotensina, pero no de bloqueadores beta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);8(supl.D): 23d-29d, 2008. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166413</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Insuficiencia cardiaca en la mujer. Diferencias de sexo en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22832^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13113^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200800</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
