<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038997</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prognostic value of troponin plasma levels in pulmonary thromboembolism: a systematic review and meta-analysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Analyze possible association between serum troponin levels and clinical evolution of patients with pulmonary thromboembolism through a systematic review of the literature. Data source. Search for original studies in Medline, Embase, Cochrane Library, Pascal, Medion and ISI Proceedings, and review of the references of the recovered articles. Study selection. Cohort studies with information on initial levels of troponin and occurrence of hospital mortality, unfavorable clinical course, or right ventricular overload in the echocardiogram were chosen. Data extraction. Data of the odds radio (OR), sensitivity, specificity, likelihood ratios (LR), population studied, type of test used, and methodology quality of the study were obtained in duplicate. Results. A total of 13 studies, that included 1,293 patients, were identified. The studies were relatively homogeneous for each outcome and no threshold effect or signs of publication bias were detected. Elevated levels of troponin identified a subgroup of patients with high risk of: dying during hospitalization (OR 6.20; 95% CI 4.04-9.52), presenting echocardiographic signs of right ventricular overload (OR 8.04; 95% CI 4.40-16.69) and having an unfavorable clinical course (OR 14.58; 95% CI 6.82-31.16). Normal levels of troponin identified a group of patients with favorable clinical course (LR 0.23; 95% CI 0.13-0.41). Conclusions. Troponin levels are useful to stratify risk in patients with pulmonary thromboembolism. In the individual patient, normal levels of troponin indicate a high likelihood of having an uncomplicated clinical course</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Latour-Pérez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Artola, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palencia-Herrejón, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gordo-Vidal, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Analizar, mediante una revisión sistemática de la literatura, la posible asociación entre los niveles de troponina en el suero y la evolución clínica de los pacientes con tromboembolismo pulmonar. Fuente de datos. Búsqueda de trabajos originales en Medline, Embase, Cochrane Library, Pascal, Medion e ISI Proceedings, y revisión de las referencias de los artículos recuperados. Selección de estudios. Se seleccionaron estudios de cohortes con información sobre los niveles iniciales de troponina y la ocurrencia de mortalidad hospitalaria, evolución clínica desfavorable o sobrecarga ventricular derecha en el ecocardiograma. Extracción de datos. Se obtuvieron por duplicado datos de odds ratio (OR), sensibilidad, especificidad, cocientes de probabilidad (CP), población estudiada, tipo de prueba utilizada y calidad metodológica del estudio. Resultados. Se identificaron 13 estudios, que incluían 1.293 pacientes. Los estudios fueron relativamente homogéneos para cada desenlace, y no se detectaron efecto umbral ni indicios de sesgo de publicación. Los niveles elevados de troponina identificaron a un subgrupo de pacientes con alto riesgo de: fallecer durante la hospitalización (OR 6,20; intervalo de confianza al 95% [IC 95%] 4,04-9,52), presentar signos ecocardiográficos de sobrecarga ventricular derecha (OR 8,04; IC 95% 4,40-16,69) y tener una evolución clínica desfavorable (OR 14,58; IC 95% 6,82-31,16). Los niveles normales de troponina identificaron a pacientes con evolución clínica favorable (CP ponderado 0,23; IC 95% 0,13-0,41). Conclusiones. Los niveles de troponina son útiles para estratificar el riesgo en pacientes con tromboembolismo pulmonar. En el paciente individual, unos niveles normales de troponina indican una alta probabilidad de seguir un curso clínico no complicado</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);29(6): 329-337, ago. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038997</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valor pronóstico de los niveles plasmáticos de troponina en el tromboembolismo pulmonar: una revisión sistemática y metaanálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30967</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31981^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23233^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12092^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14739^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12092^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
