<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053735</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Contralateral hemithyroidectomy due to carcinoma of the thyroid. Our cases reviewed and updated</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: We are reporting our 14 years' experience with prior hemithyroidectomies or contralateral hemithyroidectomies after a pathology result reporting malignancy (thyroid carcinoma) in the first surgery.                 Material and method: Twenty female patients with an average age of 45 years old have been studied and we have analyzed the initial symptoms, results of complementary tests, pathology diagnosis following initial surgery, and final outcome after a second intervention.                 Results: The incidence of malignancy shown in our series after secondary surgery was 40 % and the percentage of hemithyroidectomy on hemithyroidectomy was 3 % after operating on 650 thyroid glands.                 Conclusions: Though opinions differ in the medical literature, we feel a total thyroidectomy must be performed after a casual finding of thyroid carcinoma because of the oncologically safer outcome and the better control of the patient</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pereda Tamayo, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Palomino, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pantoja Hernández, Carlos G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ambel Albarrán, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora Santos, María Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marqués Rebollo, Luis E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pino Rivero, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo Romero, Guillerma</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Se presenta nuestra experiencia de 14 años en hemitiroidectomías sobre hemitiroidectomías previas o hemitiroidectomías contralaterales tras un resultado anatomopatológico de malignidad (carcinoma de tiroides) en la primera cirugía.                 Material y método: Hemos incluido a 20 pacientes, todas ellas mujeres, con una media de edad de 45 años. Se analizan los síntomas clínicos iniciales, los resultados de las exploraciones complementarias, el diagnóstico anatomopatológico de la primera intervención y el resultado final tras la segunda cirugía.                 Resultados: En nuestra serie la segunda hemitiroidectomía resultó positiva en un 40 % y el porcentaje de hemitiroidectomías sobre hemitiroidectomías de 650 tiroides operados fue del 3 %.                 Conclusiones: Aunque hay diferentes opiniones en la literatura médica, nosotros creemos que ante el hallazgo casual de un carcinoma tiroideo se debe completar una tiroidectomía total, por su mayor seguridad oncológica y mejor control del paciente</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;58(3): 101-104, mar. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053735</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hemitiroidectomía contralateral por carcinoma de tiroides. Nuestra casuística revisada y actualizada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22696^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22696^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9557^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
