<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045578</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Family caregivers in the University Hospital Traumatologia in Granada</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Generally hospitalization affects familiar relationships and it also obvies to take certain changes in families' routine. That is why family caregivers have acquired an important role, as they fulfil the needs of the patients. Most of the times, this activity is performed by women.Aims: The aims of this article are: to explain family care givers profile and the kind of care they provide in the following units: Maxilofacial, Neurology, Neurosurgery and Traumatology in the University Hospital Traumatología y Rehabilitación in Granada.This article will analyse different needs and problems family caregivers find within the hospital and inform about nurses opinion concerning the role of family caregivers.Design: A qualitative design has been used by means of systematic observation and focal group. Surveys and in-depth interviews have been carried out within 2 different groups:nurses and auxiliary nurses. The results obtained have been analysed by the programme Atlas/ti 2.4.Results: The results mentioned above were the appropriate for a hospital in relation with family caregivers as far as activities, level of information, and requests are concerned.Conclusión: On the whole atmosphere in hospitals is somehow hostile to family caregivers. For this reason it will be convenient to set up a different kind of professional relations between health staff and family caregivers. Moreover, it is necessary to recognize the importance of family caregivers role in the hospital</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pascual Martinez, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quero Rufian, Aurora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Lopez, Adela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerrero Ruiz, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Briones Gomez, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La hospitalización afecta a la dinámica de las relaciones familiares y obliga a cambios en la representación de los roles habituales. El papel de los cuidadores familiares adquiere toda su relevancia en la medida que satisfacen las necesidades del enfermo. Esta actividad en la mayoría de los casos es realizada por mujeres.Objetivos: Conocer el perfil y tipo de cuidados que prestan los cuidadores familiares en las unidades de Maxilofacial, Neurología, Neurocirugía y Traumatología del Hospital de Traumatología de Granada. Analizar las necesidades y problemas con los que se encuentran en el hospital. Conocer la opinión del personal de enfermería sobre el cuidador familiar.Diseño: Cualitativo, mediante Observación sistemática, grupos focales (uno con enfermeras y otro con auxiliares), encuestas y entrevistas en profundidad. El análisis de contenido ha sido realizado mediante el soporte informático Atlas/ti, 2.4.Resultados: correspondientes a la categoría de hábitat hospitalario, en relación con las actividades, nivel de información, demandas, etc, de los cuidadores familiares.Conclusiones: El ámbito hospitalario es hostil para el cuidador familiar; es necesario es¬tablecer un nuevo marco relacional entre los profesionales y los cuidadores y reconocer su presencia y actividad dentro de la institución sanitaria</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;14(48/49): 14-17, ene.-abr. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045578</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los cuidadores familiares en el Hospital Universitario de Traumatología y Rehabilitación de Granada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28598</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6930^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6940^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11797</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25783</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
