<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147276</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Performance variability in basketball players with intellectual impairment: Ankara World Championships 2013 analysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of the present study was to identify performance variability in basketball for players with intellectual impairment (II) and to compare it with able-bodied (AB) players. Official game statistics from the 13 games played in the Ankara World II-Basketball Championships (2013) were gathered and descriptive data, variability coefficient (VC), maximum scores and its Z-score were calculated from those players who participated at least 10 minutes per game (N = 46; guards = 10, forwards = 21, centers = 15). Results indicated higher performance variability and lower efficiency in shooting percentages and turnovers in II-players comparing with studies in ABplayers. Differences found between game positions indicated similar roles of guards, forwards and centers in II and AB-players. These findings are relevant to understand how II impact on basketball performance, which is a necessary step to develop specific eligibility systems in II-basketball according to the guidelines of the International Paralympic Committee (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Tejero, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Van Biesen, Debbie</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vanlandewijck, Yves</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinilla, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente estudio fue identificar la variabilidad en el rendimiento en baloncesto para personas con discapacidad intelectual (DI) y compararlo con jugadores sin DI. Las estadísticas oficiales de juego de los 13 partidos disputados en los Campeonatos del Mundo de Baloncesto para personas con DI de Ankara (2013) fueron recogidas y se analizaron las variables descriptivas, los coeficientes de variabilidad (CV), indicadores máximos y su correspondiente valor-Z en aquellos jugadores que participaron al menos 10 minutos por partido (N= 46; bases = 10, aleros = 21 y pívots = 15). Los resultados indicaron una mayor variabilidad en el rendimiento y una menor eficacia en el porcentaje de tiro y en las pérdidas de balón en jugadores con DI comparado con estudios en jugadores sin DI. Las diferencias encontradas entre las posiciones de juego indicaron roles similares de los bases, aleros y pívots en jugadores con y sin DI. Estos descubrimientos son relevantes para entender el impacto de la DI sobre el rendimiento en baloncesto, lo cual es un paso necesario para el desarrollo de sistemas específicos de elegibilidad en baloncesto para personas con DI de acuerdo a las directrices del Comité Paralímpico Internacional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;24(supl.1): 77-83, 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147276</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la variabilidad del rendimeinto en jugadores de baloncesto con discapacidad intelectual. Campeonato del mundo Ankara 2013</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24884</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
