<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90802</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-4723</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Trachoma is a keratoconjunctivitis caused by ocular infection with Chlamydia trachomatis. Is the second cause of blindness worldwide and the first avoidable. To fight against this epidemic the World Health Organization WHO has developed a program called SAFE for diagnostic, prevention, control and treatment. Population based surveys and new medications like azithromycinare basic to get this effort. To teach and train Ophthalmic Medical Assistants (OMAS) is very important to give people &#147;in situ&#147; trichias is surgery and health facilities to decrease the number of&#148; unnecessarily blindness&#148; (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Loscos, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cámara, Julio de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mariela, Vito</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tracoma es una queratoconjuntivitis causada por la Clamidea trachomatis. Es la segunda causa mundial de ceguera y la primera de causa prevenible. Para luchar contra esta epidemiala Organización Mundial de la Salud (OMS) junto a otras asociaciones han desarrollado el programa SAFE de diagnóstico prevención y tratamiento. Los estudios epidemiológicos son básicos para poder diseñar estrategias de prevención y tratamiento con los nuevos fármacos, como la azitromicina son muy importantes. La formación y la incorporación de enfermeros especialistas en Oftalmología para realizar técnicas quirúrgicas específicas &#147;in situ&#148; son fundamentales para poder disminuir el número de los &#147;innecesariamente ciegos&#148; (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. emerg;11(2): 85-90, abr.-jun. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90802</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El Tracoma: la ceguera de los pobres</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23966^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31627^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27872^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28259^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33154^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2738^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
