<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047117</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prognostic significance of the hepatopulmonary syndrome in liver cirrhosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: The prognosis of hepatopulmonary syndrome (HPS) has been only rarely investigated. Patients and method: We investigated the survival of 32 cirrhotic patients, 14 (44%) with HPS and 18 with a normal gaseous exchange (NGE), and the associated factors. Results: During a mean (standard deviation) of 56 (27) months, 9 patients in the HPS group (relative risk: 0.64) and 4 patients in the NGE group (relative risk: 0.22) died. The odds ratio was 6.42 (p &lt; 0.01; 95% confidence interval, 0.04-0.80). Patients in the HPS group died after 44 (31) months, while patients in the NGE group died 65 (21) months after inclusion (p &lt; 0.05). Overall, 46% of deaths were liver related. Factors associated with death were the right to left shunting and the increased plasmatic renin levels. Of note, the plasmatic volume and diffusing capacity were protective. Conclusions: The coexistence of HPS worsens the prognosis in liver cirrhosis</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Anniccherico Sánchez, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Martínez, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zozaya Urmeneta, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abinzano Guillén, María Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Dubois, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urbieta Echezarreta, Miren Aranzazu</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: El significado pronóstico del síndrome hepatopulmonar (SHP) se ha estudiado en pocas ocasiones. Pacientes y método: Observación de la supervivencia de 32 pacientes cirróticos, 14 (44%) de ellos con SHP y 18 con intercambio gasesoso normal (IGN), y estudio de los factores asociados. Resultados: Durante una media (desviación estándar) de 56 (27) meses fallecieron 9 pacientes (riesgo relativo de 0,64) del grupo SHP y 4 (riesgo relativo de 0,22) de los pacientes con IGN (odds ratio = 6,42; p &lt; 0,01; intervalo de confianza del 95%, 0,04-0,80). Los pacientes con SHP fallecieron una media de 44 (31) meses tras la inclusión y los pacientes con IGN, 65 (21) meses tras la inclusión (p &lt; 0,05). No todos los fallecimientos estuvieron relacionados con enfermedad hepática o disfunción pulmonar. Los factores asociados a mortalidad fueron el grado de shunt pulmonar y los valores plasmáticos de renina, mientras que el volumen plasmático y la capacidad de difusión de monóxido de carbono fueron factores de protección. Conclusiones: El SHP empeora el pronóstico de la cirrosis hepática</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);127(4): 133-135, jul. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047117</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Significado pronóstico del síndrome hepatopulmonar en la cirrosis hepática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24890</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33764^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33764^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
