<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039546</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The treatment of hydrocele as ambulatory surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: To evaluate the results of this surgical treatment of hydrocele over the first four years of integration of the Urology Department in the Major Ambulatory Surgery Unit in our Hospital. METHODS: From January 2000 to July 2004 we have performed 167 hydrocelectomies as ambulatory surgery in 152 patients (15 cases bilateral) with ages ranging from 16-87 years (mean 52.6). All procedures were performed under local anesthesia, using between 10-15ml of 1% lidocaine. The Lord&#146;s vaginalis plication technique was employed in 92% of the cases, leaving resection techniques for the remaining 8%, which presented certain degree of enlargement of the tunica vaginalis. We evaluated inclusion and discharge criteria, results, and degree of satisfaction by means of a questionnaire. RESULTS: Results are equivalent to those of inpatient surgery. Only one patient required admission to the hospital due to a postoperative complication, which was clearly independent of the ambulatory character of the process. Satisfaction with treatment was higher than 95%. CONCLUSIONS: Almost all patients with hydrocele are candidates to ambulatory surgery, significantly improving the cost-efficacy rate, without diminishing the quality of care or patient satisfaction</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Ballester, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zaragozá Fernández, Cristobal</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos de Campos, Macarena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navalón Verdejo, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juan Escudero, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordoño Domínguez, Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre Abril, Luis de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Evaluar los resultados obtenidosen el tratamiento quirúrgico del hidrocele durantelos cuatro primeros años de integración del Servicio deUrología en la Unidad de Cirugía Mayor Ambulatoria(CMA) de nuestro Hospital.MÉTODO: Desde enero de 2000 hasta julio de 2004,hemos realizado 167 hidrocelectomías con carácterambulatorio a 152 pacientes (en 15 casos bilateral),con edades comprendidas entre 16 y 87 años (media52,6). Todos los pacientes fueron intervenidos bajoanestesia local, precisando entre 10 y 15 ml de lidocaínaal 1%. La técnica de plicatura vaginal de Lord fueempleada en el 92% de los casos, reservándose lastécnicas resectivas para el 8% restante que presentabancierto grado de paquivaginalitis. Se evalúan los criteriosde inclusión y alta, así como los resultados obtenidosy el grado de satisfacción mediante la elaboraciónde un cuestionario.RESULTADOS: Los resultados obtenidos son superponiblesa los de la cirugía con ingreso. Tan solo uno de lospacientes precisó ingreso por complicación postoperatoria,la cual fue claramente independiente del régimende ambulatorización del proceso. El grado de satisfaccióncon el tratamiento recibido ha sido superior al95%.CONCLUSIONES: La práctica totalidad de los pacientesafectos de hidrocele son candidatos a ser incluidosen un programa de CMA, mejorando ostensiblementela relación costo-eficacia, no disminuyendo por ello lacalidad asistencial ni el grado de satisfacción de lospacientes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;58(5): 393-401, jun. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039546</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento del hidrocele en cirugía mayor ambulatoria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7001^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d783</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
