<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145156</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-755X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Development of the social brain during adolescence</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article describes recent research which informs our understanding of changes in social cognition during adolescence. The focus will be on mentalising, the ability to attribute and manipulate mental states in the self and others. Mentalising is supported by the medial prefrontal cortex (MPFC) and both anterior and posterior regions of the temporal lobes. In the past decade, studies have demonstrated development during adolescence of white and grey matter brain structure, with most protracted changes observed in frontal and temporal lobes, including those regions supporting mentalising. This article presents evidence that certain aspects of social cognition continue to change during adolescence, highlighting results from recent research investigating the use of theory of mind information in a communicative context. The findings highlight how adolescence, and not only childhood, is a time of continued maturation of brain and behaviour, when education and the environment can have an impact on cognitive development (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dumontheil, Iroise</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo describe resultados de investigaciones recientes sobre cambios en la cognición social durante la adolescencia. Se centra en la mentalización, la capacidad de atribuir y manipular estados mentales en uno mismo y en los demás. La mentalización está asociada con la corteza prefrontal media (MPFC) y las regiones anterior y posterior de los lóbulos temporales. En el último decenio hay estudios que demuestran que a lo largo de la adolescencia se desarrolla la estructura cerebral tanto de la sustancia blanca como de la gris, observándose los cambios más notables en los lóbulos frontal y temporal, que incluyen regiones en las que se asienta la mentalización. Este artículo demuestra que determinados aspectos de la cognición social siguen desarrollándose durante la adolescencia, presentando los resultados de estudios recientes que investigan la utilización de la teoría de la mente en un contexto comunicativo. Los resultados subrayan cómo la adolescencia, y no sólo la niñez, es una etapa de maduración continua del cerebro y del comportamiento, cuando la educación y el entorno pueden influir en el desarrollo cognitivo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. educ. (Madr.);21(2): 117-124, dic. 2015. graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145156</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desarrollo del cerebro social durante la adolescencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52519^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52519^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12023^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52519^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53745^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12946</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12023^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12023^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12023^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52519^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53745^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
