<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112767</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Primary lymphoma of the colon</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: primary colorectal lymphoma is a very rare disease, representing less than 0.5 % of all primary colorectal neoplasms. The gastrointestinal tract is the most frequently involved site of all extranodal lymphomas, the most common type of that is non-Hodgkin s lymphoma. Early diagnosis is often difficult because of unspecific symptoms. Therapeutic approaches have classically included radical resection, chemotherapy and radiotherapy. Materials and methods: we present our experience in the management of primary colorectal lymphomas over a 17-year period (1994-20011). Results: in this period 7 cases of primary colorectal lymphoma were diagnosed in our institution. Abdominal pain and change in bowel habit were the most frequent symptoms. Five patients underwent emergency surgery because of bleeding or bowel obstruction. All primary intestinal lymphomas studied were of the Bcell phenotype. Patients were followed up for a median of 59 months (range 1-180). Three of them are alive with no evidence of recurrence. Conclusion: combination treatment with chemotherapy and surgery can obtain good remission rate. Surgery can resolve complications such bleeding or intestinal perforation that are implicated in lymphoma mortality(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pascual, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pera, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-González, Blanca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grande, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: el linfoma primario de colon y recto es una patología poco prevalente, representa tan solo el 0,5 % de todas las neoplasias primarias de colon y recto. El tracto gastrointestinal es el lugar donde asientan la gran mayoría de los linfomas extranodales, siendo el más frecuente el tipo linfoma no-Hodking. El diagnóstico precoz es siempre difícil debido a que la sintomatología es muy poco específica. Los algoritmos terapéuticos han incluido clásicamente la resección radical, el tratamiento con quimioterapia y con radioterapia. Materiales y métodos: presentamos nuestra experiencia en el manejo de los linfomas primarios de colon en un periodo de 17 años (1994-2011). Resultados: en dicho periodo en nuestro centro fueron diagnosticaron 7 casos de linfoma primario de colon. El dolor abdominal y los cambios en el ritmo deposicional fueron los síntomas más frecuentes. Cinco pacientes requirieron tratamiento quirúrgico urgente debido a hemorragia digestiva u obstrucción intestinal. El estudio anatomopatológico reveló que todos los linfomas tenían el fenotipo de tipo B. Los pacientes tuvieron un seguimiento medio de 59 meses (rango 1-180). Tres de ellos siguen vivos sin evidencia de recidiva. Conclusión: el tratamiento combinado con quimioterapia y cirugía puede obtener buenos resultados de remisión. La cirugía puede resolver complicaciones como la hemorragia o la perforación intestinal, ambas directamente relacionadas con la mortalidad por linfoma(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;105(2): 74-78, feb. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112767</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Linfoma primario de colon</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6623^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3142^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8398^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3142^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6623^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3142^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7578^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7578^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8398^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7578^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3142^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
