<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110499</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cholesterol atheroembolism and combined treatment with steroids and iloprost</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cholesterol atheroembolism (CAE) is a systemic disorder whose incidence has increased in recent decades and that presents high morbidity and mortality. Although several therapeutic alternatives have been reported, there is no consensus about the best treatment for this disease. In this paper we report the case of a patient with CAE with skin, bowel and kidney involvement who presented a good response to combined therapy with steroids and prostaglandin analogues. Although there are no conclusive studies, we recommend this therapeutic alternative in the management of CAE with organic failure (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sevillano-Prieto, Ángel M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Praga, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, Ester</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caro, Jara</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La ateroembolia de colesterol (AEC) es una enfermedad sistémica cuya incidencia ha aumentado en las últimas décadas y que presenta una elevada morbimortalidad. En el momento actual se desconocen cuáles son las alternativas terapéuticas más efectivas en esta entidad. En este artículo presentamos el caso de una paciente diagnosticada de AEC con afectación cutánea, intestinal y renal, que presentó una buena evolución tras el inicio de terapia combinada con esteroides y análogos de las prostaglandinas. A pesar de que no existen estudios concluyentes, sugerimos esta alternativa para el manejo de AEC con afectación orgánica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;32(6): 824-828, nov.-dic. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110499</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ateroembolia de colesterol y tratamiento combinado con esteroides e iloprost</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31490^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28988^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11897^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13642^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4258</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
