<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-34544</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-6585</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The relationship between periodontal disease and preterm low birth weight: a literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Despite all efforts made for pregnancy and labour care, the incidence of preterm births has not decreased in the last two decades. Prematurity implies a serious threat to the health of the newborn, representing an important percentage of the perinatal health care costs. Scientific research has revealed multiple mechanisms through which remote infections such as periodontal disease can participate in the pathogenesis of preterm birth. Recent studies have demonstrated that periodontal disease is a risk factor for preterm birth, even with higher odds ratios than those calculated for traditional risk factors such as tobacco consumption, low maternal weight or alcohol consumption. It has be en suggested that the prevention and treatment of periodontal disease in pregnant women could contribute to the prevention of preterm birth. This paper reviews the scientific evidence in the literature regarding this asociation and the role of periodontal therapy in preventing preterm birth (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ediciones Avances, S.L.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A pesar de los esfuerzos realizados en el control del embarazo y el parto, la frecuencia de los partos prematuros no ha disminuido en las dos últimas décadas. El parto prematuro supone una seria amenaza para la salud del recién nacido, y representa además un porcentaje muy importante de los costes destinados a la atención sanitaria perinatal. La investigación científica ha revelado diversos mecanismos por los que infecciones remotas como la enfermedad periodontal pueden participar en la patogenia del parto prematuro. Estudios recientes han demostrado que la enfermedad periodontal es un factor de riesgo para el parto prematuro, habiéndose hallado un riesgo relativo mayor que el calculado para factores de riesgo tradicionales como el tabaquismo, bajo peso materno o consumo de alcohol. Se ha sugerido que la prevención y el tratamiento de la enfermedad periodontal en mujeres gestantes podrían contribuir a la prevención del parto prematuro. En el presente artículo revisamos la evidencia científica presente en la literatura acerca de esta asociación y del papel del tratamiento periodontal en la prevención del parto prematuro (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. periodoncia implantol. oral;16(2): 93-105, ago. 2004. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre enfermedad periodontal y parto prematuro. Bajo peso al nacimiento: una revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Bascones, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flores, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateos, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oteo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-34544</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22225^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7925^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7925^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32092^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10701^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10701^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30057^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
