<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144398</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-7279</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Occupational Therapy consists of intervention or rehabilitation through activities. It aims to practically make the person as independent as possible to perform their daily activities. The purpose of the occupational Therapist is to design and implement intervention programs directed to Alzheimer patients, dementias and other people with a condition within the psychogeriatric's area of intervention. Cognitive stimulation (a therapeutic intervention) comprise on improving the functional and cognitive performance, preventing deterioration and increasing the personal independence in the basic and daily activities and skills. Working to maintain their cognitive functions that might get affected with the condition (memory, language, praxis, perception, calculation, execution and orientation capacity). Cognitive stimulation can be applied to both, individual or group, according to the user's needs. Through specific tests and activities the results are organised in Cognitive Intervention Program (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández Aguado, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Terapia Ocupacional consiste en intervenir o rehabilitar por medio de actividades. Enfoca sus objetivos hacia la funcionalidad, para hacer a la persona lo más autónoma posible en las actividades de la vida diaria (AVD). El objetivo del Terapeuta Ocupacional es diseñar y ejecutar los programas de intervención dirigidos a personas con enfermedad de Alzheimer y otras demencias dentro del ámbito de la psicogeriatría. La estimulación cognitiva (es una intervención terapéutica) consiste mejorar el rendimiento cognitivo y funcional, evitar su deterioramiento e incrementar la autonomía personal en la AVD básicas e instrumentales. Se trabaja mantener las funciones cognitivas que se ven alteradas en la demencia (memoria, lenguaje, praxis, percepción, cálculo, capacidades ejecutivas y orientación). La estimulación cognitiva se puede aplicar tanto grupal como individual según las necesidades del usuario. Mediante pruebas y actividades concretas se estructura en lo que se llaman programas de intervención cognitiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Inf. psiquiátr;(216): 137-145, abr.-jun. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144398</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervención del terapeuta ocupacional en el área de estimulación cognitiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12374</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29494^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
