<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048487</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New clinical parameters in premenstrual syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Premenstrual symptoms probably constitute the physical and psychological alteration that affects more people than any other, including both women and the men in their environment. Up to 90% of women of childbearing age report one or more symptoms during the days before menstruation. These symptoms can alter women's behavior and well-being and can therefore affect their family, social and work circles. Despite its widespread prevalence, premenstrual syndrome as a clinical entity has not been clearly defined, and consensuated and proven diagnostic methods are lacking. Treatment recommendations supported by experimental and clinical evidence are only slowly beginning to appear. In the present review, we discuss recently published experimental data on the possible etiology of premenstrual syndrome. We propose a new symptom register, the Premenstrual Profile, to be used for the diagnosis of the three forms in which this alteration can manifest itself. Finally, we review evidence-based recommendations from reliable sources on the treatment of «normal» and «abnormal» premenstrual symptoms</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Campagne, Ghislaine</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campagne, Daniel M. </dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los síntomas premenstruales conforman, probablemente, la alteración física y psíquica que a más personas afecta, tanto a las mujeres como a los varones de su entorno. Se estima que hasta un 90% de las mujeres en edad reproductiva percibe uno o más síntomas en los días antes de la menstruación que pueden alterar su comportamiento y bienestar y, por tanto, afectar a su entorno familiar, social y laboral. A pesar de esta prevalencia generalizada, el síndrome premenstrual como entidad clínica aún carece de un contenido concreto y validado, así como de métodos diagnósticos consensuados y comprobados, y sólo tímidamente empieza a disponerse de recomendaciones de tratamiento sobre la base de evidencia experimental y clínica. Esta revisión comentará nuevos datos de investigación en cuanto a la posible etiología de la alteración premenstrual. Propondrá un nuevo perfil premenstrual, registro de síntomas de obligado cumplimiento para el diagnóstico de las 3 formas clínicas en que puede manifestarse la alteración. Finalmente, incluirá una compilación de las recomendaciones de fuentes fidedignas y basadas en la evidencia en cuanto al tratamiento de los síntomas «normales» y «no normales»</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);49(9): 493-511, sept. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048487</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevos parámetros clínicos del síndrome premenstrual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19030^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19030^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8359</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
