<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100231</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Telephone interruptions in family doctor clinics in two health centres in Saragossa</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To analyse disruptions due to telephone calls in primary care clinics, their reasons and distribution during the working day. Design. Cross-sectional descriptive study. Setting. The study was conducted in primary care, 2 urban Primary Care Health Centres in Area II of Zaragoza. Methodology. Seven primary care physicians recorded all calls, whether or not they were passed on from the admissions service to clinics, their origin and characteristics, over a period of 5.5 months. Results. The overall mean percentage of calls per day for each doctor was of 1.39 (SD 1.5), being 1.66 (SD 1.53) in San José Norte and 1.22 (SD 1.46) in San José Centro (P=.012), with a difference between 0.2 and 0.68 calls per day per clinic. The mean number of calls per day in the morning clinics and per clinic was 1.37 (SD 1.53) and 1.44 (SD 1.41) in the afternoon clinics, there being a significant difference (P=. 62). Calls originated by the patients themselves to speak directly with their doctors are more frequent in the morning than afternoon hours (28.5% and 26.5%). The distribution of calls is mainly from the 10.30 to 1 p.m., and between the 17:00 and 18:00hours. Conclusions. Quantifying the telephone calls that occur during the family physician clinics, as well as determining their distribution and reasons, allows strategies to be developed to take advantage of the phone calls, as well as minimising disruption in the clinics (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vecino-Lafoz, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montiu-Pomar, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Moreno, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orna-Esteban, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Melón-Juncosa, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Isanta-Pomar, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Analizar las interrupciones por llamadas telefónicas en las consultas de atención primaria, sus motivos y distribución en las jornadas laborales. Diseño. Estudio descriptivo y transversal. Ámbito. El estudio se lleva a cabo en atención primaria, en 2 centros de salud urbanos del sector II de Zaragoza. Metodología. Siete médicos de atención primaria registraron todas las llamadas telefónicas pasadas o no desde el servicio de admisión, a consulta, su origen y características, a lo largo de 5,5 meses. Resultados. La media global de llamadas por día para cada médico ha sido de 1,39 (DE 1,5), siendo de 1,66 (DE 1,53) en San José Norte y de 1,22 (DE 1,46) en San José Centro (p=0,000), con una diferencia entre 0,2 y 0,68 llamadas por consulta y día. La media de llamadas por consulta y día en las consultas de horario de mañana es de 1,37 (DE 1,53) y en las de horario de tarde de 1,44 (DE 1,41), no existiendo una diferencia significativa (p=0,62). Las llamadas originadas por los propios pacientes para hablar directamente con sus médicos constituyen el motivo más frecuente en los horarios de mañana y de tarde (28,5 y 26,5%). La distribución del horario de las llamadas, se centra entre las 10,30 y las 13 h, y entre las 17 y 18 h. Conclusiones. Cuantificar las llamadas telefónicas que se producen durante la consulta del médico de familia, así como conocer su distribución y motivos, permite desarrollar estrategias para aprovechar las ventajas de la llamada telefónica, a la vez que minimizar la interrupción en la consulta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);38(4): 214-219, mayo 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100231</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Interrupciones por llamadas telefónicas en la consulta del médico de familia en 2 centros de salud de Zaragoza</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14067^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14067^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11253^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14067^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11253^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14067^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
