<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-MFM2-10797</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Design and validation of two measuring scales of burden and professional support needs for formal and informal caregivers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The aim of the study was design and validation of two scales to measure the conscience of burden and the need of professional support for an integrative (care patient-familiarprofessional) both for formal and informal caregivers of patients with dementia. Method. Descriptive and correlational study for scale validation. After a literature review, preliminary items were formulated, that experts validated as adequate for content. Exploratory Factorial Analysis were done to determinate questionnaires structure (unweighted least squares extraction, oblimin rotation) and criterion validity by Pearson correlation with an external variable. Internal consistency by Cronbach alpha coefficient. Results. Of 372 answered questionnaires a total of 320 were valid. From them 85% (272) were women and 15% (48) men. Both scales (formal and informal) gave a structure with two factors named as Burden and Professional Support Needs. The first scale with 11 variables and Cronbach's alpha coefficient .917 and the second scale with 9 variables and Cronbach's alpha of .802. Conclusions. The scales of Burden and Professional Support Needs for formal and informal caregivers' showed to be reliable and valid scales, showing a model good fit to data (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bermejo, José Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villacieros, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hassoun, Hadil</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El objetivo del estudio fue el diseño y validación de dos escalas para medir la conciencia de sobrecarga y la necesidad de apoyo profesional para un cuidado integral (paciente-familiar-profesional) tanto para cuidadores formales como informales de pacientes con demencia. Método. Estudio descriptivo y correlacional de validación de escala. Tras una revisión bibliográfica se redactaron los ítems preliminares, que los expertos validaron como adecuados en cuanto a contenido. Se realizaron análisis factoriales exploratorios para determinar la estructura de los cuestionarios (extracción de mínimos cuadrados no ponderados, rotación oblimin) y de validez de criterio mediante correlación de Pearson con una variable externa. La consistencia interna mediante el coeficiente alfa de Cronbach. Resultados. De los 372 cuestionarios contestados, fueron válidos un total de 320. Un 85% (272) fueron mujeres y un 15% (48), hombres. Ambas escalas (formal e informal) dieron lugar a dos factores denominados sobrecarga y necesidad de apoyo. La primera escala de 11 ítems con alfa de Cronbach 0,917 y la segunda escala de 9 ítems con un alfa de Cronbach de 0,802. Conclusión. Las escalas de sobrecarga y necesidad de apoyo para cuidador formal e informal mostraron ser escalas fiables y válidas con buen ajuste del modelo obtenido a los datos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);28(3): 116-120, sept. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-MFM2-10797</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diseño y validación de dos escalas de medida de sobrecarga y necesidad de apoyo profesional para cuidadores formales e informales</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
