<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76409</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Functioning and disability: the International Classification of Functioning, disability and health (ICF)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The World Health Organization&#146;s International Classification ofFunctioning, Disability and Health (ICF) has provided a newfoundation for our understanding of health, functioning, anddisability. It covers most of the health and health-related domainsthat make up the human experience, and the most environmentalfactors that influence that experience of functioning and disability.With the exhaustive ICF, patients&#146; functioning &#150;including itscomponents body functions and structures and activities andparticipation&#150;, becomes a central perspective in medicine. Toimplement the ICF in medicine and other fields, practical tools(= ICF Core Sets) have been developed. They are selected sets ofcategories out of the whole classification which serve as minimalstandards for the assessment and reporting of functioning and healthfor clinical studies and clinical encounters (Brief ICF Core Set) or asstandards for multiprofessional comprehensive assessment(Comprehensive ICF Core Set). Different from generic andcondition-specific health-status measures, the ICF Core Sets includeimportant body functions and structures and contextual factors. Theuse of the ICF Core Sets provides an important step towardsimproved communications between healthcare providers andprofessionals, and will enable patients and their families tounderstand and communicate with health professionals about theirfunctioning and treatment goals. Specific applications include multiandinterdisciplinary assessment in clinical settings and in legalexpert evaluations and use in disease or functioning-managementprograms. The ICF has also a potential as a conceptual frameworkto clarify an interrelated universe of health-related concepts whichcan be elucidated based on the ICF and therefore will be an idealtool for teaching students in all medical fields and may open doorsto multi-professional learning(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Stucki, Gerold</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Geoffrey, Reed</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cieza, Alarcos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-López, Juan Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Fidalgo, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Clasificación Internacional del Funcionamiento, de la Discapacidady de la Salud (CIF) constituye el marco conceptual de laOMS para una nueva comprensión del funcionamiento, la discapacidady la salud. Es una clasificación universal que establece un marcoy lenguaje estandarizados para describir la salud y las dimensionesrelacionadas con ella. Abarca tres componentes esenciales: funcionescorporales/estructuras, actividad y participación, integrados bajo lostérminos &#147;funcionamiento&#147; y &#147;discapacidad&#147;, que dependen de lacondición de salud y de su interacción con factores contextuales. Loscomponentes están clasificados mediante categorías. Hoy por hoyconsta de 1.424 categorías organizadas en una estructura jerárquicade 4 niveles de menos preciso a más. En el caso de los factores contextualesla cuantificación de las categorías mediante calificadoresestablece en qué medida un factor actúa como barrera o facilitador.La instrumentalización de la CIF con fines prácticos ha llevadoal desarrollo de grupos de categorías (núcleos básicos) útilespara la clínica práctica, la provisión de servicios o la investigación.Los núcleos básicos son abreviados o extensos según laintención sea estudiar condiciones específicas o realizar aplicacionesintegrales multidisciplinares. Existen núcleos básicos paraenfermedades muy prevalentes según la fase del proceso: aguda,postaguda, crónica o comunitaria, cubriendo todo el proceso deenfermedad y toda la cadena sanitaria. Su aplicación clínica mejorala comunicación médico-paciente y el establecimiento de objetivosterapéuticos integrales. Asimismo, sirve para la evaluaciónmultidisciplinar en medios clínicos, legales y de programas. LaCIF logra la superación de conceptos de amplia utilización sanitaria,como bienestar, estado de salud o calidad de vida relacionadacon la salud y abre una nueva línea de enseñanza estudiantil entodas las especialidades y de formación integral multiprofesional(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;83(6): 775-783, nov.-dic.2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76409</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Funcionamiento y discapacidad: la Clasificación Internacional del Funcionamiento (CIF)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28445</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
