<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037051</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The knowledge, clinical control and attitudes of primary care physicians when dealing with epileptic patients. Preliminary findings</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Epilepsy is a common disease with mportant social and economic repercussions. Patients with epilepsy        have traditionally been discriminated by both the  general population and physicians. A physician&#146;s lack of knowledge about epilepsy could be the cause of an incorrect clinical control (CC). Aims. The purpose of this study is to examine the origins of the knowledge, the CC and the attitudes of physicians in Tenerife with respect to the treatment of patients with epilepsy. Materials and methods. In January 2003, all Primary Care physicians in Tenerife were given a questionnaire that asked them about their knowledge, CC and attitudes when dealing with cases of epilepsy. Of the 260 surveys initially sent out, 182 were returned.        Results. The questionnaire was answered by 70% of doctors, of which 34 were paediatricians and 148 were general practitioners, with no differences between sexes. Most physicians acquire their knowledge, observe and treat their first seizure in the Faculty and during their period of hospital residency. 44% of them are barely or not at all satisfied with their knowledge on        the subject. The most highly valued therapists are neurologists and neuropaediatricians. The goal that is sought is to eliminate the impact of the disease on the patient&#146;s quality of life. They rarely establish or modify antiepileptic treatment and state that they        have doubts about neuropsychological disorders and integrating patients with epilepsy in the workplace. Conclusions. The physicians in Tenerife define themselves as professionals with scant knowledge about epilepsy and feel they are poorly qualified        to treat patients with the disease, who are usually referred to specialists in Neurology</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Pérez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Casanova, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sosa, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La epilepsia es una enfermedad frecuente con gran impacto social y económico. Tradicionalmente, os epilépticos han sido discriminados por la población y por los médicos. La falta de conocimientos sobre la epilepsia por parte de los médicos podría ser causa de un control clínico (CC) incorrecto. Objetivo. Acercarse al origen de los conocimientos, al CC y a las actitudes de los médicos de Tenerife frente a los epilépticos. Materiales y métodos. Se entregó una encuesta que incluía cuestiones sobre conocimientos, CC y actitudes de los médicos frente a la epilepsia, a todos los médicos de Atención Primaria de Tenerife en enero de 2003. De 260 encuestas inicialmente repartidas, se recogieron 183. Resultados. Respondió un 70% de los médicos, 34 pediatras y 148 médicos generales y de familia, sin diferencias por sexos. La mayoría de los        médicos adquieren sus conocimientos, observan y tratan una crisis por primera vez en la Facultad y durante la residencia hospitalaria. Un 44% está poco o nada satisfecho de sus conocimientos. Los terapeutas más valorados son el neurólogo y el neuropediatra. El        objetivo deseado es la ausencia de impacto de la  enfermedad sobre la calidad de vida del paciente. Raramente inician o  modifican tratamientos antiepilépticos, y manifiestan dudas sobre la afectación        neuropsicológica y la integración del epiléptico en el trabajo. Conclusiones. Los médicos de Tenerife se definen como profesionales con escasos conocimientos en epilepsia y poco capacitados para tratar a los pacientes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;40(7): 385-393, abr. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037051</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conocimientos, control clínico y actitudes de los médicos de Atención Primaria frente a los pacientes epilépticos. Resultados previos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11724</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23897</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30459^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11252</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
