<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81169</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Changes in emergency admission times after the introduction of direct admission from emergency services</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveTo measure the differences of waiting time for the emergency admission depending on which professional is in charge ie. the emergency doctor or the specialist of a specific area.Patients and methodsOnce the Hospital Emergency Service was permitted to admit patients directly to the specialities, two periods of study where taken: Period A (before the direct admission) and Period B (after the implementation of it). The following was analysed: the number of patients taken, the complexity of their problem, the number of admissions and length of their stay.ResultsDuring Period A 41,917 patients were seen (228.07 patients/day) and during Period B 41,948 (230.48 patients/day). The average of the stay for those patients that were admitted directly from Emergencies had decreased by 1h and 42min (p=0.001). The admissions in the Internal Medicine Service kept the same waiting time in both periods.ConclusionsThe transfer of the responsibility of the admissions to emergency doctors has decreased the average waiting time of the patients in this area. The total number of admissions has not increased and has reduced the amount of work the different specialist(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Álvaro, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benítez Macías, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brun Romero, f. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Gil, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoValorar el impacto en el tiempo de espera para el ingreso urgente dependiendo del facultativo responsable de éste, el médico de urgencias o el especialista del área médica.Material y métodoTras la autorización al servicio de urgencias hospitalarias para el ingreso directo de pacientes en las especialidades médicas, se definieron dos períodos de estudio: período A (previo al ingreso directo) y período B (tras su implantación). Se analizaron el número de pacientes atendidos, su gravedad, el número y porcentaje de ingresos y el tiempo medio de estancia.ResultadosEn ambos períodos se atendieron 41.917 pacientes (228,07 pacientes/día) y 41.948 (230,48 pacientes/día), respectivamente. El tiempo medio de estancia de los pacientes ingresados directamente desde urgencias disminuyó en 1h y 42m (p=0,001); por el contrario, los ingresos en planta de hospitalización del servicio de medicina interna mantuvieron un tiempo medio de espera similar en los dos períodos analizados.ConclusionesEl traspaso de la competencia del ingreso a los facultativos de urgencias disminuye el tiempo medio de estancia de los pacientes en dicha área, sin modificar el número de ingresos y reduciendo la carga asistencial de los facultativos de la planta de hospitalización(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;210(4): 159-162, abr.2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81169</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tiempo de demora para la hospitalización tras la implantación del ingreso directo a cargo del Servicio de Urgencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12364</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10537^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
