<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151364</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-5962</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Today's work experience: Precursors of both how I feel and how Ithink about my job?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Antecedents of affective versus cognitive components of daily job satisfaction were compared. According to the affective events theory, the affective component should relate more strongly to state affect and affective work experiences than the cognitive component. In multilevel regression analyses of 280 daily reports from 40 participants, within-person variation was lower in the cognitive component (24%) than in the affective component (54%). Beyond state affect and trait affectivity, positive valence of work experiences had an incremental value only in the prediction of the affective component. The affective component is more reactive to daily work experiences than the cognitive component. Whenever the link between work and daily job satisfaction is reviewed, the components of job satisfaction measures should be considered as a moderator (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Meier, Laurenz L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elfering, Achim</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Odoni, Mauro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se comparan los antecedentes de los componentes afectivos frente a los cognitivos de la satisfacción laboral cotidiana. Según la teoría de los acontecimientos afectivos, el componente afectivo debería guardar una mayor relación con el afecto de estado y las experiencias laborales que el componente cognitivo. En los análisis de regresión multinivel de 280 informes diarios de 40 participantes, la variación intrasujeto era menor en el componente cognitivo (24%) que en el afectivo (54%). Más allá del afecto de estado y la afectividad de rasgo, la valencia positiva de las experiencias laborales tenía un valor incremental solo en la predicción del componente afectivo. Este es más reactivo a las experiencias laborales diarias que el componente cognitivo. Siempre que se revisa el vínculo entre trabajo y satisfacción laboral cotidiana deberían considerarse las medidas de satisfacción laboral como moderadoras (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. trab. organ. (1999);32(1): 11-16, ene.-abr. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151364</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La experiencia laboral hoy: ¿precursores de cómo me siento y de lo que piensoacerca de mi trabajo?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4724^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16629</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4724^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3102^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
