<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117300</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-2597</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Lupus anticoagulant in Pediatrics. Experience in our center</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. A descriptive study of the presentation forms, biological and evolution characteristics of the pediatric patients diagnosed of lupus anticoagulant in our hospital. Patients and methods. Retrospective review of all the patient who met the criteria established by the International Society of Thrombosis and Hemostasis for diagnosis of lupus anticoagulant. Results. The established criteria were met by 16 children, 9 males (53.6%) and 7 women, with a mean decimal age on diagnosis of 6.25 years (range: 1.1-13). The reasons for the coagulation study were: preoperative (n: 6, 37.5%), thrombosis study (n: 4, 25%), infection (n: 3, 8.8%), hemorrhaging (n: 2, 12.5%) and taking of rodenticide (n: 1, 6.3%). Ten cases (62.5%) remained asymptomatic and corresponded to pre-operative cases, infections and intake of rodenticide. Four of the patients had thrombosis (25%). In two of the latter, primary thrombophilia and immune or tumor pathology were also found and another case fulfilled the criteria of primary antiphospholipid syndrome, this being the only case in which the lupus anticoagulant was persistent. Two cases (12.5%) presented hemorrhages associated to decrease of a coagulation factor (transient deficits of FII and FVIII).Conclusions. Lupus anticoagulant is an uncommon finding in Pediatrics. It is more frequently found in the preoperative of ENT and/or infectious processes. The vast majority are transient and do not show clinical significance. When thrombosis is associated, it is frequently associated to primary thrombophilia and immune or tumor disorder and when it is associated to hemorrhages, it is associated to a deficit of procoagulant factors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cebeira Moro, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Ramírez, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González García, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abad Arevalillo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Guisasola, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermejo Arnedo, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Figueroa Ospina, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcos Temprano, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Estudio descriptivo de las formas de presentación, características biológicas y evolución de los pacientes pediátricos diagnosticados de anticoagulante lúpico en nuestro Hospital. Pacientes y métodos. Revisión retrospectiva de todos los pacientes que cumplieron los criterios establecidos por la Sociedad Internacional de Trombosis y Hemostasia para diagnóstico de anticoagulante lúpico. Resultados. Cumplieron los criterios establecidos 16 niños, 9 varones (53,6%) y 7 mujeres, con una mediana de edad decimal al diagnóstico de 6,25 años (rango: 1,1-13). Los motivos del estudio de coagulación fueron: preoperatorio (n: 6, 37,5%), estudio por trombosis (n: 4, 25%), infección (n:3, 18,8%), hemorragia (n: 2, 12,5%) e ingesta de raticida (n:1, 6,3%). Diez casos (62,5%) permanecieron asintomáticos y correspondieron a los casos de preoperatorio, infecciones e ingesta de raticida. Cuatro de los pacientes presentaron trombosis (25%), en dos de ellos se encontraron además trombofilia primaria y patología inmunitaria o tumoral y en otro caso se cumplieron criterios de síndrome antifosfolípido primario, único de los casos en que el anticoagulante lúpico fue persistente. Dos casos (12,5%) presentaron hemorragias asociadas a disminución de algún factor de coagulación (déficits transitorios de FII y FVIII).Conclusiones. El anticoagulante lúpico es un hallazgo poco frecuente en Pediatría. Se encuentra con más frecuencia en preoperatorio de procesos ORL y/o infecciones. La gran mayoría son transitorios y sin relevancia clínica. Cuando se asocia trombosis frecuentemente se asocia a trombofilia primaria y patología inmunitaria o tumoral y cuando lo hace a hemorragias, a déficit de factores procoagulantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Bol. pediatr;53(225): 146-151, jul.-sept. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117300</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anticoagulante lúpico en Pediatría. Experiencia en nuestro centro</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14312^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7199^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30833^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30002^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
