<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130725</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Differences in use of self-handicapping and defensive pessimism and its relation with achievement goals, self-esteem, and self-regulation strategies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this paper self-handicapping and defensive pessimism have been assessed among university students. Cluster analysis allowed us to set four groups of students: Group SH (n= 168) high in self-handicapping, Group BE (n= 179) low in self-handicapping and defensive pessimism; Group AE (n= 59) high in both self-worth protection strategies and Group PD (n= 189) high in defensive pessimism. Results indicate that SH group is less likely to subscribe to a mastery orientación than BE and PD groups and supports research that has found a positive relationship between a ego-orientation and self-handicapping. Both self-handicapping and defensive pessimism are positively associated with a ego-defensive orientation. On the other hand, findings provide support for the hypotheses that individuals low in self-esteem may be more likely to engage in self-handicapping. Finally, results also show that both PD and BE groups are significantly higher in self-regulation strategies than SH and AE groups. These findings are discussed with regard to prior research on self-handicapping and defensive pessimism (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Núñez, José Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabanach, Ramón G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Pienda, Julio A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valle, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se estudia el self-handicapping y el pesimismo defensivo en estudiantes universitarios. El análisis cluster nos permitió diferenciar cuatro grupos de estudiantes: Grupo SH (n= 168) alto en self-handicapping, Grupo BE (n= 179) bajo en self-handicapping y en pesimismo defensivo; Grupo AE (n= 59) alto en ambos tipos de estrategias de protección de la valía y Grupo PD (n= 189) alto en pesimismo defensivo. Los resultados indican que el grupo SH es menos proclive a adoptar una orientación de dominio que los grupos BE y PD y apoyan la investigación que ha encontrado relaciones positivas entre una ego-orientación y el self-handicapping. Tanto el self-handicapping como el pesimismo defensivo están positivamente asociados con una orientación ego-defensiva. Por otra parte, los datos darían soporte a la hipótesis de que los individuos con baja autoestima tenderían a implicarse en estrategias de self-handicapping. Finalmente, los resultados también ponen de manifiesto que los grupos PD y BE son significativamente más altos en estrategias de autorregulación que los grupos SH y AE. Estos datos son comentados a la luz de la investigación previa en torno al self-handicapping y el pesimismo defensivo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);16(4): 625-631, oct.-dic. 2004. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130725</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias en el uso de self-handicapping y pesismismo defensivo y sus relaciones con las metas de logro, la autoestima y las estrategias de autorregulación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d133</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10659</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33883</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3687</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28408</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6184</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
