<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98794</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-0559</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality of life, social support and impairment in a sample of persons with severe mental illness</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The principal aims of the interventions in psychosocial rehabilitation is to improve the living functioning in persons with several mental illness, being the quality of life connected with the received treatments. The article evaluates the index of quality life, social support received and psychosocial deterioration in a sample of 89 subjects with mental illness in rural and removed areas of Castilla-La Mancha, attended by the Social Integration Community Support Program (PRIS) of FISLEM Foundation. This program offers care and follow-up including integration and domestic attention as a complement to the different resources of socio sanitary attention to persons with mental illness: psychosocial and vocational rehabilitation centres and adult mental health services. The results confirm the relation between quality of life and other studied variables like social support offered by the program, psychosocial deterioration and the social and family situation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Heras Delgado, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrasco Ramírez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas Toral, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Bayón, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La mayoría de las intervenciones en rehabilitación psicosocial tienen como objetivo principal mejorar el funcionamiento de la vida de las personas con trastorno mental grave para una mejor adaptación social, estando la calidad de vida relacionada con los tratamientos recibidos. El articulo evalúa los índices de calidad de vida, apoyo social percibido y deterioro psicosocial de una muestra de 89 sujetos con trastorno mental en contextos rurales y alejados de Castilla-La Mancha, atendidos desde el Programa de Integración social y apoyo comunitario (PRIS) de la Fundación FISLEM, que ofrece unos cuidados y seguimiento continuado que incluye el apoyo a procesos de rehabilitación psicosocial y laboral, soporte social, apoyo a la integración en su contexto y atención en el domicilio como complemento a los diferentes recursos de atención socio sanitaria a personas con enfermedad mental: centros de rehabilitación psicosocial y laboral y unidades de salud mental. Se ha encontrado relación entre la calidad de vida y otras variables estudiadas como el apoyo social ofrecido por el programa, el deterioro psicosocial y la situación socio laboral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Interv. psicosoc;17(3): 321-336, sept.-dic. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98794</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida, apoyo social y deterioro en una muestra de personas con trastorno mental grave</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
