<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128796</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">How will focal therapy fit in with existing treatments?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Context: The current management of localized prostate cancer is a therapeutic challenge with different options including active radicals or active follow-up. The aim of this paper is to analyze the feasibility and validity of the &#147;Focal&#148; active treatment versus the concept of active follow-up or Radical Treatment. Evidence acquisition: We reviewed the literature on the various diagnostic methods, advantages, and difficulties of active follow-up and Radical Treatment, versus focal therapy with the possibilities of defining characteristics of aggressiveness and patient selection. Evidence synthesis: The mesh biopsy techniques along with multiparametric magnetic resonance imaging and association of factors such as tumor size, length of affected cylinder and Gleason are parameters that allow us to define location and definition of clinically significant tumors and subsidiary of focal therapies. Conclusions: The definition, location and aggressiveness of prostate cancer in low-intermediate risk tumors can be defined avoiding radical therapies with their side effects or the risks of underestimating tumors as in active follow-up without the minimum side effects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Veiga, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Emberton, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dickinson, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ahmed, H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Contexto: El manejo actual del cáncer de próstata localizado supone un reto terapéutico con diferentes opciones, incluyendo las activas radicales o el seguimiento activo. El objetivo de este trabajo es analizar la posibilidad y validez del tratamiento activo «focal» frente al concepto de seguimiento activo o tratamiento radical. Adquisición de evidencia: Realizamos una revisión de la literatura sobre los diferentes métodos diagnósticos, ventajas o dificultades del seguimiento activo y tratamiento radical frente a la terapia focal, con las posibilidades de definición de características de agresividad y selección de pacientes. Síntesis de evidencia: Las técnicas de biopsia con rejilla junto con la resonancia nuclear magnética nuclear multiparamétrica y la asociación de factores como el tamaño del tumor, la longitud del cilindro afecto y Gleason son parámetros que nos permiten afinar en la localización y definición de tumores clínicamente significantes y subsidiarios de terapias focales. Conclusiones: La definición, localización y agresividad del cáncer de próstata en tumores de riesgo bajo-intermedio puede ser definida evitando las terapias radicales con sus efectos secundarios, o los riesgos de subestimar tumores como en el seguimiento activo con los mínimos efectos secundarios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;37(10): 597-602, nov.-dic. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128796</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Cómo encajará la terapia focal en los tratamientos existentes?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34918</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30624^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30624^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
