<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110317</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cutaneous horn, actinic keratosis and squamous cell carcinoma. Presentation of a clinical case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The cutaneous horn is defined as a tumour, usually of conical appearance which prevails over the length of its diameter, with large hyperkeratosis in its extreme and due to varied causes. It may be associated with benign, pre-malignant (actinic keratosis) and malignant (squamous cell carcinoma) skin, usually requiring complete excision of the lesion and a histopathological examination. We report a case of a 94 year old woman with a cutaneous horn and an initial pathological diagnosis of actinic keratosis, which subsequently progressed to squamous cell carcinoma, along with and a brief review of the literature. The treatment is complete excision of the lesion, deepening its base due to the likelihood of association with malignant lesions(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bermejo Hernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hermida Pérez, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cuerno cutáneo se define como una lesión tumoral, por lo general de aspecto cónico, en la cual prevalece la longitud sobre su diámetro, con gran hiperqueratosis en su extremo y de variadas causas. Puede asociarse con lesiones benignas, premalignas (queratosis actínica) y malignas (carcinoma espinocelular) de piel, por lo que es necesario la exéresis completa de la lesión además de un examen histopatológico. Presentamos el caso clínico de una mujer de 94 años con un cuerno cutáneo y diagnóstico anatomopatológico inicial de queratosis actínica, que posteriormente recidivó en un carcinoma espinocelular y se hace una breve revisión de la literatura médica. El tratamiento es la exéresis completa de la lesión, profundizando en la base de la misma, por el riesgo de asociación a lesiones malignas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);39(2): 113-116, mar. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110317</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuerno cutáneo, queratosis actínica y carcinoma espinocelular. A propósito de un caso clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53062^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2463^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53062^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53062^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
