<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054810</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of rechargeable stimulators in 2 cases of cauda equina syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The first of the 2 cases of cauda equina syndrome we    report occurred following phenolization of sacral roots    after a series of operations for Hirsprung disease. The    second occurred after trauma from a bullet that hit the    spine. Fecal and urinary incontinence and neuropathic    pain in the lower extremities were present in both cases.    After various treatments failed, both patients were given    dual spinal stimulation for integrated treatment of both    incontinence and neuropathic pain. We applied a novel    approach, connecting both stimulators to a single    rechargeable generator, reducing medium&#150; and longterm    costs. Fewer generator replacements (every 2-3    years with the standard approach) and fewer generator    implantations (2 each time with the usual system) are    required when rechargeable generators are used. Patient    quality of life is thus improved. The overall cost of the    implants is reduced from their second year of use</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Abejón, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanmartín, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pozo, C. del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saz, J. del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se exponen dos casos clínicos de síndrome de cola de    caballo (postfenolización de raíces sacras el primero tras    diversas cirugías por Enfermedad de Hirsprung, y postraumático    el segundo por impacto de bala sobre la    columna), en los que están presentes síntomas de incontinencia    fecal/urinaria y dolor neuropático en extremidades    inferiores. Tras la falta de respuesta a diversos    tratamientos, se procede a aplicar en ambos casos un sistema    dual de estimulación medular (tratamiento integral    de la incontinencia y el dolor neuropático), con la novedad    en esta ocasión de conectar ambos sistemas a un    mismo generador recargable. Ello plantea una reducción    de costes a medio y largo plazo al disminuir el número    de recambios a efectuar (cada 2-3 años con los generadores    estándar), así como el número de generadores a    implantar (2 estimuladores cada vez), y una mejora en la    calidad de vida del paciente. Estos datos hablan de un    menor coste global del implante a partir del 2º año desde    su realización</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;54(2): 120-124, feb. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054810</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilización de sistemas de estimulación recargables. A propósito de dos casos de síndrome de cola de caballo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11565^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28246^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
