<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82946</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">An experimental model of ultraviolet radiation-induced cutaneous photocarcinogenesis in SKH-1 mice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Chronic exposure to solar radiation leads to pathological aging of the skin (photoaging) and is one of the principal etiological factors of skin cancer. Methods. For the present experiment, twenty SKH-1 mice were exposed to ultraviolet radiation three times a week for 60min (a total of 80 sessions). The areas exposed to radiation were subsequently examined macroscopically and microscopically. Results. All the experimental animals developed malignant neoplasias (skin carcinomas) as well as signs typical of photoaging. Conclusions. Given the great similarity between the lesions found in the experimental animals and those appearing in human skin following extensive exposure to ultraviolet radiation, we consider this model suitable for the study of photoaging and photocarcinogenesis and for the assessment of antioxidants and photoprotectors(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cano Gómez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez García, Francisco José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Pedreño Guillén, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente Ortega, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Sánchez, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. La exposición crónica a las radiaciones solares provoca el envejecimiento patológico de la piel (fotoenvejecimiento) y es uno de los principales factores etiológicos implicados en el desarrollo del cáncer cutáneo. Métodos. Para el presente experimento, hemos expuesto 20 ratones SKH-1 a radiaciones ultravioleta, que se aplicaban tres veces a la semana durante 60min (80 sesiones). Las zonas expuestas a las radiaciones han sido estudiadas macro y microscópicamente. Resultados. El 100% de los animales tratados desarrollaron neoplasias malignas, así como los signos típicos del fotoenvejecimiento. Conclusiones. Debido a la gran similitud de las lesiones desarrolladas por los animales, con las que tienen lugar en la piel humana tras la exposición crónica a las radiaciones ultravioleta, consideramos este modelo, idóneo para el estudio del fotoenvejecimiento y la fotocarcinogénesis, así como para el ensayo de sustancias antioxidantes y fotoprotectoras(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;43(4): 191-195, oct.-dic.2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82946</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Modelo de fotocarcinogénesis cutánea en ratones SKH-1 por radiación ultravioleta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10382^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51282^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2583^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6316^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d86^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12087^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51282^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
