<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81253</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Outcome of critically ill patients with acute renal failure and multiple organ failure treated with continuous venovenous haemodiafiltration</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective Acute renal failure (ARF) is associated to multiple organ failure (MOF) in critically ill patients and its mortality is high. The main objective was to evaluate the outcome of critically ill patients with ARF and MOF treated with continuous venovenous hemodiafiltration (CVVHDF).DesignRetrospective and observational study on critically ill patients.SettingMedical-surgical Intensive Care Unit (ICU) in a University Hospital of Girona.PatientsPatients admitted in ICU that developed ARF and MOF and were treated with CVVHDF.Primary variables of interestWe collected data on demographic, and severity and organic dysfunction scores (SOFA). To study the risk factors for mortality, a comparative and multiple regression statistical analysis was performed, with the main effect of the study being mortality at 30 days.ResultsWe studied 139 patients. The most frequent predisposing factors were hypotension (98%) and sepsis (82%). the most frequently affected organs were cardiocirculatory (94%) and respiratory (47%) associated to ARF. Mean SOFA score was 11.4¡À2.7 points. Survival was better in traumatic and in non-oliguric patients. The 30-day mortality was 61% and the logistic regression analysis showed that age ¡Ý60 years [OR=3.3 (95% CI 95=1.5¨C7.0)] and SOFA score ¡Ý11 points [OR=2.5 (95% CI=1.1¨C5.3)] were related to mortality.ConclusionsThe mortality rate of critically ill patients with acute renal failure and multiple organ failure remains high. Traumatic and non-oliguric patients have a better survival. Age ¡Ý60 years and SOFA ¡Ý11 points were independent risk factors associated with mortality(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Navas, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonet, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valles,  M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sirvent, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calabia, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: En los pacientes críticos el fracaso renal agudo (FRA) está  asociado a disfunción multiorgánica (DMO) y su mortalidad es alta. El objetivo principal fue evaluar la evolución de los pacientes críticos con FRA y DMO tratados con hemodia filtración venovenosa continua (HDFVVC). Diseño: Estudio retrospectivo y observacional en pacientes críticos. Ambito: Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos (UCI) medico quirúrgica del Hospital Universitario de Girona. Pacientes: Pacientes ingresados en la UCI con FRA y DMO tratados con HDF VVC. Principales variables de interés: Se recogieron variables demográficas, de gravedad y de DMO (SOFA [Sepsis-related Organ Failure Assessment score]). Análisis estadístico comparativo y de regresión logística múltiple con la mortalidad a los 30 días como efecto principal de estudio. Resultados: Se estudió a 139 pacientes. Los factores predisponentes m as frecuentes fueron hipotensión (98%) y sepsis (82%). Los órganos más frecuentemente afectados fueron los del sistema cardio circulatorio (94%) y los del sistema respiratorio (47%) asociados al FRA. ElSOFA medio fue de 11,472,7.  Los pacientes traumáticos y los no oligúricos tuvieron una mejor supervivencia. La mortalidad a los 30 días fue del 61% y el análisis de regresión logística mostró que la edad superior o igual a 60 años (OR[odds ratio] = 3,3 [intervalo de confianza {IC} del 95%:1,5&#150;7,0]) y el SOFA superior o igual a 11puntos (OR=2,5 [IC del 95%: 1,1&#150;5,3]) se relacionaron con la mortalidad. Conclusiones: La mortalidad de los pacientes críticos con FRA y DMO es alta. Los pacientes traumáticos y los no oligúricos tuvieron una mejor supervivencia. La edad superior o igual a 60 años y el SOFA superior o igual a 11 puntos fueron factores de riesgo independientes de mortalidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);34(2): 95-101, mar. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81253</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolucion de los pacientes criticos con fracaso renal agudo y disfuncion multiorganica tratados con hemodiafiltracion venovenosa continua</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52438</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6940^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53982^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53982^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31418^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9294^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9294^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
