<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037376</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Respiratory rehabilitation: situation in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To consider the implantation andthe cover of the programs of respiratory rehabilitation in theSpanish Health System; to describe the characteristics ofthe existing programs and to explore the barriers for theextension them. Methods. Semistructured interview, to six key informants,chosen by prestige criteria in the field of the respiratory rehabilitationresearch or by the scientific societies, being clinicalat the same time.Results. The informants agree in which the respiratory fisiotherapyas a component of RR programs is extended bythe first level hospitals and that mainly goes to patients withchronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD). Nevertheless,the exercise training, the more effective intervention, isinclude in only a minority of public centers (hospitals) withrehabilitation program, and only a small proportion of the patientswho need RR are provided. The relax techniques andthe smoking cessation support are not always included.Conclusions. At the moment, the attention to the patientwith COPD with a correct respiratory rehabilitation is farfrom being guaranteed in the Spanish Health System</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villegas Portero, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Briones Pérez de la Blanca, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarmiento González-Nieto, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez Calderón, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tirado Reyes, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Estimar la implantación y la coberturade los programas de rehabilitación respiratoria en el sistemasanitario público español, describir las características delos programas existentes y explorar las barreras para la ampliaciónde su implantación.Métodos. Se realizó una entrevista semiestructurada, caraa cara, a seis informadores clave, elegidos por destacar comoinvestigadores en el campo de la rehabilitación respiratoria ocomo representantes de las sociedades científicas, siendoclínicos al mismo tiempo.Resultados. Los informadores clave están de acuerdo enque la rehabilitación respiratoria entendida como fisioterapiarespiratoria está bien difundida por los hospitales de primernivel y que se dirige principalmente a pacientes con enfermedadpulmonar obstructiva crónica (EPOC). Sin embargo,sólo una minoría de centros públicos incluye en el programade rehabilitación el entrenamiento al esfuerzo, que es el componentede beneficio mejor demostrado y la rehabilitaciónrespiratoria sólo llega a una pequeña proporción de los pacientesque la necesitan. La enseñanza de técnicas de relajacióny el apoyo para dejar de fumar no son constantes.Conclusiones. Actualmente, la atención al paciente conEPOC, con una correcta rehabilitación respiratoria, está lejosde quedar garantizada en el sistema sanitario público español</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);39(3): 128-133, may.-jun. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037376</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rehabilitación respiratoria: aproximación a la situación en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1970</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12468^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28598^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12560^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5180</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
