<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106344</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adnexal tumors in pregnancy, delivery and the puerperium</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the frequency of adnexal tumors in pregnancy, childbirth and the postpartum, tumoral histology, and perinatal outcomes. Patients and methods: We performed a retrospective analysis of 25 patients diagnosed with histologically-con&amp;#64257;rmed ovarian tumor and pregnancy treated at the Obstetrics Service of the General Hospital of Mexico and the Center for Dysplasias, Gynecology and Holistic Medicine over a 2-year period. Results: The association of ovarian tumor and pregnancy occurred in one out of 424 pregnancies. The most common histological type was serous cystadenoma (52%). The most common time of diagnosis was during intraoperative cesarean section in 14 patients. Surgery did not alter the perinatal outcome. Conclusion: Women of reproductive age can develop ovarian tumors. Diagnosis can be masked by pregnancy. Tumoral resolution is recommended during the second and third trimesters. Emergency surgery is recommended only when malignancy is suspected or there is acute abdomen (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Buitrón, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Duran, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juárez Azpilcueta, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivera, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Islas, L. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Téllez, S. E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la frecuencia de tumor anexial en el embarazo, parto o puerperio, la histología tumoral y los resultados perinatales. Pacientes y método Análisis retrospectivo de 25 pacientes con diagnóstico de tumor ovárico y embarazo atendidas en el Servicio de Obstetricia del Hospital del Hospital General de México y en el Centro de Displasias, Ginecología y Medicina Integral, en 2 años de estudio, con confirmación histopatológica. Resultados La asociación tumor ovárico y embarazo fue uno en 424 embarazos. El tipo histológico más frecuente fue el cistoadenoma seroso (52%), el momento más común del diagnóstico fue el transoperatorio de la operación cesárea en 14 casos. La cirugía no alteró el pronóstico perinatal. Conclusión La mujer en edad reproductiva es susceptible de presentar tumoración ovárica, el embarazo puede ocultar el diagnóstico, se recomienda resolución de la tumoración durante el segundo y tercer trimestres y solo en casos de sospecha de malignidad y abdomen agudo, resolución quirúrgica de urgencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);39(5): 187-189, sept.-oct. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106344</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumoraciones anexiales en el embarazo, parto y puerperio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d290^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5969^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11693</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
