<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94435</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Health-related quality of life in institutionalised elderly people</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to describe Health-related Quality of Life (HRQoL) in institutionalised elderly individuals. The correlation between the degree of control of the disease and HRQoL scores has also been a subject of study in diabetic residents. Design: Cross-sectional study. Information was collected by means of a questionnaire and data collected from a review of each resident&#146;s medical chart. Participants: 121 residents of both sexes institutionalised in a nursing home, with adequate cognitive function for the purpose of the study.Results: institutionalised residents present a deteriorated HRQoL (mean VAS 66,8,SD 20,3) in comparison with other studies carried out on elderly people in the general population. 19% report to be in optimal health. Women present worse HRQoL than men, with significant results in the dimensions of &#147;personal care&#148; and &#147;activities of daily life&#148;. A worse HRQoL is found in subjects &amp;#8805;75 years and contradictory results with regard to weight. Diabetic residents have a worse HRQoL than non-diabetic patients, with significant results regarding &#147;mobility&#148;, &#147;personal care&#148; and &#147;activities of daily life&#148;. In the diabetic population, we have found no differences in terms of HRQoL, depending on the degree of control of the diabetes or type of treatment.Conclusions: as part of the assessment of the institutionalised elderly person, the assessment of HRQoL allows the identification of impaired health status and the most fragile profiles of our patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pariente Rodrigo, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Expósito, Josefina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carbajo Payo, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña Sarabia, Nicolás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tresgallo Fernández, Nieves</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Robles, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: describir la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud (CVRS) en ancianos institucionalizados. En residentes con diabetes mellitus se deseaba investigar asimismo la relación entre el grado de control de la enfermedad y las puntuaciones en la encuesta de CVRS. Material y método: Diseño: estudio transversal, con recogida de información a través de cuestionario y de datos provenientes de la historia clínica individual. Participantes: 121 personas de ambos sexos, institucionalizadas en una Residencia de Mayores, con función cognitiva adecuada al propósito del estudio. Mediciones:  CVRS, valorada mediante el cuestionario genérico Euroqol-5D. Se contemplan otros tres tipos de variables: demográficas (edad y sexo), antropométricas(peso y talla) y clínicas en el caso de ancianos con diabetes mellitus (hemoglobina glicosilada -HbA1c- y tipo de tratamiento).Resultados: los residentes presentaron una CVRS deteriorada (Escala Visual Analógica media de 66,8, DS: 20,3). El 19% refirieron un estado de salud óptimo. Las mujeres presentaron peor CVRS que los hombres, con resultados significativos en las dimensiones &#147;cuidado personal&amp;#148; y &#147;actividades cotidianas&#148;. Se encontró peor CVRS en sujetos de &amp;#8805;75 años y resultados contradictorios respecto al peso. Los residentes con diabetes mellitus tenían peor CVRS que los no-diabéticos, con resultados significativos en &#147;movilidad&#148;, &#147;cuidado personal&#148; y &#147;actividades cotidianas&#148;. Conclusiones: dentro de la valoración del anciano institucionalizado, la evaluación de la CVRS permite detectar estados de salud deficitarios y los perfiles más frágiles de nuestros residentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;11(5): 26-31, jun. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94435</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida relacionada con la salud del anciano institucionalizado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50238</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28940^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24693^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
