<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80265</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacy criteria of the treatments according to the Task Force</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present the evaluation criteria of the effectiveness of psychological treatments developed by the American Association of Psychology for the evaluation of the Treatments with Empirical Support, distinguishing between: well-established well (effective) treatments, probably effective treatments and experimental treatments. The criteria selected by the experts&#146; committee (Task Force), appointed by the association, are based on the possibility or not of reply of the intervention (including development of treatment manuals) by researchers of different teams, on the utilization of comparison group designs and on the description of the sample characteristics (diagnostic criteria, age, sex, etc.). These criteria are based on the idea of that, from the research point of view, a treatment can never be definitively validated since new studies that can make it necessary to reanalyze the result keep appearing. This study has aimed to present some examples of treatments in relationship to the criteria mentioned related with the health field, specifically with asthma, chronic pain, dysmenorrhea and fibromyalgia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rosa-Alcázar, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosa-Alcázar, A. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosa-Alcázar, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presentan los criterios de valoración de la eficacia de los tratamientos psicológicos elaborados por la APA (American Psychological Association &#145;Asociación Americana de Psicología&#146;) de los tratamientos con apoyo empírico, distinguiendo entre tratamientos bien establecidos (eficaces), tratamientos probablemente eficaces y tratamientos experimentales. Los criterios seleccionados por la comisión de expertos (Task Force) nombrada por la APA están basados en la posibilidad o no de réplica de la intervención (incluyendo la manualización del tratamiento) por investigadores de distintos equipos de trabajo, en la utilización de diseños de grupo de comparación y en la descripción de las características de la muestra (criterio diagnóstico, edad, sexo, etc.). Estos criterios están basados en la idea de que, desde el punto de vista de la investigación, un tratamiento no está nunca definitivamente validado, ya que pueden ir apareciendo estudios que hagan reanalizar los resultados. El objetivo de este estudio es presentar algunos ejemplos de tratamientos atendiendo a los criterios mencionados relacionados con el campo de la salud, en concreto, en el asma, el dolor crónico, la dismenorrea y la fibromialgia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);31(6): 248-254, Nov. - dic. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80265</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Criterios de eficacia de los tratamientos según la Task Force</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13342</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36378</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33540</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
