<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103444</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cross-cultural adaptation of the Portuguese version of the patient-generated subjective global assessment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The cross-cultural adaptation of the Patient-Generated Subjective Global Assessment is important so it can be used with confidence in Portuguese language. Objective: To perform a cross-cultural adaptation of the Portuguese version of the Patient-Generated Subjective Global Assessment and to estimate its intrarater reliability. Material and methods: This is a validation study. Face Validity was classified by 17 health professionals and 10 Portuguese language specialists. Idiomatic, semantic, cultural and conceptual equivalences were analyzed. The questionnaire was completed by 20 patients of the Amaral Carvalho Hospital (Jaú, São Paulo, Brazil) in order to verify the Comprehension Index of each item. Therefore, 27 committee members classified each item into "essential", "useful, but not essential" and "not necessary", in order to calculate the Content Validity Ratio. After, this version of the questionnaire was applied twice to 62 patients of the hospital cited above. The intrarater reliability of the nutritional status analyzed by Patient-Generated Subjective Global Assessment was estimated by Kappa statistics. Results: The Portuguese version of the Patient-Generated Subjective Global Assessment presented 10 incomprehensible expressions. The items "a year ago weight" and "dry mouth symptom" presented the lowest Content Validity Ratio. Substantial intrarater reliability (k = 0.78, p = 0.001) was observed. Conclusion: The cross-cultural adaptation of the Portuguese version of the Patient-Generated Subjective Global Assessment became simple and understandable for Brazilian patients. Thus, this version of the Patient-Generated Subjective Global Assessment was considered a valid and a reliable method (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dias do Prado, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonini Campos, JA Duarte</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la adaptación transcultural del Patient-Generated Subjective Global Assessment es importante ya que se puede utilizar con confianza en la lengua portuguesa. Objetivo: realizar una versión de adaptación transcultural al portugués del Patient-Generated Subjective Global Assessment y estimar su fiabilidad intra-observador. Material y métodos: se trata de un estudio de validación. La validez aparente fue clasificada por 17 profesionales sanitarios y 10 lingüistas portugueses. Se analizaron las equivalencias idiomáticas, semánticas, culturales y conceptuales. El cuestionario fue completado por 20 pacientes del Hospital Amaral Carvalho (Jaú, São Paulo, Brasil) con el fin de verificar el Índice de comprensión de cada ítem. Por lo tanto, 27 miembros del comité clasificaron cada ítem en "esencial", "útil pero no esencial", e "innecesario" con el fin de calcular el cociente de validez del contenido. Después, se aplicó esta versión del cuestionario dos veces a 62 pacientes del hospital antes mencionado. La fiabilidad intra-observador del estado estado nutricional analizada por el Patient-Generated Subjective Global Assessment se estimó mediante los estadísticos Kappa. Resultados: la versión portuguesa del Patient-Generated Subjective Global Assessment presentaba 10 expresiones incomprensibles. Los ítems "a year ago weight" y "dry mouth symptom" mostraron el menor cociente de validez del contenido. Se observó una fiabilidad intraobservador significativa (k = 0,78, p = 0,001). Conclusión: La adaptación transcultural de la versión portuguesa del Patient-Generated Subjective Global Assessment fue sencilla y comprensible para los pacientes brasileños. Por lo tanto, esta versión del Patient-Generated Subjective Global Assessment se consideró un método válido y fiable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;27(2): 583-589, mar.-abr. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103444</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación transcultural de la versión portuguesa de la valoración subjetiva global-generada por el paciente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2134^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
