<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057446</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of obesity among children in Ceuta. Ponce study 2005</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The continuous increasing of overweight and obesity,        among children and adolescents, constitutes an important        public health problem. It is necessary to know and        quantify this problem in order to delimit its magnitude        and to identify the main risk groups. The enKid study        (1998-2000) has estimated an obesity prevalence in Spain        of 13,9% within the population group aged 2-22 years.        Up to now, there was no data available about the city of        Ceuta. In this study, it has been estimated an obesity        prevalence of 8,75% among the Ceuta population group        aged 6-13 years</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cos Blanco, AI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amate Garrido, AM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Briz Hidalgo, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El continuo incremento del sobrepeso y obesidad en        niños y adolescentes constituye un importante problema        de salud pública que es necesario conocer y cuantificar        para delimitar su magnitud e identificar los principales        colectivos de riesgo. El estudio enKid (1998-2000) ha estimado        en España una prevalencia de obesidad del        13,9%, en una población de 2 a 22 años de edad. Hasta la        fecha no disponíamos de datos de la ciudad de Ceuta. En        este trabajo se ha estimado una prevalencia de obesidad,        en niños ceutíes de 6 a 13 años de edad, del 8,75%</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;22(4): 471-477, jul.-ago. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057446</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de obesidad infantil en Ceuta. Estudio PONCE 2005</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31670</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
