<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038334</identifier>
<setSpec>0378-4835</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinico-biological value of the cytosol concentration of hyaluronic acid in CD44v6-positive lung adenocarcinomas</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">&#149; Purpose: To study the influence of the cytosol hyaluronic acid (HA) concentrations on theclinical and biological features of CD44v6-positive lung adenocarcinomas (LAs).&#149; Material and methods: The study included 34 tissue samples. We determined theconcentration of HA, p52, cathepsin D, t-PA, NSE, cyfra 21.1, CA125, and free beta subunit ofhuman chorionic gonadotrophin in the cytosol, and of EGFR, erbB2 oncoprotein, CD44s and CD44v5on the cell surface. Other parameters considered were clinical stage, histological grade (HG), ploidy,DNA index, and S-phase cell fraction (SF) measured by flow cytometry.&#149; Results: In the tumoral group the HA/CD44v6 index values varied from 8.5 to 5,999 (107,median for the entire group) and were significantly higher (p 0.004) than those observed in 10samples of normal lung tissue obtained from the same patients. The HA/CD44v6-positive (&gt;107)adenocarcinomas had higher concentrations of erbB2 oncoprotein (p: 0.02), and greater values ofglobal SF (p: 0.009) and DNA index (p: 0.024). They were also more frequently SF+ (&gt;15 %).&#149; Conclusions: The results stand out the importance of the cytosol concentration of hyalurinicacid in the CD44v6-positive lung adenocarcinomas, in such a way that high values of theHA/CD44v6 index are associated with a higher proliferation and cellular undifferentiation, which,joined to the higher concentration of erbB2 protein, suggest a subgroup of tumors with a possiblydifferent (poorer ?) outcome. Nevertheless, given the limited number of studied patients, furtherstudies are necessary to confirm our findings</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruibal, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Argibay, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Salmón, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">&#149; Propósito: El objetivo de este estudio ha sido analizar la influencia de la concentración citosólicade ácido hialurónico (AH) sobre las características clínico-biológicas de adenocarcinomas de pulmónCD44v6 positivos.&#149; Material y métodos: El grupo estudio incluyó 34 muestras tumorales. Dosificamos las concentracionescitosólicas de AH, pS2, catepsina D, t-AP, NSE, cyfra 21.1, CA125 y fracción libre de lahormona gonadotrófica coriónica. También determinamos las concentraciones de EGFR, proteína oncogénicaerbB2, CD44s y CD44v5 en las membranas celulares. Se tuvo presente, asimismo, el estadioclínico, grado histológico, ploidía, índice de DNA y fase de síntesis celular (FS).&#149; Resultados: En el grupo tumoral los valores del índice AH/CD44v6 oscilaron entre 8.5 y 5999(mediana 107) y fueron superiores (p: 0.004) a los observados en 10 muestras de tejido pulmonarnormal de los mismos pacientes. Los adenocarcinomas pulmonares AH/CD44v6 positivos (&gt;107; medianadel grupo) mostraron mayores concentraciones de proteína oncogénica erbB2 (p:0.020) y superioresvalores de FS (p: 0.009) e índice de DNA (p: 0.024). Asimismo, fueron más frecuentementeFS+ (&gt;15 %) (p: 0.026).&#149; Conclusiones: Los resultados obtenidos parecen resaltar la importancia de la concentración citosólicade AH en los adenocarcinomas pulmonares CD44v6 positivos, de tal modo que altos valoresen el índice AH/CD44v6 se asocian con una mayor proliferación e indiferenciación celular, lo cualunido a mayores concentraciones de proteína oncogénica erbB2, sugiere un subgrupo de tumorescon un posible diferente comportamiento. Sin embargo, dada el reducido número de enfermos incluídos,creemos que son necesarios más estudios para poder confirmar nuestros hallazgos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Oncologia;28(1): 39-44, ene. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038334</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valor clínico-biológico de la concentración citosólica de ácido hialurónico en adenocarcinomas pulmonares CD44v6 positivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3619^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29336^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32845^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32062^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6972^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
