<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91085</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prediction of use of consultations in the elderly from the variables of gender, age, comorbidity and prior visit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Several variables associated with the use of health services by the elderly are already known, although there is disagreement on their effect as predictors of new visits. The aim of this study was to determine the prediction power of a model of use of consultations in people ¡Ý 65years attended in primary care. Material and methods. A total of 207 patients of both genders were studied. Outcome variables were visits to the primary care centre and visits to hospital emergency services, both also analysed as predictive of one another. Other predictive variables were age, gender and comorbidity. A multiple regression analysis was performed using 14 multivariate models. Results. The predictive ability improved with stratification and reached the highest performance in the model ¡°Visits to hospital emergency services in patients without comorbidity¡± (R2=0,251, P&lt;.000). Both types of visits were significantly correlated with age, comorbidity, and between themselves. These were the most predictive variables (up to 17.6%), whereas comorbidity contributed up to 11.8%. Conclusions. Despite the accuracy of the models, these variables are insufficient to predict new consultations in the elderly, because they hardly explain 25% of the final variability. Within the predictive ability, it was shown that a prior visit is a powerful predictor of a future visit, particularly in three strata: women, &lt; 75years and patients without comorbidity. Age and comorbidity are stronger predictors of future visits in men than in women (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-Expósito, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castelao-Barcena, L. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Garrido, A. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pariente-Rodrigo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Hernández, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olmos-Martínez, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En el anciano se conocen numerosas variables asociadas a la utilización de consultas, si bien hay discrepancias sobre su efecto como predictoras de nuevas visitas. El objetivo del estudio ha sido conocer la capacidad predictiva de un modelo de uso de consultas en población &gt;= 65 años atendida en AP. Material y métodos. Se estudian 207 pacientes. Las variables de resultado son «Visitas al centro de salud» y «Visitas a urgencias del hospital», analizadas asimismo como predictiva una de otra. Otras variables predictivas son la edad, el género y la comorbilidad. Mediante regresión múltiple se elaboran 14 modelos multivariantes, expresándose el valor del coeficiente R2, la reducción de la varianza que aporta cada variable y su significación estadística. Resultados. La capacidad predictiva mejora al estratificar, alcanzando el máximo rendimiento en el modelo «Visitas a urgencias en pacientes sin comorbilidad» (R2=0,251,p&lt;0,000). Ambos tipos de visitas se correlacionan significativamente con la edad, la comorbilidad y entre ambas. Son las variables más predictivas, con una capacidad explicativa que llega al 17,6%, mientras que la comorbilidad alcanza el 11,8%. Conclusiones. Aunque los modelos son precisos, las variables analizadas son insuficientes para predecir el uso de consultas en el anciano, pues tan sólo explican un 25% de la variabilidad final. Dentro de esa capacidad explicativa, se observa que una visita previa es un potente predictor de una visita futura, especialmente en 3 estratos: mujeres, &lt; 75 años y pacientes sin comorbilidad. La edad y la comorbilidad son más predictoras de futuras visitas en hombres que en mujeres (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);37(8): 405-411, oct. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91085</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Predicción de uso de consultas en el anciano a partir de las variables de género, edad, comorbilidad y visita previa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
