<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153008</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reemergence of measles in vaccinated patients: report of 6 cases and proposals for prevention</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A 2014 measles outbreak in Catalonia affected 131 persons. We describe a series of 6 cases diagnosed in our emergency department. All the patients were under 31 years of age and complained of flu-like symptoms, including high fever and rash. Five had been properly vaccinated and one was a health care worker. A firm diagnosis of measles need not be made in the emergency department, but a high level of suspicion is important for ruling out complications, isolating the patient, and protecting health care staff at high risk for exposure. We found that 6% of the staff of our emergency department had a low level of immunity to measles. Given our findings, we suggest that preventive treatment is necessary when health care staff have been exposed to measles and their vaccination status is unknown (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González, Araceli</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agut-Busquet, Eugènia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gené Tous, Emili</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el contexto de un brote de sarampión en Cataluña en 2014 que afectó a 131 personas, se presenta una serie de seis pacientes que fueron diagnosticados en nuestro servicio de urgencias (SU). Todos los pacientes eran menores de 31 años y consultaron por síndrome gripal con fiebre alta y exantema. Cinco de ellos habían sido correctamente vacunados y uno era personal sanitario. El diagnóstico de certeza en urgencias no es imprescindible, pero es importante su sospecha para descartar sus complicaciones, y para proceder al aislamiento del enfermo y a la protección del personal sanitario. El personal sanitario es un grupo de elevado riesgo de exposición. Se ha constatado que un 6% de los profesionales de nuestro SU presentó un mal estado inmunitario frente al sarampión. Ante estos resultados, planteamos la necesidad de realizar profilaxis postexposición en los profesionales en los que se desconozca el estado vacunal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);28(3): 182-184, jun. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153008</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reemergencia del sarampión en pacientes vacunados: descripción de seis casos y propuesta para su prevención</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35308^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8626^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23113^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53815^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
