<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155174</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Low back pain associated to inflammatory causes has clinical and exploratory features clearly different from those of pain associated to mechanical causes. After ruling out other clinical conditions which may re quire immediate diagnosis and treatment, such as infections and neoplasias, we will focus on spondylopathies as the cause of inflammatory low back pain. Directed anamnesis, a thorough clinical exam, laboratory tests and image studies, as well as individualized diagnostic criteria (when appropriate), will be the keys for the diagnosis of each of the entities included in this group of rheumatic diseases mainly involving the axial skeleton. Treatment is aimed mainly to the management of joint and extrajoint inflammatory signs developed by the patients, since there is currently no curative therapy. As regards low back pain associated to metabolic causes, the diagnosis is reviewed, as well as the therapeutic indications and current treatments for osteoporosis and Paget´s bone disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fontova, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El dolor lumbar de origen inflamatorio presenta unas características clínicas y exploratorias claramente diferentes del de origen mecánico. Descartadas situaciones clínicas que requieren un diagnóstico y tratamiento inmediatos, como infecciones y neoplasias, buscaremos como causa de dolor lumbar inflamatorio las espondiloartropatías. La anamnesis dirigida, una minuciosa exploración clínica, las pruebas de laboratorio y los estudios por la imagen, junto a criterios de diagnóstico individualizados (cuando existan), serán las claves para el diagnóstico de cada una de las entidades que forman este grupo de enfermedades reumatológicas que tienen especial predilección por el esqueleto axial. El tratamiento va dirigido fundamentalmente a controlar las manifestaciones inflamatorias articulares y extraarticulares que presenten los pacientes, ya que no existe en la actualidad un tratamiento curativo. En cuanto al dolor lumbar de origen metabólico, se revisa el diagnóstico, las indicaciones de tratamiento y los tratamientos actuales de la osteoporosis y la enfermedad ósea de Paget (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;8(supl.2): 70-78, 2001. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155174</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lumbalgia de causa inflamatoria y metabólica. Actualización del diagnóstico y tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1184^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10177^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1876^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13552^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13552^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1876^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13552^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200100</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
