<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048040</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6982</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of gastric emptying dynamics in relationship to qualitative composition of intake. Comparison between normal weight and obese subjects</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims. To analyze whether the gastric emptying profile could define obesity and to study the impact of macronutrients diet composition on gastric emptying in obese and non obese people. Material and methods. 47 subjects were selected (12 non obese and 35 obese). The study was organized in 4 visits. In each visit the subject was given isocaloric breakfast differing in macronutrient composition, (either equilibrated, or lipid, protein or carbohydrate rich) quantitative gastric emptying assay was done realized, every 15 minutes for two hours using a radionuclide technique. The week prior to the visit, the subject followed a standard 1,800 cal/day diet. Result. A significant interaction between time and diet composition is shown regardless of the group (obese or non obese) the subject belongs to. The different macronutrient composition differentialy affected gastric emptying only in the obese group. Post hoc analysis of the results showed significant differences after 45 min post breakfast between protein and carbohydrate rich breakfast. Conclusions. Gastric emptying in obese but not in non obese subjects, was significantly modified depending on the intake qualitative composition. These differences are clear when protein rich (significantly slower emtying) is compared versus hydrocarbon enriched diet (significantly faster emptying). A significant difference in gastric emptying between obese and non obese subjects cannot be stablished</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Segura Molina, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Partida Palma, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chover González, A. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Curiel, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Álvaro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escobar Jiménez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Molinero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Freire Macías, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Analizar si el perfil de vaciamiento gástrico podría ser característico en obesidad y estudiar el impacto que la relación de macronutrientes en la dieta tiene sobre el vaciamiento gástrico y las diferencias entre obesos y normopesos. Material y método. Se seleccionan 47 sujetos (12 normopeso y 35 obesos), que realizan 4 visitas durante el estudio. En cada una se administraba un desayuno isocalórico con distinta composición de macronutrientes (equilibrados, lipídico, proteico o hidrocarbonato). Se realizaron estudios cuantitativos de vaciamiento gástrico cada 15 minutos durante dos horas usando la técnica de gammagrafía. La semana previa a cada visita todos los sujetos realizaron una dieta estándar de 1.800 cal/día. Resultados. Se observa una interacción significativa entre los factores tiempo y dieta. Sin embargo, el mismo análisis no demostró esta tendencia al estudiar la evolución del vaciamiento en relación con el grupo al que pertenecía el sujeto (normopeso u obeso). La composición cualitativa de la dieta sólo influyó sobre el vaciamiento gástrico en obesos. El estudio post hoc demostró diferencias significativas fundamentalmente a partir de los 45 minutos postingesta, y entre ingestas ricas en hidratos de carbono y proteínas. Conclusiones. La composición cualitativa de la ingesta ha influido de forma significativa sobre la velocidad de vaciamiento gástrico en sujetos obesos, pero no en normopesos. Esta influencia se hace más evidente en la dieta hidrocarbonada (vaciamiento significativamente más rápido) y proteica (vaciamiento significativamente más lento). No puede establecerse una diferencia significativa de la velocidad de vaciamiento gástrico entre sujetos obesos o normopeso</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Med Nucl;25(3): 172-179, mayo 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048040</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la dinámica de vaciamiento gástrico en relación con la composición cualitativa de la ingesta. Comparación entre sujetos con normopeso y obesos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5887</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23101^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23101^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23103^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5907</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14049^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23103^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33090</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33090^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
