<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102835</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Self-perceived maladjustment of children in residential care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Residential care has historically been the main support system for youngsters in vulnerable situations. At the end of the 20th century, there were a series of legislative changes in Spain regarding the child protection system, which attempted to improve the assistance given to this group. The main aim of this study is to analyse the problems of adjustment that are currently shown by youngsters who live in residential care. 93 of these youngsters and a normative sample completed the Test Auto-evaluativo Multifactorial de Adaptación Infantil (TAMAI [Multifactor Child Adjustment Self-perception Test]; Hernández, 1996). The main results indicate that youngsters in residential care obtain higher scores in maladjustment, although differences are not significant. The reason for admission and their development stage affect the results, but not the length of stay in the residential care. These results are discussed in relation to previous research and legislative changes regarding the child protection system (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Siverio, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El acogimiento residencial ha sido históricamente el principal recurso convivencial para los menores en situación de desamparo. A finales del siglo XX, se producen en España una serie de cambios legislativos en materia de protección infantil que pretenden mejorar la atención que se le presta a este colectivo. El objetivo principal de este estudio es analizar los problemas de adaptación que manifiestan en la actualidad los menores que viven en acogimiento residencial. Noventa y tres de estos menores y una muestra normativa cumplimentaron el Test Autoevaluativo Multifactorial de Adaptación Infantil (Hernández, 1996). Los principales resultados indican que los menores de acogimiento residencial obtienen mayores puntuaciones en inadaptación, aunque las diferencias no son significativas. El motivo de ingreso y el periodo evolutivo parecen incidir en los resultados, pero no así el tiempo de estancia en acogimiento residencial. Estos resultados se discuten en relación a la investigación previa y a los cambios legislativos en materia de protección infantil (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;28(2): 541-547, mayo-ago. 2012. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102835</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inadaptación autopercibida de los menores en acogimiento residencial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28488</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2710^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2698^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2710^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2698^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
