<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115474</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-2074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Unusual cause of respiratory distress: Morgagni hernia associated to Down&#146;s syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Morgagni hernia (MH) is a rare diaphragmatic hernia with 2% rate of congenital diaphragmatic hernias. Is reported Down&#146;s syndrome (DS) the most common chromosomal anomaly. There is a wide range variation among individuals clinically by its characteristic features and associated systemic malformations. The coexistence of Morgagni hernia and DS is reported approximately 20% . A female patient with DS was admitted to emergency department for evaluation of recurrent pneumonia accompanied by persistent dry cough and fever. In the case the radiographic abnormality was actually found to be MH with intestinal loops in the right thorax. We report this case to notify an asymptomatic association between DS and MH (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sahin, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ozayar, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Degerli, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dereli, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hernia de Morgagni (HM) es una hernia diafragmática poco frecuente, con un índice de hernias diafragmáticas congénitas del 2%. El síndrome de Down (SD) es la anomalía cromosómica más frecuente notificada. Desde el punto de vista clínico, hay una variación muy amplia entre individuos por sus rasgos característicos y las malformaciones sistémicas asociadas. La coexistencia de hernia de Morgagni y síndrome de Down se ha notificado en aproximadamente un 20%. En el servicio de urgencias se ingresó a una mujer con SD para evaluar una neumonía recurrente acompañada de fiebre y tos seca persistente. En este caso, se observó que la anomalía radiográfica era en realidad HM, con asas intestinales en el lado derecho del tórax. Presentamos este caso para dejar constancia de una asociación asintomática entre el SD y la HM (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SD, Rev. med. int. Síndr. Down (Ed. castell.);17(1): 13-15, ene.-abr. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115474</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Causa inusual de dificultad respiratoria: hernia de Morgagni asociada con el síndrome de Down</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3510^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4479^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28100^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28100^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28100^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12552^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6707^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4479^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12552^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3510^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
