<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103495</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Trends in self-perceived health and chronic disability in the elderly Spanish population: evolution between years 1993 and 2006</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: This study analyzes the evolution of the health status of the non-institutionalized Spanish population of 65 and more years, during the period 1993-2006, in terms of self-perceived health and chronic disability. Subjects and methods: Data were analyzed from the National Health Surveys of non-institutionalized population in Spain in the years 1993 and 2006, through weighted logistic regression models. Results: During the period 1993-2006, there was an increase in self-perception of good health (0.4%) and chronic disability (2.0%). These increases varied with gender and age. Men presented higher prevalences of good self perceived health (GSH) and chronic disability than women, and their health evolved also differently. The gender gap in GSH reached 15.4% in 2006, while the gap in chronic disability reached 10.5%. With age, the prevalence of chronic disability increased, and self-perception of good health decreased. The evolution of health also varied with age. Individuals 75 years and older showed an opposite evolution compared to younger people, decreasing their GSH and increasing their chronic disability. Conclusions:Results are compatible with a scenario of morbidity compression, where expectancy of life in good health increases, concentrating the years in bad health and chronic disability in the late ages. Evolution differs by age and gender (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salvá, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roqué i Fiugls, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivero, Toni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bolíbar, Ignasi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: En este estudio se analiza la evolución del estado de salud de la población de 65 y más años residente en viviendas familiares en España durante el período 1993-2006, en términos de buena salud percibida (BSP) y dependencia. Sujetos y método: Se analizaron los datos de las Encuestas Nacionales de Salud realizadas a población no institucionalizada en los años 1993 y 2006 mediante modelos de regresión logística ponderados.Resultados: Durante el período 1993-2006 se observa un incremento de la percepción de buena salud (0,4%) y la dependencia (2,0%) en la población mayor española. Estos cambios presentan diferencias importantes por edad y sexo. Los varones presentan más BSP y menos dependencia que las mujeres, y una evolución distinta de su salud. La desigualdad de sexo en BSP alcanzó el 15,4% en 2006, mientras que la desigualdad en dependencia se situó en el 10,5%. Con la edad, aumenta la prevalencia de dependencia y disminuye la percepción de buen estado de salud. Además, la evolución del estado de salud varía según la edad. Las personas de 75 y más años presentan una evolución contraria a las personas más jóvenes, con una disminución de BSP y un aumento de la situación de dependencia. Conclusiones: Los resultados son congruentes con un escenario de compresión de la morbilidad, en que aumenta la esperanza de vida en buena salud, concentrando los años de mala salud y dependencia en las edades más avanzadas. Se constata una evolución distinta según sexo y edad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);139(7): 284-289, sept. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103495</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tendencias en salud percibida y dependencia de la población mayor española: evolución entre los años 1993 y 2006</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28587</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32193^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34921</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d212^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28470</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
