<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131380</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9168</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interaction of FABP4 with plasma membrane proteins of endothelial cells</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction Fatty acid binding protein (FABP4) is an adipose tissue-secreted adipokine implicated in the regulation of the energetic metabolism and inflammation. High levels of circulating FABP4 have been described in people with obesity, atherogenic dyslipidemia, diabetes and metabolic syndrome. Recent studies have demonstrated that FABP4 could have a direct effect on peripheral tissues and, specifically, on vascular function. It is still unknown how the interaction between FABP4 and the endothelial cells is produced to prompt these effects on vascular function. The objective of this work is studying the interaction between FABP4 and the plasma membrane proteins of endothelial cells. Methodology HUVEC cells were incubated with and without FABP4 (100 ng/ml) for 5 minutes. Immunolocalization of FABP4 was studied by confocal microscopy. The results showed that FABP4 colocalizates with CD31, a membrane protein marker. A strategy which combines 6XHistidine-tag FABP4 (FABP4-His), incubations with or without FABP4-His (100 ng/ml), formaldehyde cross-linking, cellular membrane protein extraction and western blot, was designed to study the FABP4 interactions with membrane proteins of HUVECs. Results The results showed different western blot profiles depending of the incubation with or without FABP4-His. The immunoblot revelead three covalent protein complexes of about 108, 77 and 33 kDa containing FAPB4 and its putative receptor. Discussion The existence of a specific binding protein complex able to bind FABP4 to endothelial cells is supported by these results. The obtained results will permit us advance in the molecular knowledge of FABP4 effects as well as use this protein and its receptor as therapeutic target to prevent cardiovascular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Heras, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Masana, Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guaita, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabré, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saavedra, Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Girona, Josefa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aragonès, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción Fatty acid-binding protein 4 (FABP4) es una adipocina secretada por el tejido adiposo implicada en la regulación del metabolismo energético y la inflamación. FABP4 circulante se asocia con obesidad, dislipidemia aterogénica y síndrome metabólico. Estudios recientes muestran una asociación entre FABP4 circulante y disfunción endotelial, aunque se desconoce cómo se produce esta. El objetivo de este trabajo es estudiar la interacción entre FABP4 con las proteínas de la membrana citoplasmática en células endoteliales. Metodología Se incubaron células HUVEC con y sin FABP4 (100 ng/ml) durante 5 min. La inmunolocalización de FABP4 se estudió mediante microscopia confocal. Para estudiar las interacciones de FABP4 con las proteínas de membrana de las células HUVEC se diseñó una estrategia que combina incubaciones con o sin 6XHistidine-tag FABP4 (FABP4-His) (100 ng/ml), cross-linking con formaldehído, extracción de proteínas de membrana y western blot. Resultados Los resultados muestran que FABP4 colocaliza con CD31, una proteína utilizada como marcador de membrana citoplasmática. Además se observan diferentes patrones de western blot en función de la incubación con o sin FABP4-His. El inmunoblot revela la existencia de 3 complejos proteicos de aproximadamente 108, 77 y 33 kDa formados por FABP4 exógena y su posible receptor/es. Discusión Los resultados obtenidos apoyan la existencia de un complejo proteico capaz de unir FABP4 a las células endoteliales mediante una unión específica. Además, nos permiten avanzar en el conocimiento de los efectos moleculares de FABP4 y, en caso de confirmarse, podrían utilizarse como diana terapéutica para prevenir enfermedades cardiovasculares (AU</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. arterioscler. (Ed. impr.);27(1): 26-33, ene.-feb. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131380</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Interacción de FABP4 con proteínas de membrana de células endoteliales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2497^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37364</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50844</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37775</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
