<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159656</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Practical aspects of the use of intrathecal chemotherapy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Intrathecal chemotherapy is frequently used in clinical practice for treatment and prevention of neoplastic meningitis. Despite its widespread use, there is little information about practical aspects such as the volume of drug to be administered or its preparation and administration. Objective: To conduct a literature review about practical aspects of the use of intrathecal chemotherapy. Materials: Search in PubMed/ Medline using the terms &#145;chemotherapy AND intrathecal&#146;, analysis of secondary and tertiary information sources. Results: The most widely used drugs in intrathecal therapy are methotrexate and cytarabine, at variable doses. One of the aspects with higher variability among different studies is their potential combination with a glucocorticoid, the specific corticoid selected and its dose. The efficacy and toxicity of the different combinations have not been compared. Regarding preparation, it is worth highlighting the recommendation to adjust pH and osmolarity to the physiological range, with the aim of improving tolerability. The volume of administration can influence distribution, and recommendated range is between 5 and 12 mL. Overall, it is recommended to extract a similar volume of cerebrospinal fluid before administration. The position of the patient during and after administration can have an impact on distribution and toxicity; lateral decubitus or sitting position is recommended in the first case, and prone and/ or supine position in the second one. Most publications don&#146;t explain how the treatment has been prepared or administered, and the lack of standardization could affect results. Conclusions: There is a great variability in practice when using intrathecal chemotherapy, despite being an effective therapy, accepted by all international groups. This uncertainty is not limited to the drugs and doses administered, but it also includes the manner of preparation and the administration technique. The heterogeneity in clinical practice can influence the efficacy and toxicity of this therapy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz Carrasco, María Sacramento</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olmos Jiménez, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espuny Miró, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cárceles Rodríguez, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La quimioterapia intratecal es utilizada frecuentemente, en la práctica clínica, para el tratamiento y prevención de la meningitis neoplásica. A pesar de su uso extendido, existe poca información acerca de aspectos prácticos tales como el volumen de fármaco a administrar o la forma de preparación y administración. Objetivo: Realizar una revisión de la literatura acerca de aspectos prácticos de la utilización de la quimioterapia intratecal. Material: Búsqueda en PubMed/Medline utilizando los términos &#145;chemotherapy AND intrathecal&#146;, análisis de fuentes de información secundarias y terciarias. Resultados: Los fármacos más utilizados en terapia intratecal son metotrexato y citarabina, con dosis variables. La asociación o no con un glucocorticoide, el corticoide concreto seleccionado y su dosis es uno de los aspectos con mayor variabilidad entre distintos estudios. No se han comparado la eficacia y toxicidad de las distintas combinaciones. En la preparación destaca la recomendación de ajustar pH y osmolaridad al rango fisiológico, con el objetivo de mejorar la tolerancia. El volumen de administración puede influir en la distribución, oscilando las recomendaciones entre 5-12 mL. En general, se aconseja extraer previamente un volumen de líquido cefalorraquídeo similar. La posición del paciente durante y tras la administración puede influir en la distribución y la toxicidad; se recomienda el decúbito lateral o la sedestación, en el primer caso, y el decúbito prono y/o supino, en el segundo. La mayoría de las publicaciones no indican cómo se ha preparado o administrado el tratamiento, y la falta de estandarización podría afectar a los resultados. Conclusiones: Existe gran variabilidad en la práctica a la hora de utilizar la quimioterapia intratecal, a pesar de ser una terapia efectiva asumida por todos los grupos internacionales. La incertidumbre no se limita a los fármacos y dosis administradas, sino que se extiende a la forma de preparación de las mezclas y la técnica de administración. La heterogeneidad en la práctica clínica puede influir en la efectividad y toxicidad de esta terapia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;41(1): 105-129, ene.-feb. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159656</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aspectos prácticos de la utilización de quimioterapia intratecal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19390^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8748^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6082^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4401^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28169^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3578^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
