<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153817</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Computer-assisted surgery navigation systems in head and neck oncology. An updated systematic literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The aim of this paper is to perform an updated review of the literature on surgical planning and navigation in the management of head and neck oncological pathology, and to assess and determine its current applications. Material and methods. An electronic search was conducted using the terms: 'craniomaxillofacial tumors', 'head and neck cancer', 'navigation system', 'computer-assisted surgery', and 'oral cancer'. Results. Sixteen articles have been published between 1991 and 2014. These are 5 reviews, 6 case series, and 5 case reports, but no systematic review. There were 10 articles that provided complete information regarding oncological disease managed with surgical navigation technology. Navigation applications in head and neck oncology can currently be divided into the following categories: guided biopsy, tumor resection and reconstruction, monitoring tumor volume, control of surgical resection margins based on CT, MRI or PET, and interdisciplinary communication network. Conclusions. Currently, there are a limited number of publications on the applications of surgical navigation in the new field of head and neck oncology. Despite the lack of systematic reviews, there seems to be a promising future for the valuable contribution made by navigation to the management of head and neck tumors, by providing anatomic and diagnostic accuracy, and surgical safety. Navigation will show to be of great use in the multidisciplinary cancer treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Centella-Gutiérrez, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dean-Ferrer, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El objetivo de este trabajo es hacer una revisión y actualización de la literatura sobre la aportación de la planificación quirúrgica y de la navegación en el manejo de la enfermedad oncológica de cabeza y cuello, para valorar y determinar sus aplicaciones actuales. Material y métodos. Se realiza una búsqueda electrónica empleando los términos craniomaxillofacial tumors, head and neck cancer, navigation system, computer-assisted surgery y oral cancer. Resultados. El número de artículos encontrados en la revisión de la literatura ha sido de 16, publicados entre los años 1991 y 2014. Entre ellos no hay ninguna revisión sistemática, hay 5 artículos de revisión, 6 series de casos y 5 casos clínicos. Solo 10 artículos aportan información completa en relación con la enfermedad oncológica manejada con tecnología de navegación quirúrgica. Actualmente las aplicaciones de la navegación en oncología de cabeza y cuello pueden enumerarse en las siguientes áreas: biopsia guiada, resección y reconstrucción de tumores, monitorización del volumen del tumor, control de márgenes de resección quirúrgica basados en TC, RMN o PET y sistema de comunicación interdisciplinar. Conclusiones. Actualmente hay un número escaso de publicaciones sobre las aplicaciones de la navegación quirúrgica en el novedoso ámbito de la oncología de cabeza y cuello. A pesar de la ausencia de revisiones sistemáticas, parece tener un futuro prometedor por la valiosa aportación que hace para el manejo de tumores de cabeza y cuello, como proporcionar precisión anatómica, precisión diagnóstica y seguridad quirúrgica, siendo de gran utilidad en el tratamiento oncológico multidisciplinar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;38(3): 136-142, jul.-sept. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153817</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aportaciones de la cirugía guiada por ordenador y navegación en oncología de cabeza y cuello. Una revisión bibliográfica sistemática y actualización</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36296^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55068^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36296^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22570^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36296^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6409^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22570^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6409^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55068^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
