<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59380</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cerebral hemorrhage in a three-year-old boy with chronic idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report the case of three-year-old boy with a two-year history of idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura who was monitored periodically in the Onco-Hematology Service. Seven days before the cerebral vascular accident, he had a hemoglobin concentration of 7.5 grams per liter and a platelet count of 6,000. After immediate transfusion of 1.5 units of platelet concentrate, hefell into a state of drowsiness, followed two hours later by a deterioration in the level of consciousness, with blurring, mydriasis with a lethargic response to light and a score of 9 on the Glasgow coma scale. Brain computed tomography revealed left frontal hemorrhage displacing structures to the right (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palomero Domínguez, M. Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Santurino, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Gómez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Niño de 3 años, afectado de púrpura trombocitopénica idiopática de dos años de evolución, controlado periódicamente en el servicio de oncohematología. Siete días antes del accidente cerebrovascular, presentaba unas cifras de hemoglobina de 7,5 g y 6.000 de plaquetas. Tras una inmediata transfusión de 1,5 unidades de concentrado de plaquetas, presentó un estado de somnolencia, y dos horas después un deterioro del nivel de conciencia con obnubilación, pupilas midriáticas con respuesta perezosa a la luz y una puntuación de Glasgow de 9. La tomografía computarizada cerebral mostró una hemorragia frontal izquierda que desplazaba las estructuras hacia la derecha (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;67(2): 85-87, feb. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59380</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hemorragia cerebral en un varón de 3 años con púrpura trombocitopénica idiopática crónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29857^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29857^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2582^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2582^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
