<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98140</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-9895</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nutritional condition of patients diagnosed of lung cancer in a high-resolution outpatient office</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Abstract. Patients diagnosed of lung cancer should receive chemotherapy, surgery or both. It has been described in the literature that malnutrition of the patient may cause greater morbidity-mortality after the treatment. Our study has aimed to discover the degree of malnutrition of the patients who are diagnosed of bronchogenic cancer in our high-resolution outpatient  office. The analysis was performed retrospectively. BMI and albumin were related with the stage and histology of the tumor. A total of 203 cases were studied. Most were men with predominance of squamous cell carcinoma lung cancer, and 71% were in an advanced stage at the time of diagnosis. Significant differences were found in BMI, although all the patients were within a range of normal weight. No significant differences were found regarding albumin values, although the very lowest values appeared in the more advanced stages. It is possible that factors in addition to the tumor itself participate in the weight loss of the patients. It would be important to determine which patients may have greater malnutrition in order to correct it early and thus avoid complications after the treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Flórez Martín, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcázar Lázaro, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Vime, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perpiñá Ferri, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Encabo Motiño, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pavón Fernández, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abad Santamaría, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen. Los pacientes diagnosticados de cáncer de pulmón deben recibir tratamiento con quimioterapia, cirugía o ambas. En la literatura está descrito que una desnutrición del paciente puede causar mayor morbi-mortalidad tras el tratamiento. El objetivo de nuestro estudio era conocer el grado de desnutrición que presentan los pacientes que son diagnosticados de cáncer broncogénico en nuestra consulta de alta resolución. El análisis se realizó de forma retrospectiva, se relacionó el IMC y la albúmina con el estadio y la histología del tumor. Se estudiaron 203 casos, la mayoría varones  con un predominio de epidermoides, en el momento del diagnóstico un 71 % se encontraban en un estadio avanzado. Se encontraron diferencias significativas en el IMC, si bien casi todos los pacientes estaban dentro de un rango de normopeso. No se encontraron diferencias significativas en cuanto a las cifras de albúmina, aunque los valores extremos más bajos aparecían en los estadios más avanzados. Es posible que intervengan factores adicionales al propio tumor en la pérdida  de peso de estos pacientes. Sería importante determinar qué pacientes pueden presentar una mayor desnutrición para intentar corregirla de forma precoz y evitar así las complicaciones tras tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. patol. respir;12(4): 149-151, oct.-dic. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98140</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estado nutricional de pacientes diagnosticados de cáncer de pulmón en una consulta de alta resolución</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22288^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
