<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042113</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-7606</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Suicide by firearm</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The mechanism chosen for suicide depends upon    various personal and social factors. In this paper, we    present an image of the more mediatic type suicide,    although not the most frequent in our means. The    variability in the entrance and exit orifices by firearm    depends on the distance, type of weapon and    anatomical region; for that reason they can    present/display a wide morphology. Although several    images of suicide by another type of arms have been    published already, today we contributed with a case of    typical suicide by handgun, paying special attention to    the injuries affecting the skull</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Soriano Maldonado, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-García, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El mecanismo elegido para cometer el suicidio    depende de numerosos factores personales y sociales. En    este número presentamos una imagen del tipo de suicidio    más mediático, aunque no por ello el más frecuente    en nuestro medio. La variabilidad en la forma de los orificios    de entrada y salida por arma de fuego depende de    la distancia, tipo de arma y región anatómica por lo que    puede presentar una morfología muy variada. Es por ello    que, aunque ya se han publicado varias imágenes de suicidio    por otro tipo de armas, aportamos un caso de suicidio    típico por arma corta con especial descripción de    las lesiones que se originan en cráneo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. med. forense;11(39): 63-67, ene. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042113</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Suicidio por arma de fuego</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13791^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1352^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15346^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19168</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
