<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-34354</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of research projects by the Spanish Agency of Evaluation and Prospective</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper describes the procedure used by the Spanish Agency of Evaluation and Prospective (ANEP) to evaluate research projects. The problems involved in the peer review system used by the ANEP are analysed, and the following parameters used in the evaluation process, and the weights assigned to them, are discussed: experience of the research team, relevance of the objectives, viability of the proposal, coordination between research groups, dissemination of results, budget suitability, research group training capability, assignment of technicians, final report, and final evaluation of the research project. Recent descriptive data from the Spanish Ministry of Science and Technology, in the research areas of Psychology and Education, are presented, providing an overview of current Spanish research in psychology and education. Results show that psychology research projects receive more favourable evaluations than projects in education. Results are disaggregated by sex, university, autonomous region, specific academic field, and other variables of interest. Finally, some tentative conclusions are drawn and future perspectives are discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Marqués, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gordillo, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñiz, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se describe el método de evaluación de los proyectos de investigación seguido por la Agencia Nacional de Evaluación y Prospectiva (ANEP). Se analiza la problemática implicada en la revisión por pares utilizada, y se comentan los siguientes parámetros considerados en la evaluación: experiencia del equipo, interés de los objetivos, viabilidad de la propuesta, coordinación entre equipos, plan de difusión establecido, adecuación del presupuesto, capacidad formativa del grupo investigador, asignación de técnicos, informe final y valoración final. Tras la descripción del procedimiento y de las dificultades más habituales de cada fase, se presentan los datos provenientes de una convocatoria reciente de Promoción General del Conocimiento del Ministerio de Ciencia y Tecnología en el área de Psicología y Educación. Los resultados de la evaluación de esta convocatoria se desglosan en función del sexo de los investigadores principales, universidades, comunidades autónomas y áreas de conocimiento, lo que permite hacerse una idea bastante ajustada y actual de la situación investigadora en las áreas de Psicología y Educación en España. Los datos indican que, en general, los proyectos de Psicología aparecen mejor valorados por los revisores que los de Educación. Finalmente, se extraen algunas conclusiones tentativas y se hacen algunas recomendaciones cara al futuro (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);16(3): 343-349, ago. 2004. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-34354</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La evaluación de Proyectos de Investigación por la Agencia Nacional de Evaluación y Prospectiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14893^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10573^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2046^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12528^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
