<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60950</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5187</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Infections caused by Malassezia sp</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The yeast from the gender Malassezia sp, previously called Pityrosporum are found as part of the microbiota of the skin and 92 to 100% of them havebeen isolated from healthy people. The taxonomy of the gender has been controversial since it was named M. furfur. These opportunistic yeasts arerelated with some human and animal (mamifers) diseases and can also cause systemic infections.According to the body site, different species have been isolated. From the trunk M. sympodialis, M. globosa, M. furfur and M. sloofiae; while in thescalp M. retricta has also been isolated, followed by M. globosa and M. sypodialis. The causal agents in pytiriasis versicolor are M. globosa (97%), associatedto M. sympodialis in one third of the cases and rarely M. sloffiae (7%) and M. furfur. For years Malassezia furfur traditionally was considered theetiological agent.In the spectrum of the infections cause by these gender we found: Seborrheic dermatitis (SD), folliculitis, septicemia, neonatal pustulosis, confluentand reticulated papillomatosis, onychomycosis, seborrheic blepharitis atopic dermatitis and psoriasis. There is a relationship with non dermatologicalentities such as dacryocyctis, otitis, sinusitis, intersticial pneumonia, peritonitis and septicemia.Pityriasis versicolor is a worldwide mycosis, representing 5% of all them. The frequency in warm climates is up to 32-50% o the cases, mainly seen inadults between 20 to 30 years of age. As diagnostic tools one uses the Wood s light and the direct microscopic exam but the culture is not necessary for the diagnosis. Now days there are molecular techniques such as analysis of cariotypification RFLP, RNAr and DNA sequences and physiological characteristicssuch as the assimilation of different sources of lipids (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torres, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Atoche-Diéguez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arenas, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las levaduras del género Malassezia sp. anterioremente Pityrosporum se encuentran formando parte de la microbiota comensal de la piel, se hanaislado en 92 a 100% en personas sanas. La taxonomía del género ha sido controversial desde la creación de M. furfur. Estas levaduras oportunistasestán relacionadas con algunas infecciones cutáneas humanas y de animales de sangre caliente (mamíferos), pudiendo llegar a producir infeccionessistémicas.Las diferentes especies se han aislado de acuerdo a la región corporal. De tronco se ha aislado M. sympodialis, M. globosa, M. furfur y M. sloofiae;mientras que en piel cabelluda, además se ha hallado M. restricta. En conducto auditivo externo la especie más frecuente es M. restricta, seguida deM. globosa y M. sympodialis. Los agentes causales de pitiriasis versicolor son M. globosa (97%), asociada a M. sympodialis en una tercera parte y másraras M. slooffiae (7%) y M. furfur. Tradicionalmente Malassezia furfur era considerada el agente etiológico.Dentro del espectro de infecciones causadas por éste género, se encuentran dermatitis seborréica (DS), foliculitis, septicemia, pustulosis neonatal,papilomatosis confluente y reticulada, onicomicosis, blefaritis seborreica, dermatitis atópica y la psoriasis. Existe relación con padecimientos no dermatológicos,como la dacriocistitis, otitis, sinusitis, neumonía intersticial, peritonitis y septicemia.La pitiriasis versicolor es una micosis de distribución mundial, representa 5% de las micosis en general, en climas calurosos se observa en 32 a 50%,predomina en adultos entre 20 y 30 años de edad. Como auxiliares de diagnóstico se utilizan la luz de Wood, examen microscópico directo, el cultivono es necesario para el diagnóstico. Ahora hay técnicas moleculares como cariotipificación, análisis por RFLP, secuencias de ARNr y ADN y características (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. cután. ibero-lat-am;36(6): 265-284, nov.-dic. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60950</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infecciones causadas por el géneroMalassezia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8464^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3901^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3901^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3901^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
