<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-66120</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The blockage of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system with angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors (ACEI) or with angiotensin receptor blockers (ARB) or both slows nephropathy progression in patients with or without diabetes. Several ACEI-based clinical trials have demonstrated that the benefit of the treatment increases in relationship to the increasing amount of renal function deterioration at study initiation. However, many physicians fail to use ACEI or angiotensin receptor blockers in patients with renal failure, fearing that either serum creatinine or potassium levels will rise</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López García, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El bloqueo del sistema renina-angiotensina-aldosterna con inhibidores de la enzima convertidora de angiotensina (IECA) o con antagonistas del receptor de la angiotensina II (ARA II) o con ambos, retrasa el deterioro de la función renal tanto en pacientes diabéticos como no diabéticos. Varios estudios con IECA han mostrado que el beneficio del tratamiento es mayor cuanto más deteriorada está la función renal en el momento del inicio del tratamiento. Sin embargo, son muchos los médicos que evitan el uso de IECA o ARA II en pacientes con insuficiencia renal por miedo al incremento de los niveles séricos de creatinina o potasio</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);34(3): 127-132, mar. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-66120</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3421^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22640^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22832^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12506^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3951^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11626^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
