<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91761</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sensory experience, crativity and unmentalizing: Technical problems</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper examines the relationship between sensorial life and creativity. It begins by analyzing the testimony of classical and modern music composers. Sensory experience and its creative integration is also looked upon in clinical case material. The second part of this paper considers self-sensoriality as a major obstacle towards metallization of psychological experience. Several technical aspects related to the therapeutic approach with patients that are isolated or have an autistic problematic are finally discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aguilar, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo analiza la vida sensorial en relación a la gestión de la creatividad. Para ello parte del testimonio de diferentes compositores tanto de la música clásica como moderna. La vida sensorial y su integración creativa es analiza, también a partir de material clínico. Es una segunda parte se plantea el papel de la autosensorialidad como un obstáculo importante en relación a la mentalización de la experiencia psicológica. Finalmente se discuten aspectos técnicos relacionados con las posibilidades de entrar en contacto con los pacientes aislados y con problemas de autismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(17): 39-45, abr. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91761</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sensorialidad, cratividad y ddesmentalización: problemas técnicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3423</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36283^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9340</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
