<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111672</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Human scabies or scabies is a contagious infestation transmitted by intimate contact between people</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study describes an outbreak of scabies among employees of the University Hospital Complex of Ourense (CHUO). The index case was a 85 years old patient who had been as a inpatient and suffered from Norwegian scabies. There were 17 diagnoses of scabies among healthcare workers. Once detected the outbread, the Unit for the Prevention of Occupational Risks, integrated at Preventive Medicine Unit implemented control measures. The early preentive measures were essential for the control measures. The early preventive measures were essential for the control of the outbreak and the prevention od disease transmission to health workers, as well as their contacts (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Magdalena Iglesias, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Sampayo, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Rodríguez, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villamarín Bello, María Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández de Armas, Lisset</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moure Rodríguez, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La sarna humana o escabiosis es una infestación contagiosa transmitida por el contacto íntimo entre las personas. El objetivo de este trabajo es describir un brote de sarna ocurrido en trabajadores de una planta de hospitalización del Complexo Hospitalario Universitario de Ourense (CHUO), cuyo origen fue una paciente de 85 años ingresada con la enfermedad. Una vez detectado el brote, la Unidad de Prevención de Riesgos Laborales (UPRL), integrada en el Servicio de Medicina Preventiva llevó a cabo las actuaciones para el control del mismo. Se produjeron 17 casos de sarna en personal sanitario. La rápida adopción de medidas preventivas fue clave para el control del brote, evitando la transmisión de la enfermedad entre el personal sanitario y demás contactos de los casos diagnosticados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;22(1): 18-23, mar. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111672</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Brote de escabiosis profesional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29063^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28589</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12914^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9113^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
