<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102231</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Focal dystonia in musicians</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: A special group of focal dystonia is that known as occupational, which include dystonic disorders triggered by repetitive motor activity, closely associated with the professional activity of a specific task that the affected person performs. In this sense, musicians are a population particularly vulnerable to this disorder, which is presented during the execution of highly trained movements. Objective: This article reviews the pathophysiology of focal dystonia and its therapeutic implications. Development: The pathophysiological basis of focal dystonia in the musician is still not well established. However, due to the contribution of neurophysiological studies and functional neuroimaging, there is growing evidence of anomalies in the processing of sensory information, sensory-motor integration, cortical and subcortical inhibitory processes, which underline this disease. Development: Clinically, it is characterised by the appearance of involuntary muscle contractions, and is associated with loss of motor control while practicing music. It is a gradual appearance and sometimes there may be a history of musculoskeletal injuries or non-physiological postures preceding the appearance of the symptoms. The neurological examination is usually normal, although subtle dystonic postures can develop spontaneously or with movements that involve the affected segments. The dystonia remains focal and is not generalised. Conclussions: Treatment is based on using multiple strategies for the management of the dystonia, with variable results. Although a specific therapy has not been defined, there are general principles that are combined in each situation looking for results. This includes, among others, pharmacological interventions, management with botulinum toxin, and sensory re-training techniques (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Chana Cuevas, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aránguiz, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alburquerque, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Un grupo especial de distonía focal son las conocidas como ocupacionales, las que incluyen trastornos distónicos desencadenados por una actividad motora repetitiva, íntimamente relacionada con la actividad profesional o tarea específica que realiza el afectado. En este sentido los músicos son una población especialmente vulnerable a esta patología, que se presenta durante la ejecución de movimientos altamente entrenados. Objetivo: En este manuscrito se revisa la fisiopatología y sus implicancias terapéuticas.Desarrollo: Las bases fisiopatológicas de la distonía focal del músico aún no se conocen completamente. Sin embargo, gracias al aporte de estudios neurofisiológicos y de neuroimágenes funcionales, existe creciente evidencia de alteraciones en el procesamiento de información sensorial, integración sensorio-motora, procesos corticales y subcorticales de inhibición, que subyacen a esta patología.Desarrollo: Clínicamente, se caracteriza por aparición de contracción muscular involuntaria y se asocia a pérdida del control motor durante la ejecución musical. Es de aparición gradual y ocasionalmente pueden existir antecedentes de lesiones musculoesqueléticas o posturas no fisiológicas que anteceden la aparición de los síntomas. El examen neurológico es usualmente normal, aunque pueden desarrollarse posturas distónicas sutiles espontáneamente o con movimientos que involucran los segmentos afectados. La distonía permanece focal y no se generaliza.Conclusiones: El tratamiento se basa en la utilización de múltiples estrategias para el manejo de la distonía, con resultado variables. Si bien no se ha definido una terapia especifica, existen principios generales que se combinan en cada situación buscando obtener resultados. Esto incluye intervenciones desde una perspectiva farmacológica, manejo con toxina botulínica, técnicas de reentrenamiento sensorial, entre otras (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;26(1): 45-52, ene.-feb. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102231</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Distonía focales en los músicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34287^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22981^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9339</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33081^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
