<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143445</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nosocomial infection due to Trichosporon asahii in a critical burned patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Invasive fungal infection is an important cause of morbimortality in patients with severe burns. The advances in burn care therapy have considerably extended the survival of seriously burned patients, exposing them to infectious complications, notably fungal infections, with increased recognition of invasive infections caused by Candida species. However, some opportunistic fungi, like Trichosporon asahii, have emerged as important causes of nosocomial infection. Case report. A case of nosocomial infection due to T. asahii in a severely ill burned patient successfully treated with voriconazole is presented. The management of invasive fungal infections in burned patients, from diagnosis to selection of the therapeutic protocol, is often a challenge. Early diagnosis and treatment are associated with a better prognosis. In this case report, current treatment options are discussed, and a review of previously published cases is presented. Conclusions. Due to the difficulty in the diagnosis of invasive mycoses and their high associated mortality rates, it is advisable to keep a high degree of clinical suspicion of trichosporonosis in susceptible patients, including burned patients. The isolation of T. asahii in clinical specimens of this type of host must raise clinical alert, since it may precede an invasive infection (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Piqueras Pérez, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tamayo Lomas, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez-Gil González, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Luengo, Ana Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Eiros Bouza, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. La infección fúngica invasiva es una causa importante de morbimortalidad en los pacientes con quemaduras graves. Los avances en el tratamiento del paciente quemado crítico han llevado a una supervivencia mayor, pero, a su vez, a un aumento de las complicaciones sépticas, en especial de las infecciones fúngicas, con un incremento de las infecciones por diferentes especies de Candida. Sin embargo, algunos hongos oportunistas, como Trichosporon asahii, están emergiendo como causa importante de infección nosocomial. Caso clínico. Presentamos un caso de infección nosocomial por T. asahii en un paciente quemado crítico tratado de forma exitosa con voriconazol. El tratamiento de las infecciones fúngicas invasivas en el paciente quemado, desde su diagnóstico hasta la elección de la mejor opción terapéutica, continúa siendo un desafío. El diagnóstico y el tratamiento tempranos de estas se asocia a un mejor pronóstico. En la discusión del caso hacemos referencia a la experiencia publicada y a las pautas de tratamiento actual. Conclusiones. Debido a la dificultad para el diagnóstico de las micosis invasivas y su asociación con una alta mortalidad, en aquellos pacientes susceptibles de padecer una trichosporonosis se debe mantener un alto grado de sospecha y vigilancia clínica para el diagnóstico de esta infección, incluidos los pacientes quemados. Su presencia en las muestras clínicas de este tipo de pacientes debe ser tenida en cuenta porque puede preceder a una infección invasiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;32(4): 257-60, oct.-dic. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143445</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infección nosocomial por Trichosporon asahii en un paciente quemado crítico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2088^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54478^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19535^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
