<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057017</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-5981</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The volar approach in the surgical treatment of distal radius fractures</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Distal radius fractures can be treated both in an orthopedic    or surgical way depending on fractures patterns and    patients general conditions. The main indication for surgical    treatment comes from a fracture with displacement of    bone fragments in a young patient with high functional demand.    The implants for osteosinthesys had changed very    much in recent years, and the ultimate designs had even    changed the indications for surgical treatment with a volar    approach. The versatility of the «fixed angle plates» had    made that the volar approach become tha main surgical    approach for most of surgical treated fractures. This technique    implies a precise x ray control during surgery for a    satisfactory outcome</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dudley, A. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Olea, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las fracturas de la extremidad distal del radio pueden ser    tratadas de forma ortopédica o quirúrgica dependiendo de    las características de la fractura y de las condiciones generales    de cada paciente. La indicación principal de la cirugía    se produce en fracturas con desplazamiento de los    fragmentos en pacientes jóvenes, con alta demanda funcional.    El material de osteosíntesis ha variado mucho en    los últimos tiempos, y los últimos modelos de placas de    osteosíntesis han cambiado las indicaciones de tratamiento    mediante abordaje volar. La versatilidad de las placas    de «ángulo fijo» han hecho que el abordaje volar sea en    estos momentos la principal vía de abordaje para la mayoría    de los tipos de fracturas tratadas quirúrgicamente. Esta    técnica requiere de un preciso control de rayos intraoperatorio    para su correcta realización</dc:description>
<dc:source>Patol. apar. locomot. Fund. Mapfre Med;5(supl.2): 47-50, 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057017</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento quirúrgico de las fracturas distales de radio por abordaje volar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10161^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12319^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
