<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162272</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Lixisenatide in patients with type 2 diabetes and obesity: Beyond glycaemic control</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To evaluate tolerance to lixisenatide and its effects on weight and metabolic control in type 2 diabetes and obese patients. Design: Prospective study. Setting: Endocrinology clinics in Almeria, Granada and Malaga. Participants: Patients with type 2 diabetes and obesity. Interventions: Response and tolerance to lixisenatide treatment. Main measurements: Clinical and analytical data of the subjects were evaluated at baseline and after treatment. Results: The study included 104 patients (51% women) with type 2 diabetes and obesity (Almeria 18.3%; Granada 40.4%; Malaga 41.3%). The mean age was 58.4±10.5 years, and the mean duration of diabetes was 11.2±6.7 years. The patients were re-evaluated at 3.8±1.6 months after treatment with lixisenatide. Significant improvements were found in weight (P&lt;.001), body mass index (P&lt;.001), waist circumference (P=.002), systolic blood pressure (P&lt;.001), diastolic blood pressure (P=.001), fasting glucose (P&lt;.001), HbA1c (P=.022), Total cholesterol (P&lt;.001), LDL-cholesterol (P=.046), triglycerides (P=.020), hypertension drugs (P&lt;.001), and lipids drugs (P&lt;.001). No changes were observed in levels of amylase related to lixisenatide treatment, and 7.9% of patients did not tolerate it. Conclusions: Lixisenatide achieved signi&amp;#64257;cant improvements in anthropometric parameters, glycaemic control (fasting glucose and HbA1c), blood pressure and lipids. It was safe and well tolerated in most patients. In addition, there was a significant increase in the use of antihypertensive and lipid-lowering therapy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Piédrola-Maroto, Gonzalo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roca-Rodríguez, M Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tinahones, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mancha-Doblas, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quesada-Charneco, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muros de Fuentes, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maraver-Selfa, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la tolerancia a lixisenatida y sus efectos sobre el peso y el control metabólico de pacientes con diabetes tipo 2 y obesidad. Diseño: Estudio prospectivo. Emplazamiento: Consultas de atención especializada de Endocrinología y Nutrición en Almería, Granada y Málaga. Participantes: Pacientes con diabetes tipo 2 y obesidad. Intervenciones: Respuesta y tolerancia al tratamiento con lixisenatida. Mediciones principales: Se analizaron datos clínicos y analíticos con medidas de cambio intrasujeto antes-después del tratamiento. Resultados: Evaluamos 104 pacientes (51% mujeres) con diabetes tipo 2 y obesidad (Almería 18,3%; Granada 40,4%; Málaga 41,3%). Edad media 58,4±10,5 años y duración media de diabetes 11,2±6,7 años. El tiempo medio desde la visita basal a la revisión tras inicio de tratamiento con lixisenatida fue de 3,8±1,6 meses. Encontramos mejoría significativa del peso (p&lt;0,001), índice de masa corporal (p&lt;0,001), circunferencia de cintura (p=0,002), presión arterial sistólica (p&lt;0,001) y diastólica (p=0,001), glucemia en ayunas (p&lt;0,001), HbA1c (p=0,022), colesterol total (p&lt;0,001), colesterol LDL (p=0,046) y triglicéridos (p=0,020). No se observó alteración de cifras de amilasa en relación con el tratamiento con lixisenatida, y el 7,9% no lo toleraron. Conclusiones: Lixisenatida consigue: 1) mejoría significativa de parámetros antropométricos y control glucémico (glucemia basal y HbA1c); 2) descenso significativo de la presión arterial y del perfil lipídico, y 3) seguridad y buena tolerancia en la mayoría de los pacientes. Además, encontramos una significativa intensificación del tratamiento antihipertensivo e hipolipemiante (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;49(5): 294-299, mayo 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162272</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lixisenatida en pacientes con diabetes tipo 2 y obesidad: más allá del control glucémico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37656^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50567^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4420</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
