<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87072</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The «burned-out» service member</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Lately the fashion in medicine is to utilize an expression that attracts more and more experts and specialists: the burnout syndrome, which could be translated by the colloquial expression «síndrome del quemado» for job-related issues. However, and in spite of the huge impact that this syndrome could have on the effi cacy of the Armed Forces there is not an abundance of specialized literature dealing in depth on how it affects Spanish military personnel, which could be the causes of its appearance in the military environment and its effects and derived consequences. The objective of this study is precisely to emphasize the high probability that an increasing number of Spanish service members will become victims of this syndrome, to increase the awareness among the responsible people of the need to adopt palliative and correcting measures, to inform the affected personnel about the urgency of the treatment, and fi nally to raise the concern so that future experts and researchers, mainly psychiatrists and psychologists,   study in depth this subject and advise on approaches, preventive and therapeutical. One unavoidable conclusion will be that it is necessary to carry out periodic evaluations among the different groups of service members of all ranks and different appointments so as to determine the prevalence of the syndrome and identify its associated professional factors. Moreover, it seems even more compulsory, if anything, to perform these studies in absolutely all personnel coming back from a foreign deployment (no matter what is its offi cial consideration) and in the members of those units (more specifi cally in the Emergency Military Unit) that have experienced an extreme situation or have become highly involved in different support operations to the populace in the national territory. Neither should it be forgotten to execute a rigorous follow-up of these personnel, and also keep in touch with their closest relatives, as they will provide useful insights in the true attitude of the service members in the environment where they act more spontaneously and naturally. There is no doubt that in today&#146;s society to be in the military implies to accept facts and develop protective strategies against the psychological risks of this profession. But that requires the active participation of the medical services, psychiatric and psychological, of the Armed Forces. The warning has already sounded, now someone responsible should initiate the appropriate procedures (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Corrales, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gándara Martín, J. J de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baños Bajo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos tiempos, se ha puesto de moda en medicina el empleo de un término que cada vez atrae a más estudiosos y especialistas: el síndrome burnout, que se podría traducir por la más coloquial expresión de síndrome del «quemado» por cuestiones relacionadas con el trabajo. Sin embargo, y a pesar de la enorme infl uencia que este síndrome puede tener en la efi cacia de las Fuerzas Armadas, no prolifera la literatura especializada que trate en profundidad en qué medida el profesional militar español puede estar afectado, cuáles podrían ser las causas de su  implantación en el seno castrense y los efectos y las consecuencias que de ellas se derivarían. El objeto de este estudio es, precisamente, alertar sobre la alta probabilidad de que un número creciente de militares españoles sean víctimas de este síndrome, concienciar a los responsables correspondientes de la necesidad de adoptar medidas paliativas y correctoras, abrir los ojos a los propios afectados sobre la perentoria urgencia  de su tratamiento y, en fi n, crear una inquietud para que futuros expertos e investigadores, principalmente psiquiatras y psicólogos, profundicen en el tema y aconsejen y aporten vías de solución, tanto preventivas como en forma de efi caces tratamientos. Una de las conclusiones ineludibles va a ser que es imprescindible efectuar valoraciones periódicas entre diversos grupos de militares de todos los empleos y en diferentes destinos,  con la fi nalidad de determinar la prevalencia del síndrome e identifi car sus factores profesionales asociados. Además, se antoja todavía más obligatorio, si cabe, realizar este tipo de estudios en absolutamente todo el personal que regrese de una misión en el exterior (independiente de la consideración ofi cial que tenga) y en los integrantes de unidades (muy concretamente en el de la Unidad Militar de Emergencias) que hayan pasado por una experiencia extrema o que hayan mantenido un alto grado de involucración en diversas operaciones de apoyo a la población civil en territorio nacional. Tampoco se debe olvidar el preciso seguimiento en el tiempo de este personal, así como del contacto con sus familiares más  allegados, que darán el pulso de la verdadera actitud del profesional en los ámbitos donde éste actúa con mayor naturalidad y espontaneidad. Sin duda, ser militar en la sociedad actual supone aceptar realidades y desarrollar estrategias que protejan al profesional de los riesgos psicológicos de su actividad. Pero ello implica la participación activa de los servicios médicos, psiquiátricos y psicológicos de las Fuerzas Armadas. El aviso está dado, sólo queda la voluntad, por parte de quien le corresponda, de poner en marcha los mecanismos pertinentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;66(1): 39-50, ene.-mar. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87072</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El militar quemado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9077^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3161^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
