<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-68878</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Monoamine oxidase A (MAO-A) is an enzyme that regulates the metabolic degradation of serotonin andnoradrenaline in the nervous system. Both neurotransmitters are clearly involved in modulating aggression. Indeed, the serotonergic system is one of the main neurotransmission systems related to the appearance of impulsive and violent behaviors. The present article provides an updated review of the role of the MAO-A enzyme in regulating aggressive behavior in experimental animals and humans (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Perea, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, José Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-López, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morabet, Loubna</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La monoaminooxidasa A (MAO-A) es una enzima que regula la degradación metabólica de serotonina y noradrenalina en el sistema nervioso. Ambos neurotransmisores han sido claramente involucrados en la modulación de la agresión. De hecho, el sistemas erotoninérgico representa uno de los principales sistemas de neurotransmisión relacionado con la aparición de conductas impulsivas y violentas. En este trabajo se presenta una revisión actualizada del papel de la enzima MAO-A en la regulación de la conducta agresiva, tanto en animales de experimentación como en humanos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);15(5): 175-181, oct.-dic. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-68878</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24311^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d382^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23962^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d378^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9187^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
