<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105606</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Self-injurious behavior in Portuguese adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In order to assess the frequency and correlates of self-injurious behavior (SIB), 569 Portuguese adolescents aged 12 to 20 years completed questionnaires assessing SIB and psychopathological symptoms. Almost 28% (n = 158) reported a lifetime history of SIB and nearly 10% had performed it in the previous month. The most frequently injured body parts were arms, hands and nails. Most of the self-injurers admit that &#147;now and then&#148; they feel some «mild» to «moderate» pain during SIB. Most of them admitted using these behaviors to avoid/suppress negative feelings, painful images or memories, to punish themselves and to avoid doing something bad. Positive emotions increased significantly after SIB. The self-injurer group reported more psychopathological symptoms. SIB appears to be a common phenomenon with specific functions in adolescence and this must be addressed by clinicians and educational professionals (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferreira Gonçalves, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosendo, Ana Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>César Machado, Bárbara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martins, Carla</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva, Eliana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Con la finalidad de evaluar la frecuencia y la correlación de la conducta autolesiva en 569 adolescentes portugueses de edades comprendidas entre 12 y 20 años de edad, se han completado cuestionarios evaluando la conducta autolesiva y los síntomas psicopatológicos. El 28% (n= 158) reportó un historial de conducta autolesiva y el 10% lo habían tenido el mes anterior. Las partes del cuerpo con mayores lesiones son los brazos, las manos y las uñas. Asimismo, la mayoría de las personas que se autolesionan admiten sentirse en ese momento con un dolor entre ligero y moderado. Además, admiten usar esta conducta con el fin de evitar o suprimir sentimientos negativos, imágenes y memorias dolorosas para autocastigarse y para evitar hacer algo malo. Las emociones positivas se incrementan de forma significativa después de la conducta autolesiva y el grupo de los que se autolesionan presentan más síntomas psicopatológicos. La conducta autolesiva parece ser un fenómeno común con funciones específicas en la adolescencia y esto debe ser tratado por profesionales del área clínica y educacional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);24(4): 536-541, oct.-dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105606</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conducta autolesiva en adolescentes portugueses</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11613^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
