<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86313</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5735</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Considerations about an approach to depathologization of the transsexualism</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this paper concepts and theories related to gender identity are reviewed. We subsequently discuss different approaches to treatment and conception of what&#146;s known as Gender Indentity Disorders. Some experts, professionals and transgender associations agree in considering transsexualism as a mental disorder. Others consider it a Sex Differentiation Disorder, while others demand depathologization of the foretold Gender Identity Disorder(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Olivares Zarco, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Polo Usaola, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se revisan conceptos y teorías relacionados con la identidad de género. Posteriormente se discuten las diferentes propuestas que abordan la consideración de los trastornos relacionados con este concepto. Dentro de los colectivos de transexuales y de profesionales estudiosos del tema, existen algunos que coinciden en conceptualizar la transexualidad como un trastorno mental, otros como un trastorno en la diferenciación sexual y otros que solicitan la despatologización del llamado trastorno de identidad de género(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Neuropsiquiatr;31(110): 285-302, abr.-jun. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86313</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consideraciones en torno a la propuesta de despatologización de la transexualidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23910^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7244</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5924</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12023^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12023^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
