<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84323</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Conformity to Masculine Gender Norms Inventory in the Spanish population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The administration of the Conformity to Masculine Norms Inventory - CMNI (Mahalik et al., 2003) in a group of Spanish men is described. The CMNI was designed to assess, from a multidimensional perspective, men's degree of conformity to a series of gender norms identified in the dominant culture of the United States of America. The questionnaire was administered to 727 men between 18 and 83 years of age with a mean age of 30.17 (S. D. 12.14), with diverse educational levels and heterogeneous work situations and who came from various regions of Spain. The reliability data are mostly satisfactory, and the correlation matrix between the subscales confirms Mahalik's (2000) theoretical model. The differences between the results obtained in the Spanish group and the American group suggest the effect of cultural factors. Factor analysis revealed a structure characterised by the grouping of items similar to the one obtained in the USA and, although it is different in some aspects, in general, it supports the structure proposed by the authors. We suggest regrouping some of the subscales that have been shown to be related in other supraordered subscales with the aim of improving the suitability of the CMNI for use in Spanish population (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cuéllar-Flores, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dresch, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-López, María del Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se analizan los resultados de la aplicación del Inventario de Conformidad con las Normas de Género Masculinas - CMNI (Mahalik et al., 2003) en un grupo de hombres adultos españoles. El CMNI fue diseñado para evaluar, desde una perspectiva multidimensional, el grado de conformidad de los hombres hacia un conjunto de normas de género identificadas en la cultura dominante de EEUU. Se ha aplicado el cuestionario a 727 hombres de entre 18 y 83 años con una edad media de 30.17 (D. T. 12.14), varios niveles educativos y situación laboral heterogénea y que procedían de varias regiones españolas. Los datos de fiabilidad son, en su mayoría, satisfactorios, y la matriz de correlaciones entre subescalas confirma el modelo teórico de Mahalik (2000). Las diferencias en los resultados obtenidos en nuestro grupo y en el grupo de estadounidenses sugieren el efecto de factores culturales (históricos, generacionales y educacionales). El análisis factorial revela una estructura caracterizada por la agrupación de ítems similar al obtenido en USA, y aunque difiere en algunos aspectos, apoya en general la estructura propuesta por los autores. Se sugiere la reagrupación de algunas de las subescalas que se han mostrado relacionadas en otras supraordenadas con el objeto de mejorar la adecuación del CMNI para ser usado en población española (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;27(1): 170-178, ene.-abr. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84323</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El Inventario de Conformidad con las Normas de Género Masculinas (CMNI) en la población española</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10746</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13113</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13329</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5924</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
