<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148013</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Deep defense to asses labor risks for noise in power station</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The labour risks evaluation techniques are carried out using several methods, through the application of normative methods applying the execution of the parameters associated with the measurements of the men&#146;s health damage thresholds. Basic security principles are nevertheless not taken into account, which enclose the good practices experiences in high-requirement security and availability industries.  Objectives: The purpose of this article is to propose a method attending on the defence in depth in order to evaluate the noise labour risks in the Thermal Power Station (TPS) of 100 MW.  Material and Methods: In order to explore the elements considered in the evaluation of the noise labours risks, interviews to technicians and specialists in labour security and health were taken. It was carried out the consultation to specialists in order to specify the elements that should be part of the security aspects according to the nominative method. The evaluation of the labours risks for noise together with the proposal were also carried out according to two methodologies prior employed.  Results: three methodologies were used. It was determined that the noise generation is not a significant aspect to keep in mind for the methodology 1. For the methodology 2 it was demonstrated a dispersion of the noise level with stable tendency to the maximal values in determining areas according to the Noise Cuban Norm, while for the methodology 3, the security aspects negatively evaluated for each step, are those which require to take corrective measures implemented to modify the negatively-qualified items to positive in order to raise the security level.  Conclusions: The evaluation using the depth security levels applied to the labour risks allows to estimate an analysis with the process approach, that allow not only to esteem the relative contribution and its causes but to resolve them in a short-term period (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salomón Llanes, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perdomo Ojeda, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miranda Cuéllar, Roani Ladislá</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las técnicas de evaluación de riesgos laborales se llevan a cabo por diferentes procedimientos, a través de las aplicaciones de métodos normativos del cumplimiento de los parámetros asociados con las mediciones de los umbrales de daño a la salud del hombre. Sin embargo, no se tienen en cuenta los principios básicos de seguridad, que incluyen las experiencias de buenas prácticas en industrias de altos requisitos de seguridad y disponibilidad. Objetivos: El objetivo de este artículo es proponer un método bajo el enfoque de defensa en profundidad para evaluar los riesgos laborales por ruido en la Central Termoeléctrica (CTE) de 100 MW.  Material y Métodos: Se aplicó la técnica de entrevistas a técnicos y especialistas en seguridad y salud del trabajo, así como tecnólogos para explorar los elementos que tomaban en cuenta en la evaluación de los riesgos laborales por ruido, y se realizó la consulta a especialistas para precisar los elementos que debían formar parte de los aspectos de seguridad de acuerdo al método propuesto. Además Se realizó la evaluación de los riesgos laborales por ruido de acuerdo a dos metodologías implementadas con anterioridad y la propuesta.  Resultados: Se muestran de acuerdo a las tres metodologías. Se determinó que la generación de ruidos no es un aspecto significativo a tener en cuenta, para la metodología 1, se evidenció una dispersión del nivel sonoro, con tendencia estable a los valores máximos en determinadas áreas según la Norma Cubana de ruido, para la metodología 2 mientras que para la metodología 3, los aspectos de seguridad evaluados negativamente por cada escalón, son los que se requieren tomar medidas correctivas dirigidas a modificar los ítems calificados negativamente a positivos para elevar el nivel de seguridad.  Conclusiones: La evaluación empleando escalones de defensa en profundidad aplicado a los riesgos laborales posibilita un análisis con el enfoque de procesos, que permite estimar la contribución relativa y sus causas, así como resolverlas en un corto plazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;61(240): 354-366, jul.-sept. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148013</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Defensa en profundidad para la evaluación de riesgos laborales por ruido en termoeléctrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32436^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3688^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32465</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16359^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51777^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
