<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129330</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The value of using administrative data in public health research: the Continuous Working Life Sample</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The use of administrative data is common practice in public health research. The present field note describes the Continuous Working Life Sample (CWLS) and its use in health research. The CWLS is built on records generated by all contacts with the social security system (work contracts, disability, etc.), plus tax data (monetary gains, income, etc.) and census data (level of education, country of birth, etc.), but does not allow individuals to be identified. The CWLS was started in 2004 with 4% (1.1 million persons) of the total population who were either contributors to or beneficiaries of the social security system. The information on the individuals in the CWLS is updated annually and lost individuals are replaced. This continuous design allows the construction of a cohort with information on working life and financial status and evaluation of their relationship with work disability. Future connection with clinical records would enable analysis of other health-related outcomes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López, María Andrée</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, José Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benavides, Fernando G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durán, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espallargues, Mireia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La utilización de datos administrativos es práctica habitual en la investigación en salud pública. El objetivo de este trabajo es describir la Muestra continua de vidas laborales (MCVL) y su utilidad en la investigación en salud. La MCVL está construida sobre registros que generan todos los contactos con la Seguridad Social (laborales, incapacidades, etc.), más datos fiscales (percepciones dinerarias, ingresos, etc.) y del padrón (nivel educativo, país de nacimiento, etc.), sin que sea posible la identificación individual. La MCVL se inició en 2004 con el 4% (1,1 millón de personas) del total de población cotizante o perceptora de la Seguridad Social. Los datos de las personas que forman parte de la MCVL son actualizados anualmente, y se sustituyen las bajas producidas. Este diseño continuo permite generar una cohorte con información de la vida laboral y económica, y valorar su asociación con la incapacidad laboral. El supuesto de conexión con la historia clínica posibilitaría el análisis de otros resultados de salud (AU) </dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;28(4): 334-337, jul.-ago. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129330</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La utilidad del uso de datos administrativos en la investigación de salud pública: la Muestra continua de vidas laborales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36415</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51292</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
