<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133842</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ultrasound-guided percutaneous drainage and sclerotherapy in a patient with isolated autosomal dominant polycystic liver disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Isolated polycystic liver disease (IPLD) is a rare genetic condition characterized by the presence of multiple liver cysts with no association with polycystic kidney disease. Most patients are asymptomatic and acute complications (cyst torsion, bleeding, infection) are uncommon. Imaging techniques, including abdominal ultrasounds, computerized axial tomography, and magnetic resonance imaging, represent a vital diagnostic modality. They are also useful for therapy support in this disease. Below we report a peculiar case of a female patient recently diagnosed with IPLD who, having received treatment with ultrasound-guided percutaneous drainage and sclerotherapy for a giant liver cyst, showed symptom and laboratory improvement (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barbado Cano, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno López, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cerpa Arencibia, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olveira Martín, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Martos, Rubén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez de Parga, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad hepática poliquística aislada (EHPA), es una rara entidad genética que se caracteriza por la presencia de múltiples quistes hepáticos, sin estar asociada a la poliquistosis renal. La mayoría de los pacientes son asintomáticos, y son infrecuentes las complicaciones agudas (torsión quística, hemorragia e infecciones). Las técnicas de imagen, como la ecografía abdominal, tomografía axial computarizada y resonancia magnética, son un método diagnóstico fundamental. Además, son útiles como apoyo terapéutico en esta enfermedad. A continuación les presentamos un caso clínico peculiar de una paciente recientemente diagnosticada de enfermedad hepática poliquística aislada, quien tras recibir un tratamiento con drenaje percutáneo de un quiste hepático gigante y escleroterapia guiada por ecografía, presentó mejoría sintomática y analítica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;107(3): 175-177, mar. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133842</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Drenaje percutáneo y escleroterapia guiada por ecografía en paciente con poliquistosis hepática aislada autosómica dominante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24871^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34293^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8281^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36296^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27990^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3577^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30024^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
