<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106846</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">An uncommon case of proximal Crohn's disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Crohn's disease (CD) is a chronic, inflammatory disorder that can involve any part of the gastrointestinal tract, from the mouth to the anus. Although CD mainly affects the terminal ileum and colon, the involvement of the upper gastrointestinal tract rarely occurs. Diagnosis is based on clinical, endoscopic and histological features. Treatment for CD of the upper gastrointestinal tract is similar to distal CD therapy. Corticosteroids added to proton pump inhibitors are usually used. The case of a 42-year-old female patient with CD located in the oesophagus, stomach and duodenum is presented. Among the complementary tests, an endoscopic evaluation of the upper gastrointestinal tract with biopsies was essential to support CD diagnosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Redondo-Sendino, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad de Crohn (EC) es un trastorno inflamatorio crónico que puede afectar a cualquier parte del tracto digestivo, desde la boca hasta el ano. Aunque se manifiesta preferentemente en íleon terminal y colon, el tracto gastrointestinal alto puede afectarse en raras ocasiones. El diagnóstico se basa en los hallazgos clínicos, endoscópicos e histológicos. El tratamiento de la EC del tracto gastrointestinal proximal es similar al indicado en la EC distal. Se emplean habitualmente glucocorticoides, asociados a inhibidores de la bomba de protones. Se expone el caso clínico de una paciente de 42 años con EC localizada en esófago, estómago y duodeno. Entre las pruebas complementarias, la endoscopia alta con toma de biopsias fue esencial para llegar al diagnóstico de EC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);38(8): 539-542, nov.-dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106846</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Un caso infrecuente de enfermedad de Crohn proximal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33400^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29396^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13178^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13178^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19276^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6082^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29396^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5897^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5897^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22622^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d673^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
