<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102047</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-9895</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pleuropulmonary synovial sarcoma presenting as recurrent pneumothorax</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Synovial sarcomas are a soft-tissue neoplasms which affects young and middle-aged people, with no difference in distribution between sexes. They are located in the extremities in the 90% of the cases. Pleuropulmonary primary synovial sarcoma SSPP is very unusual, constitutes 0.1% of pulmonary tumors. In most cases the SSPP present themselves with cough and / or hemoptysis whereas pneumothorax is an uncommon form of presentation. Prognosis is usually poor, they present high risk of local recurrence. The survival rate depends on the surgical treatment, being the complete tumor resection the main predicting factor. Surgery is the treatment of choice followed by chemotherapy, radiotherapy or both. We present a case report of a pleuropulmonary synovial sarcoma which presented with pneumothorax (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Esturi, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galbis, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gaspar, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rinaldi, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estors, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los sarcomas sinoviales son neoplasias de tejidos blandos, afectan a adultos jóvenes y de mediana edad, no existen diferencias con respecto a la distribución por sexo. Se localizan en el 90% de los casos en las extremidades. El sarcoma sinovial pleuropulmonar primario (SSPP) es muy poco frecuente, constituye el 0,1% de los tumores pulmonares. Frecuentemente se manifiesta con tos y/o hemoptisis, el neumotórax es una forma poco común de presentación. Son tumores con mal pronóstico y presentan alto riesgo de recidivas locales. Las mejores supervivencias están relacionadas con el tratamiento quirúrgico, siendo la resección completa tumoral el principal factor pronóstico. El tratamiento de elección es quirúrgico, seguido de quimioterapia, radioterapia o ambas. Presentamos el caso clínico de un sarcoma pleuropulmonar primario que clínicamente se manifestó como neumotórax (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. patol. respir;15(2): 61-63, abr.-jun. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102047</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neumotórax de repetición como presentación de sarcoma sinovial pleuropulmonar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31919^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14570^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11426^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11460^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
