<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136557</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Current role of protatic specific antigen (PSA) and its by-products in the diagnosis of prostate cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Incorporation of prostatic specific antigen (PSA) to clinical practice was a revolution in the diagnosis and modified the epidemiology of prostate cancer (PCa). Although it lacks of many characteristics of an ideal tumor marker, it is the marker most used for diagnosis and follow up of any kind of cancer. It represents the best clinical tool we have available today for screening and staging of PCa. On the contrary, its greatest limitation is the lack of tumor specificity. The use of PSA by-products and molecular isoforms tries to solve, at least partially, its limitations. Indeed, the use of FreePSA ratio (%fPSA) ad PSA density (PSAD) increase significantly the specificity of the diagnostic test and, the use of derivatives that evaluate time kinetics of PSA (PSA velocity (PSAV) and PSA doubling time (PSADT)) represents a very useful tool for prognosis estimation during treatment and follow up of the disease. The greatest advance over the last years comes from the analysis of the predecessor isoform (-2) pPSA and the phi Index. Both markers have demonstrated to improve the sensitivity and specificity results obtained to date, resulting in a decrease of unnecessary biopsies. Probably, with the ongoing development of new markers for PCa , the role of PSA on disease diagnosis and staging would be modified in a few years (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Celma, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Placer, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Planas, Jacques</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morote, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La incorporación del antígeno prostático específico (PSA) a la clínica revolucionó el diagnóstico y modificó la epidemiología del cáncer de próstata (CaP). Aunque le faltan muchas de las características de un marcador tumoral ideal, es el marcador más usado para el diagnóstico y seguimiento de cualquier tipo cáncer. Representa la mejor herramienta clínica de las que disponemos en la actualidad para el cribado y estadificación del CaP. Por contra, la mayor limitación que presenta el PSA es su falta de especificidad tumoral. El empleo de los derivados y de las isoformas moleculares del PSA trata de solventar, al menos en parte, sus limitaciones. De hecho, la utilización del cociente del PSA libre (%fPSA) y de la densidad del PSA (PSAD) aumenta de forma significativa la especificidad del test en el diagnóstico y, el uso de los derivados que evalúan la cinética temporal del PSA (velocidad del PSA (PSAV) y tiempo de duplicación del PSA (PSADT)) representan herramientas de gran utilidad para estimar el pronóstico durante el tratamiento y seguimiento de la enfermedad. El mayor avance que se ha producido en los últimos años ha venido del análisis de la isoforma precursora (-2)pPSA y del índice phi. Ambos marcadores han demostrado mejorar los resultados de sensibilidad y especificidad obtenidos hasta ahora, ocasionando una disminución de biopsias innecesarias. Es probable que con el desarrollo de nuevos marcadores para el CaP que está habiendo, en pocos años se modifique el papel que el PSA tiene en el diagnóstico y en la estadificación de la enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;68(3): 210-228, abr. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136557</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papel actual del antígeno prostático específico (PSA) y sus derivados en el diagnóstico del cáncer de próstata</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24373^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30596^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23326^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23326</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33840</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30596^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30596^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30596^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
