<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110229</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish normative studies in young adults ( NEURONORMA young adults project): norms for Stroop Color-Word Interference and Tower of London-Drexel University tests</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The Stroop Color-Word Interference Test (Stroop) measures cognitive flexibility,  elective attention, cognitive inhibition and information processing speed. The Tower of London-Drexel University version test (TOLDX) assesses higher-order problem solving and executive planning abilities. Objective: In this study, as part of the Spanish normative studies project in young adults (NEURONORMA young adults), we present normative data for the Stroop and young adults TOLDX tests. Material and methods: The sample consisted of 179 participants who are cognitively normal  and range in age from 18 to 49 years. Tables are provided to convert raw scores to scaled scores.Scores adjusted for sociodemographic factors were obtained by applying linear regression  techniques. Results: No effects were found for age and sex in either test. Educational level impacted most of the Stroop test variables and some of the TOLDX scores (Total Moves score and Total Initiation Time score). Conclusions: The norms obtained will be extremely useful in the clinical evaluation of young Spanish adults (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quintana, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casals Coll, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Benavides, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tamayo, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aranciva, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manero, R. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palomo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rognoni, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña Casanova, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El Stroop Color-Word Interference Test (Stroop) se utiliza para explorar la flexibilidad mental, la atención selectiva, la inhibición cognitiva y la velocidad de procesamiento de la información. El test Tower of London-Drexel University version (TOLDX) es útil para explorar la habilidad para resolver problemas y la planificación. Objetivo: En el presente estudio, como parte de los estudios normativos españoles del proyecto NEURONORMA jóvenes, se presentan datos normativos para el Stroop y la TOLDX. Material y métodos: La muestra está formada por 179 participantes, cognitivamente normales, de entre 18 y 49 años de edad. Se aportan tablas para convertir las puntuaciones brutas en escalares. Se aplican regresiones lineales para calcular los ajustes por factores sociodemográficos. Resultados: Se observó un efecto nulo de la edad y el género en ambas pruebas. La escolaridad influyó en la mayoría de variables del Stroop y en algunas medidas de la TOLDX (movimientos totales y tiempo de latencia). Conclusiones: Los datos normativos obtenidos son de gran utilidad clínica para la evaluación de población adulta joven española (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;28(2): 73-80, mar. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110229</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudios normativos españoles en población adulta joven (proyecto NEURONORMA jóvenes): normas para las pruebas Stroop Color-Word Interference Test y Tower of London-Drexel University</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54366^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4592</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11775</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
