<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75218</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7113</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Measurement of Nicotine, Cotinine and Caffeine by GC-NPD-MS in human breast milk simples of puerperals hospitalizad in 'Las Higueras', Talcahuano, Chile</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Human milk used as an alternative matrix for toxicological analysis offers relevant information to evaluate the neonatal risk of exposition to a variety of chemical substances. Nicotine, its metabolite, cotinine, and caffeine, have the necessaries physicochemical properties to be transferred to the human breast milk. We measured nicotine, cotinine and caffeine concentrations in human milk samples of 48 puerperals mothers (M=28 years old) elected randomly. The samples were collected in sterile containers by manual expression, and then transported to the lab where they were kept at -30ºC until the analysis. The mothers, with signed consent, filled a questioner with socio demographic data smoking habit, and intake of caffeine beverages during pregnancy. The simultaneous determination of nicotine, cotinine and caffeine in human milk samples was made by Gas Chromatography/Mass Spectrometry, with a double detection system. The methodology was 2exact, precise and lineal, with a determination coefficient (r ) greater than 0,9990 for nicotine and cotinine, and 0,9970 for caffeine. We found nicotine in 19% of the samples (14,7 to 55, 2 ng/mL), cotinine in 4% (10,5 to 136,8 ng/mL) and caffeine in 25% (9 to 250 ng/mL). The application of the analytical method allowed the determination of nicotine and cotinine as biomarkers of the smoking behaviour during lactogenesis, and gave us the possibility to determine the presence of Pethidine (n=1), Methronidazole (n=1), Methamizole (n=19) and Aminophenazone (n=19) in the human milk samples analyzed, that led us to visualize this methodology as an important tool to expand future toxicological studies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aquino, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lobos, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrios, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La utilización de la lecha materna como matriz biológica alternativa para el análisis toxicológico, proporciona información relevante al momento de evaluar el riesgo de exposición al neonato a diversas sustancias químicas. La nicotina, su metabolito, cotinina y la cafeína, poseen propiedades físicoquímicas que facilitan el paso de las mismas hacia la leche materna. Se determinaron las concentraciones de nicotina, cotinina y cafeína en leche materna de 48 madres puérperas (M=28 años) elegidas a través de un muestreo al azar simple. Las muestras se recolectaron en envases estériles por extracción manual. Se obtuvo consentimiento informado y se completó un cuestionario con los datos demográficos de la madre del neonato, el hábito de fumar e ingesta de bebidas cafeinazas durante el embarazo. La determinación simultánea de nicotina, cotinina y cafeína se realizó por Cromatografía de Gases/Espectometría de Masas con doble sistema de detección. La metodología demostró ser exacta, precisa y lineal en el rango estudiado con un coeficiente de determinación (r2) mayor a 0,9990 para nicotina y cotinina, y mayor a 0,9970 para la cafeína. Se encontró nicotina en el 19% de los casos (14,7 a 55,2ng/mL), cotinina en el 4% (10,5 y 13,8 ng/mL) y cafeína en el 25% 9 a 250 ng/mL). La cotinina son biomarcadores que indican que las madres fumaron durante la lactogénesis. También, el espectrómetro de masas detectó la presencia de Petidina (n=1), Metronizadol (n=1), Metamizol (n=19) y Aminofenazona (n=19) en las muestras de leche materna evaluadas lo que permite visualizar a esta metodología como una valiosa herramienta para ampliar el espectro de futuros estudios toxicológicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. toxicol;23(2/3): 108-112, 2006. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75218</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Determinación de nicotina, cotinina y cafeína por CG-NPD-EM en leche materna de puérperas atendidas en el hospital 'Las Higueras', Talcahuano, Chile</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9723^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2143^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2898^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3382^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9082^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2898^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
