<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93363</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Physiopathology of acute renal failure during sepsis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Acute renal failure (ARF) is an independent risk factor associated with increased mortality during sepsis. Recent consensus definitions have allowed the standardization of researchon the subject. The understanding of the physiopathology of ARF during sepsis is limited by the scarcity of histological studies and the inability to measure renal microcirculatory flows. Historically, ARF during sepsis has been considered to be a consequence of diminished renal bloodflow (RBF). Indeed, in early stages of sepsis or in sepsis associated to cardiogenic shock, RBF may decrease. However, recent studies have shown that in resuscitated sepsis, in which cardiacout put is characteristically normal or even elevated and there is systemic vasodilatation, RBF is normal or even increased, with no associated histological evidence of significant tubularnecrosis. Thus, other factors may participate in the genesis of ARF in sepsis. These includeapoptosis, glomerular and medullary microcirculatory disorders, cell changes in response to thepro-inflammatory cascade characteristic of sepsis, oxidative stress, mitochondrial dysfunction and damage induced by mechanical ventilation, among others. Sepsis associated ARF treatmentis supportive. In general, renal replacement therapies can be grouped as intermittent or continuous, and as those whose primary objective is the replacement of impaired renal function,versus those whose main objective is to secure hemodynamic stability through the clearing ofpro-inflammatory mediators (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Andresen, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mercado, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Downey, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Regueira, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La insuficiencia renal aguda (IRA) es un factor de riesgo independiente asociado a mayor mortalidad durante la sepsis. Definiciones de con senso recientes han permitido estandarizarlos trabajos de investigación en el tema. La comprensión de la fisiopatología de la IRA durante la sepsis está limitada por la escasez de estudios histológicos y por la imposibilidad de medir los flujos microcirculatorios renales. Históricamente se ha considerado a la IRA séptica como una patología dependiente de la caída del flujo sanguíneo renal (FSR). Efectivamente, en las etapas precoces de la sepsis o en la sepsis acompañada de shock cardiogénico existe compromiso del FSR; sin embargo, estudios recientes han demostrado que en la sepsis reanimada, aquella en que característicamente se observa un gasto cardiaco normal o alto y vasodilatación sistémica, el FSR es normal o incluso aumentado y no existe evidencia histológica significativa denecrosis tubular. Otros factores, distintos al puramente hemodinámico, participan en la génesis de la IRA en la sepsis. Entre éstos están la apoptosis celular, los trastornos microcirculatorios glomerulares y medulares, los cambios celulares en respuestas a la cascada proinflamatoria propia de la sepsis, el estrés oxidativo, la disfunción mitocondrial y el daño a distancia inducido por ventilación mecánica, entre otros. En la actualidad, el tratamiento de la IRA en la sepsis es de soporte. En general, las terapias de reemplazo renal pueden ser clasificadas como intermitentes o continuas, y en las que buscan primariamente el reemplazo de la función renal deteriorada, frente a aquellas cuyo objetivo principal es lograr la estabilidad hemodinámica de los pacientes mediante la remoción de mediadores proinflamatorios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);35(7): 424-432, oct. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93363</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fisiopatología de la insuficiencia renal aguda durante la sepsis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13148^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31085^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6590</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
