<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152182</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8799</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness of eccentric exercise in patellar tendinopathy. Literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Chronic patellar tendinopathy is described as the appearance of pain, inflammation and a loss of function of the patellar tendon. It is a pathology that develops through overuse in sports that involve racing, repetitive trauma and jumps. Objectives: Demonstrate the effectiveness of eccentric exercises on patellar tendinopathy, analysing some of the physiological changes that occur to the tendon and attempt to establish a protocol of specific exercises. Materials and methods: A literary search was performed of the Cochrane, ScienceDirect, Pubmed and PEDro databases. 10 articles were found that compared eccentric exercises with shockwaves, concentric exercises, a night-worn splint and stretches, grading improvements in pain, function and the quality of life of the patients. Results: The eccentric exercises were effective in treating patellar tendinopathy in comparison with other therapies such as shockwaves, stretches, night-worn splints, etc. In some of these articles evidence emerged regarding the effectiveness of eccentric exercises, in others the possibility was left open for continued research into the existence of a combination of various therapies, perhaps being the most effective and quick way of recovering from this injury. Conclusion: Eccentric exercises are effective in treating patellar tendinopathy; however, no evidence has shown that they are better than other currently applied treatments. On the other hand, no specific protocol for applying these exercises has been established (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Díaz, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La tendinopatía crónica rotuliana se describe por la aparición de dolor, inflamación y pérdida de la función del tendón rotuliano. Es una patología desarrollada por el uso excesivo en deportes que implican carreras, traumatismos repetitivos y saltos. Objetivos: Evidenciar la eficacia de los ejercicios excéntricos en las tendinopatías rotulianas, analizar algunos de los cambios fisiológicos que se dan en el tendón e intentar determinar un protocolo de ejercicios concreto. Materiales y métodos: Se ha realizado una búsqueda bibliográfica en las bases de datos Cochrane, ScienceDirect, Pubmed, PEDro. Se han encontrado 10 artículos donde se han comparado los ejercicios excéntricos con ondas de choque, ejercicios concéntricos, férula de noche y estiramientos, valorándose la mejora del dolor, la función y la calidad de vida de los pacientes. Resultados: Los ejercicios excéntricos han sido efectivos en el tratamiento de la tendinopatía rotuliana, en comparación con otras terapias como las ondas de choque, estiramientos, férulas de noche, etc. En algunos de éstos artículos se evidencia la eficacia de los ejercicios excéntricos, en otros deja abierta la posibilidad de seguir investigando en la existencia de combinación de varias terapias, pudiendo ser más efectiva y rápida la rehabilitación de esta lesión. Conclusión: Los ejercicios excéntricos son efectivos en la tendinopatía rotuliana, sin embargo no se ha demostrado que sean superiores a otros tratamientos aplicados actualmente. Por otro lado, no se ha podido determinar un protocolo concreto de aplicación de estos ejercicios  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. med. deporte;33(171): 59-66, ene.-feb. 2016. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152182</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia de los ejercicios excéntricos en tendinopatías rotulianas. Revisión bibliográfica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28214</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31206^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24852^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24852^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31206^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24852^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31206^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
