<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146966</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intraluminal pyloric duplication cyst associated with congenital diaphragmatic hernia. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The extraluminal pyloric duplication represents the least common location of all the digestive tract duplications. However, intraluminal pyloric duplication has been exceptionally reported as an extremely rare congenital anomaly in newborns and pediatric patients. We report the first case of intraluminal pyloric duplication associated with congenital diaphragmatic hernia. We present a 29 days old boy with suspected pyloric syndrome due to mechanical obstruction associated with congenital diaphragmatic hernia. The diagnosis of intraluminal pyloric duplication cyst was confirmed by intraoperative findings and subsequent histological examination. Intraluminal pyloric duplication is a rare disease causing intrinsic mechanical obstruction of the pyloric channel. It should be taken into account in the differential diagnosis of neonatal pyloric obstruction síndrome (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carli, CF  de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Veloce, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La duplicación pilórica extraluminal representa la localización menos frecuente de todas las duplicaciones del tubo digestivo; sin embargo, la duplicación pilórica intraluminal (DPI) se ha documentado de manera excepcional como una anomalía congénita de extrema rareza en recién nacidos y pacientes pediátricos. Nosotros aportamos el primer caso de DPI asociada a hernia diafragmática congénita. Presentamos el caso clínico de un niño de 29 días de vida con sospecha de síndrome pilórico debido a una obstrucción mecánica asociada a hernia diafragmática congénita. El diagnóstico de quiste de DPI fue confirmado por los hallazgos intraoperatorios y un posterior examen histológico. La duplicación pilórica intraluminal es una malformación o anomalía (mejor que enfermedad) rara, causante de la obstrucción mecánica del canal pilórico, y debería tenerse en cuenta en el diagnóstico diferencial del síndrome de obstrucción pilórica neonatal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;73(11): e319-e322, dic. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146966</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Duplicación quística intraluminal de píloro asociada a hernia diafragmática congénita. Presentación de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5024^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5024^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12143^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5024^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37754^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12143^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12143^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12143^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5024^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6708^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6708^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37754^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
