<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100313</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Uterine artery blood flow in patients with primary dysmenorrhea</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To identify the parameters of blood flow in the uterine arteries in women with primary dysmenorrhea. Methods. We selected women attending the Nuestra Señora de Chiquinquirá and Central Dr. Urquinaona hospitals in Maracaibo, Venezuela. There were 40 women with primary dysmenorrhea (group A) and 40 women without dysmenorrhea (group B). Blood flow in the uterine arteries, women's general characteristics, Doppler blood flow parameters in the uterine arteries and symptom severity were evaluated. Results. The mean age was 28.3 ± 5.8 years in group A and 26.4 ± 5.0 years in group B (P=ns). Doppler ultrasound evaluation was performed on the second day of menstruation in all women in both groups. The pulsatility index, resistance index and systolic / diastolic ratio of the uterine arteries in women with a diagnosis of primary dysmenorrhea were significantly higher than in controls (P&lt;.05). The uterine artery resistance index showed a moderate, positive and significant correlation with pain intensity (r=0.570; P&lt;.05). Conclusion. Women with dysmenorrhea showed alterations in uterine artery blood flow compared with women without dysmenorrhea (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mejia-Montilla, Jorly</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez-Ríos, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oberto-Leal, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyna-Villasmil, Nadia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyna-Villasmil, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Identificar los parámetros de flujo sanguíneo de las arterias uterinas en mujeres con dismenorrea primaria. Material y métodos. Se seleccionó a mujeres que asistieron a los hospitales Nuestra Señora de Chiquinquirá y Central Dr. Urquinaona, Maracaibo, Venezuela. Se seleccionó a 40 mujeres con dismenorrea primaria (grupo A) y 40 mujeres sin dismenorrea (grupo B). Se evaluó el flujo sanguíneo de las arterias uterinas, características generales, parámetros de flujo Doppler de las arterias uterinas y severidad de los síntomas. Resultados. Las mujeres del grupo A tenían una edad promedio de 28,3 ± 5,8 años y las mujeres del grupo B tenían una edad promedio de 26,4 ± 5,0 años (p=NS). La evaluación ecográfica Doppler se realizó en el segundo día de la menstruación en todas las mujeres de ambos grupos. El índice de pulsatilidad, el índice de resistencia y relación sistólica/diastólica de las arterias uterinas en las mujeres con diagnóstico de dismenorrea primaria fue significativamente mas alto comparado con los controles (p&lt;0,05). El índice de resistencia de la arteria uterina presentó una correlación moderada, positiva y significativa con la intensidad del dolor (r=0,570; p&lt;0,05). Conclusión. Las mujeres con dismenorrea primaria presentan alteraciones del flujo sanguíneo de las arterias uterinas al compararlo con mujeres sin dismenorrea (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);55(6): 259-263, jun. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100313</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Flujo sanguíneo de las arterias uterinas en mujeres con dismenorrea primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15000^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4475^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4475^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4475^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4475^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8768^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8767^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8768^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8768^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4475^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2624^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2624^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1164^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15000^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
