<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-64723</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Implementation of surveillance culture programs and molecular typing are important contributions of Clinical Microbiology to the control of nosocomial infections. This document provides information on collection, transport, preservation, and processing of samples for surveillance culture, as well as the criteria for interpreting and reporting the results of relevant etiologic agents in nosocomial infection. This includes methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA), glycopeptide-resistant Enterococcus spp., enterobacteria producing extended-spectrum b -lactamases (ESBLs), multiresistant Acinetobacter baumannii and carbapenem-resistant Pseudomonas aeruginosa. Details on the available methods for rapid diagnosis are also presented. The information in this document attempts to provide a general approach to the problem and may be considered a starting point for laboratories that are developing their own guidelines, according to needs defined by the multidisciplinary nosocomial infection control team (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramírez de Arellano, Encarnación</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez, M. Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Martínez, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Eliecer Cano, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padilla, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ezpeleta, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los cultivos de vigilancia epidemiológica y la tipificación molecular han sido importantes aportaciones de la Microbiología Clínica al control de la infección nosocomial. En este documento se ofrece información sobre recogida, transporte, conservación y procesamiento de muestras para cultivos de vigilancia, criterios para la interpretación de los resultados y la emisión de los mismos en relación con las bacterias de mayor interés en infección nosocomial. Se incluyen Staphylococcus aureus resistente a meticilina (SARM), Enterococcus spp. resistentes a glucopéptidos, enterobacterias productoras de betalactamasas de espectro extendido (BLEE), Acinetobacter baumannii multirresistente y Pseudomonas aeruginosa resistente a carbapenems. Esta información pretende aportar una aproximación general al problema, a partir de la cual el laboratorio desarrolle directrices propias, en función de las necesidades acordadas con el equipo multidisciplinar de control de infección nosocomial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;26(4): 220-229, abr. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-64723</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36585^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13431^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23258^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22164</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13596^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7946^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24244^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36323</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11988^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
