<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138262</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">SPECT and PET in neurology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Both single photon emmission computed tomography (SPECT) and positron emission tomography (PET) are helpful in the practice of neurology. Ictal SPECT is useful to determine the origin of focal seizures in the pre-surgical evaluation. In some centers, it is used to predict the likelihood of massive cerebral swelling after strole and of cerebral infarction after a subarachnoid hemorrhage. It has also been used to study dopaminergic function in parkinsonian syndromes and in the evaluation of dementia. Given its higher resolution and some other factors, PET is more useful in the evaluation of brain tumors, dementia and the parkinsonian syndromes. It is also useful in the presurgical evaluation of epilepsy (AU) </dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arbizu, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toledo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Masdeu, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Tanto la tomografía computarizada por emisión de fotón único (SPECT) como la tomografía por emisión de positrones (PET) tienen aplicaciones clínicas en neurología. La SPECT se utiliza sobre todo para localizar el foco epileptógeno como preparación para la cirugía de la epilepsia. En algunos centros se utiliza para determinar el riesgo de efecto de inflamación masiva cerebral después de un infarto y para detectar el riesgo de infarto después de una hemorragia subaracnoidea. También se ha utilizado para evaluar la vía dopaminérgica en pacientes parkinsonianos y para la evaluación de demencias atípicas. Para estas últimas aplicaciones y para la evaluación de tumores cerebrales, la mayor resolución y otras propiedades de la PET la hacen una técnica más idónea (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;21(5): 219-225, jun. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138262</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">SPECT y PET en neurología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9654</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1958^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1958^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3971</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1953^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9262^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24895</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9262^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38793</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1953^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1953^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
