<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142050</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Strenghts and weaknesses of peer review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The peer review paradigm in our system of professional self-regulation is a complementary evaluation procedure &#150; and as imperfect as &#150; bibliometrics. The application of peer review depends on the journal's aims and circumstances and its results should always be contextualized, especially given the current cult of considering the journal of publication more important than the article's content and message. Participation in the peer review processes is usually altruistic and requires that certain rules of courtesy and good practice be followed, one of the main problems being conflicts of interest. Peer review processes are expensive and show scant reproducibility. The system is highly subjective, conservative, and prone to bias and is generally unable to detect fraud. However, effective alternatives are lacking. Consequently, peer review procedures should be examined in greater depth and its application in optimal conditions &#150; and based on the scarce evidence available &#150; should be encouraged (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Camí, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El peer review, paradigma de nuestro sistema de autorregulación profesional, es un procedimiento de evaluación complementario y tan imperfecto como la bibliometría. Su aplicación depende de los objetivos y circunstancias y sus resultados deben contextualizarse siempre, aún más ante el culto actual que considera más importante la revista de publicación que el contenido y mensaje del propio trabajo. La participación en procesos de peer review es generalmente altruista y requiere seguir unas normas de cortesía y buenas prácticas, siendo los conflictos de intereses uno de sus principales problemas. Los procesos de peer review son caros y escasamente reproducibles. El sistema es muy subjetivo, conservador, propenso al sesgo y generalmente incapaz de detectar el fraude. Sin embargo no existen buenas alternativas, por lo que es necesario profundizar en sus procedimientos y propiciar su aplicación en las mejores condiciones posibles y sobre la base de las escasas evidencias existentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);131(supl.5): 20-24, dic. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142050</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fortalezas y limitaciones del peer review</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12078^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31204^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
