<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100573</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Posterolateral approach in trimalleolar ankle fractures: surgical technique</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Ankle fractures involving a posterior malleolar fragment are associated with worse clinical outcomes. The standard indication for its fixation is a displaced fragment that involves more than 25% of the distal articular tibia. The method of reduction and fixation of these fractures has not received much attention. The purpose of this paper is to describe the surgical technique and clinical results. Material and methods. Over a 6 year period 10 patients with an ankle fracture involving more than 25% posterior malleolus were admitted for surgery, which was performed by the first author. Postoperative management and complications were recorded, reduction accuracy evaluated in the first postoperative radiograph, and functional outcomes were measured using the American Orthopaedic Foot and Ankle Society (AOFAS) hind foot-ankle score and the modified Weber protocol. The surgical technique is described. Results. A total of 10 patients were included in the study; and the overall mean age was 53.8 (range: 19-82) years. With regard to complications, none of the 10 patients had any postoperative complication. No cases of reflex sympathetic dystrophy syndrome, superficial infection, iatrogenic lesion of the sural nerve or failure of internal fixation were recorded. One of them had screw and plate removal surgery. Clinical results were good; 9 patients regained their pre-injury activity level, with excellent or good results in both AOFAS and modified Weber protocol. Discussion. Given that posterior malleolus fractures are usually posterolateral, this approach allows perfect visualization of the fracture, articular anatomical reduction, and strong fixation. Clinical results obtained were at least equal to other case series published (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valle Cruz, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mingo-Robinet, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abril Larrainzar, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las fracturas de tobillo que incluyen un fragmento posterior se asocian a un peor resultado clínico. Es comúnmente aceptada la indicación de reducción y síntesis del maléolo posterior cuando incluye más de un 25% de la línea articular en proyección lateral. El método de fijación de estas fracturas tiene poca repercusión en la literatura. El objetivo de este trabajo, es describir la técnica quirúrgica y los resultados clínicos obtenidos. Material y métodos. Durante un período de 6 años, 10 pacientes han sido intervenidos por el primer autor. Todos ellos presentaban fracturas que incluían un fragmento posterior mayor de un 25%. Se tomaron datos de la clasificación de la fractura, del manejo postoperatorio, calidad de la reducción postoperatoria en la radiología postoperatoria, así como de cualquier complicación postoperatoria. Todos los pacientes completaron 2 cuestionarios de valoración clínica: American Orthopaedic Foot and Ankle Society (AOFAS) y Weber modificado. Se describe en detalle el abordaje posterolateral del maleolo posterior. Resultados. Diez pacientes con edades comprendidas entre 19 y 82 años fueron tratados con esta técnica. Todas las fracturas se redujeron anatómicamente. Los resultados son buenos, 9 pacientes obtuvieron un resultado excelente o bueno en las escalas de AOFAS y Weber modificada. No hubo pérdidas de reducción, infección, síndrome de distrofia simpático refleja o lesión iatrogénica del nervio sural. Una paciente precisó de la retirada del material de osteosíntesis por molestias de este. Todas las fracturas consolidaron. Discusión. Dado que la fractura del maléolo posterior es casi siempre posterolateral, el abordaje descrito permite una excelente visualización de la fractura, lo que permite su reducción anatómica y síntesis con tornillos posteroanteriores. Los resultados obtenidos son al menos equivalentes a otras series clínicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);56(4): 313-318, jul.-ago. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100573</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El abordaje posterolateral en las fracturas trimaleolares de tobillo. Técnica quirúrgica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13878^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13878^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30263^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
