<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167446</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Syphilitic posterior placoid chorioretinitis as initial presentation of early neurosyphilis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report: A 36 year-old male with a recent HIV diagnosis, presented with loss of vision of his left eye. Ophthalmoscopy revealed a unilateral yellowish placoid lesion in the macula. After fluorescein angiography, optical coherence tomography, optical coherence tomography angiography, syphilis serology, and cerebrospinal fluid results, he was diagnosed with neurosyphilis and syphilitic posterior placoid chorioretinitis. Discussion: Acute syphilitic posterior placoid chorioretinitis is a rare ocular manifestation of syphilis. All patients with characteristic clinical and angiographic findings of acute syphilitic posterior placoid chorioretinitis should be tested for a neurosyphilis and human immunodeficiency virus co-infection. Early treatment with intravenous penicillin is usually effective with good visual results (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Medina-Tapia, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Contreras-Díaz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Vicente, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rueda-Rueda, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina-Sócola, FE</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Herrero, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Varón de 36 años con diagnóstico reciente de VIH con pérdida de visión de ojo izquierdo. En fundoscopia se observó placa amarillenta en mácula. Tras angiografía con fluoresceína, tomografía de coherencia óptica, angiotomografía de coherencia óptica, pruebas serológicas y examen de LCR se llegó al diagnóstico de neurosífilis y coriorretinitis placoide posterior sifilítica. Discusión: La coriorretinitis placoide posterior es una manifestación clínica poco frecuente de sífilis ocular. En todos los pacientes con coriorretinitis placoide posterior sifilítica debe descartarse la posibilidad de neurosífilis y coinfección con el VIH. El tratamiento temprano con penicilina intravenosa suele ser efectivo, con un buen resultado visual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;92(10): 490-494, oct. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167446</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Coriorretinitis placoide posterior sifilítica como presentación inicial de neurosífilis temprana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9683^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15187^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28268^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24320^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
