<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102509</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidemiology of recurrent miscarriage</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine the possible causes of recurrent miscarriage in our environment and the pregnancy rate in these couples. Material and methods. An observational retrospective study was carried out in 172 women who attended our unit for two or more recurrent miscarriages between 2002 and 2008. Results. A total of 80.2% of the women became pregnant. Of these, 81.2% carried the fetus to term. The results of clinical study were normal in 70.9%. The alterations found were uterine in 48%, genetic in 2% and coagulation alterations in 44%. These alterations were associated in 6% of the patients. Conclusions. Most of the couples consulting for recurrent miscarriage will not receive an etiologic diagnosis after clinical study. Reproductive prognosis worsens as the number of miscarriages increases. However, up to 80.2% of these women become pregnant again, of whom 81.1% will deliver a healthy neonate (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fontes Jimenez, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Guadix, Bárbara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Navarro, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Paredes, Aida</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer las posibles causas de aborto de repetición en nuestro medio y la tasa de embarazo en estas parejas. Material y métodos. Estudio observacional retrospectivo de 172 mujeres que consultaron en nuestra Unidad durante los años 2002 a 2008 por dos o más abortos de repetición. Resultados. El 80,2% de las mujeres quedaron gestantes, 81,2% de ellos a término. El estudio de abortabilidad fue normal en el 70,9%. Las alteraciones halladas fueron: uterinas 48%, genéticas 2% y alteraciones de la coagulación 44%, apareciendo asociadas en el 6% de las pacientes. Conclusiones. La mayoría de las parejas que consultan por abortos de repetición se van a quedar sin un diagnóstico etiológico tras el estudio de abortabilidad. El pronóstico reproductivo empeora conforme aumenta el número de abortos a la consulta. Sin embargo hasta el 80,2% vuelven a quedar gestantes, llegando a tener un hijo sano en casa el 81,1% de las embarazadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);55(7): 312-320, ago.-sept. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102509</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Epidemiología del aborto de repetición</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32643^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28258^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33361^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20210^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
