<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044098</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anxiety during the weaning process. Study of a case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">María is a 26-year-old woman with Down syndrome, morbid obesity and a history of heart abnormalities, was admitted to an intensive care unit due to atypical pneumonia. At evaluation, she was sedated and connected to a ventilator. We present the continuation of a case previously reported in Enfermería Clínica. The clinical course and nursing care planning of new problems presented by María during the process of ventilator weaning until discharge from the intensive care unit (ICU) are described. The nursing diagnoses formulated during this process were: anxiety which was resolved 3 days after implementing a nursing care plan and providing assistance in the need to avoid danger, caused by agitation on reducing sedation. After the patient was satisfactorily weaned from the ventilator, the care recommended on discharge from the ICU included in the continuity of care report was planned</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miró-Bonet, Margalida</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miró-Bonet, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego-Caminero, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alorda-Terrassa, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">María es una mujer de 26 años, con síndrome de Down, obesidad mórbida y antecedentes de problemas cardíacos, ingresada en una unidad de cuidados intensivos (UCI) a causa de una neumonía atípica, y en el momento de la valoración estaba sedada y conectada a un ventilador. Este artículo presenta la continuación de un caso clínico publicado con anterioridad en Enfermería Clínica, en el que se describe la evolución clínica y la planificación de los cuidados enfermeros de los nuevos problemas que presentó María durante el proceso de destete del ventilador hasta que fue dada de alta de la UCI. Los diagnósticos enfermeros presentados durante este proceso fueron: ansiedad, que se solucionó a los 3 días de la implementación del plan de cuidados, y suplencia parcial en la necesidad de evitar peligros, causada por la agitación al disminuir la sedación farmacológica. Después de afrontar el proceso de destete satisfactoriamente, se planificaron los cuidados recomendados al alta en la UCI incluidos en el informe de continuidad de cuidados</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);16(2): 99-102, mar. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044098</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ansiedad durante el proceso de destete. Estudio de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23855^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
