<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134394</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Somatotype tendency in Chilean adolescents from Valparaíso: review from 1979 to 2011</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: A good tool to determine the biotype of growing and developing subjects that has been observed is the somatotype (ST). Objetive: This research study aims to describe the ST tendency in Chilean adolescents along the years. Methods: The bibliographic review was carried out using data from Medline, ISI Web of Knowledge, and SciELO. The key words used for the search were: somatotype, somatotyping, adolescent (in English and Spanish). The selected articles must describe ST in Chilean adolescents between 15 and 18 years of age. The graphic representation was made through a somatochart and the series ST. To analyze the trajectory of the ST, the moving average method was used (SM), and the tendency line (lineal; TL), which expresses the data direction and projection. Results: Eight articles complied with the inclusion criteria. Samples of students between 1979 and 2011 from the Regions of Valparaíso, Araucanía, and the Metropolitan region of Chile were reported. All studies correspond to transversal samples. The authors cite and/or describe the Heath-Carter anthropometric methods to assess the ST. The results showed positive TL for the endomorph component in all ages and genders. The mesomorph component maintained in male, unlike the female&#146;s component, which was negative except for the one at 18 years old. SM trajectory describes a regularity of the mesomorphic endomorph profile in female, yet with an increase in the endomorphy. In male, a change was observed from an ectomorphic mesomorph to endomorphic mesomorph. Conclusions: This progressive rise of the adipose component in both genders increases the risk of suffering non-communicable diseases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Berral, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivares, Rossy</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lizana, Pablo A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Se ha observado que el somatotipo (ST) antropométrico es un buen método para determinar el biotipo de sujetos en crecimiento y desarrollo. Objetivo: Describir la tendencia del ST en adolescentes chilenos a lo largo de los años. Métodos: La búsqueda bibliográfica se realizó en bases de datos Medline, ISI Web of Knowlegde y SciELO. Las palabras claves utilizadas para la búsqueda fueron: somatotipo, adolescente (tanto en inglés como español). Los artículos seleccionados debían describir el ST en adolescentes chilenos de 15 a 18 años de edad. Para la representación gráfica se utilizó la somatocarta y el ST de series, para el análisis de la trayectoria del ST se ocupó el mé- todo de medias móviles (SM) y líneas de tendencia (TL). Resultados: Los artículos que cumplieron con los criterios de inclusión fueron ocho. Las muestras de estudiantes se describen desde los años 1979 hasta el 2011, en las regiones de Valparaíso, Araucanía y Metropolitana. Todos los estudios corresponden a estudios transversales. Los autores citan y/o describen el método antropométrico de Healh-Carter para evaluar el ST. Se registraron TL positivas para el componente endomorfo en todas las edades y géneros, el componente mesomorfo se mantuvo en hombres, no así en mujeres que fue negativo a excepción de los 18 años. La trayectoria SM describe una persistencia del perfil meso-endomorfo en mujeres, pero con aumento de la endomorfía. En hombres se observó el cambio de un perfil ecto-mesomorfo hacia uno meso-endomorfo. Conclusiones: Este aumento progresivo del componente endomórfico en ambos géneros incrementa el riesgo de padecer enfermedades crónicas no trasmisibles  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(3): 1034-1043, mar. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134394</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tendencia del somatotipo en adolescentes chilenos de Valparaíso: revisión de 1979 al 2011</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13391^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
