<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166528</identifier>
<setSpec>1577-0354</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness of a program of physical activity in people with serious mental disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this paper the effectiveness of a physical activity and sport program is analyzed in a group of 28 people with Severe Mental Illness (SMI). An assessment was made before the start of the program and again after four months, measuring anthropometric variables, physical functional ability, balance and coordination, and social functioning and activities of daily life. The results showed statistically significant improvements in those who attended more than 50% of the sessions in all anthropometric variables, and functional fitness and motor skills, as well as the Personal and Social Performance Scale (PSP). Moreover, assistance to the program was high, keeping the same 80% of people who started it. The relevance of the results and the need to implement such interventions in the SMI is discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valenzuela, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Pardo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar-Parra, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mullor, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cangas, AJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateu, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente estudio se analiza el impacto que ha tenido un Programa de actividad física y deporte en un grupo de 28 personas con Trastorno Mental Grave (TMG). Se realizó una evaluación antes del comienzo del Programa y otra a los cuatro meses, tomando medidas antropométricas, de capacidad física funcional, equilibrio y coordinación, así como del funcionamiento social y las actividades de la vida cotidiana. Los resultados mostraron mejorías estadísticamente significativas en aquellas personas que asistieron a más del 50% de las sesiones en todas las variables antropométricas, y de condición física funcional y cualidades motrices, así como en la Escala de Funcionamiento Personal y Social (PSP).Por otro lado, la asistencia al programa fue alta, manteniéndose en el mismo el 80% de las personas que lo iniciaron. Se discute la relevancia de los resultados y la necesidad de implantar este tipo de intervenciones en el TMG (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. int. med. cienc. act. fis. deporte;17(67): 507-521, sept. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166528</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad de un programa de actividad física en personas con trastorno mental grave</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d16836^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56106^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56106^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16735</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16836^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
