<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81725</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Malignant fibrous histiocytoma of the bladder. A literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: Malignant fibrous histiocytoma (MFH) is an uncommon urinary tract tumor. This paper is intended to provide an update on its diagnostic criteria, pathological and immunohistochemical characteristics, histological classification, prognostic factors, and alternative treatments. Materials and methods: All published articles on MFH of the urinary bladder have been reviewed and a descriptive study has been done. Results: Twenty-nine cases of MFH of the bladder have been reported. The most common morphological variants are storiform-fascicular (41%) and inflammatory (36%) MFH. Non-myxoid variants have a poorer prognosis. Stage T3 MFH was found in 72% of cases at the time of diagnosis. MFH local recurrence and distant metastasis rates were 50% and 25% respectively after surgical treatment only. Conclusions: MFH of the bladder is a tumor with high local and distant recurrence rates and a low survival rate, and therefore requires early and aggressive treatment. Radical cystectomy with lymphadenectomy and adjuvant radiotherapy is considered to be the treatment of choice, eventually associated to chemotherapy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miralles-Aguado, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bosquet-Sanz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego-Vilar, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodrigo-Aliaga, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego-Gómez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Povo-Martín, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gimeno-Argente, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: El histiocitoma fibroso maligno (HFM) es un tumor poco frecuente del tracto urinario. Pretendemos actualizar los criterios diagnósticos, las características anatomopatológicas e inmunohistoquímicas, la clasificación histológica, los factores pronóstico y las alternativas terapéuticas. Material y métodos: Revisión bibliográfica y estudio descriptivo de los casos de HFM de vejiga publicados en la literatura médica internacional. Resultados: Existen 29 casos publicados de HFM de vejiga y las variantes morfológicas más frecuentes son la estoriforme-fascicular (41%) y la inflamatoria (36%). Las variantes no mixoides comportan peor pronóstico. El 72% fue T3 en el momento del diagnóstico. La tasa de recurrencia local y a distancia del HFM de vejiga fue del 50 y del 25%, respectivamente, tras tratamiento exclusivamente quirúrgico. Conclusiones: El HFM de vejiga es un tumor con alta tasa de recurrencia local y a distancia, así como baja supervivencia, requiriendo un tratamiento precoz y agresivo. La cistectomía radical con linfadenectomía y radioterapia adyuvante, con eventual quimioterapia, se considera el tratamiento de elección (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;34(4): 378-385, abr. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81725</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Histiocitoma fibroso maligno de vejiga. Revisión bibliográfica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32281</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31407^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
