<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-64186</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: Erectile dysfunction (ED) is a disorder with a high prevalence that increases with age. It is estimated that 18.9% of men&#146;s between 25 and 70 years suffer it in Spain. Most cases have a multifactorial origin and it is admitted the influence on its pathogenesis of systemic diseases, different kind of drugs, psychogenic factors, cardiovascular, endocrinological and neurological diseases. Neurologic cause erectile dysfunction may have its origin in the central or peripheral nervous system. Among possible process of neurogenic erectile dysfunction of central origin would be tumors, cerebral vascular accidents, encephalitis, Parkinson disease, multiple sclerosis and other demyelinization diseases, dementias, olivopontocerebellar degeneration and epilepsy. Myelopathies of any etiology may be, depending on their localization and extension, cause of erectile dysfunction. At the peripheral level, disorders of the sensitive tracts constituting the afferent limb of the erection spinal reflex, and the efferent vegetative or somatic tracts mediating arterial vasodilatation, cavernous smooth muscle relaxation or pelvic floor striated muscle contraction. The aim of this work is to review in detail the most relevant causes of neurogenic erectile dysfunction, their etiopathogenic mechanisms and therapeutic approaches currently considered more adequate for each particular case. Conclusions: The correct diagnostic approach to patients with erectile dysfunction passes through identification, if possible, of the etiopathogenic factors implied. Regarding this, detection and identification of a possible neurogenic risk factor will contribute to a better understanding of the physiopathology mechanisms, and more adequate diagnostic, prognostic and therapeutic approaches, mainly in those patients refractory to first line therapy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valles Antuña, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández González, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escaf, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Gómez, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: La disfunción eréctil (DE) es una alteración cuya prevalencia es elevada y aumenta con la edad. Se estima que en España afecta al 18,9% de los varones de 25 a 70 años. En la mayor parte de los casos es de origen multifactorial y en su patogenia se admite la influencia de enfermedades sistémicas, fármacos de diferentes tipos, factores psicógenos, patologías cardiovasculares, endocrinopatías y alteraciones neurológicas. La disfunción eréctil de causa neurológica puede tener su origen a nivel del Sistema Nervioso Central o Periférico. Entre las posibles causas de disfunción eréctil neurógena de origen central estarían tumores, accidentes cerebrovasculares, encefalitis, Enfermedad de Parkinson, Esclerosis Múltiple y otras enfermedades desmielinizantes, demencias, degeneración olivo pontocerebelosa y epilepsia. Las mielopatías de cualquier etiología, pueden ser dependiendo de su localización o extensión, causas de disfunción eréctil. A nivel periférico pueden ser causa de DE las alteraciones de las vías sensitivas que constituyen el brazo aferente del reflejo espinal de la erección y las de las vías eferentes vegetativas o somáticas que median en la vasodilatación arterial, la relajación del músculo liso cavernoso o la contracción de la musculatura estriada del suelo de la pelvis. La finalidad de este trabajo es revisar detalladamente las causas más relevantes de DE de origen neurógeno, sus mecanismos etiopatogénicos y los abordajes terapéuticos que en la actualidad se consideran más adecuados para cada caso particular. Conclusión: La correcta aproximación diagnóstica al paciente con DE pasa por identificar, en la medida de lo posible, los factores etiopatogénicos implicados su origen. En este sentido, la detección e identificación, de la posible presencia del factor de riesgo neurógeno, contribuirá a un mejor entendimiento de sus mecanismos fisiopatológicos y con ello a una aproximación diagnóstica, pronóstica y terapéutica más adecuada especialmente en aquellos pacientes refractarios a la terapia de primera línea (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;61(3): 403-411, abr. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-64186</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11553^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4736^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11553^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
