<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039588</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Extraintestinal manifestations in inflammatory bowel disease: differences between Crohn's disease and ulcerative colitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: The true prevalence of the extraintestinal manifestations (EM) associated with inflamatory bowel disease (IBD) may vary depending on the geographic area, IBD population, location and duration of the disease, medication and diagnostic accuracy. The aim of this study was determine the prevalence of the major EM of IBD and their differences between Crohn's disease (CD) and ulcerative colitis (UC). Patients and method: A prospective study with a total of 566 patients (295 CD with median follow up 11.6 years [range: 2-32 years] and 271 UC with median follow up 10.4 years [range: 2-36 years]. Data related to the clinical course, EM and laboratory tests were obtained at diagnosis and during follow-up. Results: EM related with IBD appeared al least once in 46.6% of the patients. Joints manifestations were the most common EM. The EM were equal frequent in UC (51.5%) as in CD (42.2%). Hepatobiliary manifestations (odds ratio [OR] = 1.91; 95% confidence interval [CI] 1.15-3.16; p = 0.007), venous thromboembolism (OR = 4.26; 95% CI, 1.3-15.4; p = 0.006) and arthralgias (OR = 1.59; 95% CI, 1.01-2.5; p = 0.035) were more frequent in UC than CD. Erythema nodosum (OR = 2.35; 95% CI, 1.13-5.0; p = 0.013) and peripheral arthritis (OR = 1.95; 95% CI, 1.02-3.74; p = 0.029) were more frequent in CD. The prevalences of ocular, and the rest of joint manifestations were not different according to UC or CD. Conclusions: Prevalence of EM in Spanish IBD patients is among the highest ever reported. The distribution of the EM observed is different between CD and UC. It is necessary to know to allow to prompt diagnosis and prevent undesirable complications</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lana, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Rubio, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendoza, Juan Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alba, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Taxonera, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: La prevalencia de las manifestaciones extraintestinales (MEI) en la enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal (EII) varía en función de las áreas geográficas, el tipo de EII, la localización, la duración de la enfermedad y el tratamiento y la rapidez en el diagnóstico. El objetivo de este trabajo ha sido determinar la prevalencia de las principales MEI en la EII y las diferencias existentes entre la enfermedad de Crohn (EC) y la colitis ulcerosa (CU). Pacientes y método: Estudio prospectivo en el que se incluyó a 566 pacientes con EII (295 con EC y seguimiento medio de 11,6 años [extremos: 2-32 años] y 271 con CU y seguimiento medio de 10,4 años [extremos: 2-36 años]. Los datos referidos a las MEI y tests de laboratorio se obtuvieron en el momento del diagnóstico y durante las visitas posteriores. Resultados: La aparición de al menos una MEI se observó en el 46,6% de los pacientes. Las MEI fueron frecuentes tanto en la CU (51,5%) como en la EC (42,2%). Las manifestaciones hepatobiliares (odds ratio [OR] = 1,91; intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 1,15-3,16), la enfermedad tromboembólica venosa (OR = 4,26; IC del 95%, 1,3-15,4) y las artralgias (OR = 1,59; IC del 95%, 1,01-2,5) fueron más frecuentes en la CU que en la EC. El eritema nodoso (OR = 2,35; IC del 95%, 1,13-5,0) y las artritis periféricas (OR = 1,95; IC del 95%, 1,02-3,74) fueron más frecuentes en la EC. La prevalencia de las manifestaciones oculares y del resto de manifestaciones articulares no difirió entre la CU y la EC. Conclusiones: La prevalencia de las MEI en los pacientes con EII españoles es una de las más altas publicadas. La frecuencia del tipo de MEI es diferente entre los pacientes con EC y CU, un aspecto que es importante conocer para realizar un diagnóstico adecuado de la EII y de sus complicaciones</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);125(8): 297-300, sept. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039588</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manifestaciones extraintestinales en la enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal: diferencias entre la enfermedad de Crohn y la colitis ulcerosa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14308^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8281^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23971^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32350^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
