<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166874</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ablation of atrial fibrillation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The lack of safe and effective antiarrhythmic drugs has led to the development of catheter ablation as an alternative means of treating atrial fibrillation. The correct use of this technique depends on accurately identifying and representing left atrial anatomy, differentiating tissue areas that maintain the arrhythmia from those that are passively activated, and defining clinically meaningful objectives. This review article describes and discusses recent advances in integrating images into navigation systems, electrogram patterns associated with tissue areas that maintain atrial fibrillation, and the latest endpoints proposed for use in the procedure (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arenal, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La ausencia de fármacos antiarrítmicos eficaces y seguros ha conducido al desarrollo de la ablación con catéter como terapia alternativa en el tratamiento de la fibrilación auricular. La adecuada aplicación de esta técnica requiere la identificación y representación fidedigna de la anatomía de la aurícula izquierda, la diferenciación de las zonas que mantienen la arritmia de las zonas que se activan pasivamente y la definición de unos objetivos de relevancia clínica. Esta revisión comenta y presenta las contribuciones más recientes en la integración de imágenes en los sistemas de navegación, las características de los electrogramas relacionados con zonas que mantienen la fibrilación auricular y los últimos objetivos que se han propuesto en este procedimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);10(supl.A): 48a-52a, 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166874</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ablación de la fibrilación auricular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32337^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35390^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30797^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4634^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
