<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148453</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Obstructive uropathy due to uterine prolapse</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Although the association between pelvic organ prolapse and obstructive uropathy is well known, it occasionally causes severe acute or chronic renal failure. A 79-year-old woman presented to the emergency department complaining of gastrointestinal and neurological symptoms. Physical examination showed a grade IV uterine prolapse. Additional assessments revealed bilateral hydronephrosis grades III/IV, urinary sepsis and acute renal failure. The diagnosis and reduction of uterine prolapse by a Hodge pessary played a key role in resolving the symptoms caused by obstructive uropathy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Padilla Iserte, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rey Otero, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hidalgo Mora, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arrufat Nebot, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Varea, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La asociación entre prolapso de órganos pélvicos y uropatía obstructiva es conocida, pero en raras ocasiones alcanza el grado de provocar secundariamente un cuadro de insuficiencia renal aguda o crónica graves. Se presenta el caso de una mujer de 79 años que consultó en urgencias por sintomatología secundaria a insuficiencia renal aguda. A la exploración se evidenció prolapso uterino grado IV. Las pruebas complementarias revelaron ureterohidronefrosis bilateral grados III/IV, sepsis urinaria e insuficiencia renal aguda. El diagnóstico y la reducción del prolapso uterino mediante un pesario de Hodge facilitó la resolución del cuadro clínico originado por la uropatía obstructiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);43(1): 35-37, ene.-mar. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148453</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uropatía obstructiva secundaria a prolapso uterino</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29576^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53982^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7022^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
