<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77140</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-6045</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Narrative review of the role of the squatting in neuromuscular conditioning and rehabilitation programs</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Squatting is a widely-used exercise in strengthening and rehabilitation programs. Its application is based on the mechanical similarities it has with sports actions and daily activities. Nevertheless, it is an exercise that has been involved in discussion. This systematic review has aimed to investigate the application of squatting in programs for healthy neuromuscular conditioning. An electronic search was conducted in the principal databases. The search strategy was focused on efficiency and safety criteria of the exercise along with methodological considerations for its application. Seventy-seven articles were found for their inclusion in the present work. It can be concluded that squatting is a functional exercise that is appropriate for use in programs of healthy strengthening of the lower limbs. Due to its technical complexity, some criteria of technical progression must be established in order to reduce inadequate patterns of execution (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Chulvi Medrano, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La sentadilla es un ejercicio ampliamente utilizado en los programas de entrenamiento y rehabilitación. Su aplicación está fundamentada en las similitudes mecánicas que posee con las acciones deportivas y de la vida cotidiana. Sin embargo, se trata de un ejercicio que ha estado envuelto de discusión. El objetivo de esta revisión narrativa fue investigar la aplicación de la sentadilla en los programas de acondicionamiento neuromuscular saludable. Se realizó una búsqueda electrónica en las principales bases de datos. La estrategia de búsqueda se centró en criterios de eficacia y seguridad del ejercicio junto a consideraciones metodológicas para su aplicación. Fueron encontrados 77 artículos para la inclusión del presente trabajo. Puede concluirse que la sentadilla es un ejercicio funcional adecuado para los programas de fortalecimiento saludable de los miembros inferiores. Debido a su complejidad técnica deberían establecerse unos criterios de progresión técnica para reducir patrones de ejecución inadecuados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. iberoam. fisioter. kinesiol. (Ed. impr.);12(1): 35-45, jun. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77140</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión narrativa del rol de la sentadilla en los programas de acondicionamiento neuromuscular y rehabilitación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7892</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52426</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2114</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22981</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12467</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38802</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
