<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037306</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hierarchical structure of authors collaboration. An analysis of papers on imaging diagnosis published by hospital Radiology departments in Comunidad Valenciana (1994-2001)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Analyze the different contribution of hierarchical categories in the papers published by radiologists of hospitals belonging to Comunidad Valenciana along the period 1994-2001, as well as their distribution in the different journals.                 Material and methods. For the recovery of the papers sample we have designed specific search profiles for EMI and Medline databases. Hierarchical category of the authors was identified through personal interviews.                 Results. We have analyzed 417 works, with 1,321 authors distributed in the following form: chief of service, 8.8%; chief of section, 12.4%; assistant physician, 50.7%, and resident, 28%. Hierarchical groupings with participation of residents were more consistent for publishing papers along all the study period (1994-2001). Higher percentage of papers (21%) corresponded to «residents + adjunct physicians» grouping. Radiología was the most productive journal (42% papers). All results were statistically significant (p &lt; 0.0001).                 Conclusion. Radiodiagnosis residents of Comunidad Valenciana hospitals showed an active participation in research papers published along the period 1994-2001, in collaboration with the rest of the hierarchical categories, basically with the assistant physician. Assistant physicians contributed most of papers. Chief of section and chief of department contributed fifth of papers</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aleixandre, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanfeliu, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valderrama, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí-Bonmatí, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguel-Dasit, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Analizar la distinta contribución de las categorías jerárquicas en los artículos publicados por radiólogos de hospitales pertenecientes a la Comunidad Valenciana en el período 1994-2001, así como su distribución en las revistas.                 Material y método. Para la recuperación de la muestra de artículos hemos diseñado perfiles de búsqueda específicos para las bases de datos IME y Medline. Se identificó la categoría jerárquica de los autores mediante entrevistas personales.                 Resultados. Hemos analizado 417 trabajos, con 1.321 firmas distribuidas de la siguiente forma: jefe de servicio: 8,8%; jefe de sección: 12,4%; adjunto: 50,7%, y residente: 28%. Las agrupaciones jerárquicas con participación de residentes fueron las que firmaron de manera más estable trabajos en todas las anualidades (1994-2001). El mayor porcentaje de firmas (21%) correspondió a la agrupación «residentes + adjuntos». Radiología fue la revista más productiva (42% de los trabajos). Todos los resultados fueron estadísticamente significativos (p &lt; 0,0001).                 Conclusión. Los residentes en radiodiagnóstico de los hospitales de la Comunidad Valenciana mostraron una participación activa en los artículos de investigación publicados en el período 1994-2001, en colaboración con el resto de las categorías jerárquicas, más frecuentemente con adjuntos. La figura del adjunto aportó el mayor número de firmas. El jefe de sección y el jefe de servicio suponen, conjuntamente, la quinta parte de las firmas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;205(6): 265-273, jun. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037306</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estructura jerárquica de la colaboración entre autores. Análisis de los artículos sobre diagnóstico por la imagen publicados por los servicios hospitalarios de Radiología de la Comunidad Valenciana (1994-2001)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3320</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22878</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28904</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
