<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103145</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality of life in workers in the environmental areas</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To describe the quality of life related to health in a working population in the context of the environmental health. Methodology: A descriptive and transverse analysis was carried out within a sample of 401 workers in the environmental area of Granada. A survey was needed to collect information regarding sociodemographic, lifestyle and medical variables, together with the COOP-WONCA. Results: The average mark in COOP-WONCA was 14,34 (DT: 3,39). There were no relevant differences in the average obtained related to the sociodemographic, lifestyle and medical variables, but they were statistically meaningful as far as the following variables are concerned: place of living (p=0,030), to have a common disease (p=0,017); to practice some sport (p=0,041); professional category (p&lt;0,001); number of meals per day (p=0,041); BMI (p=0,002), triglycerides level (p=0,022). Conclusions: Perceptions of the quality of life related to health in a population to investigate was satisfactory. A meaningful tendency could be observed in some factors that may be regarded as protectors for a better perception of the quality of life: to live in an urban area, not suffering from any pathology or common disease, to practice some sport or have a hobby, to have a good professional qualification and to have the appropriate weight (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Merino Torres, Marta Amalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino Torres, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hueso Montoro, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calero Martín de Villodres, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balanza Galindo, Serafín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pleguezuelos Navarro, Helena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo de este trabajo es describir la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud de una población de trabajadores en el contexto de la salud medioambiental. Material y Métodos: Estudio descriptivo transversal sobre una muestra de 401 trabajadores del área medioambiental de la provincia de Granada. Se aplicó un cuestionario con variables sociodemográficas, clínicas y de estilos de vida, junto con las láminas de Medición del Estado Funcional COOP-WONCA. Resultados: La puntuación media obtenida en COOP-WONCA fue de 14,34 (DT: 3,39). Las diferencias en las puntuaciones medias obtenidas en COOP-WONCA en relación a las variables sociodemográficas, clínicas y de estilos de vida no son relevantes, pero sí estadísticamente significativas en las siguientes variables: Lugar de Residencia (p=0,030); Tener una enfermedad común (p=0,017); Practicar algún deporte (p=0,041); Categoría profesional (p&lt;0,001); Número de comidas al día (p=0,041), IMC (p=0,002); Nivel de Triglicéridos (p=0,022). Conclusiones: La percepción de la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud en la población de estudio es buena. Se observa una tendencia significativa en algunos factores que podemos considerar como protectores para una mejor percepción de la calidad de vida: residir en el ámbito urbano, no sufrir patología o enfermedad común, practicar algún deporte o afición, tener mayor cualificación profesional y estar en normopeso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;58(226): 35-48, ene.-mar. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103145</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida relacionada con la salud en trabajadores del área medioambiental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28446^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9971^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
