<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041810</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7709</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Archibald project: development of an innovative children footwear which increases the stability in the first steps</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The main objective pursued with the work hereshown was to develop a new shoe type for toddlersbased on gait stability as a new innovative concept.A deep study was carried on children's gait takinginto account both fit influence and the introducedeffect when changing the characteristics of thedifferent footwear components. Many essays wheredeveloped, on both biomechanics and on anthropometrics,in two countries: Spain and Netherlands.These essays allowed developing prototypes whichwere assessed to obtain new results. As main result,new innovative children footwear was developedbased on the last design criteria and Shoe designcriteria already obtained.In the project there have participated four Spanishmanufacturers (Azorín Shoes S.L., Miró Borrás S.A.,Tecnihorma S.L. y Automática &amp; Control NuméricoS.L.), two Dutch manufacturers (Piedro Footwear yVeltman BV) and one from the Check Republic (Fare)and four Research and Development Centers, twofrom Spain (Instituto de Biomecánica de Valencia -IBV, Instituto Español del Calzado y Conexas -INESCOP) and two from The Netherlands (Institutode Tecnología Industrial - TNO, Grupo de DesarrolloPerceptual y Motor de la Facultad de MovimientosHumanos de la Universidad de Vrije)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González García, Juan C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nácher, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olaso, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ovejero, Tomás</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo principal de este trabajo fue el desarrollode un nuevo tipo de calzado para niños que comienzana caminar basado en la estabilidad de lamarcha como nuevo concepto innovador. Se llevó acabo un exhaustivo estudio de la marcha infantilconsiderando la influencia del ajuste y las característicasde los diferentes elementos de diseño. Sedesarrollaron diversos ensayos biomecánicos y serealizó un amplio estudio antropométrico en dospaíses: España y Holanda. Como resultado principalse desarrolló un nuevo calzado infantil innovadorbasado en los criterios de diseño de hormas ycomponentes obtenidos.El proyecto ha contado con la participación de cuatroempresas españolas (Azorín Shoes S.L., MiróBorrás S.A., Tecnihorma S.L. y Automática &amp; ControlNumérico S.L.), dos holandesas (PiedroFootwear y Veltman BV) y una de la República Checa(Fare), y con cuatro Centros de Investigación, dosespañoles (Instituto de Biomecánica de Valencia -IBV, Instituto Español del Calzado y Conexas -INESCOP) y dos holandeses (Instituto de TecnologíaIndustrial - TNO, Grupo de DesarrolloPerceptual y Motor de la Facultad de MovimientosHumanos de la Universidad de Vrije)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Peu;25(1): 10-18, ene. 2005. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041810</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Proyecto Archibald: desarrollo de un calzado infantil innovador que aumenta la estabilidad en los primeros pasos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1721^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13153^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5823^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6278^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
