<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162637</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Is training carried out the same as competition? Analysis of load in women´s basketball</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It is necessary to analyze the impact that the competition have on athletes, in an objective and scientific way. The knowledge of the physiological and kinematic demands in sports competition is one of the factor that will establish optimal training processes. Therefore, the main objectives of this research were to characterize and analyze the differences between training and real competition in a women's senior basketball team during 2015/16 season. The design of this research is empirical with quantitative methodology, which focuses on analyzing the relationships and differences between variables. The independent variable was the Game Situation, categorized in Small Sided Games, Full Game and Competition. Five dependent variables were recorded: Impacts, Steps and Jumps per minute (kinematic variables); and Average and Maximum Heart Rate (internal load). A descriptive analysis was performed and the univariate general linear model was used to differentiate between categories of the variable Game Situation. Finally, Bonferroni Post Hoc test was used to identify differences between groups. The results showed that higher values of Average and Maximum Heart Rate and Steps per minute were found in competition. Coaches should consider these results to adapt the training to the requirements of the competition (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Reina Román, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mancha Triguero, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Feu Molina, Sebastián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez Godoy, Sergio José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El impacto que genera la competición en los deportistas es necesario analizarlo de forma objetiva y científica. El conocimiento de las demandas fisiológicas y cinemáticas de la competición deportiva, es uno de los factores que permitirá establecer óptimos procesos de entrenamiento. Por ello, los principales objetivos de esta investigación fueron caracterizar y analizar las diferencias entre el entrenamiento y la competición real en un equipo senior femenino de baloncesto, durante la temporada 2015/16. El diseño de esta investigación es empírico con metodología cuantitativa, que se centra en analizar las relaciones y diferencias entre variables. La variable independiente fue la Situación de Juego, categorizada en Small Sided Games, Full Game y Competición. Se registraron cinco variables dependientes: Impactos, Pasos y Saltos por minuto (cinemáticas); y Frecuencia Cardíaca Media y Máxima (de carga interna). Se llevó a cabo un análisis descriptivo y se utilizó el modelo general lineal univariante para establecer diferencias entre las categorías de la variable Situación de Juego. Por último, la prueba Post Hoc de Bonferroni se empleó para identificar las diferencias entre grupos. Los resultados mostraron que se obtienen valores más altos en la competición que las situaciones de entrenamiento en el caso de la Frecuencia Cardiaca Media y Máxima, y en el caso de los pasos por minuto. Los entrenadores deben tener en cuenta estos resultados para adecuar el entrenamiento a los requerimientos de la competición (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;26(supl.1): 9-13, 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162637</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Se entrena como se compite? Análisis de la carga en baloncesto femenino</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6493^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1721^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
