<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166003</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-9895</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the origin of neoplasms in patients with malignant pleural effusion (MPE) as the initial manifestation of tumor disease. Material and methods: This is a retrospective, multicenter study. It was developed at 11 public hospitals in the Community of Madrid, and included all consecutive patients with MPE and no history of previously detected neoplasm between April 1, 2008 and April 1, 2013. Results: We studied 402 patients with MPE. We obtained a cytohistological diagnosis of the primary tumor in 339 of them (84%). Lung cancer was the most frequent origin of the MPE in both men (59%) and in women (46%), while adenocarcinoma was the most frequent histological type. Primary pleural tumors were the second most frequent (20%), 92% of which were mesotheliomas. Third were both hematological cancers and ovarian tumors (5,5%). Breast cancer, along with gastrointestinal, renal and urological tumors, were very rare (&lt;2%). It was not possible to determine the origin of the neoplasm in 39 patients (9,7%). Other distant metastases were found in 187 patients (47%). Conclusion: The lungs are the organs that most frequently produce MPE as the initial manifestation of neoplastic disease, which is followed in frequency by pleural neoplasms. Therefore, in the absence of other symptoms, clinicians should aim their initial efforts at ruling out one of these organs as the tumor origin. Our study shows that the clinical suspicion and focus should be changed when diagnosing women, because MPE is uncommon as the first manifestation of breast cancer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mahíllo-Fernández, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Abad, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villena-Garrido, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abad-Santamaría, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Rojo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santiago-Delgado, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calero-Pardo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Melchor-Íñiguez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ali-García, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Steen, Bárbara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales-Chacón, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Padilla, DE</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Granda-Orive, JI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Warnisher, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Río-Ramírez, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo-Patrón, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Verdugo-Cartas, MI</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer el origen de la neoplasia en los pacientes con derrame pleural maligno (DPM) como primera manifestación de enfermedad tumoral. Diseño: Estudio retrospectivo y multicéntrico, desarrollado en 11 hospitales públicos de la Comunidad de Madrid, en el que se incluyeron todos los pacientes consecutivos con DPM, sin antecedentes de neoplasia conocida entre el 1 de abril de 2008 y el 1 de abril de 2013. Resultados: El diagnóstico del tumor primario se realizó mediante muestras citohistológicas en 339 pacientes (84%). El cáncer de pulmón destacó como el origen más frecuente del DPM tanto en hombres (59%) como en mujeres (46%), siendo el adenocarcinoma la estirpe histológica más frecuente. Los tumores pleurales primarios ocuparon el segundo lugar en frecuencia (20%), de los que el 92% fueron mesoteliomas. En tercer lugar se situaron en igual proporción (5,5%), las neoplasias hematológicas y los tumores ováricos. El cáncer mamario, junto con los tumores digestivos, renales y urológicos fueron muy infrecuentes (&lt;2%). En 39 pacientes (9,7%) no fue posible determinar el origen neoplásico. Se hallaron otras metástasis a distancia en 187 pacientes (47%). Conclusión: El pulmón es el órgano que con mayor frecuencia produce DPM como primera manifestación de enfermedad neoplásica, seguido por las neoplasias pleurales. En ausencia de otros síntomas, el clínico debe dirigir sus esfuerzos iniciales a descartar uno de estos órganos como el origen tumoral. En mujeres, nuestro estudio obliga a cambiar la sospecha y enfoque clínico, ya que en esta situación el carcinoma mamario es muy infrecuente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. patol. respir;20(2): 41-46, abr.-jun. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166003</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Derrame pleural maligno como debut de neoplasia no conocida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19257^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29084^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11426^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
