<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106631</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Urban Air Pollutants are Significant Risk Factors for Asthma and Pneumonia in Children: The Influence of Location on the Measurement of Pollutants</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Air pollution is associated with a substantial burden on human health; however, the most important pollutants may vary with location. Proper monitoring is necessary to determine the effect of these pollutants on respiratory health. Objectives: This study was designed to evaluate the role of outdoor, indoor and personal exposure to combustion-related pollutants NO2 and O3 on respiratory health of children in a non-affluent urban area of São Paulo, Brazil. Methods: Levels of NO2 and O3 were continuously measured in outdoor and indoor air, as well as personal exposure, for 30 days using passive measurement monitors. Respiratory health was assessed with a Brazilian version of the ISAAC questionnaire. Results: Complete data were available from 64 children, aged 6-10 years. Respiratory morbidity was high, with 43 (67.2%) reporting having had wheezing at any time, 27 (42.2%) wheezing in the last month,  17 (26.6%) asthma at any time and 21 (32.8%) pneumonia at any time. Correlations between levels of NO2 and O3 measured in the three locations evaluated were poor. Levels of NO2 in indoor air and personal exposure to O3 were independently associated with asthma (both cases P=0.02), pneumonia (O3, P=0.02) and wheezing at any time (both cases P&lt;0.01). No associations were seen between outdoor NO2 and O3 and respiratory health. Conclusions: Exposure to higher levels of NO2 and O3 was associated with increased risk for asthma and pneumonia in children. Nonetheless, the place where the pollutants are measured influences the results. The measurements taken in indoor and personal exposure were the most accurate(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tetelbom Stein, Renato</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lemos, Miriam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elisabete Vieira, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Archanjo Ferraro, Alexandre</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva Cosme Pedro, Sibelli</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saldiva, Paulo Hilario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodrigues da Silva, Emerson</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Duzolina Pastro, Luciana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sly, Peter David</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Conclusiones: La exposición a niveles más elevados de NO2 y O3 se asoció a un aumento del riesgo de asma y neumonía en los niños; sin embargo, el lugar en el que se determinan los contaminantes influye en los resultados. Las determinaciones realizadas en el interior y las determinaciones personales fueron las más exactas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;48(11): 389-395, nov. 2012. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106631</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los contaminantes atmosféricos urbanos son factores de riesgo significativos para el asma y la neumonía en niños: influencia del lugar de medición de los contaminantes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d396^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4865^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1963^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12560^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4867^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4867^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201211</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
