<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053378</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perianal streptococcal dermatitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Perianal streptococcal dermatitis is a superficial skin infection of the perianal region, almost exclusively reported in children, that is caused by group A beta-hemolytic streptococci. Symptoms include perianal itching and rectal pain, secondary constipation and blood-streaked stools. There is usually a well demarcated, bright red perianal rash. The disease is often misdiagnosed and is sometimes treated inappropriately. We report the cases of a 4-year-old and a 2-year-old patient who presented the typical manifestations of the disease</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Perezagua, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcalá-Minagorre, P. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Bautista, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La dermatitis perianal estreptocócica es una infección cutánea superficial del área perianal, descrita casi exclusivamente en niños, causada por el estreptococo betahemolítico del grupo A. Los síntomas incluyen prurito anal y dolor rectal, estreñimiento secundario y deposiciones con hebras de sangre. Existe a menudo una erupción perianal bien delimitada y brillante. La enfermedad resulta con frecuencia infradiagnosticada, y en ocasiones se trata inadecuadamente. Se exponen los casos de 2 niños, de 2 y 4 años, con la forma típica de presentación de la enfermedad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;65(3): 142-143, mar. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053378</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dermatitis perianal estreptocócica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1009^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29953^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13677^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d673^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3892^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13684^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
