<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72823</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Approach to orofacial disabilities in students with motor discapacities and special education need following a transdisciplinary intervention model. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Orofacial disabilities and chewing and swallowing disorders make up a very important section of the integral treatment of a student with disability in a special education school. The different aspects that need to be considered and evaluated when working in this area are varied and of a different nature. This study aims to make known the evaluation and treatment methods of the orofacial dysfunctions made by a transdisciplinary work team in the Special Needs Education School Santísimo Cristo de la Misericordia of Murcia arising from a specific case of a student with unknown cause encephalopathy. In addition, the results obtained with this work methodology and after a period of time corresponding to a school year are analyzed in order to make known the positive aspects we observe in both the student and professionals when this therapeutic intervention model is used(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montero Mendoza, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tapia Moncalvillo, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campoy González, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diz Fariña, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Henarejos, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las disfunciones orofaciales y los trastornos de la masticación y deglución constituyen un apartado de gran relevancia dentro del tratamiento integral de un alumno con discapacidad en un centro de educación especial. Los diferentes aspectos pot valorar y tener en cuenta cuando se trabaja esta área son diversos y de diferente índole. El objetivo de este trabajo es dar a conocer, a propósito de un caso particular de un alumno con encefalopatía no filiada, los métodos de valoración y tratamiento de las disfunciones orofaciales que lleva a cabo un equipo de trabajo transdisciplinario en el Colegio de Educación Especial Santísimo Cristo de la Misericordia de Murcia. Además, se analizan los resultados obtenidos con esta metodología de trabajo y tras un período de tiempo que se corresponde con un curso escolar completo con el fin de divulgar los aspectos positivos que observamos tanto en el alumno como en los profesionales al aplicar este modelo de intervención terapéutica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);31(4): 163-173, jul.-ago. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72823</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abordaje de las disfunciones orofaciales en alumnos con discapacidad motora y necesidades educativas especiales, siguiendo un modelo de intervención transdisciplinario. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30935^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33528^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1951^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23977^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9262^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19504^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
