<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124176</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Otorhinolaryngological manifestations in patients with Behçet disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: Behçet disease (BD) is a systemic immune-mediated vasculitis of unknown origin characterised by recurrent orogenital ulceration, ocular inflammation and skin lesions. The aim of our study was to identify ear, nose and throat (ENT) manifestations associated with BD. Patients and methods: Retrospective review of the medical records of all patients diagnosed with BD who attended a tertiary public hospital in Cantabria (Spain) over a period of 22 years. Clinical manifestations, in particular those concerning ENT, were retrieved from medical records. A medical literature review of ENT manifestations was conducted. Results: Thirty-three patients (age range: 17-64 years) were included in the study. Most of them presented oral ulcers (97%). Eight patients (24%) presented oropharyngeal ulcers and 5 patients (15%) experienced audiovestibular symptoms (high frequency sensorineural hearing loss, vertigo and bilateral vestibular hypofunction). One patient had symptoms compatible with vestibular neuronitis as the presentation manifestation of Neuro-Behçet. In 4 patients (12%) the presence of odynophagia secondary to the presence of oropharyngeal lesions, initially interpreted as acute or recurrent tonsillitis, was the first manifestation of the disease, alone or associated with cutaneous or ocular lesions. Conclusions: In addition to the characteristic oral ulcers present in most patients with BD, ulcers in the oropharynx, occasionally interpreted as acute pharyngitis, are also common in these patients. Audiovestibular manifestations frequently appear during the course of the disease and may be the first symptom of central nervous system involvement (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Acle, Leticia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Obeso-Agüera, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales-Angulo, Carmelo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vergara Pastrana, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Gay, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: La enfermedad de Behçet (EB) es una vasculitis sistémica autoinmune de origen desconocido caracterizada por la aparición de úlceras orogenitales recurrentes, inflamación ocular y lesiones dérmicas. El objetivo de nuestro estudio fue identificar las manifestaciones otorrinolaringológicas asociadas a la EB. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio retrospectivo descriptivo de las manifestaciones otorrinolaringológicas de los pacientes diagnosticados de EB en un hospital terciario público en Cantabria (España) durante 22 años. Se realizó una revisión de la bibliografía de la enfermedad otorrinolaringológica asociada a la EB. Resultados: Treinta y tres pacientes con edades comprendidas entre 17 y 64 años fueron incluidos en nuestro estudio. La mayor parte de los mismos presentaba úlceras orales (97%). Ocho pacientes (24%) presentaron úlceras orofaríngeas. Cinco pacientes (15%) presentaron síntomas audiovestibulares (hipoacusia neurosensorial para altas frecuencias, síndrome vertiginoso e hipofunción vestibular bilateral). Un paciente sufrió un cuadro compatible clínicamente con una neuronitis vestibular como inicio de Neuro-Behçet. En 4 pacientes (12%) la presencia de odinofagia secundaria a la presencia de úlceras orofaríngeas, inicialmente interpretadas como amigdalitis aguda o de repetición, fue la primera manifestación de la enfermedad, sola o asociada a lesiones cutáneas u oculares. Conclusiones: Además de las características úlceras orales, presentes en casi todos los pacientes con EB, son frecuentes la aparición de úlceras en la orofaringe, ocasionalmente interpretadas como faringitis aguda. No son raras las manifestaciones clínicas audiovestibulares durante la evolución de la enfermedad, pudiendo constituir el primer síntoma de una afectación del sistema nervioso central (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;65(1): 15-21, ene.-feb. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124176</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manifestaciones otorrinolaringológicas en pacientes con enfermedad de Behçet</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6470^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28255^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10216^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27888^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24776^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
