<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83070</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adolescents, risk situations and road safety</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveDescribe the risk behaviour relationships with road safety in adolescents.DesignCross-sectional descriptive study.SettingMadrid and Andalusia Regions, representative samples.ParticipantsThe sample included 3,612 in secondary school pupils from Madrid (n=1708) and Andalusia (n=1904). The survey was carried out during May and June 2007.Main measurementsThe data collected included sociodemographic areas (age, sex, grade, father's profession, birth place, etc.) and risk situation and behaviour (risk behaviour as driver or passenger).Results16.2% of the adolescents have been involved in a dangerous situation with motorcycles during the last year. 16.7% never use a helmet when riding a motorcycle and 62% do not wear one when riding a bicycle on the road; 17.4% frequently ride a motorcycle over the speed limit and 24.5% when driving a car. There are significant differences regarding sex, grade and region (Madrid or Andalusia). There are four factors which explain 62% of the variance: drug factor, speed factor, security factor and passenger factor. Two of these have twice the probability of having a dangerous situation when riding a motorcycle: drug factor (OR=1.96; 95% CI, 1.77&#150;2.18) and the speed factor ((OR=2.13; 95% CI, 1.92&#150;2.36).ConclusionsAdolescents in higher grades and living in Andalusia were less road safety conscious. This pattern should be taken into account when designing preventive actions in Road Safety Education(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romo Avilés, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meneses Falcón, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil García, Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoDescribir los comportamientos de riesgo relacionados con la seguridad vial en los adolescentes.DiseñoEstudio descriptivo, transversal.EmplazamientoComunidades de Madrid y Andalucía.ParticipantesTres mil seiscientos doce estudiantes de los 4 cursos de ESO en Madrid (n=1.708) y en Andalucía (n=1.904).Mediciones principalesEncuesta realizada durante mayo-junio de 2007. Se recogieron datos sociodemográficos (edad, sexo, curso, profesión del padre, lugar de nacimiento, etc.) y sobre comportamientos y situaciones de riesgo (conductas de riesgo de inseguridad vial como conductor o pasajero).ResultadosEl 16,2% de los adolescentes ha vivido una situación de peligro en la moto en el último año. El 16,7% nunca se pone el casco cuando monta en moto y el 62% no lo hace en bicicleta por la carretera; el 17,4% ha ido en moto muchas veces a más velocidad de la permitida y el 24,5% cuando viajaba en coche. El sexo, el curso y la comunidad autónoma muestran asociaciones significativas. Cuatro factores, que explican el 62% de la variancia, agrupan las situaciones o las conductas de riesgo en los adolescentes: drogas, velocidad, seguridad y pasajero. Dos de ellos han tenido 2 veces más probabilidades de producir situaciones de peligro en la moto en el último año: drogas (OR=1,96; IC del 95%: 1,77&#150;2,18) y velocidad (OR=2,13; IC del 95%: 1,92&#150;2,36).ConclusionesLos chicos de cursos avanzados y los residentes en Andalucía mostraron más conductas de inseguridad vial. Este perfil debe tenerse presente al diseñar medidas preventivas en la educación vial(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;42(9): 452-458, sept. 2010. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83070</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adolescentes, situaciones de riesgo y seguridad vial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d297</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19251^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13018^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31061^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
