<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158140</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-5967</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Alineated attachments (Moral Narrative Disorder)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Since (Bowlby, 1958) noticed about linkage disorders, categories of attachment have been expanding (insecure, controlling, unattached) as the age of the children observed increased. Nevertheless, attachment is still limited to the maturational processes which are present during early childhood. Attachment theory as key theory to understand evolutionary development should be able to incorporate maturational processes of second childhood as the moral development. Development of a moral narrative is necessary to explain a subjective and complex reality. If the moral narrative is not constructed in a satisfactory way, disorders that give rise to a new category of attachments, alienated attachments, occur. This new category of attachments (subdivided into belligerent, dejected and invaded) makes visible characteristics typical of second childhood and enables a theoretical continuum starting from early infancy to adulthood (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Muga García, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde que se advirtieran los trastornos de la vinculación (Bowlby, 1958) las categorías de apego se han ido ampliando según aumentaba la edad de los menores observados. Sin embargo, el apego se sigue limitado a los procesos madurativos que concurren durante la primera infancia. El apego como teoría clave para comprender el desarrollo evolutivo debería incorporar procesos madurativos relevantes de la segunda infancia como es el desarrollo moral. La construcción de un relato moral es necesaria para explicar una realidad subjetiva y compleja. Si el relato moral no se construye de manera satisfactoria se produce un trastorno del mismo que da lugar a una nueva categoría de apegos, los apegos alienados. Esta nueva categoría de apegos (subdivididos en beligerantes, abatidos e invadidos) da visibilidad a las características propias de la segunda infancia y posibilita un continuo teórico desde los primeros meses de vida hasta la edad adulta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psiquiatr. psicoter. niño adolesc;(60): 111-114, jul.-dic. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158140</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Apegos alineados (Trastorno del Relato Moral)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37615</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9954</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55715^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
