<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121103</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reporte de un caso leiomyosarcoma of the lateral border of the tongue: report of a case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Leiomyosarcoma is an uncommon malignancy that is most commonly located in the gastrointestinal tract and female genitourinary tract. Its head and neck presentation mainly in the oral cavity is very rare. The following is a description of a clinical case of an unusual presentation of primary leiomyosarcoma of the lateral border of the tongue, bringing one more case to the isolated reports of these lesions of the head and neck as described in the literature (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Colunga, Rodolfo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toranzo Fernández, José Martín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Valdez, Laura Gabriela</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El leiomiosarcoma es una neoplasia maligna poco común que se localiza con más frecuencia en el tracto gastrointestinal y genitourinario femenino; su presentación en cabeza y cuello principalmente en la cavidad oral es muy rara. A continuación se realiza la descripción de un caso clínico de una presentación inusual de un leiomiosarcoma primario en borde lateral de la lengua, aportando así, un caso más a los reportes aislados de estas lesiones en cabeza y cuello ya descritos en la literatura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;36(1): 27-31, ene.-mar. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121103</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Leiomiosarcoma del borde lateral de la lengua: reporte de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8070^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22700^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22570^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
