<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80573</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Emotional climate in Primary Health Care teams. A qualitative approach</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The social interactions met in the Primary Health Care work teams are driven by important emotional aspects that affect the environment, results and the satisfaction of the professional and the patients. The objective of this work is to describe the emotional climate of Primary Care work teams, looking for the perceptions of different professional category and different work groups (selected by the quality of their emotional climate). Methods. A qualitative methodology was used: 2 nominal groups and 2 focal groups, with 18 physicians and nurses working in the Andalusian Primary Health Care system. The information was recorded and then a content analysis was made. Results. Health care professionals identify the following explanatory dimensions: professional relationship (high scored), shared work project, professional recognition, leadership, burnout and personal attitudes, as well as work conditions. Different opinions were recorded among physicians and nurses, especially when the group had a bad emotional atmosphere. Conclusions. More studies on the emotional climate in Primary Health Care are needed in order to propose strategies to improve satisfaction and quality of work life among professionals(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Romera, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Danet Danet, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>March Cerdá, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. Las interacciones sociales en los equipos de trabajo de Atención primaria movilizan importantes aspectos emocionales que afectan el ambiente, rendimiento y satisfacción de profesionales y pacientes. El objetivo del estudio es describir el clima emocional de los equipos de trabajo de Atención primaria, planteando si hay diferencias en la percepción del clima emocional en función de la categoría profesional y de la pertenencia a un grupo con clima emocional positivo o negativo. Métodos. Se ha empleado metodología cualitativa: 2 grupos nominales y 2 grupos focales, con 18 profesionales (personal médico y de enfermería) de Atención primaria de 2 distritos sanitarios andaluces. La información se ha grabado y posteriormente, se ha realizado un análisis de contenido. Resultados. El personal sanitario identificó las siguientes dimensiones explicativas del clima emocional: relaciones profesionales (con un alto peso), proyecto común, reconocimiento profesional, estilo de liderazgo, desgaste y actitudes personales y condiciones de trabajo. Se perciben diferencias entre las opiniones del personal médico y enfermero, asociado a la existencia de un clima emocional negativo. Conclusiones. Se requieren más investigaciones sobre el clima emocional en Atención primaria, de cara a proponer líneas de actuación para mejorar la satisfacción y la calidad de vida de los y las profesionales(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;25(4): 200-206, jul.-ago. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80573</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El clima emocional en los equipos de atención primaria. Una aproximación cualitativa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8035</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4726^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
