<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151591</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Lung ultrasound as a tool to guide the administration of surfactant in premature neonates</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: The aim of this study is to assess the usefulness of lung ultrasound (LUS) to estimate the endotracheal tube (ETT) depth position during the Intubation-Surfactant-Extubation (INSURE) procedure. Material and methods: The ETT insertion depth was estimated using the weight (insertion depth (cm)=weight (kg)+5.5). After intubation two independent neonatologists using bilateral auscultation or LUS checked the ETT depth. Results: Twelve newborns with respiratory distress syndrome were included. In two cases LUS helped to correctly replace the ETT. All the patients progressed well, with normal x-ray and LUS before discharge. Conclusions: LUS appears to be a safe and non-invasive technique and is useful in clinical situations were x-ray is not routinely performed, as it is fast and radiation free (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno Hernando, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balcells Esponera, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Fanjul, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarquella Brugada, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: El objetivo del presente estudio es la valoración mediante la ecografía pulmonar de la profundidad del tubo endotraqueal (TET) durante el procedimiento de Intubation-Surfactant-Extubation (INSURE). Material y métodos: La profundidad de inserción del TET se calculó mediante el peso del neonato (profundidad de inserción [cm] = peso [kg]+5,5). Después de la intubación, la profundidad del TET fue valorada por 2 neonatólogos independientes mediante la auscultación bilateral y la ecografía pulmonar. Resultados: Doce neonatos con membrana hialina fueron reclutados. En 2 casos la ecografía pulmonar ayudó a posicionar correctamente el TET. Todos los pacientes presentaron una buena evolución con una radiografía y una ecografía pulmonar normal al alta. Conclusiones: La ecografía pulmonar es una técnica segura y no invasiva útil en situaciones donde la radiografía de tórax no se usa habitualmente, siendo además rápida y libre de radiación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);84(5): 249-253, mayo 2016. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151591</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La ecografía pulmonar como herramienta para guiar la surfactación en neonatos prematuros</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13880^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22228</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13880^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30602^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13880^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
