<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107865</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Haemophilic pseudotumour: a rare complication of factor VIII and IX deficiency which can mimic soft tissue sarcoma. A case report and review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A rare complication of haemophilia is haemophilic pseudotumour which is an encapsulated haematoma in different stages of organization. However, it often resembling osteogenic or soft tissue sarcoma, both clinically and radiologically. We report a case of a 30 year old male with haemophilia A and a one year history of haemophilic pseudotumour of the left leg. A multidisciplinary team was responsible for his management. A supracondylar amputation was performed and immunohistochemical studies were carried out. The literature was reviewed(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mendoza-Ramírez, Saulo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Hernández, Jaqueline</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dorantes-Heredia, Rita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicuña-Honorato, Iliana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar-Neri, Erick</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gamboa-Domínguez, Armando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murguía-Pérez, Mario</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El seudotumor hemofílico es una complicación infrecuente en pacientes hemofílicos y es básicamente un hematoma encapsulado en diferentes estadios de organización, que muchas veces llega a confundirse clínica y radiográficamente como un sarcoma osteogénico o de tejidos blandos. Informamos el caso de un varón de 30 años con hemofilia A y diagnóstico de seudotumor hemofílico en miembro pélvico izquierdo con evolución de un año. Se realizó amputación supracondílea en su manejo multidisciplinario, así como un estudio inmunohistoquímico. Se revisó la literatura(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;45(4): 243-246, oct.-dic.2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107865</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seudotumor hemofílico: complicación poco frecuente en pacientes con deficiencia del factor VIII y IX que asemeja sarcoma de partes blandas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2885^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6545^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2885^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6545^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6619^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2885^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22169</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13369^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31057^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6545^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31057^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13369^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31057^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6619^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6619^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
