<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-71430</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hypophosphatasia: new therapeutic approaches</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hypophosphatasia is a rare inborn error of metabolism characterized by a deficiency of tissue non-specific alkaline phosphatase (bone, liver and kidney) which leads to abnormal mineralization of skeletal and dental tissues. There are several forms of hypophosphatasia with wide variations in severity ranging from high-mortality neonatal presentation to mild forms in adults associated with fragility fractures and osteomalacia. The biochemical diagnosis is based on measurement of low levels of serum alkaline phophatase and increased serum or urine concentrations of phosphoethalnolamine, pyridoxal 5&#146;-phosphate and inorganic pyrophosphate. To date, therapy has been quite heterogeneous with quite limited outcomes. The recent progress in research leads to new therapeutic approaches for this complex disease. The administration of parathyroid hormone in adult hypophosphatasia and enzyme replacement therapy using a novel soluble recombinant form of human alkaline phosphatase for severe forms of hypophosphatasia are currently the most promising approaches (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Torres, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varsavsky, Mariela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hipofosfatasia es una enfermedad hereditaria caracterizada por una deficiencia de fosfatasa alcalina no específica de tejido, que genera una mineralización anormal del tejido óseo y dental. La presentación clínica es muy variable, desde formas neonatales con alta mortalidad, hasta variantes más leves del adulto con fracturas por fragilidad y osteomalacia. El diagnóstico bioquímico se basa en la determinación de valores séricos bajos de fosfatasa alcalina e incremento sérico o urinario de fosfoetanolamina, piridoxal 5&#146;-fosfato y pirofosfato inorgánico. El tratamiento ha sido muy heterogéneo y con resultados limitados. Recientes avances abren nuevas líneas de investigación en esta compleja enfermedad. Actualmente, la administración de hormona paratiroidea en la hipofosfatasia del adulto y el tratamiento de sustitución enzimático, en el que se utiliza una novedosa forma soluble de fosfatasa alcalina recombinante humana en las formas clínicas más graves, constituyen los tratamientos con mejores perspectivas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);132(3): 108-111, ene. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-71430</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hipofosfatasia: nuevas perspectivas terapéuticas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d471^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7193^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33002^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200901</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
