<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161166</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Seventh Jesús Culebras Lecture. Systemic inflammatory response and multi organic dysfunction/failure following aggression: metabolic implications</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Following any aggression, the body starts an inflammatory response, mediated by humoral and cellular factors, intended to limit the process and eventually to heal. In some cases, either due to the intensity or the duration of the aggression or due to an inadequate response of the host, secondary to genetic polymorphisms, malnutrition or other causes, a state of hyper activation of inflammatory cells is originated, with liberation of immature cells and activation of monocytes and macrophages, which liberate very powerful pro inflammatory mediators that induce a state of generalized systemic inflammation. Many processes may originate this inflammatory response, (sepsis, trauma, burns, pancreatitis, etc.) with activation of leukocyte, endothelial, coagulation and neuroendocrine response systems, generating a complex of mediators (cytokines, adhesion molecules, growth factors, etc.). Clinically, the response is characterized by inflammation, anorexia, stillness, increase of vascular permeability, factors that originate edema and vasodilatation, which is followed by hypotension, tachycardia and increased cardiac output. On the other hand, the metabolic response to stress is part of the mechanism of adaptation, generated by the organism in order to survive the acute disease by means of increasing energetic substrates to vital tissues. As a result of this complex metabolic response, the control of substrate utilization is only partially regulated because, being impaired the mechanisms of energy supply, the organism seeks alternative substrates (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García de Lorenzo y Mateos, Abelardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Ante cualquier agresión, el organismo pone en marcha una respuesta inflamatoria, mediada por factores humorales y celulares, que tiende a limitar el proceso y a conseguir la curación. En algunos casos, ya sea por la intensidad o duración de la noxa, ya por una inadecuada respuesta del huésped secundaria a polimorfismos genéticos, malnutrición u otras causas, se produce un estado de hiperactivación de las células inflamatorias, con liberación de células inmaduras y activación de monocitos y macrófagos, que liberan poderosos mediadores proinflamatorios e inducen un estado de inflamación sistémica generalizada. Numerosos procesos pueden dar lugar a esta respuesta inflamatoria (sepsis, traumatismos, quemaduras, pancreatitis, etc.) con activación de los sistemas leucocitarios, endoteliales, de la coagulación y de la respuesta neuroendocrina, lo que genera un complejo entramado de mediadores (citocinas, moléculas de adhesión y factores de crecimiento, entre otros). Clínicamente, la respuesta se caracteriza por inflamación, anorexia, inmovilidad, aumento en la permeabilidad vascular que condiciona la aparición de edema, vasodilatación que se acompaña de hipotensión, taquicardia e incremento del gasto cardiaco. Por otro lado, la respuesta metabólica al estrés forma parte de ese mecanismo de adaptación, que el organismo genera para sobrevivir a la enfermedad aguda aumentando el aporte de sustratos energéticos a los tejidos vitales. Como resultado de esa compleja respuesta metabólica, el control de la utilización de los sustratos energéticos está solo parcialmente regulado por su disponibilidad, debido a que al estar alterados los mecanismos de producción energética, el organismo busca sustratos alternativos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;34(1): 244-250, ene.-feb. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161166</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Séptima Lección Jesús Culebras. Respuesta inflamatoria sistémica y disfunción/fracaso multiorgánico tras una agresión: implicaciones metabólicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1927^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13700^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9294^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32030^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32175^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
