<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154063</identifier>
<setSpec>2254-2884</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of the intravenous administration of iron carboxymaltose for controlling anemia in advanced chronic kidney disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Ferric carboxymaltose is a safe and easy dosage of intravenous iron formulation; it can be administered intravenously up to 1 gram in a single session and allows time savings of patients and nursing. We present the results of his administration in a unit of chronic kidney disease, analyzing the results and the impact on the workload of the nursing staff. Materials and methods: All patients followed in the chronic kidney disease unit at our center from January 2011 to December 2014 and who received intravenous iron carboxymaltose were analyzed. Their baseline data and clinical and laboratory results at six months were recorded. Results: 85 patients were identified during this period. Mean age of 72 ± 12 years, with a baseline estimated glomerular filtration rate of 28 ± 11 ml / min and at six months of 30 ± 11 (p &gt;0.05). Baseline and at six months hemoglobin levels were 10 ± 4 and 11 ± 3 g / dl, respectively (p &lt;0.001). The basal and final hematocrit were: 34 ± 4 vs 39 ± 6% (p &lt;0.001). Baseline ferritin levels and transferrin saturation index versus levels at six months were respectively: 88 ± 97 vs 308 ± 327 ng / ml (p &lt;0.001) and 11.2 ± 6 vs 11 ± 22.3 (p &lt;0.001 ). Since the average administration time by any formulation of intravenous iron is 30 minutes, the estimate based on the number of administrations is a saving of 85 and 170 hours on these four years when compared with formulations that require three to five respectively sessions. In turn, the number of punctures has been reduced without associated complications observed. Conclusion: Carboxymaltose iron is safe and effective showing a recovery of hemoglobin levels and iron deposits. Its ease of administration has allowed substantial time savings. This, together with its few side effects makes it ideal for outpatient administration (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García García, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero González, M Angeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Gómez, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendoza Mendoza, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La carboximaltosa férrica es una formulación de hierro endovenosa segura y de fácil dosificación, se puede administrar hasta 1 gramo iv en una sola sesión y permite ahorro de tiempo de los pacientes y de enfermería. Presentamos los resultados de su administración en una consulta de enfermedad renal crónica, analizando sus resultados y la repercusión en la carga de trabajo del personal de enfermería. Material y Métodos: Se analizaron todos los pacientes en seguimiento de la consulta de enfermedad renal crónica en nuestro centro desde Ene-11 hasta Dic-14 que recibieron carboximaltosa férrica iv. Se registraron sus datos basales y los resultados clínicos y analíticos a los seis meses. Resultados: Fueron identificados 85 pacientes en ese periodo. Edad media de 72±12 años, con un filtrado glomerular estimado basal de 28±11ml/min y a los seis meses de 30±11 (p:n.s). La hemoglobina basal y a los seis meses fueron de 10±4 y 11±3 g/dl respectivamente (p:&lt;0,001). El hematocrito basal y final fueron: 34±4 vs 39±6 % (p:&lt;0,001). Los niveles de ferritina e índice de saturación de transferrina basales vs seis meses fueron respectivamente: 88±97 vs 308±327 ng/ml (p:&lt;0,001) y 11,2±6 vs 22,3±11 (p:&lt;0,001). Dado que el tiempo medio de administración de cualquier formulación de hierro endovenoso es de 30 minutos, la estimación en base al número de administraciones es de un ahorro de 85 y 170 horas en estos 4 años si se compara con formulaciones que requieren de tres a cinco sesiones respectivamente. A su vez el número de punciones se ha reducido, sin observarse complicaciones asociadas. Conclusiones: La carboximaltosa férrica es segura y eficaz mostrando una recuperación de los niveles de hemoglobina y de los depósitos de hierro. Su facilidad de administración ha permitido ahorros sustanciales de tiempo. Esto junto a sus escasos efectos secundarios la hacen idónea para la administración ambulatoria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. nefrol;19(2): 113-117, abr.-jun. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154063</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la administración de carboximaltosa férrica intravenosa en la consulta de enfermedad renal crónica avanzada, para el control de la anemia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7668^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55420^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55420^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32369^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32369^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55420^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16595^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
