<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112750</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4008</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cross-reactivity of recombinant insulin preparations with two commercial insulin inmunoassays</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The large variability in cross-reactivities of recombinant insulin preparations with different commercial assays is noteworthy. It is imperative to know which recombinant insulin preparations a method can detect and which ones it cannot, to interpret certain laboratory results. Objective: To asses the cross-reactivity of soluble insulin, insulin NPH, glulisina and detemir with insulin inmunoassays Elecsys/E170 (Roche) and Architect (Abbott). Material and methods: Solutions of glulisine, detemir, soluble insulin and insulin NPH (20 - 1000 mU/L) were prepared and analized with insulin inmunoassays Elecsys/E170 (Roche) and Architect (Abbott). The cross-reactivity percentage was calculated for each solution. Results: With Elecsys/E170, the cross-reactivity of glulisine and detemir was &lt; 5% for all solutions. The cross-reactivity of soluble insulin was 120% and insulin NPH 106%. With Architect, the cross-reactivity of glulisine was 12,6%; detemir 130% for 20 mU/L and &gt;240% for 100 mU/L; soluble insulin 99% and insulin NPH 153%. Conclusions: Elecsys/E170 detects both preparations of insulin of human sequence but it does not detect gluisine nor detemir. Architect detects both preparations of insulin of human sequence and detemir; for gluisine the average of cross-reactivity is 12,6%. Colaboration between laboratories employing different immunoassays may be useful to throw light on some hypoglycemia profiles, where overdose or misadministration of insulin preparations is suspected (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Camarasa, María Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliver Oliver, María Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abellán Tejada, Lidia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carratalá Calvo, Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marco Descalzo, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Existe gran variabilidad en la capacidad de detección de análogos de insulina e insulinas recombinantes por los inmunoanálisis comerciales para determinación de insulina. Conocer qué preparados de insulina pueden detectar un método, y cuáles no, es necesario para interpretar algunos resultados de laboratorio. Objetivo: Determinar la reactividad cruzada de insulina soluble, insulina NPH, glulisina y detemir con los inmunoanálisis de insulina Elecsys/E170 (Roche) y Architect (Abbott). Material y métodos: Se prepararon diluciones (rango 20---1.000 mU/l) de glulisina, detemir, insulina soluble e insulina NPH. Se analizaron con los inmunoanálisis de insulina Elecsys/E170 (Roche) y Architect (Abbott). Se calculó la reactividad cruzada (%) para cada dilución. Resultados: Con Elecsys/E170 la reactividad cruzada de glulisina y detemir fue &lt; 5% en todas las diluciones; para insulina soluble, el promedio de la reactividad cruzada fue de 120% y para insulina NPH de 106%. En Architect, el promedio de la reactividad cruzada de glulisina fue del 12,6%; detemir 130% para 20 mU/l y &gt; 240% para 100 mU/l; insulina soluble 99% e insulina NPH 153%. Conclusiones: Elecsys/E170 detecta las 2 insulinas de secuencia humana y no detecta glulisina ni detemir. Architect detecta las insulinas de secuencia humana y el análogo detemir; para glulisina, el promedio de reactividad cruzada es del 12,6%. La colaboración entre laboratorios que utilizan diferentes inmunoanálisis puede ser útil para aclarar algunos cuadros clínicos de hipoglucemia, en los que se sospecha sobredosis o administración indebida de preparados de insulina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. lab. clín;6(2): 94-98, abr.-jun. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112750</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reactividad cruzada de preparados de insulina recombinante con 2 inmunoanálisis comerciales para determinación de insulina en sangre</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22512^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22512^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22512^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22512^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8338^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33556^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25169^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33556^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
