<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048115</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Restorative proctocolectomy with an ileoanal pouch: the role of laparoscopy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: the aim of this retrospective study was to evaluateearly experience with laparoscopic restorative proctocolectomy byanalyzing the perioperative results of surgical treatment.Patients and methods: seven major surgeries were performedin six patients with familial adenomatous polyposis and ulcerativecolitis. All procedures were performed under laparoscopyat our third-level hospital from June 2003 to October 2004.Results: mean surgical time was 287.5 ± 80.7 min, and medianblood loss was 300 ± 249.0 cc. There were no conversions;return of peristalsis began at 32 ± 12.4 h; average time to firstoral intake was 64.0 ± 32.8 h, and mean duration of hospital staywas 9.3 ± 1.2 days. There was one case of perineal sepsis due toileal pouch-anal anastomotic leakage, which was successfullytreated with oral intake restriction, parenteral nutrition, and intrarectaldrainage. The most common postoperative complicationwas postoperative ileus.Conclusions: we believe that the laparoscopic approach torestorative proctocolectomy may be considerably improved in ourcenter. Particular aspects for improvement include efforts toachieve lower operating and hospitalization times to equate ourresults with those reported by multicenter studies for laparoscopiccolon cancer surgery. In our opinion, learning and further trainingopportunities should be encouraged to improve surgeon experiencein the field of laparoscopy, preferably at centers specializingin restorative proctocolectomy</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carrillo Pallarés, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Tomassetti Fernández, E. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arteaga González, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Plasencia, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Malagón, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Luis, H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: el objetivo de este estudio restrospectivo es evaluarla experiencia inicial en la proctocolectomía restauradora laparoscópica,analizando los resultados perioperatorios obtenidos durantela fase de introducción de la técnica.Pacientes y métodos: entre junio de 2003 y octubre 2004,realizamos siete intervenciones mayores en seis pacientes afectosde poliposis colónica familiar y colitis ulcerosa mediante abordajelaparoscópico.Resultados: el tiempo medio quirúrgico fue: 287,5 ± 80,7min y las pérdidas hemáticas: 300 ± 249,0 cc. No hubo conversiones;el inicio del peristaltismo fue: 32 ± 12,4 h; el tiempo mediode reintroducción de la alimentación: 64,0 ± 32,8 h; el tiempomedio de estancia hospitalaria: 9,3 ± 1,2 días. Hubo un casode dehiscencia del reservorio ileoanal con sepsis perineal tratadasatisfactoriamente con dieta absoluta, nutrición parenteral y drenajedel mismo mediante punción intrarrectal. La complicaciónpostoperatoria más frecuente fue la presencia de íleo postoperatorio.Conclusiones: creemos que la proctocolectomía restauradoralaparoscópica aún debe mejorar. Estas mejoras deberían reducirlos tiempos operatorios y la estancia hospitalaria para que la laparoscopiaen este campo iguale los resultados tan favorables obte-nidos en estudios multicéntricos en la cirugía oncológica del colon.En nuestra opinión, estos cambios deberían producirse con elaprendizaje y formación de los cirujanos en laparoscopia colorrectaly siempre en centros dedicados especialmente a este tipo de cirugía</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;98(6): 420-428, jun. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048115</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Proctocolectomía restauradora con reservorio ileoanal: el papel de la laparoscopia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13886</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36514</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29872</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23971^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
