<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89836</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Entrepreneurship education: relationship between education and entrepreneurial activity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The importance of entrepreneurial activity for the economic growth of countries is now well established. The relevant literature suggests important links between education, venture creation and entrepreneurial performance, as well as between entrepreneurial education and entrepreneurial activity. The primary purpose of this paper is to provide some insights about entrepreneurship education. The meaning of entrepreneurship education is explained, and the significant increase of these educational programmes is highlighted. Literature has been suggesting that the most suitable indicator to evaluate the results of entrepreneurship education is the rate of new business creation. However, some studies indicate that the results of such programmes are not immediate. Therefore, many researchers try to understand the precursors of venture creation, concluding that is necessary to carry out longitudinal studies. Based on an overview of the research published about the existing linkage of entrepreneurship education and entrepreneurial activity, the main topics studied by different academics are addressed. For the authors, the positive impact of entrepreneurship education puts a double challenge on governments in the future: the increased need of financial funds to support entrepreneurship education and the choice of the correct educational programme (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Raposo, Mario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paço, Arminda do</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La importancia de la actividad empresarial para el crecimiento económico de los países está bien establecida. La literatura sugiere importantes relaciones entre educación, creación de negocios y desempeño empresarial, así como entre educación empresarial y actividad emprendedora. El objetivo de este artículo es proporcionar algunos esclarecimientos acerca de la educación emprendedora. La literatura sugiere que el indicador más conveniente para evaluar los resultados de la educación emprendedora es la tasa de creación de nuevos negocios. Sin embargo, algunos estudios indican que los resultados de tales programas no son inmediatos. Por tanto, muchos investigadores tratan de comprender los precursores de la creación de negocios, concluyendo que es necesario llevar a cabo estudios longitudinales. Basado en una perspectiva general de la investigación publicada acerca de la relación existente entre la educación emprendedora y la actividad empresarial, se abordan las principales líneas investigadas por diferentes académicos. Para los autores, el impacto positivo de la educación emprendedora pone un doble desafío a los gobiernos en el futuro: la creciente necesidad de fondos financieros para apoyar la educación en la creación de empresas y la elección del programa educativo más adecuado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);23(3): 453-457, jul.-sept. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89836</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Educación emprendedora: relación entre educación y actividad emprendedora</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28630^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7395^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7395^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7395^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3163^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37704^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
