<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80097</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of morbidity, resource use and costs on maintenance of remission of major depression in spain: a longitudinal study in a population setting</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To determinate the impact of comorbidity, resource use and cost (healthcare and lost productivity) on maintenance of remission of major depressive disorder in a Spanish population setting.MethodsWe performed an observational, prospective, multicenter study using population databases. The inclusion criteria were age &amp;#8805;18 years, first depressive episode between January 2003 and March 2007, with antidepressant prescription &gt;60 days after the first prescription and a follow-up of at least 18 months (study: 12 months; continuation: 6 months). Two subgroups were considered: patients with/without remission. Main measures: sociodemographic data, episodes, resource utilization bands, healthcare costs (direct) and lost productivity (indirect). Logistic regression and analysis of covariance (Bonferroni correction) were used for analysis.ResultsA total of 4,572 patients were analyzed and 54.6% (95% confidence interval: 53.2&#150;56.0%) were considered in remission. Patients in remission were younger (52.6 vs. 60.7), with a lower proportion of women (71.7% vs. 78.2%), and showed less general morbidity (6.2 vs. 7.7 episodes/year), lower resource utilization bands/year (2.7 vs. 3.0), fewer sick leave days (31.0 vs. 38.5) and shorter treatment duration (146.6 vs. 307.7 days); p&lt;0.01. Lack of remission was associated with fibromyalgia (odds ratio [OR]=2.5), thyroid alterations (OR=1.3) and hypertension (OR=1.2); p&lt;0.001. The annual healthcare cost was &#128;706.0 per patient in remission vs. &#128;1,108.3 without remission (p &lt;0.001) and lost productivity was &#128;1,631.5 vs. &#128;2,024.2, respectively (p &lt;0.001).ConclusionsPatients not achieving remission showed higher morbidity, resources use, healthcare costs and, especially, productivity losses(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salvatella-Pasant, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sicras-Mainar, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanca-Tamayo, Milagrosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro-Artieda, Ruth</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Nicuesa, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Determinar el impacto de la comorbilidad, el uso de recursos y los costes (sanitarios y en pérdidas de productividad laboral) en el mantenimiento de la remisión de la depresión en un ámbito poblacional español.MétodosDiseño observacional, prospectivo, multicéntrico, realizado con bases de datos poblacionales. Los criterios de inclusión fueron: edad &amp;#8805;18 años, inicio del episodio depresivo entre enero de 2003 y marzo de 2007, prescripción de antidepresivos &gt;60 días después de la primera prescripción y duración del seguimiento de 18 meses (estudio: 12 meses; continuación: 6 meses). Se consideraron 2 subgrupos: pacientes en remisión y sin remisión. Las principales mediciones fueron sociodemográficas, episodios, bandas de utilización de recursos, costes sanitarios (directos) y en pérdidas de productividad (indirectos). Se realizó análisis de regresión logística y de análisis de la covarianza (ajuste Bonferroni).ResultadosSe reclutaron 4.572 sujetos. El 54,6% (intervalo de confianza del 95%: 53,2&#150;56,0%) se consideraron en remisión. Los pacientes en remisión mostraron menor edad (52,6 frente a 60,7 años), mayor proporción de mujeres (71,7% frente a 78,2%), más morbilidad general (6,2 frente a 7,7 episodios/año), menos bandas de utilización de recursos/año (2,7 frente a 3,0), menor incapacidad laboral (31,0 frente a 38,5 días) y menor duración del tratamiento antidepresivo (146,6 frente a 307,7 días); p&lt;0,01. Los pacientes sin remisión se asociaban a fibromialgia (odds ratio [OR]=2,5), alteraciones (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;24(1): 13-19, ener. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80097</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de la morbilidad, uso de recursos y costes en el mantenimiento de la remisión de la depresión mayor en España: estudio longitudinal de ámbito poblacional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d44</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3885^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6446^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3885^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6446^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201001</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
