<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164859</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of off-label prescribing: profile, evidence and evolution</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The objectives of the study were to describe the extent and profile of off-label prescriptions, to evaluate the level of evidence supporting these indications, to assess the research activity in these conditions, and to determine to what extent these were authorized as new indications five years after the application. Methods: A cross-sectional study including all applications conducted in the Hospital Universitario Reina Sofía in Córdoba during 2010. Analysis: level of evidence according to the criteria by SIGN-NICE (Scottish Intercollegiate Guidelines Network, National Institute for Health and Care Excellence) and CEBM (Centre for Evidence-based Medicine), registered clinical trials (source: ClinicalTrials.gov), and review of product specifications and monthly newsletters from the Spanish Agency of Medicines and Medical Devices. Results: There were 190 applications for off-label prescription for 82 different indications. The most requested medications were: tacrolimus, mycophenolate, colistimethate and everolimus; the immunosuppressant group had the highest number of uses for non-approved indications. Out of the applications, 52.4% were based on some clinical trial, while the rest had a low level of evidence (observational studies and case reports). We have found on-going clinical trials for 67% of the indications, but new indications in their product specifications have only been authorized for nine drugs (bevacizumab, deferasirox, everolimus, lenalidomide, methotrexate, sildenafil, sorafenib, raltegravir and tenofovir). Conclusions: We have detected a major volume of off-label prescription without good supporting evidence, which identifies these indications and medications as interesting research lines, but that require follow-up in terms of effectiveness and costs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cárdenas Aranzana , Manuel Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ocaña Riola, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prado Llergo, José Ramón del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Reina, Encarnación</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz García, Azucena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Los objetivos del estudio fueron describir la magnitud y el perfil de las prescripciones fuera de ficha técnica (off-label), evaluar el nivel de evidencia en el que se sustentan estas indicaciones, valorar la actividad investigadora en estas enfermedades y determinar en qué grado se autorizan como nuevas indicaciones transcurridos cinco años desde la solicitud. Métodos: Estudio transversal que incluyó todas las solicitudes realizadas en el Hospital Universitario Reina Sofía de Córdoba durante 2010. Análisis: nivel de evidencia según criterios de SIGN-NICE (Scottish Intercollegiate Guidelines Network, National Institute for Health and Care Excellence) y del CEBM (Centre for Evidence-based Medicine), ensayos clínicos registrados (fuente: ClinicalTrials.gov) y la revisión de fichas técnicas e informes mensuales de la Agencia Española del Medicamento. Resultados: Hubo 190 solicitudes offlabel para 82 indicaciones distintas. Los medicamentos más solicitados fueron tacrolimus, micofenolato, colistimetato y everolimus, constituyéndose el grupo de inmunosupresores como el de mayor número de usos en indicaciones no aprobadas. El 52,4% de las solicitudes estaban basadas en algún ensayo clínico, mientras que el resto tuvo un bajo nivel de evidencia (estudios observacionales y casos). Hemos encontrado ensayos clínicos en activo para el 67% de las indicaciones, pero solo nueve fármacos han visto autorizadas nuevas indicaciones en su ficha técnica (bevacizumab, deferasirox, everolimus, lenalidomida, metotrexato, sildenafilo, sorafenib, raltegravir y tenofovir). Conclusiones: Se ha detectado un importante volumen de usos offlabel en ausencia de buena evidencia, lo que identifica a estas indicaciones y medicamentos como líneas de investigación interesantes pero con necesidad de seguimiento de efectividad y costes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;41(4): 458-469, jul.-ago. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164859</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de las prescripciones fuera de ficha técnica: perfil, evidencia y evolución</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24613^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4403^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9365^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30103^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30152^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53366^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31498^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53689^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
