<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128300</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dermatitis Caused by Hair Dye (Quinone Produced by the Action of Aqueous Hydrogen Peroxide on p-Phenylenediamine Hydrochloride), by Juan De Azúa</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the first issue of Actas Dermo-Sifiliográf icas, Juan de Azúa published a magnificent article on contact dermatitis caused by hair dyes, which reflects his profound knowledge of allergy and how the skin responds to chemical stimuli. It gives a brilliant description of irritative and allergic dermatitis, although without naming the allergic form explicitly. Of note is how he is concerned about the composition of «those Parisian dyes»; so much so that he contacted the local laboratory to determine their chemical composition and how they work. It is a delight to study the case histories and treatments administered to these 15 patients. During the months of treatment, he reports trying different officinal formulas that, although unknown to most of today&#146;s dermatologists, nevertheless managed to cure the patients in the end (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Conde, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este primer número de Actas Juan de Azúa publica un magnífico artículo sobre la dermatitis de contacto por tintes capilares, comprobándose sus altos conocimientos sobre la alergia y la forma de responderla piel a estímulos químicos. Describe magistralmente las dermatitis irritativas y las alérgicas, aunque a estas últimas no les da esta denominación propiamente dicha. Es de destacar cómo se preocupa por la composición de «estos tintes parisinos» poniéndose en contacto con el Laboratorio Municipal para poder conocer la composición química y su forma de actuar. Es una delicia leer detenidamente las historias y el tratamiento realizado a los 15 enfermos que cita, son meses de tratamientos en los que se alternan diversas fórmulas magistrales desconocidas hoy día por la mayoría de los dermatólogos pero que al final... conseguían curar al enfermo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;100(2): 100-102, mar. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128300</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dermitis producida por una tintura para el pelo. (Quinona resultante de la acción del agua oxigenada sobre el clorhidrato de parafenileno-diamina), por Juan de Azúa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3894^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6355^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38889</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6355^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10848^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3894^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10848^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6355^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
