<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043874</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-1637</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The advantages and disadvantages of different treatments of incisor overbite: 3 clinical cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The continued prevalence of incisor overbite seen in dental offices has led to the creation of new corrective therapies. Systems which cause the intrusion of the incisors with additional gentle extrusion of the molars are the most effective. Three patients with severe incisor overbite were each treated with different therapeutic methods: lingual brackets (LB), brackets + retroincisor supports (B+AR) and brackets + reverse curve Ni-Ti arch (B+IA). Patients were monitored every 15 days and photographs were taken of the patients at the initiation, the middle and end of the treatment. Data was collected regarding three points: total duration of treatment, the incidence of detachment of brackets and how long the patient noted impaired phonation. Treatment with B+IA was the longest compared to treatments LB and B+RS, with were pf similar duration. The number of detachments of brackets was greater with B+IA, while the other two methods had a similar number of detachments. Treatment with LB produced more impairment of phonation than the other two methods. We found that B+RS is the best treatment option for incisor overbite, as it is effective, easy, comfortable and cost effective</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Leonés, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albadalejo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La continua presencia de casos de sobreoclusión incisiva en las consultas dentales ha llevado a la creación de nuevos métodos terapéuticos para su corrección, y los que provocan la intrusión de los incisivos, acompañados de una leve extrusión de los molares, son los más eficaces. Tres pacientes con sobreoclusión incisiva grave fueron tratados con 3 métodos terapéuticos diferentes: brackets linguales (BL), brackets + apoyos retroincisivos (B+AR) y brackets + arcos Ni-Ti con curva de Spee invertida (B+AI). Los pacientes fueron controlados cada 15 días y se realizaron fotografías de control al principio, a mitad y al final del tratamiento. Estos 3 métodos se compararon en función de 3 variables definidas: el tiempo total del tratamiento, el número de desprendimientos de brackets y el tiempo durante el cual el paciente presentó molestias en la fonación. El tiempo de tratamiento fue mayor para B+AI con respecto a BL y B+AR, que fueron similares. El número de desprendimientos en B+AI fue mayor que en los otros 2 métodos, que fueron iguales. BL presentó mayores molestias en la fonación que los otros 2 métodos. B+AR, por tanto, se presenta como la mejor opción de tratamiento para la sobreoclusión incisiva, al ser un método eficaz, fácil, cómodo y económico</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ortod. esp. (Ed. impr.);45(4): 229-237, oct.-dic. 2005. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043874</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ventajas e inconvenientes de diversos tratamientos de la sobreoclusión incisiva a partir de 3 casos clínicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3781</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10149^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14480^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7358^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10147^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
