<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84891</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: analysis and evaluation of a multidisciplinary approach, postoperative results and survival of a group of patients with resected pancreatic cancer after a multimodal therapy. Design: descriptive, prospective and observational study. Patients: between January 2004 and December 2004, 124 patients with pancreatic cancer were evaluated. In 30 patients pancreatic resection was performed, and they are the object of this study. Results of preoperative evaluation, postoperative morbidity and mortality, and long term survival were studied. Results: diagnostic evaluation was completed in ambulatory basis in 20% of the patients. In 63% of cases, admission was done in the same day of surgery. In 3 patients (9%), tumor resection was not achieved, therefore, concordance between radiological and surgical resectability rate was 91%. Resectability rate was 24.1%. Surgical Mortality was 3.3%, with a global morbidity rate of 56.6%. Survival at one, two, three and, four years was 76.2%, 56.3%, 43%, y 27.3% respectively. Conclusions: technological development and coordination of efforts in multidisciplinary teams offer an accurate evaluation of tumor involvement, and may reduce the number of laparotomies without tumor resection. The application of a systematic and generalized multimodal treatment in pancreatic cancer is progressively showing a tendency of progressive increase in resectability and survival rates in pancreatic cancer(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morales, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Bonafe, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riera, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilella, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Socías, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González de Cabo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arriví, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Falcó, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dolz, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuadrado, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Noguera, J . F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Company, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicens, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: analizar la evaluación del abordaje multidisciplinario de un grupo de pacientes con cáncer de páncreas resecado, los resultados postoperatorios y la supervivencia tras la aplicación de un tratamiento multimodal. Diseño: estudio descriptivo prospectivo observacional. Pacientes: entre enero de 2004 y diciembre 2009 se evaluaron 124 pacientes con cáncer de páncreas. De ellos, se realizó la resección pancreática con intención curativa en 30 casos que constituyen el objeto del estudio. Se analizaron los resultados del estudio preoperatorio de extensión tumoral, la morbi-mortalidad postoperatoria, y la supervivencia. Resultados: la evaluación diagnóstica se hizo en régimen ambulatorio en el 20% de los pacientes. En el 63% de los casos, el ingreso fue el mismo día de la intervención. En 3 pacientes intervenidos no se consiguió realizar la resección del tumor (9%), por lo que la tasa de concordancia entre la resecabilidad radiológica y la quirúrgica fue del 91%. La tasa de resecabilidad quirúrgica fue del 24,1%. La mortalidad quirúrgica de la serie fue de un 3,3%, con una morbilidad global del 56,6%. La supervivencia al año, dos, tres y cuatro años fue del 76,2%, 56,3%, 43%, y 27,3% respectivamente. Conclusiones: el desarrollo tecnológico y la evaluación multidisciplinar coordinada, permite realizar una evaluación precisa de la extensión tumoral, y puede reducir el número de laparotomías sin resección del tumor. Con la aplicación de una terapia multimodal sistemática combinada, la resecabilidad quirúrgica y la supervivencia a medio y largo plazo parece que están aumentando de forma progresiva(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;103(1): 5-12, ene. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84891</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación multidisciplinaria y tratamiento multimodal del cáncer de páncreas resecado. Estudio observacional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5538^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23947^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8374^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10378^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3162^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d284^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3162^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11621^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10368^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10378^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10368^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10368^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201101</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
