<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166212</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">One-stop consultation in cardiology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The use of one-stop consultations is growing. Cardiology is one of the specialties that will benefit most from it. The approach has undoubted advantages, such as, in particular, the speed of the diagnostic and therapeutic processes. Nonetheless, this approach should by no means be considered the only way of providing specialized care. It can and should coexist with traditional care since some investigations cannot be incorporated into the one-stop consultation model. Furthermore, the implementation of this approach or of its findings may be limited by a lack of resources, poor organization, or the low cost-effectiveness of particular investigations into certain conditions. The need for subsequent follow-up in patients should not be considered as a limitation of the approach since it does not affect its decision-making ability. Moreover, follow-up can take the same form as it would with traditional consultations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Caballero Gu&amp;#776;eto, Julia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montijano Cabrera, Ángela M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El modelo de consulta de alta resolución está en expansión. La cardiología es una de las especialidades que más se beneficia de ella. El sistema está avalado por indudables ventajas, en especial, la agilidad en la estrategia diagnóstico-terapéutica. Sin embargo, no debe considerarse un modo exclusivo de asistencia especializada. Puede y debe coexistir con la asistencia tradicional, pues ciertas exploraciones no son subsidiarias de alta resolución. Además, pueden surgir limitaciones en la implementación del modelo y/o en sus resultados, debido a la escasez de recursos, a una inadecuada organización de éstos, o a la reducida rentabilidad de determinadas exploraciones en enfermedades concretas. No se puede considerar una limitación la necesidad de seguimiento posterior de los pacientes, ya que éste nada tiene que ver con la capacidad resolutiva del modelo y se realiza de forma similar a las consultas tradicionales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);7(supl.C): 30c-36c, 2007. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166212</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La consulta de acto único en cardiología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11653^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11799^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11799^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2353^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11653^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2353^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11653^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
