<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142535</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Outcomes of a general hospital-based Home Parenteral Nutrition (HPN) program; report of our experience from a 26-year period</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Home parenteral nutrition (HPN) was introduced in Spain in the late 1980s. Our hospital was a pioneering medical centre in this field. Aim: Analyze outcomes of our HPN program. Methods: Retrospective study of patients receiving HPN between 1986-2012. Study variables are expressed as frequency, mean ± SD (range), median [interquartile range]. Parametrics, non-parametrics test and survival analysis (p &lt; 0.05) were applied. Results: 91 patients (55 females and 36 males, mean age: 50.6 ± 5 yrs.) who received HPN for an accrual period of 55,470 days (median: 211 days [range: 63-573]) were included. The most prevalent underlying condition was cancer (49.5%), with the commonest HPN indication being short bowel syndrome (41.1%). The most frequently used catheter type was the tunneled catheter (70.7%). The complication rate was 3.58/1,000 HPN days (2.68, infection; 0.07, occlusion; 0.07 thrombosis; and 0.59, metabolic complications). Complications were consistently associated with both the underlying condition and HPN length. Infections were most frequent within the first 1,000 days of HPN. Liver disease incidence was related to HPN duration. HPN could be discontinued in 42.3% of patients. Ten-year survival rate was 42%, and varied across the underlying conditions. Conclusions: In the present series, the commonest reason for HPN was cancer. Our complication rate is in keeping with that reported in the literature. The overall survival rate was 42%, and varied across the underlying conditions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garcia-Peris, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frias, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuerda, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bretón, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camblor, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velasco, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Higuera, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La nutrición parenteral domiciliaria (NPD) se introdujo en España a finales de 1980. Nuestro hospital fue pionero en este campo. Objetivo: Analizar los resultados de nuestro programa de NPD. Métodos: Estudio retrospectivo de los pacientes que recibieron NPD entre 1986-2012. Las variables se expresan como frecuencias, media ± DE (rango), mediana [intervalo intercuartílico]. Se aplicaron pruebas paramé- tricas, no paramétricas y análisis de la supervivencia (p &lt; 0,05). Resultados: 91 pacientes (55 mujeres, edad media: 50,6 ± 5 años). La duración total del tratamiento con NPD fue de 55.470 días (mediana: 211 días [rango: 63-573]). El diagnóstico principal y la indicación de NPD más frecuentes fueron el cáncer (49,5%) y el síndrome del intestino corto (41,1%). El tipo de catéter más utilizado fue el tunelizado (70,7%). La tasa de complicaciones totales fue de 3,58/1.000 días HPN (2,68 para infecciones; 0,07, oclusiones; 0,07 trombosis, y 0,59, complicaciones metabólicas) y se asoció al diagnóstico principal y la duración de la NPD. Las infecciones fueron más frecuentes en los primeros 1.000 días de NPD. La incidencia de hepatopatía se relacionó con la duración de este tratamiento. En el 42,3% de los pacientes se pudo suspender la NPD. La tasa de supervivencia global a los diez años fue del 42% con diferencias entre los diagnósticos principales. Conclusiones: En nuestra serie, la razón más común para la NPD fue el cáncer. Nuestra tasa de complicaciones esta acorde con la literatura. La tasa de supervivencia global fue del 42% (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;30(2): 359-365, ago. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142535</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados del programa de nutrición parenteral domiciliaria (NPD) de un hospital general; análisis de 26 años de actividad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5661^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30401^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30376^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
