<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98051</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Myelodysplastic syndrome in the elderly: comprehensive geriatric assessment and therapeutic recommendations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The onset of myelodysplastic syndromes (MDS) is usually around the age of 70. Despite this, most clinical trials are restricted to younger subjects. Thus, the management of elderly patients with MDS is not always optimal. Physiologically, elderly patients show characteristics that differ from those of younger patients and that condition their pharmacological treatment. In this regard, the comprehensive geriatric assessment (CGA) becomes particularly important. This document gathers conclusions from the 1st Meeting of Members of the Sociedad Española de Medicina Geriátrica and the Sociedad Española de Hematología y Hemoterapia, with the objective of proposing the establishment of CGA instruments to assist in the decision-making process of elderly patients with MDS. The results of this consensus document will focus on the diagnosis, prognosis, treatment and management of adverse events in this age group (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>De Paz, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Altés, Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>del Cañizo, Consuelo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Arrieta, Jesús María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La edad de presentación de los síndromes mielodisplásicos (SMD) suele ser alrededor de los 70 años. A pesar de esto, la mayor parte de los ensayos clínicos se restringen a sujetos más jóvenes, con lo cual el tratamiento de los pacientes mayores con SMD no siempre es el mejor. El paciente mayor presenta características fisiológicas que lo diferencian del adulto, y esto condiciona el tratamiento farmacológico. En este sentido, la valoración geriátrica integral (VGI) cobra especial importancia. Este artículo recoge las conclusiones de la I Reunión de Especialistas de la Sociedad Española de Medicina Geriátrica y de la Sociedad Española de Hematología y Hemoterapia, y propone la implantación de instrumentos de la VGI que ayuden en el proceso de toma de decisiones del paciente mayor con SMD. Los resultados se centrarán en el diagnóstico, pronóstico, tratamiento y manejo de los efectos adversos en este grupo de pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);138(3): 119-119, feb. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98051</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome mielodisplásico en el paciente mayor: valoración geriátrica integral y recomendaciones terapéuticas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19006^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d974^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29199</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24693^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
