<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123853</identifier>
<setSpec>2174-5544</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Amniocentesis: A practice guideline</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Amniocentesis, initially described by Steele and Borg in 1966, is an invasive prenatal diagnostic procedure used in the second trimester. It consists of inserting an ultrasound-guided spinal needle through the abdominal and uterine wall and into the amniotic cavity in order that a sample of the amniotic fluid that surrounds the foetus, and contains cells of foetal origin, can be aspirated. Amniocentesis is performed after 16 weeks gestation, so that chromosomal, biochemical, molecular, or microbiological studies can be performed on the amniotic fluid. The procedure carries a risk of foetal loss in approximately 0.5% when it is performed in the second trimester after the fusion of the amniotic and chorionic membrane, as well as lesser risk of other complications such as, loss of amniotic fluid (0.3%), placental haemorrhage, intra-amniotic infection, abdominal wall haematoma, or foetal injury. As international experience accumulates, more factors that can help to improve the safety and ease of the procedural technique are being determined. We have described a new aspiration method to perform amniocentesis that uses a Vacutainer® (BD Vacutainer Systems, Plymouth, United Kingdom), to obtain a continuous vacuum when the needle is already inserted in the amniotic cavity, in contrast to the standard aspiration technique using a syringe or suction pistol where the negative pressures are discontinuous. However, the classic technique with continuous syringe aspiration continues being valid and the most used. Based on 30 years experience, and on the volume of procedures performed in our centre (more than 20,000 invasive procedures), together with an up to date literature review, we have established an updated practice guideline for performing amniocentesis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bennasar, Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Goncé, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parra-Saavedra, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, Josep M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz-Lemini, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borobio, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borrell, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La amniocentesis es un procedimiento de diagnóstico prenatal invasivo de segundo trimestre, descrito inicialmente en 1966 por Steele y Berg. Consiste en la introducción de una aguja espinal a través de la pared abdominal, la pared uterina y la cavidad amniótica bajo guía ecográfica continua, de forma que se pueda aspirar una muestra del líquido amniótico que envuelve el feto y que contiene células de origen fetal. La amniocentesis se realiza a partir de las 16 semanas de gestación y en el líquido amniótico se pueden realizar estudios cromosómicos, bioquímicos, moleculares o microbiológicos. El procedimiento conlleva un riesgo de pérdida fetal de aproximadamente el 0,5% cuando se realiza en el segundo trimestre, después de la fusión de la membrana amniótica con el corion, además de un riesgo menor de otras complicaciones, como la pérdida de líquido amniótico (0,3%), hemorragia placentaria, infección intraamniótica, hematoma de la pared abdominal o traumatismo fetal. A medida que la experiencia internacional se acumula, se van determinando los factores que pueden ayudar a mejorar aún más la seguridad y la facilidad técnica del procedimiento. Hemos descrito un nuevo método de aspiración para realizar la amniocentesis que emplea un Vacutainer® (BD Vacutainer Systems, Plymouth, Reino Unido), para obtener un vacío continuo cuando la aguja ya está insertada dentro de la cavidad amniótica, en contraste con la técnica estándar de aspiración mediante jeringa o «pistola» en que las presiones negativas son discontinuas. Sin embargo, la técnica clásica con aspiración con jeringa continua siendo válida y la más utilizada. Basados en la experiencia de 30 años y en el volumen de procedimientos realizados en nuestro centro (más de 20.000 procedimientos invasivos realizados), junto con una revisión de la bibliografía publicada hasta la fecha, hemos planteado una guía práctica actualizada para la realización de la amniocentesis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Diagn. prenat. (Internet);25(1): 20-27, ene.-jun. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123853</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Amniocentesis: guía práctica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d793</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d664^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28087^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
