<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101040</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mirror neurons and theory of mind in explaining empathy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Empathy is a person´s ability to experiment other people´s thoughts and feelings and to react to them in an adequate manner. There are two different components within the concept of empathy: cognitive and emotional. The former implies the ability to understand thoughts and feelings of another person; the latter allows the individual to share the mental state of another person responding to his/her demands. We comment here on two theories that explain empathy: the mirror neurons and the Theory of Mind. Mirror neurons are a particular type of neurons which are activated when an individual performs an action, but also when he/she observes a similar action performed by someone else. For theory of mind, to attribute mind to another person is a theoretical activity because we cannot what he/(she is thinking about or feeling, and, in this way, we interpret his/her behavior. We deduce a genetic continuity between both theories in a different explanatory level: mirror neurons at a neuronal level (basic neuroscience) and theory of mind at a cognitive level. Implications of both theories in the explanation of autism are discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Marqués, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maestú Unturbe, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García García, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La empatía es la capacidad de una persona para vivenciar los pensamientos y sentimientos de los otros, reaccionado adecuadamente. Diferenciamos en la empatía dos componentes; cognitivo y emocional. El componente cognitivo comprende los pensamientos y sentimientos del otro. El componente afectivo comparte el estado emocional de otra persona. Comentamos dos teorías para explicar la empatía: las neuronas espejo y la teoría de la mente. Las neuronas espejo son un tipo particular de neuronas que se activan cuando un individuo realiza una acción, pero también cuando él observa una acción similar realizada por otro individuo Para la teoría de la mente atribuir mente a otro es una actividad pero generamos hipótesis sobre lo que está pensando o sintiendo e interpretamos así su comportamiento. Argumentamos una continuidad genética entre ambas teorías, que se sitúan a nivel explicativo distinto: las neuronas espejo a nivel explicativo distinto: las neuronas espejo a nivel neuronal (neurociencia básica) y la teoría de la mente en el nivel cognitivo. Mostramos implicaciones de ambas teorías en la comprensión del autismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;17(2/3): 265-279, dic. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101040</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neuronas espejo y teoría de la mente en la explicación de la empatía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53745</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54420^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4721</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
