<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-62182</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-2399</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gender differences in the hospitalization and reperfusion delays in the acute coronary syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To study delay times in women with acute coronary syndrome (ACS) and STsegment elevation (STSEACS) until administration of possible reperfusion therapy as wellas its possible differences in relationship to the men.Material and methods. A study was conducted in 1,849 patients consecutively hospitalizedin a Coronary Unit from January 2000 to December 2005 who had been diagnosed of ACS.Different delay times were studied from the beginning of the symptoms, comparing thembetween genders and correcting this by variable age.Results. The percentage of women was 24.4% with a mean age of 71.5 years. Mediumdelay time from the beginning of the symptoms to contact with the first health careagent was significantly (p &lt; 0.001), longer for women than for men, 164 min. vs 120 min.Reperfusion treatments were used in 57.6% of the subjects, with a significant difference(p &lt; 0.01) of 7.6% between men (59.5%) and women (51.9%).Conclusions. Delay times are greater in women than men, above all regarding thebeginning of the symptoms until arrival to the first health care agent.Currently, reperfusion treatments are performed more in men than in women, thedifferences are minimum when adjusted by age(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alconero Camarero, A. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San José Garagarza, J, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Cacho, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cobo Sánchez, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Estudiar los tiempos de retraso hasta una eventual terapéutica de reperfusiónen las mujeres con síndrome coronario agudo (SCA) y elevación del segmento ST, así comolas posibles diferencias en relación con los varones.Material y métodos. Se ha llevado a cabo un estudio con 1.849 pacientes con diagnósticode SCA ingresados consecutivamente en una Unidad Coronaria, desde enero de 2000 a diciembrede 2005. Se estudian diversos tiempos de retraso desde el inicio de los síntomas,se comparan entre sexos y se corrigen por la variable edad.Resultados. Fueron mujeres el 24,4%, con una media de edad de 71,5 años. La medianaen el tiempo de retraso desde el inicio de los síntomas hasta el contacto con el primerescalón sanitario fue significativamente (p &lt; 0,001) más prolongada en las mujeres queen los hombres, 164 minutos frente a 120 minutos. Los tratamientos de reperfusión seemplearon en el 57,6% de los sujetos, con una diferencia significativa (p &lt; 0,01) del 7,6%entre hombres (59,5%) y mujeres (51,9%).Conclusiones. Los tiempos de retraso son mayores en las mujeres que en los hombres,sobre todo desde el inicio de los síntomas hasta la llegada al primer escalón sanitario.Los tratamientos de reperfusión se realizan más en hombres que en mujeres, aunque,ajustando por edad, las diferencias son mínimas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Intensiva;20(2): 44-49, abr.-jun. 2009. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-62182</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias de género en los retrasos de ingreso y reperfusión en el síndrome coronario agudo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23771^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5932^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
