<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041701</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Laparoscopic appendicectomy and pregnancy. Personal experience and review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Pregnancy has been considered to be an absolute contraindication to the laparoscopic approach because of the theoretical effects of the pneumoperitoneum on the fetus and the occupation of the working space by the gravid uterus. Despite the growing literature on the subject, experience with frequent entities, such as acute appendicitis, is limited. Objective. The aim of this study was to report our experience with laparoscopic appendicectomy in pregnancy, to review the scientific evidence available on the safety of this procedure, and to establish the most relevant practical features for the use of this approach during pregnancy. Material and methods. We retrospectively reviewed six laparoscopic appendectomies performed in pregnant women. We also reviewed the available literature on well documented laparoscopic appendectomies during pregnancy.Results. All the procedures were laparoscopically completed. The mean operating time was 46 min. All patients were discharged within the first 48 postoperative hours. There were no surgical complications. All patients delivered healthy infants with appropriate weight for gestational age. For the literature review, 17 references were collected that included data on 94 laparoscopic appendectomies performed in pregnant women. There was only one fetal death associated with the surgical approach and the overall fetal mortality rate was less than that classically registered in the literature for the open approach. Conclusions. Laparoscopic appendectomy in pregnant women is as safe and effective as the open approach and confers all the benefits of minimally invasive surgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Sanz, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corral-Sánchez, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual-Pedreño, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Picazo-Yeste, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seoane-González, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcello-Fernández, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los efectos del neumoperitoneo sobre el feto y la ocupación del espacio de trabajo por el útero grávido han hecho que el embarazo se haya considerado una contraindicación para la cirugía laparoscópica. A pesar de la progresiva aparición de bibliografía al respecto, llama la atención la limitada experiencia con enfermedades frecuentes, como es el caso de la apendicitis aguda. Objetivo. El objetivo de este trabajo es aportar nuestra experiencia con la apendicectomía laparoscópica durante el embarazo, revisar la evidencia científica disponible sobre su seguridad y establecer los aspectos prácticos más relevantes para el uso de este tipo de abordaje en la mujer gestante. Material y métodos. Revisamos retrospectivamente 6 casos de apendicectomía laparoscópica realizada en pacientes gestantes. Además, revisamos la literatura disponible en la que se recogen casos, bien documentados, de apendicectomía laparoscópica en este tipo de paciente. Resultados. Todos los procedimientos se completaron por vía laparoscópica. El tiempo medio de cirugía fue de 46 min. Todas las pacientes recibieron el alta hospitalaria dentro de las primeras 48 h postoperatorias sin que se registraran complicaciones quirúrgicas. Los recién nacidos presentaron un peso adecuado para su edad gestacional y los parámetros de bienestar fetal fueron satisfactorios al nacimiento. Con respecto a la bibliografía revisada, se han seleccionado 17 publicaciones que recogen datos de 94 apendicectomías laparoscópicas realizadas en pacientes gestantes. Sólo se registró un caso de muerte fetal en relación con la vía de abordaje y la tasa de mortalidad fetal no superó a la obtenida, clásicamente, con el abordaje tradicional. Conclusiones. La apendicectomía laparoscópica en la paciente gestante es una técnica tan eficaz y segura como la vía abierta y aporta todos los beneficios de la cirugía mínimamente invasiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);78(6): 371-376, dic. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041701</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Apendicectomía laparoscópica y embarazo. Experiencia personal y revisión de la bibliografía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28105</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1068^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1070^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11457^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1070^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11457^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13886^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
