<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040399</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Incidence of infectious spondylitis in the province of Albacete (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Infectious spondylitis (IS) is an infrequent disease, although there are few data on its real incidence. To date, only one study, carried out in Denmark, that rigorously assesses the incidence of this disease has been published. Objectives. To determine the incidence of IS in the nonpediatric population of the province of Albacete, and to analyze differences according to etiology, age, sex, and geographical area. Methods. We carried out a retrospective search of all the IS cases diagnosed in the province of Albacete during the period 1990-2002 and calculated the adjusted incidence rates using census data.Results. The incidence of IS was 2.40 cases/10 5 inhabitants/year. Brucellar spondylitis had an incidence of 1.18 cases/10 5 inhabitants/year, with a predominance in the rural area and in men. Distribution by age was bimodal, with a first peak around 40 years old and a second peak around 60 years old. The incidence has significantly decreased in the last few years. Pyogenic spondylitis (incidence of 0.64 cases/10 5 inhabitants/year) showed a maximum incidence at around 60 years old, while its distribution by sex and geographical area was more uniform. Tuberculous spondylitis had an incidence of 0.45 cases/10 5 inhabitants/year and its frequency increased with age. Conclusion. The incidence rates of IS were higher than those reported in most previous studies, although they were similar to those observed in the most rigorous reports. These findings suggest that the frequency of IS could have been underestimated. The three etiologic groups analyzed showed distinct epidemiological profiles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Segura-Luque, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Alfaro, Elisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solera-Santos, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lizán-García, Máxima</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vives-Soto, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solís-García del Pozo, Julián</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. La espondilitis infecciosa es una enfermedad infrecuente, aunque existen pocos datos sobre su incidencia real. Hasta la fecha, sólo se ha publicado un estudio, realizado en Dinamarca, que valora de forma rigurosa su incidencia. Objetivos. Conocer la incidencia de espondilitis infecciosa en la población no pediátrica de la provincia de Albacete, así como el comportamiento por etiologías, grupos de edad y sexo y zonas geográficas. Métodos. Búsqueda retrospectiva de todos los casos diagnosticados de espondilitis infecciosa en la provincia de Albacete durante el período 1990-2002, calculando las tasas de incidencia ajustadas, a partir de los datos censales. Resultados. La incidencia de espondilitis infecciosa fue de 2,40 casos/10 5 habitantes/año. La incidencia de la espondilitis infecciosa brucelar fue 1,18 casos/10 5 habitantes/año, con predominio en la zona rural y en varones y con una distribución por edad bimodal (con un primer pico de incidencia alrededor de los 40 años y un segundo a los 60 años). Su incidencia se ha reducido de forma importante en los últimos años. La espondilitis infecciosa piógena (incidencia de 0,64 casos/10 5 habitantes/año) mostró un pico de incidencia alrededor de los 60 años y un comportamiento por sexo y por zonas geográficas mucho más uniforme. La espondilitis infecciosa tuberculosa tuvo una incidencia de 0,45 casos/10 5 habitantes/año y su frecuencia aumentó con la edad. Conclusión. Se obtuvieron tasas de incidencia superiores a la mayoría de los estudios previos y sólo comparables a los estudios más rigurosos, lo que sugiere que la incidencia de espondilitis infecciosa puede haber sido subestimada. Los tres grupos etiológicos del estudio mostraron un comportamiento epidemiológico distinto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;23(9): 545-550, nov. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040399</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incidencia de la espondilitis infecciosa en la provincia de Albacete</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10199^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13550^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13550^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23612^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2030^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10199^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
