<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-28227</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The laminopahy saga</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims. Our aim was to clinically characterise Emery-Dreifuss muscular dystrophy, to differentiate the X-linked forms of inheritance from the forms involving autosomal dominant inheritance, from a genetic point of view, and to describe the phenotypical heterogeneity of mutations in the LMNA gene itself. Development. We describe the identification of the mutations in the lamina A/C gene, the LMNA gene, which was made possible thanks to the networks allowing workers in different countries to collaborate. Mutations in this gene are responsible for autosomal dominant Emery-Dreifuss disease, as well as other diseases that are phenotypically very distinct, such as limb girdle muscular dystrophy associated with cardiac conduction defects (LGMD1B), dilated myocardiopathy with conduction defects (DCM-CD), Dunnigan-type familial partial lipodystrophy (FPLD) and, finally, an autosomal recessive form of axonal neuropathy or Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 2 (AR-CMT). Conclusions. Laminas are intermediate filaments that constitute the inner nuclear membrane of any cell and the mutations in the lamina A/C gene can give rise to such distinct clinical patterns as a kind of muscular dystrophy that is similar to the well-known X-linked EmeryDreifuss disease or a form of Charcot-Marie-Tooth-type neuropathy. Work is currently being conducted on an experimental animal model capable of providing us with a better understanding of the physiopathological mechanisms involved in the production of these tissue-specific diseases, although they are due to mutations in a gene that codifies for proteins that are expressed all over (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Caracterizar clínicamente la distrofia muscular de Emery-Dreifuss, diferenciar las formas de herencia ligadas al cromosoma X de las formas de herencia autosómica dominante desde el punto de vista genético, y describir la heterogeneidad fenotípica en mutaciones del mismo gen LMNA. Desarrollo. Se describe la identificación de las mutaciones en el gen de la lamina A/C, gen LMNA, gracias a las redes de trabajo colaborativo entre diferentes países. Las mutaciones en este gen son responsables de la enfermedad de Emery-Dreifuss autosómica dominante, además de otras enfermedades fenotípicamente muy diferentes, como la distrofia muscular de cinturas asociada a defectos de conducción cardíaca (LGMD1B), la miocardiopatía dilatada con defectos de conducción (DCM-CD), la lipodistrofia familiar parcial de tipo Dunningan (FPLD) y, finalmente, una forma autosómica recesiva de neuropatía axonal o enfermedad de Charcot-Marie-Tooth tipo 2 (AR-CMT). Conclusiones. Las laminas son filamentos intermedios que forman parte de la cubierta interna nuclear de cualquier célula, y las mutaciones en el gen de las laminas A/C pueden producir cuadros clínicos tan diferentes como una distrofia muscular similar a la conocida enfermedad de Emery-Dreifuss ligada al cromosoma X y una forma de neuropatía tipo Charcot-Marie-Tooth. Actualmente, se trabaja sobre un modelo experimental animal para profundizar en los mecanismos fisiopatológicos que intervienen en la producción de estas enfermedades, específicas de tejido aunque se deben a mutaciones en un gen que codifica proteínas que se expresan de forma ubicua (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;37(8): 772-774, oct. 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La saga de las laminopatías</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Bonne, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-28227</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d34293</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9346</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10833</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34191</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37521</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
