<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166885</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pregnancy and Contraception</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Since today a substantial number of patients with congenital heart disease (CHD) will have reached adulthood, it is important that the question of contraception and the risks associated with pregnancy are discussed with young women with the disease. At the appropriate time (possibly at the start of adolescence), these young women should be offered preconception counseling to help them avoid preventable risks and plan their future. With this aim in mind and to ensure that the appropriate level of care is provided for mothers during pregnancy, delivery and the puerperium and for the fetus and newborn child, it is essential that a multidisciplinary team of cardiologists, obstetricians, gynecologists, anesthesiologists, neonatologists and experts in fetal medicine develop and implement consensual clinical practice guidelines (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Baró, Francesc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Goya, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Subirana, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casaldàliga, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pijuan, María Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la actualidad, un gran número de pacientes con cardiopatía congénita (CC) ha alcanzado la edad adulta, por lo que la problemática de la anticoncepción y los riesgos en caso de embarazo deberían abordarse en todas las jóvenes con estas enfermedades y ofrecerles, en el momento adecuado (posiblemente al inicio de la adolescencia), consejo preconcepcional con el objetivo de prevenir riesgos evitables y ayudarlas en la planificación de su futuro. Para ello, a la vez que para lograr un cuidado adecuado del embarazo, el feto, el parto y el posparto, es importante que un equipo multidisciplinario, constituido por cardiólogos, obstetras, ginecólogos, anestesiólogos, neonatólogos y expertos en medicina fetal, elabore y ponga en práctica unos protocolos de actuación consensuados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);9(supl.E): 48e-56e, 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166885</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gestación y anticoncepción</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5950^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3286^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22968</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32069</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6702^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11689^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50221</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200900</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
