<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160576</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-7823</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Although mindfulness is integrated in many positive psychology manuals as a «positive» technique, they have hardly developed the implications of their use or have investigated the relationship between mindfulness and human well-being. Analyze the main strengths of the two fields, the possibilities of integration and possible contradictions between their messages, is essential in order to establish bridges. Mindfulness is a meditation technique, implicit in a set of values and ethical conditions that largely conform to the proposed budgets from positive psychology, such as the development of kindness, compassion, and positive emotions. The aim of this paper is to present the one hand commonalities and similarities, and secondly differences between mindfulness and positive psychology. Major studies that have investigated the role that mindfulness and contemplative practices on human well-being will also be presented. Finally it will be discussed and future research arise and intervention to bring both proposals (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alvear, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Enrique, Angel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soler, Joaquim</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Campayo, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cebolla, Ausiàs</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A pesar de que mindfulness está integrado en muchos manuales de psicología positiva como una técnica «positiva», apenas se han desarrollado las implicaciones que tiene su uso ni se ha investigado la relación entre mindfulness y bienestar humano. Analizar las principales potencialidades de los dos ámbitos, las posibilidades de integración, así como las posibles contradicciones entre sus mensajes, es fundamental de cara a establecer puentes. Mindfulness es más que una técnica de meditación, lleva implícitos una serie de valores y condicionantes éticos que se adecuan en buena medida con los presupuestos que se proponen desde la psicología positiva, como el desarrollo de la amabilidad, la compasión, y las emociones positivas. El objetivo de este artículo es presentar por un lado aspectos comunes y similitudes, y por otro lado diferencias entre mindfulness y la psicología positiva. También se presentarán los principales estudios que han investigado el papel que tiene mindfulness y las prácticas contemplativas sobre el bienestar humano. Finalmente se discutirá y plantearán futuras líneas de investigación e intervención para acercar ambas propuestas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pap. psicol;38(1): 12-18, ene.-abr. 2017. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160576</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Psicología positiva contemplativa: integrando mindfulness en la psicología positiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32693^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12476</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55384^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6391</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29210</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
