<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046832</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Giant intertesticular epidermoid cyst</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: To report a rare case of a giant epidermoid cyst in an intertesticular localization, analyzing its histological and pathologic features, and to perform a bibliographic review.    METHODS/RESULTS: We report the case of a 49-year-old male consulting for a slowly growing intra-scrotal mass of five years of evolution causing discomfort because of its size. After excision the pathology report showed the    presence of a keratoid epidermoid cyst very big in size.    CONCLUSIONS: Superficial scrotal epidermoid cysts are frequent in clinical practice; that is not the case of the    so-called &#147;intra scrotal inclusion cysts&#148;. Epidermoid cysts are firm, mobile, slowly growing, generally asymptomatic intra epidermal neoformations. There are descriptions in multiple sites, even the genitalia, nevertheless their size in this location does not usually pass 5 cm</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Álvarez, Roberto C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Benito, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Robles, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jalón Monzón, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Gómez, Jesús M. </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Múgica, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Martín Blanco, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Regadera Sejas, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Añadir a la literatura un caso clínico poco frecuente de quiste epidermoide gigante de localización intertesticular, analizando las características histológicas y patológicas del mismo y realizando una revisión    de la literatura al respecto.    MÉTODOS/RESULTADOS: Presentamos el caso de un varón    de 49 años que consultó por bultoma intraescrotal de 5 años de evolución y lento crecimiento que le ocasionaba molestias por su gran tamaño. Tras exéresis del mismo, el resultado anatomopatológico de la muestra evidenció la presencia de un quiste epidermoide queratinoso de gran tamaño.    CONCLUSIONES: Los quistes epidérmicos escrotales superficiales    son de frecuente aparición en la práctica clínica, no así los denominados &#147;de inclusión&#148; intraescrotales. Los Quistes Epidermoides son neoformaciones intraepidérmicas,    firmes y móviles de crecimiento lento y habitualmente asintomáticos. Están descritos en múltiples localizaciones, incluso en genitales, sin embargo el tamaño de estos a este nivel no suele superar los 5 cm</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;59(3): 297-299, abr. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046832</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Quiste epidermoide gigante intertesticular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4895^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14112^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
