<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103698</identifier>
<setSpec>2174-5544</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Complications of monochorionic twin pregnancies: Key concepts for the diagnosis and management</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Monochorionic twin pregnancy (MC) occurs in one in 250 pregnancies and represents a significant proportion of perinatal morbidity and mortality in twin pregnancies, and in general. The optimal management of MC is based on two fundamental aspects: early classification of chorionicity and close monitoring. The differential diagnosis of the complications of MC is still a challenge to the fetal medicine specialist. This is due to the frequent overlap of clinical signs and the complex relationships between the potential complications. However, the differential diagnosis and subsequent decisions are based on relatively simple rules. While some cases can be really complicated, clinical experience shows that in most cases proper classification and management can be achieved through the consistent use of simple concepts. This review provides an overview that allows a comprehensive understanding of MC twin pregnancies, the typical complications and the key concepts that allow an appropriate differential diagnosis and specific management(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortiz, Javier Urbano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Eixarch, Elisenda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crispi, Fátima</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martinez, Josep Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gratacós, Eduard</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puerto, Bienvenido</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El embarazo gemelar monocorial (MC) se presenta en uno de cada 250 embarazos y representa una proporción significativa de morbi mortalidad perinatal en los embarazos gemelares y en general. El manejo óptimo de los MC se basa en 2 aspectos fundamentales: clasificación temprana de la corionicidad y seguimiento estricto. El diagnóstico diferencial de las complicaciones del MC sigue siendo todavía un reto para el especialista de medicina fetal. Esto se debe a la frecuente superposición de signos clínicos y a las relaciones complejas entre las potenciales complicaciones. La experiencia clínica demuestra que en la mayoría de los casos la clasificación y el manejo adecuado se pueden lograr mediante la aplicación sistemática de conceptos sencillos. Esta revisión proporciona una visión global que permite una compresión integral de los embarazos gemelares MC, sus posibles complicaciones y los conceptos claves que permiten un diagnóstico diferencial adecuado y un manejo específico(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Diagn. prenat. (Internet);23(3): 93-101, jul.-sept. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103698</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Complicaciones del embarazo gemelar monocorial: claves para el diagnóstico y tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29633</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52870^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32092^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54811^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5440^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5440^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32092^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
