<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044870</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparative analysis of the frequencies of diverse congenital birth defects and their time trends in 11 autonomous communities in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Knowledge of the frequency of the distinct congenital defects over time in the various Autonomous Communities in Spain is important, not only to quantify the scope of the problem and to plan the necessary resources, but also to have surveillance systems and analyze the impact of the diverse health interventions. The aim of this study was to analyze the comparative frequencies of 6 types of congenital defect in the 11 Autonomous Communities participating in the Epidemiological Network on Rare Disease Research (REpIER). Subjects and methods: We analyzed data from the Spanish Collaborative Study of Congenital Malformations (ECEMC) corresponding to the 11 Autonomous Communities participating in REpIER (Andalusia, Aragon, the Canary Islands, Cantabria, Castilla-La Mancha, Catalonia, the Autonomous Community of Madrid, the Autonomous Community of Valencia, Extremadura, La Rioja, and the Principality of Asturias) from 1980 to 2003. The ECEMC is a clinical-epidemiological research program on the causes of congenital defects, structured as a permanent registration system with a case-control design. The program is hospital-based. The defects studied were anencephaly, spina bifida, cleft lip with or without cleft palate, cleft palate only, limb reduction defects, and Down syndrome in infants born to mothers aged 34 years or older. To analyze the time trends in each Autonomous Community, the lineal trend test (chi-square with 1 degree of freedom) and chi-square with k-2 degrees of freedom to detect deviations from linearity were used. Results: The time trend of the frequencies was not the same for all the defects studied or for all the Autonomous Communities. The highest concordance between the 11 Autonomous Communities analyzed was observed in the decreasing secular trend for Down syndrome in infants born to mothers aged 34 years or older, which was statistically significant in 8 Autonomous Communities. The frequency of anencephaly significantly decreased in 6 Autonomous Communities, and in a further 2 no cases were registered. The frequency of spina bifida significantly decreased in 6 Autonomous Communities. The secular distribution of the frequencies of the other 3 types of malformations studied showed no significant trends in most of the regions. Conclusions: Since pregnancy terminations after prenatal detection of anomalies became legal in Spain, the frequency of prenatally diagnosable birth defects has clearly decreased. This decrease has not been equal in all the regions. Differences were found in the time the decreases began and in their intensity, which may reveal, among other factors, differences in health care</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Frías, María Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendioroz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Pinilla, Elvira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermejo, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: El conocimiento de la frecuencia de los distintos defectos congénitos a lo largo del tiempo y en las diferentes comunidades autónomas es importante, no sólo para cuantificar la magnitud del problema y planificar los recursos necesarios, sino para disponer de sistemas de vigilancia y analizar el impacto de las diversas actuaciones sanitarias. El objetivo de este trabajo ha sido analizar comparativamente en las 11 comunidades autónomas que participan en la REpIER (Red Epidemiológica de Investigación en Enfermedades Raras) las frecuencias de 6 tipos de defectos congénitos. Sujetos y métodos: Se han utilizado los datos del ECEMC (Estudio Colaborativo Español de Malformaciones Congénitas) correspondientes a las 11 autonomías que participan en la REpIER (Andalucía, Aragón, Canarias, Cantabria, Castilla-La Mancha, Cataluña, Comunidad de Madrid, Comunidad Valenciana, Extremadura, La Rioja y el Principado de Asturias), en el período 1980-2003. El ECEMC es un programa de investigación clínico-epidemiológico acerca de las causas de los defectos congénitos, estructurado como un sistema permanente de registro, con un diseño de tipo caso-control y de base hospitalaria. Los defectos estudiados han sido: anencefalia; espina bífida; labio leporino, con o sin fisura del paladar; sólo fisura del paladar; defectos por reducción de extremidades, y síndrome de Down en hijos de mujeres con más de 34 años. Para el análisis de la tendencia temporal en cada autonomía se ha utilizado la prueba de tendencia lineal (&amp;#967;2con 1 grado de libertad) y la &amp;#967;2 con k-2 grados de libertad para detectar desviaciones de la linealidad. Resultados: La distribución temporal de las frecuencias no es igual para todos los defectos estudiados ni en todas las comunidades. La mayor concordancia entre las 11 autonomías estudiadas se observa para la disminución secular del síndrome de Down en madres de más de 34 años, que es significativa en 8 comunidades. La anencefalia disminuye significativamente en 6 autonomías, y en otras 2 no se registró ningún caso. La espina bífida muestra descensos estadísticamente significativos en 6 circunscripciones autonómicas. La distribución secular de las frecuencias de los otros 3 tipos de malformaciones estudiadas no presenta tendencias significativas en la mayoría de las autonomías. Conclusiones: Desde que hay en España la posibilidad legal de realizar una interrupción voluntaria del embarazo tras la detección prenatal de anomalías, se observa un claro descenso de las frecuencias al nacimiento de los defectos para los que es posible el diagnóstico prenatal. Dicho descenso no ha sido igual en todas las comunidades, ni en lo que se refiere a su comienzo ni en cuanto a su intensidad, lo que puede estar poniendo de manifiesto, entre otros factores, diferencias en cuanto a la atención sanitaria</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);49(5): 221-237, mayo 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044870</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis comparativo de las frecuencias de ciertos defectos congénitos y su evolución secular en 11 comunidades autónomas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29127^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d770^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29353^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29441</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31341^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29352^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
