<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118097</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perinatal results in 492 breech presentation: cesarean section vs vaginal delivery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze the perinatal results in our hospital comparing vaginal delivery and cesarean section in breech presentation singleton pregnancies at term. Material and Methods: All live ante-partum singleton fetuses in breech presentation, at 37 to41+6 weeks and days who delivered between July 2006 and August 2010 were included in the study. We compared perinatal results between cesarean section and vaginal delivery Results: There were no differences in Apgar score at 5 minutes &lt; 7, pH umbilical cord &lt; 7,base de&amp;#64257;cits and lactate, neonatal intensive care unit admission or perinatal mortality Conclusions: With appropriate maternal and fetal conditions and a quali&amp;#64257;ed medical team, a breech vaginal delivery could be propose obtaining good perinatal outcomes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Savirón Cornudella, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejero Cabrejas, E. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castán Mateo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodriguez Solanilla, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campillos Maza, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Marcilla, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Royo Arilla, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar los resultados perinatales de nuestro hospital en fetos en presentación podálica en gestaciones únicas a término comparando partos vaginales y por cesárea. Material y métodos Se incluyen todos los fetos vivos anteparto en gestaciones únicas, en presentación de nalgas entre las semanas 37 a 41+ 6 días de gestación nacidos entre el 1 de julio de 2006 y el 1 de septiembre de 2010. Comparamos los resultados perinatales en función del parto por cesárea o vía vaginal. Resultados No se objetivaron diferencias en cuanto a la puntuación en el test de Apgar a los 5 min &lt; 7, pH de cordón al nacimiento &lt; 7, déficit de bases y ácido láctico, ingreso en UCI neonatal, ni en las muertes perinatales. Conclusiones Cuando se cumplen los criterios materno-fetales adecuados y se dispone de personal médico cualificado, puede ser correcto plantear un parto de nalgas vía vaginal, obteniéndose buenos resultados perinatales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);41(1): 17-22, ene.-mar. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118097</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados perinatales en 492 presentaciones podálicas: cesárea vs. parto vaginal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1971^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22968^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3708^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7922</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2625^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52135^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1040</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
