<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049836</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The secrecy of hazardous drinking</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this instante, hazardous drinking jeans alcohol consumption, which exceeds a certain threshold value. Clinical history is considered an insufficient diagnostic procedure, because patients tend to underestimate their drinking. The challenge is to find effective methods to detect hazardous drinking but also in establishig a reliable golden standard when developing these methods. For research purposes, a time-line follow back is the best available option. For clinical purposes, less time-consuming methods are needed and a verbal interview is preferred above structured questionnaires and biochemical markers. Thus, there is urgent need to have evidence of the effectiveness of short face-to-face interviews in a confidential atmosphere. In future, new technologies and event-level methodology may serve as aids both for research and clinical purposes to reveal the secret of hazardous drinking</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Seppä, Kaija</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La ingesta peligros de bebidas se refiere, en este caso, al consumo de alcohol que excede de un determinado umbral. La historia clínica se considera un procedimiento de diagnóstico insuficiente porque los pacientes tienden a subestimar lo que beben. El reto radica en encontrar métodos efectivos para detectar el consumo peligroso de bebidas, pero también en establecer un patrón fiable a la hora de desarrollar estos métodos. El seguimiento temporal es la mejor opción con fines clínicos, se necesitan métodos que requieran menos tiempo y se prefieren las entrevistas verbales a los cuestionarios estructurados y los marcadores bioquímicos. Y así, existe la urgent necesidad de hacerse con pruebas sobre la efectividad de las entrevistas breves cara a cara en un ambiente de confianza. En el futuro, las nuevas tecnologías y la metodología que sigue el nivel de los hechos pueden servir para revelar el secreto del consumo peligroso de bebidas con fines investigadores y clínicos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);18(2): 105-110, abr. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049836</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El secreto del consumo peligroso de bebidas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29633</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d438^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d438^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d438^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1652^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d438^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1652^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
