<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131626</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of assisted training with neurofeedback on EEG measures, executive function and mood in a healthy sample</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The training in neurofeedback (NF) consists of teaching individuals to modify, adjust and enhance their brain activity pattern. The aim of our research was to evaluate the effect of training on cognitive processes, specifically executive function, and mood in a non-clinical sample. A sample of30 female college students were assigned to three groups: HD: right hemisphere(n = 10), HI: left hemisphere (n = 10) and control (n = 10). The dominance pattern of beta and the inhibition of the theta pattern were trained in a single session. Measures of executive function (Iowa GamblingTest) and questionnaires of mood were taken pre and post training. We found that NF training produced significant positive changes in executive performance in the HD group. In the EEG a tendency to improve beta rhythm after the training emerged too. Additionally, significant correlations were found between executive performance and negative mood in relation to theta frequency band. We conclude that the protocol seems effective to enhance some aspects of executive function as well as to decrease theta power improves the negative mood (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vasquez, Milena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garijo, Evelio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aliño, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvador, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gadea, Marien</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El entrenamiento en neurofeedback (NF) consiste en enseñar a los individuos a modificar, regular y potenciar su patrón de actividad cerebral. El objetivo de nuestra investigación fue evaluar el efecto del entrenamiento sobre los procesos cognitivos de función ejecutiva y sobre el afecto en una muestra de población normal. Se seleccionó una muestra de 30 mujeres estudiantes universitarias, asignadas a tres grupos: HD: hemisferio derecho (n=10), HI: hemisferio izquierdo (n=10) y control (n=10). Se entrenó durante una sola sesión el predominio del patrón beta y la inhibición del patrón theta y se realizó una evaluación pre y post-entrenamiento de la función ejecutiva (Iowa Gambling Test) y del afecto (cuestionarios PANAS y POMS). Se encontró que el entrenamiento en NF produjo cambios positivos significativos en el rendimiento ejecutivo en el grupo HD. En relación con el EEG, se encontró una tendencia al cambio tras el entrenamiento de ondas beta. Se encontraron correlaciones entre el rendimiento ejecutivo y el afecto negativo, y la banda de frecuencia theta. Se concluye que el protocolo resulta efectivo para potenciar aspectos de la función ejecutiva y que la disminución de ondas theta favorece la disminución del afecto negativo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;31(1): 317-323, ene. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131626</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos del entrenamiento asistido con neurofeedback sobre el EEG, los procesos de función ejecutiva y el estado de ánimo en una muestra de población normal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4641^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1642^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14203^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53744^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54210</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
