<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101668</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Study of a population-wide epidemic outbreak of mumps virus G1 in Jerez de la Frontera (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectivesTo characterize the mumps outbreak, assess the effectiveness of vaccines and discuss prevention and control measures.DesignObservational cross-sectional study of cases by person, place, and time.LocationCity Jerez de la Frontera and 8 Primary Care centres.ParticipantsA total of 116 cases of mumps were reported throughout seven months, with the last case in June 2008.MeasurementsMain outcomes: age, sex, place of study or work, symptoms start date, clinical description, complications, and genotype of virus isolation, history and vaccination compositions. Calculation of total vaccine effectiveness. Active case finding and contact studies were performed on the families, work places and leisure areas.ResultsThe mean age of the cases was 16.24 years(SD 10.6). The majority (68.96%) of the cases were children at school and 31.03% arose from family and work areas. Mumps vaccine coverage rates were above 90%. The complete vaccine effectiveness (2 doses); for those under 20 years-old it was: 99.84% (95% CI=99.77 - 99.89), being lower in schools with the highest attack rate, immunised with current vaccine from Jeryl Lynn strain: 71.01% (95% CI=55.85 80.97). Two doses of this strain were used in 13.79% of the cases. Susceptible populations were vaccinated at the start of the outbreak: 11,381 doses used in schools and 93 outside schools.ConclusionsAn outbreak of mumps virus G 1 population with high rates of mumps vaccine coverage, with areas with low vaccine effectiveness with current vaccine. Mass vaccination of population has contributed to the resolution of the outbreak(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peña González, Pascasio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Serna, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almenara Barrios, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivosCaracterizar el brote epidémico, evaluar la efectividad vacunal y analizar las medidas de prevención y control.DiseñoEstudio observacional transversal de casos según persona, lugar, tiempo.Emplazamiento: Ciudad Jerez de la Frontera y 8 centros de atención primaria.ParticipantesSe incluyen 116 casos de parotiditis notificados a lo largo de 7 meses, el último caso en junio de 2008.Mediciones principalesVariables principales: edad, sexo, centro de estudio o trabajo, fecha de inicio de los síntomas, descripción clínica, complicaciones, aislamiento y genotipo del virus, antecedentes y composición de las vacunas administradas. Cálculo de la efectividad vacunal total. Se ha realizado una búsqueda activa de casos y estudio de contactos en el medio familiar, laboral y ocio.ResultadosEdad media casos 16,24 años (DE: 10,6). El 68,96% de los casos han sido alumnos y el 31,03% procedían del medio familiar y laboral. Las tasas de coberturas de vacunación antiparotiditis fueron superiores al 90%. La efectividad vacunal completa (2 dosis), en menores de 20 años, ha sido: 99,84% (IC 95%=99,77-99,89), siendo menor en el centro docente con mayor tasa de ataque, inmunizados con la actual vacuna, procedente de cepa Jeryl Lynn: 71,01% (IC 95%=55,85-80,97). El 13,79% de los casos tienen 2 dosis de esta cepa. Iniciado el brote se procedió a vacunar a la población susceptible: 11.381 dosis en el medio docente y 93 en el medio extraescolar.ConclusionesBrote de parotiditis, por virus G1, en población con altas tasas de cobertura de vacuna antiparotiditis, con territorios con baja efectividad con la actual vacuna. La vacunación masiva poblacional ha contribuido a la resolución del brote(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;44(6): 320-327, jun. 2012. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101668</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de un brote epidémico de ámbito poblacional por el virus de la parotiditis G1 en JEREZ de la Frontera</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9298^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9298^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9300^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9300^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9300^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9298^s32386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28589^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9298^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9298^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9298^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
