<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055955</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sleep apnea-hypopnea syndrome. Concept, diagnosis and medical treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The sleep apnea-hypopnea syndrome (SAHS) is        characterised by daytime sleepiness, cardiorespiratory        and cognitive disorders, secondary to repeated        episodes of obstruction of the upper airway during        sleep. This disease is highly prevalent in the general        population and has damaging effects on the cardiovascular        system; it increases the incidence of traffic accidents        due to excessive somnolence, reduces the quality        of life and is associated with an excess of mortality.        It usually affects obese patients and the most important        symptoms are snoring and repeated respiratory        pauses. With each apnea and/or hypopnea there is a        fall in saturation that alters the nocturnal average and        ends up causing serious cardiovascular problems in        the medium to long term. The destructuring of the        architecture of sleep leads to daytime sleepiness that        can interfere in social and working life. Diagnosis is        carried out by means of polysomnography or respiratory        poligraphy, an abbreviated method that is valid        for 75% of cases. The most efficient medical treatment        is the application of positive pressure to the airway        (Continuous positive airway pressure - CPAP) that has        scarce and light secondary effects and is in general        well-tolerated. Once adapted, the patient must carry        out an adjustment of the pressure through polysomnography        and with the autoCPAP, which can vary pressure        until the respiratory events are corrected. Primary        care has an essential role to play in suspicion of the clinical        symptoms, the correct utilisation of the referral        criteria and the control of patients receiving treatment        once adapted</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cascante, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Eguía, V. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Síndrome de apneas-hipopneas del sueño        (SAHS) se caracteriza por somnolencia diurna excesiva,        trastornos cardiorrespiratorios y cognitivos, secundarios        a episodios repetidos de obstrucción de la vía        aérea superior durante el sueño. Esta enfermedad es        muy prevalente en la población general y tiene efectos        deletéreos sobre el sistema cardiovascular; aumenta la        incidencia de accidentes de tráfico a causa de la excesiva        somnolencia, deteriora la calidad de vida y se asocia        a un exceso de mortalidad. Suele afectar a pacientes        obesos y los síntomas más importantes son los        ronquidos y las pausas respiratorias repetidas. Cada        apnea y/o hipopnea condiciona una puntual caída en la        saturación que altera la media nocturna y termina ocasionando        serios problemas cardiovasculares a mediolargo        plazo. La desestructuración de la arquitectura del        sueño conduce a la excesiva somnolencia diurna capaz        de interferir en la vida socio-laboral. El diagnóstico se        realiza mediante polisomnografía o poligrafía respiratoria,        método abreviado válido para el 75% de casos. El        tratamiento médico más eficaz es la aplicación de presión        positiva en la vía aérea (CPAP) que tiene escasos        y leves efectos secundarios y es, en general, bien tolerado.        Una vez adaptado el paciente debe realizarse un        ajuste de la presión mediante polisomnografía o con        las autoCPAP, capaces de variar la presión hasta la        corrección de los eventos respiratorios. El papel de la        atención primaria es fundamental en la sospecha del        cuadro, la utilización correcta de los criterios de derivación        y el control de los pacientes en tratamiento una        vez adaptados</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;30(supl.1): 53-74, 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055955</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de apnea-hipopnea del sueño. Concepto, diagnóstico y tratamiento médico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34202^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38345^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34202^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30611^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34202^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7148^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
