<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82859</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Parents presence at the examination. How much do they know about their children's rights?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Personal freedom is an indisputable fundamental right that can only be limited by Law. However there are problems when there is uncertainty about that responsibility, disabled people or the elderly, for example. This may also include children and adolescents. In this latter case, the different legal standards seem to contradict when it comes to defining when a minor is considered an adult. This fact, corroborated by the daily experiences of a paediatrics clinic, has led to producing this article, in which an attempt is made to find out how much knowledge parents have of their children' rights as patients. Results from this preliminary study, show a high degree of parental ignorance on their children' rights to decide for themselves as regards their health (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castelló, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sebastiá, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La autonomía de las personas es un derecho fundamental indiscutible que tan solo puede verse limitado en las circunstancias que marque la ley. Sin embargo frecuentemente surgen problemas cuando existe incertidumbre sobre esa competencia. Cuando se trata con personas discapacitadas o ancianos, por ejemplo. También con niños y adolescentes. Sobre estos últimos, las diferentes normas legales parecen no ser capaces de determinar el momento en el que deben ser considerados como adultos. Este hecho, corroborado por junto con las experiencia del día a día de una la consulta de pediatría, nos ha conducido a elaborar el trabajo que sigue, en el que se pretende valorar el conocimiento de los padres sobre los derechos de sus hijos como pacientes. Los resultados de este estudio preliminar, muestran un alto grado de desconocimiento de los padres acerca de los derechos de sus hijos a decidir por sí mismos, en lo que respecta a su salud (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);36(10): 586-589, dic. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82859</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los padres a examen. ¿Cuál es su conocimento de los derechos de sus hijos?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2697^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35120</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10479^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10476^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1698</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37689^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2697^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
