<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-30898</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Electrophysiology of executive functions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. In neuropsychology, executive functions have been defined as those that coordinate the flow of information processing in the brain. In the last decade its study has undergone an important development, partly due to the use of functional neuroimaging. Development. Electrophysiological techniques have also provided a link between two specific components of the event related brain potential (ERP) and certain control and monitoring processes, as those described in theoretical frameworks of executive functioning (i.e., Norman &amp; Shallice). On the one hand, attentional set shifting paradigms allow us to relate the anteriorly (P3a; latency 300-350 ms) and posteriorly (P3b; latency 450-600 ms) distributed components of the so-called &#145;novelty P3&#146;, with a more general mechanism of attentional set shifting that could account for both stimulus and task novelty. On the other hand, &#145;error related negativity&#146; (ERN or En) has shown its sensitivity to action-monitoring (i.e., error detection and error correction processes), during the execution of response-selection RT tasks. Conclusions. The comprehension of these two executive processes represents critical aspects in our understanding of brain function, and has direct applications to the design of both theoretical models and assessment and rehabilitation programs for patients with dysexecutive disorders (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La Neuropsicología define las funciones ejecutivas cerebrales como aquellas que coordinan el procesamiento de la información en el cerebro. Su estudio ha experimentado un importante avance en la última década promovido por la utilización de las técnicas de neuroimagen funcional. Desarrollo. Las técnicas de medición electrofisiológica han permitido establecer una relación entre dos componentes específicos del potencial evocado (PE) cerebral y determinados procesos de control y monitorización descritos en modelos teóricos sobre funcionamiento ejecutivo, como el de Norman y Shallice. Por un lado, los aspectos anterior (P3a; latencia 300350 ms) y posterior (P3b; latencia 450-600 ms) del componente P3 a la novedad (del inglés, novelty P3), se han vinculado con un sistema genérico de cambio atencional ante las demandas novedosas del entorno y de la tarea, gracias al empleo de los paradigmas experimentales de cambio de set atencional. Por otro lado, el PE denominado negatividad relacionada con los errores (del inglés, error related negativity o ERN) se ha mostrado sensible a los procesos de monitorización de la conducta (p. ej., detección de errores y generación de acciones correctivas), durante la ejecución de tareas de selección de respuesta con tiempo de reacción. Conclusiones. La comprensión de estos dos subprocesos ejecutivos supone un elemento clave en el concepto del funcionamiento del cerebro con aplicaciones directas sobre la generación, tanto de modelos teóricos como de protocolos de evaluación y rehabilitación de pacientes con alteraciones disejecutivas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;38(4): 359-365, feb. 2004. graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Electrofisiología de las funciones ejecutivas</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Barceló, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-30898</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d9149</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5168</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3102</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8776</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13733</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4667</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2569</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28561</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
