<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160485</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Review of rehabilitation treatment for cervical dystonia: an update</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The aim of this study was to provide an update on rehabilitation treatment for cervical dystonia (CD), in terms of both its effectiveness and the strategies used. Study search and selection strategy. A total of 21 studies were identified by a search in electronic database for scientific articles published in English or Spanish from January 2000 to February 2016, with the keywords: cervical dystonia, treatment, rehabilitation, physiotherapy, and spasmodic torticollis. Inclusion criteria were: clinical trials of patients diagnosed with CD receiving rehabilitation treatment and with an adequate methodological quality according to the Jadad scale. Results and conclusions. Five studies were selected. In general, we recommend: relaxation exercises, stretching, motor re-education, balance, coordination and proprioception. The exercises should initially be supervised and, once learned, should be made in short and frequent self-rehabilitation sessions in order to induce neuroplasticity. It seems clear that the combination of a physiotherapeutic program and botulinum toxin treatment is beneficial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferrer, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juste, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calatayúd, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Farias, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iñigo, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morello, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El objetivo de este trabajo es realizar una actualización sobre el tratamiento rehabilitador de la distonía cervical (DC), tanto de su eficacia como de las estrategias utilizadas. Búsqueda y selección de estudios. Se identificaron 21 estudios mediante la búsqueda en bases de datos electrónicas de los artículos científicos publicados tanto en inglés como en castellano entre enero de 2000 y febrero de 2016, con las palabras clave: distonía cervical, tratamiento, rehabilitación, fisioterapia, tortícolis espasmódica. Los criterios de inclusión fueron: ensayos clínicos con pacientes diagnosticados de DC en tratamiento rehabilitador y con una calidad metodológica aceptable según la escala de Jadad. Resultados y conclusiones. Se han seleccionado 5 estudios. En líneas generales se aconseja: ejercicios de relajación, estiramientos, reeducación motora, equilibrio, coordinación y propiocepción. Los ejercicios deben ser inicialmente tutelados y una vez aprendidos deben realizarse en sesiones cortas y frecuentes de autorrehabilitación con el objetivo de inducir neuroplasticidad. Parece claro que la asociación de un programa fisioterápico al tratamiento con toxina botulínica es beneficioso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);51(1): 43-51, ene.-mar. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160485</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión del tratamiento rehabilitador en la distonía cervical: una puesta al día</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14493^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11866^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33528^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14493^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52426^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9316^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4648^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33081^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
