<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-63791</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The presence of pubic hair is exceptional in healthy infants of both sexes. In most of the cases described in the literature, the process was self-limited and no etiology was found. Nevertheless, in some patients, this finding has been associated with other manifestations of hyperandrogenism related to potentially serious diseases such as congenital adrenal hyperplasia or virilizing tumors. In the present article, we describe seven infants followed-up in the Pediatric Endocrine Clinic because of scrotal hair. In all patients, the process was self-limited and resolved spontaneously and no hormonal or developmental alterations were observed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quintanar Rioja, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sentchordi Montane, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayala Bernardo de Quirós, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Granero, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonet Serra, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La aparición de vello sexual es excepcional en los lactantes de ambos sexos. La mayoría de los casos descritos en la bibliografía constituyen procesos autolimitados, en los que su etiología no ha sido definida. Sin embargo, en algunos casos se ha asociado con otras manifestaciones de hiperandrogenismo relacionadas con procesos potencialmente graves como son la hiperplasia suprarrenal congénita y tumores productores de andrógenos. En el presente artículo se describe los casos de 7 lactantes varones que fueron vistos en la consulta de endocrinología pediátrica por vello escrotal. En todos ellos el proceso fue autolimitado, sin que se observaran alteraciones hormonales o en el desarrollo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);68(2): 146-148, feb. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-63791</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6350^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12992^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200802</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
