<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100418</identifier>
<setSpec>2013-6889</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pictorial creativity in fronto-temporal dementia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Some fronto-temporal dementia (FTD) patients may show remarkable preservation of their artistic creativity, and more often, in spite of the absence of an artistic background, others develop de novo artistic skills. Artistic creativity relies on complex mechanisms wich encompass the revelation of an ability and a need to produce, an incubation preiod, insight and artistic production per se. Copying skills and visuo-perceptive functions are largely preserved in FTD. As many of those who develop artistic creativity have unilateral anterior temporal dysfunction together with impaired language and social function, their creativity has been conceptualised as a'paradoxical facilitation', i.e., the release of right posterior neocortial areas, implicated in heteromodal and polysensory integration. However, although creativity stems as well from the confluence of several highly integrated functions such as working memory, sustained attention, planning, and cognitive flexibility, which are related to prefrontal functioning, its enhancement following prefrontal injury is puzzling. It may be explained by the role of hypofrontality in a type production which is more intuitive, less bound to cognitive, social and acedemic conventions. Prefrontal and language dysfunction may also explain the change in these patients'viewpoints but also in their behaviour, maked by an urge to produce combined with a contraction of their scope of interest in the accomplishment of their artistic work.(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sellal, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Thomas-Antérion, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Algunos pacientes con demencia frontotemporal (DFT) pueden presentar una notable conservación de su creatividad artística y, más a menudo, otros, en ausencia de antecedentes artísticos, desarrollan habilidades artísticas de novo. La creatividad artística se basa en mecanismos complejos que incluyen: el descubrimiento de la capacidad y necesidad de producir, el período de incubación, la percepción y la producción artística per se. La capacidad de copiar y las funciones visuoperceptivas están ampliamente conservadas en la DFT. Como muchos de los que desarrollan una creatividad artística tienen una difusión temporal anterior unilateral, junto con un deterioro del lenguaje y de las funciones sociales, su creatividad se ha conceptualizado como &lt;&gt;, es decir, la liberación del área posterior derecha del neocórtex implicada en la integración heteromodal y multisensorial. Sin embargo, aunque la creatividad se debe también a la confluencia de varias funciones altamente integradas, relacionadas con la funcionalidad prefrontal, tales como la memoria de trabajo, la atención mantenida, la planificación y la flexibilidad cognitiva, el incremento de dicha creatividad después de una lesión prefrontal resulta desconcertante. Esto puede ser explicado por el papel de la hipofrontalidad en un tipo de producción que es más intuitiva, menos ligada a las convenciones cognitivas, sociales y académicas. La difusión prefrontal y la del lenguaje podrían explicar el cambio en los puntos de vista de estos pacientes pero también en su conducta, marcada por una urgencia en producir, combinada con una reducción de las áreas de interés a la hora de realizar su trabajo. (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Alzheimer (Barc., Internet);(50): 13-19, ene.-abr. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100418</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Creatividad pictórica en demencia frontotemporal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53512^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1083^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3423</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8738</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53512^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8683</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1160</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
