<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045266</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Glucose levels in non-diabetic patients. Is it a prognostic factor in acute coronary syndrome?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The role of glucose elevation above levels considered normal in non- diabetic patients with acute coronary syndromes (ACS) is not adequately defined. The aim of this study was to determine the association between serum glucose at admission and 1-year mortality in this type of patients. Methods. We studied 648 non diabetic patients admitted consecutively with ACS. Serum glucose was determined at admission, together with classical risk factors, biochemical and inflammatory markers. The primary endpoint was all cause mortality at one year follow-up. Results. Patients with normal glucose had lower mortality than patients with impaired fasting glucose (14.1% vs 5.7% 1-year mortality) or with glucose levels in diabetic range (24.7% vs 5.7% 1-year mortality). Conclusions. In non-ST elevation acute coronary syndromes, elevated levels of glucose in non-diabetic patients are strong predictors of all cause death at one year follow-up. This prognostic value is independent of other risk factors biochemical and inflammatory markers</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fácila, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bellido, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bertomeu-González, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boda, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanchos, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yacer, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. No está bien definido el papel de la elevación de glucosa por encima de los valores considerados como normales en los pacientes no diabéticos con síndrome coronario agudo (SCA). El objetivo del presente estudio es analizar los efectos sobre el pronóstico a un año de los niveles de glucemia obtenidos durante el ingreso en este tipo de pacientes. Métodos. Estudiamos a 648 pacientes no diabéticos consecutivos con SCA, en los cuales se midieron los niveles de glucosa durante su estancia hospitalaria junto con los factores de riesgo clásicos, los marcadores bioquímicos e inflamatorios. El criterio de evaluación principal fue la muerte por todas las causas a un año. Resultados. Los pacientes con glucemia normal durante el ingreso presentaban un menor porcentaje de fallecimientos en el seguimiento que los que presentaban una glucosa basal alterada (14,1% frente a 5,7%), así como en rango de diabetes (24,7% frente a 5,7%). Conclusiones. Los niveles de glucosa obtenidos durante el ingreso en los pacientes no diabéticos con SCA sin elevación del ST son predictores de muerte, independientemente de factores bioquímicos, epidemiológicos clásicos e inflamatorios</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;206(6): 271-275, jun. 2006. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045266</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Niveles de glucemia en pacientes no diabéticos. ¿Es un factor pronóstico en el síndrome coronario agudo?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7124^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1812^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
