<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-AOT-2377</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4466</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Leptospirosis as a case study of the decline of social medicine in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper focuses on a particular case of the public health administration under Franco which shows its decay in the rural areas. Leptospirosis was fought specially in the rice fields, and I afford to evaluate its similarities and disimilarities to previous health campaigns brought about by the idea of Social Medicine. It became a public health hazard after the Civil War, due to its consequences on delicate moments of rice production such as the harvest, although no organised measures were taken until 1953. It was thanks to the first agreement on technical assistance signed with the WHO, that allowed the arrival of Brenno Babudieri, a world famous Italian microbiologist on the matter, who tested a vaccine in Spain. But public health initiatives regarding leptospirosis were laboratory centered, scattered and apparently dependent on the will of the provincial medical officer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Ocaña, Esteban</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Con el presente trabajo pretendo explorar el agotamiento de la Sanidad franquista en torno a un ejemplo concreto, el de la lucha contra la leptospirosis en el mundo rural, en especial en torno al cultivo del arroz, comprobando las semejanzas y diferencias de dicho empeño con el de otros anteriores surgidos de la matriz médico-social. Dicha enfermedad endemoepidémica rural fue singularizada como enemigo en la posguerra, por sus consecuencias sobre la producción en momentos delicados del cultivo de arroz, como la siega, si bien no fue hasta 1953 cuando se comenzó a actuar con algún sistema, merced al primer acuerdo de asistencia técnica firmado con la OMS, que permitió la venida de Brenno Babudieri, un microbiólogo italiano de fama mundial en este campo, quien probó en España una vacuna. Pero las iniciativas fueron provinciales y no coordinadas, dependientes aparentemente de la voluntad de los Jefes Provinciales de Sanidad y centradas sólo en medidas de laboratorio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Asclepio;69(2): 0-0, jul.-dic. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-AOT-2377</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ocaso de la medicina social en España: el caso de la leptospirosis</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
