<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118937</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of environment, rural or urban, in the perception of the supports and needs of caregivers in hospitals</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. After the Functional Plan was implemented with support measures for caregivers in hospitals of Granada (Spain), the effectiveness and impact of environment on the perception and needs of caregivers was analysed. Materials and methods. A qualitative, phenomenological study was made through semi-structured interviews. A total of 45 caregivers included in the Functional Plan participated. In addition, perceived social support, family functioning, and the anxiety level was measured, respectively, through the Duke-UNC, Apgar Family, and Goldberg Scale questionnaires. The data were qualitatively analysed by open, axial, and selective coding, and the questionnaires by descriptive statistics. Results. The caregivers of the urban setting valued more the support that made their life easier in the hospital and the social support at home, while caregivers in rural settings valued the hospital support oriented towards education in care for life after returning home, all linked to the personalization of care. The personal disturbances due to care occurred in all the settings, although differences appeared in psychic repercussions and in the type of drugs and their consumption. There were differences in terms of support needed and the difficulties encountered. Conclusions. The setting where caregivers live determine their perceptions of the care and some of their needs in the hospital. The measures questioned in the Functional Plan should be reviewed and some priorities should be redefined, including additional measures, depending on the family situation of the caregivers (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gorlat-Sánchez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Expósito-Ruiz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Caro, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quero-Rufián, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peinado-Gorlat, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz-Quintana, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. Tras implementar un Plan Funcional con medidas de apoyo a personas cuidadoras en dos hospitales de Granada, se analizan la eficacia y el efecto del medio en la percepción y las necesidades de la persona cuidadora. Material y método. Se realizó un estudio cualitativo, fenomenológico, a través de entrevistas semi-estructuradas. Participaron 45 personas cuidadoras incluidas en el Plan Funcional. Se midieron además apoyo social percibido, función familiar y nivel de ansiedad mediante los cuestionarios Duke-unc, Apgar familiar y Escala de Goldberg, respectivamente. El análisis de los datos cualitativos se llevó a cabo mediante codificación abierta, axial y selectiva, y los cuestionarios mediante estadística descriptiva .Resultado. Las personas cuidadoras del ámbito urbano valoraron más los apoyos que les facilitaban la vida en el hospital y los apoyos sociales para el domicilio y las del ámbito rural los apoyos hospitalarios orientados a educación en cuidados para cuando estuviesen en su domicilio, todos ellos vinculados a la personalización de cuidados. Las alteraciones personales por el cuidado están presentes en ambos ámbitos aunque difieren en las repercusiones psíquicas y en el tipo de fármacos y su consumo. Existen diferencias en cuanto a los apoyos necesarios y las dificultades encontradas. Conclusiones. El ámbito donde habitualmente viven las personas cuidadoras condiciona sus percepciones del cuidado y algunas de sus necesidades en el hospital. Se deberán revisar las medidas del Plan Funcional cuestionadas, redefinir algunas prioridades e incluir medidas adicionales en función de la situación familiar de las personas cuidadoras (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;36(3): 441-454, sept.-dic. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118937</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia del ámbito, rural o urbano, en la percepción de los apoyos y las necesidades de las personas cuidadoras en el hospital</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32193^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12797^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51255^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14904^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
