<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157620</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-0618</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Obesity, a disease of childhood and adolescence</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Obesity, which started to be considered as a public health disorder at the end of the 20th century, is acquiring nowadays dimensions of epidemic. In most of the cases, this pathology results from an inadequate feeding, frequently turned into a large dietetic, psychological and social problem in developed countries; obesity in the adolescence leading to the most severe consequences in the adulthood. However, obesity has appeared not only in industrialized countries, but also in developing countries. Food behaviour must be conceived from a global perspective, like the result of the interactions of subjects&#146; features (biological, psychological and cultural), together with the food and the environment around, especially those related to the social influence of their peers, marketing messages and lifestyle. These are the reasons why obesity must be individually treated from different aspects in an integral way. With the aim to get a favourable prognosis, not only weight and physical activity management must be pursued, but also changes in the general behaviour. For this purpose, an appropriate psychological therapy and follow-up is necessary (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marcos, Ascensión</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Martínez, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La obesidad, que empezó a plantearse como un problema de salud pública a finales del siglo XX, está adquiriendo dimensiones de epidemia en la actualidad. Esta patología es el resultado en la mayoría de los casos de una mala alimentación, convirtiéndose en un gran problema dietético, psicológico y social muy frecuente en los países civilizados, que llega a tener las consecuencias más graves de la obesidad del adolescente en la edad adulta. Sin embargo, no hay que olvidar el creciente aumento de su incidencia también en los países en vías de desarrollo. El comportamiento alimentario se debe concebir desde una perspectiva integral, producto de la interacción de las características del sujeto (biológicas, psicológicas, culturales), de los alimentos a que tiene acceso y del entorno que le rodea (especialmente la influencia social de su grupo etario y de la publicidad, así como su estilo de vida). Ante esto queda claro que el tratamiento de la obesidad debe ser individual e integral. Para conseguir un buen pronóstico, no solo se debe perseguir una disminución de peso a través de una restricción dietética y un aumento de actividad física, sino un cambio comportamental de hábitos generales para lo cual es necesario una terapia y seguimiento psicológico adecuados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Real Acad Farm;82(n.extr): 137-145, 2016. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157620</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La obesidad, una enfermedad de la infancia y adolescencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55220^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3222^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54847^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5350</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
