<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056994</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-5981</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prospective and randomized study in patients with low back pain or sciatic pain with ozonetherapy treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: A prospective and randomized study to compare the        clinical results between conservative vs. intra-discal/para-lumbar        vertebrae ozone treatment in patients with low back pain and patients        affected of sciatic pain.        Patients and method: This is a randomized study for 103 patients        (44 with low back pain and 59 with sciatic pain) whose        treatment was ozone versus relative rest and analgesic (control        group). To evaluate: scale for measuring the intensity of pain, the        Oswestry questionnaire for the disability caused by lumbar pain,        the hand-flow distance, the Lasseguè test and the reinsertion of        the patients to their labour activities. The clinical follow-up was        6 months.        Results: Using the scale for the intensity of pain and the Oswestry        questionnaire for all the patients with low back pain (ozone or conservative        treatment) we found an improvement of their symptoms        (p 0.001), with no differences in the results between the control        group and the ozone group. For the group of patients affected of        sciatic pain treated with ozone we found improvement of the pain        after the treatment (p 0,001) and the Oswestry questionnaire        40,4% (p 0.001).The Lasseguè test was negative or improved in        83,2% patients after the treatment in the ozone group. In the patients        with low back pain treated with ozone the 58,3% re-started        working in their jobs. For the ozone group with sciatic pain the        78,6% were able to develope their ordinary work. The contained        discal herniasdisk responded better to the treatment with O3.        Conclusions: paralumbar vertebrae ozone does not improve the        clinical evolution of low back pain, although it present analgesic        effects in the short term. The treatment with intradisk more paralumbar        ozone can be one first option in the treatment of the        sciatic pain when the conservative treatment fail</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Hidalgo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Contreras Joya, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ansede Alonso, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: estudiar los resultados clínicos en pacientes con lumbalgias        y ciáticas, tratados con ozono (O3) paravertebral e intradiscal.        Pacientes y método: se incluyeron 103 pacientes, 44 diagnosticados        de lumbalgia y 59 de ciatalgia tratados, prospectiva y        aleatoriamente, con ozono o con reposo y analgesia. Se evaluaron        con la escala de intensidad de dolor, cuestionario Oswestry,        distancia mano-suelo, Lasseguè e incorporación laboral. El seguimiento        clínico fue de 6 meses.        Resultados: en el grupo de lumbagos encontramos diferencias        con el tratamiento en ambos grupos (p  0,001) sin ver diferencias        entre el grupo control y el tratado con ozono.        En el grupo de ciatalgia tratado con O3 encontramos diferencia        inicial y final del dolor (p 0,001) y la escala de Oswestry presentó        una mejoría del 40,4% (p 0,001). En el grupo control        con ciatalgia no mejoró el dolor y empeoró en la escala de Oswestry        (p 0,5).        En el grupo control un 36,2% mostraron un Lasseguè negativo        después del tratamiento, mientras que en los tratados con O3        fueron un 83,2%.        En el grupo de lumbalgia control causaron alta laboral, por curación        o mejoría el 46,6% y el 58,3% tratados con O3; en el grupo        ciatalgia control fueron el 18,2% frente al 78,6% de los tratados        con O3. Las hernias de disco contenidas respondieron mejor al        tratamiento con O3.        Conclusiones: el O3 paravertebral no mejora la evolución clínica        de las lumbalgias. El tratamiento con O3 intradiscal y paravertebral        puede indicarse en el tratamiento de ciáticas y lumbociáticas        secundarias a hernias discales cuando fracasa el tratamiento        conservador</dc:description>
<dc:source>Patol. apar. locomot. Fund. Mapfre Med;5(1): 46-54, ene.-mar. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056994</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio prospectivo y aleatorizado en pacientes con lumbalgias o lumbociatálgias tratados con ozonoterapia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32027^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12966^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10311^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7568^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
