<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046815</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influenza surveillance. New solutions to an old problem</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The pandemic potential of influenza has made this disease the principal target of both national and international surveillance systems. The intrinsic characteristics of sentinel networks enable them to integrate epidemiological and virological information of a high incidence disease such as influenza, so helping in the early detection and characterization of the circulating influenza viruses and in evaluating their spread capacity in the population. A sentinel network, which covers 75% of the population, was created in Spain more than ten years ago. This provides a new approach to human influenza surveillance based on the individualized reporting of each case and the linkage of clinical, epidemiological and virological data. This system has contributed to a more accurate evaluation of influenza activity in Spain. In spite of the limitations of this sentinel system, which mainly derive from the lack of representativeness that any surveillance system based on population samples can encounter, it provides data which have proved useful for the follow-up and control of influenza. Rapid information transmission is one of the main advantages of the system, allowing its integration in the international disease surveillance networks and improving the timeliness of both information spread and formulation of recommendations</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mesonero, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateo, Salvador de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larrauri, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El potencial pandémico de la gripe ha convertido a esta enfermedad en el objetivo preferente de los sistemas de vigilancia nacionales e internacionales. Los sistemas centinela, por sus características, permiten una integración de información virológica y epidemiológica de esta enfermedad de elevada incidencia, ayudando a detectar y caracterizar precozmente los virus de la gripe circulantes y evaluando su capacidad de propagación en la población. La creación en España, hace más de 10 años, de un sistema centinela, que cubre actualmente el 75% de la población nacional, supuso una forma diferente de abordar la vigilancia de la gripe humana, a través de la declaración individualizada de los casos de la enfermedad y la unión de datos clínicos, epidemiológicos y microbiológicos, y ha contribuido a una evaluación más correcta de la actividad de la gripe en el territorio español. A pesar de las limitaciones de este sistema centinela, derivadas fundamentalmente de los problemas de representatividad que todo sistema de vigilancia basado en muestras de población puede presentar, los datos que aporta se han revelado útiles para el seguimiento y el control de la gripe. La rapidez en la transmisión de la información es uno de los principales atributos del sistema, que posibilita su integración en las redes de vigilancia internacional de la enfermedad y ayuda a lograr una mejor oportunidad en la difusión de la información y formulación de recomendaciones</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;20(1): 67-73, ene. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046815</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La vigilancia de la gripe. Nuevas soluciones a un viejo problema</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
