<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131405</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nutrition education and Food services en Preschool Education Institution: Spain and Turkey</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The aim of this study is to present the general features, food services and nutrition education states of pre-school education institutions (PEI) in Turkey and Spain. Material and method: This is an observational study conducted in a convenience sample of 24 Preschool centers in Spain and Turkey in the scope of a European Union Lifelong Learning Programme Leonardo Da Vinci Mobility Project (LLP - LDV VETPRO). Data were collected by means of personal interviews and observation method. Data were analyzed in SPSS for Windows 15.0 software using descriptive statistical methods. Results: In both countries nutrition education activities are introduced into daily education activities. Despite all the centers analyzed included some kind of nutrition related activities, only one institution in Spain and none in Turkey had a structured, sustainable and comprehensive nutrition education program. In Spain, art and play are highly used in nutrition education activities, while language and drama are highly used in Turkey. Conclusions: In this study, similarities and differences in food service and nutrition education practices in pre-school institutions in Spain and Turkey were presented. Cooperation between countries and the transfer of good practice will yield structured, sustainable and comprehensive nutrition education projects which will play role in bringing up healthy children, and thus healthy adults (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Akta, Nazan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esra Angin, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo de este estudio es describir las características generales, los servicios de alimentación y las actividades de educación nutricional en las instituciones de educación preescolar (PEI) en Turquía y en España. Material y método: Se ha realizado un estudio observacional en una muestra de conveniencia de 24 centros de educación preescolar de España y Turquía, en el marco del Programa Leonardo Da Vinci de Movilidad de la Unión Europea. La información se recogió mediante entrevistas personales y el método de observación. Los datos se analizaron mediante SPSS para Windows 15.0, usando los métodos estadísticos descriptivos. Resultados: En ambos países se realizan actividades de educación nutricional en los centros de educación preescolar. Sin embargo, tan solo en uno de los centros estudiados en España se contempla un programa estructurado, global y sostenible. En Turquía no se detectó ninguno. En España las actividades de educación nutricional se realizan a través de la educación plástica y el juego; en Turquía se utiliza principalmente el área lengua y teatro. Conclusión: Este trabajo pone de manifiesto las semejanzas y diferencias en servicios de alimentación y en las prácticas de educación nutricional en las instituciones de educación preescolar en España y Turquía . La cooperación entre países y la transferencia de buenas prácticas puede contribuir a la instauración de proyectos de educación nutricional globales, sostenibles y estructurados, que tienen un papel importante en la crianza de niños sanos, y por lo tanto de adultos sanos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;17(1): 6-12, ene.-mar. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131405</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La Educación nutricional y los servicios de alimentación en las instituciones de educación preescolar en España y Turquía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d16570^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23583^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5350^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24439</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23583^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52460^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52504^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50323</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52488^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
