<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122478</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Natural history of venous thromboembolism in patients from the Mediterranean region. A systematic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Patients with cardiovascular diseases living in the Mediterranean area have a better outcome than those in other parts of the world, but it is not known whether these differences also occur with venous thromboembolism (VTE). Methods: We searched the Medline and EMBASE databases to identify clinical trials and cohort studies of patients with VTE who had been treated with anticoagulant therapy for 3 months. Two reviewers independently extracted the data in a standardized manner. A total of 24 studies that included 7,225 patients (2,414 from the Mediterranean region and 4,811 from other regions) were analyzed. Results: The patients from the Mediterranean area were predominately women and older, and the idiopathic VTE was less frequent than in other regions. Compared with patients from other regions, patients from the Mediterranean region had an increased rate of recurrent deep vein thrombosis (4.35% vs. 2.68%; odds ratio [OR], 1.65; 95% confidence interval [95% CI] 1.27-2.15), fatal recurrent VTE (0.75% vs. 0.35%; OR, 2.11; 95% CI 1.09-4.12) and fatal bleeding (0.25% vs. 0.06%; odds ratio: 3.99; 95% CI 1.00-16.0). The case-fatality rate (CFR) for recurrent VTE was 12.8% (95% CI 7.99-19.1) in the Mediterranean region and 8.41% (5.15-12.9) in other areas. The CFR for major bleeding was 11.3% (95% CI 4.72-22.1) and 3.22% (95% CI 0.83-8.53), respectively. Conclusions: Compared to other regions, patients with VTE from the Mediterranean region have greater mortality during the first 3 months of treatment due to a greater incidence of recurrent VTE and severe hemorrhaging (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo Hernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Muñoz-Torrero, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zamorano, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monreal, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trujillo Santos, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Capitán, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: El pronóstico de las enfermedades cardiovasculares es mejor en los países mediterráneos que en otras partes del mundo. Se desconoce si estas diferencias también acontecen en la enfermedad tromboembólica venosa (ETV) Métodos: En las bases de datos Medline y EMBASE se revisaron los ensayos clínicos y estudios de cohortes de pacientes con ETV que habían recibido tratamiento anticoagulante durante 3 meses. Dos revisores extrajeron independientemente los datos de forma reglada. Se seleccionaron 24 estudios con un total de 7.225 pacientes incluidos (2.414 del área mediterránea y 4.811 de otras regiones). Resultados: Entre los pacientes del área mediterránea predominaban las mujeres, tenían mayor edad, y la ETV idiopática fue menos frecuente que en otras regiones del mundo. Comparados con otros países, los pacientes del área mediterránea presentaron más recidivas de trombosis venosa profunda (4,35% frente a 2,68%; odds ratio [OR]: 1,65; intervalo de confianza al 95% [IC95%]: 1,27-2,15), recidivas mortales de ETV (0,75% frente a 0,35%; OR: 2,11; IC95%: 1,09-4,12) y sangrado mortal (0,25% frente a 0,06%; OR: 3,99; IC95%: 1-16). En el área mediterránea el porcentaje de recidivas de ETV mortal fue del 12,8%, IC95%: 7,99-19,1 frente al 8,41%, IC95%: 5,15-12,9 en otras zonas del mundo. El porcentaje de hemorragias mortales fue del 11,3%, IC95%: 4,72-22,1 frente al 3,22%, IC95%: 0,83-8,53 en otras zonas geográficas. Conclusiones: Los pacientes con ETV del área mediterránea tienen una mayor mortalidad durante los 3 primeros meses de tratamiento imputable a una mayor incidencia de ETV recidivante y de hemorragias graves (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;214(4): 184-191, mayo 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122478</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Historia natural de la enfermedad tromboembólica venosa en el área mediterránea. Una revisión sistemática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28632</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52618^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32692^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28590</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
