<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043290</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Transdermal fentanyl in the treatment of neuropathic pain of spinal cord injured patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Design. Prospective, longitudinal and open-labeled study. Objectives. Assess analgesic efficacy of transdermal fentanyl in neuropathic pain secondary to spinal cord injury comparing it with other groups of patients with neuropathic pain. Material and methods. Patients with neuropathic pain affected by spinal cord injury were included, the control group being formed by amputee patients and those affected by cerebrovascular accident. The pain characteristics were recorded: intensity according to visual analogue scale and Lattinen scale, interference with sleep and side effects presented. Controls were conducted by seriated visits, monitoring the changes seen regarding pain after administration of transdermal fentanyl. Pearson's x 2 test and the t-test were used in the statistical study, values of p &lt; 0.05 being considered as significant. Results. A total of 32 patients were included in the study, 20 with spinal cord injury, 8 amputees and 4 patients with cerebrovascular accident. Neuropathic pain intensity decreased in both groups, the global decrease on the visual analogue scale being determined from 7.54 to 3.8 at three months (p &lt; 0.05) and on the Lattinen scale from 12.78 to 7.14 (p &lt; 0.05). Decrease on the visual analogue scale was less intense in the spinal cord injured group, from 7.7 to 4.91 (p &lt; 0.05), than in the amputees and in patients with cerebrovascular accidents. Conclusions. Transdermal fentanyl is an effective therapeutic alternative for treatment of neuropathic pain secondary to spinal cord injury although the decrease in pain intensity is less than in patients with neuropathic pain of another origin</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Enríquez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alemán, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Bravo, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bárbara Bataller, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández González, Z</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez Suárez, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miranda Calderín, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina Estévez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Diseño. Estudio prospectivo, longitudinal y abierto. Objetivos. Valorar la eficacia analgésica del fentanilo transdérmico en dolor neuropático secundario a lesión medular comparándola con otros grupos de pacientes con dolor neuropático. Material y métodos. Se incluyeron pacientes con dolor neuropático afectos de lesión medular, conformándose un grupo control de enfermos amputados y afectos de un accidente cerebrovascular. Fueron registradas las características del dolor: intensidad según escala analógica visual y escala de Latineen, interferencia con el sueño y los efectos secundarios presentados. Se realizaron controles mediante visitas seriadas, monitorizándose los cambios manifestados respecto al dolor tras la administración del fentanilo transdérmico. En el estudio estadístico se emplearon la prueba de x 2 de Pearson y la prueba t, siendo considerados significativos valores de p &lt; 0,05. Resultados. Treinta y dos pacientes fueron incluidos en el estudio, 20 lesionados medulares, 8 amputados y 4 pacientes afectos de un accidente cerebrovascular. La intensidad del dolor neuropático se redujo en ambos grupos, determinándose el descenso global en la escala analógica visual, de 7,54 a 3,8 a los tres meses (p &lt; 0,05) y en la escala de Lattinen de 12,78 a 7,14 (p &lt; 0,05). El descenso en la escala analógica visual fue menos intenso en el grupo de lesionados medulares, de 7,7 a 4,91 (p &lt; 0,05), que en amputados y en pacientes con accidentes cerebrovasculares. Conclusiones. El fentanilo transdérmico es una alternativa terapéutica eficaz para el tratamiento del dolor neuropático secundario a lesión medular, si bien el descenso de intensidad del dolor es menor que en pacientes con dolor neuropático de otro origen</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);40(1): 6-13, ene.-feb. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043290</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fentanilo transdérmico en el tratamiento para el dolor neuropático del lesionado medular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13272^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28037^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19283^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9630^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13502^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
