<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80592</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-2074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anaemia and celiac disease in a patient with Down syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Down syndrome (DS) is associated with an increase drisk of celiac disease (CD) than that found ingeneral population. An adolescent girl with DS and CD presenting with severe anaemia is reported. A 13 year-old girl was admitted to hospital for anaemia and a 4 week-history of asthenia, anorexia, and disturbed bowel habit. Her past medical history was remarkable for hypermenorrhea and occasional vomiting. Heart rate was 106xminute and blood pressure112/48 mmHg. On physical exam she was pale and a systolic murmur was heard. Blood tests depicted a severe hypochromic normocytic anaemia with haemoglobin values of 4,7 g/dL Gastrointestinal bleeding was ruled out on the basis of several image studies and a bone marrow study was also normal. Iron supplement with ferrous sulphate was prescribed. A month later she was readmitted to hospital for abdominal pain, vomiting and diarrhoea. Serum endomysium antibodies and tissue transglutaminase antibodies were found to be positive and an intestinal biopsy confirmed the diagnosis of CD. She was started on a gluten-free diet and the iron supplement was maintained. She subsequently followed a favourable clinical course with cessation of gastrointestinal symptoms and correction of the manaemia. Several authors have suggested that people with DS should be routinely screened for CD even if they area symptomatic. Moreover, the existence of CD should be specially considered in people with DS who present with gastrointestinal symptoms or anaemia of unclear etiologies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vila Cerén, Clara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Demestre Guasch, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sala Castellví, Pere</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ducet Vilardell, Purificació</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Raspall Torrent, Frederic</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llorens Jové, Mª Esperança</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elizari Saco, M. Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las personas con síndrome de Down (SD) tienen más probabilidades de presentar enfermedad celiaca (EC) que la población general. Se presenta un caso de EC que se manifiesta con anemia importante, en una chica adolescente con SD. Paciente de sexo femenino de 13 años de edad, con SD, que ingresa por anemia acompañada de astenia, anorexia y alteración del ritmo intestinal de unas 4 semanas de evolución. Tiene antecedentes de menstruaciones abundantes y algún vómito antes del inicio de la enfermedad actual. Al constatarse la palidez cutánea sele practica analítica y ésta indica una importante anemia, con cifra de hemoglobina de 4,7 g/dL, por lo que la paciente es derivada al hospital. La exploración física muestra una frecuencia cardiaca de 106xminuto,tensión arterial de 112/48 mmHg, palidez cutánea y de mucosas y soplo sistólico. La anemia es normocítica hipocroma y con ferropenia. Los estudios de imagen descartan patología hemorrágica gastrointestinal. El estudio de médula ósea también es normal. Se inicia tratamiento con sulfato ferroso por vía oral. Un mes después, la paciente vuelve a ingresar por dolor abdominal, vómitos y diarrea. Durante el ingreso se practican determinación de anticuerpos antiendomisio y antitransglutaminasa tisular, que resultan positivos. La biopsia intestinal confirma EC. Se instaura una dieta sin gluten y se mantiene el tratamiento con hierro, tras lo cual sigue una evolución favorable y recuperación dela anemia. Hay autores e instituciones que recomiendan la práctica de cribado de EC en personas asintomáticas con SD. En cualquier caso, en las que presentan sintomatología gastrointestinal o de otros tipos &#150;como puede ser una anemia no explicable por otros motivos&#150;, debe descartarse la posibilidad de EC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SD, Rev. med. int. Síndr. Down (Ed. castell.);12(1): 8-11, mar. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80592</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anemia y enfermedad celiaca en una paciente con síndrome de Down</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2481^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1255^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23944^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2481^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6127^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2481^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27787^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
