<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042603</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment and control of cardiovascular risk in primary care in Spain. The PREVENCAT study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: The PREVENCAT study was designed to estimate the control of the main cardiovascular risk factors (CVRF) and their treatment in a sample of population having the diagnoses of hypertension (HT), type 2 diabetes mellitus (DM2) or hypercholesterolemia (HC) who was attended by primary care physicians in Spain. Patients and method: Cross-sectional study in patients with HT, DM2 and/or HC, who were consecutively recruited. We describe the treatments for HT, DM2 and HC and analyze and the association between several potential predictors and the control of these CVRF. Results: 2,649 patients were included in the study. 95% of HT patients were under treatment, as were 84% of DM2 and 71.4% of HC patients; most common drugs were diuretics, sulphonylureas and statins, respectively. Monotherapy was more frequent than combined therapy for hypertension treatment. The frequency of HT and DM2 treatment was similar among the subgroups defined by the presence or absence of the other two diagnoses. However, HC treatment was more common in the presence of DM2 (p = 0.001). Age, previous cardiovascular disease (CVD), DM2, obesity and sedentarism were all predictors of poor blood pressure control despite drug treatment. Age, previous CVD, HT and sedentarism were predictors of poor HC control. Conclusions: CVRF treament was high although heterogeneous and not based on the best available evidence. DM2, previous CVD and obesity were associated with insufficient blood pressure control</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Coca, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordóñez, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dalfó, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esmatjes, Enric</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Zurro, Armando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gomis, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Juanatey, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llisterri, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: El estudio PREVENCAT se diseñó para estimar el control de los principales factores de riesgo cardiovascular (FRCV) y el tratamiento de éstos en la población asistida en atención primaria (AP) que presenta hipertensión arterial (HTA), diabetes mellitus tipo 2 (DM2) o hipercolesterolemia (HC). Pacientes y método: Estudio transversal en pacientes con HTA, DM2 y/o HC, reclutados de forma consecutiva por médicos de AP en España. Se evaluó el tratamiento de la HTA, la DM2 y la HC y se analizó la relación entre el control de estos FRCV y diversos factores potencialmente predictivos. Resultados: Se incluyó a 2.649 pacientes. La frecuencia del tratamiento farmacológico fue del 95% en la HTA, del 84% en la DM2 y del 71,4% en la HC, y los fármacos más utilizados fueron los diuréticos, las sulfonilureas y las estatinas, respectivamente. En el tratamiento de la HTA predominó la monoterapia. La frecuencia del tratamiento de la HTA y de la DM2 fue homogénea en los subgrupos definidos por la presencia o ausencia de los otros dos diagnósticos. Sin embargo, el tratamiento de la HC fue más frecuente en presencia de DM2 (p = 0,001). La edad, la enfermedad cardiovascular (ECV), la DM2, la obesidad y el sedentarismo fueron predictivos del control de la presión arterial (PA), mientras que el tratamiento con fármacos, la edad, la ECV, la HTA y el sedentarismo lo fueron del control de la HC. El tratamiento con fármacos fue el único factor predictivo del control de la glucemia basal. Conclusiones: El tratamiento de los FRCV considerados fue elevado aunque muy heterogéneo y no basado en la mejor evidencia disponible. La DM2, la ECV y la obesidad se asociaron al mal control de la PA</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);126(6): 201-205, feb. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042603</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento y control del riesgo cardiovascular en atención primaria en España. Estudio PREVENCAT</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3963^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
