<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142480</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of a questionnaire to measure overall Mediterranean lifestyle habits for research application: the MEDiterranean LIFEstyle index (MEDLIFE)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: the Mediterranean Lifestyle index (MEDLIFE) was developed as a questionnaire to capture adherence to an overall Mediterranean healthy lifestyle. The reliability of the MEDLIFE as an independent questionnaire must be evaluated prior its use in research studies. Objective: to assess the inter-method reliability of the MEDLIFE as a short and independent research tool. Design: the 28-item MEDLIFE questionnaire and a 142-item validated questionnaire (full-Q) from which we derived the 28-items MEDLIFE (MEDLIFE-derived) were administered simultaneously to 196 adults (mean age 41.4 ± 9.2 y) living in Madrid, Spain. The reliability was assessed by Kappa (k) statistics, intra-class correlation coefficients (ICC) and limits of agreement (LOA). Results: overall correlation between the two instruments was 0.626. MEDLIFE had an acceptable ability to rank participants by MEDLIFE-derived from full-Q (ICC=0.544). Absolute agreement showed very good concordance for 10.7% of the items evaluated; good to moderate concordance for most items, and fair concordance for 32.1% of the items. Intake of sweets, processed meats, low-fat dairy products and cereals were overestimated by MEDLIFE. About 38%, 15%, 12% and 10% of participants who scored 1-point for those items in MEDLIFE also scored 1-point in the MEDLIFE-derived respectively. Bland Altman&#146;s analysis showed that LOA ranged from -4.66 to 7.45 (mean=1.40). Conclusion: the MEDLIFE is a valid instrument to measure overall adherence to the Mediterranean lifestyle in middle age adults from a Spanish population, and could be used as an independent questionnaire in clinical and epidemiological studies for such population. Its generalizability and predictive validity for clinical outcomes remains to be investigated (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pocock, Stuart</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sotos-Prieto, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bodega, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peñalvo, Jose Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos-Beneit, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mattei, Josiemer</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: el índice de estilo de vida mediterráneo (MEDLIFE) fue desarrollado como un cuestionario para recoger la adherencia a un estilo de vida saludable mediterráneo. La fiabilidad del MEDLIFE como cuestionario independiente debe ser evaluada antes de su uso en estudios de investigación. Objetivo: evaluar la fiabilidad inter-método del MEDLIFE como herramienta de investigación corta e independiente. Diseño: cuestionario corto del MEDLIFE de 28 ítems y un cuestionario largo validado de 142 ítems, del cual se derivó posteriormente el cuestionario del MEDLIFE de 28 ítems (MEDLIFE-derivado), se administraron simultáneamente a 196 adultos (edad media 41,4 ± 9,2 años) con residencia en Madrid, España. La fiabilidad se evaluó mediante el coeficiente kappa de Cohen, el coeficiente de correlación intraclase (CCI) y el límite de acuerdo (LOA). Resultados: el grado de correlación entre los dos instrumentos fue 0,626. El MEDLIFE tuvo una capacidad aceptable para clasificar a los participantes mediante el MEDLIFE-derivado (ICC=0,544). El grado de acuerdo absoluto (coeficiente kappa) mostró muy buena concordancia para el 10,7% de los ítems evaluados; de buena a moderada para la mayoría de los ítems, y razonable para el 32,1% de los ítems. La ingesta de dulces, carnes procesadas, productos lácteos bajos en grasa y cereales se sobreestimó por el MEDLIFE. El 38%, 15%, 12% y 10% de los participantes que obtuvieron 1 punto para esos ítems en el MEDLIFE también obtuvieron 1 punto en el MEDLIFE-derivado, respectivamente. El análisis de Bland Altman mostró un rango de LOA de -4,66 a 7,45 (media = 1,40). Conclusión: el MEDLIFE es un instrumento válido para medir la adherencia global al estilo de vida mediterráneo en adultos de mediana edad de una población española, y podría ser utilizado como cuestionario independiente en estudios clínicos y epidemiológicos para tal población. Su generalización y validez predictiva para los parámetros clínicos debe ser investigada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(3): 1153-1163, sept. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142480</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación de un cuestionario para medir los hábitos de estilo de vida mediterráneos para su aplicación en investigación: índice de estilo de vida mediterráneo (MEDLIFE)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37653^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
