<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045522</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparative results between vertical ringed gastroplasty and duodenal switch in morbid obesity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The only effective long-term treatment for morbid obesity is bariatric surgery.                 Aim. To compare the long-term results of vertical banded gastroplasty (VBG) and duodenal switch (DS). Quality of life, weight loss and reoperations were evaluated. Material and methods. A retrospective study of 85 patients with VBG and 49 with DS with a follow-up of more than 5 years was performed. The mean preoperative body mass index (BMI) was 48.8 kg/m2 in VBG patients and 50.33 kg/m2 in DS patients. Results. At 5 years, 87.5% of patients with DS had maintained a percentage of excess weight lost (%EWL) of more than 50%, and were therefore counted as successes, compared with 55% of those with VBG (p &lt; 0.0001). Eight VBG patients (9.4%) and one DS patient (2.04%) required re-operations due to failure of the technique. None of the VBG patients with a %EWL of more than 50% could eat a normal diet, whereas more than 80% of patients with DS had no dietary restrictions.                 Conclusions. At 60 months follow up, only the DS patients fulfilled the requirements of the American Society of Bariatric Surgery of %EWL superior to 50% in more than 75% of the patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez, Nieves</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bengochea, Marcelo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baltasar, Aniceto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferri, Lirios</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serra, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bou, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Sólo la cirugía bariátrica ha demostrado ser eficaz en el control de la obesidad mórbida.  Objetivo. Comparar los resultados a largo plazo de la gastroplastia vertical anillada (GVA) y el cruce duodenal (CD). Se estudia la evolución de la pérdida de peso, el número de reintervenciones y la calidad de vida. Material y método. Se trata de un estudio retrospectivo que incluye a 85 pacientes con GVA y a 49 con CD, con un seguimiento no inferior a 5 años. En la GVA la media del índice de masa corporal (IMC) fue de 48,8 kg/m2, y en el CD de 50,33 kg/m2.  Resultados. A los 5 años, el 87,5% de los pacientes con CD mantenía un PSP &gt; 50% y, por tanto, fueron considerados éxitos, frente a un 55% en la GVA (p  80% afirmó no tener ningún tipo de restricción en la dieta. Conclusiones. A los 60 meses de seguimiento, sólo el grupo con CD cumple el requisito de la ASBS (American Society of Bariatric Surgery) de mantener un PSP &gt; 50% en el 75% de los pacientes a largo plazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);79(5): 283-288, mayo 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045522</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultado comparativo entre la gastroplastia vertical anillada y el cruce duodenal en la obesidad mórbida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23862</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23642^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
