<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133159</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-7546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of 24 sessions of resistance training in a patient with gonarthrosis bilateral: a case study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To evaluate the effects of 24 moderate-high intensity progressive Resistance Training (RT) on functional capacity, muscle strength and body composition in an elderly patient with gonarthrosis (GA) bilateral. Methods. Functional capacity, muscle strength and anthropometric variables were measured before and after 24 training sessions. The patient performed a 12-weeks progressive RT (2 times/week), between 8 and 12 repetitions maximum, using the major muscle groups of the upper and lower limbs. Results. There was an improvement in the sit-to-stand test (46,1%), in sit and reach test (33,3%), the muscle strength increased in all exercises analyzed and the anthropometric indices enhanced. Conclusion. The results of this study indicate that 24 sessions of progressive RT, can be effective in improving anthropometric indices, functional capacity and muscle strength of elderly patients diagnosed with GA bilateral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Silva-Grigoletto, M. E. da</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abrahin, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodrigues, R. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beas-Jiménez, J. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sousa, E. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marçal, A. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Evaluar los efectos de 24 sesiones de ejercicio de fuerza (EF) progresivo, de intensidad moderada/alta sobre la capacidad funcional, la fuerza muscular y la composición corporal de un anciano con gonartrosis (GA) bilateral. Método. La capacidad funcional, la fuerza muscular y las variables antropométricas fueron medidas antes y después de 24 sesiones de entrenamiento. El paciente realizó el EF progresivo entre 8 y 12 repeticiones máximas, utilizando los principales grupos musculares de los miembros superiores e inferiores, 2 veces por semana durante 12 semanas. Resultados. Hubo una mejora en el test de sentarse y levantase (46,1%), en el sentar y alcanzar (33,3%), así como un aumento de la fuerza muscular en todos los ejercicios analizados y mejora de los índices antropométricos. Conclusión. Los resultados de este estudio indican que 24 sesiones de EF progresivo pueden ser eficaces en la mejora de índices antropométricos, la capacidad funcional y la fuerza muscular de un paciente anciano diagnosticado de GA bilateral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. andal. med. deporte;8(1): 16-19, mar. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133159</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de 24 sesiones de entrenamiento de fuerza en un paciente con gonartrosis bilateral: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33759^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33759^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
