<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115647</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Knowledge of the cost of the treatments delivered from the Hospital Pharmacy Department and perception of the health status</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the influence of the knowledge of the financial cost of the treatment and perception of the patient of his/her health status and the health care received from the Hospital Pharmacy Department (HPD). Method: During a four-month period, from July to October of 2009, a questionnaire was provided to all the patients coming to the Hospital Pharmacy Department to gather their medications, except for those starting their therapies. The patients returning the completed questionnaire at a next visit were provided with the second part, in which they were informed on the monthly cost of their treatments and some questions from the main questionnaire were asked again. Results: 682 questionnaires were provided, of which 240 (35.3%) were returned completed. 223 patients were given the second part, of which 151 (22.1%) were returned. In general, the patients were satisfied with their treatments (90.4%) and with the care provided at the HPD (95.4%), 69.2% had good knowledge of their treatment, and 59.2% considered themselves as good compliers, and 17.5% did not usually consult with the pharmacist at the HPD. The patient's satisfaction analysis before (7.75; SD: 1.90) and after knowing the treatment cost (7.80; SD: 1.91) did not show statistically significant differences, with the exception of those patients derived from the Infectious Disease Department (p = 0.015) that were less satisfied after knowing the cost. Conclusions: The knowledge on the treatment cost could not be related in general with changes in the attitude of the patients towards their treatments, being necessary the design of more profound studies. Besides, it should be recommended to undertake the improvement actions detected by the patients in order to increase the quality of the pharmacy care delivered (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Llopis, Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente Valor, M. Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintana Vergara, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bargues Ruiz, J. Adrià</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Tinoco, M. Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Alcaraz, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Valorar la influencia del conocimiento del coste económico del tratamiento sobre la percepción del paciente de su estado de salud y la atención recibida en el Servicio de Farmacia Hospitalaria (SFH). Método: Durante un periodo de cuatro meses, de julio a octubre de 2009, se entrega una encuesta a todos los pacientes que acuden a recoger medicación al Servicio de Farmacia Hospitalaria (SFH), excepto a los que inician el tratamiento. A los pacientes que devuelven la encuesta principal cumplimentada en una visita posterior, se les hace entrega de la segunda parte, en la que se les informa del coste mensual de su tratamiento y se reformulan preguntas de la encuesta principal. Resultados: Son repartidas 682 encuestas, de las cuales son contestadas 240 (35,3%). Se entrega la segunda parte de la encuesta a 223 pacientes, de las que se devuelven 151 (22,1%). En general, los pacientes están satisfechos con el tratamiento (90,4%) y con la atención recibida en el SFH (95,4%), tienen un buen conocimiento del tratamiento (69,2%), se consideran cumplidores (59,2%%) y no suelen consultar al farmacéutico del SFH (17,5%). En el análisis de la satisfacción del paciente antes (7,75; DE: 1,90) y después de conocer el coste del tratamiento (7,80; DE: 1,91) no se han encontrado diferencias estadísticamente significativas, excepto en los pacientes derivados desde la Unidad de Enfermedades Infecciosas (p = 0,015), menos satisfechos tras conocer el coste. Conclusiones: No se ha podido relacionar el conocimiento del coste del tratamiento, en rasgos generales, con cambios en la actitud de los pacientes frente al mismo, siendo necesario el diseño de estudios más amplios. Asimismo, sería recomendable acometer los puntos de mejora detectados por los pacientes para elevar la calidad de la Atención Farmacéutica ofrecida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;37(1): 50-58, ene.-feb. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115647</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conocimiento del coste de los tratamientos dispensados desde el Servicio de Farmacia Hospitalaria y percepción del estado de salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11016^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50249</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30152^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
