<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043930</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Medicinal plants to treat obesity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Due to the large market that obesity generated, one of the largestfields for alternative therapies is in fact the treatment of obesity. Thelack of pharmacological options that traditional medicine presentsfor this condition and the difficulty representing the modification ofhabits such as the diet and exercise compel the population to find alternativesthat offered a rapid solution for their excess weight problems.Therapies based on medicinal herbs are usually first choice,once the adoption of healthy habits has been ruled out. In general,herbs used for the treatment of obesity have a good safety profileand a low incidence rate of interaction with drugs. However, theyhave a low, if non existent, efficacy. Worth mentioning are casessuch as Ephedra, for its multiple adverse effects, or Hypericum, forits numerous pharmacological applications</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Serrano Ruiz, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tratamiento de la obesidad es, debido al enorme mercado que representa, uno de los campos en los que más interés ponen las terapiasalternativas. La falta de opciones farmacológicas de la medicinatradicional ante este problema y la dificultad que supone la modificaciónde hábitos como la dieta y el ejercicio hacen que la poblaciónbusque alternativas que supongan una solución rápida para sus problemasde sobrepeso. Las terapias basadas en hierbas medicinalesson habitualmente la primera elección, una vez descartada la adopciónde hábitos higiénicos saludables. En general, las hierbas que seutilizan para el tratamiento de la obesidad poseen un buen perfil deseguridad y una baja tasa de interacciones con fármacos, aunque sueficacia es escasa, cuando no inexistente. Mención aparte merecencasos como la Ephedra, por sus múltiples efectos adversos, o el Hipérico,por su gran cantidad de interacciones farmacológicas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;8(9): 62-64, nov. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043930</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hierbas medicinales para tratar la obesidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8682^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19609^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35789^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34154^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
