<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127533</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ureteral endometriosis in a single-kidney patient. Case report and literatura review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Endometriosis is defined as the presence of ectopic endometrial tissue outside the normal confines of the uterine cavity. Urinary tract involvement is uncommon, its incidence being about 5%. We report the case of a 44 year-old patient with a single left kidney admitted to the urology department of our hospital diagnosed with left-sided hydronephrosis. She also complained of pain in the left renal fossa for more than a month. A study of left obstructive uropathy was performed, revealing a mass effect in the left distal ureter. Given the findings and the patient's history (a single left kidney), we decided to perform ureterectomy and to fix the bladder to the psoas, as well as to perform an intraoperative biopsy. The histopathological report of the surgical specimen confirmed the previous diagnosis of ureteral endometriosis. The patient is currently asymptomatic and has normal renal function (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mainez Rodríguez, Juan Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zamora Martínez, Tomás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Sagarra Oceja, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Villalba, Antonio José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Fernández, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conde Redondo, Consuelo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marina García-Tuñón, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La endometriosis se define como la presencia de tejido endometrial funcionante localizado de manera ectópica fuera de la cavidad uterina. La afectación del aparato urinario es poco frecuente evidenciándose únicamente en el 5% de las pacientes con endometriosis. Presentamos el caso de una paciente de 44 años monorrena izquierda, que ingresa en el servicio de urología por hidronefrosis y dolor en fosa renal de un mes de evolución. Se realiza estudio de uropatía obstructiva izquierda evidenciándose efecto masa en uréter distal izquierdo. Dados los hallazgos y los antecedentes de la paciente (monorrena izquierda) se decide realizar ureterectomía y vejiga psoica, con toma de biopsia intraoperatoria. El estudio histopatológico de la pieza reveló el diagnóstico de endometriosis ureteral. La paciente en la actualidad se encuentra asintomática y con función renal normal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);57(7): 303-307, ago.-sept. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127533</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Endometriosis ureteral en paciente monorrena. Presentación del caso y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4794^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3632^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3421^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4794^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4794^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23501^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23501^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4794^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52122^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
