<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150255</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Association between personality traits and substance use in Spanish adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Substance use is considered one of the most frequent risk behaviors during adolescence. Personality factors are linked to consumption during adolescence. Although there are studies on personality and consumption among Spanish adolescents, some outcomes are contradictory, and more studies including larger samples and using validated measures are needed. The aim of this study is to analyze the relationship between different personality factors and substance use among Spanish adolescents. Participants were 1,455 students aged between 13-18 years. The adaptation of the 16PF-IPIP Personality Inventory was applied to assess Warmth, Stability, Gregariousness, Friendliness, Sensitivity, Trust, Openness to experience, Sociability, Perfectionism, and Calmness. Participants were asked about their different consumption substances during their lifetime. Results provide evidence for a relationship between personality factors and psychoactive substance use. There are different distributions of alcohol use regarding personality traits. Furthermore, personality factors have some influence on consumption of alcohol, cannabis, and cocaine. Trust and Calmness influence average alcohol, cannabis, and cocaine consumption, whereas Sociability had no statistically significant influence on any of the three substances. The results from this study are highly useful in the design of preventive programs, as they provide more evidence of the role of personality traits as a risk factor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Orgilés, Mireia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillon Riquelme, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gonzálvez, María T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espada, José P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Secades, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El consumo de sustancias está considerado como una de las conductas de riesgo más frecuentes durante la adolescencia. Los factores de personalidad están relacionados con el consumo en la adolescencia. Aunque existen estudios sobre personalidad y consumo en adolescentes españoles, algunos resultados son contradictorios y son necesarios más estudios con muestras de mayor tamaño y que utilicen medidas validadas. El objetivo de este estudio es analizar la relación entre los diferentes factores de personalidad y el consumo de sustancias en adolescentes españoles. Participaron 1,455 estudiantes de secundaria entre 13 y 18 años. Se aplicó la adaptación del Inventario de Personalidad 16PFIPIP para evaluar Calidez, Estabilidad, Gregarismo, Amigabilidad, Sensibilidad, Confianza, Apertura, Sociabilidad, Perfeccionismo y Calma. Se preguntó a los participantes acerca de las diferentes sustancias que habían consumido a lo largo de su vida. Los resultados evidencian la relación entre las variables de personalidad y el consumo de sustancias psicoactivas. El consumo de alcohol presenta diferentes distribuciones con respecto a los rasgos de personalidad. Por otra parte, los factores de personalidad tienen cierta influencia en el consumo de alcohol, cannabis y cocaína. Confianza y Calma tienen influencia en el consumo de alcohol, cannabis y cocaína, mientras que Sociabilidad no presenta ninguna influencia estadísticamente significativa en ninguna de las tres sustancias. Los resultados de este estudio son de gran utilidad a la hora de diseñar programas preventivos, ya que proporcionan mayor evidencia sobre el papel de los rasgos de personalidad como factores de riesgo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);28(2): 108-115, 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150255</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asociación entre rasgos de personalidad y consumo de sustancias en adolescentes españoles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d991^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d991^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22937^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30236^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d991^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
