<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128654</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hyperhomocysteinemia related cerebral venous trombosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Moderate hyperhomocystinemia is a causal risk factor for atherosclerosis and venous  thromboembolism. Recent researches have tried to find out a causal relationship. However, only a small number of cases have been reported on hyperhomocysteinemia and cerebral venous thrombosis in the world medical literature. Case report. We present the case of a 21 years old woman, and oral contraceptives taker, who consulted for a one week clinical picture of biparietal headache, nausea and vomiting. Examination revealed bilateral papilledema, and subsequent CT scan, MRI and MR angiography showed thrombosis of the left lateral sinus. Immunologic tests (antinuclear antibodies, antiphospholipid antibodies) were negative. Hypercoagulability studies showed persistent homocysteine high levels. The patient improved and was discharged after treatment with anticoagulants and therapeutic measures against brain edema. Discussion. The 70 percent of the patients with thrombosis of the cerebral venous sinuses present hypercoagulable states, including moderate hyperhomocysteinemia. Several mechanisms are proposed for venous thrombosis in hyperhomocysteinemia, homocysteine induced endothelial dysfunction between others. Otherwise, oral contraceptives can increase the risk of venous thrombosis in other prothrombotic conditions. Folic acid and vitamins supplementation therapy are commented (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castella Murillo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Tous, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cueli Rincón, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Hernández, MD</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castilla Guerra, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Bolaños, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Moreno, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La hiperhomocisteinemia moderada es un factor de riesgo independiente para la arteriosclerosis y la enfermedad tromboembólica. En los últimos años existe un interés creciente por determinar su relación causal; sin embargo, se recogen pocos casos en la literatura asociados a la trombosis venosa cerebral. Caso clínico. Mujer de 21 años que toma anticonceptivos orales. Una semana antes del ingreso, comienza con cefalea opresiva biparietal continua que interfiere el sueño, acompañada de nausea y vómitos, y que empeora con las maniobras de Valsalva. En la exploración neurológica destaca un papiledema bilateral de predominio izquierdo. El resto de la exploración fue normal. En distintas pruebas de neuroimagen &#150;tomografía computarizada (TAC), resonancia magnética (RM) y angiorresonancia magnética&#150; se objetiva una trombosis de seno transverso izquierdo. Se realizó un estudio inmunológico (ANA, ANCA y anticuerpos antifosfolípidos), que fue normal. En el estudio de hipercoagulabilidad, la concentración de homocisteína resultó elevada de forma repetida. Tras un tratamiento anticoagulante, y medidas antiedema, evolucionó satisfactoriamente. Discusión. El 70% de las trombosis de seno venoso se deben a estados protrombóticos, entre ellos la hiperhomocisteinemia moderada. Su patogénesis parece ser multifactorial, incluido el daño endotelial directo. Por otra parte, se comenta el papel facilitador de los anticonceptivos orales sobre estados protrombóticos subclínicos, además de discutirse las posibilidades terapéuticas con ácido fólico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;37(11): 1040-1043, dic. 2003. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128654</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trombosis venosa cerebral en relación con la hiperhomocisteinemia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34258^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33775^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33775^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34258^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3295^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33775^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33775^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34258^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
