<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150403</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychiatric comorbidity in a sample of cocaine-dependent outpatients seen in the Community of Madrid drug addiction care network</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of this study was to estimate the current prevalence of psychiatric disorders in cocaine-dependent patients who attend different treatment centres in the Community of Madrid. A prospective multicentre study was used, and a total of 197 cocainedependent subjects were assessed. The assessment instrument used for diagnosis was the Psychiatric Research Interview for Substance and Mental Disorders (PRISM-IV). The main findings of this study were a high prevalence of psychiatric comorbidity in cocaine-dependent patients seeking treatment (64.0%). The most common Non Substance Use Disorders found were attention-deficit/hyperactivity Disorders (34.5%) and depressive disorders (13.7%). The most common Substance Use Disorder was alcohol dependence (28.4%). Cocaine-dependent patients who had a depressive disorder and were alcohol dependent presented a more severe clinical profile and a higher degree of psychopathology, measured using different assessment tools, than the patients who were only cocaine dependent. These data suggest that the presence of psychiatric comorbidity could constitute a risk factor associated with the severity of cocaine dependence. The clinical heterogeneity found also indicates the need to search for individualised treatments that more specifically fit the needs of this population (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rubio Valladolid, Gabriel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferre Navarrete, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peñas Pascual, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fraguas Herráez, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual Arriazu, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Gras, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iceta Ruz de Gauna, Mariano de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio fue estimar la prevalencia actual de trastornos psiquiátricos en pacientes dependientes de cocaína atendidos en los diferentes centros de tratamiento en la Comunidad de Madrid. Se trata de un estudio multicéntrico prospectivo realizado con una muestra de 197 sujetos con dependencia de cocaína. El instrumento de evaluación utilizado fue la Psychiatric Research Interview for Substance and Mental Disorders (PRISM-IV) (Entrevista de Investigación Psiquiátrica para Trastornos Mentales y Sustancias). La prevalencia actual de comorbilidad psiquiátrica encontrada fue del 64.0%. Los trastornos psiquiátricos más frecuentes no relacionados con el consumo fueron el trastorno por déficit de atención e hiperactividad (34,5%) y los trastornos depresivos (13,7%). El trastorno por uso de sustancias más frecuente fue la dependencia del alcohol (28.4%). Los pacientes dependientes de cocaína que presentaron un trastorno depresivo y los que presentaron dependencia del alcohol mostraron un perfil clínico de mayor gravedad y un mayor grado de psicopatología medido a través de diferentes instrumentos de evaluación en relación con los pacientes que sólo presentaban dependencia de la cocaína. Estos datos sugieren que la presencia de comorbilidad psiquiátrica podría constituir un factor de riesgo asociado a la gravedad de la dependencia de la cocaína. La heterogeneidad clínica encontrada recomienda la búsqueda de tratamientos individualizados que se ajusten de manera mas especifica a las necesidades de esta población. (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);28(1): 6-18, 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150403</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comorbilidad psiquiátrica en una muestra de pacientes con dependencia de cocaína atendidos ambulatoriamente en la red drogas de la Comunidad de Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d555^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d555^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33536^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33536^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23312^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
