<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100384</identifier>
<setSpec>2174-5544</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">BACs-on-Beads&#153; technology applied to prenatal diagnosis and the cytogenetic study of abortion remains</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACs-on-Beads (BoBs) technology is based on DNA sequences from Bacterial Artificial Chromosomes fixed in Luminex® microspheres. The study sample and the reference DNA are labeled with similar but complementary BoBsTM probes. After the hybridisation, signal intensities were analysed using the Luminex® 100/200 instrumental system. This technology has been applied to rapid prenatal diagnosis with a kit designed to analyse aneuploidy for chromosomes 13, 18, 21 and sex chromosomes, and a panel of 9 microdeletion syndromes: DiGeorge, Williams-Beuren, Prader-Willi, Angelman, Smith-Magenis, Wolf-Hirschhorn, Cri du Chat, Langer-Giedion, and Miller-Dieker syndrome. Based on a similar technology, KaryoLite-BoBsTM kit allows the identification of aneuploidy for all 24 chromosomes, and can be applied to the analysis of products of conception, among other possibilities. In this study we present our current experience in the application of BAC-on-BeadsTM technology in 332 amniotic fluid samples; 48 chorionic villus samples and 71 samples from products of conception(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Herrero, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio Lluesa, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos-Galindo, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayala-Álvarez, Gustavo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Conejero, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La tecnología de BACs-on-Beads utiliza sondas de ADN procedentes de Cromosomas Artificiales Bacterianos o BAC fijados en microesferas Luminex®. La muestra marcada y los ADN de referencia marcados se hibridan respectivamente con las mismas sondas BoBsTM complementarias. Después de la hibridación se leen las intensidades de la sen&#152; al mediante el sistema instrumental Luminex® 100/200. Se puede aplicar al diagnóstico prenatal rápido con un kit disen&#152; ado para descartar aneuploidías para los cromosomas 13, 18, 21 y los cromosomas sexuales así como ganancias y pérdidas de ADN asociadas con 9 síndromes de microdeleción como son: Síndrome de DiGeorge, Síndrome de Williams-Beuren, Síndrome de Prader-Willi, Síndrome de Angelman, Síndrome de Smith-Magenis, Síndrome de Wolf-Hirschhorn, Síndrome de Cri du Chat, Síndrome de Langer-Giedion, y Síndrome de Miller-Dieker. Basados en esta misma tecnología se ha desarrollado un kit llamado KaryoLite-BoBsTM, que permite descartar aneuploidías para los 24 cromosomas y que se puede aplicar al estudio de alteraciones cromosómicas numéricas en restos abortivos. En este trabajo se presentan los resultados de nuestro grupo tras la aplicación de la tecnología de BAC-on-BeadsTM en 332 muestras de líquido amniótico, 48 muestras de vellosidades coriales y en el estudio de aneuploidías en 71 muestras de restos abortivos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Diagn. prenat. (Internet);23(2): 76-82, abr.-jun.2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100384</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tecnología BACs-on-Beads&#153; aplicada al diagnóstico prenatal y al estudio citogenético de restos abortivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11655^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3600^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3600^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4100^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22152</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d793</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53964^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53964^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22152^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11655^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50244</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
