<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79570</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Individualistic and collectivistic work values of female and male nurses in multicultural environment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: Identify whether individualistic or collectivistic values prevail within the nursing profession and whether the profile of prevailing values remains the same for both men and women. Check whether there exist gender differences in the degree to which these professionals participate in both individualistic and collectivistic values. Material and Methods: The scale of measure used is the EVAT-30. The participants were 186 female and male nurses from an public hospital, located in the South of Spain. analyses of mean difference, t tests, and MANOVA analyses were carried out. Results: Both genders value more individualistic work values than collectivistic values. Female nurses show a higher preference for individualistic values than male nurses, there being no gender differences in respect to collectivistic values. Conclusions: We suggest the necessity to explore in greater depth the analysis of these values relating them with the efficency of nursing workgroups and to identify the factors that determine the gender differences (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salinas Martínez de Lecea,  J. María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar Luzón, M del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo-Salguero, Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Comprobar si en los profesionales de enfermería predominan los valores individualistas o los colectivistas y si el perfil de valores predominante se mantiene tanto en las mujeres como en los hombres. Comprobar si existen diferencias de género en el grado en el que estos profesionales participan de los valores individualistas y colectivistas. Material y Métodos: La escala de medida utilizada es la EVAT-30. Los participantes fueron 186 enfermeros de un hospital público ubicado al Sur de España. Se realizaron análisis de diferencias de media, prueba t y análisis MANOVA. Resultados: Ambos géneros valoran más los valores laborales individualistas que los colectivistas. Las enfermeras prefieren más los valores individualistas que los enfermeros, no existiendo diferencias de género en los valores colectivistas. Conclusiones: Se sugiere la necesidad de profundizar en el análisis de estos valores relacionándolos con la eficacia de los equipos de trabajo en enfermería e identificando los factores que determinan las diferencias de género (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;17(4): 5-5, oct.-dic. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79570</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valores laborales individualistas y colectivistas de enfermeras y enfermeros en un entorno multicultural</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3487</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16629</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9912^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
