<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115377</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Is there a specific relationship between childhood separation anxiety and the later development of panic and agoraphobia disorders?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">One persistent hypothesis in the literature is that heightened levels of early separation anxiety are a specific risk factor for developing panic disorder (with or without agoraphobia). In the review carried out by Silove, Manicavasagar, Curtis, &amp; Blaszczynski (1996) these authors concluded that both phenomena were associated, but whether this association reflected a specific relationship or existed also in relation to other disorders was an issue that remained inconclusive. Moreover, they advanced the hypothesis of the possible persistence of early separation anxiety disorder into adulthood, rendering the sufferer vulnerable to panic. Since then, a number of studies have investigated this question, some of them prospectively, so the present article aims to review them critically. The analysis of 28 studies confirms the association between separation anxiety and panic disorder, but it raises great doubts about the specificity of such relationship. Furthermore, separation anxiety disorder also exists in adulthood, but its relationship with panic disorder does not seem to be specific either</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bados, Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reinoso, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benedito, Núria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Diversos autores han afirmado que el nivel elevado de ansiedad por separación en la infancia es un factor específico de riesgo para el trastorno de pánico (con o sin agorafobia). En la revisión realizada por Silove, Manicavasagar, Curtis y Blaszczynski (1996) estos autores concluyeron que ambos fenómenos están asociados, pero que los datos eran inconsistentes sobre si esta asociación era específica o existía también respecto a otros trastornos. Además, avanzaron la hipótesis de que el trastorno por ansiedad de separación en la infancia puede progresar a un trastorno equivalente en la adultez y predisponer al desarrollo del pánico. Debido a que desde entonces han surgido numerosos estudios sobre el tema, algunos de ellos prospectivos, llevamos a cabo una revisión crítica de los mismos. El análisis de los 28 estudios confirma la asociación entre ansiedad por separación y trastorno de pánico, pero plantea grandes dudas sobre la especificidad de esta relación. Por otra parte, el trastorno de ansiedad por separación se da en la adultez, pero su relación con el trastorno de pánico tampoco parece específica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;16(2): 143-161, mayo-ago. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115377</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Existe una relación específica entre la ansiedad por separación en la infancia y la aparición posterior de los trastornos de pánico y agorafobia?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1015^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d383^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29912^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200808</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
