<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130242</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Previous abstinence time as a predictive factor at 12 months follow-up in a multi-component smoking cessation program</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The objective of this study is to analyze the length of the longest period of previous abstinence time as a predictor of the results of a smoking cessation program at 12 months follow-up. Material and methods. A cross-sectional study was conducted on a sample of 475 smokers who had participated in a multi-component smoking cessation group therapy program. The independent variable is the longest abstinence time passed, measured in weeks, before the current treatment. Success was defined as self-reported abstinence. Bivariate analyses were applied to the independent variable and to other variables in order to determine the factors that would be part of a logistic regression model using contrasts Student t or &amp;#967;2 comparisons, as appropriate. Those that showed statistical significance were entered into a multivariate logistic regression model. Results. Within the studied variables, previous abstinence time and sex were the only predictive variables of success at 12 month follow-up. Conclusions. The probability of being abstinent at 12 months follow-up was significantly associated with the length of the previous longest period of abstinence, and this is the best of the predictors considered. Successful cessation programs depend more on the relationship with the consumer biographical aspects than with biological factors. The history of previous attempts is a more valuable source of information for designing treatments than others traditionally considered (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Arnedillo, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Vegazo-Sánchez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morante-Benadero, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El objetivo de esta investigación es analizar la variable tiempo previo de abstinencia como factor predictor en un programa de deshabituación tabáquica a los 12 meses de seguimiento. Material y métodos. Se ha realizado un estudio analítico transversal en una muestra formada por 475 fumadores que habían accedido a una unidad de tabaquismo para un tratamiento multicomponente en grupo. Como variable independiente se toma el tiempo de abstinencia más largo por el que ha pasado el individuo previamente al tratamiento actual, medido en semanas. Se consideró éxito la abstinencia autodeclarada. Se aplicaron análisis bivariantes para la variable independiente considerada y para otras variables, con el fin de determinar qué factores podrían estar formando parte de un modelo de regresión logística, utilizando contrastes t de Student o prueba &amp;#967;2, según procediera. Aquellas que mostraron significación estadística se introdujeron en un modelo de regresión logística multivariante. Resultados. El tiempo previo sin fumar y el sexo son las únicas variables predictoras de éxito a los 12 meses de seguimiento, entre las consideradas. Conclusiones. La probabilidad de permanecer abstinente en el seguimiento a los 12 meses está significativamente asociada a la duración del período previo más largo de abstinencia, y es el mejor de los predictores considerados. El éxito en los programas de deshabituación depende más de la relación biográfica con el consumo que de aspectos biológicos. La historia de intentos previos es una fuente de información más valiosa para diseñar los tratamientos que otras variables tradicionalmente consideradas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);40(8): 436-440, nov.-dic. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130242</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El tiempo previo de abstinencia como factor predictor a los 12 meses en un programa multicomponente para dejar de fumar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29815^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51528</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29815^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29815^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13761^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29815^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29815^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
