<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107469</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-7546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship between Health-Related Fitness and Quality of life in elderly with type 2 diabetes: an exploratory study in the province of Seville</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To characterize the type 2 diabetic (DM2) population treated in primary care consultations in regard of Health-Related Fitness (HRF) and Health-Related Quality of Life (HRQoL), and, on the other hand, to confirm if there is a relationship between HRF and HRQoL in DM2 patients. Methods. A cross-sectional, observational, case-control study was performed to compare the HRF and HRQoL between 42 DM2 patients and 54 patients without DM2 and the relationship between these two concepts was revealed. Results. In regard of HRF, statistically significant differences were found in the hand dynamometer test in favor of DM2 patients group (p=, 025) and statistically significant differences were achieved in favor of the reference group in sit and reach test (p=, 001). Pearson´s correlation coefficient revealed a moderate to high level of correlation between the different dimensions and index of EQ-5D-3L and strength, mobility and balance tests (p&lt;,05). Conclusions. This study showsthe relationship between EQ-5D-3L componentsand strength, mobility and balance tests in DM2 patients treated in primary care, key functional capacities to a correct development of daily activities in these patients(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pozo-Cruz, J. T. del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alfonso-Rosa, R. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caraballo Daza, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pozo-Cruz, J. del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pozo-Cruz, B. del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Caracterizar a la población adulta-mayor afectada por diabetes mellitus tipo 2 (DM2) tratada en las consultas de atención primaria en cuanto al nivel de condición física relacionada con la salud (CFRS) y calidad de vida relacionada con la salud (CVRS), y por otro lado, corroborar si existe relación entre los diferentes test de CFRS y la CVRS. Método. Se utilizó un diseño transversal observacional de casos y controles para comparar la CFRS y la CVRS (evaluada mediante el cuestionario EQ-5D-3L) entre 42 pacientes con DM2 y 54 pacientes sin DM2, y se estableció la relación existente entre la CFRS y la CVRS en los pacientes con DM2. Resultados. En cuanto a la CFRS, los pacientes con DM2 obtuvieron mayores resultados en el test de dinamometría manual que sus pares sin dicha afección (p &lt; 0,025). Los valores alcanzados en el test sit and reach fueron mayores en el grupo control que en el grupo DM2 (p &lt; 0,001). No se detectaron diferencias estadísticamente significativas en cuanto a la CVRS entre ambos grupos. El coeficiente de correlación de Pearson desveló un nivel de correlación de moderado a alto entre los componentes de la CVRS y los test de fuerza, movilidad y equilibrio que componen la CFRS (p &lt; 0,05). Conclusiones. Este estudio muestra la asociación existente entre la CVRS evaluada con el EQ-5D-3L y los test de fuerza, movilidad y equilibrio dinámico en pacientes con DM2 tratados en atención primaria, cualidades vitales para el desarrollo de las actividades de la vida diaria de estos pacientes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. andal. med. deporte;5(3): 91-98, sept. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107469</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asociación entre la condición física relacionada con la salud y la calidad de vida en pacientes diabéticos tipo 2 tratados en atención primaria: un estudio exploratorio en la provincia de Sevilla</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12034^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
