<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96969</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-1285</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Aesthetic all-ceramic restorations. Cercon System</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aesthetic dentistry is dedicated to imitate nature by maintaining the size, shape, colour and symmetry. Technology has developed metal-free ceramic materials so capable of reproducing a natural appearance, that traditional materials have been replaced by them. The yttrium partially-stabilized zirconium oxide does not only have the advantage of being extremelly resistant, but it is also highly translucent. It has a translucency that allows about 50% of the incident light to pass through, a characteristic that is vital for providing a more natural appearance to restorations. The duration of scanning and milling procedures will depend on the size of the object, the number of objects proccessed and the steps selected (CAM or CAD/CAM). The framework of the densely sintered zirconium oxide with its precise fit is veneered with the veneering ceramic developed especially for this purpose. Almost in all cases, there are several treatment alternatives for the same diagnosis. The success of these restorations will be predicted as long as it is founded on sustaining biological principles. The aim of this paper is to concisely present the sequences for a clinical treatment in a schematic and illustrative manner (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Bodereau, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bessone, LM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabanillas, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La estética en odontología está orientada a imitar la naturaleza, a tratar de conservar las proporciones, las formas, el color, la simetría. La tecnología ha desarrollado materiales cerámicos libres de metal que han reemplazado a los materiales tradicionales, capaces de imitar mejor a la naturaleza. El óxido de circonio parcialmente estabilizado con itrio, no solo es extremadamente resistente, sino que posee la ventaja de ser altamente translucido. Su translucidez de aproximadamente el 50% de la luz incidente, permite la elaboración de restauraciones con apariencia natural. La duración del proceso de escaneado y fresado dependerá del tamaño del objeto, del número de objetos procesados y de los pasos seleccionados (CAM o CAD/CAM). La estructura de óxido de circonio densamente sinterizado con su preciso ajuste, se cubre con la cerámica de recubrimiento que ha sido especialmente desarrollada para este propósito. En casi todos los casos que se nos plantean hay un solo diagnóstico, pero distintas alternativas de plantear el tratamiento. El éxito de estas restauraciones será predecible siempre que se fundamente en el conocimiento de los principios biológicos que la sustentan. El objetivo de esta publicación es exponer de manera concisa las bases teóricas a modo esquemático y las imágenes de la secuencia del tratamiento clínico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av Odontoestomatol;27(5): 231-240, sept.-oct. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96969</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Restauraciones estéticas de porcelana pura. Sistema Cercon</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3791^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30762^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3808^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201100</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
