<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59897</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Early Detection of Addictive Behaviour in Primary Health Care. Use of MULTICAGE CAD-4</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To find out the frequency of specific disorders within the general population using primary healthcare relating to the control of impulses with addictive risk. Design: A cross-sectional descriptive study. Location: Urban health centre, Area 9 of the Madrid Health Service (Spain). ParticipantsA total of 457 patients who came to primary care (PA) were selected by consecutive sampling. Method: Self-completion of the MULTICAGE-CAD4 survey (which measure eight scales for the risky behaviour being studied). Results: There was a risk in at least one of the scales in 46.4% of the sample, of which 17.3% (13.7-20.9) showed risky behaviour on the alcohol scale; 9% (6.2-11.7) for other drugs; 4.4% (2.4-6.4) for gambling; 9.4% (6.6-12.2) for addiction to the Internet; 4.8% (2.7-6.7) for addiction to videogames; 18.8% (15.1-22.5) for eating disorders; 16% (12.5-19.4) for compulsive shopping and 5.5% (3.3-7.7) for addiction to sex. The occurrence of addiction to alcohol, gambling and sex were higher for men, while eating disorders were more prevalent in women. Conclusions: We are facing a widespread set of problems related to addictions that are often hidden; this study shows that these addictions can be detected within primary healthcare by effective screening tools such as MULTICAGE CAD-4, which is both economic, and easy to implement within primary healthcare centres(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gallardo Alonso, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedrero Pérez, Eduardo J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz Cuesta, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Monje, M. Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Girón, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: conocer las frecuencias de determinados trastornos de control de los impulsos con riesgo adictivo en la población consultante en atención primaria. Diseño: estudio descriptivo transversal. Emplazamiento: centro de salud urbano del Área 9 del Servicio Madrileño de Salud. Participantes: 457 pacientes que acudieron a consultas de atención primaria (AP) seleccionados mediante muestreo consecutivo. Mediciones principalesautocumplimentación de la encuesta MULTICAGE-CAD4 (que mide ocho escalas correspondientes a los comportamientos de riesgo que se estudian). Resultados: el 46,4% tenía al menos una de las escalas alterada. Mostró comportamiento de riesgo en la escala del alcohol el 17,3% (13,7-20,9) y en la de otras drogas, el 9% (6,2-11,7); en el juego, el 4,4% (2,4-6,4); en la de internet, el 9,4% (6,6-12,2) y en los videojuegos, el 4,8% (2,7-6,9); en la conducta alimentaria, el 18,8% (15,1-22,5); en el gasto compulsivo, el 16% (12,5-19,4) y en el sexo compulsivo, el 5,5% (3,3-7,7). Las escalas de alcohol, ludopatía y adicción al sexo están más frecuentemente alteradas entre los varones y los trastornos de la alimentación más entre las mujeres. Conclusiones: los comportamientos de riesgo adictivo son frecuentes en la población consultante; casi la mitad de la muestra tiene puntuaciones con criterio para estimar como problemática al menos una de las conductas exploradas. Las conductas de riesgo más frecuentes fueron los trastornos de la alimentación, el consumo de alcohol y el gasto compulsivo. Entre los jóvenes menores de 25 años, el gasto compulsivo y el abuso de internet(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;41(1): 25-32, ene. 2009. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59897</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Detección precoz de conductas adictivas en atención primaria: utilización del MULTICAGE CAD-4</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30236^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200901</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
