<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88288</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Viral gastroenteritis in hospitalized children. A multicentre prospective study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The objective of this study was to determine prospectively the viral etiology of acute gastroenteritis (AGE) in hospitalized weaning babies and describe the clinical characteristics of the principal virus detected. Patients and methods: All children aged 1 to 23 months admitted to 3 hospitals during October 2006-March 2007 were followed for the presence of AGE from the time of hospital admission until 72 hours after hospital discharge. A stool sample of children with AGE was tested for calicivirus (norovirus and sapovirus), rotavirus, adenovirus and astrovirus by RT-PCR. Results: Of the 1,576 hospitalized children, 1,300 (82.5%)were fully monitored being our study cohort. A total of 242children had AGE (18.6% of the cohort) and stool samples from217 children were obtained (89.7%). In 91 cases (42%) were positive to rotavirus, 72 (33.2%) to norovirus, 7 (3.2%) to astrovirus, and in 2 to adenovirus, not detecting sapovirus in any case, 13 children (6%) showed mixed infections by two or more viruses and 32 (14.7%) cases were negative for the analyzed virus. Norovirus AGE have less apathy and weight loss than thecases of rotavirus but a higher percentage of stools with blood. Conclusions: The viruses are a frequent cause of AGE among the hospitalized children of less than 2 years of age being rotavirus the principal virus found followed by norovirus. Few clinical differences were observed between rotavirus and norovirus and analytical determination is necessary for their differentiation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Gimeno, M. V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Asensi-Botet, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pons Morales, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Moreno, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Correcher-Medina, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bretón Martínez, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Fauquier, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez-Domingo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El objetivo de este estudio fue determinar prospectivamente la etiología vírica de la gastroenteritis aguda (GEA) en lactantes hospitalizados, así como describir las características clínicas de los principales virus. Pacientes y métodos: Desde octubre de 2006 hasta marzo de2007, se realizó el seguimiento de todos los niños de 1-23 meses de edad hospitalizados en tres hospitales, desde el momento de la admisión hasta las 72 horas tras el alta, para detectarla presencia de GEA. Se analizó una muestra de heces de los niños con GEA para la detección de rotavirus, calicivirus (norovirus y sapovirus), astrovirus y adenovirus mediante transcripción inversa y reacción en cadena de la polimerasa. Resultados: De un total de 1.576 pacientes hospitalizados, se pudo realizar el seguimiento de 1.300 (82,5%), que han constituido nuestra cohorte de estudio. Un total de 242 niños tuvieron GEA (un 18,6% de la cohorte), obteniéndose muestra de heces de 217 (89,7%). En 91 casos (42%) se detectaron rotavirus, en 72 norovirus (33,2%), en 7 astrovirus (3,2%) y en2 adenovirus; no se detectó sapovirus en ningún caso. Trece niños (6%) presentaron infecciones mixtas por dos o más virus, y 32 (14,7%) resultaron negativos para todos los virus analizados. En los casos de GEA por norovirus se observa menor apatía y pérdida de peso que en los casos de rotavirus, pero mayorporcentaje de heces con sangre.Conclusiones: Los virus son una causa frecuente de GEA enlos niños menores de 2 años hospitalizados; el principal virus hallado es el rotavirus, seguido del norovirus. Debido a las escasas diferencias clínicas observadas entre rotavirus y norovirus, es necesaria su determinación analítica para su diferenciación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;69(2): 53-59, feb. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88288</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gastroenteritis vírica en niños hospitalizados. Estudio prospectivo multicéntrico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35604^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31778^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2711^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21079^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2172^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d267^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1265^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
