<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-9494</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of a dessert in patients with dysphagia, one more set in advanced basic nutrition</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Decrease in the capacity to deglution solids and liquids is a problem in many people, this problem decreases quality of life. The objective of our work is to evaluate the acceptance degree of a dessert (stewed fruit) (including in the normal diet of the Hospital) in a group of patients with dysphagia.  Methods: Forty seven patients were studied in Hospital Universitario del Rio Hortega (Valladolid) in July of 2000. The main pathology of these patients was; (n = 12) 25,5% acute stroke, (n = 16) 34% aero-digestive tumors (larynx carcinoma (n = 5), cavum carcinoma (n = 9), oesaphagus carcinoma (n = 2)) and 40,4% (n = 19) chronic neurologic disease (Alzheimer, vascular dementia, and parkinson). All patients took a oral triturated diet, a dessert with apple and pear (Resource fruits Instant®). All patients took a portion of the dessert and after that a acceptance questionnaire was filled.  Results: Global acceptance of the product was 7,25 ± 1,5, this punctuation was higher in the tumoral group 8 ± 1,1 points, 6,86 ± 1,4 in patients with acute stroke and 6,7 ± 1,5 in patients with chronic neurologic disease (p &lt; 0,05). Different organoleptic characteristics were analyzed, mean punctuation in texture was 1,79 ± 0,6, color 2,2 ± 0,5, smell 2,24 ± 0,59 and taste 1,95 ± 0,61, in a scale of 1 (very good) until 5 (very bad), a total of 57,9% patients responded very good (1) or good (2) in texture scale, 71,1% in color scale, 60,5% in smell scale and 63,2% in taste scale. Conclusion: Acceptance of this product in patients with dysphagia has been elevated, showing useful in these patients with nutrition alterations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Grupo Aula Médica, S.A.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: Las dificultades para deglutir alimentos y bebidas son un problema en la vida de muchas personas, constituyendo un claro detrimento en su calidad de vida. El objetivo de nuestro trabajo es evaluar el grado de aceptación de un postre en forma de compota incluido en la dieta hospitalaria de un grupo de pacientes con alteraciones en la deglución. Métodos: Estudiamos un total de 47 pacientes ingresados en el Hospital Universitario del Río Hortega (Valladolid) en julio del 2000. Los motivos de ingreso de estos pacientes fueron los siguientes: (n = 12) 25,5 por ciento accidentes cerebrovasculares agudos, (n = 16) 34 por ciento tumores del tracto aéreo-digestivo superior [neoplasia de laringe (n = 5), neoplasia de orofaringe (n = 9), neoplasia de esófago (n = 2)] y un 40,4 por ciento (n = 19) patología neurológica degenerativa (demencia de Alzheimer, demencia, multiinfarto y parkinson avanzado). A todos los pacientes se les administró con la dieta pautada oral (dieta triturada), un postre en forma de compota con sabor a manzana y pera (Resource compota de frutas Instant®).Se administró a cada paciente una ración del postre y posteriormente se realizó una encuesta de satisfacción. Resultados: La valoración global del producto por parte de los pacientes fue de 7,25 ñ 1,5 sobre 10, fue superior en el grupo de pacientes con tumores alcanzando una puntuación de 8 ñ 1,1 frente a 6,86 ñ 1,4 en pacientes con accidente cerebrovascular y 6,7 ñ 1,5 en pacientes con alteraciones neurológicas crónicas (p &lt; 0,05). Al analizar la aceptación del producto en sus diferentes apartados la media obtenida por la textura fue de 1,79 ñ 0,6, color 2,2 ñ 0,5, olor 2,24 ñ 0,59 y sabor 1,95 ñ 0,61, en una escala del 1 (muy bueno) al 5 (muy malo), de este modo un 57,9 por ciento de los pacientes respondieron que la textura era muy buena (1) o buena (2), un 71,1 por ciento que el color era bueno o muy bueno, un 60,5 por ciento que el olor era bueno o muy bueno así como un 63,2 por ciento en cuanto al sabor. Conclusión: La aceptación por parte de los pacientes con disfagia de este producto ha sido elevada, mostrándose por tanto útil en este grupo de pacientes donde las alteraciones nutricionales son frecuentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;16(2): 55-58, mar. 2001. tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de un postre en pacientes con alteración en la deglución, un paso más en la alimentación básica avanzada</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Cabezas, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Terroba, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izaola, O </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luis, DA de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuéllar, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aller, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-9494</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
