<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103809</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Towards the new spectral-domain optical coherence tomography based classification of age-related macular degeneration</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Age-related macular degeneration (AMD) is major social and health problem in industrialised societies. The contribution of the new diagnostic techniques, mainly spectral-domain optical coherence tomography (SD-OCT), has led to a better understanding of this disease. Aim: To review the current clinical classification of AMD, to describe the new tomographic classification of wet AMD, and to review the new topographical findings in dry AMD. Development: There are two classically described forms of AMD: dry and wet; there are also three progressive stages of severity: early, intermediate and advanced. This purely clinical stratification does not take into account any criteria based on SD-OCT. On the other hand, a new SD-OCT based classification has been proposed for choroidal neovascularisations secondary to AMD: types 1 (equivalent to occult), 2 (equivalent to classic), and 3 (equivalent to retinal angiomatous proliferation). Finally, SD-OCT offers exclusive and valuable information on the evaluation of dry AMD as regards subretinal drusenoid deposits, drusenoid pigment epithelium detachments, drusen coalescence, or the appearance of subretinal fluid in absence of choroidal neovascularisation. Conclusions: Dry AMD exhibits a range of tomographical signs that also have their own relative risk of progression to advance stages of the disease. We need an international consensus in order to follow-up and treat in the best way all those patients with AMD, not only with the wet but also with the dry form(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dolz-Marco, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Llopis, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego-Pinazo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La degeneración macular asociada a la edad (DMAE) es un problema sociosanitario de primer orden en las sociedades industrializadas. La aportación de las nuevas técnicas diagnósticas, fundamentalmente la tomografía de coherencia óptica de dominio espectral (SD-OCT), ha ayudado a comprender mejor esta enfermedad. Objetivo: Recordar la clasificación clínica vigente de la DMAE, exponer la nueva clasificación tomográfica de la DMAE exudativa, y revisar los nuevos nuevos hallazgos tomográficos de la degeneración macular seca. Desarrollo: Clásicamente se distinguen dos formas de DMAE: seca y exudativa; asimismo existen tres estadios progresivos de severidad: precoz, intermedio y tardío. Esta estratificación puramente clínica de la enfermedad no hace referencia a criterios basados en la SD-OCT. Por otra parte, se ha sugerido una nueva clasificación de las neovascularizaciones coroideas secundarias a DMAE fundamentada en la SD-OCT: tipos 1 (equivalente a la oculta), 2 (equivalente a la clásica) y 3 (equivalente a la proliferación angiomatosa retiniana). Por último, la SD-OCT aporta una valiosa y exclusiva información en la evaluación de la DMAE seca sobre los depósitos drusenoides subretinianos, los desprendimientos drusenoides del epitelio pigmentario, la coalescencia de las drusas, o la aparición de fluido subretiniano en ausencia de neovascularización coroidea. Conclusiones: La DMAE seca presenta un espectro de signos tomográficos que además cuentan con unos riesgos propios de progresión hacia formas avanzadas de la enfermedad. Se hace necesario un consenso internacional para poder seguir y tratar de la mejor manera a todos los pacientes englobados dentro del espectro de la DMAE, no solo en su forma exudativa, sino también en su forma seca(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;87(8): 247-252, ago. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103809</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hacia la nueva clasificación de la degeneración macular asociada a la edad basada en la tomografía de coherencia óptica de dominio espectral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8440^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33766</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53858</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24863</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8440^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8440^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24818</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34460</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8440^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24866</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34460^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
