<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150556</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impaired awareness of hypoglycaemia in subjects with type 1 diabetes. Results of an online survey in a diabetes web site</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the frequency of impaired awareness of hypoglycaemia (IAH) using a specific questionnaire (Spanish version) in a free access diabetes-related web site. Methods: Data from a free access Spanish version of the Clarke test previously uploaded to the website of the Fundación para la Diabetes (March 2014&#150;January 2015) were assessed. In addition to the eight questions in Clarke's questionnaire, information on type of diabetes, age, and disease duration was obtained. The Clarke test divided participants into three categories: normal awareness, uncertain and IAH. Results: Of the 418 participants with type 1 diabetes, 51.2% were aged 36&#150;55 years. In 34.7%, diabetes had been diagnosed &gt;15 years before, while disease duration was &lt;2 years in 11%. According to Clarke categories, 23.4% had IAH, 15.3% uncertain awareness, and 61.3% normal awareness. The longer the duration of diabetes, the higher the Clarke test score. According to the Clarke test, 14.1% of participants had experienced at least one episode of severe hypoglycaemia in the previous year, and half of these (7.4%) had suffered severe hypoglycaemia two or more times. All but one of the participants with two or more episodes of severe hypoglycaemia had IAH. Conclusions: Our study shows that the rate of IAH using an online survey is similar (25%) to that previously reported in other geographical areas, increases with diabetes duration, and identifies subjects prone to severe hypoglycaemia  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quiros, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salaverria, Vanesa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ávila, Dalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conget, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giménez, Marga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dueñas, Belen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar la frecuencia de hipoglucemia desapercibida (HD) en una amplia cohorte de pacientes adultos con diabetes tipo 1 (DT1) a través de un cuestionario específico disponible para ser rellenado en la Web de manera voluntaria. Metodología: Desde marzo de 2014 a enero de 2015 se recogieron los resultados del cuestionario en lengua española de percepción de la hipoglucemia para adultos con DT1 (Test de Clarke versión en castellano) disponible on-line en la página Web de la Fundación para la Diabetes. Además, la encuesta on-line incluía datos sobre el tipo de diabetes, la edad y el tiempo de evolución de la enfermedad. La puntuación final del cuestionario cataloga a los pacientes en 3 categorías: percepción normal, indeterminada y anormal-HD ante una situación de hipoglucemia. Resultados: De los 418 participantes con DT1 el 51,2% tenía una edad entre 36-55 años. En el 34,7% la DT1 la diabetes tenía una duración &gt; 15 años y en el 11% menos de 2 años. De acuerdo con el resultado del cuestionario de Clarke, un 23,4% de los pacientes presentaba una HD, un 15,3% una percepción indeterminada y en el 61,3% el resultado fue normal. A mayor duración de la DT1, mayor puntuación del cuestionario. El 14,1% de los participantes había tenido una hipoglucemia grave durante el año anterior y la mitad de ellos (7,4%) había presentado &amp;#8805; 2 episodios. De estos últimos todos, excepto uno, presentaban HD. Conclusión: Como en estudios precedentes realizados en otras áreas geográficas, nuestro estudio demuestra que casi una cuarta parte de los pacientes con DT1 tiene alterada la capacidad para percibir los síntomas de hipoglucemia. Esta anomalía es más frecuente conforme aumenta la duración de la enfermedad, e identifica las personas en riesgo de presentar hipoglucemia grave (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;63(3): 121-125, mar. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150556</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hipoglucemia desapercibida en personas con diabetes tipo 1. Resultados de una encuesta &#147;on line&#148; en una Web de diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54008^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53806^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7181^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
