<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155159</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Painful sensitive neuropathies include disorders of the peripheral nervous system whose main symptom is pain. In general, at the initial stages it is difficult to determine if pain is the neuropathic cause or if it has another origin, mainly due to the lack of objective data in the clinical examination, so more complex additional examinations are usually required. Within this group of diseases, the most frequent forms are diabetic painful neuropathy and those associated to AIDS. The latter have increased in frequency due both to the increased survival rate of these patients and the use of new antiviral drugs with peripheral neurotoxic effects. Pain associated to herpes zoster and postherpetic neuralgia are considered as secondary to injury of the peripheral nervous system, despite some authors have also described injuries in the central nervous system (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Íñiguez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las neuropatías sensitivas dolorosas incluyen las alteraciones del sistema nervioso periférico cuyo síntoma fundamental es el dolor. En general en los momentos iniciales es difícil determinar si el dolor es de causa neuropática o de otro origen, debido sobre todo a la escasez de datos objetivos en la exploración clínica, por lo que suele ser necesario recurrir a exploraciones complementarias más complejas. Dentro de este grupo de enfermedades las formas más frecuentes son la neuropatía dolorosa diabética y las asociadas al sida. Estas últimas están aumentando en frecuencia tanto por el incremento en la supervivencia de estos pacientes como por la utilización de nuevos fármacos anti-virales con efectos neurotóxicos periféricos. El dolor asociado al herpes zóster y la neuralgia postherpética, se consideran secundarios a lesión del sistema nervioso periférico aunque algunos autores también han descrito lesiones en el sistema nervioso central (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;7(supl.2): 49-59, 2000. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155159</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neuropatía sensitivas dolorosas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1348^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50489^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50489^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9672^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9672^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6721^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50489^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11566^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6721^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2616^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23777^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23777^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23777^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1343^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1349^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1349^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
