<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122526</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Health care circuit for patients with soft tissue sarcomas of the extremities. A tortuous and slow road to referral units</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyse the waiting periods elapsed since soft tissue sarcomas become symptomatic until their specific treatment in our unit, and to determine new strategies for the improvement of referral circuits. Material and methods: This is an ambispective observational study of a cohort of 61 patients, with previously untreated soft tissue sarcomas, obtained from our Musculoskeletal Tumors Database. Several variables related to the patient, tumour, and health care circuit were analysed, as well as the different periods between the initial symptoms of the disease and the first consultation in our unit. The significance level was _=0.05. Results: The mean size of the sarcomas was 11.3 cm. Thirty-six patients (59%) followed the usual circuit of the National Health System in Spain. The time elapsed since the disease became symptomatic until the first medical consultation was greater than 9.5 months, and nearly another 8.5 months to the consultation in our specific unit. Statistically significant relationships were found between the independent and dependent variables. Discussion: The study shows that the care of patients with soft tissue sarcomas in our environment is far away from the times of care in our neighbouring countries. Conclusions: It is essential to make the population and health  professionals aware of this disease, as well as to remember that there is a referral circuit that must be used (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo García, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maderuelo, Fernández J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas Ramos, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Herráez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Pascua, L. R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar los tiempos de espera transcurridos desde que los sarcomas de partes blandas (SPB) se hacen sintomáticos hasta su tratamiento específico en nuestra Unidad de Tumores Músculo-Esqueléticos (UTME) para proponer estrategias de mejora en los circuitos de derivación. Material y métodos: Estudio observacional, longitudinal y ambispectivo de una cohorte de 61 pacientes con SPB vírgenes obtenidos e identificados de forma continúa del registro de pacientes de la UTME. Se analizó la relación entre diferentes tiempos transcurridos desde que la enfermedad se hizo sintomática hasta la primera consulta en la UTME, y diversas variables ligadas a la persona, tumor y circuito asistencial. Se usó un nivel de significación _ = 0,05. Resultados: El tamaño medio de los sarcomas fue de 11,3 cm. Treinta y seis pacientes (59%) siguieron el circuito habitual del Sistema Nacional de Salud en nuestro país. El tiempo medio transcurrido desde que la enfermedad se hizo sintomática hasta la primera consulta médica fue superior a 9,5 meses; y el que transcurrió desde esta hasta la primera en nuestra UTME fue de casi 8,5 meses. Algunas variables independientes mostraron relación estadísticamente significativa con las variables dependientes analizadas. Discusión: El estudio muestra que la asistencia a los pacientes con SPB de las extremidades en nuestro medio está muy lejos de los tiempos que transcurren en los países de nuestro entorno. Conclusiones: Parece fundamental la necesidad de concienciar a la población sobre la enfermedad y recordarla entre los profesionales sanitarios, al igual que la existencia de un circuito de derivación que es necesario utilizar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);58(3): 160-170, mayo-jun. 2014. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122526</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Circuito de asistencia a pacientes con sarcomas de partes blandas de las extremidades: un tortuoso y lento camino hasta las unidades de referencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8254^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13369^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12888^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55032^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
