<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89794</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Testing Objective Structured Clinical Evaluation (OSCE) for nursing students experience developed during the years 1995-2009</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective structured clinical examination (OSCE) has been recognized as an effective evaluation tool in the health area and has been implemented by an important sector of educational institutions, the Faculty of Medicine and School of Nursing. The present article describes the OSCE organized by the Institute of Health Studies in collaboration with the University Schools of Catalan Nursing. Between the years of 2002 and 2009, OSCE annual exams took place with the participation of 1.803 students. The global results remained stable with a median grade of slightly less than 60%, and the competence component that evaluated communicative capacity was the one in which students obtained the best results.The reliability obtained surpassed the minimum recommended by international standards. It's important underline the positive value to the students of all aspects of the test. From this experience it seems evident that it would be useful to take advantage of the OSCE tests in order to show the students their strong points and ways to improve. We should highlight, not only as a goal but also as an opportunity, the assessment by competencies that the European space of higher Education provides at the end of studies for a Nursing degree(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Castela, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solà Pola, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molins i Mesalles, Ainhoa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pulpón Segura, Anna M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las pruebas de Evaluación Clínica Objetiva y Estructurada (ECOE) han sido reconocidas como un formato eficaz de evaluación en el ámbito de la salud e implementadas por un importante sector de instituciones educativas: Facultades de Medicina y Escuelas de Enfermería. El presente artículo describe la experiencia en la realización de las pruebas ECOE organizadas por el Institut de Estudis de la Salut con la colaboración de la Escuelas Universitarias de Enfermería catalanas. Entre los años 2002 y 2009 se realizaron ECOE anuales en las que participaron 1.803 alumnos. Los resultados globales se mantuvieron estables con una nota media ligeramente inferior al 60% y la competencia que evaluó la capacidad comunicativa fue en la que los estudiantes obtuvieron mejores resultados. Las cifras de fiabilidad obtenidas superaron el mínimo recomendado por los estándares internacionales y los alumnos valoran positivamente su participación en las mismas.  De la experiencia se concluye que sería conveniente aprovechar las pruebas ECOE para mostrar a los estudiantes sus puntos fuertes y aspectos a mejorar. Cabe destacar, como un reto pero también como una oportunidad, la evaluación por competencias que contempla el Espacio Europeo de Educación Superior al final de los estudios del Grado en Enfermería(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;34(7/8): 512-519, jul.-ago. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89794</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pruebas de evaluación clínica objetiva y estructurada (ECOE) para estudiantes de enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4579^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4579^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4579^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13725^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13725^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
