<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112865</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Development in the use of endovascular techniques for the infrainguinal revascularisation of lower limbs in the period 2005-2011: Experience for a single center</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: There is a growing trend in the number of infrainguinal endovascular revascularisations being performed in recent years. Objective: The primary aim of this study is to describe the development of the use of endovascular procedures for infrainguinal revascularisation in a hospital centre since its introduction in 2005 to the present date. Material and methods: A study was conducted on the 391 infrainguinal revascularisations performed out of a total of 6.867 procedures. A cross-sectional study was performed by reviewing surgery records, surgical protocols, and medical histories, and sorting them into endovascular and open surgery. Clinical compromise and morphological technical success were analysed in the endovascular procedures group in order to compare them over the study period. Results: A large majority (81.32%) presented as critical limb ischaemia. An increasing trend was observed in the number infrainguinal revascularization procedures performed, mainly at the expense of the endovascular group, which increased both in absolute numbers and proportionally compared to open surgery procedures (23.4% to 58,5%; P&lt;0.05). A slight increase in the rate of technical success was also noted when comparing the beginning and the end of the period, although this was not statistically significant (P=0.37). Conclusions: The use of endovascular techniques in lower limb revascularisation in our institution has experienced a marked growth in recent years, with a tendency to increase further. Although we do not have the necessary data to ensure this, we believe that the use of these procedures may be an important factor in the increasing number of candidates for the lower limb revascularisations observed in our series (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salazar Alvarez, A. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riera de Cubas, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibrahim Achi, Z</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuervo Vidal, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alvarez Garcia, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernandez Heredero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las intervenciones endovasculares en el sector infrainguinal han experimentado una tendencia creciente. Objetivo: Describir la evolución que ha sufrido el uso de los procedimientos endovasculares infrainguinales en nuestro centro desde su introducción en el año 2005 hasta la actualidad. Material y métodos: De 6.867 procedimientos, fueron seleccionados los 391 de revascularización infrainguinal. Estudio de corte transversal, revisando los registros de quirófano a través de los protocolos quirúrgicos e historias clínicas, clasificándolos en procedimientos endovasculares y abiertos. Se revisó el compromiso clínico y el éxito técnico morfológico de los procedimientos endovasculares para compararlos durante el periodo. Resultados: El 81,32% fueron intervenidos por isquemia crítica. Se evidenció una tendencia al aumento global de procedimientos de revascularización infrainguinal, fundamentalmente a expensas de los endovasculares, los cuales se incrementan tanto en números absolutos como en proporción con los procedimientos abiertos (23,4 a 58,5%; p &lt; 0,05). También se observó un leve aumento de la tasa de éxito técnico al comparar el inicio y el final del periodo, aunque no estadísticamente significativo (p = 0,37). Conclusiones: El uso de técnicas endovasculares en la revascularización de miembros inferiores en nuestro centro ha ido en claro aumento en los últimos años, presentando una tendencia a seguir incrementándose. Aunque no poseemos datos que nos permitan asegurarlo, pensamos que el uso de estos procedimientos puede ser un factor importante en el aumento de pacientes candidatos a revascularización de miembros inferiores observado en nuestra serie (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;65(3): 91-96, mayo-jun. 2013. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112865</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución del uso de técnicas endovasculares para revascularización infrainguinal de miembros inferiores en el periodo 2005-2011. Experiencia de nuestro centro</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29897^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7439^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23812^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54238^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
