<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125072</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparison of level of satisfaction of users of home care: Integrated model vs. dispensaries model</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the level of satisfaction of users that receive home health care through two different models of primary health care: integrated model and dispensaries model. Design: cross-sectional, observational study. Location: Two primary care centers in the province of Barcelona. Participants: The questionnaire was administered to 158 chronic patients over 65 years old, of whom 67 were receiving health care from the integrated model, and 91 from the dispensaries model. Main measurements: The Evaluation of Satisfaction with Home Health Care (SATISFAD12) questionnaire was, together with other complementary questions about service satisfaction of home health care, as well as social demographic questions (age, sex, disease, etc). Results: The patients of the dispensaries model showed more satisfaction than the users receiving care from the integrated model. There was a greater healthcare continuity for those patients from the dispensaries model, and a lower percentage of hospitalizations during the last year. The satisfaction of the users from both models was not associated to gender, the health perception, or independence of the. Conclusions: The user satisfaction rate of the home care by primary health care seems to depend of the typical characteristics of each organisational model. The dispensaries model shows a higher rate of satisfaction or perceived quality of care in all the aspects analysed. More studies are neede to extrapolate these results to other primary care centers belonging to other institutions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gassó, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gorina, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Limonero, Joaquín T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peñart, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Comparar el grado de satisfacción de los usuarios que reciben atención domiciliaria a través de 2 modelos de atención primaria: integrado y dispensarizado. Diseño: Estudio transversal, observacional. Emplazamiento: Dos centros de atención primaria de la provincia de Barcelona. Participantes: Ciento cincuenta y ocho pacientes crónicos mayores de 65 años que recibían atención domiciliaria: 67 mediante el modelo integrado y 91 mediante el modelo dispensarizado. Mediciones principales: Se administró la escala de Evaluación de la Satisfacción del Servicio de Atención Domiciliaria (SATISFAD-12), así como preguntas complementarias relacionadas con la satisfacción del servicio de atención domiciliaria y características sociodemográficas. Resultados: Los usuarios del modelo dispensarizado estaban más satisfechos que los del modelo integrado. Existía una mayor continuidad asistencial en el modelo dispensarizado y un menor porcentaje de ingresos hospitalarios en el último año. La satisfacción de los usuarios de ambos modelos no estaba asociada al género ni a la percepción de salud y autonomía por parte del paciente. Conclusiones: El grado de satisfacción de los pacientes de atención primaria domiciliaria parece depender de las características propias de cada modelo organizativo, siendo el modelo dispensarizado el que presenta un mayor grado de satisfacción o calidad asistencial percibida. Se debería realizar un mayor número de estudios para generalizar estos resultados a otros centros de atención primaria pertenecientes a otras instituciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;46(6): 276-282, jun.-jul. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125072</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de la satisfacción de los usuarios de atención domiciliaria: modelo integrado vs. modelo dispensarizado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30652</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32196^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10221</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201407</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
