<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78257</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Uncemented knee arthroplasty: supervivorship and long-term functional outcome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To analyze the long term survivorship and functional results of a model of uncemented knee prosthesis. Materials and methods: We carried out a prospective observational study of patients implanted between 1989 and 1996 with the Low Contact Stress Mobile-Bearing Total Knee Replacement (Depuy, Warsaw, IN, EEUU). Variables studied included: age, gender, follow-up, Knee Society Score, implant survivorship and reasons for revision. A total of 96 arthroplasties out of 127 reached the end of follow-up Mean age was 79 years. Mean follow-up was 14 years. Eleven prostheses were revised (6 following aseptic loosening and 5 because of problems with the mobile bearings). Survivorship curves were obtained considering length of follow-up, time elapsed between the primary and the revision surgery and the &#147;revision following loosening of a metal component&#148; and &#147;need for revision&#148; events. Results: When "need for revision" was considered as the endpoint, survivorship curves revealed a survivorship rate of 96.45% at 9 years and 92.78% at 12 years. When the endpoint was the "need to revise metal components" 14.5-year survivorship was 93.75%. Mean Knee Society Score was 89.2 points. Conclusion: The use of the uncemented LCS knee has resulted in excellent clinical and functional results as measured by the Knee Society Score, as well as 93.75% survivorship at 14 years and a half, considering the survivorship of the metal implant (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arroyo-Salcedo, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Freire, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-García, A. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Yagüe, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leal-Helmling, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bello-Prats, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer-Santacreu, E. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar la supervivencia a largo plazo y el resultado funcional de un modelo de prótesis de rodilla no cementada. Material y método: Realizamos un estudio prospectivo observacional de pacientes operados entre los años 1989 y 1996 con el modelo Low Contact Stress Mobile-Bearing Total Knee Replacement(R) (Depuy, Warsaw, IN, EE. UU.). Las variables estudiadas fueron edad, sexo, tiempo de seguimiento, puntuación del Knee Society Score (KSS), supervivencia del implante y motivos de la revisión. Un total de 96 artroplastias de 127 completaron el seguimiento. La media de edad fue de 79 años. La media de seguimiento fue de 14,5 años. Once prótesis se reintervinieron (6 por aflojamiento aséptico de implantes y 5 por problemas de componentes móviles). Se obtuvieron curvas de supervivencia al considerado el tiempo de seguimiento, el tiempo desde la cirugía primaria hasta la reintervención y el episodio «recambio por aflojamiento de componente metálico» y «necesidad de reintervención». Resultados: Las curvas de supervivencia arrojaron una supervivencia del 96,45% a los 9 años y del 92,78% a los 12 años, y se consideró la «necesidad de reintervención» como punto final. Al considerar la necesidad de recambio de componentes metálicos, la supervivencia a los 14 años y medio fue del 93,75%. La puntuación media del KSS funcional fue de 89,2. Conclusión: En nuestra experiencia y con el modelo protésico utilizado, las prótesis totales de rodilla no cementadas proporcionan un resultado clínico y funcional excelente, valorado por el KSS, y una supervivencia del 93,75% a los 14 años y medio al considerar la supervivencia del implante metálico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);54(2): 106-110, mar.-abr. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78257</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Supervivencia y resultado funcional a largo plazo de prótesis de rodilla no cementadas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33578^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7895^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34549^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33578^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7895^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
