<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79503</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validity and reliability of three teachers&#146; ratings scales of socials be-haviors in preschoolers and scholars children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this study was to expose validity and reliability of three teacher&#146;s ratings scales of socials behaviors in one sample (N=262) of preschoolers and scholars (grade one) Costa Ricans children. We design one scale of prosocial behavior (ECPRO) and other to evaluate the ability of exploiter the other&#146;s expertise (EXHAD). Moreover we adapt one scale of machiavellian behavior (EMach). Teachers completed three scales for each participant. Factor structure was evaluated by principal components analysis. This analysis show that ECPRO is form by one component &#147;Disposition for help others&#148;, EXHAD is constitute by two components &#147;Social Learning by Observation&#148; and &#147;Exploiting the Fruits of Other&#146;s Expertise&#148;; whereas EMach is constitute by three components &#147;Machiavellian Tactics&#148;, &#147;Ambivalent Attitudes Toward the Others&#148; and &#147;Social Understanding&#148;. The three teacher&#146;s ratings scales show evidence of construct validity and internal reliability; furthermore ECPRO and EMach show discriminant validity. In addition these findings suggest that teachers are an excellent choice to evaluate this kind of socials behaviors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Villagra, Odir</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padilla Mora, Michael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fornaguera Trías, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Estudiamos la validez y confiabilidad de tres escalas para evaluar conductas sociales niños y niñas costarricenses de preescolar y primer grado (n=262). Una de las escalas evalúa el comportamiento prosocial (ECPRO), otra evalúa la habilidad de explotar la experticia de los demás (EXHAD), y una más evalúa el comportamiento maquiavélico (EMach) en el ámbito escolar. Las escalas son completadas por docentes previamente capacitadas, de modo que el puntaje de cada niño o niña depende del criterio de su maestra respectiva. La estructura factorial de cada escala fue evaluada mediante un análisis de componentes principales. Según este análisis la ECPRO exhibió una estructura unidimensional caracterizada por un componente denominado &#147;Disposición para Ayudar a los Otros&#148;, la EXHAD mostró dos componentes principales denominados &#147;Aprendizaje Social por Observación&#148; y &#147;Explotación de la Frutos de la Experticia de los Demás&#148;, y la EMach reveló tres componentes: &#147;Tácticas Maquiavélicas&#148;, &#147;Actitudes Ambivalentes hacia los Demás&#148; y &#147;Comprensión Social&#148;. Las escalas arrojaron evidencia sobre una adecuada confiabilidad interna y validez de constructo. La ECPRO y la EMach evidenciaron validez discriminante entre sí. Además, estos hallazgos sugieren que el criterio de las maestras es una muy buena alternativa para evaluar este tipo de conductas sociales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;26(1): 104-111, ene.-jun. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79503</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validez y confiabilidad de tres escalas para evaluar conductas sociales en preescolares y escolares</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28461</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8429</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
