<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115417</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Victimization experiences and poly-victimization in a clinical smaple of minors: internalizing, externalizing and symptomatology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This sutdy is aims to analyze the incidence of victimiation in a clinical simple of adolescents and to assess the impact of poly-victimization in their mental health. The sample was composed of 133 adolescents, aged 12 to 17 years, whom were all referred to 13 child and adolescent mental healthcare units. The results showed that adolescent outpatients attended in mental healthcare units are highly victimized. Poly-victimization was significantly related to the level of psychological distress, having a greater impact than specific types of victimization (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Abad, Judit</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereda, Noemí</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guilera, Georgina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio es analizar la incidencia de victimización en una muestra clínica de adolescentes y evaluar el impacto de la polivictimización en su salud mental. La muestra la integraron 133 adolescentes de entre 12 y 17 años referidos a 13 centros de salud mental infantil y juvenil. Los resultados muestran que los adolescentes atendidos en servicios de salud mental tienen un nivel elevado de victimización, así mismo, ponen de manifiesto que la polivictimización se encuentra significativamente relacionada con el nivel de malestar psicológico, mostrando un impacto mayor que los tipos específicos de victimización (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(21): 41-50, abr. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115417</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencias de victimización y polivictimización en una muestra clínica de menores: internalización, externalización y sintomatología psicopatológica general</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5221</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7600</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33199^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
