<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160175</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of mobile health applications in primary care users</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: There are more than 165,000 mobile aplications (apps) related to health (mHealth) available to patients, promoting their empowerment and reducing healthcare costs; but not all are reliable, safe and quality. Objective: To analyze the use of mHealth for patients in a Primary Care Center (CAP). Methods: Cross-sectional study based on surveys of 274 patients, aged 16 to 65 years attending nursing consultation CAP Santa Eulalia Sud (L'Hospitalet de Llobregat) that have a mobile device with Internet. Results: Most respondents (68 %) use my health: physical exercise (63.4 %), food (41.4 %) and information about health services (26.3 %); discharged following recommendations from family/ friends (71 %), Internet (45.9 %), social networks (40.3 %), media (31.7 %) and health professionals (12.9 %). Perceived drawbacks download: suitability of the apps (61.3 %), reliability of information (58.1 %) and error in interpreting the information (30.1 %). Users (89 %) and non-users (70 %) of mHealth are interested in the information provided by a health professional about it. Conclusions: More and more users of mHealth and criteria in selecting there apps that cast doubt discharged reliable and quality. The difficulties expressed and desire information demonstrate the need for health professionals to guide and advise on such apps, indicating the patient the most appropriate, the most reliable, the easiest to interpret and manage to avoid mistakes, and provide them with knowledge on how to use them (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dolado Martín, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berlanga Fernández, Sofía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fabrellas Padres, Núria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Existen más de 165 000 aplicaciones móviles (apps) relacionadas con la salud (mHealth) a disposición de los pacientes, que favorecen su empoderamiento y disminuyen costes sanitarios. Sin embargo, no todas son fiables, seguras y de calidad. Objetivo: Analizar el uso de la mHealth por pacientes de un Centro de Atención Primaria (CAP). Material y métodos: Estudio descriptivo transversal basado en 274 encuestas realizadas a pacientes, de 16 a 65 años, que acudían a consulta de enfermería del CAP Santa Eulàlia Sud (L&#146;Hospitalet de Llobregat) que tuvieran un dispositivo móvil con Internet. Resultados: La mayoría de encuestados (68 %) utiliza apps de salud: ejercicio físico (63.4 %), alimentación (41.4 %) e información de servicios de salud (26.3 %); descargadas siguiendo recomendaciones de amigos/familiares (71 %), Internet (45.9 %), redes sociales (40.3 %), medios de comunicación (31.7 %) y profesionales sanitarios (12.9 %). Perciben como inconvenientes en su descarga: idoneidad de la app (61.3 %), fiabilidad de la información (58.1 %) y error al interpretar la información (30,1 %). Los usuarios (89 %) y no usuarios (70 %) de mHealth están interesados en la información proporcionada por un profesional sanitario sobre ello. Conclusiones: Cada vez hay más usuarios de mHealth y los criterios en la selección de las apps ponen en duda que las descargadas sean fiables y de calidad. Las dificultades manifestadas y el deseo de información indican la necesidad de que los profesionales sanitarios guíen y asesoren sobre este tipo de app, indicando al paciente la más idónea, la más fiable, la más sencilla de interpretar y manejar, para evitar errores, y proporcionarles conocimientos sobre cómo utilizarlas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;40(2): 96-101, feb. 2017. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160175</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso de aplicaciones móviles de salud en usuarios de Atención</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55440^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51868^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55440^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29495^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
