<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-68373</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Suppurative thrombophlebitis is a very infrequent complication of the central venous catheterization. The majority of the cases are produced by species of staphylococci. A 22-year-old colombian-woman, student, without toxic habits was admitted because of temporary left astrocytoma (grade II). Nine days after implementing a catheter in the right subclavianve in she presented high fever (39.5 º C), shivers, progressive rightside neck swelling and odinofagia. She had leukocytosis (26,300 cells/µl) and normal cerebrospinal fluid. After with drawing the catheter, Staphylococcus aureus was isolated in the tip of the catheter and in four bottles of blood cultures. A neck CT demonstrated expansion and absence of contrast in the right internal jugular vein. The patient evolved satisfactorily with cloxacillin, gentamycin and low molecular weight heparin</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramos Martínez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Romero, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saura Lorente, P. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parajón Díaz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La tromboflebitis supurada es una complicación muy infrecuente de la cateterización venosa central. La mayoría de los casos están producidos por especies de estafilococos. Se presenta el caso de una mujer de 22 años natural de Colombia sin hábitos tóxicos que estaba ingresada tras haber sido intervenida de un astrocitoma temporal izquierdo de grado II. A los 9 días de la implantación de un catéter en la vena subclavia derecha presentó fiebre elevada, escalofríos y tiritona junto a tumefacción progresiva laterocervical derecha y odinofagia. Tenía leucocitosis de 26.300 células/µl y líquido cefalorraquídeo normal. Tras retirar el catéter se aisló Staphylococcus aureus en la punta del catéter y en los cuatro frascosobtenidos en los hemocultivos. Una TAC de cabeza y de cuello con contraste evidenció distensión y ausencia de contraste en la vena yugular interna derecha. La paciente evolucionó satisfactoriamente con cloxacilina, gentamicina y heparina de bajo peso molecular</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;25(6): 284-286, jun. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-68373</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3050^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14309^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14309^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13596^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7769^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23255^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8141^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23183^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8141^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23183^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5444^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
