<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82362</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish Catheter Ablation Registry. 9th Report of the Spanish Society of Cardiology Working Group on Electrophysiology and Arrhythmias (2009)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. This article reports the findings of the 2009 Spanish national Catheter Ablation Registry. Methods. Data were collected in two ways: retrospectively using a standard questionnaire and prospectively from a central database. Each center chose its own preferred method of data collection. Results. Data were collected from 59 centers. The total number of ablation procedures carried out was 8546, giving a mean of 145±101 procedures per center. The three most frequently treated conditions were atrioventricular nodal reentrant tachycardia (n=2341; 27%), typical atrial flutter (n=1859; 21.7%) and accessory pathways (n=1758; 20.5%). The fourth most common condition was atrial fibrillation (n=1188; 14%), the number of which has grown by 44% since the 2008 registry. The overall success rate was 93%, major complications occurred in 1.9%, and the mortality rate was 0.046%. Conclusions. Data from the 2009 registry show that the number of ablations carried out continued to increase and exceeded 8000 for the first time. In addition, they show, in general, a higher success rate and a lower number of complications. Cavotricuspid isthmus ablation, as treatment for typical atrial flutter, continued to be the second most common procedure. There was a substantial increase in the number of catheter ablations performed for atrial fibrillation compared with previous years (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Infante, Ernesto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Bolao, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macías-Gallego, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Se detallan los resultados del Registro Nacional de Ablación del año 2009. Métodos. La recogida de datos se llevó a cabo mediante dos sistemas: de forma retrospectiva con la cumplimentación de un cuestionario y de forma prospectiva a través de una base de datos común. La elección de uno u otro por cada centro fue voluntaria. Resultados. Se recogieron datos de 59 centros. El número total de procedimientos de ablación fue 8.546, con una media de 145 ± 101 procedimientos. Los tres sustratos abordados con más frecuencia fueron la taquicardia intranodal (n = 2.341; 27%), la ablación del istmo cavotricuspídeo (n = 1.859; 21,7%) y las vías accesorias (n = 1.758; 20,5%). El cuarto sustrato abordado (n = 1.188; 14%) fue la ablación de fibrilación auricular, que mostró un incremento del 44% con respecto al registro del año 2008. La tasa general de éxito fue del 93%; la de complicaciones mayores, del 1,9% y la de mortalidad, del 0,046%. Conclusiones. En el registro del año 2009 se mantiene una línea de continuidad ascendente en el número de ablaciones realizadas, se supera por primera vez los 8.000 procedimientos y, en líneas generales, se observa una elevada tasa de éxito y un número de complicaciones bajo. La ablación del istmo cavotricuspídeo como tratamiento del aleteo auricular típico continúa como el segundo sustrato más frecuentemente abordado. Se observa un mayor incremento en el número de procedimientos de ablación de fibrilación auricular con respecto a años anteriores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;63(11): 1329-1339, nov. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82362</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Registro Español de Ablación con Catéter. IX Informe Oficial de la Sección de Electrofisiología y Arritmias de la Sociedad Española de Cardiología (2009)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30797^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30797^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13993^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1150^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30797^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30797^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52886^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52886^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52886^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52886^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52886^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201011</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
