<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124757</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diseases caused by environmental conditions in a tertiary hospital of Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Sick Building Syndrome (SBS) has more incidence of headache, irritation of mucous tissues and fatigue among workers. These symptoms get better or even disappear when workers leave the building. Objectives: The main aim of our research project was to check if the symptoms that some workers of one Tertiary Hospital in the Community of Madrid showed were those of SBS. Material and Method: For that purpose, we carried out a "cross-sectional descriptive study" through a questionnaire completed by staff members of the hospital both randomly selected and willing to take part. Results: 207 questionnaires were collected, 164 (79.2%) of women and 43 (20.8%) of men. The average age was 41.4 years, 42.6 in women and 36.6 in men (p &lt;0,01). More cases were found in certain areas of the hospital (laboratories and operating theaters). We were measured environmental conditions were measured: humidity 23 to 26% (recommended values above 30%) and normal temperature. 92 cases (44.4%) were found with symptoms that define the ESS (&gt; 20% of those studied) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez de la Pinta, M. Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Ruiz, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Fernández, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dietl Sagües, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuentes Piñeiro, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borda Olivas, Jenry Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El Síndrome del edificio enfermo (SEE) cursa con una mayor incidencia de síntomas como cefaleas, irritación de mucosas y sensación de fatiga, que mejoran o incluso desaparecen al abandonar el edificio. La Organización Mundial de la Salud (OMS) estima que este problema afecta al 30% de los edificios modernos y causa molestias al 10-30% de sus ocupantes. Objetivo: Determinar si los síntomas manifestados por los trabajadores de un hospital terciario de la Comunidad de Madrid se corresponden con los síntomas que definen el SEE. Material y Método: Estudio descriptivo transversal. Se pasó un cuestionario a un grupo de trabajadores, seleccionados de forma aleatoria y voluntaria. Resultados: Se recogieron 207 cuestionarios, 164 (79,2%) de mujeres y 43 (20,8%) de hombres. La edad media fue 41,4 años, 42,6 en mujeres y 36,6 en hombres (p&lt; 0,01). Se encontró reagrupamiento de casos en algunas áreas del hospital (laboratorios y quirófanos) y se midieron condiciones ambientales: humedad 23-26% (valores recomendados superiores al 30%) y temperatura normal. Se encontraron 92 casos (44,4%) con síntomas que definen el SEE. Conclusiones: El edificio en el que se desarrolla nuestro estudio cumple los criterios que se establecen en la definición de SEE (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;60(234): 53-63, ene.-mar. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124757</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patologías relacionadas con las condiciones ambientales de un hospital terciario de la Comunidad de Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d398^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32611^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
