<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051286</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4603</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Voice quality in hearing impaired children. The influence of the type of hearing aid used</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To analyse voice quality obtained in speech of hearing impaired children through the use of digital hearing aids, in comparison to purely analogue prosthesis.    Materials and method. Longitudinal study with a group of 10 children, between 5 years and 10 years old, with 1 st-degree severe-to-profound hearing loss. They initially used analogue hearing aids and changed to digital models. During 2 years, the evolution of their voice quality was recorded in the production of vowel /a:/. The data obtained were compared with those obtained by a control    group, with similar characteristics but users of only analogue hearing aids.    Results and Conclusions. Statistically significant differences have been observed both in the Fo as well as the Jitter analysed of vowel /a:/, to the advantage of children using digital hearing aids, who show parameters of voice quality that are much closer to normal parameters. On the contrary, there are no significant differences with regard to the Shimmer. As a conclusion, we should state the importance of using the newest digital hearing aids, as well as of early diagnosis and appropriate speech therapeutic practice, in order to have a more favourable incidence on the normalisation of voice in hearing impaired children</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gou, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casanova, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Analizar la calidad vocal obtenida en el lenguaje de niños sordos mediante el uso de audífonos digítales, en comparación con prótesis puramente analógicas. Material y métodos. Estudio longitudinal en un grupo de 10 niños, entre 5 años y 10 años de edad, con pérdida auditiva severa o profunda de primer grado. Portadores inicialmente de audífonos analógicos, se procedió a cambiarlos por modelos digitales, registrándose a lo largo de 2 años la evolución de su calidad vocal en la producción de la vocal /a:/. Los datos obtenidos han sido comparados con los obtenidos por un grupo control, de características similares, usuarios únicamente de audífonos analógicos.    Resultados y conclusiones. Se han observado diferencias estadísticamente significativas tanto en la Fa como en el Jitter analizado de la vocal /a:/, a beneficio de los niños usuarios de audífonos digitales, los cuales presentan unos parámetros de calidad vocal que se aproximan    mucho más a los parámetros de normalidad. Por el contrario, respecto al Shimmer no han aparecido diferencias significativas. Hay que concluir la importancia del uso de audífonos digitales de última generación, además del diagnóstico precoz y de la práctica logopédica adecuada, para incidir más favorablemente sobre la normalización de la voz en los niños sordos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. logop. foniatr. audiol. (Ed. impr.);26(2): 84-90, abr.-jun. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051286</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad vocal en niños sordos. La influencia del tipo de audífono empleado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1307^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13446^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6461^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3655^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13448^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13453^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13450</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
