<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058274</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">T lymphocyte immunophenotype as a diagnostic marker of late-onset neonatal sepsis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background                 Given the high risks associated with neonatal sepsis, there is a need for a diagnostic marker that would predict the disease before the results of blood or cerebrospinal fluid cultures are available. We evaluated changes in the CD4+ T lymphocyte immunophenotype in neonates with late-onset sepsis to try to improve the test combinations currently used (C reactive protein, immature:total neutrophil ratio, leukocytosis).                 Patients and methods                 We performed a prospective cohort study in 24 neonates with late-onset sepsis and 48 non-infected controls with a gestational age of 37 weeks or less. CD4+ T lymphocyte subpopulations in peripheral blood samples were identified by labeling with monoclonal antibodies and quantified by flow cytometry. Diagnostic performance curves were constructed by logistic regression.                 Results                 As a marker of late-onset neonatal sepsis, a percentage of CD4+/CD45RO+/CD45RA­ T lymphocytes of &gt; 3.5 % showed a sensitivity of 94.1 %, specificity of 69.2 %, positive predictive value of 80.0 %, negative predictive value of 90.0 %, and odds ratio of 36.0 (p  10.0 mg/L, the specificity of this combination of tests increased to 94.7 % and the positive predictive value to 85.7 %.                 Conclusions                 A percentage of CD4+/CD45RO+/CD45RA­ T lymphocytes of &gt; 3.5 % is an effective indicator of late-onset neonatal sepsis in preterm infants. If this marker is combined with a C-reactive protein level of &gt; 10.0 mg/l, its diagnostic performance is improved</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Pérez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moro Serrano, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dorado Moles, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Figueredo Delgado, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción                 Dada la elevada morbimortalidad asociada con la sepsis neonatal, es necesario un marcador diagnóstico que prediga la enfermedad antes de obtener el resultado del cultivo de sangre y/o líquido cefalorraquídeo.                 Se evaluaron los cambios en el inmunofenotipaje de los linfocitos T CD4+ en neonatos con sepsis de comienzo tardío con el fin de mejorar los resultados obtenidos con los test diagnósticos empleados actualmente (proteína C reactiva, índice neutrófilos inmaduros/neutrófilos totales, leucocitosis).                 Pacientes y métodos                 Un estudio de cohortes prospectivo se llevó a cabo en 24 neonatos con sepsis de comienzo tardío y 48 recién nacidos controles no infectados, de edad gestacional igual o inferior a 37 semanas. Se identificaron las subpoblaciones de linfocitos T CD4+ en sangre periférica mediante tinción con anticuerpos monoclonales y cuantificación por citometría de flujo. Se construyeron curvas de rendimiento diagnóstico mediante regresión logística.                 Resultados                 Como marcador de sepsis neonatal de comienzo tardío, un porcentaje de linfocitos T CD4+/CD45RO+/CD45RA­ &gt; 3,5 % muestra una sensibilidad del 94,1 %, una especificidad del 69,2 %, un valor predictivo positivo del 80,0 %, valor predictivo negativo del 90,0 %, y una odds ratio de 36,0 (p  10,0 mg/l, la especificidad de esta combinación de marcadores aumenta al 94,7 % y el valor predictivo positivo, al 85,7 %.                 Conclusiones                 Un porcentaje de linfocitos T CD4+/CD45RO+/CD45RA­ &gt; 3,5 % es un buen indicador de sepsis neonatal de comienzo tardío en neonatos pretérmino. Y si se combina con una proteína C reactiva &gt; 10,0 mg/l el rendimiento diagnóstico mejora</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);67(6): 536-543, dic. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058274</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inmunofenotipificación de linfocitos T como marcador diagnóstico de sepsis neonatal tardía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5567^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23473^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23473^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28990^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
