<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057844</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The spectrum of familial mediterranean fever</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Familial mediterranean fever (FMF) is a disease whose importance in recent years is reappearing thanks to the advances in molecular genetics. The diagnosis is established by symptoms, presence of inflammatory episodes of fever and serositis, family background and genetic study. Identification of the most prevalent mutations of the MEFV gene may confirm atypical or incomplete forms of FMS that are difficult to recognize based on the classical major and minor criteria. Knowledge of this more extensive clinical spectrum makes it possible to have a new diagnostic and therapeutic perspective based on the treatment of colchicine and secondary prevention of AA amyloidosis</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Cerezo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estébanez Muñoz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barbado Hernández, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La fiebre mediterránea familiar (FMF) es una enfermedad cuyo protagonismo en los últimos años está resurgiendo gracias a los avances en genética molecular. El diagnóstico se establece por la clínica, presencia de accesos inflamatorios de fiebre y serositis, antecedentes familiares y estudio genético. La identificación de las mutaciones más prevalentes del gen MEFV permite confirmar formas atípicas o incompletas de FMF, que difícilmente podrían ser reconocidas basándonos en los criterios mayores y menores clásicos. El conocimiento de este espectro clínico más amplio, permite dar una nueva perspectiva diagnóstica y terapéutica basada en el tratamiento con colchicina y prevención secundaria de la amiloidosis AA</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;207(10): 508-509, nov.2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057844</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El espectro de la fiebre mediterránea familiar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27974^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10696^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10696^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10696^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
