<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118401</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Immunological adjuvants. Determinant factors in the efficacy-toxicity ratio of the contemporary vaccines</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To achieve effective and safe vaccines for the prevention of not yet controlled or re-emergent infectious diseases, one of the more importance aspects is to have immunological adjuvants that allow inducing a protective immune response with an appropriate safety pro&amp;#64257;le. Since 1926 the aluminium compounds have been used as adjuvants for human vaccines, and only in the last 10 years some new products have been registered. Although there an enormous quantity of proposed candidates, the toxicity is the mainfactor that has limited their introduction into the clinic. In this work the mechanism of action are updated, and the toxicity of the immunological adjuvants are revised, especially those that have obtained clinical approval or are close to getting it (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Batista-Duharte, Alexander</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lastre, Miriam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez , Oliver</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Para lograr vacunas eficaces y seguras para la prevención de enfermedades infecciosas aún no controladas o re-emergentes, uno de los aspectos de mayor importancia es contar con adyuvantes que permitan inducir una respuesta protectora efectiva con un adecuado perfil de seguridad. El hidróxido de aluminio se ha utilizado como adyuvante en vacunas humanas desde 1926, y solo en los últimos 10 años se han registrado algunos nuevos productos, a pesar de la enorme cantidad de candidatos propuestos, siendo la toxicidad el principal factor que ha limitado su introducción en la clínica. En este trabajo se actualizan los últimos avances en cuanto a mecanismos de acción y toxicidad de los adyuvantes vacunales y se revisan los adyuvantes que han obtenido licencias sanitarias y otros que están próximos a lograrlo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;32(2): 106-114, feb. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118401</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adyuvantes inmunológicos. Determinantes en el balance eficacia-toxicidad de las vacunas contemporáneas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27905^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23123^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28582^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
