<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81126</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Functional Imaging of Tumors. Part 1</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Most advances in conventional diagnostic imaging techniques have focused on improving the spatial resolution and speed of acquisition of images or on new contrast agents. However, tumors are extremely complex biological models with a series of characteristics like hypoxia, metabolism, cellularity, angiogenesis, and functionality of the lymph nodes that are very important in oncology but cannot be adequately studied with these diagnostic imaging methods. In this article, we discuss the possible contributions of different functional imaging techniques based on computed tomography, magnetic resonance imaging, or positron emission tomography to obtain information about different biological processes and characteristics that are very important for diagnosing, staging, planning treatment, evaluating the response to treatment, and monitoring the evolution of cancer patients, as well as for the development of new drugs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Goh, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilanova, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padhani, A. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villalba Martín, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Figueiras, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los principales avances en el campo de las técnicas convencionales de imagen diagnóstica se habían centrado tanto en mejorar la resolución espacial y la velocidad de adquisición de los datos como en la introducción de nuevos medios de contraste. Sin embargo, los tumores representan modelos biológicos tremendamente complejos, existiendo una serie de características (hipoxia, metabolismo, celularidad, angiogénesis o funcionalismo de los ganglios linfáticos) de gran importancia en el campo de la oncología y que no pueden ser estudiadas adecuadamente con estos métodos diagnósticos. En este trabajo se presenta la posible aportación de distintas técnicas de imagen funcional basadas en el uso de la TC, la RM o la PET para obtener información de características y procesos biológicamente muy importantes para el diagnóstico, estadificación, planificación terapéutica, valoración de respuesta o seguimiento evolutivo de los pacientes oncológicos; así como para el desarrollo de nuevos fármacos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);52(2): 115-125, mar.-abr. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81126</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Imagen funcional tumoral. Parte 1</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22878^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38793^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
