<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054897</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9744</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gerontology prevention: Old and the problems of the caretaker</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In gerontology is has four forms to act that    they affect of a direct form own the old one, by a    side its affective surroundings that serious the informal    system of cares, that occurs him on the    part of family, but less direct or it can by some    person friend, which this structured and is shared    in common as well, and on the other hand the    formal system of cares, being a this structured,    fluctuating and evolutionary system but extensive,    but less, that are practiced by sanitary professionals.    For the geriatric gerontology the fundamental    thing is the Cost / Utility corresponding    to this relation cost I diagnose or therapy and the    gained quality of years of life for the old patient.    Is important that the psicology support to the informal    caretakers of a real and continued form,    makes diminish to institutionalize of the patient    and maintains the caretaker in one better emotional    form</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castro Carratalá, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zarzosa López, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En gerontología hay cuatro formas de actuar    que afectan de una forma directa al propio anciano;    por un lado su entorno afectivo que sería el    sistema informal de cuidados, que se dan por parte    de algún familiar, más menos directo o podría    ser por alguna persona amiga, el cual esta estructurado    y a su vez es solidario, y por otro lado el    sistema formal de cuidados, siendo este un sistema    más extenso, pero menos estructurado, fluctuante    y evolutivo, que son practicados por profesionales    sanitarios. Para el geriatra gerontólogo lo    fundamental es el Coste / Utilidad correspondiendo    a esta relación, coste de un diagnóstico o terapéutica    y la calidad de los años de vida ganados    para el paciente anciano. Es importante señalar    que el soporte psicológico a los cuidadores informales    de una forma real y continuada, hace disminuir    la institucionalización del paciente y mantiene    al cuidador en una mejor forma emocional</dc:description>
<dc:source>Geriátrika (Madr.);22(3): 92-96, mayo-jun. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054897</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevención en Gerontología: El anciano y los problemas del cuidador</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17140^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6448^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28470</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
