<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040696</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adequacy of anticoagulant prevention in patients with atrial fibrillation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Although there is a consensus about the use of oral anticoagulants (OAC) to prevent stroke inpatients with atrial fibrillation this treatment is underused in actual practice. Our aim was to determine the proportion ofpatients with previously known atrial fibrillation who were receiving OAC before stroke onset and their characteristics.Patients and methods. We recruited 50 patients who were admitted with acute stroke and previously known atrial fibrillationover a period of one year. Patients were classified according to the type of antithrombotic treatment they were on. The clinicalpicture was evaluated by the NIHSS. Functional prognosis was estimated by modified-Rankin score at discharge. Results. Of50 patients, 16 (32%) were receiving OAC before stroke. Four variables were associated with prescription of OAC: treatmentwith digoxin, previous ischemic stroke or transient ischemic accident, congestive heart failure and the type of AF (chronic vsparoxysmal). Age and medical history of arterial hypertension, diabetes mellitus or ischemic cardiopathy did not influencethe prescription. According to the NIHSS and modified-Rankin scales patients on OAC showed less serious strokes andpresented a better functional situation at discharge than those who were not on that treatment. Conclusions. This studyhighlights the need to improve medical education about OAC in patients with atrial fibrillation because only 32% of patientsreceived OAC before stroke although 90% of them should receive it according to current guidelines. Our results suggest thatOAC treatment not only prevents stroke but may also contribute to the development of less serious strokes with a betterfunctional prognosis</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-García, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benavente-Fernández, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calleja-Puerta, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Lahoz, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega-Cerezales, V. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Rodríguez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las evidencias científicas demuestran queel tratamiento anticoagulante constituye la profilaxis más eficaz enpacientes con fibrilación auricular. Se presenta una cohorte depacientes con ictus y fibrilación auricular conocida y se analiza laadecuación del tratamiento anticoagulante previo en función desus características clínicas y demográficas. Pacientes y métodos.Estudio de observación prospectivo, que incluye pacientes ingresadosdurante un año en un Servicio de Neurología por ictus agudo ycon antecedente de fibrilación auricular no valvular. Se comparó elperfil clínico y el pronóstico funcional de cada paciente con el tratamientoprevio. Resultados. Se estudiaron 50 pacientes. El 32% recibíantratamiento con anticoagulantes orales (ACO), el 34% conantiagregantes plaquetarios y el 34% no recibía ningún tratamientoantitrombótico. Se demostraron diferencias estadísticamente significativasen los pacientes tratados con ACO en cuanto a los antecedentesde tratamiento con digoxina, isquemia cerebral, insuficienciacardíaca y tipo de fibrilación. Los antecedentes de hipertensiónarterial, diabetes mellitus y la edad no influyeron en suprescripción. Se encontró una tendencia estadísticamente no significativaa una clínica menos grave al ingreso y a un mejor estadofuncional al alta, basado en las escalas NIHSS y Rankin modificadaen los tratados con ACO. Conclusiones. Sólo el 32% de los pacientesrecibían tratamiento previo con ACO, pese a que más del90% tenían indicación para ello. Los resultados obtenidos sugierenuna necesidad de optimizar las medidas de prevención primaria,máxime cuando se observa un mejor estado funcional final en pacientestratados con ACO</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;41(7): 399-403, oct. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040696</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adecuación de la profilaxis anticoagulante en pacientes con fibrilación auricular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2582</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2583^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1150</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
