<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136057</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">ISO 9001:2008 Quality Certification of a multidisciplinary pain program</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and aims: Pain management constitutes an organisational challenge in all types of clinical establishments. The ISO 9001 Norms can be an effective way of integrating the different components of a comprehensive multidisciplinary programme. ISO 9001 International Standards ensure that products and services are safe, reliable and of good quality. The experience of applying the ISO 9001 norms for the effective management of pain in a large university hospital is shown here. Methods: A Multidisciplinary Pain Committee was created in a 1,400-bed university hospital in Madrid (Spain). Nineteen doctors from 17 specialties, 3 nurses, one pharmacist and one of the hospital directors were integrated in six working groups with the objective of implementing the necessary steps leading to the ISO 9001 Quality Certification of the organisation. A process map was designed, operating procedures were developed and quality indicators were chosen. A quality manual and a welcome manual were written, policies for risk management and data protection were outlined, and a critical incidents registry was created. Setting up the process and completing the tasks took around one and a half years. Results: After the effective implementation of all of the ISO 9001 recommendations, process management became the regular methodology for work in the different areas integrated in the institutional pain programme. A quality committee monitored both the compliance with the norms and the data derived from the quality indicators. Once the committee was satisfied with the results, an accredited agency (Bureau Veritas Certification) for the external audit was chosen. The ISO 9001 Quality Certificate was awarded in March 2013. Conclusions: ISO 9001 international standards can be effectively applied to a multidisciplinary pain programme in a tertiary care hospital. Process management can be a useful methodology for work leading to efficiency, safety and quality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mañas Rueda, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Ramón, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ledesma Rodríguez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Salcedo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reinoso Barbero, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aparicio Grande, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santolaya de Suñer, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: el tratamiento del dolor constituye un desafío de gestión en todo tipo de establecimientos clínicos. Las Normas ISO 9001 pueden ser un método eficaz para integrar los diferentes componentes de un programa multidisciplinar integral. Los citados estándares internacionales aseguran que los productos y servicios son seguros, fiables y de buena calidad. Se muestra la experiencia de aplicar las Normas ISO 9001 para la gestión eficaz del dolor en un hospital universitario de gran tamaño. Métodos: se constituyó una comisión multidisciplinar de lucha contra el dolor (Comisión &#147;Hospital sin Dolor&#148;) en un hospital universitario de 1.400 camas en Madrid. Diecinueve médicos de 17 especialidades, 3 enfermeras, un farmacéutico y un miembro de la dirección del centro se integraron en seis grupos de trabajo con el objetivo de implementar los pasos necesarios para la certificación en calidad de la organización conforme a la Norma ISO 9001. Se diseñó un mapa de procesos, se identificaron los procedimientos operativos y se eligieron indicadores de calidad representativos de la actividad desarrollada. Se elaboraron un manual de calidad y un manual de bienvenida para los profesionales, se desarrollaron las políticas de gestión de riesgos y de protección de datos, y se creó un registro de incidentes críticos. La planificación y el desarrollo de las diferentes fases del proyecto requirieron aproximadamente un año y medio de trabajo. Resultados: tras la implementación de las recomendaciones de la Norma ISO, la gestión por procesos se adoptó como la metodología de trabajo habitual en las diferentes áreas integradas en el programa institucional de lucha contra el dolor. Un comité de calidad monitorizó tanto el cumplimiento de las normas como los datos derivados del sistema de gestión de la calidad. Una vez el comité constató la adecuación del sistema, una agencia externa acreditada (Bureau Veritas) fue la encargada de realizar la auditoría externa. El Certificado de Calidad fue otorgado en marzo de 2013. Conclusiones: los estándares internacionales de calidad de la Norma ISO 9001 pueden ser utilizados eficazmente en un programa multidisciplinar de lucha contra el dolor en un hospital de tercer nivel. La gestión por procesos constituye una metodología de trabajo adecuada para asegurar la eficiencia, la seguridad y la calidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;22(2): 80-86, mar.-abr. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136057</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Certificación en calidad, conforme a la Norma ISO 9001: 2008, de un programa interdisciplinar de tratamiento del dolor</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2608^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17193^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54522^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51706</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31061^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
