<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058284</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Review of standards and recommendations for the design of a neonatology unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Standards for the design of a neonatology unit are reviewed. The process should begin with a planning team to outline the desired objectives to be achieved, followed by the intervention of a team of architects.         Medical considerations, standards and recommendations, as well as architectural considerations (adequate privacy and intimacy, need for social support and communication, flexibility and accessibility) should be taken into account.         From the architectural point of view, the greatest problem is the space available; furthermore, if the aim is to personalize the unit for the newborn and family, the need for space will be even greater.         The following aspects should be analyzed and integrated into the design of the unit: standards and recommendations regarding space, the site of the unit, area of direct neonatal care, electrical installation, equipment, lighting and noise levels, nursing staff, communication systems, maintenance and refurbishment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Doménech Martínez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Losada Martínez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Luna, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perapoch López, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García del Río, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo Macián, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Herrera, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se revisan los estándares para el diseño de una unidad de neonatología. El proceso debe iniciarse con un equipo de planificación que debe indicar los objetivos que se desean conseguir, para que posteriormente intervenga el equipo de arquitectos.         Se deben tener en cuenta las aportaciones médicas, los estándares y recomendaciones, y las aportaciones arquitectónicas (adecuada privacidad e intimidad, necesidad de apoyo social y comunicación, flexibilidad y accesibilidad).         Desde el punto de vista arquitectónico, el mayor problema es el del espacio disponible, y debemos tener en cuenta que si queremos personalizar el entorno del cuidado para el recién nacido y su familia e introducir los cuidados centrados en la familia, las necesidades de espacio serán aún mayores.         Se analizan los estándares y recomendaciones relativos al espacio, ubicación de la unidad, área de atención directa al neonato, instalación eléctrica, iluminación y nivel de ruido, equipamiento, personal de enfermería, sistemas de comunicaciones, mantenimiento y renovación</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);67(6): 594-602, dic. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058284</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión de los estándares y recomendaciones para el diseño de una unidad de neonatología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6906^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5260^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12436</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21037^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1112^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21037^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21037^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32553</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9552^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
