<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97497</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Functional and dysfunctional synaptic plasticity in prefrontal cortex: roles in psychiatric disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Prefrontal cortex (PFC) mediates an assortment of cognitive functions including working memory, behavioral flexibility, attention, and future planning. Unlike the hippocampus, where induction of synaptic plasticity in the network is well-documented in relation to long-term memory, cognitive functions mediated by the PFC have been thought to be independent of long-lasting neuronal adaptation of the network. Nonetheless, accumulating evidence suggests that prefrontal cortical neurons possess the cellular machinery of synaptic plasticity and exhibit lasting changes of neural activity associated with various cognitive processes. Moreover, deficits in the mechanisms of synaptic plasticity induction in the PFC might be involved in the pathophysiology of psychiatric and neurological disorders such as schizophrenia, drug addiction, mood disorders, and Alzheimer's disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Goto, Yukiori</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Otani, Satoru</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yang, Charles R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La corteza prefrontal (CPF) interviene en un conjunto de funciones cognitivas como la memoria operativa, la flexibilidad conductual, la atención y la planificación del futuro. A diferencia del hipocampo, en donde la inducción de la plasticidad sináptica en la red está bien documentada respecto a la memoria a largo plazo, las funciones cognitivas que se producen a través de la CPF se han considerado independientes de la adaptación neuronal de larga duración de la red. No obstante, la evidencia que se está acumulando sugiere que las neuronas prefrontales poseen la maquinaria celular de la plasticidad sináptica y muestran cambios persistentes de la actividad neural asociada a diversos procesos cognitivos. Además, los déficits en los mecanismos de inducción de la plasticidad sináptica en la CPF podrían intervenir en la fisiopatología de trastornos psiquiátricos y neurológicos como la esquizofrenia, la drogadicción, los trastornos del estado de ánimo y la enfermedad de Alzheimer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);18(1): 18-27, ene.-mar. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97497</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Plasticidad sináptica funcional y disfuncional en la corteza prefrontal: papel en los trastornos psiquiátricos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31881^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30601^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30601^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53841^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6115^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6115^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
