<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-30369</identifier>
<setSpec>1136-4890</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">An anatomic study of the positional relationships between the lateral pterygoid muscle and its surrounding nerves</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We investigated forty-five head halves of 25 Japanese cadavers in order to obtain precise anatomical knowledge of the courses and distribution of the branches of the mandibular nerve positionally related to the lateral pterygoid muscle. After complete removal of the bony elements, several patterns of the positional relationships between the lateral pterygoid and surrounding nerves were noted. The lateral pterygoid is innervated by branches of the anterior and middle deep temporal nerves, the main trunk of the mandibular nerve and the auriculotemporal nerve, and by branches originating from the forks of these nerves. In two specimens, the buccal nerve was composed of the root from the common trunk with the anterior deep temporal nerve and the root of the middle deep temporal nerve. Based on the positional relationships between the masticatory muscles and the branches of the mandibular nerve, the lateral pterygoid is located in the center of the muscles. Variations in the nerve routes related to the lateral pterygoid are considered to reflect the variability of the differentiation patterns of the anlage of the muscle (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sociedad Anatómica Española</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se investigaron 25 mitades de la cabeza de 25 cadáveres japoneses para obtener un conocimiento preciso de los trayectos y distribución de las ramas del nervio mandibular relacionadas con el músculo pterigoideo lateral. Después de la extracción completa de los elementos óseos, se observaron diversos patrones de las relaciones de posición entre el pterigoideo lateral y los nervios circundantes. El pterigoideo lateral es inervado por ramas de los nervios temporales profundos anterior y medio, el tronco principal del nervio mandibular y el nervio auriculotemporal, y por ramas que se originaron en las bifurcaciones de estos nervios. En dos especímenes, el nervio bucal estaba constituido de la raíz del tronco común con el nervio temporal profundo anterior la raíz del nervio temporal profundo medio. Según las relaciones de posición entre los músculos masticadores y las ramas del nervio mandibular, el pterigoideo lateral está localizado en el centro de los músculos. Se consideran las variaciones en las rutas del nervio relacionadas con el pterigoideo lateral para reflejar la variabilidad de los patrones de diferenciación de los anejos del músculo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Eur. j. anat;7(supl.1): 5-14, jul. 2003. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio anatómico de las relaciones posicionales entre el músculo pterigoideo lateral y sus nervios circundantes</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Sato, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Akita, K</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Shimokawa, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-30369</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d4271^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2136</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8506^s22037</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12061^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
