<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75028</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Therapeutic efficacy of anidulafungin for the treatment of oesophageal candidiasis, candidemia and invasive candidiasis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Anidulafungin is a new echinocandin that appears to have several advantagesover existing antifungals. It is unique because it slowly degrades in humans,undergoing a process of biotransformation rather than being metabolized.It exhibits high in vitro and in vivo activities against Candida spp. andAspergillus spp. In several clinical studies investigating Candida esophagitis;candidemia and invasive candidiasis, the clinical efficacy of this echinocandinwas similar, or even superior, to that of established antifungals in candidemia.Antifungal activity against strains no longer susceptible to conventionalantifungal agents, such as fluconazole and amphotericin B suggests thatanidulafungin can be used as salvage therapy in life-threatening fungalinfections. The limited toxicity profile, minimal drug&#150;drug interactions and thefact that does not require dosage adjustment in subjects with hepatic or renalimpairment, establishes this echinocandin as an attractive new option for thetreatment of invasive fungal infections(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montejo González, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Catalán González, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León Gil, Cristóbal</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La anidulafungina es una nueva equinocandina que tiene ventajas respectoa otros antifúngicos. Es la única de su grupo con un metabolismoautobiodegradable. Exhibe una elevada actividad in vitro e in vivo frentea Candida spp. y Aspergillus spp. En diferentes ensayos clínicos se haapreciado que la eficacia de la anidulafungina es similar a la de otrosantifúngicos, e incluso en candidemias es el único superior al comparador alfinal del tratamiento y dos semanas después. La actividad de laanidulafungina frente a cepas resistentes a antifúngicos convencionales leconvierte en un fármaco de primera línea para el tratamiento &#147;de rescate&#148; enestas situaciones. El excelente perfil de seguridad, las limitadas interaccionesque presenta con otros fármacos y el hecho de no requerir ajustes dedosificación en pacientes con fracaso renal o hepático, son factores quehacen de esta equinocandina una nueva y atractiva opción terapéutica eninfecciones fúngicas invasoras(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;25(2): 107-118, 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75028</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad clínica de la anidulafungina en el tratamiento de las candidiasis esofágicas, candidemias y candidiasis invasoras</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5025^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2209^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52786^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30095^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5794^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200800</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
