<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052112</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical profile and impact of the unscheduled return to Emergency Department by elders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. The characteristics of patients aged 65 years and over that return to the Emergency Department (ED) have not been sufficiently analysed. The aim of this study is to determine the differentiating elements of the elderly that return to ED and evaluate the impact on them of such a return. Methods. Descriptive study where the unit of analysis is the unscheduled return to ED. The analysis of data begins with a description of the entire sample. After that, comparisons are made between the elderly and patients aged under 65 years that return, and between the elderly that return and those that do not return. The significance level for comparison tests is p&amp;#8804;0.05. Results. Sixty-one per cent of the reasons for the first visit by the elderly was because of neurological alterations (p&lt;0,001). Only 22% of them had been attended by senior doctors on their first visit (p=0,001). When they returned to ED, 63% of them were admitted to hospital; in contrast to 28% of younger patients (p&lt;0,001). Conclusions: There are differences between the elderly patients that return and those who do not, and also with respect to young adults. The impact of return on this group of patients is reflected in the high rates of admission to hospital. An adaptation of resources to the special needs of this type of user in ED would be advisable</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ojeda, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguirre-Jaime, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Sanz, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las características de los pacientes mayoresde 65 años que retornan a urgencias no han sido suficientementedescritas. El propósito de este estudio consiste enconocer los elementos diferenciadores de los mayores queretornan al Servicio de Urgencias Hospitalario (SUH) y valorarel impacto de ese retorno inesperado en el paciente mayor.Material y métodos. Estudio retrospectivo analíticoobservacional cuya unidad de análisis es el retorno inesperadoal SUH. El examen de los datos comienza con una descripciónde toda la muestra. A continuación se realizancomparaciones de variables clínicas y asistenciales, asícomo de destino al alta entre pacientes mayores y más jóvenesque retornan y entre mayores que retornan y que no lohacen. Se prefija como resultado estadísticamente significativopara todas las pruebas de contraste el nivel de p&amp;#8804;0,05.Resultados. El 61% de los motivos de consulta en la primeravisita de los pacientes mayores retornados fueron lasalteraciones neurológicas (p&lt;0,001). Sólo el 22% de elloshabían sido atendidos por médicos adjuntos en la primeravisita (p=0,001). Al retornar a urgencias ingresaron el 63%de ellos frente al 28% de los más jóvenes (p&lt;0,001).Discusión. Existen diferencias entre los pacientes mayoresque retornan con los que no lo hacen y también con respectoa los adultos jóvenes. El impacto del retorno sobre estegrupo de pacientes viene reflejado por las altas tasas de ingresos.Sería conveniente la adaptación de recursos a las necesidadesespeciales para este tipo de usuario en los SUH</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;29(2): 199-206, mayo-ago. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052112</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfil clínico-asistencial e impacto del retorno inesperado a urgencias de un mayor de 65 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10553^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
