<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-19280</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ten contributions of the use of qualitative methodology in a Primary Care in-house audit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Qualitative methodology, originally belonging to the Social Sciences domain, has been incorporated progressively to Health Research to the scepticism of many and the admiration of others. Nowadays, validity and fiability of these qualitative techniques is still questioned by a great amount of health researchers and their use provokes doubt among reviewers and other members of the scientific community. This article presents as a fundamental measure of the validity of the qualitative methodology its precise use to approach research objectives specific to them and, echoing the extra issue of the Health Services Research journal on December 1999 on this methodology, gathers the contribution of the use of these techniques from a complementary point of view, in an Internal Communication Audit conducted in the Primary Care Services of four Regional Health Systems: Area II of the INSALUD (National Health Institute), Basque Health System, Canary Health System and Andalusian Health System (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ministerio de Sanidad y Consumo</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La metodología cualitativa, propia en su origen de las ciencias sociales, se ha ido incorporando progresivamente a la investigación en salud, ante el escepticismo de muchos y la admiración de otros. Todavía hoy en día la validez y fiabilidad de las técnicas cualitativas de recogida y análisis de datos es cuestionada por una parte importante de los investigadores de ciencias de la salud y su utilización provoca la duda entre revisores y otros miembros de la comunidad científica. Este artículo presenta como medida fundamental de validez de la metodología cualitativa su utilización específica para el abordaje de determinados objetivos de investigación que le son propios y, haciéndose eco del número especial dedicado a esta metodología del número de Health Services Research de diciembre de 1999, recoge la aportación del uso de estas técnicas, desde un punto de vista de la complementariedad, en una Auditoria de Comunicación Interna realizada en los servicios de atención primaria de cuatro sistemas regionales de salud: Área II del Insalud, Servicio Vasco, Servicio Canario y Servicio Andaluz de Salud (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;76(5): 483-492, sept. 2002.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diez aportaciones del empleo de la metodología cualitativa en una auditoría de comunicación interna en Atención Primaria</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>March Cerdá, Joan Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bilbao Acedos, Izaskun</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto Rodríguez, María Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-19280</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d3173</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8655</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
