<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159737</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The neural networks of facial expression</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION. Face perception involves a broad network of connections between cortical and subcortical regions for the exchange and synchronization of information using white matter fibers. This precise communication system can be affected by the structures and the pathways that connect them. AIMS. To establish the neural substrate underlying the perception of facial expression and to analyze the different factors involved in modulating the integrity of this neural network, with the aim being to introduce improvements into rehabilitation programs. DEVELOPMENT. When the complex neural network involved in the perception of facial expression is altered by trauma, neurodegenerative disorders, developmental disorders, social isolation or negative contexts, the adaptive capacity to interact with the environment also deteriorates. CONCLUSIONS. Maintaining the neural network integrity responsible for processing facial expression requires considering different variables. To a greater or lesser extent, these variables modify the structure or function of neural networks, such as aerobic training, transcranial magnetic stimulation, transcranial electrical stimulation, and learning. These variables are affected by age, and the type and course of the condition or generator context, and raise the need for rehabilitation protocols that are adapted and designed to delimit the deficient neuronal substrate (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López, RM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gordillo, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arana, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mestas, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La percepción de caras involucra una amplia red de conexiones entre regiones corticales y subcorticales que intercambian y sincronizan información a través de haces de sustancia blanca. Este preciso sistema de comunicación puede verse afectado tanto a través de las propias estructuras como por las vías que las conectan. Objetivos. Delimitar el sustrato neuronal que subyace a la percepción de la expresión facial y analizar los diferentes factores que participan modulando la integridad de esta red neuronal, con el fin de proponer mejoras en los programas de rehabilitación. Desarrollo. Cuando la compleja red de conexiones que participa en la percepción de la expresión facial se altera por traumatismos, patologías neurodegenerativas, trastornos del desarrollo, incluso por aislamiento social o contextos negativos, se deteriora también la capacidad para interactuar de manera adaptativa con el entorno. Conclusiones. La posibilidad de restaurar la integridad de la red neuronal encargada del procesamiento de la expresión facial pasa por tener en cuenta diferentes variables que en mayor o menor grado se han mostrado capaces de modificar la estructura o funcionalidad de las redes neuronales, como el entrenamiento aeróbico, la estimulación magnética transcraneal, la estimulación eléctrica transcraneal y el aprendizaje, sin bien estas variables estarían condicionadas por la edad, el tipo y evolución del trastorno o el contexto generador, lo que plantearía la necesidad de protocolos de rehabilitación ajustados y orientados a delimitar el sustrato neuronal del déficit (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;64(3): 125-132, 1 feb., 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159737</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Redes neuronales de la expresión facial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51212^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55509^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33140^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9608^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9608^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9608^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9819^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56095^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56095^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51212^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5250</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
