<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61051</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1473</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hemangiopericytoma of the posterior fossa: case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hemangiopericytoma is an uncommon mesenchymalneoplasm arising from Zimmerman&#146;s pericytes, whichusually locates in soft tissues. Meningeal hemangiopericytomaaccounts for less than 1% of all intracranialtumours. Typically, it behaves aggressively, showingdistinct tendency to recur locally or distantly along theneural axis and to present extraneural metastases.We describe a 74-year-old patient who presentedunspecific symptoms and whose physical exam revealeda painless retroauricular mass which was adhered toskin. Neuroimaging studies showed a large posteriorfossa tumour with intense enhancement after contrastinfusion that caused striking occipital-mastoid osteolisisand which was exclusively fed by external carotid arterybranches. The patient underwent gross total resectionof the tumour, and once the histological diagnosis ofhemangiopericytoma was confirmed, she underwentinitial adjuvant radiotherapy. Sixteen months after surgery,the patient remains recurrence free.The treatment of choice of intracranial hemangiopericytomais gross total resection, which must beattempted when technically feasible, followed by adjuvantradiotherapy providing total doses over 50 Gy.This combination has demonstrated increasing recurrence-free interval in these patients. Close and longtermfollow-up is mandatory in order to achieve earlydiagnosis of recurrence or metastases in these patients,since they can appear several years, even decades, afterinitial proper treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Zamarrón, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivero-Garvía, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boto, G. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-González, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El hemangiopericitoma es un tumor mesenquimalinfrecuente originado de los pericitos de Zimmerman,que habitualmente asienta en tejidos blandos. Suvariante meníngea supone menos del 1% de todos lostumores intracraneales. Característicamente presentaun comportamiento agresivo, con marcada tendencia arecurrir localmente y a lo largo del neuroeje, así como ametastatizar en localizaciones extraneurales.Presentamos el caso de una paciente de 74 años quedebutó con clínica inespecífica, observándose durantela exploración física una masa retroauricular no dolorosaa la palpación, adherida a la piel. El estudio deneuroimagen demostró una lesión de gran tamaño localizadaen la fosa posterior que realzaba intensamentetras la administración de contraste, asociada a llamativaosteolisis occípito-mastoidea y cuya vascularizaciónprovenía exclusivamente de ramas de la arteria carótidaexterna. La paciente se sometió a la resección quirúrgicacompleta de la lesión, administrándose radioterapia inicialadyuvante una vez confirmado histológicamenteel diagnóstico de hemangiopericitoma. Dieciséis mesesdespués de la intervención, la paciente se encuentralibre de enfermedad.El tratamiento de elección del hemangiopericitomaintracraneal es su resección quirúrgica completa, siempreque sea técnicamente posible, seguida de radioterapiaadyuvante con dosis superiores a los 50 Gy. Estacombinación ha demostrado aumentar el intervalo detiempo libre de recurrencia. Un estrecho seguimiento alargo plazo de estos pacientes es esencial para detectarrecurrencias o metástasis a distancia precozmente,pudiendo aparecer incluso décadas después del adecuadotratamiento inicial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurocirugia (Astur);19(5): 446-452, sept.-oct. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61051</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hemangiopericitoma de la fosa posterior: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1958^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6544^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3404</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6544^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1958^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
