<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104034</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Atrial fibrillation management in the hospital emergency department: 2012 update</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Atrial fibrillation is the most frecuently sustained arrhythmia managed in emergency departments, and accounts for a high and increasing prevalence in Spain. Atrial fibrillation is increases mortality, is associated with substantial complications and, therefore, has a relevant impact in running of the health care system. Management requires consideration of diverse clinical variables and a large number of possible therapeutic approaches, justifying action plans that coordinate the work of medical staff in the interest of providing appropriate care and optimizing resources. These evidence-based guidelines contain recommendations for managing atrial fibrillation in the special circumstances of hospital emergency departments. Stroke prohylaxis, rate control, rhtyhm control, and related diagnostic and logistic issues are discussed in detail (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tercedor Sánchez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Del Arco Galán, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Lozano, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mont Girbau, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arribas Ynsaurriaga, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Martínez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suero Méndez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coll-Vinent Puig, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La fibrilación auricular (FA) es la arritmia sostenida de mayor prevalencia en los servicios de urgencias (SHU), que presentan una frecuentación elevada y creciente en España. La FA es una enfermedad grave, que incrementa la mortalidad y asocia una relevante morbilidad e impacto en la calidad de vida de los pacientes y en el funcionamiento de los servicios sanitarios. La diversidad de aspectos clínicos a considerar y el elevado número de opciones terapéuticas posibles justifican la implementación de estrategias de actuación coordinadas entre los diversos profesionales implicados, con el fin de incrementar la adecuación del tratamiento y optimizar el uso de recursos. Este documento recoge las recomendaciones para el manejo de la FA, basadas en la evidencia disponible, y adaptadas a las especiales circunstancias de los SUH. En él se analizan con detalle las estrategias de tromboprofilaxis, control de frecuencia y control del ritmo, y los aspectos logísticos y diagnósticos relacionados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);24(4): 300-324, ago. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104034</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo de los pacientes con fibrilación auricular en los servicios de urgencias hospitalarios (actualización 2012)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21027^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5478^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d902^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
