<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73737</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We live an almost schizophrenic paradox in the rich countries: even when we enjoy thebest life quality and life expectancy with the best health indicators, the feeling of disease andthe dependence on the sanitary system are increasing. It is a fact that we have changed the waywe value health and disease, limits between them have become diffuse, health is another consumer&#146;sgood.Inter alia, pharmaceutical industry has a very important role in the medicalisation of life,collaborating in the transformation of some normal situations into pathological ones and generatingdiseases from potentially treatable situations. Pediatrics is involved in this phenomenon too, so you can observe how pharmacological treatments for the attention deficit and hyperactivitydisorder have increased, and on the contrary, diagnosis of gastroesophageal reflux has diminishedparallel to the disappearance of its main pharmacological treatment.Nevertheless, there are other agents directly or indirectly implicated in this phenomenon ofcommercialization called &#147;disease mongering&#148;, ranging from sanitary staff to institutions. It iscompulsory to identify and understand the problem in order to seek solutions(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morell Sixto, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez González, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintana Gómez, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los países ricos vivimos una paradoja casi esquizofrénica: a pesar de tener mayor calidady esperanza de vida con mejores indicadores de salud, la sensación de enfermedad y la dependenciadel sistema sanitario es cada vez mayor. Es un hecho innegable que hemos cambiado laforma de valorar la salud y la enfermedad, diluyéndose los límites entre ambos y pasando a serla salud un bien de consumo más.Entre otros, la industria farmacéutica tiene un papel muy importante en la medicalizaciónde la vida, colaborando en la transformación de algunas situaciones normales en patológicas yen la génesis de enfermedades a partir de situaciones potencialmente tratables. La Pediatría noes ajena a este fenómeno; basta observar el espectacular incremento de tratamientos farmacológicospara el déficit de atención con hiperactividad, o en sentido contrario la disminución deldiagnóstico de reflujo gastroesofágico, en paralelo a la desaparición de la principal alternativade tratamiento farmacológico. Pero hay otros agentes implicados directa e indirectamente en estefenómeno de mercantilización de las enfermedades llamado disease mongering, desde el colectivomédico sanitario hasta las instituciones. Identificar y entender el problema es básico parabuscar soluciones(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;11(43): 491-512, jul.-sept. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73737</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Disease mongering, el lucrativo negocio de la promoción de enfermedades</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8676^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3177^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4407^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28626</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4407^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22431</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6442^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4407^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4407^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
