<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74110</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Can ¿overlooking¿ a disease in the anamnesis shorten the patient¿s life?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Making a suitable and complete anamnesis is extremely important for the Primary Care physician. We present the caseof a 61-year old male patient who consulted due to overweight,joint pain and fever consistent with brucellosis. Thepatient&#146;s evolution was poor, with a tumor in left shoulder,that was finally diagnosed as melanoma metastasis. The patientwas already aware of the melanoma diagnosis but &#147;unconsciously&#148;forgot to mention it in the anamnesis for no apparentreason.There was a 4-month delay in the diagnosis of the metastasis.If the patient had reported the melanoma background,the diagnosis would have been better oriented, with the consequentearlier treatment of the metastasis as well as improvedlife expectancy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pascual Aguirre, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berrospi Melgarejo, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leal Hernández, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano Sánchez, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La realización adecuada y exhaustiva de la anamnesis es de suma importancia para el médico de Atención Primaria. Presentamos un varón de 61 años que consulta por sobrepeso, dolores articulares y fiebre compatibles con brucelosis. El paciente presenta una mala evolución y sufre una tumoración en hombro izquierdo, que acaba diagnosticándose de metástasis de melanoma. El diagnóstico de melanoma ya era conocido por el paciente, pero fue ¿inconscientemente¿ olvidado por éste en la anamnesis sin motivo aparente. Hubo un retraso de 4 meses en el diagnóstico de las metástasis. Si se hubiese informado de los antecedentes de melanoma se hubiera orientado mejor el diagnóstico, y el tratamiento de dichas metástasis hubiese sido más precoz y probablemente hubiera mejorado su expectativa de vida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);34(10): 517-518, dic. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74110</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Olvidar¿ una patología en la anamnesis ¿puede acortar la vida del paciente?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8287^s22064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8657</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28470</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8714^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31274^s22064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
