<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100543</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Management of cases and research model</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Management of cases is a way of advancing and improving integrated, coordinates ans continuous attention, with the focus on shared responsibility in coordinating care, resourcesm services and professionals. The nurse is the leader of the project since he/she has an overall view aimed at covering needs and fostering self-care. The nurse is an agent of change in this new management and leadership scenario in the health system. The aim of this study is to offer a refection on possible research lines on nursing cares applied to management of cases. The NANDA-NIC-NOC languages comprise an original project to provide an overview of nursing thought, a structure and content to plan care and to take clinical decisions. Evidence-based nursing establishes a useful means to interconnect theory and practice, by providing tools to implement the results from research in nursing clinics and so avoid variations of practice. The use of nursing research focused on measuring results can direct and guide the organization of health services. Case manager nurses have reported results that are effective in reducing mortality and readmissions but it is necessary to develop research questions using terms and elements from the nursing conceptual framework that provide sound results and avoid variations in the clinic (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valverde Jiménez, MR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Corominas, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El modelo de gestión de casos es una forma de avanzar y mejorar la atención integrada, coordinada y continuada, centrado en la responsabilidad compartida de coordinar los cuidados, recursos, servicios y profesionales. La enfermera es líder de este proyecto por tener una visión integral orientada a cubrir necesidades y fomentar el auto-cuidado. Significa un agente de cambio en este nuevo escenario de gestión y liderazgo dentro del sistema sanitario. El objetivo del trabajo es hacer una reflexión sobre posibles líneas de investigación en cuidados de enfermería, aplicadas a la gestión de casos. Los lenguajes NANDA-NIC-NOC constituyen un proyecto original para proporcionar un panorama general de pensamiento enfermero, una estructura y un contenido para planificar cuidados y tomar decisiones clínicas. La enfermería basada en la evidencia establece un medio útil que interconecta teoría y práctica dando instrumentos para implementar los resultados de investigación entre las enfermeras clínicas evitando la variabilidad en la práctica. El uso de la investigación enfermera enfocada a medir resultados, orientará la organización de los servicios de salud. Las enfermeras gestoras de casos han demostrado resultados de efectividad en disminución de la mortalidad y los reingresos pero es necesario construir preguntas de investigación empleando términos y elementos del marco conceptual enfermero que aporten resultados sólidos y eviten variabilidad en la clínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;11(26): 246-250, abr. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100543</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Modelo de gestión de casos e investigación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53395^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53395^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37706</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33937^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33937^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
