<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95057</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bereavement: assessment, diagnosis and treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Throughout their life, all human beings suffer in greater or lesser extent the grief due to a loss. It is an inevitable experience which causes suffering, but it also can be an opportunity for growth. Objectives: with this study our goal is to conduct a bibliographical review both of the articles published over the last few years of studies related with bereavement, as well as of the most relevant details contained in recent literature. Materials and methods: the bibliographical references on which we have based our research have been gathered from Medline and PsycINFO computerized data bases. The majority of the articles are of Anglo-Saxon origin and noteworthy Spanish journals related with the topic have also been consulted. Results: according to the content of the results, we have tried to organize the study in the following areas: evolution of grief; diagnosis of complicated bereavement; predictors of pathological bereavement, prevention and treatment. Conclusions: the majority of the studies found on bereavement are descriptive; however, there are few studies with an adequate experimental design. Nevertheless, we believe that it is necessary to further investigate the fundamental aspects of this complex reality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gil Jiliá, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bellver, Ascensión</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballester, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A lo largo de la vida, todos los seres humanos sufren en mayor o menor medida el duelo por una pérdida. Es una experiencia inevitable que conlleva sufrimiento pero también puede ser una oportunidad de crecimiento. Objetivo: realizar una revisión bibliográfica tanto de los artículos publicados durante los últimos años sobre estudios relacionados con el duelo, como de los aspectos más relevantes contenidos en la literatura reciente. Material y método: las referencias bibliográficas en las que nos hemos basado han sido recogidas de las bases computerizadas Medline y PsycINFO, siendo la mayoría de los artículos encontrados de procedencia anglosajona; además se han consultado las principales revistas españolas relacionas con el tema. Resultados: en función del contenido de los resultados, hemos tratado de organizar el trabajo en las siguientes áreas: evaluación del duelo; diagnóstico de duelo patológico; prevención y tratamiento. Conclusiones: la mayoría de estudios encontrados sobre el duelo son descriptivos, en cambio hay pocos estudios con un diseño experimental adecuado. No obstante, consideramos que es necesario investigar más sobre los aspectos fundamentales de esta compleja realidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);5(1): 103-106, jun. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95057</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Duelo: evaluación, diagnóstico y tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23274</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
