<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76112</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Chronic diseases and functional deterioration in activities of daily living in community-dwelling elders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveTo analyze the influence of chronic medical conditions on functional performance of activities of daily living, both basic (BADL) and instrumental (IADL), among the socially-active older population.MethodsWe performed a cross-sectional study of 380 individuals aged over 64 years old who regularly attended community centers in the city of Zaragoza. The Older Americans Resources and Services (OARS) questionnaire was completed in a personal interview. A multivariate logistic regression model was used to analyze functional capacities for BADL and IADL as dependent variables, and socio-demographic variables and chronic medical conditions as predictive variables.ResultsThe risk of showing dependence for BADL significantly increased in the presence of mild and severe mental illness (OR=4.02; 95% CI=1.81&#150;8.95; and OR=10.61; 95% CI=4.68&#150;24.05, respectively), heart disease (OR=2.79; 95%CI=1.32&#150;5.91), rheumatism/osteoarthritis (OR=2.75; 95% CI=1.42&#150;5.33) and age 75 years or older (OR=2.70; 95% CI=1.42&#150;5.13). For IADL, these risks increased with mild and severe mental illness (OR=2.11; 95% CI=1.10&#150;4.04; and OR=4.50; 95% CI=2.27&#150;8.90, respectively), age 75 years or older (OR=3.06; 95% CI=1.78&#150;5.25) and heart disease (OR=2.64; 95% CI=1.35&#150;5.16).ConclusionThere was greater level of independence for BADL than for IADL. The factor creating most dependence was mental illness, followed by heart disease and rheumatism/osteoarthritis. A declining ability to perform IADL should prompt early assessment of dependence, as it is the first sign to appear. Prevention is fundamental for independent functioning in older people(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Terrer, Tomás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Magallón Botaya, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio Aranda, Encarnación</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lázaro Alquézar, Angelina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoAnalizar la influencia de las enfermedades crónicas en el desempeño funcional de las actividades de la vida diaria, tanto básicas (ABVD) como instrumentales (AIVD), en población mayor socialmente activa.MétodoEstudio transversal de 380 individuos mayores de 64 años que acuden con regularidad a centros de convivencia de Zaragoza capital. Se cumplimentó por entrevista personal el cuestionario OARS, valorándose mediante un modelo multivariante de regresión logística, de forma diferenciada, la capacidad funcional para las ABVD y las AIVD como variables dependientes y las variables sociodemográficas y enfermedades crónicas como predictivas.ResultadosEl riesgo de presentar dependencia para las ABVD aumenta significativamente en presencia de alteraciones mentales leves (odds ratio [OR] = 4,02; intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%: de 1,81 a 8,95), graves (OR = 10,61; IC del 95%: de 4,68 a 24,05), enfermedad cardíaca (OR = 2,79; IC del 95%: de 1,32 a 5,91), reumatismo/artrosis (OR = 2,75; IC del 95%: de 1,42 a 5,33) y tener 75 o más años (OR = 2,70; IC del 95%: de 1,42 a 5,13). Para las AIVD, alteraciones mentales leves (OR = 2,11; IC del 95%: de 1,10 a 4,04), graves (OR = 4,50; IC del 95%: de 2,27 a 8,90), tener 75 o más años (OR = 3,06; IC del 95%: de 1,78 a 5,25) y enfermedad cardíaca (OR = 2,64; IC del 95%: de 1,35 a 5,16).ConclusiónEl nivel de independencia es mayor para las ABVD que para las AIVD. La patología mental es la que se más relaciona con elevados niveles de dependencia, seguida de la cardíaca y de reumatismo/artrosis. El deterioro para el desempeño de las AIVD debería considerarse para una valoración temprana de la dependencia, al ser el primero en aparecer y condicionar de modo fundamental el manejo independiente de los mayores(AU9</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);44(5): 244-250, sep.-oct.2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76112</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedades crónicas y deterioro funcional para las actividades de la vida diaria en población mayor no institucionalizada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32193^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d212</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28940^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
