<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049660</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Immunohistochemical comparative study of the expression of CD4 and CD20 cells in periodontal disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: the role of immunologicalreaction in periodontal disease has been described byseveral reports. The purpose of present research was toinvestigate by immunohistochemistry the density and distributionprofile utilizing the antibodies anti-CD4 and anti-CD20 in 17 cases of chronic gingivitis and 25 of chronicperiodontitis. Results: It was observed immunopositivityfor CD4 cells in diffuse profile by all connective tissue inall chronic gingivitis cases. Out of the 25 cases of chronicperiodontitis, 22 (88%) presented a focal profile distribution.In relation to the CD 20 cells, 16 cases of chronic gingivitishad shown positivity either juxtaepithelial positionas in distant areas of the epithelia (10 cases, 62.5%). Immunopositivityfor the anti-CD20 was observed in 22 chronicperiontitis cases (88%), predominantly in focal profile injuxtaepithelial and distant position of epithelium (17 cases,77.3%). The statistical analysis demonstrated no differencesin relation to the density of CD4 and CD20 cells betweengingivitis and periodontitis cases studied. Conclusion:It was concluded that, although there was no statisticaldifference, a higher density of lymphocytes B wasobserved in both groups, suggesting the predominant participationof the humoral immunity response in different stagesof the periodontal disease</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pina Godoy, Gustavo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almeida Freitas, Roseana de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alves Uchôa Lins, Ruthinéia Diógenes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gordón-Núñez, Manuel Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dantas da Silveira, Ericka Janine</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leite Vieira de Figueiredo, Cláudia Roberta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes y métodos: El papel de la respuestainmune en la citopatogenia de la enfermedad periodontalconstituye tema de estudio de diversos investigadores. Elobjetivo de éste trabajo fue investigar a través de inmunohistoquímicala densidad y el patrón de distribución de lacélulas inflamatorias mononucleadas (linfocitos T helper elinfocitos B), utilizando los anticuerpos anti CD4 y antiCD20 en 17 casos de gingivitis crónica y 25 casos deperiodontitis crónica. Resultados: Fue observada inmunopositividadpara las células CD4 en un patrón difuso portodo tejido conectivo de todos los casos de gingivitis crónica.De los 25 casos de periodontitis crónica, 22 (88%)presentaron un patrón de distribución en pequeños focosaislados. Con relación a las células CD20, 16 casos de gingivitiscrónica exhibieron positividad en un patrón focal dedistribución tanto en posición yuxtaepitelial como en áreasdistantes del epitelio (10 casos, 62,5%). En los casos deperiodontitis crónica fue observada marcación positivapara el anticuerpo anti CD20 en 22 casos (88%), predominandoel patrón focal en posición yuxtaepitelial y distantedel epitelio (17 casos, 77,3%). El análisis estadístico nomostró diferencia significativa en la densidad de célulasCD4 y CD20 positivas entre los casos de gingivitis yperiodontitis crónica. Conclusión: Fue concluido que apesar de no ser constatada tal diferencia estadística, hubouna mayor densidad de linfocitos B en ambos grupos,sugiriendo una mayor participación de la respuesta inmunehumoral el los diferentes estadios de la enfermedadperiodontal</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;39(1): 19-25, abr. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049660</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio comparativo del patrón de expresión inmunohistoquímico de las células CD4+ y CD20+ en la enfermedad periodontal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23473^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10701^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24525^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23164^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6030^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32850^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
