<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-MFM2-10944</identifier>
<setSpec>2014-9832</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nursing students' perception about the educational environment after the implementation of a curricular innovation in the University of Chile</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The School of Nursing of the University of Chile implemented in 2013 a new curriculum based on professional skills. The aim of this study was to evaluate the impact of this curricular innovation through the perception of the educational environment of students who, in 2014, experienced different types of curricula, either former or innovated. Subjects and methods. This was a cross-sectional study. Three cohorts (n = 300), two of them with a former curriculum and another with an innovated curriculum, were surveyed with the DREEM questionnaire. This instrument was designed to measure the perception of the educational environment, and consists of 50 items, divided into five sub-scales: perception about teaching, teachers and learning environment, academic and social self-perception. Results. Overall scores of the perception of the educational environment were significantly higher in the innovated curriculum cohort. No differences were detected between both cohorts with former curriculum. Of the 50 items in the DREEM questionnaire, students with an innovated curriculum presented 23 items with scores considered good (mean &gt; 3.0) and only two items with worrying scores (mean &lt; 2.0). Both cohorts with a former curriculum presented 8 and 11 items with scores considered good, and 10 and 7 items with worrying scores, respectively. Conclusions. According to the students' perception, the process of curricular innovation implemented in the School of Nursing has managed to correct deficient aspects of the former curriculum. However, it is still necessary to work on some aspects in order to remedy them and obtain an effective and successful teaching-learning process (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Véliz, Gabriela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bustamante-Delgado, Sandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La Escuela de Enfermería de la Universidad de Chile implantó en 2013 un nuevo currículo basado en competencias profesionales. El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar el impacto de esta innovación curricular a través de la percepción del ambiente educacional de los estudiantes que, durante 2014, cursaban diferentes tipos de currículos, antiguo o innovado. Sujetos y métodos. Estudio transversal de tres cohortes (n = 300), dos con currículo antiguo y otra con currículo innovado, a las cuales se aplicó el cuestionario Dundee Ready Educational Environment Measure (DREEM). Este instrumento fue diseñado para medir la percepción del ambiente educacional y consta de 50 ítems, divididos en cinco subescalas: percepción de la enseñanza, de los profesores y del ambiente de aprendizaje, y autopercepción académica y social. Resultados. Las puntuaciones totales de la percepción del ambiente educacional fueron significativamente mayores en la cohorte con currículo innovado. No se encontraron diferencias significativas entre ambas cohortes con currículo antiguo. De los 50 ítems del cuestionario DREEM, los estudiantes con currículo innovado presentaron 23 ítems con puntuaciones consideradas buenas (media &gt; 3) y sólo dos ítems con puntuaciones preocupantes (media &lt; 2). En cambio, ambas cohortes con currículo antiguo tuvieron 8 y 11 ítems con puntuaciones buenas, y 10 y 7 ítems con puntuaciones preocupantes, respectivamente. Conclusiones. De acuerdo con la percepción de los estudiantes, el proceso de innovación curricular implementado en la Escuela de Enfermería ha logrado corregir aspectos deficitarios del currículo antiguo. Sin embargo, aún es necesario trabajar sobre ciertos aspectos a fin de remediarlos y obtener un efectivo y exitoso proceso enseñanza-aprendizaje (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Fund. Educ. Méd. (Ed. impr.);20(6): 279-286, nov.-dic. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-MFM2-10944</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Percepción de los estudiantes de enfermería acerca del ambiente educacional tras la implantación de una innovación curricular en la Universidad de Chile</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
