<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60889</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Laparoscopic radical hysterectomy in the sow used as an experimental animal model</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To gain practice in laparoscopic surgery, using the sow as an experimental animal model. Material and method: The sow was used to practice radical hysterectomy, describing the anatomic-surgical «landmarks» that must be followed to complete this kind of surgery. Conclusions: Before performing laparoscopic surgery in a woman, surgeons must follow a step-by-step training period that provides confidence and security. These steps can be learnt using animal models. Thus, when helping an oncological surgeon or when performing surgery, surgeons will have already acquired the experience in handling the genitourinary and pelvic-vascular systems. This experience will be highly useful when performing surgery involving these structures (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Esteban Navarro, Fermín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Ramos, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Ruiz, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escrich López-Davalillo, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nassar Melic, Nadia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrillo de Albornoz, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordónez Pérez, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Adiestramiento en la cirugía laparoscópica, utilizando la cerda como modelo animal experimental. Material y método: Se emplea la cerda para la práctica de una histerectomía radical. Se describen los «hitos» anatomoquirúrgicos que hemos de seguir para completar este tipo de cirugía. Conclusiones: Antes de realizar una cirugía laparoscópica en una mujer tenemos que desarrollar un aprendizaje «por pasos» que nos dé confianza y seguridad. Estos pasos pueden aprenderse en modelos animales. Así, cuando se ayude a un cirujano oncólogo o se llegue a actuar como cirujano, se habrá adquirido previamente una experiencia en manejo de aparato genitourinario y vascular pélvico que será muy importante para poder enfrentarnos a esas estructuras (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);52(4): 215-220, abr. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60889</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Histerectomía radical laparoscópica en la cerda utilizada como modelo animal experimental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7225^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7225^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
