<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-32731</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cardiogenic shock associated with an inappropriate nutritional programme: re-feeding syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Situations of cardiac arrest have been reported in under-nourished patients with protein and calorie deficits when the provision of nutrients was initiated in an uncontrolled manner. The recognition of the association between the provision of food in these circumstances and the serious clinical consequences, generally heartbeat disorders, has led this condition to be described as "re-feeding syndrome".  The case presented here is of severe acute respiratory failure and cardiogenic shock in a 44-year-old female patient with severe protein and calorie malnutrition associated with the start of hyperproteic nutritional support. Treatment with inotropic-vasoactive drugs and diuretics together with a progressive nutritional programme brought about the complete reversal of her heart failure and the concomitant endocrine-metabolic syndrome (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Grupo Aula Médica, S.A.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se han comunicado situaciones de paro cardíaco en pacientes con desnutrición proteico-calórica en los que se iniciaba aporte de nutrientes de manera incontrolada. El reconocimiento de la asociación entre el aporte de alimentos en estas circunstancias y los eventos clínicos graves, generalmente trastornos del ritmo cardíaco, llevó a describirlo como &#147;síndrome de realimentación&#148;. Presentamos un caso de influencia respiratoria aguda grave y shock cardiogénico en una paciente de 44 años con desnutrición proteico-calórica grave asociado al inicio de un soporte nutricional hiperproteico. El tratamiento con drogas inotrópicas-vasoactivas y diuréticos junto con un programa nutricional progresivo consiguió la reversión completa de la insuficiencia cardíaca y del síndome endocrino-metabólico concomitante (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;19(3): 175-177, mayo 2004.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Shock cardiogénico asociado a un programa nutricional inapropiado: síndrome de realimentación</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Romero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos-Ferrer, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ricart, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cervera-Montes, M </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borrás, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-32731</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13148</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13957</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4074</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
