<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93953</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neurocognition in schizophrenia: a study of the productivity and visibility of Spanish authors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper provides a map of the scientific productivity of authors affiliated to a Spanish institution and who have addressed one of the most important current topics in schizophrenia: The study of cognitive performance. A search of the Web of Science yielded 125 articles that met the inclusion criteria. In order to provide a comprehensive overview of scientific productivity, we examine several bibliometric indicators, concerning both productivity and impact or visibility. The analysis also focuses on qualitative aspects of key theoretical importance, such as the kinds of cognitive functions that are most often assessed and the tests most widely used to evaluate them in clinical practice. The study shows that interest in the subject of cognitive function in schizophrenia has increased considerably in Spain since the beginning of this century. The results also highlight the need to standardize the type of tests to be used in the cognitive assessment of patients with schizophrenia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Benito, Juana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pino, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Emilio Rojo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guilera, Georgina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo se centra en ofrecer un mapa de la productividad científica de los autores adscritos a una institución española que se han interesado por uno de los tópicos actuales más relevantes en la esquizofrenia: el estudio del rendimiento cognoscitivo. Se localizaron los estudios en la Web of Science y cumplieron criterios de inclusión 125 artículos. Con la finalidad de ofrecer una visión completa de la productividad científica se analizan diversos indicadores bibliométricos, tanto de productividad como de impacto o visibilidad. Además, se analizaron aspectos cualitativos de gran relevancia teórica actual, como son el tipo de funciones cognoscitivas que más se evalúan, así como los test más utilizados en el campo de la clínica para evaluarlas. Este estudio evidencia que el interés en España por el tema de la función cognitiva en la esquizofrenia ha aumentado considerablemente con la entrada al siglo XXI, teniendo expertos en nuestras instituciones con impacto elevado a nivel internacional. También se constata la necesidad de estandarizar y normalizar el tipo de pruebas que se deben utilizar en la evaluación cognoscitiva de los pacientes con esquizofrenia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);24(1): 22-28, ene.-mar. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93953</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neurocognición en la esquizofrenia: estudio de la productividad y visibilidad de los autores españoles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50131</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50093</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50089</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
