<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72785</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Control of therapeutic inertia in the treatment of arterial hypertension by using different strategies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveTo evaluate the efficacy of different interventions on therapeutic Inertia (TI) in mild-to-moderate hypertension (AHT).DesignControlled, randomised clinical trial.SettingTwo hundred clinics in 5 primary care centres. Spain.ParticipantsA total of 1104 patients with uncontrolled hypertension were included.InterventionFour groups with 276 patients were formed: 1) Control group (CG): standard health intervention; 2) Education intervention and a program of home blood pressure monitoring (HBPM) (EG); 3) Card control intervention and HBPM programme (CHG); 4) Education intervention, card control and HBPM programme (ECHG).Main measurementsTI was calculated by the rate: (Number of patients whose pharmacological treatment was not changed in each visit/Number of patients with an average BP &amp;#8805;140mmHg and/or &amp;#8805;90mmHg in the general population or &amp;#8805;130 and/or 90mmHg in diabetics). The mean BPs and the percentage of controlled patients were calculated. The mean number of people that required an intervention in order to avoid TI was calculated (NI).ResultsA total of 921 patients completed the study, and 1842 visits were made, with TI in 36.8% (IC=5.8%) of the sample and in 82.58% (IC=8.2%) of the uncontrolled hypertensive patients. The TI was 60% (CI=4.2%), 38.4% (CI=4.4%) 30.2 (CI=4.3%) and 14.7 (CI=3.3%) (p=0.001) for CG, EG, CHG and ECHG, respectively. The percentage controlled at the end of study was 35.3% (CI=1.1%), 54.7% (CI=1.8%), 60.2% (CI=2.1%) and 65.1% (CI=2.2%) (p&lt;0.01) for CG, EG, CHG and ECHG, respectively. The NI were 4.6, 3.3 and 2.2 for CG, EG, CHG and ECHG, respectively.ConclusionsTI was very significant among the uncontrolled hypertensive patients. The studied interventions are effective for improving TI(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gil Guillén, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín De Pablos, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espinosa García, Jacinto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casado Martínez, José Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez Contreras, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Figuera Von Wichman, Mariano de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martel Claros, Nieves</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Conclusionesla IT ha sido muy relevante entre los hipertensos no controlados. Las intervenciones estudiadas son eficaces para disminuir la IT(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;41(6): 315-323, jun. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72785</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El control de la inercia terapéutica en el tratamiento de la hipertensión arterial mediante diferentes estrategias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32137^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d555^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28838^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10546^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
