<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119389</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Proteomic biomarkers in Parkinson&#146;s disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Parkinson&#146;s disease (PD) is a neurodegenerative disorder that affects movement and is caused by the death of  the dopaminergic neurons in the compact part of the substantia nigra. Its diagnosis is essentially clinical, but although the signs and symptoms of PD are well known, the rate of diagnostic error is relatively high. It is estimated that 10-30% of  patients initially diagnosed with PD are later reclassified. This disease has a high prevalence beyond the age of 60, and one of its biggest problems is that it is diagnosed when the degenerative process is already at a very advanced stage. Therefore, it is necessary to look for other biomarkers that make it possible to carry out an early diagnosis of PD, follow up its development, distinguish it from other related pathologies (parkinsonisms) and help monitor the effect of novel therapies. The fact that there are mutations that lead to PD, as well as polygenetic combinations that can act as risk factors, suggests the possibility of measuring the proteins resulting from the expression of these genes in peripheral tissues. And once their sensitivity and specificity have been proved they could be used as biomarkers for PD, even in the early phases of the disease. The aim of this work is to focus on a detailed review of the main candidate proteomic biomarkers researched to date by discussing the most recent literature (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Durán, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vives, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bandrés, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrero, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad de Parkinson (EP) es un trastorno neurodegenerativo que afecta al movimiento, cuya causa es la muerte de las neuronas dopaminérgicas de la parte compacta de la sustancia negra. El diagnóstico es fundamentalmente clínico, pero, a pesar de que los signos y síntomas de la EP se conocen bien, el error diagnóstico es relativamente alto. Se calcula que un 10-30% de los pacientes inicialmente diagnosticados de EP se reclasifican posteriormente. Esta enfermedad tiene una alta prevalencia a partir de los 60 años, y uno de los mayores problemas que tiene es que su diagnóstico se hace cuando el proceso degenerativo está muy avanzado. Por tanto, es necesaria la búsqueda de biomarcadores que permitan un diagnóstico precoz de la EP, seguir su progresión, diferenciarla de otras patologías  relacionadas (parkinsonismos) y que ayuden a monitorizar el efecto de nuevas terapias. El hecho de que existan mutaciones que conducen a la EP, así como combinaciones poligénicas que pueden actuar como factores de riesgo, sugiere que es posible analizar las proteínas resultantes de la expresión de estos genes en tejidos periféricos, que, una vez demostrada su sensibilidad y especificidad, podrían utilizarse como biomarcadores de la EP, incluso en fases iniciales de la enfermedad. El objetivo del presente trabajo es centrarse en una revisión detallada de los principales biomarcadores proteómicos candidatos investigados hasta el momento, discutiendo la literatura más reciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;58(4): 166-174, feb. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119389</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Biomarcadores proteómicos en la enfermedad de Parkinson</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51089^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51166^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34510^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
