<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79098</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">External temporary pacemakers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">An external non-invasive pacemaker serves to stimulate the heart by means of an external connection, either transcutaneous or percutaneous. An external pacemaker is composed of a stimulus generator connected to some electrodes in a patch which is applied directly on the thorax wall and these have the function of transmitting electric current. To implant an external non-invasive pacemaker is an emergency treatment which is employed as a transitory measure. The correct use of this technique is based upon adequately placing its patch and on being knowledgeable about the pacemaker generator, which can provide satisfactory results. This article hopes to provide nursing professionals with knowledge about this kind of pacemaker, its placement and management. The authors describe all the steps involved use of this pacemaker, starting with prior steps, the correct placement of the pacemaker electrode patch, how to use the generator and finally, a description of the necessary care after this pacemaker has been implanted. The authors emphasize the specific aspects in the use of an external non-invasive pacemaker by nursing personnel so that these are capable of solving the most frequent problems, thereby contributing to an improvement in the integral care a patient receives(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Artázcoz Artázcoz, M. Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arilla Iturri, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El marcapasos externo no invasivo (MENI) sirve para estimular el corazón a través de una vía externa (transcutánea o percutánea). Un marcapasos externo está compuesto por un generador de estímulos conectado a unos electrodos-parche que se aplican directamente sobre la pared torácica y son los encargados de transmitir el impulso eléctrico. La implantación del MENI es un tratamiento de urgencia que se emplea de forma transitoria. La correcta utilización de esta técnica se basa en la adecuada colocación de los parches y en el conocimiento del aparato generador-marcapasos, ofreciendo resultados satisfactorios. El presente artículo pretende facilitar a los profesionales de enfermería el conocimiento, colocación y manejo de este tipo de marcapasos. Se describen todos los pasos del proceso, comenzando por la actuación previa, la correcta colocación de los electrodos-parche marcapasos, la utilización del generador y finalizando con la descripción de los cuidados necesarios después de la colocación. Se hace énfasis en los aspectos específicos de la utilización del MENI por parte del personal de enfermería de manera que éste sea capaz de resolver los problemas más frecuentes, contribuyendo a la mejora en la atención integral del paciente(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;31(11): 774-777, nov. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79098</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Marcapasos temporal externo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3222^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10326^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4638^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200811</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
