<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161931</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of factors contributing to psychological distress, functional capacity and quality of life in patients with peripheral facial palsy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. The aim of this study was to analyse various factors that can contribute to psychological distress, functional capacity and quality of life in people with incompletely resolved peripheral facial palsy (PFP). Material and methods. We performed a retrospective cross-sectional study in 31 patients with incompletely resolved PFP. The factors analysed were: severity, age, gender, laterality, aetiology, degree of initial nerve injury, duration, marital status and occupation. Psychological distress was assessed through the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS), disability through the Facial Disability Index (FDI) and quality of life through the Facial Clinimetric Evaluation Scale (FaCE) questionnaires. Results. The most important factor was severity, with statistically significant correlations with FaCE Total (r=0.596; p&lt;0.01), FaCE Social (r=0.444; p&lt;0.05), FDI Physical (r=0.539; p&lt;0.01), and FDI Total (r=0.395; p&lt;0.05). Age was correlated with FDI Social (r=0.36; p&lt;0.05). Patients with a partner showed more disability, with statistically significant differences in mean scores of FDI Physical (p&lt;0.01) and FDI Total (p&lt;0.01). Working with the public was associated with lower quality of life, with statistically significant differences in FaCE Total (p&lt;0.05). Conclusion. The severity of PFP is directly correlated with disability and quality of life. Age influences social disability. Marital status is associated with disability and occupation with quality of life. The other factors studied had little influence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valdés-Vilches, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calero-Muñoz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Ferreras, TR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moracén-Naranjo, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bienzobas-Allué, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Aristizabal, U</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. El objetivo de este trabajo es analizar diferentes factores que pueden influir en la afectación psicológica, la capacidad funcional y la calidad de vida en personas que han sufrido una parálisis facial periférica (PFP) no resuelta completamente. Material y métodos. Se realizó un estudio transversal retrospectivo con 31 pacientes que habían sufrido una PFP cuya resolución fue incompleta. Los factores analizados fueron: severidad, edad, sexo, lateralidad, etiología, grado de lesión inicial del nervio, tiempo de evolución, estado civil y ocupación laboral. Se utilizaron cuestionarios de afectación psicológica (Escala de Ansiedad y Depresión Hospitalaria [HADS]), discapacidad (Índice de Discapacidad Facial [FDI]) y calidad de vida (Facial Clinimetric Evaluation Scale [FaCE]). Resultados. El factor más relevante fue la severidad, con correlaciones estadísticamente significativas con el FaCE total (r=0,596; p&lt;0,01), el FaCE social (r=0,444; p&lt;0,05), el FDI física (r=0,539; p&lt;0,01), y el FDI total (r=0,395; p&lt;0,05). La edad se correlacionaba con el FDI social (r=0,36; p&lt;0,05). Los que tenían pareja presentaban mayor discapacidad, con diferencias de medias estadísticamente significativas en el FDI física (p&lt;0,01) y el FDI total (p&lt;0,01). Trabajar de cara al público asociaba una peor calidad de vida, con diferencias estadísticamente significativas en el FaCE total (p&lt;0,05). Conclusión. La severidad de la PFP tiene una correlación directa con la discapacidad y la calidad de vida. La edad influye en la discapacidad social. El estado civil se asocia con la discapacidad y el trabajo con la calidad de vida. La influencia del resto de factores es poco relevante (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);51(2): 73-78, abr.-jun. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161931</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de los factores que influyen en la afectación psicológica, la capacidad funcional y la calidad de vida en pacientes con parálisis facial periférica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50241</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5258^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5258^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8519^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
