<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95664</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Transanal resection using a single port trocar: a new approach to NOTES</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction The morbidity and mortality, along with the functional changes that arise from radical surgery of rectal cancer, has led to an increasing interest in local treatment in the early stages of cancer of the rectum. Conventional transanal surgery has a high recurrence rate, for this reason transanal endoscopic microsurgery (TEM) is considered the treatment of choice in the last few years in large rectal adenomas and in early rectal cancer (low risk T1).Patients and method We have intervened five patients, four with a diagnosis of villous adenoma of the rectum, and one in situ rectal carcinoma, using this new transanal approach, with a single port device. Results The locations of the lesions were in the mid-rectum, at a mean distance of 9cm (range 6-10) from the anal margin. All of them were situated in the posterior side. The resection margins were negative in all cases. The mean size of the adenomas was 4cm, three being sessile shaped, and one with a short, thick pedicle (&gt;1cm); the size of the carcinoma was 3cm. The mean surgical time was 55minutes. All the patients were discharged 48hours after the surgical procedure. Conclusion We believe that the transanal endoscopic approach with a single port device is a simple, easily reproducible and cost-effective procedure when compared to TEM (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cantero Cid, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lima Pinto, Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Alegre, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Jiménez, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Pérez, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Elosua, Tomás</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción La morbilidad y la mortalidad, así como las alteraciones funcionales que conllevan la cirugía radical del cáncer de recto, han hecho que se produzca un incremento en el interés por el tratamiento local del cáncer de recto en estadios precoces. La cirugía transanal convencional ofrece una tasa de recurrencia elevada por lo que en los últimos años la TEM se considera el tratamiento de elección en los adenomas rectales de gran tamaño y en el cáncer de recto precoz (T1 de bajo riesgo).Pacientes y método Hemos intervenido cinco pacientes, con diagnóstico de adenoma velloso de recto (4) y carcinoma in situ de recto (1), mediante este nuevo abordaje transanal, utilizando un dispositivo monopuerto. Resultados La localización de las lesiones fue en recto medio, a una distancia media del margen anal de 9cm (r: 6-10). Todas las lesiones estaban situadas en cara posterior. Los márgenes de resección en todos los casos fueron negativos. El tamaño medio de los adenomas fue de 4cm, siendo tres de forma sésil y uno con pedículo corto y grueso (&gt; 1cm); el carcinoma tenía un tamaño de 3cm. El tiempo medio quirúrgico fue de 55 minutos. Todos los pacientes fueron dados de alta a las 48 horas del procedimiento quirúrgico. Conclusión Pensamos que el abordaje transanal endoscópico a través de un dispositivo monopuerto es un procedimiento sencillo, fácilmente reproductible y coste-efectivo comparado con la TEM (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);89(1): 20-23, ene. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95664</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resección transanal a través de un trocar monopuerto. Una nueva aproximación al NOTES</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54198^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12424^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31678^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201101</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
