<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147640</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Study of the use of analgesics in the management of occasional, mild and moderate painful conditions, in community pharmacies (FANAL study)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To know the pattern of use of OTC analgesic drugs (acetylsalycilic acid [ASA], ibuprofen, paracetamol) in community pharmacies for occasional pains; its dosage, satisfaction, tolerability and the profile of patient that consume them. Methods: Observational, descriptive, comparative and multicentre post-marketing study, carried out at community pharmacies of the Autonomous Region of Madrid. In a first stage of the study dispensation and sociodemographic data were included; and in a second stage, after three days, satisfaction, posology and tolerability data were registered. Statistical analyses were done with SPSS v.12.0 software. Results: 53 community pharmacists recruited 1010 patients, 73.5% of them (n= 704) were women and mean age was 41.6 years old (SD= 14.8). Most of the patients (40.5%) acquired ibuprofen as OTC analgesic; 78.9% of patients requested the analgesic by self-medication. Headache (39.0%), dysmenorrhoea (14.6%) and muscular pain (14.4%) were the most frequent pain disorders among patients, and dental pain was the disorder for wich pharmaceutical care was more often requested (37.1%). Self-medication, in terms of dosage, was correct in 72.8% of patients (n= 606), being ibuprofen the drug that showed a higher overdosage (65.0%). Most of the patients (86.6%) were satisfied with the analgesic taken. 5.1% of patients (n= 46) reported having had annoyances after treatment. Statistical significant differences were not found between presence/absence of annoyances and the analgesic taken (x2 test, p= 0.0479). Conclusions: The results of the study show a good satisfaction and tolerability for three analgesics studied, being ibuprofen the most consumed and ASA the most required by the patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hours Pérez, JE</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferreres Giménez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pueyo Alamán, MG</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Redín Flamarique, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido Costa, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer el patrón de utilización de analgésicos de especialidad farmacéutica publicitaria (EFP) (ácido acetilsalicílico [AAS], ibuprofeno, paracetamol), para dolores ocasionales, desde las farmacias comunitarias, así como su dosificación, satisfacción y tolerabilidad y el perfil del paciente que los consume. Métodos: Estudio postautorización, observacional, descriptivo, comparativo y multicéntrico, llevado a cabo en farmacias comunitarias de la Comunidad Autónoma de Madrid. En una primera fase se recogieron datos del acto de dispensación y sociodemográficos del paciente, y en una segunda fase, al cabo de 3 días, se recogieron datos de satisfacción, posología y tolerabilidad. El análisis estadístico se realizó mediante el programa SPSS v. 12.0. Resultados: Cincuenta y tres farmacéuticos comunitarios reclutaron un total de 1.010 pacientes. Un 73,5% de los pacientes (n= 704) eran mujeres y la media de edad obtenida fue de 41,6 años (desviación estándar de 14,8). El ibuprofeno fue la EFP más dispensada (40,5%). Un 78,9% de los pacientes solicitaron el analgésico por automedicación. Los trastornos dolorosos más frecuentes fueron el dolor de cabeza (39%), la dismenorrea (14,6%) y el dolor muscular (14,4%); el dolor dental fue el trastorno para el que se solicitó mayor indicación farmacéutica (37,1%). Un 72,8% de los pacientes (n= 606) se automedicaron correctamente en términos de dosificación, y el ibuprofeno fue el fármaco con mayor sobredosificación (65%). La mayoría de los pacientes (86,6%) quedaron satisfechos con el analgésico adquirido. Un 5,1% (n= 46) refirió haber tenido molestias con el tratamiento. No se obtuvieron diferencias significativas entre la presencia/ausencia de molestias y el analgésico administrado (prueba x2, p= 0,0479). Conclusiones: Los resultados muestran una buena satisfacción y tolerabilidad de los analgésicos estudiados; el ibuprofeno fue el fármaco más consumido y el AAS, el más solicitado por los pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;9(1): 10-18, mar. 2007. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147640</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de la utilización de analgésicos en el tratamiento de procesos dolorosos ocasionales, leves y moderados, en farmacias comunitarias (estudio FANAL)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28145^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27951^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d714^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
