<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167574</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Development of a food composition database for valoration of dietary intake in Peruvian Amazon</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: The aim of this study was the development of a specific food composition database of Peruvian Amazonia with which value the dietary intake of the population. Methodology: An observational surveying study has been performed at which 303 individuals aged 3-83 years were selected. To compiling a register of basic food reminders of 24 hours (R24) and frequency foods consumption questionnaires (FFQ) over a four-year period were collected, and were complemented by the National Household Budget Survey. The database was formulated on the basis of guidelines described by Greenfiel and Southgate and those proposed by INFOODS. Results: A food composition database was developed using the indirect method with 135 foods provided information on the content in energy, macronutrients, sodium, potassium, phosphorus, calcium, iron, thiamine, riboflavin, folic acid, B12, B6, C, A y D. The references used were those of composition of Peruvian foods, Central America&#146;s, McCance and Widdowson&#146;s and USDA&#146;s tables, among others. Conclusion: The database development was indispensable for the dietary model valuation in this community, because the Composition of Peruvian Foods Tables do not provide sufficiently complete information on nutrient composition of foods the most consumed in Amazonia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Rodríguez, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina Recio, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Saldaña, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Rojas, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: el objetivo de este trabajo ha sido la elaboración de una base de datos de composición de alimentos (BDCA) específica para la Amazonía peruana con la que valorar el consumo dietético de la población. Metodología: se ha llevado a cabo un estudio observacional de encuestación en el que fueron seleccionados 303 individuos de tres a 83 años de edad. Para la elaboración de una lista de alimentos básicos se recogieron recordatorios de 24 horas (R24) y cuestionarios de frecuencia de consumo de alimentos (CFCA) en un periodo de cuatro años, que se complementaron con información de la Encuesta Nacional de Presupuestos Familiares. La elaboración de la BDCA se realizó en base a las directrices descritas por Greenfiel y Southgate y a las propuestas por INFOODS. Resultados: se elaboró una base de datos de composición de alimentos (BDCA) por método indirecto con 135 alimentos que proporcionaban información sobre el contenido en energía, macronutrientes, sodio, potasio, fósforo, calcio, hierro, tiamina, riboflavina, ácido fólico, B12, B6, C, A y D. Las fuentes de información utilizadas han sido las tablas de composición de alimentos peruanos, las de Centroamérica, las de McCance y Widdowson y las del USDA, entre otras. Conclusión: el desarrollo de la base de datos era imprescindible para la valoración del patrón dietético de esta comunidad, ya que las tablas de composición de alimentos peruanos no proporcionan una información completa sobre la composición nutricional de los alimentos que son más consumidos en la Amazonía (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;34(5): 1133-1137, sept.-oct. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167574</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Elaboración de una tabla de composición de alimentos para la valoración de la ingesta dietética en la Amazonía peruana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5350^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4080^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10757^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25401^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9936^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4074^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
