<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107815</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacy and toxicity of erlotinib in non-small cell lung cancer treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To evaluate the efficacy and toxicity of erlotinib in patients with non-small cell lung cancer. Method Patients were selected from an outpatients&#146; dispensing database. The time period selected was from January 2008 to January 2010. Data was collected from patient's medical history &#150; electronic and paper based. We used Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumours (RECIST) to measure response and measured time to progression and overall survival. Toxicity was evaluated according to the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE).Results We found partial response in 5/46 patients and stable disease in 14/46 patients. Time to disease progression was 4.01 months (median 2.33 months) and overall survival was 5.63 months (median 4.67). The most common toxicities were rash, anorexia, asthenia, infection and gastrointestinal side effects. Patients who developed skin toxicity had a (statistically significant) greater time to progression and overall survival rate than the group that did not develop this toxicity (mean time to progression: 2.76 vs. 7.87 months; mean overall survival: 10.74 months vs. 3.98).Conclusions Survival analysis findings suggest lower efficacy in our patient population in comparison with data seen in other publications, and adverse events followed the expected pattern. Although our greatest limitation was sample size, which must be kept in mind, this therapy could be an alternative for patients with non-small cell lung cancer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mucientes-Molina, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Constenla-Caramés, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedrido-Reino, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lago-Rivero, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias-Santos, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero-Ventosa, E. Y</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Evaluar la efectividad y toxicidad del erlotinib en pacientes con cáncer de pulmón no microcítico. Métodos Los pacientes se han seleccionado de una base de datos de dispensación a pacientes ambulatorios. El periodo de tiempo seleccionado fue de enero 2008 a enero 2010 y para la recolección de datos se empleó la historia clínica del paciente en formato electrónico y en papel. Como medida de respuesta hemos usado los criterios RECIST (Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors), también hemos medido el tiempo hasta la progresión y la supervivencia global. La toxicidad se evaluó según la Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE).Resultados Se encontraron respuestas parciales en 5/46 pacientes y criterios de enfermedad estable en 14/46 pacientes. El tiempo hasta progresión de la enfermedad fue 4,01 meses (mediana 2,33 meses) y la supervivencia global 5,63 meses (mediana 4,67). Las toxicidades más frecuentes fueron exantema, anorexia, astenia, infecciones y efectos adversos gastrointestinales. Los pacientes que desarrollaron toxicidad cutánea tuvieron un tiempo hasta la progresión y una supervivencia global mayor (estadísticamente significativo) que el grupo que no la desarrolló (media de tiempo hasta la progresión: 7,87 meses versus 2,76; media supervivencia global: 10,74 meses versus 3,98).Conclusiones Los hallazgos del análisis de supervivencia indican una efectividad menor en nuestra población de pacientes en relación con otras publicaciones y las reacciones adversas describen el patrón esperado. A pesar de tener en cuenta nuestra principal limitación, el tamaño de la muestra, podría tratarse de una alternativa para los pacientes con cáncer de pulmón no microcítico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;36(2): 68-76, Mar. -Abr. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107815</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad y toxicidad de erlotinib en la farmacoterapia del cáncer de pulmón no microcítico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32281</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23827^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d974^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31722^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
