<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78337</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treating severe systemic lupus erythematosus with rituximab. An open study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) is an autoimmune disease that may be associated to high morbidity and mortality. Disease course is variable and unpredictable and although the prognosis and survival of these patients has dramatically improved, treatment of severe multiorganic organic affection in this condition remains a therapeutic challenge. Since B lymphocytes have an important role in the pathogenesis of SLE, it is expected that the targeting of these cells exerts a significant therapeutic effect in SLE patients with severe multiorganic manifestations. In an open clinical trial, we have explored the therapeutic potential of Rituximab (an anti-CD20 monoclonal antibody) administration in SLE patients with severe nephritis (n=22) or neuropsychiatric manifestations (n=6) or massive pulmonary hemorrhage (n=3). In most cases, we observed significant improvement in both clinical and laboratory parameters, with good tolerance and few side effects. Thus, patients with severe lupus nephritis showed improvement in disease activity (MEX-SLEDAI index) with a significant reduction (p&lt;0.05), as well as proteinuria in most of them (from 3.710g/L to 1.786g/L, p&lt;0.05); patients with serious neurologic involvement had complete remission of their manifestations; but those with pulmonary massive hemorrhage did not have any response. Rituximab could have an important therapeutic potential in severe SLE, and that it is necessary to carry out a controlled blinded clinical trial to further support this point (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Irazoque, Fedra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrade, Lilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Amaro, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aranda, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borjas, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vigna-Pérez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Valdés, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abud-Mendoza, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuevas-Orta, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El lupus eritematoso siste´mico es un padecimiento con bases autoinmunes que puede asociarse a elevada morbilidad y mortalidad. El curso es variable e impredecible, y aunque el prono´ stico y la supervivencia de los pacientes han mejorado importantemente, la afeccio´n multiorga´nica puede representar un reto terape´utico. Dado que los linfocitos B tienen un papel protago´nico en esta enfermedad, es esperable que como blanco del tratamiento, pueda resultar en un efecto terape´utico significativo en el lupus eritematoso. En este estudio cl&amp;#305;´nico abierto, exploramos el potencial terape´utico de la administracio´n de rituximab (un anticuerpo monoclonal) en pacientes con lupus grave: nefropat&amp;#305;´a (n ¼ 22), manifestaciones neuropsiquia´tricas (n ¼ 6) o hemorragia pulmonar masiva (n ¼ 3). En la mayor&amp;#305;´a de los pacientes, observamos mejor&amp;#305;´a significativa, tanto en los para´metros cl&amp;#305;´nicos como de laboratorio y gabinete, con buena tolerancia y pocos eventos adversos. De tal manera que los pacientes con nefropat&amp;#305;´a lu´ pica grave mostraron disminucio´n significativa de la actividad de la enfermedad (MEX-SLEDAI) (po0,05), tambie´n en los niveles de proteinuria (de 3.710 g/L a 1.786 g/L, po0,05); los pacientes con afeccio´n neurolo´ gica grave tuvieron remisio´n completa de sus manifestaciones, aunque en aquellos con hemorragia pulmonar masiva no observamos respuesta alguna. Rituximab pudiera tener un importante potencial terape´utico en los pacientes con lupus grave; es necesario el realizar un estudio cl&amp;#305;´nico doble ciego controlado a largo plazo que ratifique nuestros hallazgos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);5(4): 147-152, jul.-ago. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78337</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento del Lupus Eritematoso Severo con Rituximab. Un estudio abierto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7344^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8356^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19233^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32850</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9380^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
