<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104313</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-7279</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This work reflects the experience of diverse members of the Day Hospital for Adolescent in Martorell, which is defined by its service to adolescents and by its willingness to take in the malaise nd crises they suffer. What appeared here are testimonies of a clinical work oriented by «not to complete», by the nonobligatory nature of admission here, the «not wanting to» and the particularized path offered to the patients so that they can make the Hospital a place of their own. The coordinator, the teacher, the cook and the psychologists give account of their work and what they have learnt through short stories that illustrate, in the words of these adolescents, how by «being different this centre works» (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hielga, Salomé</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bertrán, Soledad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Mayoralas, M. Cruz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bugos Bonel, Francisco José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este trabajo se refleja la experiencia de diversos miembros del equipo del Hospital de Día de Adolescentes de Martorell, un lugar definido por estar al servicio de los adolescentes, por estar dispuesto a acoger el malestar y las crisis que los atraviesan. Lo que aquí se presentan son testimonios de un trabajo clínico orientado por el descompletamiento, la no obligatoriedad del ingreso, el «no querer que» y el recorrido particularizado que se ofrece a los pacientes, para que puedan hacer del Hospital un lugar propio. El coordinador, la profesora, la cocinera y una psicóloga dan cuenta de su labor y de su aprendizaje a través de viñetas que ilustran, en palabras de los propios adolescentes, cómo, por «ser diferente», «este sitio funciona» (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Inf. psiquiátr;(206): 375-383, oct.-dic. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104313</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El hospital de día de adolescentes de Martorell</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4581^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3188^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36377^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11798</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3648</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
