<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122448</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pelvic congestion syndrome: outcome after embolization with coils</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To study the clinical manifestations and findings at venography in patients with pelvic congestion syndrome and to evaluate the outcome after percutaneous embolization using coils. Materials and methods: We studied 34 women referred to the vascular radiology unit from the vascular surgery department for clinical suspicion of pelvic congestion syndrome. All patients underwent venography to assess the competence of the ovarian veins and to detect other varicose pelvic veins. When pelvic varicose veins were detected, they were embolized with coils. Clinical outcomes were recorded after reviewing the clinical history and administering a questionnaire over the phone. Results: In 22 of the 34 patients, signs of pelvic venous insufficiency were found. The symptoms were mainly pelvic and perineal heaviness (20/22) and pelvic pain (18/22). The technical success of venography and embolization was 100%, with three minor complications that did not require hospitalization. Pelvic heaviness improved in 14 patients (in 13 it was completely eliminated). Pain disappeared in 11 patients and was partially alleviated in another 2.  Conclusion: In patients with pelvic congestion syndrome, the embolization of insufficient pelvic veins achieves clinical improvement with short hospital stays and few complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Esteban Hernández, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Edo Prades, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer Puchol, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrero Asensi, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudiar las manifestaciones clínicas y los hallazgos venográficos en las pacientes con síndrome congestivo pélvico (SCP), y evaluar los resultados después de la embolización percutánea con espirales. Materiales y métodos: Se estudiaron 34 mujeres en la sección de Radiología Vascular del hospital, todas remitidas con sospecha clínica de SCP desde el servicio de Cirugía Vascular. Las pacientes se estudiaron mediante venografía, valorando la competencia de las venas ováricas y la existencia de otras venas varicosas pélvicas. En las pacientes en las que se detectaron varices pélvicas se procedió a la embolización percutánea con espirales. Posteriormente se registró el resultado clínico revisando el historial clínico de las pacientes y por medio de un cuestionario telefónico. Resultados: En 22 de las 34 pacientes se encontraron signos de insuficiencia venosa pélvica. Los síntomas que referían las pacientes eran principalmente la sensación de peso pélvico y perineal (20/22) y el dolor pélvico (18/22). El éxito técnico alcanzado en las distintas venografías y embolizaciones fue del 100%. En 3 ocasiones se presentaron complicaciones menores que no requirieron de ingreso hospitalario. La mejoría de la sensación de peso pélvico se constató en 14 pacientes (en 13 fue completa). El dolor desapareció en 11 pacientes y disminuyó de forma parcial en otras 2. Conclusión: La embolización de las venas insuficientes pélvicas consigue una mejoría clínica en las pacientes con SCP, con cortos periodos de hospitalización y escasas complicaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);56(3): 235-240, mayo-jun. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122448</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El síndrome congestivo pélvico. Resultados tras la embolización con espirales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23418^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4695^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54529</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15051^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31202^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
