<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042902</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Continuous analgesia of the upper limb with brachial plexus blockade in chronic cancer pain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective:To assess the effectiveness of brachial plexus blockadefor the management of severe cancer pain.Method:In six patients with upper limb bone metastases, we assessedthe effectiveness of continuous blockade of thebrachial plexus.Results:All the study patients had a favorable evolution andanalgesia increased with the treatment, without side effects.Conclusions:Continuous analgesia of the brachial plexus is an effectivemethod for the management of upper limb pain causedby metastases</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Narváez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Condori, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballon, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Glasinovic, K</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo:Evaluar la utilizdad del bloqueo del plexo braquial en eltratamiento del dolor intenso oncológico.Método:Evaluamos en 6 pacientes con metástasis óseas delmiembro superior la efectividad de un bloqueo continuo delplexo braquial.Resultados:Todos los pacientes del estudio tuvieron una evoluciónfavorable y un incremento en la analgesia con el tratamientosin que se produjeran efectos adversos.Conclusiones:La analgesia continua del plexo braquial es un métodoefectivo para el control del dolor del miembro superior pormetástasis</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;12(8): 501-504, dic. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042902</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Analgesia continua de miembro superior por bloqueo de plexo braquial en dolor crónico oncológico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1942</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1136^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9579</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9600^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1884^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
