<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96818</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidemiology of community-acquired rotavirus gastroenteritis in Fuenlabrada (Madrid)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Rotavirus is the main aetiological agent of severe acute gastroenteritis in childhood. Material and methods: A prospective study on the incidence and cost of acute gastroenteritis in childrenunder 5 years. Results: Rotavirus was the most frequent aetiological agent. The cumulative incidence of hospitalisation decreased over the study period.Conclusions: Rotavirus is the most common cause of acute community acquired gastroenteritis requiring hospital admission in the area of Fuenlabrada (Madrid) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García, M. Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Escalada, Alba</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zafra, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivero, M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Rotavirus es el agente etiológico principal en las formas graves de gastroenteritis aguda (GEA) en la infancia. Material y métodos Estudio prospectivo de la incidencia y coste de GEA adquirida en la comunidad en menores de 5 años. Resultados Rotavirus fue el agente etiológico más frecuente. La incidencia acumulada de hospitalización por esta causa disminuyó a lo largo del periodo del estudio. Conclusiones Rotavirus es la causa más frecuente de GEA adquirida en la comunidad que requiere ingreso hospitalario en el área de Fuenlabrada (Madrid) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;29(6): 432-434, jun.-jul. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96818</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Epidemiología de la gastroenteritis por rotavirus adquirida en la comunidad en el área de Fuenlabrada (Madrid)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31778^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12776^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31549^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3995^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201107</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
