<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99799</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4008</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Multicentre evaluation of different methods for the determination of direct HDL-cholesterol compared to the precipitation method</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The results of quality assurance programs suggest that there are significant differences between the homogeneous methods available for the measurement of HDL cholesterol. However, the possible influence of matrix effects in the lyophilized samples used and the absence of a true value in these samples means that a full assessment of these methods cannot be made. In this multicentre pilot study we compared the most used homogeneous methods in our country with the phosphotungstic acid-MgCl2 method. Material and methods. Each laboratory processed about one hundred serum samples from patients with one or two homogeneous methods and sent frozen aliquots of the samples in special packaging with dry ice to the central laboratory where they were processed by the precipitation method. Results. The imprecision of homogeneous methods were good and lower than those of the precipitation method, and met the quality specifications for bias and total error (TE). However, not all homogeneous methods met the minimum quality objectives, as some procedures produced a very high positive bias (relative to the comparison method) and one, a low negative bias. In addition, the study of the agreement between methods, made by stratifying patients according to HDL cholesterol concentrations, showed differences. Conclusions. These results suggest that there are discrepancies in the assessment of the levels obtained with homogeneous methods, probably due to a high inaccuracy in some of them, and it is advised that the laboratories be aware of the characteristics of inaccuracy and bias of the direct method used compared to the reference method (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calmarza Calmarza, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puzo Foncillas, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar Doreste, José Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esteban Salán, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fabiani Romero, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Román, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez Vázquez, Milagros</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Gerique, Juan Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martin-Ballesteros, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Sardina, Romina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los resultados de los programas de garantía de calidad indican que existen diferencias significativas entre los métodos homogéneos disponibles para la medición del colesterol HDL. Sin embargo, la posible influencia de efectos matriz en las muestras liofilizadas empleadas y la ausencia de un valor verdadero en estas muestras, hace difícil la valoración completa de estos métodos. En este estudio experimental multicéntrico hemos comparado los métodos homogéneos más utilizados en nuestro medio, con respecto al de precipitación de ácido fosfotúngstico-MgCl2. Material y métodos. Cada laboratorio procesó unas 100 muestras de suero de pacientes por uno o dos métodos homogéneos y envió alícuotas congeladas de las muestras analizadas al laboratorio central donde se procesaron por el método de precipitación. Resultados. Las imprecisiones de los métodos homogéneos fueron buenas e inferiores a las de precipitación, que cumplía las especificaciones de calidad para sesgo y error total (ET). Sin embargo, no todos los métodos homogéneos cumplían los objetivos de calidad mínimos, pues algunos procedimientos producían sesgos positivos muy altos (en relación al método de comparación) y uno un sesgo negativo muy bajo. El estudio de la concordancia, realizado estratificando a los pacientes según las concentraciones de colesterol HDL, mostró diferencias entre los métodos. Conclusiones. Estos resultados sugieren que existen discrepancias en la valoración de las magnitudes obtenidas con los métodos homogéneos, probablemente generada por una elevada inexactitud en algunos de ellos y que es conveniente que los laboratorios conozcan las caracteristicas de imprecisión y sesgo del metodo directo que utilizan con respecto al de referencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. lab. clín;5(1): 18-27, ene.-mar. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99799</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación multicéntrica de distintos métodos para la determinación de colesterol HDL directo con respecto al colesterol HDL de precipitación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10969</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8250^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13431^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8250^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13431^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13431^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13431^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29347^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24872</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29563^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10969^s22065</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29347^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13431^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8250^s22065</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
