<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88470</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neurotrophic corneal ulcer in an HIV patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report:We present the case of a 29 year-oldmanwhocame to the EmergencyDepartmentdue to pain in the right eye. Therewas demonstrated a complete corneal de-epithelialisation.There was no clinical improvement after appropriate treatment, which was complicated bymigraine and vomiting. The computerized tomography (CT) scan showed images suggestiveof cerebral toxoplasmosis. After the complete tarsorrhaphy a restitution ad integrum wasobserved.Conclusion: The diagnosis of a neurotrophic corneal ulcer due to an affected trigeminal nervein the context of a cerebral toxoplasmosis, tarsorrhaphy is an effective procedure to take inaccount in corneal epithelial defects resistant to other treatments(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Benítez-Herreros, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paz Moreno-Arrones, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero-García Tenorio, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Drake-Rodríguez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Se presenta el caso de un varón 29 an&#152; os acude a Urgencias de oftalmología pordolor en ojo derecho. Se evidenció una desepitelizacion corneal completa. Tras un tratamientoadecuado no se evidenció mejoría clínica, complicándose el cuadro con cefalea yvómitos. la tomografía axial computarizada (TAC) evidenció imágenes sugestivas de toxoplasmosiscerebral. Tras la tarsorrafia completa se observó una restitución ad integrum delcuadro.Conclusión: Ante el diagnóstico de una úlcera corneal neurotrófica por afectación del trigéminoen el contexto de toxoplasmosis cerebral, la tarsorrafia es un procedimiento eficaz atener en cuenta ante defectos epiteliales corneales resistentes a otros tratamientos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;86(1): 27-30, ene. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88470</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Úlcera corneal neurotrófica en paciente con VIH</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29772^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27978^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201101</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
