<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165924</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Lifestyle, adherence to Mediterranean diet, anthropometric characteristics in a group of university health sciences students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: University students are facing important changes of lifestyle, the pattern of adherence to Mediterranean Diet and nutritional status. The objective of this study was to know the characteristics of these factors implemented in university students of Valencia and their associations.  Methods: A cross-sectional study on University students aged 18 to 27 years. We evaluated the characteristics of lifestyles and anthropometric values by gender and age and the association between them by univariate and bivariate analysis, including the Mann-Whitney U-test and Spearman correlations. Results: Of a total of 682 students we observed a low prevalence of obesity (1.5%). Women presented higher levels of tobacco consumption (32.5%), while men were more prone to skip breakfast showed higher frequencies in the lack of breakfast (7.1%). The younger age group (&amp;#8804;23) had a lower adherence to the Mediterranean diet. A positive correlation was observed between BMI, smoking (p=0.001) and adherence to the Mediterranean diet (p&lt; 0.0001). There is also negative correlation between BMI and the frequency of breakfast (p=0.007), lunch (p=0.002) and snack (p=0.006).  Conclusions: The university students present mainly a suitable BMI with a low prevalence of obesity. There is room for improvement in the adherence to a Mediterranean Diet, the habit of eating breakfast and healthy lifestyles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guillem Saiz, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yang Wang, Yang</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillem Saiz, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saiz Sánchez, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guadalupe Fernández, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: Los estudiantes universitarios viven importantes cambios de estilo de vida, patrón de adherencia a dieta mediterránea y estado nutricional. El objetivo de este estudio fue conocer las características de estos factores en universitarios valencianos y las asociaciones de estos entre sí. Métodos: Estudio descriptivo transversal en estudiantes universitarios de 18 a 27 años. Se evaluaron las características de estilos de vida, valores antropométricos, por género y edad, así como la asociación entre ellos mediante análisis descriptivo univariante y bivariante, incluyendo el test de U-Mann Whitney y la correlación de Spearman. Resultados: Entre los 682 estudiantes estudiados hay una baja prevalencia de obesidad (1,5%). Las mujeres presentan mayor nivel de consumo de tabaco (32,5%), mientras que los hombres muestran mayores frecuencias en la falta de desayuno (7,1%). Asimismo, el grupo de menores de 23 años destaca por una baja adherencia a la dieta mediterránea. Se observó una correlación positiva entre IMC, consumo de tabaco (p=0,001) y adherencia a la dieta mediterránea (p&lt;0,0001). Existe correlación negativa entre IMC y frecuencia de desayuno (p=0,007), almuerzo (p=0,002) y merienda (p=0,006). Conclusiones: Los alumnos universitarios presentan mayoritariamente un IMC adecuado con baja prevalencia de obesidad. Existe margen de mejora en la adherencia a dieta mediterránea, en el hábito de desayuno y en los estilos de vida saludable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;23(2): 0-0, abr.-jun. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165924</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estilos de vida, adherencia a la dieta mediterránea, características antropométricas en un colectivo de universitarios de ciencias de la salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13723^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13720^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37653</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
