<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93898</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Youth sport environment perceived by athletes. parents, coaches and managers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study had a two-fold objective: first, to create a measure to assess athletes&#146;, parents&#146;, coaches&#146; and managers&#146; perception of the sport environment for children and second, to analyse the differences among them with respect to their perceptions of that environment. The participants &#150;333 athletes, 333 parents, 63 coaches and 46 managers&#150; completed the Perception of Youth Sport Environment Questionnaire, created for this investigation. An exploratory factor analysis revealed the existence of five dimensions in perceiving sport context: good refereeing, sportspersonship, educational coaches, respectful parents and competition organisation. The multivariate analyses of the sport environment dimensions based on group and gender showed that managers were the most critical agents in their evaluations of the youth sport context, including their own organisation. The results are discussed for their practical applications to coaching and managing youth sports (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez, Melchor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guzmán, José Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pablos, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carratalà, Vicent</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El propósito de este trabajo fue doble. Primero, crear un instrumento para valorar la percepción que los deportistas, padres, entrenadores y gestores tienen del entorno deportivo juvenil. Segundo, analizar las diferencias de percepción entre ellos sobre ese entorno. Los participantes, 333 deportistas, 333 padres, 63 entrenadores y 46 gestores, respondieron al Cuestionario de Percepción del Entorno Deportivo Juvenil, creado para esta investigación. Un análisis factorial exploratorio reveló la existencia de cinco factores: Buen arbitraje, deportividad, entrenadores educadores, padres respetuosos y organización de la competición. Los análisis multivariados de las dimensiones del entorno deportivo en función del grupo y el género mostraron que, entre los diferentes agentes, los gestores fueron los más críticos con todas las dimensiones del entorno deportivo, incluso con su propia organización. Se discuten los resultados por su aplicación práctica para la gestión y el entrenamiento del deporte juvenil (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;20(2): 337-352, jul.-dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93898</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Percepción del entorno deportivo juvenil por deportistas, padres, entrenadores y gestores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54376^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54376^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10479^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29938^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
