<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166067</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The use of the interpersonal distance in the motor behavior of boxers with different sport level</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to compare the motor performance (i.e., reaction time and response accuracy) of a reduced boxers sample with different sport levels (n = 4 advanced and n = 4 novices) during the perception of sequences of 10 trials containing opponents&#146; attacks at different distances (i.e., short, medium, long), both in field (3D) and laboratory-based scenarios (2D). The likelihood of the opponent&#146; actions was manipulated according to the participant´s distance. The participants had to react quickly and accurately, performing a proper dodge to the opponent&#146;s hits. A high-speed camera was used to analyze motor behavior. The results showed that the advanced group reacted faster than the novices in the short and long distances, being more accurate at all distances. When the dimensionality was included into the analysis, the group of higher level was faster (2D) and more accurate (2D and 3D) at the three distances. Therefore, the advanced boxers used the interpersonal distance as contextual information to improve the defensive behavior against the opponents (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Fernández, Rodrigo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campo, Vicente Luis del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del estudio fue comparar el comportamiento motor (i.e., tiempo de reacción y precisión en la respuesta) en una muestra reducida de boxeadores de diferente nivel deportivo (n = 4 avanzados y n = 4 noveles) durante la percepción de series de 10 acciones de ataque del oponente a diferentes distancias (i.e., corta, media, larga), tanto en situación real (3D) como video-proyectada (2D). La probabilidad de aparición de unas acciones u otras del oponente fue manipulada en función de su distancia de separación al participante. Los participantes debían de reaccionar rápida y precisamente, ejecutando una esquiva adecuada al ataque del oponente. Se utilizó una cámara de alta velocidad para analizar el comportamiento motor. Los resultados mostraron que los boxeadores avanzados reaccionaron antes que los noveles en la distancia corta y larga, siendo más precisos en todas las distancias. Cuando se incluyó la dimensionalidad en el análisis, el grupo de mayor nivel fue más rápido en las tres distancias (2D) y más preciso (2D y 3D). Por todo ello, los boxeadores avanzados usaron la distancia interpersonal como información situacional para mejorar su comportamiento defensivo frente a los oponentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;26(2): 87-93, 2017. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166067</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El uso de la distancia interpersonal en el comportamiento motor de boxeadores de diferente nivel deportivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4276</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12364</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10741</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1939^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
