<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-33790</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neuronal survival following axotomy: a model for the experimental section of the optic nerve</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. Retina is a privileged tissue to study the central nervous system (CNS) due to the disposition of different cell types and synaptic plexus. Moreover, the retina and the optic nerve are accessible for manipulation and surgery. Neuronal consequences of axotomy have been widely studied in this portion of the CNS. This paper offers a brief review of the morphological changes experienced by axotomized cells. We show these consequences in retinal ganglion cells (RGCs) injured by optic nerve section. Development. Neurons transmit information to other cells through their axons; by cutting the axon not only the synaptic transmission is interrupted, but cell death is induced in axotomized neurons. In many cases degeneration of pre and postsynaptic neurons is also triggered. However, in the retinal model, some RGCs are able to survive to axotomy; they experience profound changes trying to adapt to a new situation. Such changes have been observed in labeled axotomized cells. Conclusion. Knowledge of the qualitative and quantitative changes after injury, as well as the determination of no return point in the evolution of the lesion are aspects that must be known before to start a repairing therapy of the function (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. La retina se considera un tejido privilegiado para el estudio del sistema nervioso central (SNC) debido a su ordenada disposición en capas celulares y en plexos sinápticos, así como al fácil acceso que tanto la retina como el nervio óptico ofrecen al investigador. Por ello, en la retina se han investigado las consecuencias que para las neuronas del SNC tiene la sección de su axón. Así, en este artículo pretendemos ofrecer una breve revisión de los acontecimientos que suceden en las células ganglionares de la retina (CGR) como consecuencia de la sección del nervio óptico. Desarrollo. El axón neuronal lleva la información a otras células; su sección provoca no sólo la interrupción inmediata de la transmisión nerviosa, sino también la muerte retardada de la neurona axotomizada y la degeneración de las neuronas pre y/o postsinápticas. Sin embargo, unas pocas CGR sobreviven más tiempo, mientras desarrollan unos cambios con los que pretenden adaptarse a una situación nueva en la que han perdido la fuente de factores tróficos. Dichos cambios se han estudiado mediante técnicas de marcaje químico e inmunohistoquímico aplicado a preparaciones de retinas, previamente lesionadas, completas o a secciones de éstas. Conclusión. El conocimiento de las fases por las que las neuronas atraviesan y los cambios cuantitativos y cualitativos que sufren, así como la determinación del punto sin retorno en la evolución de la lesión, son aspectos que deben conocerse antes de iniciar un tratamiento reparador de la función (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;38(11): 1043-1049, jun. 2004. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Supervivencia neuronal a la axotomía: modelo de sección experimental de nervio óptico</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Villa Polo, P de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Germain, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-33790</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d12582</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33568</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30827</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2505</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
