<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80788</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of telmisartan vs olmesartan on metabolic parameters, insulin resistance and adipocytokines in hypertensive obese patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Angiotensin II regulates the production of adipokines. The objective was to study the effect of treatment with telmisartan versus olmesartan in hypertensiveobese and overweight patients. Subjects: A sample of 65 overweight and obese patients with mild to moderate hypertension was analyzed in a prospective way with a randomized trial. Patients were randomized to telmisartan (80 mg/day) or olmesartan (40 mg/day) for 3 months. Weight, body mass index, blood pressure, basal glucose, insulin, total cholesterol, LDLcholesterol, HDL-cholesterol, triglycerides, HOMA, QUICKI, leptin and adiponectin were determined at basal time and after 3 months of treatment. Results: Sixty five patients gave informed consent and were enrolled in the study. Patients treated with telmisartan had a significative decrease of glucose 10.53 mg/dl (CI 95%: 2.6-18.5), insulin 2.51 mUI/L (CI 95%: 2.07-7.17) and HOMA 1.08 (CI 95%: 0.39-2.55). Patients treated with olmesartan had a significative decrease of total cholesterol 20.2 mg/dl (CI 95%: 5.8-34.9) and LDL cholesterol 22.6 mg/dl (CI 95%: 9.7-35.6). Only leptin levels have a significant decrease in telmisartan group 7.39 ng/ml (CI 95%: 1.47-13.31). Conclusion: Telmisartan improved blood pressure, glucose, insulin, HOMA and leptin in hypertensive diabetic patients. Olmesartan improved blood pressure and lipid levels (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Luis, DA de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dueñas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Castrillón, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conde, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aller, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Sagrado, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izaola, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La angiotensina II puede regular la producción de adipocitoquinas. El objetivo de nuestro trabajo fue evalaur el efecto sobre parámetros bioquímicos del tratamiento con telmisartan versus olmesartan en pacientes obesos hipertensos. Pacientes: Se analizó una muestra de 65 pacientes con hipertensión moderada severa y obesidad, mediante un ensayo clínico randomizado. Los pacientes fueron randomizados en dos ramas; telmisartan (80 mg/día) u olmesartan (40 mg/día) durante 3 meses. Se determinaron en el tiempo basal y tras 3 meses los siguientes parámetros; peso, índice de masa corporal, presión arterial, glucosa, insulina, colesterol total, LDL-colesterol, HDL-colesterol,triglicéridos, HOMA, QUICKI, leptina y adiponectina. Resultados: Los pacientes que recibieron telmisartan tuvieron una disminución significativa de los niveles de glucosa 10,53 mg/dl (CI 95%: 2,6-18,5), insulina 2,51 mUI/L (CI 95%: 2,07-7,17) y HOMA 1,08 (CI 95%: 0,39-2,55). Los pacientes tratados con olmesartan presentaron una disminución significativa de colesterol 20,2 mg/dl (CI 95%: 5,8-34,9) y LDL colesterol 22,6 mg/dl (CI 95%: 9,7-35,6). Solo, los niveles de leptina disminuyeron de manera significativa con telmisartan 7,39 ng/ml (CI 95%: 1,47-13,31). Conclusion: Telmisartan mejora los niveles de presión arterial, glucosa, insulina, HOMA y leptina en pacientes hipertensos obesos. Olmesartan mejoró los niveles de presión arterial y el perfil lipídico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;25(2): 275-279, mar.-abr. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80788</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de telmisartan vs olmesartan sobre parámetros antropométricos, resistencia a la insulina y adipocitoquinas en pacientes hipertensos obesos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1585^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1588^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14679^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2834^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7274^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14156^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52657^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
