<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040085</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6709</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Microbiologically influenced corrosion: looking to the future</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This review discusses the state-of-the-art of research into biocorrosion and the biofouling of metals and alloys of industrial usage. The key concepts needed to understand the main effects of microorganisms on metal decay, and current trends in monitoring and control strategies to mitigate the deleterious effects of biocorrosion and biofouling are also described. Several relevant cases of biocorrosion studied by our research group are provided as examples: (i) biocorrosion of aluminum and its alloys by fungal contaminants of jet fuels; (ii) sulfate-reducing bacteria (SRB)-induced corrosion of steel; (iii) biocorrosion and biofouling interactions in the marine environment; (iv) monitoring strategies for assessing biocorrosion in industrial water systems; (v) microbial inhibition of corrosion; (vi) use and limitations of electrochemical techniques for evaluating biocorrosion effects. Future prospects in the field are described with respect to the potential of innovative techniques in microscopy (environmental scanning electron microscopy, confocal scanning laser microscopy, atomic force microscopy), new spectroscopic techniques for the study of corrosion products and biofilms (energy dispersion X-ray analysis, X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy, electron microprobe analysis) and electrochemistry (electrochemical impedance spectroscopy, electrochemical noise analysis) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Videla, Héctor A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera, Liz K</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Esta revisión describe la situación actual de la investigación en biocorrosión y bioensuciamiento (biofouling) de metales y de aleaciones de uso industrial. También se describen los conceptos clave necesarios para comprender los efectos principales de los microorganismos en el deterioro del metal, así como las tendencias actuales en las estrategias de supervisión y control para atenuar los efectos perjudiciales de la biocorrosión y del bioensuciamiento. Como ejemplos, se describen algunos casos destacados de biocorrosión estudiados por nuestro grupo de investigación: (i) biocorrosión del aluminio y de sus aleaciones por hongos contaminantes de los combustibles de motores de propulsión a chorro; (ii) corrosión del acero causado por bacterias sulfatorreductoras (SRB); (iii) interacciones de biocorrosión y bioensuciamiento en ambientes marinos; (iv) estrategias de supervisión para evaluar la biocorrosión en sistemas industriales del agua; v) inhibición microbiana de la corrosión; (vi) uso y limitaciones de las técnicas electroquímicas para evaluar los efectos de la biocorrosión. Se describen las perspectivas futuras en este campo en relación al potencial de las técnicas innovadoras en microscopia (microscopia electrónica de barrido ambiental, microscopia confocal laser de barrido, microscopia de fuerzas atómicas), de las nuevas técnicas espectroscópicas usadas para el estudio de la corrosión de productos y de los biofilmes (análisis mediante rayos-X de dispersión de energía, espectroscopia fotoelectrónica de rayos X, análisis mediante microsonda electrónica) y de la electroquímica (espectroscopia de impedancia electroquímica, análisis del ruido electroquímico) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int Microbiol;8(3): 169-180, sept. 2005. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040085</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Corrosión de origen microbiológico: mirando al futuro</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4635^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13440^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32342</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3359</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35502</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32433</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13818^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13818^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10764^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
