<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84030</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Rectal cancer: Which patients benefit from radiotherapy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The prognosis of patients with rectal cancer has improved in recent years, particularly as regards the lower probability of local recurrence. These positive results are obtained through correct preoperative staging and an adequate surgical resection of the affected lesion, as well as a multidisciplinary therapeutic approach. Based on the available scientific evidence, our aim is to clarify the framework in which options for the right therapy can be taken, especially in relation to the preoperative staging and its limitations, with regards to radiotherapy and its indications. We also emphasize the need of a tailor-made approach for each case (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Santos,  Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manzanares Sacristán, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Pérez, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ais Conde,  Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fadrique Fernández, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Picatoste Merino,  Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El pronóstico de los pacientes con cáncer de recto ha mejorado en los últimos años, sobre todo en relación con la menor probabilidad de recidiva local. Estos resultados se consiguen con una correcta estadificación preoperatoria, una adecuada escisión quirúrgica de la lesión y un abordaje terapéutico multidisciplinar. Basándonos en la evidencia científica disponible, nuestro propósito es tratar de clarificar el marco en el cual se toman las decisiones terapéuticas, especialmente en relación con la estadificación preoperatoria y sus limitaciones y con el tratamiento con radioterapia y sus indicaciones, así como resaltar la necesidad de un enfoque individualizado en cada caso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);87(6): 350-355, jun. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84030</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cáncer de recto: qué pacientes se benefician de la radioterapia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d20180</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12424^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33861</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12424^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9557^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12424^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
