<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039555</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Selective arterial embolization in the treatment of non tractable hematuria</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: Non tractable hematuria has ;;a varied etiology. It may be a complication difficult to ;;treat. We report the case treated in our hospital by selective ;;arterial embolization. ;;METHODS: We report the case of an 86-year-old patient ;;who underwent radiotherapy for transitional cell carcinoma. ;;Later on, she presented with hematuria, not responding to ;;usual therapeutic management. Urinary diversion did not ;;solve the problem either. We decided to proceed with ;;selective arterial embolization of the hypogastric arteries ;;using polyvinylalcohol microspheres and metallic coils. ;;RESULTS: Hematuria disappeared after embolization, ;;without the recurrence after nine months of follow-up. ;;Immediate outcome was characterized by a post-embolization ;;syndrome which was treated with antipyretics, antibiotic ;;and morphine derivatives. ;;It diminished progressively and disappeared in 48 hours. ;;CONCLUSIONS: Arterial selective embolization is a useful ;;therapeutic resource for the management of non tractable ;;hematuria, mainly in cancer patients, which present a ;;deteriorated general status</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Medina López, Rafael Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias López, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Congregado Ruiz, Carmen Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peiró de las Heras, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual del Pobil Moreno, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Argüelles Salido, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVOS: La hematuria incoercible es uncuadro de etiología diversa. Puede ser una complicacióndifícil de controlar. Nos proponemos presentar un caso tratadoen nuestro hospital con embolización arterial selectiva.MÉTODOS: Comunicamos el caso de una paciente de86 años sometida a tratamiento radioterápico debido aneoplasia urotelial. Presentó posteriormente una hematuriaque no cedió a las medidas terapéuticas habituales.Tampoco la derivación urinaria solucionó el cuadro. Porello optamos por practicar una embolización arterial selectivade arterias hipogástricas, con microesferas de polivinilode alcohol y coils metálicos.RESULTADO: La hematuria desapareció desde el momentode la embolización, sin reaparecer en un tiempo deseguimiento de nueve meses. La evolución inmediata secaracterizó por un &#147;síndrome post-embolización&#148;, tratadocon antitérmicos, antibiótico y derivados mórficos. Cedióprogresivamente hasta desaparecer a las 48h.CONCLUSIONES: La embolización arterial selectiva esun recurso terapéutico útil para el manejo de hematuriasde difícil control, sobre todo en enfermos neoplásicos, yade por sí muy deteriorados</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;58(5): 453-457, jun. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039555</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Embolización arterial selectiva en el tratamiento de la hematuria incoercible</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4695</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6566^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
