<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148414</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8799</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Differences in ground reaction forces between running shoes with two types of drop</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: In running shoes, drop is referred to the difference between the thickness of sole of the heel and thickness of sole of the forefoot and toes. The drop is classified into three types according to the measurement. Every drop has its own characteristics that affect the realization of race cycle. Little is known the effect of drop on the kinetics, for this reason the objective of the study was to compare the forces of reaction with two types of drop. Material and methods: We conducted a study in 14 male subjects who ran on at least 4 hours a week and which should bring two pairs of running shoes, a pair of fast taxiing and another pair of long running. The ground reaction forces were measured (running speed, contact time, and braking, propulsion, take off and oscillation forces), with SVE/IBV force platform. We collected the data to each subject and also proceeded to determine the drop of each pair of shoes. Results: In the time of support in both feet, between the drops of maximum and minimum both in the right foot and left foot there were significant differences (p = 0.001 and p = 0.010), indicating that the time was reduced with the use of one smaller drop. For this reason there was positive correlation in two drops, between the time of support and the step speed. (r = -0.717, p = 0.004). Conclusions: We conclude that with lower drop shoes influence the kinetics of the race, shortening the time of the shoe with the ground support. However, neither features anthropometric, nor carry different drop in running shoes influenced the ground reaction forces (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cuevas García, José Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Nova, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez González, M Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Lloris, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: En las zapatillas de correr, el drop hace referencia a la diferencia entre el grosor de la suela del talón y el grosor de la suela del antepié y dedos. El drop se clasifica en tres tipos según la medición. Cada uno tiene características propias que afectan a la consecución del ciclo de la carrera. Se conoce poco el efecto del drop sobre la cinética, Por eso el objetivo del estudio fue comparar las fuerzas de reacción con dos tipos de drop. Material y métodos: Se realizó un estudio a 14 sujetos varones que corrían al menos 4 horas a la semana y que debían aportar dos pares de zapatillas de correr, un par de rodaje rápido y otro par de rodaje largo. Se midieron las fuerzas de reacción del suelo (velocidad de carrera, tiempo de apoyo y fuerzas de frenado, propulsión, despegue y oscilación), con plataforma de fuerzas SVE/IBV. Se recogieron los datos a cada sujeto y También se procedió a determinar el drop de cada par de zapatillas. Resultados: En el tiempo de apoyo en ambos pies, entre los drops máximo y mínimo tanto hubo una diferencia de en el pie derecho como en el pie izquierdo hubo diferencias signicativas (p = 0,001 y p = 0,010, indicando que el tiempo se reducía con el uso de un drop menor. Por esto hubo correlación positiva en los dos drops, entre el tiempo de apoyo y velocidad del paso . (r= - 0717, p = 0.004) Conclusiones: En conclusión pudimos decir que Las zapatillas con menor drop influyen en la cinética de la carrera, acortando el tiempo de apoyo de la zapatilla con el suelo. Sin embargo, ni las características antropométricas, ni llevar diferente drop en las zapatillas in_uyó en las fuerzas de reacción del suelo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. med. deporte;32(170): 382-386, nov.-dic. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148414</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias en las fuerzas de reacción del suelo entre zapatillas de carrera con dos tipos de drop</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4943^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12793^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23143</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14532^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14532^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12793^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4943^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
