<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052930</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cross-cultural validation of Antonovsky's Sense of Coherence Scale (OLQ-13) in Spanish elders aged 70 years or more</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Sense of Coherence (SOC) is a construct relating to coping strategies in the face of traumatic events. SOC is defined as a personal disposition towards perceiving life experiences as understandable, manageable and meaningful. The construct has shown itself to be a predictor of self-reported and objective health in a variety of contexts. Although the SOC construct has been studied, among the elderly in particular, the scale has never been validated in the Spanish aged population. This paper reports on the cross-cultural validation of Antonovsky's Sense of Coherence Scale (OLQ-13) in a sample of Spanish senior citizens. Subjects and method: We studied a sample of population from 8 locations across Spain, totaling 419 subjects aged 70 years or over. The psychometric attributes of the scale were studied. These included acceptability, scale assumptions, internal consistency, factor structure, construct validity (convergent validity, differential analyses, inter-domains correlation), and precision. Results: The internal consistency of the scale was adequate (Cronbach = 0.80). SOC showed moderate correlations with self-reported indices of physical health, quality of life and depression. The scale was found valid in differential analyses conducted for gender, age groups, levels of disability and functional impact of diseases. Principal components analysis yielded four factors accounting for 65.59% of the variance. The Meaningfulness domain acted as an independent factor. Conclusions: The OLQ-13 is a valid and reliable instrument for use on Spanish elderly populations, including those with low educational level</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barrio, José Luis del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Virués-Ortega, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Martín, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano, Luis M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: El sentido de coherencia (SOC) es un constructo relacionado con el afrontamiento de situaciones traumáticas que se ha empleado extensamente como predictor de medidas de salud percibida y objetiva. El SOC es una disposición personal hacia la valoración de las experiencias vitales como comprensibles, manejables y significativas. Esta medida se ha mostrado especialmente informativa en poblaciones envejecidas, pese a lo cual la escala no se ha validado en población española anciana. En este trabajo presentamos la validación transcultural y el estudio de las propiedades métricas de la escala de SOC de Antonovsky, de 13 ítems (OLQ-13), en una muestra de población de ancianos españoles. Sujetos y método: La muestra estuvo compuesta por 419 personas de más de 70 años procedentes de 8 localidades españolas. Se estudiaron la aceptabilidad, asunciones escalares, consistencia interna, estructura factorial, validez de constructo (validez convergente, análisis diferenciales, correlación entre dominios) y precisión del instrumento. Resultados: La consistencia interna de la escala fue adecuada (* de Cronbach = 0,80). El SOC mostró validez convergente con medidas autorreferidas de salud física, calidad de vida y depresión. La escala también demostró ser válida en sucesivos análisis diferenciales según grupos de edad, sexo, niveles de discapacidad y de impacto funcional de enfermedades. El análisis de componentes principales ofreció una solución multifactorial con un porcentaje de la variancia explicada del 65,59%. La subescala de significación parece formar un factor independiente. Conclusiones: El OLQ-13 es una escala válida y fiable para su uso en poblaciones ancianas españolas, incluidos grupos con bajo nivel de instrucción</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);128(13): 486-492, abr. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052930</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación transcultural de la Escala de Sentido de Coherencia de Antonovsky (OLQ-13) en ancianos mayores de 70 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8192</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
