<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151423</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Transsexualism: a brain disorder that begins to known</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Transsexualism describes the condition when a person&#146;s psychological gender differs from his or her biological sex. People with gender identity disorder suffer persistently from this incongruence and they search hormonal and surgical sex reassignment to the desired anatomical sex. This review, from an ethical perspective, intends to give an overview of structural and functional neurobiological correlations of transsexualism and their course under cross-sex hormonal administration. Several studies demonstrate an  increased functional connectivity between cortex regions reaffirming psychosocial distress of psychologicalbiological sex incongruity. Such distress can be ascribed to a disharmonic body image due to changes in the functional connectivity of the key components of body representation network. These brain alterations seem to imply a strategic mechanism dissociating bodily emotions from bodily images. For a number of sexually dimorphic brain structures or processes, signs of feminization or masculinization are observable in transsexual individuals, who during hormonal administration seem to partly further adjust to characteristics of the desired sex. These changes allow a reduction of psychosocial distress. However, a model leading to a 'gender affirmation' does not solve the problem, since brain disorders causing it are not corrected. This is a serious medical ethics issue. Prejudices should be left aside. To know what happens in the brain of transsexuals is a medical need, both to define what is and what is not, and so to choose an adequate treatment, and to decide and guide legal actions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Moratalla, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calleja Canelas, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La transexualidad describe la condición de una persona cuyo sexo psicológico difiere del biológico. Las personas con trastorno de identidad de género sufren de forma persistente por esta incongruencia y buscan un cambio de la anatomía sexual, mediante tratamiento hormonal y quirúrgico. Esta revisión, desde una perspectiva ética, ofrece una visión de las correlaciones neurobiológicas estructurales y funcionales de la transexualidad y los procesos de cambio cerebrales por la administración de las hormonas del sexo deseado. Varios estudios demuestran un aumento de la conectividad funcional entre regiones de la corteza cerebral, que son huellas de la angustia psicosocial generada por la discordancia entre el sexo psicológico y el biológico. Tal angustia se puede atribuir a una imagen corporal incongruente debida a los cambios en la conectividad funcional de los componentes clave de la red de representación del cuerpo. Parte de los cambios de la conectividad suponen un mecanismo de defensa puesto que disocia la emoción sentida de la imagen corporal. Las personas transexuales presentan signos de feminización o masculinización de estructuras y procesos cerebrales con dimorfismo sexual y que durante la administración hormonal se desplazan parcialmente aún más hacia las correspondientes al sexo deseado. Estos cambios permiten una reducción de la angustia psicosocial. Sin embargo, un modelo de 'reasignación del sexo' no resuelve el problema, puesto que no se trata la alteración cerebral que lo causa. Se trata de una grave cuestión de ética médica. La liberación de los prejuicios para conocer lo que ocurre en el cerebro de los transexuales es una necesidad médica, tanto para definir lo que es y no es un tratamiento terapéutico, como para guiar las acciones legales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad Bioet;27(89): 81-92, ene.-abr. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151423</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Transexualidad: una alteración cerebral que comienza a conocerse</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14582^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54231^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13114^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29557</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54230^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54230^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56101^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54231^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14582^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1853^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56101^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14582^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56101^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55143</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54231^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54230^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13114^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
