<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155900</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mutational prevalence of BRCA1 and BRCA2 genes in patients with breast and ovarian cancer treated in the Health Area of La Ribera (Comunidad Valenciana, Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Breast cancer is the most frequent neoplasia in women, with BRCA1 and BRCA2 germline mutations being involved in 5%-10% of cases. Early genetic analyses in families affected by this disease are crucial for the identification of family members at risk and thus candidates for surveillance programmes. More than 3,000 different mutations in BRCA gene have been described with different allelic prevalence depending on the geographic area analyzed. The aim of this study was to determine, by massive sequencing (NGS), which pathological mutations in BRCA1 and BRCA2 genes are prevalent in patients treated in the Health Area of La Ribera (Comunidad Valenciana, Spain) and its relation with clinic-pathological characteristics. Our data show that patients with BRCA mutations are mainly premenopausal women with cancer and a family history. The predominant detected mutation in our region is c.9026_9030delATCAT in exon 23 of BRCA2 gene (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cuevas, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz, Montse</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lafuente-Sanchis, Aránzazu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zúñiga, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cáncer de mama es la neoplasia más frecuente en la mujer, estando implicadas mutaciones en la línea germinal de los genes BRCA1 y BRCA2 en un 5-10% de los casos. El análisis genético precoz en familias portadoras de mutaciones en BRCA permite la detección de pacientes de riesgo en los que llevar a cabo unas adecuadas medidas de seguimiento o profilácticas. Se han descrito más de 3.000 mutaciones distintas en BRCA relacionadas con la enfermedad, variando su prevalencia alélica según el área geográfica analizada. El objetivo de este trabajo ha sido determinar mediante secuenciación masiva (NGS) qué mutaciones patológicas en los genes BRCA1 y BRCA2 son las prevalentes en los pacientes atendidos en la Unidad de Riesgo de Cáncer de Mama Familiar del Hospital de La Ribera y cuáles son sus características clinicopatológicas. Nuestro estudio muestra que los pacientes con mutaciones en BRCA fueron principalmente mujeres premenopáusicas con algún tipo de cáncer y con antecedentes familiares. La mutación con mayor prevalencia detectada en nuestra población de estudio fue c.9026_9030delATCAT del exón 23 en el gen BRCA2 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;49(4): 214-218, oct.-dic. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155900</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia mutacional de los genes BRCA1 y BRCA2 en pacientes con cáncer de mama y ovario atendidos en el Área de Salud de La Ribera (Comunidad Valenciana, España)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5928</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33161</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9346^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10229^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
