<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129124</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Presence of Anxiety and Depression in Patients With Bronchiectasis Unrelated to Cystic Fibrosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Patients with chronic bronchiectasis (BQ) may suffer from psychological disorders. The objective of this study was to assess the presence of anxiety and depression in patients from a specialised BQ Unit, using validated questionnaires. Patients and methods: We included patients consecutively diagnosed with BQ (unrelated to cystic fibrosis) by high resolution computed tomography in the study. Patients were clinically stable in the previous three weeks and voluntarily completed the Beck Depression Inventory, State-Trait Anxiety Inventory and St. George's Respiratory Questionnaire, after signing the informed consent. They were classified according to their scores on the psychological screening questionnaires, and their results were compared with the clinical, radiological and functional parameters and Quality of Life. Results: 70 patients were included, 48 women and 22 men, with a mean age of 64.19 years. Thirty-four percent (34%) of patients showed symptoms of depression, and around 55% had scores above the 50th percentile in trait and state anxiety. The amount of sputum was associated with trait anxiety. Bacterial colonisation was related to anxiety (trait and state), especially Pseudomonas aeruginosa colonisation. Female patients showed a higher risk of depression. There was no relationship between the Quality of Life scores and the established classifications of anxiety and depression. Conclusions: A high percentage of patients with BQ presented anxiety (trait and state) and depression. The daily sputum production and bacterial colonisation (especially with P. aeruginosa) were the variables most related to anxiety; depression was more common in women. We believe that the presence of psychological disorders should be evaluated, especially in patients with this profile (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cisneros, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernandes Vasconcelos, Gilda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segrelles Calvo, Gonzalo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Punter, Rosa Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Girón Moreno, Rosa María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ancochea, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los pacientes con bronquiectasias (BQ), como enfermos crónicos, pueden verse afectados por trastornos psicológicos. El objetivo del trabajo fue valorar la presencia de síntomas de ansiedad y depresión, mediante cuestionarios validados, en pacientes con BQ controlados en una unidad monográfica. Pacientes y métodos: De forma consecutiva se incluyeron en el estudio pacientes diagnosticados de BQ, no relacionadas con fibrosis quística, mediante una tomografía axial computarizada de alta resolución. Los enfermos estaban en fase estable en las últimas 3 semanas y cumplimentaron los cuestionarios Inventario de Depresión de Beck, Escala de Ansiedad Estado-Rasgo y Cuestionario Respiratorio St. George, después de firmar el consentimiento informado. Los pacientes fueron clasificados según las puntuaciones obtenidas en los cuestionarios de cribado psicológico y sus resultados se compararon con las variables clínicas, radiológicas y funcionales y con las puntuaciones de calidad de vida. Resultados: Setenta enfermos, 48 de ellos mujeres y 22 hombres, con una edad media de 64,19 años, respondieron de forma voluntaria a los cuestionarios. El 34% de los pacientes mostraron síntomas de depresión, y alrededor del 55% puntuaciones por encima del percentil 50 en ansiedad (rasgo y estado). La cantidad de expectoración se relacionó con la ansiedad rasgo. La colonización bacteriana se relacionó con la ansiedad (rasgo y estado), especialmente la colonización por Pseudomonas aeruginosa. El sexo femenino mostró mayor riego de depresión. No existió relación entre las clasificaciones establecidas de ansiedad y depresión y las puntuaciones de calidad de vida. Conclusiones: Los pacientes con BQ muestran en un alto porcentaje presencia de síntomas de ansiedad, rasgo y estado, así como de depresión. Los más afectados por ansiedad son los más expectoradores y los colonizados por bacterias, y por depresión, las mujeres. Creemos que es necesario valorar la presencia de psicomorbilidad asociada, especialmente en este perfil de enfermos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;49(10): 415-420, oct. 2013. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129124</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos psicológicos y calidad de vida en pacientes con bronquiectasias no relacionadas con fibrosis quística</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2017^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11988^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
