<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-63696</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES. Know the clinical criteria used in primary health care for the diagnosis of osteoporosis in postmenopausal women and know the clinical and sociodemographic characteristics of the patients who can receive treatment. DESIGN. Multicenter, descriptive study. SITE. Primary Health Care Center of all the Spanish territory. PARTICIPANTS. Postmenopausal women of 50 years or older with clinical diagnosis of osteoporosis. PRINCIPAL MEASUREMENTS. Sociodemographic and clinical data, risk factors for osteoporosis and methods used for the diagnosis. RESULTS. A total of 745 women with a mean age of 62 years (range 50-86) participated. The most frequent risk factor was a family background of osteoporosis (48.6%), followed by early menopause (30.7%). The most frequent diagnostic criteria were the combination of clinical history, risk factors of osteoporosis and conventional X-ray (20.3%). Densitometry was used alone or in combination with other examinations in 32% of the patients. The differences in the use of densitometry according to age groups were not significant (¾ 61 years: 28.9% versus &gt; 61 years: 35.6%; p &gt; 0.06). CONCLUSIONS. Diagnosis of osteoporosis in Primary Health Care in our setting is mainly a clinical diagnosis that takes the risk factors of the disease into account. Conventional X-ray and, to a lesser degree, densitometry are also used. In accordance with the current recommendations, it would be necessary to increase the use of the densitometry in primary health care in Spain for management of the treatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grifols, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Badia, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guilera, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuentes, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVOS. Conocer los criterios clínicos que se utilizan en Atención Primaria para el diagnóstico de la osteoporosis en mujeres posmenopáusicas y conocer las características clínicas y sociodemográficas de las pacientes susceptibles de recibir tratamiento. DISEÑO. Estudio multicéntrico descriptivo. EMPLAZAMIENTO. Centros de Atención Primaria de toda la geografía española. PARTICIPANTES. Mujeres posmenopáusicas de 50 años o más con diagnóstico clínico de osteoporosis. MEDICIONES PRINCIPALES. Datos sociodemográficos y clínicos, factores de riesgo para la osteoporosis y métodos utilizados para su diagnóstico. RESULTADOS. Participaron 745 mujeres con una edad media de 62 años (rango 50-86). El factor de riesgo más frecuente fue tener antecedentes familiares de osteoporosis (48,6%), seguido de menopausia precoz (30,7%). Los criterios diagnósticos más frecuentes fueron la combinación de la historia clínica, los factores de riesgo de osteoporosis y la radiología convencional (20,3%). En el 32% de las pacientes se utilizó la densitometría ósea (DMO) sola o en combinación con otras exploraciones. Las diferencias en la utilización de DMO según grupos de edad no fueron significativas (¾61 años: 28,9% frente a &gt; 61 años: 35,6%; p &gt; 0,06). CONCLUSIONES. El diagnóstico de la osteoporosis en Atención Primaria en nuestro medio es principalmente un diagnóstico clínico que tiene en cuenta los factores de riesgo de la enfermedad. Se utiliza también la radiología convencional y en menor proporción la DMO. De acuerdo a las recomendaciones actuales, sería necesario aumentar el uso de la DMO en Atención Primaria en España para el manejo de la enfermedad</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);33(2): 45-49, feb. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-63696</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24823^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24823^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
