<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133953</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neuronal communication and synaptic metabolism in childhood epilepsy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Basic neuroscience and neurometabolism are providing a rapidly increasing amount of knowledge on paediatric epilepsy and, more specifically, on the mechanisms involved in synaptic communication. There is, however, a mismatch between these advances and a vision that integrates them in a global way, in clinical and therapeutic practice. Aims. To offer an integrative view of the different molecular and metabolic mechanisms that are known and postulated in paediatric epilepsy, and to suggest concepts such as &#145;synaptic metabolism&#146; and &#145;synaptic phenotypes&#146; as useful tools for developing this approach. Development. We also review the most notable studies that attempt to explain the essential characteristics of synaptic communication in the developing brain by means of different molecules, essentially synaptic proteins, ion channels (chlorine, sodium and potassium co-transporters), and pre- and post-synaptic compartmentalisation, as well as the main players in metabolism (neurotransmitters, energy metabolism, growth factors and lipids). This combination of biological mechanisms has led to examples of &#145;synaptic phenotypes&#146; being suggested in two specific cases of genetic (SCN1A) and metabolic epilepsy (epilepsy with response to pyridoxine). Conclusions. A holistic perspective, which takes into account the diversity of elements that are related and which take place at certain times in neurodevelopment, can help to define phenotypes, channels for synaptic metabolism and brain connectivity, which facilitate not only the understanding of the pathophysiology, but also new therapeutic approaches in paediatric epilepsy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cortès Saladelafont, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Duarte, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Cazorla, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los conocimientos que la neurociencia básica y el neurometabolismo están aportando en epilepsia pediátrica, y en concreto en mecanismos de comunicación sináptica, crecen rápidamente. Existe, no obstante, una desconexión entre estos avances y una visión que los integre de manera global y en la práctica clínica y terapéutica. Objetivos. Ofrecer una visión integradora de los diferentes mecanismos moleculares y metabólicos que se conocen y postulan en epilepsia pediátrica, y sugerir conceptos como el de &#145;metabolismo sináptico&#146; y &#145;fenotipos sinápticos&#146; como herramientas útiles para desarrollar este enfoque. Desarrollo. Se revisan los estudios más destacados que intentan explicar las características esenciales de la comunicación sináptica en el cerebro en desarrollo, a través de diferentes moléculas, básicamente proteínas sinápticas, canales iónicos (cotransportadores de cloro, sodio y potasio), la compartimentalización pre y postsináptica, y los principales actores metabólicos (neurotransmisores, metabolismo energético, factores de crecimiento y lípidos). A partir de esta combinación de mecanismos biológicos se sugieren ejemplos de &#145;fenotipos sinápticos&#146; en dos casos concretos de epilepsia genética (SCN1A) y metabólica (epilepsia con respuesta a la piridoxina). Conclusiones. Una perspectiva holística, entendiendo la diversidad de elementos relacionados y que suceden en determinados momentos del neurodesarrollo, puede ayudar a delinear fenotipos, vías de metabolismo sináptico y conectividad cerebral, que faciliten no sólo la comprensión de la fisiopatología, sino nuevas aproximaciones terapéuticas en epilepsia pediátrica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;60(5): 219-228, 1 mar., 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133953</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comunicación neuronal y metabolismo sináptico en epilepsia infantil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13949^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32115^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4813</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9608^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51243</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
