<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74249</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Complete vesico-ureteral reconstruction with ileum in a case of genitourinary tuberculosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Genitourinary tuberculosis represent 3,2% of the possible sites of the disease. The lack of treatment or an inadecuate one may lead to severe complications. We report a case and review thoroughly the literature of genitourinary tuberculosis which needed a complete vesico-ureteral reconstruction. Clinical case: A 39 year old female patient with history of pulmonary tuberculosis who had lumbar pain and left ureterohydronephosis. She required a percutaneous urinary derivation and was diagnosed of tuberculosis by means of the urine culture. 18 months afterwards she had a right renal annulation and a left distal ureteral stenosis. A right nephectomy was performed and the left proximal ureter was desinserted accidentally, 1 cm below the pielo-ureteral junction, which required a permanent nephostomy. Then her bladder became gradually retractile. Because she was a young patient and had bad quality of life a complete reconstruction of her left urinary way was performed with an ileum made neobladder and neoureter. Discussion and Conclussions: Bladder and ureter reconstruction with ileum is a good option in difficult cases of lack or irreversible damage of the urinary way. Vesico-ureteral reconstruction letting urethral miction improves quality of life (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Congregado Ruiz, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina López, Rafael A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Resina, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torrubia Romero, Francico J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La tuberculosis genitourinaria representa el 3,2% del total de las localizaciones posibles de la enfermedad. La ausencia de tratamiento o su manejo inadecuado, puede desencadenar complicaciones severas. Presentamos un caso clínico y realizamos una revisión bibliográfica de una paciente con tuberculosis genitourinaria que requirió una reconstrucción vésico ureteral completa. Caso clínico: Mujer de 39 años con antecedentes personales de tuberculosis pulmonar, que debuta con dolor lumbar y ureterohidronefrosis izquierda que precisa derivación urinaria percutánea con diagnóstico de tuberculosis en urocultivo. A los 18 meses del diagnóstico presentó una anulación renal derecha por la que se decidió nefrectomía derecha y estenosis ureteral distal izquierda en cuyo intento de corrección quirúrgica se produjo desinserción de uréter un cm por debajo de la unión pieloureteral que obligó a nefrostomía en raqueta definitiva. A todo ello se sumó en los meses siguientes, retracción progresiva vesical. Debido a la edad de la paciente y el deterioro de su calidad de vida se realizó una reconstrucción completa de la vía urinaria izquierda mediante una neovejiga y neoureter con ileon. Discusión y conclusiones: La reconstrucción de vejiga y uréter con íleon, es una buena opción en casos complejos en los que la vía urinaria está ausente o lesionada de forma irreversible. La reconstrucción vesicoureteral, permitiendo micción por uretra mejora sustancialmente la calidad de vida de estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;33(6): 706-711, jun. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74249</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reconstrucción vésico-ureteral completa con íleon en un caso de tuberculosis genitourinaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1768^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7265^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14912^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14803^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14803^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14803^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
