<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96772</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychological differences of breast cancer patients according to the type of breast surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Breast cancer patients could experiment an important reduction in psychological adjustment due to mastectomy. So, breast reconstruction is considered a procedure to reverse the sequels of breast mastectomy. Two groups were evaluated in order to determine if anxiety and depression symptoms, coping style and quality of life in breast cancer patients are different for each kind of patient, according to the type of surgery (mastectomy or breast reconstruction). A first group was made up of 36 patients with breast cancer who had undergone unilateral mastectomy (simple or modified radical) and the second group was formed by 36 patients with breast reconstruction postmastectomy (immediate or delayed). This study used a psychosocial survey, the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HAD), Mental Adjustment to CancerScale (MAC), and The EORTC QLQ-C30 for the evaluation. In general, mastectomy patients showed highersymptoms of anxiety and depression than the breast reconstruction patients. In the same way, breast reconstruction patients develops more effective copingstrategies and reports better quality of life than breast mastectomy patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín Rodríguez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rincón Fernández, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borda Más, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez San Gregorio, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las pacientes con cáncer de mama pueden experimentar importantes secuelas psicológicas producidas por la mastectomía, considerándose la reconstrucción mamaria como un procedimiento reversivo de las mismas. Para conocer si la sintomatología ansiosa y depresiva, las estrategias de afrontamiento empleadas o la calidad de vida manifestada por las pacientes, difiere de unas a otras según el tipo de cirugía realizada (mastectomía unilateralo reconstrucción mamaria) se estudiaron 2 grupos. Un primer grupo formado por 36 pacientes sometidas a mastectomía unilateral (simple o radical modificada) y un segundo grupo constituido por 36 mujeres con reconstrucción mamaria postmastectomía (inmediata o diferida). Para la evaluación psicológica se empleó una Encuesta Psicosocial, junto a la Escala de Ansiedad y Depresión en Hospital (HAD), la Escala de Afrontamiento del Cáncer (MAC) y el Cuestionario de Calidad de Vida para Cáncer de la EORTC (QLQ-C30). En general, las pacientes mastectomizadas presentaron una mayor presencia de sintomatología ansiosa y depresiva que las pacientes con reconstrucción mamaria postmastectomía. Igualmente, las pacientes con reconstrucción mamaria emplearon estrategias de afrontamiento más eficaces y gozaron de una mayor calidad de vida que las mujeres mastectomizadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;36(4): 359-368, dic. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96772</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias psicológicas en pacientes con cáncer de mama según el tipo de cirugía mamaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29995^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8580^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
