<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87868</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8799</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of jump in plaform dynamometer in male and female handball player</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This report was made in 36 handball players from two  first division teams, one male and other female, in Sevillle during the season 2003-04. Every subject carried out a five minutes warming up on a cicloergometer to avoid the influence of that on the results. After this they performed the same jump protocol: first a squat jump type (SJ) followed by a countermovement jump (CMJ), and finally  a series of continues jumps for 30 seconds with Bosco technique. The main aim was to find out if there were differences in physics variable during jumps and to obtain reference values on this platform in handball. The results showed a greater explosive force level in  men during SJ ( height: 29&#146;35 &amp;#61617; 3&#146;48 cm., power: 50&#146;14 ±5&#146;07 W/kg, velocity: 2&#146;59 ± 0&#146;13 m/s, absolute force: 1405&#146;3 ± 213&#146;7 N, and relative force: 24&#146;7 ± 1&#146;8 N/kg),  there were significant differences in every variable in women (18&#146;78 ± 3&#146;48 cms, 37&#146;59 ± 4&#146;44 W/kg, 2&#146;13 ± 0&#146;15 m/s, 815&#146;1 ± 125&#146;4 N, 22&#146;3 ± 1&#146;9 N/kg). Every parameter obtained during CMJ were higher in men and they  showed significant differences except elastic capacity, but there wasn&#146;t differences. Height, power and fatigue force indices (in height and power) during continuous jumps were higher in men and they showed significant  differences respect women. Behaviour variables during every type of jump were similar  both for men and women, but greater in men except elastic capacity, which was higher in women (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Centeno, Ramón A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Puerto, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Da Silva, Marzo Edir</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viana- Montaner, Bernardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Naranjo, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beas, Juan de Dios</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo fue realizado en 36 jugadores de balonmano de dos equipos de primera división  nacional, uno de hombres y otro de mujeres, de Sevilla durante la pretemporada 2003-04. Todos los sujetos efectuaron el mismo calentamiento en cicloergómetro para evitar la influencia del  mismo sobre los resultados. Posteriormente realizaron el  mismo protocolo de saltos: primero un squat jump (SJ),  seguido de un countermovement jump (CMJ), y por último saltos continuos con contramovimiento durante 30 segundos siguiendo la técnica de Bosco. El objetivo principal era ver qué diferencias existen entre las diferentes variables físicas durante el salto, así como obtener valores  de referencia en la plataforma de fuerza para este deporte. Los resultados mostraron valores mayores en los hombres  (altura: 29&#146;35 ± 3&#146;48 cms, potencia: 50&#146;14 ±5&#146;07 W/kg,  velocidad: 2&#146;59 ± 0&#146;13 m/s, fuerza absoluta: 1405&#146;3 ±  213&#146;7 N, y fuerza relativa: 24&#146;7 ± 1&#146;8 N/kg) en las variables obtenidas durante un SJ, siendo significativa todas las diferencias con las mujeres (18&#146;78 ± 3&#146;48 cms, 37&#146;59 ± 4&#146;44  W/kg, 2&#146;13 ± 0&#146;15 m/s, 815&#146;1 ± 125&#146;4 N, 22&#146;3 ± 1&#146;9 N/kg).  También son mayores en los hombres todos los parámetros obtenidos durante un CMJ así como significativos, menos  la capacidad elástica que es mayor en las mujeres aunque  la diferencia no es significativa. La altura, potencia y los índices de resistencia a la fuerza veloz en altura y potencia en los saltos continuos son mayores en los hombres y significativa la diferencia con las mujeres. El comportamiento de las variables obtenidas durante la realización de todos los tipos de salto en los jugadores de  balonmano es similar en hombres y mujeres, aunque presentan valores mayores en aquellos, excepto la capacidad elástica que es mayor en las mujeres (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. med. deporte;25(125): 189-197, mayo-jun. 2008. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87868</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis del salto en plataforma dinamométrica en jugadoras de balonmano</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3672</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27233^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1860^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32211^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
