<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74874</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Theoretical integration of different measures of emotional regulation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study examines the possibility of theoretical integration of different measure of emotional regulation. In particular, we analyse the empirical relationship existing between such measures with the aim of gaining a better understanding of the mehanisms on which emotional management operates. The study was carried out with 161 undergraduates that were evaluated through three measures of emotinl regulation: Perceived Emotional Inelligence (TMMS); Emotional Suppression and emotional reappraisl strategies (ERQ), Emotional copig (EAC) and in criterion variabes such as Self-Esteem and Life Satisfaction (SWLS). Likeise, the present study investigates the incremental, convergent and disriminant validity of emotional regulation measures to account for the variance of the several criterion variables: life satisfaction and self-esteem. The results obtained pointed to expected direction, showing that the dimensions of the various tendencies studied seem to be assessing in practice the same type of emotional management strategies(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cabello González, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Aranda, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Berrocal, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Extremera, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente estudio examina la posibilidad de integración teórica de diferentes medidas de regulación emocional. En concreto se analiza la relación empírica existe entre ellas con el objetivo de comprendermejor los mecanismos sobre os que trabaja el mnejo emocional. En el estudio participaron 161 estudiantes univrsitarios que fueron evuados a través de tres medidas de regulació emocional: Inteligencia Emocional Percibida (TMMS); Estrategias de Supresión emocional y Reevaluación Cognitiva (ERQ); Afrontaietno Emocional (EAC) y en variales criteio como la Autoestima y la Satisfacción Vital (SWLS). Además este estudio investiga la validez incrmental, convergente y discriminanate de las medids de regulación emocinal para explicar la varianza de diferentes variables criterio: la satisfacción vital y la autoestima. Los resultados obtenidos fueron en la dirección esperada, mosrando que las dimensiones d elas diferentes corrientes estudiadas parecen estar evluando en la práctica el mismo tipo de estrategias de manejo emocional(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;12(2/3): 155-166, dic. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74874</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Una aproximación a la integración de diferentes medidas de regulación emocional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33145^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36316</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
