<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88778</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of the C677T mutation in methylenetetrahydrofolate reductase gene in venous thromboembolic disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Venous thromboembolism (VTE) is a multifactorial disease in which both environmental and genetic factors are involved. The presence of mutations in genes coding for haemostatic, fibrinolytic and, also, inflammatory proteins is associated with an increased risk of first episode and recurrence of venous thrombosis. So, in the last years, several polymorphisms associated with thrombosis have been reported. Recently, the 677C &gt; T polymorphism in the methylenetetrahydrofolate reductase (MTHFR) gene (a C &gt; T substitution at base pair 677 leading to the exchange of alanine to valine) has been proposed by some studies to be a thrombophilic risk factor. This mutation causes moderate hyper-Hcy, and Hyper-Hcy is well known to cause VTE. We analysed the role of C677T MTHFR in VTE, as well as its clinical applicability(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-López, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alberca, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano, F. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Porras, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad tromboembólica venosa (ETV) es considerada como una enfermedad multifactorial. Es necesaria la presencia de factores genéticos, que predisponen al individuo a la trombosis, y factores ambientales, que desencadenan la trombosis (interacción gen-ambiente). En los últimos años se han descrito numerosos polimorfismos asociados con un mayor o menor riesgo a padecer una enfermedad trombótica en sus distintas variantes. Una de estas mutaciones de interés es la C677T del gen metilentetrahidrofolato reductasa (MTHFR), que consiste en la sustitución de una citosina por una timina en el nucleótido 677. Este cambio de aminoácido genera una variante de MTHFR termolábil con capacidad reducida para metabolizar la homocisteína, pudiendo aparecer una hiperhomocisteinemia leve-moderada, factor de riesgo conocido en la ETV. Por tanto, C677T MTHFR podría predisponer a la aparición y recurrencia de la ETV. Este artículo pretende analizar el papel concreto desempeñado por este polimorfismo en la ETV, así como su aplicabilidad clínica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;62(6): 225-231, nov.-dic. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88778</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de la mutación C677T del gen de la metilentetrahidrofolato reductasa en la enfermedad tromboembólica venosa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33775^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33361^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33775^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33361^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52618^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9346^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33361^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52618^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52618^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33775^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
