<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92014</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Using the novel The stranger by Albert Camus as if it were a clinical case, tries to demonstrate two hypothesis; first, that neurosis of behavior is really a psicosis by deficit second, that in neurosis of behavior, the subjects are hiperadapted to their environment. They depend so much on their support from reality are modified. In that case that decompensation will express through the somatic side or at the legal side. These patients are unable to make psychic decompensations of neurotic or psychotic type (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zubiri, Mikel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Tomando la novela El extranjero de Albert Camus como si de un caso clínico se tratara, trato de mostrar dos hipótesis. Una, que la entidad de neurosis de comportamiento  corresponden a sujetos hiperadaptados a su medio. Y que dependen de tal forma de su medio, que se descompensan en cuanto alguno de sus puntos de apoyo de la realidad se  modifica. Y en ese caso su descompensación será, o bien por el lado somático, o bien por el lado legal. Siendo incapaces de hacer descompensaciones psíquicas del estilo neurótico o psicótico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(61): 169-182, dic. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92014</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El extranjero de Albert Camus o la neurosis de comportamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13384^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13863</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9686^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3433^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
