<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161857</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Do the parents of overweight children need glasses?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Misperception of body appearance of children decreases the effectiveness of interventions aimed at the prevention and treatment of childhood obesity, since many of them are focused on changes in eating habits and physical activity. We designed a questionnaire that was applied to all children aged 2 to 14 years who attended the consultation for three months (November 2014 to January 2015) and who were already diagnosed as overweight/obese, and a similar group without overweight/obesity. Parents of children with overweight/obesity in our study, underestimate the problem of their children, because they do not believe that there is a problem. They do not see them fat (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ronald Adhemar Castillo, RA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo Castro, RL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre Quiralte, M de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abubacrin Banani, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La percepción errónea de la apariencia corporal de los hijos limita la efectividad de las intervenciones destinadas a la prevención y tratamiento de la obesidad infantil, ya que gran parte de ellas se enfocan a cambios en los hábitos de alimentación y actividad física. Diseñamos un cuestionario que se aplicó a todos los niños de 2 a 14 años que acudieron a la consulta durante tres meses (de noviembre de 2014 a enero de 2015) y que ya estaban diagnosticados de sobrepeso/obesidad, y un grupo similar sin sobrepeso/obesidad. Los padres de los niños con sobrepeso/obesidad de nuestro estudio infravaloran el problema de los hijos, porque no creen que exista ningún problema. No les ven gordos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;19(73): 43-47, ene.-mar. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161857</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los padres de los niños obesos, ¿necesitan gafas?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1853</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55220^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55220^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
