<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89732</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Early detection of hearing loss in children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hearing is the usual way of acquiring the language, one of human being&#146;s most important features. The sanitary system in general and primary care in particular have the great responsibility of detecting hearing loss in children, nevertheless early diagnosis and proper treatment prevent the most important consequence of child hearing loss: being raised without language. PrevInfad recommends early detection of hearing loss through universal newborn screening. This paper tries to clarify the reasons for this recommendation and the justification of a universal newborn screening program, reviewing the state of the arguments in the field, and also intends to serve as a guide for the clinicians in Primary Care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Delgado Domínguez, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La audición es la vía habitual para adquirir el lenguaje, uno de los más importantes atributos humanos. El sistema sanitario en general, y la Atención Primaria en particular, tiene una gran responsabilidad a la hora de detectar la pérdida auditiva durante la infancia, porque el diagnóstico precoz y la rehabilitación adecuada previenen la consecuencia más importante de la hipoacusia infantil: crecer sin un lenguaje. PrevInfad recomienda la detección precoz de la hipoacusia mediante la realización del cribado neonatal universal. Este texto pretende aclarar las razones para esta recomendación y la justificación de un programa de cribado neonatal universal de hipoacusia, revisando la situación del debate en este terreno, así como servir de guía de actuación del profesional de Atención Primaria en esta patología (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;13(50): 279-297, abr.-jun. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89732</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Detección precoz de la hipoacusia infantil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3655^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6470^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6470^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6470^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
