<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102798</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Robotic assisted radical cystectomy: oncological safety</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: To describe the quality parameters established based on surgical and pathological aspects of bladder carcinoma treatment in the study published by the Bladder Cancer Collaborative Group (BCCG) and compare them against the publications of the International Robotic Cystectomy Consortium (IRCC)  Ligament. METHODS: A MEDLINE database search for articles published by BCCG and IRCC and description of them. RESULTS: Margins: IRCC work globally presented 6.8% of positive margins, a result close to the 6.5% of BCCG. The margins were similar in patients with organ-confined disease (. pT2) and those with extravesical disease (pT3-pT4), IRCC work showed a 4.6% positive margin compared to open surgery. In those who had lymph node involvement, negative margins were 6% higher for conventional surgery (BCCG: 14% vs. IRCC: 20%). The impact of learning curve in surgical margins in robotic surgery was not significant.Lymphadenectomy: In BCCG&#129;fs work, 11% of patients did not have a lymphadenectomy performed, 9% underwent an LL, 67% SL and 13% EL. The mean number of lymph nodes collected was 12.5, with a median of 11. In the IRCC, 82.9% of patients underwent lymphadenectomy (defined as with more than 10 lymph nodes removed), of which 43% had more than 20 nodes removed. The median of the entire series was 17 nodes (range 0-68). CONCLUSIONS: The robotic assisted laparoscopic radical cystectomy (RALRC) is a technique with similar results to conventional surgery in terms of surgical margins and enables the performance of an adequate pelvic lymphadenectomy. Long term results are pending of a longer follow-up of patients operated to date(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Monzó Gardiner, Juan Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Describir los parámetros de calidad establecidos en base a los aspectos quirúrgicos y patológicos del tratamiento del cáncer urotelial de vejiga en el trabajo publicado por el Bladder Cáncer Collaborative Group (BCCG) y compararlos con las publicaciones del International Robotic Cystectomy Consortium (IRCC). MÉTODOS: Búsqueda en la base de datos MEDLINE de los artículos publicados BCCG y el IRCC y descripción de los mismos. RESULTADO: Márgenes: El trabajo del IRCC presentó globalmente un 6,8% de márgenes positivos, resultado próximo al 6,5% del BCCG. Los márgenes resultaron similares en pacientes con enfermedad organoconfinada (&amp;#8804;pT2 ) y, en aquellos con enfermedad extravesical (pT3-pT4), el trabajo del IRCC presentó un 4,6% más de márgenes positivos con respecto a la cirugía abierta. En aquellos que presentaron afectación ganglionar, los márgenes negativos fueron un 6% mejor para la cirugía convencional (BCCG: 14% frente a IRCC: 20%). El impacto de la curva de aprendizaje en los márgenes quirúrgicos en cirugía robótica no resultó significativo. Linfadenectomía: En el trabajo del BCCG al 11% de los pacientes no le realizaron linfadenectomía, a un 9% le hicieron una LL, a un 67% LE y a un 13% LA. El promedio de ganglios recogido fue de 12,5 ganglios, con una mediana de 11. En el IRCC al 82,9% de los pacientes le realizaron linfadenectomía (definida como aquella con mas de 10 ganglios resecados), de los cuales al 43% le extrajeron más de 20 ganglios. La mediana de toda la serie fue de 17 ganglios (rango: 0-68). CONCLUSIONES: La CRLAR es una técnica con resultados similares a la cirugía convencional en cuanto a los márgenes quirúrgicos y permite realizar una linfadenectomía pélvica adecuada. Los resultados a largo plazo están pendiente de un seguimiento mas prolongado de los casos intervenidos hasta la fecha(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;65(6): 593-598, jul.-ago. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102798</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguridad oncológica de la cistectomía radical laparoscópica asistida por robot</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24595^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24595^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19341</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8374</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8384</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8375^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
