<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-68736</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The social identity theory (SIT) and the self-categorization theory have had considerable influence on contemporary Social Psychology, making notable contributions to our understanding of the social dimension of behaviour. In the present work, we summarise the bases of these theories and critically review the most controversial elements of SIT, exploring its limits and potential. As shown here, the literature offers a heterogeneous body of research that includes outstanding efforts of synthesis and integration, but also numerous fragmentary studies and decontextualized interpretations that have generated distorted views of group behaviour. Taking into account the multidimensional, contextually mediated, dynamic and functional nature of identitary processes, which clearly emerge in the most serious works in the field, there is obviously a need to review the epistemological and methodological tools currently employed, with a view to developing practices that allow the study of group phenomena in a manner more suited to their complexity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>San José Sebastián, M Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Scandroglio, Bárbara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Martínez, Jorge S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Teoría de la Identidad Social (TIS) y la Teoría de la Auto-Categorización del Yo han tenido gran influencia en la Psicología Social contemporánea, proporcionando reseñables contribuciones a la comprensión de la dimensión social de la conducta. En este trabajo se sintetizan los fundamentos de dichas teorías y se revisan críticamente los elementos más controvertidos de la TIS, examinando sus límites y potencialidades. Se muestra que la literatura ofrece un panorama heterogéneo que reúne, junto a notables esfuerzos de síntesis e integración, numerosos trabajos fragmentarios e interpretaciones descontextualizadas que han generado visiones distorsionadas del comportamiento grupal. Tomando en consideración el carácter multidimensional, contextualmente mediado, dinámico y funcional de los procesos identitarios, patente ya en los trabajos más cualificados, se hace necesario revisar las herramientas epistemológicas y metodológicas al uso dentro del área y evolucionar hacia prácticas que permitan estudiar los fenómenos grupales en modo más acorde a su complejidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);20(1): 80-89, ene.-mar. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-68736</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1538</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33143</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
