<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-8027</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ethmoidal metastasis of renal adenocarcinoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The sinonasal tract and, more specifically, the ethmoid sinus, are uncommon sites for metastatic tumors. Fewer than 100 cases have been reported in the world literature. We report the case of a 65-year-old woman who underwent nephrectomy and adrenalectomy for renal cell carcinoma (hypernephroma) with adrenal metastasis. Four months later the patient was seen for repeated epistaxis and nasal obstruction, which was diagnosed as ethmoidal metastasis of renal adenocarcinoma in a second biopsy. The second metastasis was removed by lateral rhinotomy but recurred six months later. Palliative surgery was performed and the patient died eight months later from brain metastases. Therapeutic strategies for metastatic nasal tumors are reviewed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sanidad y Ediciones (SANED, S.L.)</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La región naso-sinusal y el etmoides en concreto, son localizaciones excepcionales para tumores metastásicos. Menos de 100 casos han sido descritos en la literatura mundial. Presentamos el caso de una mujer de 65 años intervenida de nefrectomía con suprarrenalectomía por un adenocarcinoma renal (hipernefroma) con metástasis suprarrenal. Cuatro meses después la paciente consultó por epistaxis de repetición y obstrucción nasal, siendo diagnosticada de metástasis etmoidal de adenocarcinoma renal en una segunda biopsia. Esta segunda metástasis fue extirpada por vía para- látero-nasal con recidiva local a los seis meses. Se realizó cirugía paliativa y la paciente falleció a los ocho meses por metástasis cerebrales. Se revisan las estrategias terapéuticas para los tumores nasales metastásicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;51(1): 76-79, ene. 2000. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Metástasis etmoidal de adenocarcinoma renal</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Aguilar, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larrosa, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Traserra, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-8027</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d22935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7855</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29936</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22601</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31474</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5097</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200001</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
