<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103881</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Best&#146;s vitelliform macular dystrophy associated with choroidal neovascularization</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report: We report the case of a child with a sudden loss of vision of the left eye. Ophthalmoscopic examination revealed vitelliform lesions in both foveal centers, as well as an adjacent hemorrhage in his left eye. Fluoresce in angiography confirmed the presence of a neovascular membrane in his left eye. The electrooculogram showed disease. According to complementary studies the patient was diagnosed with Best&#146;s disease associated with choroidal neovascularization. Discussion: The diagnosis of Best&#146;s vitelliform macular dystrophy is often a casual finding as visual acuity tends to remain stable for long periods of time. A sudden deterioration in vision may suggest complications, such as choroidal neovascularization(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-De-Arcelus, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Arumí, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Céspedes, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Se presenta el caso de un niño con pérdida súbita de visión en ojo izquierdo. El examen funduscópico revela una lesión foveal viteliforme bilateral, y una hemorragia adyacente en ojo izquierdo. La angiografía con fluoresceína confirma la presencia de una membrana neovascular en ojo izquierdo. El electrooculograma resulta patológico. Tras completar el estudio, es diagnosticado de enfermedad de Best asociada a neovascularización coroidea. Discusión: El diagnóstico de enfermedad de Best puede ser casual dado que la agudeza visual suele permanecer estable. Una pérdida súbita de visión ha de sugerirnos la aparición de complicaciones tales como neovascularización coroidea(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;87(10): 333-336, oct. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103881</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Distrofia macular viteliforme de Best asociada a neovascularización coroidea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33766</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53968</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53968^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53968^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4657</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28243</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53968^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
