<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73552</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bacterial bloodstream infections in critical patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bloodstream infection, together with ventilator-associated pneumonia, is the most frequent nosocomial infection in critically ill patients; it is associated with significant morbidity and mortality. As bloodstream infections in critical patients are usually due to intravascular catheters, they can be caused by both gram-positive and gram-negative microorganisms. Furthermore, infection with multiresistant organisms is becoming more common, and this makes the choice of empirical antibiotic treatment more difficult.Patients with severe community-acquired infections account for a large percentage of patients who require admission to intensive care units for hemodynamic instability or organ dysfunction. Many of these also have bacterial bloodstream infections; about 30% of all bacterial bloodstream infections in critical patients occur in this group of patients. Among this group, 70% develop severe sepsis or septic shock, both of which have high mortality. Recently, another classification scheme included a distinct group comprising patients with community-acquired bloodstream infections after recent or intermittent contact with healthcare facilities. When choosing the empirical antibiotic treatment, it is important to bear in mind that this group has specific characteristics that are often comparable to nosocomial infections.We describe the characteristics, origins, causes, and most common complications of nosocomial, community-acquired, and healthcare-related bacterial bloodstream infections in critical patients to make it easier to recognize them early and initiate efficacious empirical antibiotic therapy and thus improve the prognosis of these patients(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sabatier, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallés, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peredo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La bacteriemia es, junto con la neumonía asociada a la ventilación mecánica, la infección nosocomial más frecuente en los pacientes críticos y se asocia a una importante morbimortalidad. La principal causa de bacteriemia en estos pacientes son los catéteres intravasculares y, por consiguiente, los microorganismos grampositivos se equiparan en frecuencia a los microorganismos gramnegativos como causantes de estas infecciones. Además, y con una frecuencia cada vez más elevada, en muchas ocasiones estos microorganismos son multirresistentes, lo que dificulta la elección del tratamiento antibiótico empírico.También las infecciones graves adquiridas en la comunidad representan una parte importante de los pacientes que por inestabilidad hemodinámica o disfunción orgánica requieren ingreso en la unidad de cuidados intensivos. Una parte importante presenta también bacteriemia, y representa aproximadamente un 30% del global de las bacteriemias de los pacientes críticos. En estos casos más de un 70% se manifiesta como sepsis grave o shock séptico, y se acompaña también de una significativa mortalidad. Además, recientemente se ha diferenciado a una población de pacientes con infecciones adquiridas en la comunidad, pero que tienen algún contacto reciente o intermitente con algún tipo de asistencia sanitaria que presentan unas características específicas y equiparables en muchas ocasiones a las infecciones nosocomiales que deberían tenerse en cuenta en el momento de la elección del tratamiento antibiótico empírico.El objetivo de esta revisión es conocer las características, los orígenes, las etiologías y las complicaciones más frecuentes de los pacientes críticos con bacteriemia nosocomial, bacteriemia comunitaria o bacteriemia asociada a cuidados sanitarios con el fin de reconocerlas precozmente e iniciar un tratamiento de soporte y antibiótico empírico eficaz que pueda mejorar el pronóstico de estos pacientes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);33(7): 336-345, oct. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73552</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bacteriemia en el paciente crítico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
