<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037294</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cardiovascular risk factors control effectiveness in type 2 diabetic population of Ciudad Real province</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Basis. Diabetes mellitus type 2 has a very aggressive atherosclerosis profile, which means that the control of the cardiovascular risk factors should be very demanding. There are doubts concerning the attainment of such suitable objectives in primary care because of the difficulties for reproducing the conditions of clinical trials. Methods. Observational, descriptive, cross-sectional, and multicenter study. It was designed in order to establish the level of control of principal risk factors (tobacco, hypertension, hyperglycemia, dyslipemia, obesity), and the use of aspiri, in type 2 diabetics cared in Primary Care centers in Ciudad Real province. 405 patients were evaluated by 33 physicians from 18 Primary Care centers. Results. HbA1c values &lt; 7% were obtained in 51.51%, 45.9% of patients showed obesity, average glycemia was 163.61 ± 51.47. Blood pressure &lt; 130/85 was detected in 18.50% of patients, 62.22% of patients took some hypotensive drug and 51.20% antihipertensives. LDL-c &lt; 100 mg/dl was detected in 10.21% but only 30.61% was on hypolipemic drugs. HDL-c was not determined in 26% of patients, and was 45 mg/dl in 66.44%. Aspirin was prescribed in 31.35%; 9.63% of patients were smoker. No patient reached all necessary prevention objetives. Conclusions. The control of the different risk factors in type 2 diabetics in Primary Care does not guarantee appropiate cardiovascular prevention.The behavior concerning to smoking was good in this study, and the levels of HDL-c and triglycerides were acceptable. Pharmacological treatment should have been most frequent and intense</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grupo ELIPSE</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos. La diabetes mellitus tipo 2 presenta un perfil arteriosclerótico muy agresivo, por lo que el control de los factores de riesgo cardiovascular ha de ser muy exigente. Existen dudas acerca de la consecución de tales objetivos idóneos en el ámbito de la asistencia primaria, por la dificultad de reproducir las condiciones de los ensayos clínicos. Métodos. Estudio observacional, descriptivo, transversal y multicéntrico. Se diseñó para conocer en diabéticos tipo 2 el grado de control de los principales factores de riesgo (tabaco, hipertensión arterial, hiperglucemia, dislipidemia, obesidad) junto al uso de aspirina en Atención Primaria de la provincia de Ciudad Real. Se recogieron 405 pacientes por 33 médicos de 18 centros de salud. Resultados. Se obtuvieron valores de HbA1c  45 mg/dl en el 66,44%. La aspirina se indicó a un 31,35% y fumaban el 9,63%. Ningún enfermo logró todos y cada uno de los objetivos exigibles de prevención. Conclusiones. En Atención Primaria el grado de control de los distintos factores de riesgo en los diabéticos tipo 2 no garantiza una prevención cardiovascular correcta. Fue adecuado el comportamiento en cuanto al tabaquismo y aceptable sólo respecto al colesterol ligado a lipoproteína de alta densidad y triglicéridos. El tratamiento farmacológico debería haber sido más utilizado e intenso</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;205(5): 218-222, may. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037294</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad en el control de factores de riesgo cardiovascular en diabéticos tipo 2 de la provincia de Ciudad Real</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7124^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27951^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
