<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047345</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality of life and social functioning in schizophrenic patients treated with olanzapine: 1 year follow-up naturalistic study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To measure health related quality of life (HRQL) and social functioning in schizophrenic patients treated with olanzapine under regular clinical practice conditions.        Methods. Out-patients diagnosed of schizophrenia and beginning treatment with olanzapine, quetiapine, risperidone or typical oral antipsychotics were included. Information on socio-demographic characteristics was obtained and in each visit (baseline, 3, 6 and 12 months) they were administered the generic HRQL questionnaire Euro- QoL-5D (EQ-5D) and the Social Functioning Scale (SFS).                Results. A total of 1,198 patients were followed-up for 12 months. Mean age (SD) was 38.6 (13.3) years and 62.9 % of them were men. In basal conditions the most affected dimensions of EQ-5D were anxiety/depression (76 %), and daily activities (73.6 %). After 12 months treatment the cohort of patients treated with olanzapine showed a better HRQL in the self-care dimension compared to all other treatments (p &lt; 0.05), and in the dimensions of pain/discomfort, anxiety/depression and usual activities compared to the group treated with quetiapine and risperidone (p &lt; 0.05). The Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) of the EQ-5D questionnaire showed a better health state after 12 months in the group treated with olanzapine compared to the groups of quetiapine or risperidone (p &lt; 0.05). The SFS showed a better improvement in the cohort of olanzapine in the three studied dimensions after 12 months: isolation and social relationships in comparison to the risperidone group (p &lt; 0.05), interpersonal communication in comparison to the risperidone and quetiapine group (p &lt; 0.05) and independence performance in comparison to all the other treatments (p &lt; 0,05).                Conclusion. Schizophrenic patients treated with olanzapine for one year show a better improvement in HRQL and social functioning than those treated with other antipsychotics</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escobar, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bousoño García, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivares Díez, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lara, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayoral, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ros, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanjuán, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Torres, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montejo González, A. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Evaluar la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud (CVRS) y funcionalidad social de los pacientes esquizofrénicos tratados en monoterapia con olanzapina en condiciones de práctica clínica habitual.        Métodos. Se reclutaron pacientes ambulatorios diagnosticados de esquizofrenia que iniciasen tratamiento en monoterapia con olanzapina, quetiapina, risperidona o antipsicóticos típicos orales. Se recogieron las variables sociodemográficas del paciente. En cada visita (basal, 3, 6, 12 meses) se administró el cuestionario genérico de CVRS EuroQoL-5D (EQ-5D) y la Escala de Funcionamiento Social.                Resultados. Se siguieron un total de 1.198 pacientes. La edad media (DE) era de 38,6 (13,3) y un 62,9 % era hombres. Según el cuestionario EQ-5D basalmente las dimensiones más afectadas fueron ansiedad/depresión (76 %) y actividades cotidianas (73,6 %). A los 12 meses la cohorte tratada con olanzapina presentó una mejor CVRS en la dimensión de cuidado personal respecto al resto de tratamientos (p &lt; 0,05) y un porcentaje menor en las dimensiones de dolor/malestar, ansiedad/ depresión y actividades habituales respecto al grupo tratado con quetiapina o risperidona (p &lt; 0,05). Según la Escala Visual Analógica (EVA) del cuestionario EQ-5D la cohorte tratada con olanzapina presentó mejor estado de salud a los 12 meses que los tratados con quetiapina o risperidona (p&lt;0,05). La Escala de Funcionamiento Social demostró una mejora a los 12 meses en los pacientes tratados con olanzapina en las tres dimensiones estudiadas: aislamiento y relaciones sociales respecto a los tratados con risperidona (p&lt;0,05), comunicación interpersonal respecto a los tratados con risperidona o quetiapina (p &lt; 0,05) e independencia de ejecución respecto al resto de tratamientos (p&lt;0,05).                Conclusión. La mejora en la CVRS y funcionamiento social al año de seguimiento es mayor en aquellos pacientes tratados con olanzapina que con otros antipsicóticos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;34(1): 7-15, ene. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047345</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida y funcionamiento social en pacientes con esquizofrenia en monoterapia con olanzapina: estudio naturalístico de 1 año de seguimiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1593^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12946</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29918^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32618^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
