<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76116</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Renal function evaluation methods in the elderly: Reliability and clinical implications</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Chronic renal disease (CRD) is found in a third of the Spanish population aged more than 65 years old. Detection and early treatment would increase survival and help to reduce associated cardiovascular morbidity and mortality as well as the risk of pharmacological iatrogeny. Determination of the glomerular filtration rate has traditionally been considered the best parameter for renal function evaluation, which should not be based exclusively on serum creatinine concentration or creatinine clearance. The application of predictive equations is useful in the diagnosis, classification and outpatient management of patients with CRD. Most studies performed in the elderly have found that the Modification of Diet in Renal Disease (MDRD-4) has greater precision and accuracy than the Cockcroft-Gault formula, and is considered the nomogram of choice in this age group. The Cockcroft-Gault formula can be used when rapid estimation of renal function or drug adjustments are required, so long as the limitations of this method are taken into account(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Carracedo, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baztán Cortés, Juan J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad renal crónica (ERC) se encuentra presente en la tercera parte de la población española mayor de 65 años. Su detección e intervención de forma precoz aportarían un efecto beneficioso sobre la supervivencia, contribuyendo en la reducción de la morbimortalidad cardiovascular asociada y en la disminución del riesgo de yatrogenia farmacológica. La determinación del filtrado glomerular ha sido considerada tradicionalmente como el mejor parámetro de evaluación de la función renal, cuya valoración no debe basarse únicamente en los resultados de concentración sérica o aclaramiento de creatinina. La aplicación de ecuaciones predictivas resulta útil en el diagnóstico, la clasificación y el control ambulatorio de pacientes con ERC. En la mayoría de los estudios realizados sobre población anciana, la fórmula MDRD-4 (Modification of Diet in Renal Disease) obtiene una precisión y una exactitud más razonable que Cockcroft-Gault (CG), considerándola como el nomograma de elección en este sector poblacional. Las situaciones clínicas en las que se precise una rápida estimación de función renal o ajustes farmacológicos aproximados permiten el uso de la ecuación de CG, siempre recordando sus limitaciones(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);44(5): 266-272, sep.-oct.2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76116</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Métodos de evaluación de la función renal en el paciente anciano: fiabilidad e implicaciones clínicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7852^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7231^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24693^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
