<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121290</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of compliance with the self-regulation agreement of the food and drink vending machine sector in primary schools in Madrid, Spain, in 2008</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetivos Evaluar el cumplimiento del convenio de autorregulación del sector de máquinas expendedoras de alimentos y bebidas en las escuelas de primaria de Madrid. Métodos Estudio de prevalencia de máquinas expendedoras en las 558 escuelas de primaria de Madrid en 2008. A partir del directorio de colegios registrados, se detectó la existencia de máquina mediante entrevista telefónica. El conocimiento y el cumplimiento del acuerdo se evaluaron mediante inspección in situ de las máquinas (accesibilidad, tipo de publicidad, productos ofertados).Resultados La prevalencia de colegios con máquina fue del 5,8%. Ninguna escuela conocía el convenio. La mayoría de las máquinas eran accesibles a estudiantes de primaria (79,3%) y contenían mayoritariamente productos altamente energéticos y bajos en nutrientes (58,6%).Conclusiones Observamos un bajo cumplimiento de los acuerdos del convenio. En la batalla contra la epidemia de la obesidad, debería priorizarse una regulación más estricta de la industria alimentaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Royo-Bordonada, Miguel A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Huedo, María A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objectives To evaluate compliance with the self-regulation agreement of the food and drink vending machine sector in primary schools in Madrid, Spain. Methods Cross-sectional study of the prevalence of vending machines in 558 primary schools in 2008. Using the directory of all registered primary schools in Madrid, we identified the presence of machines by telephone interviews and evaluated compliance with the agreement by visiting the schools and assessing accessibility, type of publicity, the products offered and knowledge of the agreement. Results The prevalence of schools with vending machines was 5.8%. None of the schools reported knowledge of the agreement or of its nutritional guidelines, and most machines were accessible to primary school pupils (79.3%) and packed with high-calorie, low-nutrient-dense foods (58.6%).Conclusions Compliance with the self-regulation agreement of the vending machines sector was low. Stricter regulation should receive priority in the battle against the obesity epidemic (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;28(1): 65-68, ene.-feb. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121290</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación del cumplimiento del convenio de autorregulación del sector de máquinas expendedoras de alimentos y bebidas en las escuelas de primaria de Madrid, España, en 2008</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16566^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5646^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50324</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
