<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120064</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Malnutrition prevalence in hospitalized elderly diabetic patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND AIMS: Malnutrition prevalence is unknown among elderly patients with diabetes mellitus. Our objectives were to determine malnutrition prevalence in elderly in patients with diabetes, and to describe their impact on prognosis. METHODS: An observational multicenter study was conducted in 35 Spanish hospitals. Malnutrition was assessed with the Mini Nutritional Assessment (MNA) tool. Patients were followed until discharge.RESULTS:1,090 subjects were included (78 ± 7.1 years; 50% males). 39.1% had risk of malnutrition, and 21.2% malnutrition. A 15.5% of the malnourished subjects and 31.9 % of those at risk had a BMI &amp;#8805; 30 kg/m(2). In multivariate analysis, female gender (OR = 1.38; 95% CI: 1.19-1.11), age (OR = 1.04; 95% CI: 1.02-1.06) and presence of diabetic complications (OR = 1.97; 95% CI: 1.52-2.56) were associated with malnutrition. Length of stay (LOS) was longer in at-risk and malnourished patients than in well-nourished (12.7 ± 9.9 and 15.7 ± 12.8 days vs 10.7 ± 9.9 days; p &lt; 0.0001). After adjustment by age and gender, MNA score (OR = 0.895; 95% CI 0.814-0.985) and albumin (OR = 0.441; 95% CI 0.212-0.915) were associated with mortality. MNA score was associated with the probability of home discharge (OR = 1.150; 95% CI 1.084-1.219). CONCLUSION: A high prevalence of malnutrition among elderly in patients with diabetes was observed, regardless of BMI. Malnutrition, albumin, and MNA score were related to LOS, mortality and home discharge (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Candela, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burgos, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Ángela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz París, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matía, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La prevalencia de desnutrición es desconocida entre los ancianos con diabetes mellitus. Objetivos: Determinar la prevalencia de desnutrición en ancianos hospitalizados con diabetes mellitus, y describir su impacto en el pronóstico clínico. Material y métodos: Se llevó a cabo un estudio multicéntrico en 35 hospitales españoles. La desnutrición fue valorada mediante la herramienta Mini Nutritional Assessment (MNA). Los pacientes fueron seguidos hasta el alta. Resultados: Fueron incluidos 1.090 sujetos (78 ± 7,1 años; 50% hombres). 39,1% mostraron riesgo de desnutrición y 21,2% desnutrición establecida. El 15,5% de los sujetos desnutridos y 31,9 % de aquellos en riesgo tenían un IMC &amp;#8805;30 kg/m2. En el análisis multivariante, el sexo femenino (OR = 1,38; IC 95%: 1,19-1,11), la edad (OR = 1,04; IC 95%: 1,02-1,06) y la presencia de complicaciones por diabetes (OR = 1,97; IC 95%: 1,52-2,56) se asociaron al diagnóstico de desnutrición. La estancia media fue mayor en sujetos en riesgo y con desnutrición que en los pacientes bien nutridos (12,7 ± 9,9 y 15,7 ± 12.8 días vs 10,7 ± 9,9 días; p &lt; 0,0001). Tras ajustar por edad y sexo, la puntuación del MNA (OR = 0,895; IC 95% 0,814-0,985) y el valor de albúmina (OR = 0,441; IC 95% 0,212-0,915) se asociaron de forma independiente con la mortalidad. La puntuación del MNA se asoció con la probabilidad de alta a domicilio (OR = 1,150; IC 95% 1,084-1,219). Conclusiones: Se observó una elevada prevalencia de desnutrición entre los ancianos hospitalizados con diabetes, independientemente del IMC. El diagnóstico de desnutrición, el valor de albúmina y la puntuación del MNA se asociaron con la estancia media, mortalidad y destino al alta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;28(3): 592-599, mayo-jun. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120064</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de desnutrición en ancianos hospitalizados con diabetes mellitus</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d421^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50320</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
