<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99480</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The beginnings of the Sociedad Farmacéutica del Mediterráneo Latino: II Meeting of the Sociedad Farmacéutica del Mediterráneo latino, held in 1956</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION: The second international meeting of the Society took place in Barcelona at a time in which the internationalization of Spanish pharmacy was minimal after the Civil War and the ostracism to which Spain was subjected after World War II, and made a novelty of a meeting of these features for pharmacists, educators and pharmacy in general. The conference marked the consolidation of the Society, three years after its founding as a section of the Unión Medica Mediterránea and allowed the contact of the Spanish pharmacists with their colleagues from France and Italy.           OBJECTIVE: To determine the origin of the participants in the meeting and major topics of papers and the potential social impact of the meeting. Comparison of the by laws in 1956 to current ones                                          METHODS: A search of the records containing the name and data of the participants in the meeting and the journals that published papers and other publications of the period, as well as the by laws                                                       CONCLUSION / DISCUSSION: In those days, papers were grouped into three sections, Physico-Chemical- Pharmaceutical Sciences and Toxicology, Life Sciences and Professional Affairs, Industrial and History of Pharmacy. The changes in the published papers and the by laws of the society allow to see the evolution of the main concerns in the participating countries towards community pharmacy and the receptiveness to other health professionals, as well as a greater role for women in pharmacy(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bonet Clols, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bel Prieto, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">INTRODUCCIÓN: La segunda reunión internacional de la sociedad tuvo lugar en Barcelona en unos momentos en que la internacionalización de la farmacia española era mínima, tras la Guerra Civil y el ostracismo al que se vio sometida España tras la Segunda Guerra Mundial, por lo que una reunión de estas características supuso una novedad para los profesionales farmacéuticos, docentes y la farmacia en general; la celebración del congreso significó la consolidación de la Sociedad, tres años después de su fundación como una sección más de la Unión Médica Mediterránea y permitió el contacto de los farmacéuticos españoles con sus colegas de Francia e Italia.                   OBJETIVO: Determinar la procedencia de los asistentes a la reunión y los principales temas de las comunicaciones presentadas y de la posible repercusión social de la reunión. Comparación de los estatutos de la Sociedad en 1956 con los actuales                                                      METODOLOGÍA: Consulta del fichero en que constan los asistentes a la reunión y de las revistas en las que se publicaron las comunicaciones y de otras publicaciones de la época, así como de los estatutos de la Sociedad                 CONCLUSIÓN /DISCUSIÓN: En aquellos tiempos las comunicaciones se agruparon en tres secciones, de Ciencias Físico-Químico-Farmacéuticas y Toxicológicas, de Ciencias Biológicas y de Asuntos Profesionales, Industriales e Historia de la Farmacia La evolución de las comunicaciones publicadas y de los estatutos de la sociedad permite ver la evolución de las principales preocupaciones en los países participantes hacia la farmacia comunitaria y la apertura de la farmacia a otros profesionales de la salud, así como un mayor protagonismo de la mujer en la farmacia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;51(supl.3): 219-231, jul. 2010. graf, tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99480</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los Inicios de la Sociedad Farmacéutica del Mediterráneo Latino: II Reunión de la Sociedad Farmacéutica del Mediterráneo Latino, celebrada en 1956</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4582^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4582^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4582^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4582^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11016^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10786^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10786^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201007</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
