<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157453</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-9891</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Can the laryngeal mask play a role in electroconvulsive treatment? A pilot study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Optimising ventilation control in the anaesthetic process of electroconvulsive therapy (ECT) can be a method for improving the effectiveness and safety of some treatments. There are several approaches for inducing adequate therapeutic seizures in patients with medical co-morbidity or in those with high seizure thresholds, although all of them present limitations. A new approach is hyperventilation with laryngeal mask, a method that improves oxygenation, achieves hypocapnia, and lowers seizure threshold. Thus, hyperventilation with laryngeal mask could, hypothetically, be useful to decrease the energy needed to obtain adequate therapeutic seizures. Material and methods. A randomized crossover study was conducted on 14 patients on maintenance ECT, using a laryngeal mask versus a facemask. When laryngeal masks were applied, the energy was reduced by 45% compared with the energy required when ventilated with facemasks (performed with standard dose). Results. The results of the study revealed that, despite a 45% energy reduction with laryngeal mask, there were no significant differences in seizure length in either group. Conclusions. These results prompt us to propose ventilation with laryngeal mask as an alternative to decrease energy applied without lowering seizure times. This is a preliminary study with a small sample, which opens new lines of research. Larger samples and other measurements of seizure adequacy are needed in future studies, in order to study possible improvements in ventilation and minimising adverse effects of ECT, especially in patients with medical co-morbidities (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pifarré, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Gómez, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Buj-Alvarez, Imma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sousa-Duso, Monia de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marco, Gregorio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, Montse</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Optimizar el control de la ventilación en el proceso anestésico de la terapia electroconvulsiva (TEC) puede ser una forma de mejorar la efectividad y la seguridad del tratamiento. Existen varios métodos para inducir una convulsión terapéutica adecuada en pacientes con enfermedad médica comórbida o en aquellos con elevado umbral convulsivo, aunque todos presentan alguna limitación. Un nuevo abordaje es la hiperventilación con mascarilla laríngea, que produce una mayor oxigenación e hipocapnia, disminuyendo el umbral convulsivo. Este hecho puede, hipotéticamente, servir para disminuir la energía necesaria para obtener una convulsión terapéutica adecuada. Material y métodos. Se ha realizado un estudio piloto aleatorizado y cruzado con 14 pacientes en TEC de mantenimiento, utilizando mascarilla laríngea versus mascarilla facial. Las sesiones de TEC con mascarilla facial se realizaron con la energía estándar, mientras que en las sesiones de TEC con mascarilla laríngea se disminuyó la energía en un 45%. Resultados. A pesar de la reducción del 45% en la energía aplicada con el uso de mascarilla laríngea, no se han encontrado diferencias significativas en la duración de la convulsión en ambos grupos. Conclusiones. Con estos resultados se podría proponer la ventilación con mascarilla laríngea como una alternativa para disminuir la energía aplicada sin repercutir en la duración de la crisis. Este es un estudio preliminar con una muestra pequeña, aunque abre nuevas líneas de investigación. Sería necesario aumentar la muestra y valorar otras medidas de calidad de las convulsiones en futuros estudios con el fin de estudiar sus efectos no solo en la dosis de energía necesaria, sino también en una posible mejora de la ventilación y una posible minimización de los potenciales efectos secundarios de la TEC, algo que sería relevante sobre todo en pacientes con comorbilidad médica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psiquiatr. salud ment. (Barc., Ed. impr.);9(4): 203-209, oct.-dic. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157453</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Puede tener un papel la mascarilla laríngea en la práctica de la terapia electroconvulsiva? Un estudio piloto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4637^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4641^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4641^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30675^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30675^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30675^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4637^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30675^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
