<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155250</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anxiety in the parents of children treated in pediatric emergency services in Andalusia and its association with aspects of family functioning</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To assess the level of anxiety in the parents of children treated in hospital emergency departments in Andalusia and its association with dimensions of family functioning. Methods. Descriptive observational study based on a cross-sectional survey. We recruited a convenience sample of parents bringing children to 6 pediatric emergency services in the Spanish autonomous community of Andalusia in 2012. The variables recorded were place of origin, educational level, anxiety level on the Spielberger State-Trait Anxiety Inventory, and family functioning according to the Family Adaptability and Cohesion Scale, version 2. Results. A total of 637 parents were included. Their mean (SD) age was 35.4 (8.4) years; 399 (62.6%) were women. The mean anxiety score was 44.26 (10.15), and we found no differences between mothers and fathers. Lower anxiety levels were associated with higher levels of family cohesion (r = &#150;0.37; P &lt; .001) and adaptability (r = &#150;0.36; P &lt; .001). Conclusion. The parents of children attended in pediatric emergency departments in Andalusia have high levels of anxiety. Anxiety is inversely associated with family adaptability and cohesion (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vílchez-Lara, María J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Castillo, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar el grado de ansiedad y su asociación con diversos elementos del funcionamiento familiar en progenitores cuyos hijos fueron atendidos en servicios de urgencias pediátricos andaluces. Metodología. Estudio observacional descriptivo tipo encuesta de análisis transversal. Se seleccionó, mediante un muestreo por oportunidad, a los progenitores de los niños que fueron atendidos en 6 servicios urgencias pediátricos de la Comunidad Autónoma de Andalucía en 2012. Se recogieron datos demográficos, lugar de origen, nivel educativo, el grado de ansiedad mediante el Inventario de Ansiedad Estado-Rasgo de Spielberger (STAI) y el funcionamiento familiar según la Escala de Cohesión y Adaptabilidad Familiar, versión 2 (FACES II). Resultados. Se incluyeron 637 progenitores, con una edad media de 35,4 (DE = 8,4) años, de los cuales 399 (62,6%) fueron mujeres. La puntuación media en ansiedad fue de 44,26 (DE = 10,15), sin diferencias significativas respecto al sexo de los padres. Los grados menores de ansiedad se asociaron a mayor cohesión (r = &#150;0,37; p &lt; 0,001) y adaptabilidad familiar (r = &#150;0,36; p &lt; 0,001). Conclusiones. El grado de ansiedad de los padres de niños atendidos en los servicios de urgencias pediátricos andaluces es algo elevado y se asocia de forma inversa con la cohesión y la adaptabilidad familiar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);28(4): 239-242, ago. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155250</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La ansiedad y su asociación con elementos de funcionamiento familiar en los padres de niños atendidos en servicios de urgencias pediátricos andaluces</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28084</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10479^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6932^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
