<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127176</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1473</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endonasal skull base endoscopy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION AND OBJECTIVE: The endoscopic endonasal techniques used in skull base surgery have evolved greatly in recent years. Our study objective was to perform a qualitative systematic review of the likewise systematic reviews in published English language literature, to examine the evidence and conclusions reached in these studies comparing transcranial and endoscopic approaches in skull base surgery. MATERIAL AND METHODS: We searched the references on the MEDLINE and EMBASE electronic databases selecting the systematic reviews, meta-analyses and evidence based medicine reviews on skull based pathologies published from January 2000 until January 2013. We focused on endoscopic impact and on microsurgical and endoscopic technique comparisons. RESULTS: Full endoscopic endonasal approaches achieved gross total removal rates of craniopharyngiomas and chordomas higher than those for transcranial approaches. In anterior skull base meningiomas, complete resections were more frequently achieved after transcranial approaches, with a trend in favour of endoscopy with respect to visual prognosis. Endoscopic endonasal approaches minimised the postoperative complications after the treatment of cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) leaks, encephaloceles, meningoceles, craniopharyngiomas (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanromán-Álvarez, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miranda-Lloret, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Botella-Asunción, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pancucci, Giovanni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perez-de-Sanromán, Laila</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Simal-Julián, Juan Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Borredá, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Evangelista-Zamora, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo Las técnicas endoscópicas aplicadas a la base de cráneo han experimentado un fulgurante avance en los últimos años. Este trabajo plantea como objetivo la revisión sistemática de, a su vez, las revisiones sistemáticas publicadas en la literatura inglesa, para examinar las conclusiones y las evidencias halladas en los estudios que comparan cirugía abierta frente a endoscópica de base de cráneo. Material y métodos Se ha realizado una revisión sistemática cualitativa en las bases de datos MEDLINE y EMBASE de la literatura inglesa disponible desde el año 2000, seleccionando las revisiones sistemáticas, metaanálisis y revisiones de medicina basada en la evidencia de las diferentes patologías de la base de cráneo, focalizándonos en el impacto de la cirugía endoscópica y en la comparativa entre los abordajes endonasales endoscópicos y transcraneales. Resultados Los abordajes endoscópicos endonasales han alcanzado tasas de resección completa de craneofaringiomas y cordomas, superior a los abordajes transcraneales clásicos. Respecto a los meningiomas de fosa craneal anterior, los abordajes transcraneales consiguen una tasa de resección completa mayor que los abordajes endoscópicos con una tendencia favorable a la endoscopia, en cuanto a pronóstico visual. Los abordajes endoscópicos han alcanzado minimizar las complicaciones postoperatorias en el tratamiento de las fístulas de líquido cefalorraquídeo (LCR), encefaloceles, meningoceles, craneofaringiomas (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurocirugia (Astur);24(5): 210-215, sept.-oct. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127176</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Endoscopia endonasal de base de cráneo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28266^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32869^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20179^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3413^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8750^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54198^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
