<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76323</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Chest Ultrasonography</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Chest ultrasonography is a useful tool for assessing disease activity in the peripheral lung parenchyma, pleura, chest wall, diaphragm, and mediastinum. Ultrasound imaging also provides highly useful guidance in invasive diagnostic and therapeutic procedures. The main advantages of this imaging technology are the absence of ionizing radiation and the possibility of real-time bedside applications. The chief indications and limitations of chest ultrasonography and the principal sonographic signs are reviewed(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vollmer, Iván</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gayete, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La ecografía torácica es útil en la valoración de enfermedades del parénquima pulmonar periférico, pleura, pared torácica, diafragma y mediastino, y también es de gran utilidad como guía en procedimientos intervencionistas diagnósticos y terapéuticos. Sus principales ventajas radican en la ausencia de radiaciones ionizantes, la capacidad de explorar en tiempo real y la posibilidad de realizar la exploración en la cabecera del paciente. En este artículo se revisan sus principales indicaciones y limitaciones, así como su semiología básica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;46(1): 27-34, ene.2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76323</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ecografía torácica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8830^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11425^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8830^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11426^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36507^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11427^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14294^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11460^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201001</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
