<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043414</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Variability of antibiotic prescribing for respiratory tract infections in two European countries</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Treatment for respiratory tract infections (RTI) in the primary care setting is empirical. Antibiotic prescribing patterns differ among countries and are based on the prevalence of antibiotic resistance in the geographical area. The aim of this study was to compare the antibiotics prescribed by general practitioners (GPs) for RTIs between Spain and Denmark. Methods. Observational multicenter survey carried out in the primary healthcare setting. Two groups of GPs in Spain and Denmark recorded all contacts with RTI patients during a 3-week period between November 2001 and January 2002. Results. A total of 2833 RTI cases were registered. Broad-spectrum penicillins and combinations of these drugs plus beta-lactamase inhibitors were the antibiotics most frequently prescribed by Spanish GPs (62.3%), followed by macrolides (22.3%). In contrast, narrow-spectrum penicillins were most commonly prescribed by Danish GPs (58% of all prescriptions), followed by macrolides (29%) (P &lt; .001). Antibiotics most frequently prescribed for ear, tonsillar, sinus and bronchopulmonary infections were broad-spectrum penicillins among Spanish GPs and narrow-spectrum penicillins in Denmark. Spanish GPs prescribed penicillin V only for tonsillitis, accounting for 5.1% of the antibiotics used for this condition, whereas this drug accounted for 91.7% of the prescriptions by their Danish colleagues for the same indication. Conclusions. The substantial differences in RTI management between the participating GPs should make us reflect on the rational use of antibiotics. The discrepancies disclosed may indicate dissimilarities in recommendations, traditions, habits, or antibiotic pressures between the countries studied (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gahrn-Hansen, Bente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Munck, Anders</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bjerrum, Lars</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cots, Josep María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miravitlles, Marc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llor, Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Forés, Dolors</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boada, Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. En atención primaria, el tratamiento de las infecciones del tracto respiratorio (ITR) es empírico. Los patrones de prescripción de antibióticos son distintos entre países y vienen dados por la prevalencia de resistencias antimicrobianas existentes. El objetivo de este estudio fue comparar qué antibióticos prescriben los médicos de atención primaria en las ITR en España y Dinamarca. Métodos. Estudio observacional multicéntico efectuado en atención primaria de salud. Dos grupos de médicos de atención primaria de España y de Dinamarca registraron todas las visitas con ITR durante un período de 3 semanas entre noviembre de 2001 y enero de 2002. Resultados. Se registraron un total de 2.833 casos de ITR. Los antibióticos más prescritos por los médicos españoles fueron las penicilinas de amplio espectro, asociadas o no a inhibidores de betalactamasas (62,3%), seguido de los macrólidos (22,3%), mientras que en el caso de los daneses fueron las penicilinas de espectro reducido (58% de todos los antibióticos prescritos), seguido de los macrólidos (29%; p &lt; 0,001). En las infecciones óticas, amigdalares, sinusales y broncopulmonares, los antibióticos más prescritos por los médicos españoles fueron las penicilinas de amplio espectro y en Dinamarca las penicilinas de espectro reducido. Los médicos españoles sólo prescribieron fenoximetil penicilina para las amigdalitis, suponiendo en esta infección el 5,1% del total, mientras que los colegas daneses la prescribieron en el 91,7% para esta indicación. Conclusiones. Las importantes diferencias existentes en el tratamiento antibiótico de las ITR entre los médicos participantes debe hacernos reflexionar sobre la utilización racional de los antibióticos. Esto podría ser producto de tradiciones, hábitos, recomendaciones y presiones distintas entre ambos países (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;23(10): 598-604, dic. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043414</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variabilidad de la prescripción antibiótica en las infecciones respiratorias en dos países de Europa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32818^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10209^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10600^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12561^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32697^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14133^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12561^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10209^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3730^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
