<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046799</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neurosyphilis and bladder dysfunction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: Syphilis is a systemic disease the course of which follows successive clinical stages. Central nervous system and spinal cord involvement on late phases may lead to bladder dysfunction. We report one case of neurosyphilis with associated bladder hyperreflexia. ;;METHODS/RESULTS: 51-year-old male with the diagnosis of neurosyphilis consulting for voiding disorders with ;;evidence of detrusor hyperactivity of neurogenic etiology on the urodynamic study. ;;CONCLUSIONS: The differential diagnosis of neurogenic ;;bladder in patients with psychiatric or neurological symptoms should include neurosyphilis. Etiologic diagnosis is obtained by cerebrospinal fluid examination, and the diagnosis of bladder dysfunction by urodynamic study</dc:description>
<dc:creator>José Luis Martín Benito, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Robles, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jalón Monzón, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Rodríguez, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Álvarez, Roberto Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Faba, Oscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Múgica, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Martín Blanco, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Regadera Sejas, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: La sífilis es una enfermedad sistémicaque cursa en estadios clínicos sucesivos. La afectacióndel sistema nervioso central y de la médula espinal en fases tardías puede provocar disfunción vesical. Presentamosun caso de neurosífilis con hiperreflexia asociada.MÉTODO: Varón de 51 años diagnosticado de neurosífilisque consultó por trastornos miccionales objetivando en el estudio urodinámico un detrusor hiperactivo de causa neurogénica.CONCLUSIONES: En el diagnóstico diferencial de vejiga neurógena en pacientes que presentan síntomas psiquiátricosy neurológicos debería ser considerada la neurosífilis.El diagnóstico etiológico es por examen del líquido cefalorraquídeo y el diagnóstico de su disfunción vesical mediante estudio urodinámico</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;59(2): 189-192, mar. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046799</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neurosífilis y disfunción vesical</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9683^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1775^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
