<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-12020</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dysesthesia of the external auditory canal and decreased hearing sensation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We have not found in the literature an explanation for the intermittent and transient decreased lesser hearing sensation in patients with dysesthesia of the external auditory canal (EAC). In this paper we offer a possible explanation for it. Our hypothesis is that the stimulation of the sensory fibers of the trigeminal and facial nerves in the EAC is able to increase the stiffness of the ossicular chain by means of a reflex stimulation of malleus and stapes muscles. This intermittent and transient increase of the ossicular stiffness could explain the intermittent and transient decrease of hearing sensation in these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sanidad y Ediciones (SANED, S.L.)</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la literatura no hemos encontrado una explicación para la disminución intermitente y transitoria de la sensación sonora en pacientes con patología "irritativa" del conducto auditivo externo (CAE). En este artículo ofrecemos una posible explicación. Hipotetizamos que la estimulación de las fibras sensitivas de los nervios trigémino y facial en el CAE es capaz de producir un aumento de la rigidez de la cadena osicular a través de la estimulación refleja de los músculos del martillo y el estribo. Este aumento intermitente y transitorio de la rigidez provocaría la disminución intermitente y transitoria de la sensación sonora en estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;53(5): 384-386, mayo 2002. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patología "irritativa" del conducto auditivo externo y disminución de la sensación sonora</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Calvo Moya, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosell Cervilla, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Purriños, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-12020</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d14097^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9149</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12442</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29638</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4488</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13585^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10481^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14675^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5255^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6471^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6470</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
