<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161222</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ketamine in the treatment of suicidal ideation associated with resistant depression. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There are currently very few quick, effective and safe treatments for reducing suicidal ideation in depression and especially in resistant depression, perhaps with the exception of electroconvulsive therapy (ECT). Ketamine is an anaesthetic with NMDA receptor antagonist properties that, in sub-anaesthetic doses, has demonstrated a really quick and significant improvement in depressive symptoms and suicidal ideation. The improvement in suicidal ideation produced by ketamine is independent of the improvement observed in depressive symptoms. On the other hand, in most of the cases, the improvement in the suicidal ideation is not maintained in time with a single infusion of ketamine and repeated doses are necessary to maintain the therapeutic effect. A case is presented of suicidal ideation in resistant depression with difficulties of using ECT and with a previous history of 18 psychiatric admissions. The patient improved with continuous perfusions of ketamine and minimal adverse effects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palmer, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villar, Mariano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la actualidad disponemos de pocos tratamientos rápidos, efectivos y seguros para reducir la ideación suicida en la depresión y especialmente en la depresión resistente, quizá con la excepción de la terapia electroconvulsiva (TEC). La ketamina es un anestésico con propiedades antagonistas del receptor NMDA que ha demostrado producir, a dosis subanestésicas, una mejoría rápida y firme de los síntomas depresivos y de la ideación suicida. La mejoría de la ideación suicida llevada a cabo por la ketamina es independiente de la mejoría observada en la sintomatología depresiva. Por otra parte, en la mayor parte de los casos, la mejoría de la ideación suicida no se mantiene en el tiempo con una sola perfusión de ketamina y se necesitan dosis repetidas para mantener el efecto terapéutico. Presentamos un caso de ideación suicida en depresión resistente con dificultades de utilizar la TEC y con una historia previa de 18 ingresos psiquiátricos que mejora con perfusiones continuas de ketamina y con efectos adversos mínimos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);24(1): 24-27, ene.-abr. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161222</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ketamina en el tratamiento de la ideación suicida asociada a depresión resistente. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7815^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55361</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54296</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
