<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163701</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of chondroitin sulfate on brain response to painful stimulation in knee osteoarthritis patients. A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled functional magnetic resonance imaging study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Knee osteoarthritis is causing pain and functional disability. One of the inherent problems with efficacy assessment of pain medication was the lack of objective pain measurements, but functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) has emerged as a useful means to objectify brain response to painful stimulation. We have investigated the effect of chondroitin sulfate (CS) on brain response to knee painful stimulation in patients with knee osteoarthritis using fMRI. Methods: Twenty-two patients received CS (800mg/day) and 27 patients placebo, and were assessed at baseline and after 4 months of treatment. Two fMRI tests were conducted in each session by applying painful pressure on the knee interline and on the patella surface. The outcome measurement was attenuation of the response evoked by knee painful stimulation in the brain. Results: fMRI of patella pain showed significantly greater activation reduction under CS compared with placebo in the region of the mesencephalic periaquecductal gray. The CS group, additionally showed pre/post-treatment activation reduction in the cortical representation of the leg. No effects of CS were detected using the interline pressure test. Conclusions: fMRI was sensitive to objectify CS effects on brain response to painful pressure on patellofemoral cartilage, which is consistent with the known CS action on chondrocyte regeneration. The current work yields further support to the utility of fMRI to objectify treatment effects on osteoarthritis pain (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Monfort, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrero, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Solà, Marina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Contreras-Rodríguez, Oren</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llorente-Onaindia, Jone</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montañés, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benito, Pere</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vergés, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pujol, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco-Hinojo, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Deus, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz, Hector</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción:  La artrosis de rodilla es causa de dolor e incapacidad funcional. Uno de los problemas para evaluar la eficacia de los analgésicos ha sido la falta de medidas objetivas de dolor, aunque la resonancia magnética funcional (RMf) ha surgido como un medio útil para objetivar la respuesta del cerebro a la estimulación dolorosa. Hemos investigado el efecto del condroitín sulfato (CS) sobre la respuesta del cerebro a la estimulación dolorosa de la rodilla en pacientes con artrosis mediante RMf. Métodos: Veintidós pacientes recibieron CS (800mg/día) y 27 placebo y fueron evaluados inicialmente y después de 4 meses de tratamiento. En cada sesión de RMf se aplicó presión dolorosa sobre la interlínea de la rodilla y en la superficie de la rótula. El resultado se cuantificó como la atenuación de la respuesta cerebral a la estimulación dolorosa de la rodilla. Resultados: La RMf de la maniobra rotuliana mostró una reducción de la activación en la región de la sustancia gris periacueductal del mesencéfalo significativamente mayor durante el tratamiento con CS que en la condición de placebo. El grupo de CS, pero no el de placebo, mostró además una reducción de la activación en la representación cortical de la pierna tras el tratamiento. No se observaron efectos del CS con presión dolorosa sobre la interlínea de la rodilla. Conclusiones: La RMf fue sensible para objetivar los efectos del CS sobre la respuesta del cerebro a la presión dolorosa sobre el cartílago rotuliano-femoral, que es un resultado coherente con la acción conocida del CS sobre la regeneración de los condrocitos. El presente trabajo muestra nuevamente la utilidad de la RMf para objetivar los efectos del tratamiento en el dolor de origen artrósico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);148(12): 539-547, jun. 2017. graf, tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163701</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos del condroitín sulfato sobre la respuesta cerebral a la estimulación dolorosa en pacientes con artrosis de rodilla. Estudio de resonancia magnética funcional aleatorizado, doble ciego y controlado con placebo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33759^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54669^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2859^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11350^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28387</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
