<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92328</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of bladder-prostate ultrasound in the diagnosis of obstruction/hyperactivity in males with BPH</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: The aim of this paper is to describe the clinical-surgical characteristics of patients who underwent laparoscopic procedures for the management of urinary tract stone disease when performing extracorporeal, percutaneous or endourological procedures was not available.METHODS: A descriptive study based on information from the medical records of patients who underwent surgical laparoscopic management of urinary stone disease between January 2001 and May 2010 at a third level hospital. Epidemiological, clinical and procedure-related variables were taken from the medical urirecords.Univariate analysis was performed with the statistical software STATA 10.1.RESULTS: There were 29 procedures (27 patients) for treatment of urinary stone disease in adults. The average age was 45 years. 55% of patients were men. 17 stones were found on the right side, 5 were pyelic, 19 of the proximal ureter, 4 of the medium ureter and 1 distal. All patients underwent laparoscopic surgery as first surgical option. Average operative time was 142 ± 32 minutes. Three procedures were defined as failures. Hospital stay presented a median of 2 days. There were seven complications.CONCLUSION: Laparoscopic surgery is a good surgical option for the management of urinary tract stone disease in adults(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Restrepo, Jaime Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Herney Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jorge G. Carbonell, Jorge G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo, Diego Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: El objetivo principal del presente artículo fue describir las características clínicoquirúrgicas de los pacientes que fueron llevados a procedimientos laparoscópicos como manejo de enfermedad litiásica del tracto urinario cuando no se dispone de equipamiento para la realización de procedimientos extracorpóreos, percutáneos ni endourológicos.MÉTODOS: Se realizó un estudio observacional descriptivo basado en la información de las historias clínicas de los pacientes que fueron llevados a cirugía laparoscópica como manejo de enfermedad litiásica entre enero de 2001 y mayo de 2010 en el Hospital Universitario del Valle. Se tuvieron en cuenta variables epidemiológicas, clínicas y relacionadas a los procedimientos. Se realizó un análisis univariado con el programa estadístico STATA 10.1.RESULTADOS: Se encontraron 29 procedimientos (27 pacientes) para manejo de enfermedad litiásica en adultos. La edad promedio fue 45 años. 55% de los pacientes fueron hombres. 17 cálculos se encontraron al lado derecho y de la totalidad de ellos 5 eran piélicos, 19 proximales, 4 en uréter medio y 1 distal. Todos los pacientes fueron llevados a cirugía laparoscópica como primera opción quirúrgica. La duración promedio del acto quirúrgico fue 142 ± 32 minutos. Tres procedimientos fueron definidos como fallidos. El tiempo de hospitalización presentó una mediana de 2 días. Se presentaron 5 complicaciones.CONCLUSION: La cirugía laparoscópica es una buena opción quirúrgica para manejo de la enfermedad litiásica del tracto urinario en adultos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;64(9): 891-896, nov. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92328</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de la ecografía vésico-prostática en el diagnóstico de obstrucción/hiperactividad en varones con HBP</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52129^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11913^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52129^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11913^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201111</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
