<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-11974</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy in aids patients: any change in the highly active antiretrovi ral therapies era?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims: Progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy (PML) develops in up to 4-8% of all AIDS patients. Before highly active antiretroviral therapies (HAART) the median survival was only 4-6 months. In this study we analyzed epidemiological parameters in AIDS-related LMP patients in search for differences in the incidence and prognosis between before and after HAART era. Mehods : Retrospective review of clinical histories of patients diagnosed of AIDS and PML at Hospital Meixoeiro in Vigo, Spain, between 01/01/94-31/05/97 (Before-HAART period) and 01/06/97-30/04/00 (After-HAART period). PML was diagnosed by clinical and neuroimaging criteria, with biopsy in 2 cases and positive JC virus hibridation in CSF in another case. Results: We identified 12 patients (global prevalence of 3.8%, without differences between periods): 11 males, 10 intravenous drugs users (IDU), mean age of 38 years (31-43). In 6, LMP was the first opportunistic infection. When PML was diagnosed, 6 patients had a HIV viral load (VL)&gt;250.000 copies of RNA/ml (range, 254.000-3.170.000), and overall a mean CD4 lymphocytes counts of 89 x 10 6/ml (40-134). Three patients received cytarabine+Interferon with zidovudine (2 patients) and zidovudine+lamivudine (1 patient) and other patient HAART+cidofovir, but no improvement was observed. The median survival was 10 months in before-HAART group and 17 months in after-HAART group, with a survival &gt;48 months in 2 patients in the last group. Conclusions: LMP is observed in severely immunosuppressed IDU men (VL&gt;log 5 copies RNA/ml and CD4&lt;150 x106/ml). Complementary treatments were ineffective and only in patients with HAART a prolonged survival was observed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Arán Ediciones, S.A.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: La leucoencefalopatía multifocal progresiva (LMP) afecta al 4-8 por ciento de pacientes con SIDA, con supervivencias de 4-6 meses antes de las terapias antirretrovirales de gran actividad (TARGA). Estudiamos las variables epidemiológicas de pacientes con SIDA y LMP para evaluar posibles diferencias en incidencia y evolución entre la época pre y postTARGA. Métodos: Revisión retrospectiva de historias de pacientes con infección VIH y LMP del Hospital Meixoeiro de Vigo entre el 01/01/9431/05/97 (periodo preTARGA) y 01/06/97-30/04/00 (periodo TARGA).El diagnóstico de LMP se realizó mediante criterios clínicos y de neuroimagen, obteniéndose confirmación biópsica en 2 casos e hibridación + para virus JC en LCR en otro caso. Resultados: Identificamos 12 pacientes con LMP (prevalencia global del 3,8 por ciento, sin diferencias entre periodos): 11 varones, 10 usuarios de drogas parenterales (UDVP), edad media de 38 años (31-43). En 6, la LMP fue la primera infección oportunista. Al diagnóstico de LMP, 6 pacientes presentaban carga viral del VIH&gt;250.000 copias ARN/ml (rango, 254.000-3.170.000), y en todos se obtuvieron recuentos medios de CD4 de 89 x106/l (40-134). Recibieron citarabina+Interferón 3 pacientes (2 con AZT y 1 AZT+3TC) y 1 paciente TARGA+cidofovir, todos sin mejoría. La mediana de supervivencia en el grupo preTARGA fue 9 meses y en el TARGA 17 meses, observándose en 2 pacientes del último supervivencias &gt;48 meses. Conclusiones : La LMP se observa principalmente en varones UDVP, con inmunodeficiencia avanzada (CV&gt;log 5 copias ARN/ml y CD4&lt;150 x106/l). Los tratamientos adyuvantes empleados fueron inefectivos y sólo en pacientes bajo TARGA se consiguieron supervivencias prolongadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;19(5): 230-233, mayo 2002.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Leucoencefalopatía Multifocal Progresiva en pacientes con SIDA: ¿hay algún cambio en pacientes bajo terapias antirretrovirales de gran actividad?</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>González Vázquez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Fernández, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montes Santiago, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Martín, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Asorey Carballeira, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morano Amado, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Álvarez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-11974</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35395</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28604</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29364</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
