<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98719</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Advances in the management of ulcerative colitis presented at Digestive Disease Week 2011</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Many studies on ulcerative colitis were presented in Digestive Disease Week 2011, some of which reported important information for clinical practice. Some authors have reported predictive factors of colectomy in these patients, as well as the most frequent complications associated with surgical treatment. Other studies provided new data on the incidence of dysplasia and colorectal cancer, as well as on the correlation between clinical activity and endoscopy in patients with ulcerative colitis. In this congress, special attention was drawn to studies evaluating the effectiveness of new drugs in ulcerative colitis, such as adalimumab, and to studies proposing strategies to optimize the effectiveness of the conventional drugs, such as 5-aminosalicylates, thiopurines or steroids (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Chaparro, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la Digestive Disease Week 2011 se han presentado numerosos trabajos sobre la colitis ulcerosa, muchos de ellos con información relevante para la práctica clínica. Se han identificado factores predictores de la necesidad de colectomía en estos pacientes, así como de las complicaciones asociadas al tratamiento quirúrgico. Además, se han aportado nuevos datos sobre la incidencia de displasia y cáncer colorrectal, así como de la correlación entre la actividad clínica y la endoscópica en los pacientes con colitis ulcerosa. Pero sin duda, la mayor parte de la atención la han centrado los estudios sobre el tratamiento de la enfermedad, evaluando la eficacia de nuevos fármacos en la colitis ulcerosa y proponiendo estrategias para la optimización de los tratamientos clásicos, como los 5-aminosalicilatos, las tiopurinas o los esteroides (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;34(supl.2): 52-59, oct. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98719</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Novedades en el manejo de la colitis ulcerosa presentadas en la Digestive Disease Week 2011</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33400^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3113^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23971^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13642^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
