<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132596</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Obesity associated risk using Edmonton staging in bariatric surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">With a prevalence of Morbid Obesity of 1,2% of the Spanish population, the current criteria for Bariatric Surgery do not classify patients taking into consideration co-morbidities or functional status. We need new staging systems useful in predicting mortality and able to support prioritizing treatments. Aim: Applying Edmonton staging system to patients awaiting Bariatric Surgery. Method: Data collected from 81 patients from 2011- 2013 after pre-surgery protocol. Weight, height, waist, BMI, biochemical parameters and blood pressure are registered. Also taken down are hepatic, renal, osteoarticular diseases, sleep-apnea syndrome and/or gastro-oesophageal reflux, if present. Edmonton staging of ten variables is applied to each patient. Results: 81 patients: 67% women, average age 47y, 18% below 30y. Average BMI of 47, 90% of patients have a BMI &gt;40. 34% of patients show sleep-apnea syndrome and 25% gastro-oesophageal reflux. 9% of the patients have a BMI &gt;45, diabetes mellitus and sleep-apnea syndrome. Applying the Edmonton Staging, nine patients (11%) are in the highest risk range (stage 3), 70% are in the high-risk range (stage 2) and 15 patients (18%) are included in the low-risk range. No patient was found to be in stage 0 without obesity risk factors. Conclusions: The Edmonton staging system provides us with information on presence or extent of co-morbidities that guide decision making in individuals. The mortality- predictive ability of Edmonton proposal could help to assist in determining the urgency of Bariatric Surgery and establish better criteria to prioritize these group of patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cardenas, Jersy J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez, Clotilde</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cos, Ana Isabel de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roldán, María Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pelegrina, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pallardo, Luis Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Con una prevalencia de obesidad mórbida del 1,2% en población española, los criterios de indicación para Cirugía Bariátrica (CB) no consideran comorbilidades ni estado funcional. Es necesaria una aproximación diagnóstica capaz de predecir mortalidad y sustentar criterios de priorización terapéutica. Objetivo: Aplicar la propuesta Edmonton como sistema de estadiaje clínico para la clasificación de pacientes en lista de espera de CB. Método: Se recogen datos de 81 pacientes (2011 &#150; 2013), tras protocolo prequirúrgico. Se registra peso, talla, IMC, cintura, determinaciones bioquímicas, TA, presencia de enfermedad hepática, renal, osteoarticular, síndrome apnea-hipopnea del sueño (SAHS) y reflujo gastroesofágico. Se aplica a cada persona la propuesta de estadiaje de Edmonton, con 10 variables.  Resultados: 67% mujeres. Edad media: 47 años, 18% con edad inferior a 30 años. IMC medio: 47 (37-67), 90% IMC &gt; de 40. El 34% de los pacientes presentan SHAS y el 25% enfermedad por reflujo. Un 9% asocia IMC &gt; 45, disglucosis-diabetes mellitus y SAHS. Aplicando el modelo de Edmonton, nueve pacientes (11%) se sitúan en el rango de mayor riesgo (estadío 3), 70% en rango de riesgo elevado (estadío 2), y 15 pacientes (18%), están incluidos en la condición de bajo riesgo. Ningún paciente se situaba en estadio 0, sin factores de riesgo asociados a obesidad. Conclusiones: El estadiaje de Edmonton nos aporta información sobre la presencia y extensión de co-mobilidades, que apoye la toma de decisiones terapéuticas. La capacidad predictiva de mortalidad de la propuesta de Edmonton podría ser útil para establecer criterios de priorización quirúrgica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(1): 196-202, ene. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132596</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Riesgo asociado a obesidad según estadiaje de Edmonton en cirugía bariátrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13273^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24004^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51221^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
