<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158214</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-5887</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Organ Transplantation in Brazil y Spain: How the ethics and legal criteria protect the living donor in both countries?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study compares the specific Organ Transplantations Laws from Spain and Brazil. Its objective is investigate how the legal devices protect the organ living donors in both countries, where the incentives for living donation has been stimulated lately. From the analysis of the «Document on Transplantation from Living Donors», published from Bioethics and Law Observatory Opinion Group from Barcelona University (OBD-UB), in 2011, it has been concluded that the living donations should not be stimulated (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marinho, Sonia Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schramm, Fermin Roland</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo realiza una comparación entre las legislaciones específicas de trasplantes de órganos de España y Brasil. Su objetivo es averiguar cómo los dispositivos legales protegen a los donantes vivos de órganos. Tomando como base el documento del Grupo de Opinión del Observatorio de Bioética y Derecho (en adelante, OBD), de la Universidad de Barcelona, sobre «Trasplante de órganos de donante vivo», publicado en 2011, los autores concluyen que las donaciones a partir de personas vivas deben ser estimuladas sólo en algunos casos muy específicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. bioét. derecho;(38): 55-70, 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158214</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trasplante de órganos en Brasil y en España: ¿cómo los criterios ético-legales protegen al donante vivo en ambos los países?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29074^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1963^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1698^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30112^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8062^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50207</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29074^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33201^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33201^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
