<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95014</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interdisciplinary attention to the sequels of the disease and/or treatments in pediatric oncology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Medical advances in the last decades have increased the cancer survival rate, leading to short-and long term sequelae caused by the disease and/or treatment and with different degrees of severity. Recent imaging studies have shown brain damage (white and grey matter involvement) by chemo- and radiotherapy. Pathology, treatments, age, sex, etc. modulate brain damage and its sequelae. Together with neuropsychological deficit, which has been largely described, motor problems and daily life activities are frequent and determine subsequent social, school and work adaptation. We propose specialist´s interdisciplinary involvement in and follow- up of brain damage in children with more serious sequelae. Interaction of different disciplines (neuropsychology, pediatric neurology, family therapy, physiotherapy, occupational therapy and speech therapy, among others) in these teams can improve  quality of life of patients and their  families (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Celma, Mercedes Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Plasencia, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moran, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Cuenca, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fournier, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañete, Adela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prades, Olivia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernabeu, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los avances en la medicina de las últimas décadas han permitido el aumento del número de supervivientes en oncología. La mayor supervivencia ha hecho que sean visibles secuelas, de distinto grado, a corto y largo plazo por la enfermedad y/o tratamientos. Recientes estudios de imagen muestran daño cerebral (afectando de sustancia blanca y gris) tanto por quimio como radioterapia. La patología, tratamientos, edad, sexo modulan el daño cerebral y sus secuelas.Junto con los déficit neuropsicológicos, ampliamente descritos, son frecuentes los problemas motores, actividades de la vida diaria que condicionan a su posterior adaptación escolar, laboral y social. Proponemos la atención y seguimiento interdisciplinar de especialistas en daño cerebral para algunos casos con secuelas más acusadas. La interacción de distintas disciplinas (neuropsicología, neuropediatría, terapia familiar, fisioterapia terapia ocupacional, logopedia&#133;) en estos equipos puede mejorar la calidad de vida de los pacientes y sus familias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);6(2/3): 381-411, dic. 2009. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95014</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Atención interdisciplinar  a las secuelas de la enfermedad y/o tratamientos en oncología pediátrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d974^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10542^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12314^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
