<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122941</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To study the body image built by patients with breast cancer after surgery, radical mastectomy and partial mastectomy, related to body parts directly involved in surgery and not directly related to it, and to investigate how this image affects bodily self-esteem. Method: Our sample comprised 23 patients (12 had been subjected to radical mastectomy and 11 to partial mastectomy) and 24 healthy women (they served as control group). Participants were assessed with the Body Grid technique. We analyzed the differences between groups using one way ANOVA and non-parametric tests (namely, H de Kruskal Wallis and U de Mann-Whitney). Results: Our findings allowed us to identify which were the most damaged aspects about self-esteem and body image in these patients, showing that there were no significant differences in body image and bodily self-esteem between patients subjected to radical and partial mastectomy. However, we found significant differences between body parts directly involved in surgery and those not directly related to it. Finally, we found significant differences between both groups of patients and the control group regarding body image and self-esteem.Conclusions: Our results show that the Body Grid Technique is helpful to identify the most affected aspects of body image in patients subjected to mastectomy and tailor psychological treatments aimed at improving body image in these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Nieto, Rebeca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segura Valverde, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saúl Gutiérrez, Luis Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudiar la imagen corporal que construyen las pacientes diagnosticadas de cáncer de mama tras someterse a intervención quirúrgica, mastectomía radical y cirugía conservadora, tanto en lo referente a aspectos corporales relacionados directamente con la lesión como a zonas corporales no relacionadas, e investigar cómo esa imagen afecta a la autoestima centrada en lo corporal. Método: Contamos con una muestra de 23 pacientes (12 mujeres mastectomizadas y 11 con cirugía conservadora) y 24 mujeres sanas que sirvieron como grupo control. El instrumento de evaluación utilizado es la Técnica de la Rejilla Corporal. Se analizaron las diferencias entre los grupos mediante ANOVA de un factor y las pruebas no paramétricas H de Kruskal Wallis y U de Mann-Whitney. Resultados y conclusiones: Los resultados del estudio han permitido identificar qué aspectos son los más dañados en la autoestima y autoimagen de las pacientes, estableciendo que no existen diferencias significativas en la imagen corporal global y la autoestima centrada en lo corporal entre mujeres mastectomizadas y mujeres sometidas a cirugía conservadora, aunque sí en la imagen que se tiene de las zonas corporales específicamente implicadas en la cirugía. Sí se han encontrado diferencias entre estos dos grupos y el grupo de mujeres sanas en imagen corporal global y autoestima. Los resultados obtenidos permitirán identificar los aspectos de la imagen corporal más afectados en las pacientes y por tanto orientar posibles intervenciones psicológicas futuras hacia la reconstrucción adaptativa y sana de los mismos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);11(1): 45-57, jun. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122941</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Imagen corporal y autoestima en mujeres mastectomizadas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23753^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1853^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8580^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
