<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043871</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-7823</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reply to González-Blanch (2006): Must be regulated today as health professions all the disciplines related to health? Commentary on professor Buela-Casal and colleagues studies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article is a reply to González-Blanch´s commentaries about the studies conducted by Buela-Casal´s research group aboutthe image of Psychology as a sanitary profession that were published in issue 91 of Papeles del Psicólogo. The comments andcritics made by González-Blanch are only personal opinions, which are even wrong most of the times, for example, the proposeof using different procedures for the data recollection in the same study. On the other hand, it is contradictory as well toconsider that the samples have representativity problems and, at the same time, to recognize that some results are really interesting.But, the most amazing thing is the interpretation that he makes about the data from the study with general population</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Buela-Casal, Gualberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo es una réplica a los comentarios de González-Blanch sobre los estudios realizados por el grupo de Buela-Casalsobre la imagen de la psicología como profesión sanitaria y que fueron publicados en el número 91 de Papeles del Psicólogo.Los comentarios y críticas realizadas por González-Blanch no son más que simples opiniones personales, las cuales en lamayoría de los casos son incorrectas, como por ejemplo, proponer que se utilicen procedimientos distintos en la recogida deinformación en un mismo estudio. Por otra parte, el mismo autor se contradice al considerar que las muestras tienen problemasde representatividad y al mismo tiempo resalta algunos resultados que parecen interesarle especialmente. Pero quizá lomás sorprendente es la interpretación que él hace de las respuestas del estudio con la población general</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pap. psicol;27(1): 61-64, ene. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043871</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Réplica a González-Blanch (2006): ¿deben regularse hoy como profesiones sanitarias todas las disciplinas relacionadas con la salud? Comentario sobre los estudios del profesor Buela-Casal y colaboradores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17227^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6432^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12023^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8678^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
