<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80912</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Arrhythmia and right heart disease: from genetic basis to clinical practice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Historically, left ventricular cardiomyopathy and coronary heart disease have been regarded as the main causes of ventricular arrhythmia and sudden cardiac death. However, within last two decades, arrhythmias originating from the right ventricle have begun to attract the attention of the scientific world for a number of reasons. Ventricular arrhythmias originating from the right ventricle usually affect younger patients and can lead to sudden cardiac death. The pathophysiologic mechanism of these arrhythmias is not fully understood, which can leave room for a range of different interpretations. Moreover, the intriguing world of genetics is increasingly being drawn into the pathogenesis, diagnosis and prognosis of some of these arrhythmias. This review considers the pathogenesis, diagnosis and treatment of arrhythmogenic right ventricular cardiomyopathy or dysplasia (ARVD), Brugada syndrome, right ventricular outflow tract ventricular tachycardia, and arrhythmias in the right side of the heart due to congenital heart disease. In addition, because ventricular arrhythmias associated with right ventricular heart diseases such as Brugada syndrome and ARVD can explain up to 10-30% of sudden cardiac deaths in young adults in the general population and an even greater percentage in young athletes, this article contains a brief analysis of screening tests used before participation in sports, life-style modification, and treatment options for athletes affected by these conduction disorders (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Brugada, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Capulzini, Lucio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brugada, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brugada, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La cardiopatía isquémica y la miocardiopatía del ventrículo izquierdo se han considerado históricamente la principal causa de arritmias ventriculares (AV) y de muerte súbita cardiaca (MSC). Sin embargo, en las últimas dos décadas, las arritmias originadas en el ventrículo derecho (VD) han atraído la atención del mundo científico por diversas razones. Las AV originadas en el VD suelen afectar a pacientes de menor edad y pueden conducir a la MSC. El mecanismo fisiopatológico de esas arritmias no se ha aclarado por completo y a veces deja margen para diferentes interpretaciones. Además, cada vez se involucra en mayor medida al intrigante mundo de la genética en los aspectos patogénicos, diagnósticos y pronósticos de algunas de estas arritmias. En esta revisión se analiza la patogenia, el diagnóstico y el tratamiento de la miocardiopatía/displasia arritmogénica del ventrículo derecho (DAVD), el síndrome de Brugada (SB), la taquicardia ventricular de tracto de salida ventricular derecho (TV-TSVD) y las arritmias derechas debidas a cardiopatías congénitas (CPC). Además, dado que las arritmias ventriculares en las enfermedades del VD como el SB y la DAVD pueden explicar hasta un 10-30% de las MSC en los adultos jóvenes de la población general y un porcentaje aún mayor de las de los deportistas jóvenes, se analiza brevemente el uso de pruebas de detección sistemática previas a la participación en actividades deportivas, la modificación del estilo de vida y las opciones terapéuticas existentes para los deportistas jóvenes afectados por estos trastornos eléctricos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;63(8): 963-983, ago. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80912</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Arritmias y enfermedades del corazón derecho: de las bases genéticas a la clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4634^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22878^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1150^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52136^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6505^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52136^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30797^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30797^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13993^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30163^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21027^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1150^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6484^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6484^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22878^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30163^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9394^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
