<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131223</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tackling child overweight in Primary Care: the role of motivational interviewing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: the primary objective is to assess the impact of a programme for tackling child overweight based on motivational interviewing, by measuring changes in the body mass index Z-scores, eating patterns and physical activity levels. The agreement between two physical activity questionnaires will also be assessed. Methods: we propose to carry out an interventional study on children aged between 6 and 12 years old. All children from five paediatric doctor's lists at the participating primary care health centres identified as overweight in the 6-year-old health check-up will be candidates for this study (body mass index &gt;85th percentile and &lt; 95th percentile). Children with secondary obesity or those who would not be properly followed-up will be excluded from the study. A six-session intervention based on motivational interviewing, will be performed. A nutrition and physical activity questionnaire will be administered at baseline, at 4months and at the end of the intervention. Factors associated to pre-post changes will be studied via multivariate regression models. The agreement between the physical activity questionnaires will be assessed with the Kappa coefficient. Statistical analysis will be performed using SPSS version 21. The greatest limitation of this study is the lack of skills for motivational interviewing among the participating clinicians. To address this limitation, the participating clinicians will attend specific workshops on motivational interviewing focused on child obesity. Another limitation is the lack of a control group (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aguirre Sorondo, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Conde, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero Barrigón, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Totoricaguena Imaz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leizaola Olarreaga, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solorzano Sánchez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gorrotxategi Gorrotxategi, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cancio López, H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: plantear un programa de intervención sobre el sobrepeso, desarrollado por los profesionales de Atención Primaria (AP), basado en la entrevista motivacional. Analizar las variaciones del Z score del índice de masa corporal (IMC), del patrón nutricional, del nivel de actividad física y la concordancia entre dos diferentes escalas para ese fin. Metodología: diseño: estudio de intervención en niños entre 6 y 12 años que en el control del programa de salud infantil de los seis años tengan un IMC &gt; P85 y &lt; P95), pertenecientes a cinco consultas de Pediatría de AP. Serán excluidos los que tengan una obesidad secundaria o aquellos en los que no sea posible realizar un seguimiento adecuado. Se les realizará una intervención de seis sesiones basadas en la entrevista motivacional y se realizará una encuesta nutricional y dos de actividad física, en el momento basal, a los cuatro meses y al final de la intervención. Análisis estadístico: los factores que se asocian con los cambios pre- y posintervención se estudiarán mediante modelos de regresión multivariante. La concordancia entre las escalas de actividad física se estudiará con el índice de Kappa. Los análisis estadísticos se realizarán con el software SPSS® versión 2. Limitaciones: la falta de habilidad en la técnica de la entrevista motivacional por parte de los pediatras. Para superar dicha limitación se ha proyectado realizar un taller de formación específica a los participantes. Otra limitación es la falta de grupo control (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;16(64): e199-e207, oct.-dic. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131223</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Protocolo del estudio: abordaje del sobrepeso en Atención Primaria. Papel de la entrevista motivacional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35170^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35170^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
