<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140262</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8799</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychophysiological response in a high altitude tactical parachute jump. A case study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The study of the different phases of actual warfare that in the current theathers of operations have been poor studied in the specific literature, although in the last years several studies have shown the increased warfighter organic response in situations of symmetrical, asymmetrical, close quarter and melee combats due to the combat stress. Despite this study and to the best of our knowledge there are no studies focusing on extreme situations previous to the combat as parachute jumps, especially high altitude jumps as the HALO (High Altitude Low Opening). This research aimed to study the psychophysiological response of a warfighter performing a HALO parachute jump. A HALO jump, jump at 18,000 feet and opening at 4,000 feet, performed by an experimented jumper (over 200 jumps) of the Paratrooper Brigade of the Spanish Army (170 cm; 61 kg; 25 years) were analyzed. Before and after the HALO jump parameters of muscle strength, cortical arousal, blood levels of creatinekinase and glucose, blood oxygen saturation, rated of perceived exertion and specific fine motor skills were assessed; during the jump heart rate, heart rate variability (to analyze autonomic modulation) and accelerometry (by a GPS device) were evaluated. The data showed as a HALO jump caused an increased sympathetic modulation, reaching values of maximum heart rate of 217 beats per minute, a decreased in cortical arousal and muscle strength, an increased blood levels of creatinekinase, a maintenance of blood glucose and oxygen saturation, a rated of perceived exertion lower than the assessed organic response and no effect on specific fine motor skills of the warfighter. This novel research could be used to improve actual training systems in paratroopers&#146; brigades (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Robles-Pérez, José Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Clemente-Suárez, Vicente Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montañez-Toledo, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El estudio de las diversas facetas del combate a las que el soldado tiene que hacer frente ha sido poco investigado en la literatura científica, aunque en los últimos años varios estudios han mostrado la alta respuesta orgánica del combatiente debido al estrés en situaciones de combate simétrico, asimétrico, a corta distancia y en combate cuerpo a cuerpo, pero sigue sin haber estudios centrados en situaciones límite previas al combate como los saltos paracaidistas, especialmente en saltos a alta cota como el HALO (High Altitud Low Opening). Esta investigación tenía por objeto estudiar la respuesta psicofisiológica en la realización de un salto HALO. Se analizó a un saltador experimentado (más de 200 saltos) de la Brigada Paracaidista del Ejército de Tierra Español (25 años; 61 kg; 170 cm) en un salto HALO, salto a 18000 pies y apertura a 4000 pies. Antes y después de la maniobra se evaluaron parámetros de fuerza muscular, activación cortical, concentración sanguínea de creatinfosfokinasa y glucosa, saturación de oxígeno en sangre, percepción subjetiva de esfuerzo y habilidades motrices finas especificas; durante el salto se evaluó la frecuencia cardiaca, la variabilidad de la frecuencia cardiaca para el estudio de la modulación autonómica y la acelerometría mediante un dispositivo GPS. Los datos muestran como un salto HALO provocó un aumento de la modulación simpática, alcanzando valores de frecuencia cardiaca máxima de 217 pulsaciones, una disminución de la activación cortical y de la fuerza muscular, un aumento de la concentración sanguínea de creatinfosfokinasa, una mantenimiento de valores de glucosa sanguínea, de saturación de oxígeno, una percepción subjetiva de esfuerzo inferior a la respuesta orgánica evaluada y ningún efecto sobre la habilidad motriz fina especifica del combatiente. Este novedoso resultado puede ser utilizado para mejorar la preparación de los paracaidistas de combate (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. med. deporte;32(167): 144-148, mayo-jun. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140262</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Respuesta psicofisiológica en un salto táctico paracaidista a gran altitud. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12039^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12039^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32981^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1371^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1371^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1371^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6493^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12039^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12039^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
