<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85699</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of a hand hygiene campaign on alcoholic hand rub consumption in a tertiary hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveTo evaluate the influence of a hand hygiene program on consumption of alcoholic hand rub, and specifically the impact of the development of hand washing training in a tertiary hospital belonging to the Cantabrian Health Service in Spain.MethodsWe performed an ecological study from January 2005 to December 2008. The dependent variable was consumption of alcoholic hand rub (ml/day). As the independent variable, we used the hand hygiene campaign developed by the Cantabrian Health Service. The relationship between alcoholic hand rub consumption and the campaign was evaluated using multiple linear regression.Results and conclusionsThe training received in hand hygiene in hospital wards was associated with consumption of alcoholic hand rub, which improved as the campaign became consolidated (in 2008) and showed a positive effect, particularly its training aspects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Antolín-Juárez, Francisco Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cal López, Marta de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Robles-García, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rebollo-Rodrigo, Henar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro-Córdoba, Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llorca, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dierssen-Sotos, Trinidad</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoValorar la influencia sobre el consumo de preparados de base alcohólica de una campaña de mejora de la higiene de manos, y más concretamente del desarrollo de talleres prácticos sobre higienización de manos en un hospital de tercer nivel del Servicio Cántabro de Salud.MétodosSe realizó un estudio ecológico con datos de enero de 2005 a diciembre de 2008. La variable dependiente fue el consumo de preparados de base alcohólica (ml/día). Como variable independiente se utilizó la campaña de mejora de la higiene de manos desarrollada en el Servicio Cántabro de Salud. Para valorar la relación del consumo con la campaña se utilizó un análisis de regresión lineal múltiple.Resultados y conclusionesDestaca la asociación entre la formación recibida sobre higiene de manos en las unidades de hospitalización y el consumo de preparados de base alcohólica, que mejora al consolidarse la campaña (año 2008) y demuestra un efecto positivo de ésta, en especial de sus aspectos formativos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;24(4): 358-360, jul. -agos. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85699</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de una campaña de mejora de la higiene de manos sobre el consumo de soluciones hidroalcohólicas en un hospital de tercer nivel</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d431</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28450</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6917</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
