<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154410</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Antipsychotic response in delusional disorder and schizophrenia: a prospective cohort study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Scientific evidence focused on the treatment response in delusional disorder (DD) patients is scarce, and the findings are controversial. Our goal was to compare the antipsychotic response at the 12-week followup between patients diagnosed with DD and patients diagnosed with schizophrenia and to identify potential response dimensions. Methods. A prospective, observational, cohort study with 12-week follow-up was conducted with DD and schizophrenia patients matched for sex, age and cumulative years of disease. The following scales were assessed: Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS; 5-factors), Personal and Social Performance Scale (PSP), Clinical Global Impression Scale (CGI), and Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS). Treatment response was defined as a &amp;#8805;30% reduction in the total PANSS score. Linear and logistic regression models were used to investigate the potential predictive value of psychopathological variables for the antipsychotic response. Results. Response percentages in DD and schizophrenia were 61.5% and 69.2%, respectively. The duration of untreated psychosis, antipsychotic dosage, and diagnosis did not predict antipsychotic response. In the whole sample, improvement in positive symptoms was significantly associated with the clinical global improvement (p=0.006). explaining almost 20% of the variance in the model. Within the DD group, improvement in cognitive symptoms explained 30% of the variance in clinical global improvement. Conclusions. Both response percentages and required antipsychotic doses were similar between DD and schizophrenia. Changes in positive symptoms were associated with clinical global improvement in the entire sample, and improvement in cognitive symptoms was correlated with global improvement exclusively in DD (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Penadés, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Rodríguez, Alexandre</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torra, Mercè</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernardo, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Catalán, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La evidencia científica centrada en la respuesta terapéutica en pacientes con trastorno delirante (TD) es escasa, y los hallazgos contradictorios. Nuestro objetivo fue comparar la respuesta antipsicótica a las 12 semanas en pacientes con TD y esquizofrenia, e identificar potenciales dimensiones de respuesta. Metodología. Se llevó a cabo un estudio prospectivo, observacional, de cohortes de 12 semanas de seguimiento en pacientes con TD y esquizofrenia, apareados por sexo, edad y años de evolución. Se administraron las siguientes escalas: Escala de los Síndromes Positivo y Negativo (PANSS; 5-factores), Funcionamiento Social y Personal (PSP), Impresión Clínica Global (CGI) y Escala Columbia de Severidad Suicida (C-SSRS). La respuesta al tratamiento fue definida como una reducción en puntuación total de PANSS &amp;#8805;30%. Se realizaron análisis de Regresión Lineal y Regresión Logística para investigar el valor predictivo de los dominios psicopatológicos sobre la respuesta antipsicótica. Resultados. Los porcentajes de respuesta en TD y esquizofrenia fueron 61,5% y 69,2% respectivamente. La duración de la psicosis no tratada, la dosis antipsicótica y el diagnóstico no predijeron la respuesta antipsicótica. En la muestra total, la reducción de síntomas positivos se asoció de forma significativa a una mejoría clínica global (p=0.006) dando cuenta de hasta un 20% de la varianza del modelo. En la submuestra de pacientes con TD, la mejoría en síntomas cognitivos se asoció a la mejoría en impresión clínica global llegando a explicar un 30% de su varianza (p=0.030) (AU). Conclusiones. Tanto los porcentajes de respuesta como las dosis antipsicóticas fueron similares en el TD y en la esquizofrenia. El cambio en síntomas positivos se asoció a mejoría clínica global en la muestra total, y el cambio en síntomas cognitivos se correlacionó con la impresión clínica global exclusivamente en el TD</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;44(4): 125-135, jul.-ago. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154410</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Respuesta antipsicótica en trastorno delirante y esquizofrenia: estudio prospectivo de cohortes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3707^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3707^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
