<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90366</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Protein Contact Dermatitis: Review of 27 Cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Protein contact dermatitis (PCD) is a rare and underdiagnosed condition that many dermatologists fail to recognize. Nevertheless, increasing awareness of the condition and the substances responsible has led to a rise in the number of published cases in recent years. Objective: To determine the clinical characteristics and allergens implicated in PCD in our setting. Material and methods: A retrospective observational study of all patients diagnosed with PCD in the last 10years was undertaken in the Skin Allergies Unit of the Department of Dermatology at Hospital General Universitario in Valencia, Spain. All patients were assessed by skin-prick test with the standard GEIDAC allergen panel and by prick-by-prick test with foods or other products that were linked to immediate skin symptoms following handling. Results: Twenty-seven patients (8 men and 19 women) were diagnosed with PCD, and 26 of the cases were occupational in origin. The mean age of the patients was 32.3years and 51.8% had a history of atopy. The latency period varied from 2 months to 27years. The most commonly affected areas were the backs of the hands and the forearms. Four patients had an oral allergy syndrome. In order of frequency, the substances responsible for PCD were fish (9 patients, 33.3%), latex (8 patients, 29.6%), potato (4 patients, 14.8%), chicken (3 patients, 11.1%), flour (3 patients, 11.1%), alpha amylase (2 patients, 7.4%), aubergine (2 patients, 7.4%), pork (1 patient, 3.7%), garlic (1 patient, 3.7%), and Anisakis (1 patient, 3.7%). Conclusions: PCD is a clinically relevant condition that dermatologists should include in the differential diagnosis of chronic dermatitis affecting the hands or forearms in patients at high occupational risk, particular those in the food preparation industry (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Bel, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuadra, J. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alegre, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La dermatitis de contacto por proteínas (DCP) es una patología infrecuente, poco conocida por el dermatólogo e infradiagnosticada. Recientemente el número de casos publicados de DCP ha ido en aumento por un mayor conocimiento de esta entidad, así como del espectro de sustancias responsables de la misma. Objetivo: Estudiar las características clínicas y los alérgenos implicados en la DCP en nuestro entorno. Material y métodos: Se trata de un estudio observacional y retrospectivo de todos los pacientes diagnosticados de DCP en los últimos 10 años en la Sección de alergia cutánea del Servicio de Dermatología del Hospital General Universitario de Valencia. Todos los pacientes fueron estudiados mediante pruebas epicutáneas con la batería estándar del GEIDAC y mediante pruebas cutáneas con los alimentos y/o productos que al manipularlos relacionaban con síntomas cutáneos inmediatos. Resultados: Un total de 27 pacientes (8 varones y 19 mujeres) fueron diagnosticados de DCP, 26 de los cuales fueron de origen laboral. La edad media fue de 32,3 años, y el 51,8% tenían historia personal de atopia. El tiempo de sensibilización fue variable, entre dos meses y 27 años. Las áreas más frecuentemente afectadas fueron el dorso de las manos y los antebrazos. Cuatro pacientes presentaron un síndrome oral de alergia. Las sustancias responsables de la DCP fueron, por orden de frecuencia, pescados (9/27, 33,3%), látex (8/27, 29,6%), patata (4/27, 14,8%), pollo y harina (3/27, 11,1%), alfa-amilasa y berenjena (2/27, 7,4%) y carne de cerdo, ajo y anisakis (1/27, 3,7%). Conclusiones: La DCP es una entidad de relevancia clínica que el dermatólogo debe considerar en el diagnóstico diferencial de una dermatitis crónica de las manos y/o antebrazos en pacientes con alto riesgo ocupacional, particularmente manipuladores de alimentos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;102(5): 336-343, jun. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90366</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dermatitis de contacto por proteínas. Revisión de 27 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22673^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23923^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7147^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30757^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5651^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
