<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165355</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Risk behavior patterns for chronic diseases and associated factors among adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background/objective: Simultaneous engagement in risk behaviors for chronic non-communicable diseases (NCDs) might exert a synergistic effect on adolescent health. This study aimed to identify risk behavior patterns for NCDs in adolescents and analyze associated factors. Methods: Cross-sectional study conducted between 2009 and 2011, with 1,716 participants aged 10-17 years of a cohort study in Central-West Region, Brazil. Demographic, economic, anthropometric, and lifestyle characteristics were collected. Risk behaviors evaluated were alcohol consumption, tobacco experimentation, insufficient physical activity, sedentary behavior, skipping breakfast, and low diet quality. Principal component analysis was used to identify patterns of risk behaviors and multiple linear regression analysis to quantify the association between independent variables and patterns of risk behavior. Results: Three patterns of risk behaviors were identified: «legal drugs», «diet and screens», and «silent». After adjustment, legal drugs pattern showed direct association with age (&amp;#946; = 0.13; 95% CI = 0.09; 0.16) and inverse association with maternal education (&amp;#946; = -0.07; 95% CI = -0.14; -0.01). Diet and screens pattern were directly associated with female gender (&amp;#946; = 0.14; 95% CI = 0.04; 0.23), age (&amp;#946; = 0.11; 95% CI = 0.08; 0.14), and economic class (&amp;#946; = 0.15; 95% CI = 0.04; 0.25). Silent pattern was directly associated with maternal education (&amp;#946; = 0.09; 95% CI = 0.03; 0.15), being overweight (&amp;#946; = 0.17; 95% CI = 0.06; 0.28), and female gender (&amp;#946; = 0.32; 95% CI= 0.22; 0.41). Conclusions: Three risk behavior patterns were identified and the associated factors were socioeconomic status, age, and female gender (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferreira, Márcia Gonçalves</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sena, Edilayane de Meneses Sousa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodrigues, Paulo Rogério Melo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fiuza, Rosemeyre França de Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muraro, Ana Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción/objetivo: la participación simultánea en los comportamientos de riesgo para las enfermedades no transmisibles (ENT) podría ejercer un efecto sinérgico sobre la salud de los adolescentes. El propósito del estudio fue identificar patrones de comportamiento de riesgo para las ENT en adolescentes y analizar factores asociados. Métodos: se realizó un estudio transversal entre 2009-2011, con 1.716 participantes de entre 10 y 17 años, de un estudio de cohorte en la Región Centro-Oeste, Brasil. Se recogieron las características demográficas, económicas, antropométricas y de estilo de vida. Los comportamientos de riesgo evaluados fueron el consumo de alcohol, la experimentación con el tabaco, la actividad física insuficiente, el comportamiento sedentario, omitir el desayuno y la baja calidad de la dieta. El análisis de componentes principales se utilizó para identificar patrones de comportamientos de riesgo y el análisis de regresión lineal múltiple para cuantificar la asociación entre las variables independientes y los patrones de comportamiento de riesgo. Resultados: Se identificaron tres patrones de comportamientos de riesgo: «drogas legales», «dieta y pantallas» y «omisión». Después del ajuste, el patrón de drogas legales mostró asociación directa con la edad (&amp;#946; = 0,13; IC del 95% = 0,09; 0,16) e inverso con la educación materna (&amp;#946; = -0,07; IC del 95% = -0,14; -0,01). El patrón de dieta y pantallas se asoció directamente con el sexo femenino (&amp;#946; = 0,14; IC del 95% = 0,04; 0,23), la edad (&amp;#946; = 0,11; IC del 95% = 0,08; 0,14) y la clase económica (&amp;#946; = 0,15; IC del 95% = 0,04; 0,25). El patrón de omisión se relacionó directamente con la educación materna (&amp;#946; = 0,09; IC del 95% = 0,03; 0,15), el sobrepeso (&amp;#946; = 0,17; IC del 95% = 0,06; 0,28) y el sexo femenino (&amp;#946; = 0,32; IC del 95% = 0,22; 0,41). Conclusiones: se identificaron tres patrones de comportamiento de riesgo y los factores asociados fueron el nivel socioeconómico, la edad y el sexo femenino (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;34(4): 914-922, jul.-ago. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165355</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patrones de comportamiento de riesgo para enfermedades crónicas y factores asociados entre adolescentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52508</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30863^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
