<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055844</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1780</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Alcoholism and anxiety: animal models</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Animal models for the study of alcoholism has    been developed during the last years. These models contribute in revealing the mechanisms    involved in this pathology. A synthesis of the main models used with rodents is presented    along with studies that show the complex links between anxiety and alcoholism. The    results indicate that alcohol acts as anxiolytic during early stages of consumption and as    an anxiogenic agent when absent after chronic or acute doses, that the forced administration    of ethanol provokes anxiolytic effects, and that the application of stressors alters the voluntary    consumption of alcohol. There are few experiments that tested the relationship between    alcoholism and frustration, a state considered equal to physical pain and to learned fear.    The first results on the later subject obtained by the authors are described</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mustaca, Alba E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kamenetzky, Giselle V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se han desarrollado modelos animales para el estudio del alcoholismo que permiten establecer    los mecanismos involucrados en esta patología. Se presenta una síntesis de los    principales modelos usados con roedores y las investigaciones que dan cuenta de las relaciones    complejas que existen entre ansiedad y alcoholismo. Los resultados indican que el    alcohol actúa como ansiolítico al comienzo del consumo y como ansiogénico con la privación    del mismo después de su administración aguda o crónica; que la administración    forzada de etanol provoca efectos ansiolíticos, y que la aplicación de estresores altera el    consumo voluntario de alcohol. Hay escasos estudios que hayan evaluado las relaciones    entre alcoholismo y frustración, un estado que se considera análogo al dolor físico o al    miedo aprendido. Se describen los primeros resultados obtenidos por los autores sobre ese    tema</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int. j. psychol. psychol. ther. (Ed. impr.);6(3): 343-364, 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055844</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alcoholismo y ansiedad: modelos animales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4255</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12752</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d431^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14543^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
