<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108171</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Physical activity and metabolic syndrome: Citius-Altius-Fortius</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Metabolic syndrome (MS) is a term that has been used in the last decades to define a group of risk factors that include: visceral obesity, arterial hypertension, hyperglycemia and atherogenic dyslipidemia, which predispose the individual to cardiovascular disease (CVD) and type 2 diabetes mellitus (DM2). Physical activity has been a fundamental element to understand MS and its etiology, given the fact that sedentarism is associated with weight gain and increased abdominal fat, which then predisposes the individual to a pro-inflammatory adiposopathy with insulin resistance, and the manifestation of the MS phenotype. The beneficial effects of exercise on the human body are of sufficient merit to evaluate, plan and apply intervention programs that lower the risk for DM2 and CVD. The following review analyzes the concept, molecular basis, and clinical evidence for exercise as a primary tool in endocrine and metabolic disorders(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aguirre-Urdaneta, Miguel A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojas-Quintero, Joselyn J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lima-Martínez, Marcos M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome metabólico (SM), es un término empleado en los últimos años para designar un grupo de factores de riesgo que incluyen obesidad visceral, hipertensión arterial, hiperglucemia y dislipidemia aterogénica, los cuales predisponen al individuo a desarrollar enfermedad cardiovascular (ECV) y diabetes mellitus tipo 2 (DM2). La actividad física ha sido parte fundamental para entender el SM y su etiología, ya que el sedentarismo se asocia con ganancia de peso y aumento de grasa visceral, lo cual predispone al individuo a una adipocitopatía proinflamatoria con resistencia insulínica y aparición del fenotipo característico del SM. Los efectos beneficiosos que el ejercicio ejerce sobre el cuerpo humano justifican la evaluación, planificación y aplicación de programas de intervención que disminuyan el riesgo de DM2 y ECV. La siguiente revisión analiza los conceptos, bases moleculares y evidencia clínica del ejercicio como abordaje primordial en los trastornos endocrino-metabólicos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;28(6): 123-130, nov.-dic. 2012. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108171</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actividad física y síndrome metabólico: Citius-Altius-Fortius</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8836^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
