<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039353</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Antibiotic prescription quality at an hospital emergency service</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and aim: Many patients receive an antibiotic prescription at hospital emergency departments. It could be considered adequate if it is effective against an appropiate bacteria spectrum and the dosage prescripted is correct. The aim was to evaluate the antibiotic prescriptions quality at an hospital emergency department. Method: Restrospective study of patients attended because an infectious disease at an emergency department during a 12 days period analyzing the antibiotic prescrition quality. Results: One hundred eighty nine patients were included (48 ± 23 years; 52% women). More frequent diseases attended were respiratory infections (58 patients 31%), urinary tract infections (33 patients, 17%) and gastroenteritis (22 pacientes, 12%). Most frequent precribed antibiotic was amoxicillin with clavulanic acid (54%). In 82 cases (43%) prescription was considered incorrect. More frequent reason were having a disease that does not need antibiotics (40%), excesive dosage (27%), treatment period unaproppritate prologed (26%), short dosage (10%) and wrong antibiotic selection (5%). Conclusions: A huge proportion of patients attended at an hospital emergency departement received an inadequate antibiotic treatment. Some important measures should be undertaken in order to improve the antibiotic presciption quality</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramos Martínez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcos García, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo Corbella, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cornide Santos, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Un número elevado de pacientes atendidos en los servicios de urgencia hospitalarios recibe un tratamiento antimicrobiano. Una cobertura bacteriana adecuada y posología correcta son características relevantes de la prescripción antibiótica. El objetivo fue evaluar la calidad en la prescripción antibiótica en un servicio de urgencia hospitalario. Método: Estudio retrospectivo de los pacientes atendidos en un servicio de urgencia por patología infecciosa durante 12 días examinando la calidad del tratamiento antibiótico prescrito. Resultados: Se incluyeron 189 pacientes (48 ± 23 años; 52% mujeres). Las enfermedades más frecuentes fueron infección respiratoria (58 pacientes 31%), infección del tracto urinario (33 pacientes, 17%) y gastroenteritis aguda (22 pacientes, 12%). El antibiótico prescrito con más frecuencia fue amoxicilina/clavulánico (54%). En 82 casos (43%) hubo una prescripción antibiótica incorrecta. Los motivos más frecuentes fueron ausencia de indicación de tratamiento antibiótico (40%), dosificación excesiva (27%), período de tratamiento inadecuadamente prolongado (26%), dosificación insuficiente (10%) y antibiótico distinto del apropiado (5%). Conclusiones: Una proporción muy elevada de pacientes atendidos en un servicio de urgencias recibieron un tratamiento antibiótico incorrecto. Deberían establecerse medidas para mejorar la calidad de la prescripción antibiótica</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;22(6): 266-270, jun. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039353</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de la prescripción de antibióticos en un servicio de urgencia hospitalario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22164^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d673^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
