<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82123</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">You have jaundice. What did you eat?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) is an enzyme present in red blood cells. Most people who have this enzyme deficiency have been asymptomatic throughout their life. However, when a patient comes into contact with one of the triggering factors (beans, some antibiotics, infections), they may present with severe hemolytic anemia that debuts with jaundice, asthenia and coluria. The deficiency of this enzyme is hereditary and is linked to the X chromosome. It is transmitted by mothers to half of their sons. The daughters who receive the gene may be affected or be carriers, so that genetic counseling is important (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sabaté-Cintas, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilà-Moneny, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pablos-Herrero, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fabra-Noguera, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giménez-Jiménez, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La glucosa-6-fosfato deshidrogenasa (G6PD) es una enzima presente en los glóbulos rojos. La mayoría de las personas que presentan déficit de esta enzima se encontraran asintomáticas a lo largo de toda la vida. Pero si el paciente entra en contacto con alguno de los factores desencadenantes (habas, algunos antibióticos, infecciones) puede presentar una anemia hemolítica severa que debutará con icteria, astenia y coluria. El déficit de esta enzima es hereditario ligado al cromosoma X, así pues es transmitida por las madres portadoras a la mitad de sus hijos varones, las hijas que reciben el gen pueden verse afectadas o ser portadoras, siendo importante el consejo genético. Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) is an enzyme present in red blood cells. Most people who have this enzyme deficiency were asymptomatic throughout life. But if a patient comes into contact with one of the triggers (beans, some antibiotics, infections) may present a severe hemolytic anemia with icteria debut, asthenia and coluria. The deficit of this enzyme is linked to hereditary X chromosome, so it is transmitted by mothers to half their sons, daughters who receive the gene may be affected or be carriers,being the important genetic counseling (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);36(8): 477-479, oct. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82123</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estás ictérico, ¿qué has comido?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7734^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5339^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d758^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5339^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d758^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5339^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5339^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7734^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7734^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
