<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137330</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: to review the pharmacologic characters of ketamine, its analgesic properties and its application on cancer pain. Matherial and methods: a review till October 2009 using the key words: ketamine, pain, neoplasm, palliative care. Potencial sources provided by bibliographic references in reviewed articles were used, as well as searches on line in Google and recognized texts of Anaesthesia. Results: ketamine is a dissociative anaesthetic with analgesic effect at sub-anaesthetic doses, where it has an antagonism effect to central sensibilitation and anti-tolerance effect to opioids. These properties make ketamine a useful treatment for refractory cancer pain. Nevertheless, it is not free of side effects being the psychotomimetic the most frequent ones. It has also been described its use as a sedative in oncologic patients with good results. Conclusions: although the beneficial ketamina's properties in the management of refractory pain, there is not yet enough evidence to confirm those characteristics. Thus, more randomized clinical trials are needed. After the review done, some recommendations are given for the use of ketamine as a co-analgesic in the treatment of difficult pain control in advanced cancer patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Porta-Sales, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jové-Casulleras, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casals-Merchán, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Barboteo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo-Burdalo, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: ofrecer una revisión de las características farmacológicas de la ketamina, sus propiedades analgésicas y su aplicación en el manejo del dolor oncológico. Material y métodos: revisión de la literatura hasta octubre de 2009 utilizando las palabras clave: ketamina, dolor, neoplasia, cuidados paliativos. Asimismo, se han utilizado posibles fuentes bibliográficas suministradas en las referencias de los artículos, búsquedas vía on-line a través de Google y el uso de textos reconocidos de anestesia general. Resultados: la ketamina es un anestésico disociativo con efecto analgésico a dosis subanestésicas, teniendo como peculiaridades una acción antagonista sobre la sensibilización central y la disminución de la tolerancia del uso crónico de los opioides. Estas propiedades hacen que sea un fármaco co-analgésico útil en el dolor oncológico refractario, Sin embargo no está libre de efectos secundarios, siendo los psicomiméticos los más frecuentes, También se ha descrito su uso para la sedación del paciente oncológico con buenos resultados. Conclusiones: a pesar las propiedades beneficiosas de la ketamina en el manejo del dolor refractario, aún no existe la suficiente evidencia científica para confirmadas, siendo necesarios más ensayos clínicos randomizados bien diseñados. Tras la revisión realizada se proponen unas recomendaciones para su uso como co-analgésico en el tratamiento del dolor de difícil control en el paciente con cáncer avanzado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;17(4): 241-250, jul.-ago. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137330</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ketamina en el tratamiento del dolor oncológico: revisión de farmacocinética, farmacodinámica, interacciones medicamentosas y recomendaciones de uso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d714^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7815^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10334^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4409</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
