<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92313</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Observational cross-sectional study in primary care and hospital care of the clinical profile of non-controlled type 2 diabetes mellitus patients in initial treatment phase (EUPHORIA study)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: There is not enough evidence of the level of glycaemic control when treatment was initiated with metformin, since the diagnosis of DM2 was established. Objective: 1) To calculate the prevalence of non-controlled (HbA1c &gt; 7%) type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) in clinical practice in patients on metformin only; 2) to describe the clinical profile of non-controlled T2DM patient on metformin treatment, to determine the differences between Primary Care (PC) and Hospital Care (HC), the evaluation of cardiovascular risk (CVR) and medication adherence. Material and methods: Observational, cross-sectional, two phase (A and B), multicentre and national study. In phase A, the percentage of visits made in one day by non-controlled DM2 patients on metformin treatment was evaluated. In phase B, which included patients with inadequate glycaemic control, demographic and clinical data, CVR factors (CVRF) and medication adherence, were determined. Results: A total of 238 physicians from hospitals and 305 physicians from primary care participated in the study. In phase A, 1,169 T2DM patients on metformin were included, among whom 53.9%, from PC, and 65.3% from HC, did not have glycaemic control. A total of 1,742 patients were included in phase B: 55.0% from PC and 54.3% from HC were male, with a mean age of 62.5 years in PC and 60.7 years in HC. There was a high prevalence of CVRF in PC and HC (89.3% vs 90.0% with metabolic syndrome, 88.2% vs 88.0% with overweight or obesity, 95.1% vs 94.0% dyslipaemia, 65.1% vs 64.2% hypertension, 59.7% vs 67.4% sedentary, and 14.2% vs 13.3% were smokers). A total of 72.9% of patients in PC and 62.8% in HC were non-compliers with pharmacological treatment. Conclusions: The proportion of non-controlled T2DM patients, on monotherapy with metformin, is high and they showed a high number of CVRF(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gambús, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Font, Beatriu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franch-Nadal, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: No existe suficiente evidencia del grado de control glucémico cuando se inicia tratamiento con metformina, desde que se establece el diagnóstico de diabetes mellitus tipo 2 (DM2). Objetivos: a) Determinar la prevalencia de DM2 no controlada (hemoglobina glucosilada &amp;#8805; 7%), en pacientes en monoterapia con metformina en la práctica clínica habitual, y b) describir el perfil clínico del paciente con DM2 no controlado en monoterapia con metformina, estableciendo las diferencias entre atención primaria (AP) y hospitalaria (AH), evaluación del riesgo cardiovascular (RCV) y cumplimiento terapéutico. Material y métodos: Estudio observacional, transversal, en dos fases (A y B), multicéntrico y nacional. En la fase A se evaluó el porcentaje de pacientes con DM2 no controlados en monoterapia con metformina visitados durante un día. En la fase B se incluyó a los pacientes con inadecuado control glucémico y se determinaron los datos demográficos, clínicos, factores de RCV y cumplimiento terapéutico. Resultados: Participaron 238 médicos de AH y 305 de AP. En la fase A se incluyó a 1.169 pacientes en monoterapia con metformina, de los que el 53,9 y el 65,3% en AP y en AH, respectivamente, no mostraban adecuado control glucémico. En la fase B se incluyó a 1.742 pacientes con control glucémico insuficiente, observándose que el 55,0% en AP y 54,3% AH eran varones, con una edad media de 62,5 años en AP y 60,7 años en AH y alta prevalencia de FRCV tanto en AP como en AH (el 89,3 frente al 90,0% síndrome metabólico; el 88,2 frente al 88,0% sobrepeso/obesidad; el 95,1 frente al 94,0% dislipemia; el 65,1 frente al 64,2% hipertensión; el 59,7 frente al 67,4% sedentarismo, y el 14,2 frente al 13,3% eran fumadores). El 72,9% de pacientes de AP y 62,8% de AH no cumplían el tratamiento farmacológico. Conclusiones: La proporción de pacientes con DM2 en monoterapia con metformina no controlados es elevada y presentan un elevado número de FRCV asociados(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;27(3): 69-77, mayo-jun. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92313</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio observacional transversal en consultas de atención primaria y atención hospitalaria del perfil clínico del paciente con diabetes mellitus tipo 2 no controlado en fase inicial de tratamiento (estudio EUPHORIA)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
