<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131736</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fluoride content of bottled natural mineral waters in Spain and prevention of dental caries</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: The aim of the study was to determine the concentration of fluoride in natural mineral waters marketed in Spain in order to prevent tooth decay without the risk of causing dental fluorosis Design: Descriptive and cross-sectional study during 2012. Location: Natural mineral waters marketed in Spain. Participants: Three bottles with different bottling dates of 109 natural mineral waters (97 Spanish and 12 imported brands). Main measures: Determination of fluoride by ion chromatography Results: Median fluoride concentrations of the natural mineral waters bottled in Spain was 0.22 (range 0.00-4.16; interquartile range:0.37). Most samples (61 brands, 62%) contained less than 0.3 mg/L. There are 19 Spanish brands with more than 0.6 mg/L. The median level in imported brands was 0.35 (range 0.10-1.21; interquartile range: 0.23). Only 28 of the 109 brands examined (25.6%) specified the fluoride content on the label. Good correlation was observed between the concentrations indicated and those determined. Conclusions: Fluoride concentrations in natural mineral waters showed high variation. Given the growing consumption of natural mineral waters in Spain, this type of information is important to make proper use of fluoride in the primary prevention of dental caries (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Maraver, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vitoria, Isidro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almerich-Silla, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armijo, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El propósito del estudio es conocer la concentración en flúor de las aguas minerales naturales comercializadas en España para poder prevenir la caries dental sin el riesgo de causar fluorosis dental. Diseño: Estudio descriptivo y transversal a lo largo de 2012.  Emplazamiento: Aguas minerales naturales comercializadas en España. Participantes: Tres muestras con fechas distintas de embotellado de 109 marcas de aguas minerales naturales (97 marcas españolas y 12 aguas importadas). Medición principal: Determinación analítica por cromatografía iónica del contenido en fluoruro en el agua. Resultados: La concentración mediana de fluoruro de las aguas minerales naturales españolas es de 0,22 (rango 0,00-4,16; rango intercuartil: 0,37). La gran mayoría (61 marcas, 62%) contenían menos de 0,30 mg/L. Hay 19 marcas que contienen más de 0,6 mg/L. Hay 19 marcas españolas que contienen más de 0,6 mg/L. En las 12 aguas minerales importadas, la mediana es de 0,35 (rango 0,10-1,21; rango intercuartil: 0,23). Sólo en 28 de las 109 marcas examinadas (25,6%) se especificaba el contenido de fluoruro en la etiqueta. Se observa una buena correlación entre las concentraciones indicadas y los valores analizados. Conclusiones: Las concentraciones de fluoruro en las aguas minerales naturales comercializadas en España muestran una gran variabilidad. Dado el creciente consumo de las aguas minerales naturales en España, este tipo de información es de suma importancia para poder hacer una correcta utilización de flúor en la prevención primaria de la caries dental (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;47(1): 15-24, ene. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131736</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fluoruro en aguas minerales naturales envasadas en España y prevención de la caries dental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9088^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9088^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31463^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3745^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3745^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9088^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9088^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2160^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5593^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5593^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2160^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5590^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
