<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040439</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nursing, simply complicated</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">From a very young age, we played doctors and nurses. Back then, society was positive that a nursing profession existed. Now, is society's vision adequate? Evidently not. But, Why does this distortion exist? Fundamentally this occurs because the professionals themselves do not have a clear identity regarding their profession. And Why is this? Because the education transmitted has important lacks, the sanitary system dampens innovation and creativity, there are no appropriate leaders, lobbies transform into "wolves", and neither do we have a tradition which facilitates association and cooperation amongst professionals. These are some of the factors which the author develops in this deep, brave analysis about the reality of the nursing profession in order to arrive at the conclusion that we must have clear in our minds what nursing power is, a power which interacts with the community, and that this is important not only as a power in itself but rather as a means to increase the intrinsic value of nursing, none other than providing care</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Riera, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">De bien pequeños ya jugamos a ser enfermeras. Luego la sociedad sí tiene claro que existe la profesión enfermera. Ahora, ¿su visión es la adecuada? Evidentemente, no. Pero, ¿a qué se debe esta distorsión? Fundamental-mente, a que los propios profesionales no tienen una identidad clara al respecto. Y ¿por qué? Porque la enseñanza transmitida tiene carencias importantes, el sistema sanitario fagocita la innovación y la creatividad, no existen líderes apropiados, los lobbies se transforman en «lobos», y tampoco tenemos una tradición asociativa y de cooperación. Éstos son algunos de los elementos que el autor desarrolla en este profundo y valiente análisis sobre la realidad enfermera para llegar a concluir que debemos tener claro cuál es el poder enfermero, aquel que interactúa con la comunidad, y que éste es importante no como poder en sí mismo, sino para alcanzar el bien intrínseco de enfermería, que no es otro que la prestación de cuidados</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;28(4): 255-264, abr. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040439</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermería, sencillamente complicado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12960^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9907</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
