<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152370</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Social skills training for people with schizophrenia: what do we train?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper gives a broad definition of the characteristics and incidence for schizophrenia, and introduces the various deficits in social skills and social function faced by patients with this disorder. The role of Social Skills Training (SST), which can be used to improve some of these deficiencies in social skills, social function, cognition and competence, including the history and efficacy of such training, is addressed. An outline is given of the Brief Cognitive-Behavioural SST for schizophrenia patients, designed by our clinical research group (University of Barcelona and General Hospital of Igualada, Spain), along with the parameters of the study, risk factors for certain patients and results. We then indicate future directions focusing on the sue of virtual reality as a modern technology to enhance treatment and highlighting potential areas for further study (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rus calafell, Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribas Sabaté, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Maldonado, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lemos Giráldez, Serafín</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo proporciona una definición amplia sobre las características y la incidencia de la esquizofrenia y presenta los distintos déficit en habilidades sociales y en funcionamiento social que sufren los pacientes con este trastorno. Se aborda el papel del entrenamiento en habilidades sociales (EHS), que puede utilizarse para mejorar algunas de estas deficiencias en habilidades sociales, en el funcionamiento social, en las cogniciones y en la competencia, incluyendo la historia y la eficacia de dicho entrenamiento. Se expone un esquema del &#147;EHS cognitivo conductual breve&#148; para pacientes con esquizofrenia desarrollado por nuestro grupo clínico de investigación (Universidad de Barcelona y Hospital General de Igualada, España), junto con los parámetros del estudio, los factores de riesgo para ciertos pacientes y los resultados. Finalmente, presentamos las perspectivas futuras, centrándonos en el uso de la realidad virtual como una tecnología moderna para mejorar el tratamiento y resaltar áreas potenciales para estudios futuros (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;22(3): 461-477, 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152370</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Entrenamiento en habilidades sociales para personas con esquizofrenia: ¿Qué entrenamos?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12030^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12030^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55704</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12946</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3102^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29986^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
