<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152300</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Foster care children in treatment: what are they like? Understanding in order to help</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study features a comparison of the the social, demographic and clinical characteristics of two subgroups within a clinical population: one group of children in residential care (case group) versus another group of children living in a family environment (control group). We observed a more severe clinical profile in the case group. Anxiety and adjustment disorders were the most prevalent diagnosis in both groups, and were present in a third of all patients. Attachment disorder was highly prevalent in the case group, while virtually non-existent in the control group. This was the most significant difference between the two groups (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín Alonso, Sonsoles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Fraile, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Pinar, Dina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este trabajo se comparan, dentro de una población clínica, las características sociales, demográficas y clínicas de dos subgrupos, uno de menores en acogimiento residencial (grupo caso) y otro que reside en un entorno familiar (grupo control). Encontramos un perfil de mayor gravedad clínica en el grupo caso. Los trastornos neuróticos y reacciones de estrés, diagnosticados en un tercio de los pacientes, son los que alcanzan la mayor prevalencia en ambos grupos. El trastorno de la vinculación, también muy presente en el grupo caso, pero prácticamente inexistente en el de control, es el que provoca la discrepancia de mayor significación entre ambos grupos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(26): 29-40, nov. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152300</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Cómo son los niños que atendemos y que residen en un centro de infancia? Conocer para ayudar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2721^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5715^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5715^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28462</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33204^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33204^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9686^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9686^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9686^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5715^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36411</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
