<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158735</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Seroprevalence of varicella-zoster virus antibodies after the recent introduction of the universal childhood immunisation schedule in the Community of Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: In November 2006, the Community of Madrid included the chickenpox vaccine into the immunisation schedule for children from 15 months of age. This was withdrawn in January 2014. Seroprevalence of antibodies to the virus is estimated after the first 2-3 years from the inclusion of the vaccine, and as well as its evolution since 1999. Material and method: A cross-sectional study was conducted on the target population consisting of residents in the Community of Madrid between 2 and 60 years of age. Measurement of IgG antibodies was performed using an ELISA technique. Seroprevalence was estimated according to sociodemographic characteristics using multiple logistic regressions. The results are compared with previous surveys. Also, the seroprevalence and geometric mean of the antibody according immunisation status and history of the disease are presented. The confidence level used is 95%. Results: A total of 4,378 subjects were included, with a response rate of 69%. The estimated seroprevalence was 95.3% (95% CI: 94.6% - 95.9%). Over 90% of children from the age of 10 have antibodies. The seroprevalence was higher in people with less education. The seroprevalence of immunity vaccine exceeds 90% in the first year after vaccination, but in the second year decreased to 82.6% (95% CI 56.0 - 94.7). Significant differences, attributable to universal vaccination, were found compared to previous surveys. Discussion: Continued surveillance is needed in order to assess the impact of the withdrawal of the recommendation to vaccinate at 15 months (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz Moreno, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Rodríguez, M Angeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barranco Ordóñez, Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Comas, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordobás Gavín, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Blázquez, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: En la Comunidad de Madrid se incluyó la vacuna frente a varicela en el calendario infantil en noviembre del 2006 a los 15 meses de edad. Dicha recomendación se retiró en enero del 2014. Se estima la seroprevalencia de anticuerpos frente al virus tras los 2-3 primeros años desde la inclusión de la vacuna y su evolución desde 1999. Material y método: Estudio descriptivo transversal. La población diana son los residentes en la Comunidad de Madrid entre 2 y 60 años. La medición de anticuerpos IgG se realizó mediante técnicas de ELISA. Se estima la seroprevalencia según características sociodemográficas mediante regresión logística múltiple. Los resultados se comparan con encuestas previas. Asimismo, se presentan la seroprevalencia y la media geométrica de anticuerpos según el estado vacunal y los antecedentes de la enfermedad. El nivel de confianza utilizado es del 95%. Resultados: Participaron 4.378 sujetos, con una tasa de respuesta del 69%. La seroprevalencia estimada es del 95,3% (IC del 95%, 94,6%-95,9%). Más del 90% de los niños a partir de los 10 años de edad presentan anticuerpos. La seroprevalencia fue mayor en personas con menor nivel educativo. La seroprevalencia de inmunidad vacunal supera el 90% en el primer año tras la vacunación pero en el segundo año desciende hasta el 82,6% (IC del 95%, 56,0-94,7). Se encontraron diferencias significativas con las encuestas anteriores atribuibles a la vacunación universal. Discusión: Es necesario continuar la vigilancia epidemiológica para valorar el impacto de la retirada de la recomendación de vacunar a los 15 meses de edad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;34(10): 633-638, dic. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158735</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seroprevalencia de anticuerpos frente al virus de la varicela zóster tras la introducción reciente de la vacunación infantil universal en la Comunidad de Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6721^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31925^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24874</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50259</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52406^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
