<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89039</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical symptoms following surgery for lumbar disc herniatiron: prophylaxis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION. The symptomatic appearance of post-operative fibrosis following surgery for lumbar disc herniation is bad news for both the patient and the surgeon. A method of preventing this undesired outcome would be of great utility (between  2 and 18% of the patients suffer from it after said surgery). Here we report one approach to achieving this outcome, through the development of a physical barrier: a matrix of collagen, with three main attributes: A) Hemostatic function B) Physical barrier due to its porosity C) Regenerating function through the matrix. METHODS. A retrospective investigation was made of 500 patients whom had undergone spinal surgery with canal approach;  250 took part in the control group and 250 took part in the collagen Dural matrix group. Prior to wound closure, the matrix was placed both in the area of the bone defect and in the area of the affected nerve root. Thereby creating a physical barrier that prevents fibrotic entrapment of the nerve root. Further, in the event of CSF leakage (fistula) the matrix accomplished complete closure of the dural defect through the process of fibroblast migration and the formation of a new connective tissue  sheet continuous with the existing dura. There was a minimum follow-up of Two year that included a series of clinical and radiological exams DISCUSSION. The progress of patients treated with DuraGen showed a better result since there was no symptomatology due to fibrosis. Further, in the event of fistula, the fistula was closed. When there was a need for new surgery it was due to other causes: relapse, bone fragment or infection. The matrix allowed an easy dissection. CONCLUSION. The collagen matrix proved its effectiveness as a physical barrier preventing root entrapment and hence its  symptomatology. In addition, it proved to be a regenerator of dura preventing the occurrence of fistulae. RESULTS. From all the control group patients, 8% showed secondary symptomatology of fibrosis that required treatment through: new surgery (lumbar fixation: arthrodesis) or placement of a neurostimulator. There were no patients with symptomatology due to fibrosis in the collagen dural matrix group (2% vs. 8%) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arrotegui, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">INTRODUCCIÓN. La presencia de sintomatología secundaria a la fibrosis postquirúrgica tras la cirugía de la Hernia de disco y Estenosis de canal es una de las peores noticias tanto para el paciente como para el cirujano. Se hace necesario una prevención de dicha sintomatología (entre el 2 y el 18% de los pacientes la presentan tras dicha cirugía), mediante el desarrollo de una barrera física: matriz de colágeno, con una tripe accion A) Función de Hemostasia B) barrera física por la porosidad C) función regeneradora por la matriz.  MATERIAL Y METODOS. Se ha realizado un estudio clinico en un total de 500 pacientes intervenidos de Cirugia de raquis con abordaje del Canal; 250 pertenecian al grupo control , 250 al grupo matriz de Colágeno. Tras la cirugía se coloco La matriz tanto en la zona del defecto oseo , como en la zona de revision de la raíz: de esta manera se crea una barrera física que impide  al fibroblasto del músculo poder atrapar a la raíz tras la cicatrizacion del músculo .ademas en caso de fistula de LCR la matriz favoce el paso de fibroblastos entre la dos laminas de la dura a traves de la matriz y se produce un sellado completo del orificio. El seguimiento minimo fue de dos años y se realizaron controles clinicos y radiológicos de forma seriada.  RESULTADOS. Del total de pacientes del grupo control ; un 8% presentaron sintomatología secundaria a fibrosis que requiero tratamiento mediante: nueva cirugía (Fijación Lumbar: artrodesis) o colocación de un neuroestimulador . En el grupo D no se presentaron pacientes con sintomatonología quirúrgica por fibrosis, 2% vs 8%. DISCUSIÓN. La evolucion de los pacientes tratados con la matriz obtuvieron un mejor resultado al no presentar sintomatología  por fibrosis , ademas en caso de fistula esta quedo sellada. En los casos en los que hubo que reoperar por otros factores: recidiva , fragmento oseo o infeccion el duragen permitio una disección sin dificultad . CONCLUSION. La matriz de colágeno demostro su eficacia como barrera física impidiendo el atrapamiento de raíz y por ende su sintomatología ademas de ser un regenerador de dura impidiendo la esistencia de fistulas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;13(3): 101-105, jul.-sept. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89039</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impotencia funcional y/o ciatalgia tras cirugía de la hernia discal lumbar: profilaxis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7568^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33888</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29340^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31505^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5538^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
