<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046999</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Follicular adenomatoid odontogenic tumor: immunohistochemical study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Adenomatoid odontogenic tumor (AOT) is an uncommon benign odontogenic lesion that affects young patients, with female predominance, mainly in second decade, showing a radiolucent unilocular image associated with an unerupted tooth, usually a canine.In spite of previous and confusing denominations, such as adenoameloblastoma or adenomatoid ameloblastic tumor, AOT is a benign tumor with a very low rate of recurrence, that show a peculiar morphological picture (basaloid appearance with glandular-like structures, calcifying areas, and amiloid-like material) that allow its histopathological recognition.We present a clinicopathological analysis of a case of follicular AOT affecting the mandible in a 9 years-old female patient associated with unerupted lower left canine. Immunohistochemical study showed some data previously unrecognised.All cellular types that composed AOT showed nuclear positivity for p63 indicating a basal characterization in the different cellular components. According to its benign character and low potential for recurrence, AOT revealed a scant proliferative activity (2-3% nuclei showed Ki-67 positivity) limited to some epithelial nodules (AE1-3 +) of fusiform appearance. Absence of reactivity for hormonal receptors (RE and RPg) excluded a possible hormonodependence in AOT that could explain the observed female predominance</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Artes Martinez, María Jose</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vera Sirera, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vera Sempere, Francisco José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonet Marco, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tumor odontogénico adenomatoide (TOA) es una infrecuente lesión odontogénica benigna, que aparece en pacientesjóvenes, generalmente mujeres en la segunda década de la vida, a menudo como una lesión radiolúcida de aspecto quístico unilocular, en asociación a un diente, usualmente canino, no erupcionado.A pesar de haberse denominado también adenoameloblastoma o tumor ameloblástico adenomatoide, el TOA es una lesión benigna con una muy baja tendencia a la recidiva, mostrando una morfología muy peculiar (apariencia basaloide con estructuras glanduliformes, calcificaciones esferulares, presencia de material amiloide) que facilitan su reconocimientohistológico. Se presenta un análisis clínico-patológico de un TOA de tipo folicular de maxilar inferior, en asociación a la inclusiónde un canino inferior izquierdo, en una paciente pediátrica de 9 años. El estudio inmunohistoquímico realizado muestra algunos datos previamente no referidos. A pesar de existir distintos tipos celulares en el TOA se observo una universal inmunorreactividad para p63, demostrando el carácter basal de los distintos elementos que lo constituyen. En concordancia con su benignidad y con su baja tasa de recidiva existe una escasa actividad proliferativa (2-3% de núcleos marcados por el antígeno Ki-67), estando la proliferación reducida a pequeños nódulos de células epiteliales (AE1-3 +) de núcleos elongados o fusiformes; de otra parte la mayor incidencia en pacientes de sexo femenino no puede ser explicada en base a la existencia de una hormonodependecia tumoral dada la ausencia de expresión de receptores hormonales (RE y RPg)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);11(4): E305-E308, jul. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046999</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumor odontogenico adenomatoide folicular: Estudio inmunohistoquimico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24235^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d244^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24273^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
