<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136410</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5274</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder: a model predicting of comorbidity with behavior disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper examines the co-morbidity profile of the Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) and Behavior Disorder (BD), exploring the pattern that predicts this psychopathological association. A sample of 90 ADHD subjects aged 6 to 16 is analysed. Using a differential methodology, ADHD+BD is compared with the absence of co-morbidity. ADHD was assessed according to DSM-IV standards and the co-morbidity by means of CSI. Intellectual profile (as measured by WISC-R), academic performance, the relational dimension, psychiatric antecedents and nucleus of coexistence were taken into account. Descriptive and exploratory statistics were used and a logistic regression was implemented. The differential profile implies that ADHD+BD subjects present a significantly higher deterioration in the relational dimension, academic performance and percentage of separated parents. The pattern predicting ADHD+BD includes the relational dimension, whereas ADHD + Conduct Disorder includes the relational dimension and separated parents (p &lt;.05) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Mateos, Juan Delgado</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Villalobos, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Pintado, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El estudio analiza el perfil de comorbilidad del Trastorno por Déficit de Atención con Hiperactividad (TDAH) y trastornos del comportamiento (TC), explorando el modelo que predice esta asociación psicopatológica. Metodología de investigación: Se analiza una muestra de 90 casos con TDAH (6-16 años). Mediante investigación diferencial se compara la agrupación TDAH+TC con la ausencia de esta comorbilidad. El caso de TDAH se valoró según criterios DSM-IV y la comorbilidad mediante el CSI. Se consideraron las variables perfil intelectual (WISC-R), resultados académicos, dimensión relacional, antecedentes psiquiátricos y núcleo de convivencia. Se utilizaron estadísticos descriptivos y exploratorios, implementando un procedimiento de regresión logística. Resultados: El perfil diferencial implica que los casos TDAH+TC presentan, significativamente, mayor deterioro en dimensión relacional, resultados académicos y proporción de padres separados. El modelo que predice TDAH+TC está formado por el factor relacional, mientras que en TDAH + Trastorno Disocial incluye factor relacional y padres separados (p&lt;0.05) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. salud;15(1): 9-31, ene.-abr. 2004. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136410</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastorno por déficit de atención con hiperactividad: un modelo predictor de comorbilidad con trastornos del comportamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33525^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2699^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28084</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4274^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8037^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52882^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
