<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155706</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-695X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Devic neuromyelitis optica</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Neuromyelitis optica (NMO) or Devic's disease is an autoimmune, inflammatory and demyelinating disorder of the central nervous system that affects mainly the optic nerve and the spinal cord. NMO was first considered a form of multiple sclerosis (MS). However, recent findings have led to the conclusion that NMO is a distinct disorder, presenting important immunopathological, clinical, prognostic and therapeutic differences from MS. The recent discovery and measurement of the anti-aquaporine-4 antibody (anti-AQP4 or NMO-IgG) has revived the scientific interest and has boosted research of new lines of treatment for NMO. We present the clinical case of a ten year-old boy who, after an accidental fall, presents bilateral knee pain, and pain in the upper and lower back, which at first is thought to be a contusion. However, after 48 hours it develops negatively, persisting the pain, loss of strength and lower limb paraesthesia, difficulty in sitting up, inability to walk, and urinary incontinence. Transverse myelitis is suspected and the patient is sent to the hospital emergency service, where after 24 hours he develops a right optic neuritis. Finally, a neuromyelitis optica or Devic's disease is diagnosed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aguilar-Shea, Antonio L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bravo-Lizcano, Ruth</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sierra-Santos, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil-Gulias, Lorraine</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La neuromieltis óptica (NMO) o enfermedad de Devic es un trastorno autoinmune, inflamatorio y desmielinizante del sistema nervioso central, que afecta principalmente al nervio óptico y la médula espinal. Considerada anteriormente como una variante de esclerosis múltiple (EM), hallazgos recientes han ayudado a concluir que la NMO es una entidad que presenta importantes diferencias inmunopatológicas, clínicas, de pronóstico y de respuesta al tratamiento, en comparación con la EM. El reciente descubrimiento y medición del anticuerpo antiacuaporina 4 (anti-AQP4 o también, NMO-IgG) ha reavivado el interés científico y activado la investigación de nuevas líneas de tratamiento de la NMO. Presentamos el caso clínico de un paciente varón de 10 años que acude a la consulta por presentar, tras una caída accidental, gonalgia bilateral, dorsalgia y lumbalgia que impresionan inicialmente de contusiones y que, sin embargo, tras 48 horas evolucionan negativamente con persistencia de dolor, pérdida de fuerza y parestesias en los miembros inferiores, dificultad para incorporarse, incapacidad para deambular e incontinencia urinaria. Ante la sospecha de mielitis transversa se deriva al paciente al servicio de urgencias hospitalario, donde desarrolla a las 24 horas de ingreso una neuritis óptica derecha; finalmente es diagnosticado de neuromielitis óptica o enfermedad de Devic (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. clín. med. fam;9(2): 114-118, jun. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155706</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neuromielitis óptica de Devic</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30952^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29486^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10481^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29486^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30952^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29486^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10481^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27729^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29510^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29486^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27729^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29594^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22562^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27729^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
