<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159845</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Historical evolution of body hygiene: from ancient to modern modern societies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The general aim of inquiry is to study the evolution of corporal hygiene holistically from ancient times to the present. As specific aims we considered: 1-to describe the health consequences of trends in corporal hygiene of modern societies; 2- to describe the role of modern nursing in corporal hygiene care. Methodology and sources: an integrative review was conducted in Medline / Pubmed, Scielo and Lilacs data and a documentation Reverse Search, obtaining a total of 30 jobs. Daily personal hygiene habits have changed considerably throughout history. In ancient Greece and Rome the bathroom acquired social expression and entertainment in addition to therapeutic, and its etymological root is derived from the Greek goddess of health &#145;Hygieia&#146;. In medieval times personal hygiene deserved only an aesthetic importance linking the disease with pobredumbre air, as in the Renaissance where the phantasmagoria around the bathroom also arises. In the nineteenth century, and advances in microbiology, the hygienist movement emerged also enriching hygiene as a concept. Currently developed societies achieve high levels of personal hygiene which recent research suggests that may be counterproductive to health, reconsidering what the best personal hygiene habits based on scientific evidence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez García, Carmen Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Martínez, Francisco José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Susarte, Ana María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo general del estudio es estudiar la evolución de la higiene corporal de forma holística desde la edad antigua a la actualidad. Como objetivos específicos nos planteamos: 1-describir las consecuencias para la salud de las tendencias en higiene corporal de las sociedades modernas; 2- describir el rol de la enfermería moderna en los cuidados higiénicos corporales. Metodología y fuentes: se realizó una revisión integradora en las bases de datos Medline/Pubmed, Scielo, y Lilacs y búsqueda inversa de documentación, obteniendo un total de 30 trabajos. Los hábitos cotidianos de higiene corporal han sufrido importantes variaciones a lo largo de la historia. En la antigua Grecia y Roma el baño adquiría expresión social y de ocio además de terapéutica, incluso su raíz etimológica deriva de la Diosa griega de la salud &#145;Hygieia&#146;. En la época medieval la higiene corporal sólo merecía una importancia estética relacionando la enfermedad con la pobredumbre del aire, al igual que en el renacimiento donde además surge la fantasmagoría en torno al baño. Con el siglo XIX y los avances en microbiología surge el movimiento higienista enriqueciendo además a la higiene como concepto. Actualmente las sociedades desarrolladas alcanzan elevados niveles de higiene corporal donde recientes investigaciones señalan que pueden ser contraproducentes para la salud, replanteándose cuáles son los mejores hábitos de higiene corporal basados en la evidencia científica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;20(46): 115-126, sept.-dic. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159845</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución histórica de la higiene corporal: desde la edad antigua a las sociedades modernas actuales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31040^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3489</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28450^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13304^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
