<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103173</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Detection of latent tuberculosis infection in peritoneal dialysis patients: new methods</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The risk for tuberculosis (TB) is increased in patients with chronic renal failure and dialysis. Tuberculin skin test (TST) is the classical diagnostic method for screening despite its low sensitivity. New methods based on interferon&#150;gamma have been developed. The aim of this study was to evaluate if Quantiferon® TB&#150;gold In Tube (QFT&#150;GIT) could be useful in the diagnosis of TB infection in patients on peritoneal dialysis (PD). Patients and methods: Fifty&#150;four patients on PD were included in the study. They were evaluated for latent tuberculosis with QFT&#150;GIT, TST and an assessment by an expert pulmonologist using patient's medical history and x&#150;rays. Agreement between test results was determined. Results: The prevalence of a positive TST was 29.6% for the first test and 31.5% for the second (booster effect). A positive chest x&#150;ray increased the rate of detection of patients with latent TB infection up to 42.6% and the expert physician's evaluation to 44.4%. The correlation between QFT&#150;GIT and TST was fair (ê=0.36; P=.006), as it was between TST and expert physician's evaluation (ê=0.257; P=.06). Conclusions: According to our experience QFT&#150;GIT represents an important advantage in the diagnosis of latent TB infection in chronic renal failure patients on PD. It may complement but not replace TST (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Robledo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodrigo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molinos, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agüero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palomar, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agüero, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias Guillén, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El riesgo de tuberculosis (TB) está aumentado en pacientes con insuficiencia renal crónica y en diálisis. La prueba de la tuberculina (PT) es el test de cribado clásico en estos pacientes, a pesar de su baja sensibilidad. En los últimos años se han desarrollado nuevos métodos diagnósticos que se basan en la producción de interferón gamma tras la estimulación con antígenos de M. tuberculosis. El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar si el Quantiferon® TB&#150;gold In Tube (QFT&#150;GIT) puede contribuir en el diagnóstico de la infección tuberculosa en pacientes en diálisis peritoneal (DP). Pacientes y métodos: Se incluyeron 54 pacientes en DP. Se valoró la posibilidad de infección tuberculosa latente mediante el QFT&#150;GIT, la PT y la valoración clinicorradiológica por parte de un neumólogo experto. Se estudiaron las concordancias entre los tests. Resultados: La prevalencia de un resultado positivo para el test de la tuberculina fue del 29,6% para el primer test y del 31,5% para el segundo (valorando el efecto booster). Una radiografía de tórax positiva aumentaba la detección de infección tuberculosa latente hasta un 42,6% y la del neumólogo hasta un 44,4%. El nivel de correlación entre el QFT&#150;GIT y la PT fue moderado (kappa = 0,36; p = 0,006), al igual que entre la PT y la valoración del neumólogo (kappa = 0,257, p = 0,06). Conclusiones: El QFT&#150;GIT aporta algunas ventajas en el diagnóstico de la infección tuberculosa en pacientes con insuficiencia renal crónica en DP, y puede complementar a la prueba de la tuberculina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;31(2): 169-173, abr. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103173</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Detección de la infección tuberculosa latente en pacientes en diálisis peritoneal: Nuevos métodos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53483^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29469^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22710^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
