<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154815</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Legal framework of the anesthesioiogist in a day case surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The legal framework anesthesiologist at Ambulatory Surgery, is gaining on importance in recent years, more and more professionals will become aware of the legal implications you may incur while performing our daily work. Analysis of court decisions in Spain shows that anesthesiology is a specialty with high compensatory amounts. It is very important that anesthesiologists know everything about standards of services and facilities where we do care work, just as we must know the rules of professional associations and scientific societies, and the laws of regional and state level that affect our work (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Puertas Domínguez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López del Castillo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morillas Sendin, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Abascal, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matute González, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El marco legal del anestesiólogo en Cirugía Mayor Ambulatoria está cobrando relativa importancia en los últimos años. Cada vez más los profesionales vamos tomando conciencia de las implicaciones legales en las que podemos incurrir al realizar nuestro trabajo diario. El análisis de sentencias judiciales en España demuestra que es una especialidad con altas cuantías indemnizatorias. Es muy importante que los anestesiólogos conozcamos todo lo relativo a las normas de los servicios y centros donde desarrollamos nuestra labor asistencial, de igual manera debemos conocer las normas de los colegios profesionales y de las sociedades científicas, y las leyes de ámbito regional y estatal que afectan a nuestro trabajo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;19(2): 64-70, abr.-jun. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154815</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Marco legal del anestesiólogo en la cirugía mayor ambulatoria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d787^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8062^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29004</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
