<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036619</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">D-dimer levels in venous thromboembolism</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Venous thromboembolism (VTE) is associated with substantial morbidityand mortality. The clinical signs and symptoms are unspecific, widely varying from asymptomatic to sudden death. The diagnostic algorithm of VTE is an evolving field, in which D-dimers (DD) determination has been used as one of the preferred screening tests. Clinical management studies are clarifying the role of DD in the diagnostic paradigm of VTE. Published reports support the use of plasma DD determination in patients with a low clinical probability of VTE. Patients with moderate or high clinical probability of VTE show a higher probability of false negative plasma DD values. This fact forces the clinician to use more complex diagnostic test in order to either confirm or exclude VTE.A variety of different qualitative and semi-quantifiable assays are available for plasma DD determination. There is a wide variation in performance and there are discrepancies in the comparability of the different assays. Therefore, in order to both appropriately incorporate plasma DD determination in the diagnostic strategies of VTE and to reduce unnecessary investigations, clinicians should ensure that they are familiar with the diagnostic performance of the assay used in their own institution allowing a safer and cost-effective procedure</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Monreal, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soto, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad tromboembólica venosa (ETV) posee una elevada morbimortalidad. La presentación clínica se caracteriza por ser inespecífica y variar en un amplio rango de posibilidades, desde asintomática a la muerte súbita. Estos hechos dificultan su manejo en la práctica clínica habitual y han llevado en los últimos años a la búsqueda de algoritmos que simplifiquen su diagnóstico. Con este propósito se ha incorporado la determinación plasmática de dímero-D (DD) como método de cribado de la ETV. La determinación plasmática de DD tiene su mayor aplicación en la valoración inicial de los pacientes con baja probabilidad clínica de presentar ETV. Un mayor número de falsos negativos de DD en pacientes con probabilidad clínica moderada o alta de presentar ETV obliga a exploraciones diagnósticas más complejas que confirmen o excluyan la enfermedad. Actualmente, hay una amplia variedad de métodos para la determinación de DD, tanto cuantitativos como semicuantitativos, pero los resultados obtenidos por las diferentes técnicas no son extrapolables. Por tanto, es aconsejable conocer el tipo y las características de la técnica disponible en cada  centro para incorporarla a la estrategia diagnóstica y reducir la realización de exploraciones innecesarias, manteniendo un elevado margen de seguridad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);124(19): 749-753, mayo 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036619</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad del dímero-D en la enfermedad tromboembólica venosa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14308^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22443^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14308^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
