<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91930</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Arterial embolizarion in splenic artery aneurysm</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Splenic artery aneurysms are rare and occur predominantly in women. Most of them are asymptomatic until rupture. We report a previously healthy 42 year-old woman who presented with non specific symptoms: dyspepsia and constipation. Laboratory tests were normal. Subsequent examinations (ultrasound and CT) showed a large aneurysm of the splenic artery without any sign of rupture. Endovascular treatment remained successfully performed using coil embolization. During a 12- months follow-up period, the patient was asymptomatic and no evidences of complications or splenic infarction were observed on CT scans (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Legaz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruíz-Tovar, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moya Forcén, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliver García, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calpena Rico, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armañanzas, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los aneurismas de la arteria esplénica son infrecuentes y ocurren predominantemente en mujeres. La mayoría son asintomáticos. Presentamos un caso clínico referente a una mujer 42 años con síntomas inespecíficos de dispepsia y estreñimiento.  En exámenes rutinarios (TC y ECO) se identificó un aneurisma de arteria esplénica distal de unos 2 cm. Se decidió tratamiento ndovascular con coils.Tras un año de seguimiento la paciente se encontraba asintomática sin complicaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;14(2): 83-85, abr.-jun. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91930</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Embolización arterial en aneurisma arteria esplénica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4695^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d794^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13540^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4478^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3267^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
