<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116551</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8799</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The exercise in the prevention and treatment of the diseases in elderly</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this part of the work the effects are exposed that the exercise exerts about the causing factors of the aging, and on the prevention and the rehabilitation of some illnesses like the cardiovascular ones, and those that influence on the atherosclerotic process among those that are included: the hyperlipidemia, the diabetes, the obesity and the hypertension. Affections so important are also included as the cancer, the osteoporosis and the gallstone. The functional decline of the old men is a fact of great transcendency, due to the difficulties that he/she originates to carry out the activities involved in the average life. The exercise is a good collaborator to attenuate these problems. Other facts included in this work are: the mechanisms for those that the exercise improves the health, the recommendations that the OMS contributes for its use for the adults and the effects that he/she takes place about the quality of the life. Lastly are exposed a series of proposals to stimulate the practice of the exercise in this group of people (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marcos Becerro, Juan Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En esta parte del trabajo se exponen los efectos que el ejercicio ejerce sobre los factores causantes del envejecimiento, y sobre la prevención y la rehabilitación de algunas enfermedades como las cardiovasculares, y las que influyen sobre el proceso arteriosclerótico entre las que se incluyen: la hiperlipidemia, la diabetes, la obesidad y la hipertensión. También engloban afecciones tan importantes como el cáncer, la osteoporosis y la litiasis biliar. El declive funcional de los ancianos es un hecho de gran trascendencia, debido a las dificultades que origina para realizar las actividades involucradas en la vida corriente. El ejercicio es un buen colaborador para atenuar estos problemas. Otros hechos incluidos en este trabajo son: los mecanismos por los que el ejercicio mejora la salud, las recomendaciones que la OMS aporta para su utilización por los mayores y los efectos que produce sobre la calidad de vida. Por último, se exponen una serie de propuestas para estimular la práctica del ejercicio en este grupo de personas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. med. deporte;29(150): 784-802, jul.-ago. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116551</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El ejercicio en la prevención y tratamiento de las enfermedades en personas mayores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50504^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53992^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50219</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
