<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95148</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Improvement in the measurement technique of pulmonary artery pressure by Doppler echocardiography with contrast in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To evaluate the benefit of contrast echocardiography in the assessment of systolic pulmonary artery pressure (PAPs). Design Compare standard reference (Doppler-echocardiography) with contrast. Location Echocardiography department. Patients Ambulatory chronic obstructive patient disease (COPD). Intervention Continuous wave Doppler spectral signal of tricuspid regurgitation (TR) was evaluated before and after intravenous injection of a galactose-based intravenous echo-enhancing agent. A four patterns scale classified the quality of the TR signal: 0=absent regurgitation; 1=protosystolic signal not allowing the recognition of peak velocity; 2=non-homogenous signal intensity, albeit allowing the measurement of maximal velocity; and 3=uniform pansystolic velocity signal. PAPs was estimated adding 10mmHg to the transtricuspid gradient, calculated from the TR peak velocity. Results PAPs was only calculated reliably in 20 (49%) patients before the administration of contrast. Seventeen patients were classified as pattern 2, and three as pattern 3 on the scale of the TR quality signal. After contrast 41 (95%) patients showed a reliable TR signal. Two were classified as pattern 1, 11 as pattern 2 and 28 as pattern 3 on the scale of the TR quality signal. In the 20 patients in whom PAPs was estimated before contrast, a significant increase in PAPs values occurred after contrast, 44±10mmHg vs. 56±15mmHg (p&lt;0.01). ConclusionThe use of an echocardiography contrast agent increases the number of COPD patients in whom PAPs can be estimated non-invasively and may avoid underestimation of the PAP value (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carreras, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Thomas, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borrás, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leta, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabello, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pons-Lladó, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Evaluar el beneficio del contraste en la ecocardiografía para medir la presión de arteria pulmonar sistólica (PAPs). Diseño Estándar de referencia (ecocardiografía) comparada con contraste. Ambito Gabinete de ecocardiografia. Pacientes Ambulatorio con enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica (EPOC). Intervención La señal de la regurgitación tricuspidea (RT) por Doppler fue evaluada antes y después de administrar contraste intravenoso (Levovist(R)). Se definió una escala de 4 patrones de señal de RT: 0=ausencia de regurgitación; 1=señal protosistólica que no permite la medida de la velocidad pico; 2=señal de intensidad no homogénea pero que permite la medida de la velocidad pico y 3=señal uniforme y pansistólica. El valor de la PAPs fue estimado añadiendo 10mmHg al gradiente transtricuspideo. Resultados La PAPs fue calculada solo en 20 (49%) pacientes antes del contraste. Diecisiete pacientes fueron clasificados en el patrón 2 y 3 en el patrón 3 de la señal de la RT. Tras la administración de contraste 41 (95%) pacientes mostraron señal de RT. Dos fueron clasificados en el patrón 1, 11 con el patrón 2 y 28 con el 3. En los 20 pacientes en los que la PAPs fue estimada antes del contraste se observó aumento de su valor, 44±10mmHg vs. 56±15mmHg (p&lt;0,01). Conclusión El uso de un agente de contraste intravenoso en la ecocardiografía Doppler aumenta el número de pacientes EPOC en los que la PAPs puede ser estimada de manera no invasiva y podría evitar una infraestimación del valor de la PAPs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);34(8): 506-512, nov. 2010. graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95148</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Optimización en la técnica de medida de la presión arterial pulmonar por ecocardiografía Doppler con el uso de contraste en pacientes con enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1822^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d555^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23233^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14660^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12088^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7155^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201011</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
