<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039025</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Change and stability of the factors that affected parenting negatively</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In child maltreatment prevention field and parenting support, is very relevant the study of the variables related with the change or stability of those factors that affect parenting negatively. The purpose of this longitudinal study was to detect the predictors of change (increase or decrease) and no-change of those negative factors that affect parenting, in a period of a year, in the context of a preventive programme «Mother child psychosocial support». 520 mothers and their babies aged from 3 to 18 months old constituted the group from which a sample of 85 was randomly selected. The results showed that «no-change» is better predicted than change. Punitive discipline in mother's childhood, low maternal satisfaction and reporting something they don't like in their 3 month babies, predicted to maintenance of high score in the factors under study. Good marital relationship and more visits to the Program predicted the maintenance of low score in those factors</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pons-Salvador, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cerezo, M. Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernabé, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la prevención del maltrato infantil, un área de interés lo constituye el estudio de las variables relacionadas con los factores que afectan negativamente la parentalidad. El propósito de este estudio longitudinal fue detectar en un año las variables que predicen «cambio» (Aumento o disminución) y «no cambio» de esos factores, dentro del programa de prevención «Apoyo Psicológico Materno-Infantil». 520 madres y sus niños de 3 a 18 meses constituyeron el grupo del cual se obtuvo una muestra aleatoria de 85. Los resultados de los análisis discriminantes mostraron que se predice mejor la estabilidad que el cambio. La historia de disciplina punitiva de la madre, la baja satisfacción materna y la percepción de su bebé cuando tenía tres meses explicaban el mantenimiento elevado de dichos factores, mientras que la buena relación de pareja y el mayor nivel de participación en el programa explicaban el mantenimiento bajo en los mismos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);17(1): 31-36, feb. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039025</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambio y estabilidad en los factores que afectan negativamente a la parentabilidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2696^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2696^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10476</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12113^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
