<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92762</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Hemorrhoids surgery presents a post-operative pain of moderate to severe in intensity. So we must make a multimodalanalgesic anesthetic technique to ensure the success of this procedure in the outpatient setting. We conducted a comparative study to assess the efficacy of pudendal nerve in hemorrhoidal surgery in ambulatory patients. Patients and methods: Prospective study forty-three patients divided into two groups according to surgical technique (Milligan-Morgan or Longo), underwent bilateral blockade of the pudendalnerve, with 20 ml of levobupivacaine 0.5%. The pain was assessed with the verbal numeric scale in the recovery room, hospital discharge, and 24, 48.72 hours. Results: two groups were similar with respect to demographic variables, physical status, history, duration of surgery and anesthesia. Pudendal block was performed successfully in all patients. The assessment of postoperative pain at discharge and 24 hours of highstatistically significant difference between both techniques. Even afterthe first 24 hours in any severe pain. Only 4 patients required rescue analgesia at home at 48 and 72 hours, two in each group. Conclusions: Our results show that the bilateral blockade of the pudendal nerve with 0.5% levobupivacaine associated with general anesthesia reduces postoperative pain, as well as the additional analgesic medication consumption (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fajardo Pérez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Vega, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cassinello Plaza, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinta, J. C. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Antonio San Román, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodrigo Tirado, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La cirugía de hemorroides presenta un dolor postoperatorio de intensidad moderada-severa. La realización una técnica anestésico-analgésica multimodal garantiza el éxito de este procedimiento en cirugía ambulatoria. Realizamos un estudio observacional para valorar la eficacia del bloqueo de los nervios pudendos en cirugía hemorroidal en pacientes ambulatorios. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio prospectivo en cuarenta y tres pacientes divididos en dos grupos según técnica quirúrgica utilizada(Milligan-Morgan o Longo), a los cuales se les realizó bloqueo bilateral de los nervios pudendos, con 20 ml de levobupivacaína 0.5%. El dolor fue valorado con la escala verbal numérica en la sala de reanimación, al alta hospitalaria, y a las 24, 48,72 horas. Resultados: Ambos grupos fueron homogéneos con respecto alas variables demográficas, estado físico, antecedentes, duración de la cirugía y de la anestesia. El bloqueo pudendo se realizo con éxito en todos los pacientes. La evaluación del dolor postoperatorio al alta hospitalaria y a las 24 horas postalta muestra diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre ambas técnicas. Sin embargo, posteriormente no existen diferencias entre ambas técnicas. En las primeras 24 horas en el domicilio ningún paciente presento dolor severo, independientemente del grupo y solo 4 pacientes precisaron analgesia de rescate en el domicilio a las 48 y 72 horas, dos en cada grupo. Conclusiones: Nuestros resultados muestran que el bloqueo bilateralde los nervios pudendos con levobupivacaína al 0.5% asociadoa la anestesia general proporciona un buen control del dolor postoperatorio en las primeras 24 horas con baja incidencia de complicaciones en ambos grupos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;16(1): 18-22, ene.-mar. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92762</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio prospectivo de la eficacia del bloqueo de los nervios pudendos para analgesia postoperatoria de cirugía hemorroidal ambulatoria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6638^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9600^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
