<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142563</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Review of the novelties from the 2014 ECTRIMS-ACTRIMS Joint Congress, presented at the 7th Post-ECTRIMS Meeting (II)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">For the seventh year in a row the Post-ECTRIMS Meeting has been held in Madrid (Spain). Renowned specialists in multiple sclerosis and national leaders in this area have gathered once again to discuss the novelties presented at the 2014 ECTRIM-ACTRIMS World Congress. That meeting gave rise to this review, which is published in two parts. This second part shows that immunological phenomena are increasingly more present in the pathogenesis of the disease, and that the interaction between inflammation and neurodegeneration is becoming more apparent. Metabolic, mitochondrial dysfunction and oxidative stress phenomena are also involved in axonal degeneration and the experimental models open up the way to promising new therapeutic approaches for regenerative strategies. Although ambitious, inducible neural progenitor cells have become a promising alternative to the conventional treatments with stem cells, and the identification of new genetic variants of susceptibility to multiple sclerosis opens up the way to the discovery of new drugs. Reconsidering the value of old drugs and procedures would be another alternative therapeutic development (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Cermeño, José C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meca Lallana, José E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saiz, Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz García, Delicias</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ginestal, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Antigüedad, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brieva, Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arroyo, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montalban, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Pinel, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Comabella, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casanova Estruch, Bonaventura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calles Hernández, M Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliva Nacarino, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramió Torrentà, Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olascoaga, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Merino, Juan A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendibe Bilbao, María del Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tintoré, Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oreja Guevara, Celia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Por séptimo año consecutivo se ha celebrado en Madrid (España) la Reunión Post-ECTRIMS. Reconocidos especialistas en esclerosis múltiple y líderes de opinión nacionales se han reunido un año más para exponer las novedades presentadas en el Congreso Mundial ECTRIMS-ACTRIMS 2014, y fruto de esa reunión se genera esta revisión que se publica en dos partes. En esta segunda parte se pone de manifiesto que los fenómenos inmunológicos cada vez están más presentes en la patogenia de la enfermedad, y que la interacción entre inflamación y neurodegeneración es más evidente. Fenómenos metabólicos, de disfunción mitocondrial y de estrés oxidativo también se implican en la degeneración axonal, y los modelos experimentales abren paso a nuevos enfoques terapéuticos con esperanza para las estrategias regenerativas. Aunque resulte ambicioso, los progenitores neurales inducibles se convierten en una prometedora alternativa a los tratamientos convencionales con células madre, y la identificación de nuevas variantes genéticas de susceptibilidad a la esclerosis múltiple abre camino al descubrimiento de nuevos fármacos. Replantear el valor de antiguos fármacos y procedimientos sería otra alternativa de desarrollo terapéutico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;61(6): 271-283, 16 sept., 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142563</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión de las novedades del congreso conjunto ECTRIMS-ACTRIMS 2014, presentadas en la VII Reunión Post-ECTRIMS (II)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31306</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54426</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30883</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32850^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55509^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22316^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6522^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7336^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29437^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
