<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131503</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Protocol of health examination on voice professional</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The principal objective of this work is to determinate a propose of preventive health screenings on voice workers. Materials and Methods:Voice disorders mainly affect groups of people who use their voice is a key element as part of their work, especially teachers and telemarketers. According to studies, the prevalence may vary between 18 and 57% in teachers and approximately 13% of telemarketers. The need to assess and prevent diseases in all elements involved in voice production, and the obligation to prevent and detect nodules of the vocal chords in professionals at risk, justify the development of this protocol. Results: We propose a protocol with specific content including past medical history, habits, current situation and occupational history, which we need to be aware of in order to assess these patients properly, and a subjective evaluation of the voice and specific aerodynamic examination complemented by the Voice Handicap Index (VHI). Conclusions:This is a protocol very easy to use in medical evaluation y not expensive for the company (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Serrano Estrada, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Farjemutiloa, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González García, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual Albarrán, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El principal objetivo de este trabajo es realizar una propuesta de reconocimiento preventivo de salud para trabajadores de la voz. Material y Métodos: La patología de la voz tiene su incidencia más elevada en aquellos colectivos que utilizan la voz como elemento clave de su actividad profesional, especialmente en docentes y teleoperadores. Según estudios, la prevalencia de puede oscilar de un 18% a 57% en docentes y aproximadamente 13 % en teleoperadores. La necesidad de valorar y prevenir las patologías en todos los elementos que intervienen en la producción de la voz, así como la obligación de prevenir y detectar nódulos de las cuerdas vocales en profesionales con riesgo,  justifican la elaboración de este protocolo.Resultados: Proponemos un protocolo con un contenido específico conteniendo historia clínico laboral que recoja la información con  anamnesis, hábitos, situación actual e historia laboral, que debemos conocer para la adecuada valoración de estos trabajadores, una valoración subjetiva de la voz y una exploración específica aerodinámicacomplementada con el test Índice de incapacidad vocal VOICE HANDICAP  INDEX (VHI). Conclusiones:Este protocolo es fácil de hacer por los profesionales sanitarios y no es caro para las empresas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;23(4): 422-431, dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131503</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abordaje de la vigilancia de la salud en trabajadores con uso profesional de la voz</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27926^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10894^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51559</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28119^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27926^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16902^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28119^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35170^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53079^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8009^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15233^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9247^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53079^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
