<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150006</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Methodological problems when analyzing data from a research on semantic-conceptual memory in Alzheimer&#146;s patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of this work is to present, from a methodological standpoint, a series of problems that had to be solved when analyzing data from a research on semantic-conceptual memory in Alzheimer&#146;s patients or when dealing with adequate techniques or methods for specific stances. The problems have arised in two types of tests: in the verbal fluency one and in the definition of categories. The first one demanded from the subjects the production of semantic exemplars. One has analyzed not only the obvious frequency of the units/exemplars/unit of time but also the sequence or scheme generated by data. This new approach also analyzes and helps us to infer how the subject (healthy or ill) searches in his/her conceptual memory. Regarding the category definition test, for analyzing in a precise way the types of attributes that subjects generate and also their frequencies, a taxonomy and a specific analysis for attribute treatment is proposed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peraita Adrados, Herminia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Mardomingo, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garriga Trillo, Ana Julia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El trabajo que presentamos pretende exponer desde un punto de vista metodológico una serie de problemas que han tenido que ser solventados al analizar los datos procedentes de un estudio de la memoria semántico-conceptual en enfermos de Alzheimer, así como las técnicas y métodos adoptados en cada caso. Los problemas se han generado en torno a dos tipos de pruebas: en la de fluidez verbal (o producción de ejemplares de categorías semánticas), se ha analizado además de, obviamente, el número de unidades/ejemplares producidos por unidad de tiempo, la secuencia o patrón según la cual se han ido generando, lo cual implica tratar de analizar e inferir cómo el sujeto (sano y enfermo) «busca» en su almacén conceptual. Por otra parte en la prueba de definición de categorías, y para poder analizar de manera precisa los tipos de atributos que los sujetos generan así como sus frecuencias/ocurrencias, se ha propuesto una taxonomía y un tipo de análisis específico para el tratamiento de atributos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);12(supl.2): 192-195, 2000. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150006</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Problemas metodológicos al analizar datos de producción de ejemplares y de atributos en un estudio sobre deterioro semántico en enfermos de Alzheimer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13042</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
