<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139480</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Exclusive enteral nutrition continues to be first line therapy for pediatric Crohn's disease in the era of biologics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Exclusive enteral nutrition (EEN) has been to be more effective than corticosteroids in achieving mucosal healing without their side effects. Objectives: To determine the efficacy of EEN in terms of inducing clinical remission in newly diagnosed CD children and to study the efficacy of this therapeutic approach in improving the degree of intestinal mucosa inflammation. Materials and methods: The medical records of patients with newly diagnosed Crohn's disease treated with EEN were reviewed retrospectively. The degree of mucosal inflammation was assessed by fecal calprotectin (FC). Remission was defined as a PCDAI&lt;10. Results: Forty patients (24 males) were included, the age at diagnosis was 11.6±3.6 years. Of the 34 patients who completed the EEN period, 32 (94% per-protocol analysis) achieved clinical remission. This percentage fell to 80% in the intention-to-treat analysis. The compliance rate was 95%. Duration of EEN was 6.42 weeks (IQR 6.0&#150;8.14). FC was significantly higher in patients with moderate and severe disease. Median baseline FC levels (680&amp;#956;g/g) decreased significantly to 218&amp;#956;g/g (P&lt;0.0001) after EEN. We found a statistically significant correlation between FC and PCDAI (rho=0.727; P&lt;0.0001). Early use of thiopurines (&lt; 8 weeks) versus subsequent use was not associated with improved outcomes during the follow-up. Conclusions: EEN administered for 6-8 weeks is effective for inducing clinical remission and decreasing the degree of mucosal inflammation. We did not find differences in terms of maintenance of remission in patients treated early with thiopurines (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lacasa Maseri, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Girón Fernández-Crehuet, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Nieto, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicioso Recio, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navas-López, V. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blasco-Alonso, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sierra Salinas, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La nutrición enteral exclusiva (NEE) ha demostrado ser más efectiva que los esteroides para alcanzar la curación mucosa sin sus efectos secundarios. Objetivos: Determinar la eficacia de la NEE para inducir la remisión clínica y mejorar el grado de inflamación mucosa en pacientes con EC durante su primer brote. Material y métodos: Revisión de las historias clínicas de pacientes con EC tratados con NEE durante su primer brote. El grado de inflamación mucosa se estimó mediante la calprotectina fecal (CF). Se definió remisión como PCDAI &lt; 10. Resultados: Se incluyó a 40 pacientes (24 varones) con una edad al diagnóstico de 11,6 ± 3,6 años. La duración de la NEE fue de 6,42 semanas (RIC 6,0-8,14). De los 34 pacientes que completaron el período de NEE, 32 (94% en el análisis por protocolo) alcanzaron la remisión clínica. Este porcentaje descendió al 80% en el análisis por intención de tratar. La tasa de cumplimiento fue del 95%. Los valores de CF fueron significativamente más altos en pacientes con brotes moderados y graves. La CF basal fue de 680&amp;#956;g/g y descendió de forma significativa a 218&amp;#956;g/g al final del periodo de NEE (p &lt; 0,0001). Hubo correlación estadísticamente significativa entre CF y PCDAI (rho=0,727; p &lt; 0,0001). La introducción precoz del tratamiento con tiopurinas (antes de las 8 semanas) no se asoció a una mejor evolución durante el seguimiento. Conclusiones: La NEE administrada durante 6-8 semanas es efectiva para inducir la remisión clínica y mejorar el grado de inflamación mucosa. No encontramos diferencias en términos de mantenimiento de la remisión en pacientes tratados precozmente con tiopurinas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);83(1): 47-54, jul. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139480</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La nutrición enteral exclusiva continua siendo el tratamiento de primera línea en la enfermedad de Crohn pediátrica en la era de los biológicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1716^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30324^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23971^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
