<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119094</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cyberbullying in the Basque Country: sex differences in victims, perpetrators and observers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The study aimed to analyze sex differences in cyberbullying, with a sample of 3,026 participants from the Basque Country (Spain), aged from 12 to 18 years, 51.5% female and 48.5% male. The Cyberbullying Test was administered (Garaigordobil, 2013) to assess the frequency with which 15 behaviors had been received, performed and observed during the past year, and obtaining four psychometric indicators: victimization, perpetration, observation, and aggressive victimization. It was found a significantly higher percentage of female victims (female= 17.6%, male= 12.5%), although the average of behaviors in both sexes was similar. The percentage of perpetrators was similar (male= 7.8%, female= 7.7%), although the average behavior of perpetration was significantly higher in males. The percentage of aggressive victims was similar (male= 5.2%, female= 5.1%), and the mean of behaviors that had been received/performed was also similar. The percentage of female observers was significantly higher (female=38%; male= 27.1%), and the mean of behavior observation by females was also higher. The study provides prevalence rates of cyberbullying in the Basque Country, and supports the need for prevention and intervention</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garaigordobil, Maite</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aliri, Jone</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El estudio tuvo como objetivo analizar diferencias de sexo en ciberacoso, con una muestra de 3.026 participantes del País Vasco (España) de 12 a 18 años, 51,5% mujeres y 48,5% varones. Se administró el &#147;Test cyberbullying&#148; (Garaigordobil, 2013) que evalúa la frecuencia con la que 15 conductas han sido sufridas, realizadas y observadas durante el último año, obteniendo cuatro indicadores psicométricos: victimización, perpetración, observación, victimización-agresiva. Se encontró un porcentaje significativamente mayor de mujeres víctimas (mujer= 17,6%; varón= 12,5%), aunque la media de conductas en ambos sexos fue similar. El porcentaje de agresores fue similar (varón= 7,8%; mujer= 7,7%), aunque la media de conductas de perpetración de los varones fue significativamente superior. El porcentaje de víctimas-agresivas fue similar (varón= 5,2%; mujer= 5,1%) y la media de conductas sufridas/realizadas fue análoga. El porcentaje de mujeres observadoras fue significativamente superior (mujer= 38%; varón= 27,1%) y la media de conductas de observación de las mujeres fue superior. El estudio provee información sobre la prevalencia del ciberacoso en el País Vasco y apoya la necesidad de prevención e intervención</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;21(3): 461-474, sept.-dic. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119094</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ciberacoso ("cyberbullying") en el País Vasco: diferencias de sexo en víctimas, agresores y observadores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33199^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d378^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
