<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142078</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Biofilm formation and genetic variability of BCR1 gene in the Candida parapsilosis complex</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Candida parapsilosis sensu stricto, Candida orthopsilosis, and Candida metapsilosis are cryptic species that belong to the C. parapsilosis complex, which has been increasingly associated to fungemia in various geographic regions, principally due to the capability of these yeasts to form biofilms on indwelling medical devices. BCR1 is one of the most studied genes related to Candida spp. biofilms. Aims. To evaluate the biofilm forming capability of a subset of 65 clinical isolates of the C. parapsilosis complex using two conventional approaches, and to look for an association between the biofilm forming phenotype and genetic variants of a fragment of BCR1. Methods. The biofilm determination was carried out by crystal violet staining and tetrazolium reduction assay. On the other hand, a segment of BCR1 gene was sequenced by Sanger methodology. Results. C. parapsilosis sensu stricto was statistically associated with a low biofilm production phenotype, while C. orthopsilosis was significantly associated with both phenotypes (high and low biofilm producers). According to the BCR1 sequence analysis, genetic variability was detected in C. orthopsilosis and C. metapsilosis without a particular biofilm formation phenotype association. Conclusions. Under the adopted experimental design, C. parapsilosis sensu stricto was associated with the low biofilm phenotype and C. orthopsilosis with both phenotypes (high and low biofilm producers). On the other hand, an association between a biofilm forming phenotype and a particular genetic variant of the analyzed BCR1 fragment was not found (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Sánchez, Irám P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Bello, Romel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, Gloria M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, José G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Treviño-Rangel, Rogelio de J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosas-Taraco, Adrián G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. Candida parapsilosis sensu stricto, Candida orthopsilosis y Candida metapsilosis son especies crípticas que integran el complejo C. parapsilosis, asociado de forma creciente a fungemia en diversas regiones geográficas. Dicho crecimiento se debe principalmente a la capacidad de estas levaduras de crear biopelículas en los dispositivos médicos. El gen BCR1 es uno de los más estudiados en las biopelículas de Candida spp. Objetivos. Evaluar la capacidad de formación de biopelícula de un conjunto de 65 aislamientos clínicos del complejo C. parapsilosis mediante dos metodologías convencionales, así como establecer una posible asociación entre el fenotipo productor de la biopelícula y las variantes genéticas de un fragmento de BCR1. Métodos. La determinación de la presencia de biopelícula se llevó a cabo mediante tinción con cristal violeta y el análisis de reducción de la sal de tetrazolio. Además, se secuenció un segmento del gen BCR1 mediante el método Sanger. Resultados. C. parapsilosis sensu stricto presentó una asociación estadísticamente significativa con un fenotipo de baja producción de biopelícula, mientras que C. orthopsilosis tuvo una asociación estadísticamente significativa con ambos fenotipos (alta y baja producción de biopelícula). Según el análisis de la secuencia de BCR1, existe variabilidad genética en C. orthopsilosis y C. metapsilosis sin ninguna asociación particular a los fenotipos relacionados con la formación de biopelícula. Conclusiones. Bajo el diseño experimental adoptado, C. parapsilosis sensu stricto se asoció con un fenotipo de baja producción de biopelícula y C. orthopsilosis con ambos fenotipos (alta y baja producción de biopelícula). Por otra parte, no se encontró ninguna asociación estadísticamente significativa entre los fenotipos de formación de biopelícula y variantes genéticas particulares en el fragmento analizado de BCR1 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;32(3): 180-184, jul.-sept. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142078</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">/ Formación de biopelícula y variabilidad genética del gen BCR1 en el complejo Candida parapsilosis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2209^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2207^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2207^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5978</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32342^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
