<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153139</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The Molecular Registry of Pituitary Adenomas (REMAH): A bet of Spanish Endocrinology for the future of individualized medicine and translational research</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pituitary adenomas are uncommon, difficult to diagnose tumors whose heterogeneity and low incidence complicate large-scale studies. The Molecular Registry of Pituitary Adenomas (REMAH) was promoted by the Andalusian Society of Endocrinology and Nutrition (SAEN) in 2008 as a cooperative clinical-basic multicenter strategy aimed at improving diagnosis and treatment of pituitary adenomas by combining clinical, pathological, and molecular information. In 2010, the Spanish Society of Endocrinology and Nutrition (SEEN) extended this project to national level and established 6 nodes with common protocols and methods for sample and clinical data collection, molecular analysis, and data recording in a common registry (www.remahnacional.com). The registry combines clinical data with molecular phenotyping of the resected pituitary adenoma using quantitative real-time PCR of expression of 26 genes: Pituitary hormones (GH-PRL-LH-FSH-PRL-ACTH-CGA), receptors (somatostatin, dopamine, GHRH, GnRH, CRH, arginine-vasopressin, ghrelin), other markers (Ki67, PTTG1), and control genes. Until 2015, molecular information has been collected from 704 adenomas, out of 1179 patients registered. This strategy allows for comparative and relational analysis between the molecular profile of the different types of adenoma and the clinical phenotype of patients, which may provide a better understanding of the condition and potentially help in treatment selection. The REMAH is therefore a unique multicenter, interdisciplinary network founded on a shared database that provides a far-reaching translational approach for management of pituitary adenomas, and paves the way for the conduct of combined clinical-basic innovative studies on large patient samples (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Leal-Cerro, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castaño,  Justo P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Escolá, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvador, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gaztambide, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Robledo, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Venegas-Moreno, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castaño, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valassi, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gilabert, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez-Costa, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luque, Raúl M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Webb, Susan M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soto-Moreno, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, Clara V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marazuela, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernabéu, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Madrazo-Atutxa, Ainara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Tejada, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fajardo, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Picó, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gálvez, María Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lucas-Morante, Tomás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivero-Cortés, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora, Mireia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puig-Domingo, Manel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los adenomas hipofisarios son tumores infrecuentes de diagnóstico complejo, cuya heterogeneidad y baja incidencia dificultan estudios a gran escala. El Registro Molecular de Adenomas Hipofisarios (REMAH) nació en 2008 en el seno de la Sociedad Andaluza de Endocrinología y Nutrición (SAEN), como estrategia de cooperación clínico-básica y multicéntrica, para mejorar el diagnóstico y tratamiento de tumores hipofisarios mediante la combinación de información clínica, anatomopatológica y molecular. En 2010, la Sociedad Española de Endocrinología y Nutrición (SEEN) lo extendió a nivel nacional, estableciendo 6 nodos con protocolos y métodos comunes de recogida de muestras y datos clínicos, análisis molecular y anotación en un mismo registro (www.remahnacional.com). El registro combina datos clínicos con el fenotipado molecular del adenoma intervenido, mediante PCR cuantitativa en tiempo real de la expresión de 26 genes: hormonas hipofisarias (GH-PRL-LH-FSH-PRL-ACTH-CGA), receptores (somatostatina, dopamina, GHRH, GnRH, CRH, arginina-vasopresina, ghrelina), otros marcadores (Ki67, PTTG1) y genes de control. Hasta 2015 se ha obtenido información molecular de 704 adenomas, de los 1.179 pacientes registrados. Esta estrategia permite abordar análisis comparativos y relacionales entre el perfil molecular de los distintos tipos de adenomas y el fenotipo clínico del paciente, lo que puede ofrecer un mejor conocimiento de la enfermedad y, potencialmente, ayudar en la selección del tratamiento. El REMAH constituye una red única, multicéntrica e interdisciplinar, cimentada en una base de datos compartida, que aporta un enfoque traslacional de gran proyección potencial para el manejo de los adenomas hipofisarios y abre el camino para estudios conjuntos clínico-básicos innovadores con un elevado número de pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;63(6): 274-284, jun.-jul. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153139</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El Registro Molecular de Adenomas Hipofisarios (REMAH): una apuesta de futuro de la Endocrinología española por la medicina individualizada y la investigación traslacional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d178^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11344^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53692</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3500^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53784^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28402^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
