<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126633</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship between alcohol, drug use and traffic accidents related to nightlife among a spanish youth sample in three autonomous communities in 2007</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The phenomenon known as binge drinking and other drug abuse frequently occurs among young people in nightlife-related areas. This study analyzes the risk behaviours and the accident rate related to alcohol and other drugs among a sample of young people involved in nightlife. Method: A total of 440 young people from 3 Spanish Autonomous Communities took part. The sample size was estimated by means of Respondent Driven Sampling. The statistical analyses mined frequencies and measurements of the relationship of driving risk-related behaviour in relation to the accident rate, number of cases of drunkenness, frequency of accidents during the past month, influence of gender and age, as well as the predictiveness of these variables as regards the accident rate. Results: A total of 50.2% of these young people had gotten into a vehicle with a driver who was drunk and/or under the influence of drugs, 23.2% has driven when drunk and 23.5% under the influence of drugs. The greater the degree of involvement in nightlife, the higher the frequency of drunkenness [ chi2 (9)=112.24; p&lt; .000 ] the greater the number of cases of drunkenness, the higher the frequency of thes behaviors: getting into a vehicle with drivers who are drunk or under the influence of drugs [ c2=36,442, (3) p&lt;0.001 ], drunken driving [ chi2 =23,748, (3) p&lt;0.001 ] and driving while under the influence of drugs [ chi2=23,816 (3) p&lt;0.001 ]. The regression analysis highlighted drunken driving (odds-ratio=5.4) as the risk behaviour most related to traffic accidents. Conclusions: There is a high incidence of risk behaviours while driving vehicles. Drunkenness, drug use and involvement in nightlife increase the frequency of these behaviours. Drunken driving was the best accident predictor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calafat Far, Amador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blay Franzke, Nicole T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Adrover Roig, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juan Jerez, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: El fenómeno conocido como consumo concentrado de alcohol y otras drogas se produce de manera frecuente entre los jóvenes en las áreas recreativas nocturnas. El presente estudio analiza las conductas de riesgo y la siniestralidad asociada al alcohol y otras drogas en una muestra de jóvenes que participan de la vida recreativa nocturna. Método: Participaron 440 jóvenes de 3 comunidades autónomas. El tamaño de la muestra fue estimado mediante Respondent Driven Sampling. Los análisis estadísticos exploraron frecuencias y medidas de asociación de conductas de riesgo en conducción en relación con la siniestralidad, número de estados de embriaguez, frecuencia de accidentes en el último mes, influencia de sexo y edad, así como la potencia predictiva de dichas variables respecto a la siniestralidad. Resultados: Un 50,2% de los jóvenes ha subido con un conductor ebrio y/o drogado, un 23,2% ha conducido embriagado y un 23,5% bajos los efectos de otras drogas. A mayor implicación en la noche, mayor frecuencia de embriaguez [ chi2 (9)=112,24; psubirse con otros conductores ebrios o drogados [ chi2 = 36.442, (3) p&lt;0.001 ], conducir ebrio [ chi2 =23,748, (3) p&lt;0,001 ] y conducir drogado [ chi2 = 23,816 (3) p&lt;0,001 ]. El análisis de regresión destacó conducir ebrio (odds-ratio=5,4) como conducta de riesgo más asociada a los accidentes de tráfico. Conclusiones: Las conductas de riesgo durante la conducción de vehículos muestran una elevada incidencia. Embriaguez, uso de drogas e implicación en la noche aumentan la frecuencia de dichas conductas. Conducir ebrio fue el mejor predictor de los accidentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;82(3): 323-331, mayo.-jun. 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126633</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación del consumo de alcohol y drogas de los jóvenes españoles con la siniestrabilidad vial durante la vida recreativa nocturna en tres comunidades autónomas en 2007</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3636</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16843</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
