<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115720</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pediatric trauma and its relation to social health determinants</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Trauma represents in Chile and in the world, the major cause of death in children, adolescents and young adults; and is one of the most important causes of morbidity. It is a significant public health problem, because its consequences are transcendental in magnitude and impact. Objective: To identify the Social Health Determinants (SHD) that impact trauma in children, describe the relationship between the SHD identified, and propose comprehensive strategies to lessen the impact. Methods: A literature review was made from Medline/Pubmed, Lilacs, ProQuest, Cinhal and Scielo, between October 2011 and January 2012. Selected for analysis were 15 articles that met the inclusion criteria. Results: The SHD that are related to the incidence and severity of trauma in children are: education and literacy, socioeconomic status, and physical environment. These can cause a positive or negative impact on the health of children with regard to morbidity and mortality from external causes. Conclusion: To reduce the trauma of children in Chile, it is essential to educate the population. Educational programs should be designed and implemented by multidisciplinary teams in coordination among sectors, taking into account the social determinants of health involved, such as low educational level, low socioeconomic status and inadequate physical environment; also considering the ability of people to access and understand the information given by health professionals (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>San Juan Hurtado, Lorena Alejandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pino, Paola Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monasterio Ocares, María Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: Los traumatismos representan en Chile y el mundo, la principal causa de muerte en niños, adolescentes y adultos jóvenes, y es una de las causas más importantes de morbilidad. Es un problema relevante de salud pública, debido a que sus consecuencias, son trascendentes en magnitud e impacto. Objetivo: Identificar los DSS que tienen impacto en el traumatismo en pediatría, describir la relación entre los DSS identificados, y proponer estrategias globales para disminuir el impacto. Metodología: Revisión bibliográfica, se realizó una búsqueda en las bases de datos Medline/Pubmed, Lilacs, ProQuest, Cinhal y Scielo, entre los meses de octubre 2011 y enero 2012. Para el análisis fueron seleccionados 15 artículos que cumplían con los criterios de inclusión. Resultados: Los determinantes sociales de la salud que se relacionan con la incidencia y la severidad del traumatismo en pediatría son: educación y literacidad, ingreso y status social, y ambiente físico. Los cuales pueden causar un impacto positivo o negativo en la salud de la población infantil con respecto a la morbimortalidad por causas externas. Conclusión: Para prevenir el traumatismo infantil en Chile, es indispensable educar a la población. Los programas educativos deben ser diseñados por equipos multidisciplinarios e implementados en forma intersectorial; teniendo en cuenta los determinantes sociales de la salud involucrados, tales como: bajo nivel de escolaridad, bajo nivel socioeconómico y ambiente físico inadecuado; considerando además, la capacidad de las personas para acceder y comprender la información otorgada por los profesionales de la salud (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;12(32): 320-335, oct. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115720</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Traumatismo en pediatría y su relación con los determinantes sociales de la salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28637^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
