<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130265</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-0740</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The midwives and the Maternity Insurance during the Spanish Second Republic</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this report is to examine the important role played by midwives in the beginning and subsequent evolution of Maternity Insurance during the Spanish Second Republic that has been forgotten by other studies. Methodology: Historical research which uses primary sources such as all of the documentation produced by the Instituto Nacional de Prevision and other files obtained from various national archives. Results: Maternity Insurance granted a prominent role to midwives in prenatal care, delivery care and postnatal care of women workers. It&#146;s estimated that at least 2,223 midwives collaborated with the Insurance program during the first 9 trimesters of its functioning. Conclusions: Maternity Insurance wasn&#146;t limited to the improvement of the mothers&#146; health by monitoring them throughout pregnancy and by providing professional attendance at birth and postpartum care, but it also provided newborn care for the infants&#146; first 6 months of life. The beginning of the program opened up an important source of work opportunities and an increase of wages for midwives during the Second Republic. It also influenced in the progressive institutionalization of childbirth during the 20th century. The integration in the hospital structure, which was strongly hierarchic, contributed to the progressive subordination of the midwife under the doctor during normal birth (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gomis, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Berdún, Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente trabajo es analizar el importante papel que la matrona tuvo en la puesta en marcha y evolución posterior del Seguro de Maternidad durante la Segunda República y que ha sido ignorado por otros estudios. Metodología: Investigación histórica que emplea como fuentes primarias toda la documentación producida por el Instituto Nacional de Previsión, así como la obtenida en diferentes archivos nacionales. Resultados: El Seguro de Maternidad confirió gran protagonismo a la matrona en el seguimiento del embarazo y la atención al parto y al posparto de las mujeres trabajadoras. Al menos 2.223 matronas colaboraron con el Seguro durante los 9 primeros trimestres de funcionamiento de éste. Conclusiones: El Seguro de Maternidad no se limitó a la mejora de la salud materna mediante el control del embarazo y la asistencia profesional al parto y al posparto, sino que también se ocupó de las enfermedades del bebé durante los 6 primeros meses de vida. Su puesta en marcha supuso una importante fuente de oportunidades de trabajo y de ingresos para las matronas durante la Segunda República. También influyó en la progresiva institucionalización del parto que tuvo lugar durante el siglo xx. Esta integración en estructuras hospitalarias, fuertemente jerarquizadas, contribuyó a la progresiva subordinación de la matrona a la figura del médico en la atención al parto normal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Matronas prof;15(3): 76-84, jul.-sept. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130265</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La matrona y el Seguro de Maternidad durante la Segunda República (1931-1936)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15331^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50264</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7517^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7519^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3708^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17570^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
