<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105549</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A multidisciplinary approach to the detection of malingering in chronic low back pain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A multidimensional study on the symptom exaggeration in chronic low back pain patients is presented. The main aim is to detect discriminant patterns of malingered pain-related disability in order to develop a detailed protocol to the assessment of suspected malingering in cases with false or grossly exaggerated physical or psychological symptoms motivated by external incentives. Overall sample (n=88) was divided in four groups: low back pain patients not involved in litigation (n=15), low back pain patients involved in litigation (n=23), analogue low back pain-instructed participants (n=20), and control group (n=30). Several medical and psychological tests were administered to participants, including: medical complementary tests, self-efficacy and life personal self-report scales, the Oswestry Disability Index, the Chronic Disability Index of Waddell, the SF-36 Health Survey, the Structured Inventory of Malingered Symptomatology (SIMS), and the Minnesota Multiphasic Personality Inventory &#150; 2 &#150; Restructured Form (MMPI-2-RF). Data on mean group differences and predictive accuracy of the instruments used are presented. A protocol for the detection of malingering based on the differential profile scores between low back pain non-litigants and litigants is also addressed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casado Morales, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santamaría Fernández, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Ordi, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Capilla Ramírez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo es el estudio multidimensional del patrón de exageración de síntomas en lumbalgia crónica, con el fin de obtener indicadores discriminantes de simulación de dolor y discapacidad, y elaborar un protocolo detallado de actuación para aquellos casos en los que el profesional de la salud implicado detecte la posibilidad de existencia de síntomas de simulación, en especial en aquellos pacientes en los que el contexto social, laboral, familiar o personal haga pensar en la obtención de beneficios económicos o eximentes laborales. La muestra del estudio estaba compuesta por 88 participantes, divididos en cuatro grupos: lumbalgia no litigante (n=15), lumbalgia litigante (n=23), lumbalgia análogo (n=20) y grupo control (n=30). Se les administra una batería de pruebas médicas y psicológicas, que incluyen diversas pruebas médicas complementarias: Escala de Valoración Personal Vital, Escala de Autoeficacia Percibida, Índice de Discapacidad de Oswestry (IDO), Índice de Discapacidad Crónica de Waddell (IDC), Cuestionario de Salud SF-36, Inventario Estructurado de Simulación de Síntomas (SIMS) e Inventario Multifásico de Personalidad de Minnesota 2 Forma Reestructurada (MMPI-2-RF). Se presentan datos referidos a diferencias entre grupos y validez predictiva de los instrumentos utilizados y se propone un protocolo de actuación para la detección de la simulación en función del perfil diferencial obtenido entre los pacientes no litigantes y litigantes con sospecha clínica de simulación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);23(3): 145-154, jul.-sept. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105549</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abordaje multidisciplinar para la detección de la simulación en lumbalgia crónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10221^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8479^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37554</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
