<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130387</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The cost of applying the dependency law to Alzheimer disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To calculate the formal cost of social care for people with Alzheimer disease according to the implementation of the dependency law in Gipuzkoa (Spain). Method. A retrospective observational study was carried out of the database of the Dependency Care Services of Gipuzkoa from 2007 to 2012, using a prevalence-based bottom-up approach. Results. The average annual formal cost per person was &#128;11,730. The annual population cost was &#128;34.7 million, representing 19% of the annual expenditure corresponding to the dependency law and 29% of the total cost of Alzheimer disease. Conclusions. Despite the implementation of the new law, most of the burden of the disease is bourne by the family (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arrospide, Arantzazu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zapiain, Ander</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soto-Gordo, Myriam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aiarza, Arantza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abecia, Luis Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mar, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Calcular el coste social de la atención a las personas con enfermedad de Alzheimer según la aplicación de la Ley de Dependencia en Gipuzkoa. Método. Se llevó a cabo un estudio observacional retrospectivo de la base de datos de los Servicios de Atención a la Dependencia de Gipuzkoa de 2007 a 2012. Se utilizó el enfoque bottom-up basado, en última instancia, en la prevalencia. Resultados. El coste formal medio anual por persona fue de 11.730 &#128;. El coste poblacional formal anual fue de 34,7 millones de euros, que representa el 19% del gasto anual por dependencia y el 29% del coste total de la enfermedad de Alzheimer. Conclusiones. A pesar de la aplicación de la nueva ley, la mayor parte de la carga que genera la enfermedad de Alzheimer recae directamente en los familiares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;28(5): 389-392, sept.-oct. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130387</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El coste de la aplicación de la Ley de Dependencia a la enfermedad de Alzheimer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12075^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17513^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12075^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17513^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
