<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143532</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Is our self nothing but reward?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Neuroscience has increasingly explored the neural mechanisms underlying our sense of self. Recent studies have demonstrated the recruitment of regions like the ventral tegmental area, ventromedial prefrontal cortex, and the ventral striatum to self-specific stimuli&#151;regions typically associated with reward-related processing. This raises the question of whether there is a relationship between self and reward and, if so, how these different fields can be linked. Three relationship models that aim to explore the relationship between self and reward are discussed here: integration, segregation, and parallel processing. Their pros and cons are reviewed in light of the most recent findings. The conclusion is that both the fields of self and reward may benefit from increased interaction. This interaction may help to fill in some of the missing pieces regarding reward-related processing, as well as illuminate how brain function can bring forward the philosophical concept and psychological reality of self (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hayes, Dave J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Northoff, Georg</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La neurociencia ha venido explorando de manera creciente los mecanismos que subyacen en nuestra percepción del yo. Estudios recientes han puesto de manifiesto el reclutamiento de regiones como el área del tegmento ventral, la corteza prefrontal ventromedial y el estriado ventral con los estímulos específicos del yo; y estas regiones se asocian habitualmente a los procesos relacionados con la recompensa. Esto plantea la cuestión de si existe o no una relación entre el yo y la recompensa y, de ser así, de qué manera pueden estar relacionados estos diferentes campos. Se comentan aquí 3 modelos de relación que pretenden explorar la relación entre el yo y la recompensa: integración, segregación y procesamiento paralelo. Se examinan sus pros y sus contras a la luz de los hallazgos más recientes. La conclusión es que tanto el campo del yo como el de la recompensa pueden obtener un efecto beneficioso con un aumento de la interacción. Esta interacción puede ser útil para completar algunos de los elementos que faltan en el procesamiento relacionado con la recompensa, así como para aclarar de qué forma la función cerebral puede conducir al concepto filosófico y la realidad psicológica del yo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);19(supl.1): 42-48, dic. 2012. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143532</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Es el yo simplemente la recompensa?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8776</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33143</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53784</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
