<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167200</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New thalamic potential associated with somatosensory evoked potentials</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The response of the thalamus during the study with somatosensory evoked potentials (SSEP) is not sufficiently understood. Case report. A 17-year-old man undergoing surgery for deep brain stimulation in the centromedian nucleus for drugresistant epilepsy under complete sedation. During the intervention, the responses to SSEPs of the thalamic nuclei were recorded by means of four microelectrodes. These responses can be decomposed into three types: local field potentials (LFP), low amplitude fast oscillations (LFO), and high amplitude slow oscillations (HSO). LFO are widespread in much of the registered regions. However, HSOs are located at a single point in the registry and are closely associated with LFPs. Conclusions. Although the presence of LFO has been considered as an indicator of the presence of the sensory thalamus, its wide extension by different thalamic nuclei suggests that it is an unspecific response to SSEPs. However, the restricted spatial location of HSO and their association with LFP suggest that these newly described potentials are the markers for the presence of the sensory thalamus. Their identification may prove very useful in thalamic deep brain stimulation either in awake patients or especially in those requiring sedation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vega-Zelaya, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres, Cristina V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navas-García, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sola, Rafael G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastor, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La respuesta del tálamo durante el estudio con potenciales evocados somatosensoriales (PESS) no está suficientemente comprendida.  Caso clínico. Varón de 30 años intervenido con sedación completa mediante estimulación cerebral profunda en el núcleo centromediano por epilepsia farmacorresistente. Durante la intervención se registraron las respuestas de los núcleos talámicos mediante cuatro microelectrodos a los PESS. Estas respuestas se pueden descomponer en tres tipos: potenciales de campo local (PCL), oscilaciones rápidas de baja amplitud (ORB) y oscilaciones lentas de gran amplitud (OLG). Las ORB están muy extendidas por gran parte de las regiones registradas (&gt; 5 mm) y en los cuatro electrodos simultáneamente. Sin embargo, las OLG están localizadas en un único punto del registro y están íntimamente asociadas con los PCL. Además, el análisis de wavelets muestra un componente espectral y un tiempo de aparición diferentes. Conclusiones. Aunque se ha considerado la presencia de ORB como indicador de la presencia del tálamo sensorial, su amplia extensión por diferentes núcleos talámicos sugiere que se trata de una respuesta poco específica a los PESS. Sin embargo, la localización espacial restringida de los OLG y su asociación con PCL sugiere que estos potenciales de nueva descripción son los marcadores de la presencia del tálamo sensorial. Su identificación puede resultar muy útil en estimulación cerebral profunda talámica en pacientes despiertos y, especialmente, en los que precisen sedación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;65(7): 322-326, 1 oct., 2017. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167200</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevo potencial talámico asociado con potenciales evocados somatosensoriales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14166^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4641^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38807^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5170</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55840^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4639^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
