<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149860</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0620</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intelectural disability and the prison setting</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The prevalence of intellectual disability (ID) in the prison setting has scarcely been studied. Although some approximations or estimates regarding people with intellectual disabilities have been performed in Spain, there is little in the way of reliable data. Objectives: 1) To determine the prevalence of ID in a sample population in the residential modules of a Spanish prison, 2) Obtain data on the prevalence of ID in prison psychiatric units and hospitals. Methods: 1) A TONI II test was performed on a sub-sample (n = 398) of a prevalence study in Spanish prisons33 to identify inmates with intellectual disabilities. 2) We reviewed the reports of the psychiatric department of Parc Sanitari Sant Joan de Deu to establish the diagnosis at discharge of patients with a primary diagnosis of intellectual disability 3) Data from the Directorate General of Prisons on the prevalence of ID in Prison Psychiatric Hospitals was reviewed. Results: The data obtained from the TONI II test found 3.77% of the study population has an IQ below 70, and 7.54% has a borderline IQ rate. Assessment of penitentiary psychiatric hospitalization data showed these figures to be higher. Conclusions: The data from a Spanish prison population showed that ID levels were higher than those in the community, especially amongst prisoners requiring specialized psychiatric care. What is also evident is that adequate resources are required in prisons and in the community to provide better care for people with intellectual disabilities who are in the pathway of the criminal justice system (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tort, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dueñas, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicens, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zabala, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, DM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La prevalencia de discapacidad intelectual (DI) en el entorno penitenciario ha estado escasamente valorada. En España, a pesar de diversas aproximaciones o estimaciones no existen datos fiables respecto a las personas que sufren de DI. Objetivos: 1) Determinar la prevalencia de DI en una muestra de la población penitenciaria española, ubicada en módulos residenciales 2) Obtener datos sobre la prevalencia de DI en unidades y hospitales psiquiátricos penitenciarios. Métodos: 1) Se realizó una administración del TONI II en una submuestra (n: 398) de un estudio de prevalencia en cárceles españolas para identificar los internos con DI. 2) Se revisaron la memorias del Área Psiquiátrica Penitenciaria del Parc Sanitari Sant Joan de Deu para determinar los pacientes con diagnostico principal de DI. 3) Se revisaron datos de documentos de la Dirección General de Instituciones Penitenciarias para obtener la prevalencia de discapacidad intelectual en los Hospitales Psiquiátricos Penitenciarios. Resultados: Los datos del TONI II fueron que un 3,77% de la población estudiada presenta un Coeficiente Intelectual (CI) por debajo de 70, y un 7,54% presentaba una inteligencia límite. Siendo mayores cuando valoramos la hospitalización psiquiátrica. Conclusiones: Los datos de DI en población penitenciaria presentan unas tasas elevadas, especialmente aquellos que precisan una atención psiquiátrica especializada. Lo que pone de relieve que son necesarios recursos (penitenciarios y comunitarios) para una mayor atención de las personas con DI durante el recorrido en el ámbito penal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. sanid. penit;18(1): 25-33, mar.-jun. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149860</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La discapacidad intelectual y el ámbito penitenciario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6934^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6934^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6934^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6934^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
