<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112964</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Direct clinical practice: conceptual analysis. Central competence for the development Of advanced nursing practice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The recent implementation in Spain of post degree in nursing has made possible the emergence of new advanced profiles, which direct clinical practice is the core competence. Objective: To analyse and clarify the term of direct clinical practice. Methodology: A conceptual analysis was carried out based on Rogers&#146;s evolutionary approach. A review of the literature was made in the following data bases: PubMed, CINAHL, ISI Web of Knowledge, Psych INFO (Ovid) and Cochrane Library. Furthermore, five books about advanced practice nursing were revised. Results: 7 articles and 4 books based on the inclusion criteria were selected. After their analysis the concept of direct clinical practice is defined. Conclusions: This paper clarifies the concept of direct clinical practice and helps to have a stronger base of knowledge. This will serve as foundation to improve and perfect the conceptualization of this term(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pardavila Belio, Miren Idoia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canga Armayor, Navidad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vivar, Cristina G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La aprobación en España del posgrado en enfermería ha posibilitado el surgimiento de nuevos perfiles profesionales más avanzados, cuya competencia central es la práctica clínica directa. Objetivo: analizar y clarificar el término de práctica clínica directa. Metodología: se realizó un análisis conceptual basado en el método evolutivo de Rogers. Para ello, se llevó a cabo una revisión de la evidencia disponible en Pubmed, CINAHL, ISI Web of Knowledge, PsychINFO (Ovid) y la Cochrane Library. Asimismo, se revisaron cinco libros referentes en la práctica avanzada de enfermería. Resultados: se seleccionaron siete artículos y cuatro libros en base a los criterios de inclusión. Del análisis de los mismos se ofrece una definición del término práctica clínica directa. Conclusiones: este trabajo clarifica el concepto de práctica clínica directa y con ello contribuye a tener una base de conocimiento más sólida que sirva de fundamento para mejorar y perfeccionar la conceptualización del término PCD(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;36(5): 364-370, mayo 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112964</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Práctica clínica directa: análisis conceptual. Competencia central para el desarrollo de la práctica avanzada en enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9920^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53366^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9920^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9920^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9920^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4579^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4579^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53368^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7755^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4579^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53368^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53368^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4579^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4579^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201305</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
