<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100834</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Drug interactions and clinical relevance: It all began with cheese</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In a drug interaction, the effects of one drug can be increased or decreased or a quite new effect produced by the previous, concurrent or subsequent administration of another substance, including prescription and nonprescription drugs, food, tobacco or alcohol. The effect of the interaction can be desirable, inconsequential, or adverse. The increasing number of drugs available and the increasing use of multidrug therapeutic regimens enhance the potential for drug interactions. However, in clinical practice, most interactions are not significant or rarely of significance. It is when the interaction leads to adverse consequences that it comes to the attention of the patient and physician. Interactions may occur by pharmacokinetic or pharmacodynamics mechanisms. Pharmacokinetic interactions represent the modification of one substance (the interacting substance) on the ADME processes of absorption, distribution, metabolism or excretion of a drug (the index drug). Subsequently, It may lead to changes in the concentration of the index drug at the receptor sites. Drug interactions with a pharmacodynamic basis involve actions on the same receptor or physiological systems through either synergism or antagonism. Many drug interactions can be predicted if the pharmacodynamics effects, pharmacokinetic properties and mechanisms of action of the interacting agents are known. The most obvious interactions are those producing altered pharmacokinetic of drugs with a low therapeutic index (oral anticoagulants, antidiabetic drugs, digoxin, benzodiazepines and immunosuppressant and cytotoxic drugs)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carrillo Norte, Juan Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Postigo Mota, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Una interacción medicamentosa ocurre cuando se produce una alteración medible cuantitativa (aumento o disminución), o cualitativa (aparición de un efecto, síntoma o signo no habitual), de la respuesta de un fármaco, como consecuencia de la administración previa o concomitante de otra sustancia química, ya sea esta otro fármaco, una hierba medicinal, cualquier componente alimentario de la dieta, tabaco, alcohol o drogas ilegales. La interacción puede no tener consecuencias, ser beneficiosa, o producir resultados adversos en el paciente. Debido a la disponibilidad de múltiples fármacos y regímenes terapéuticos, el riesgo potencial de interacciones farmacológicas es muy elevado. No obstante, en la práctica clínica, la mayoría de ellas carecen de relevancia clínica. Sólo cuando se producen reacciones adversas como resultado de la interacción, esta adquiere interés para el médico y el paciente. Las interacciones pueden ocurrir a nivel farmacocinético o farmacodinámico. En las farmacocineticas la sustancia precipitante actúa sobre los procesos de la ADME (absorción, distribución, metabolismo o excreción de fármacos) del fármaco objeto y, como consecuencia, se producen cambios en la concentración del medicamento a nivel de la biofase. Las interacciones con un mecanismo farmacodinámico ocurren en el mismo receptor o en un sistema fisiológico determinado, produciendo un sinergismo o antagonismo de la respuesta farmacológica. Las interacciones pueden predecirse y evitarse si se conocen los efectos farmacodinámicos, las propiedades farmacocinéticas y los mecanismos de acción de los agentes que interaccionan en el proceso. Las más evidentes son aquellas que producen una alteración en la farmacocinética de un fármaco con un bajo índice terapéutico (anticoagulantes orales, antidiabéticos, digoxina, benzodiacepinas, inmunosupresores y quimioterapicos)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;35(4): 248-258, abr. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100834</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Interacciones farmacológicas y relevancia clínica. Todo comenzó con el queso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1593^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4116^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4409^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
