<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132632</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Glycemic response to Carob (Ceratonia siliqua L) in healthy subjects and with the in vitro hydrolysis index</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this study was to determine the in vivo glycemic index of carob tablets with healthy subjects and to determine the in vitro glycemic index of carob tablets and carob flour by the hydrolysis index. Seven healthy volunteers consumed portions of carob tablets containing 26g of available carbohydrate. Their capillary blood was taken at intervals after carob or glucose consumption. The glycemic hydrolysis index by an in vitro technique was based in the release of glucose after enzymatic treatment of carob tablets and carob flour. The determination of the fiber content was performed using the enzymatic- gravimetric method. By the in vivo determination, the estimated glycemic index of carob tablets could be considered low (&amp;#8804; 55). By the in vitro determination, the estimated glycemic index ranged from 40.1+0.02 of carob tablets to 40.6+0.05 of carob flour. The total fiber values obtained for carob flour samples were from 42.6% ± 0.49 to 42.9% ± 0.68 with no statistical significant differences between samples. Carob tablets and carob flour could be classified as low glycemic index food and low glycemic load food. Carob flour is a high fiber food, containing mainly high levels of insoluble fiber (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramos Dorneles, Marcelo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carneiro Hecke Krüger, Cláudia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomzack Tulio, Lindamir</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos, Leticia Fuganti</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, Luciana Milek dos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente estudio tuvo como objetivos determinar el índice glucémico in vivo de barras de algarroba en individuos saludables y determinar el índice glucémico in vitro  de barras de algarroba y harina de algarroba, utilizando el índice de hidrólisis. Siete voluntarios saludables consumieron porciones de barras de algarroba conteniendo 26 g de carbohidratos. Se han recolectado muestras de sangre capilar tras la ingestión de barras de algarroba y de glucosa. El índice de glucosa in vitro se basó en la liberación de glucosa tras el tratamiento enzimático de barras de harina de algarroba. La determinación de fibras se realizó por el método enzimático-gravimétrico. Por la determinación in vitro, el índice glicémico estimado puede ser considerado bajo (&amp;#8804; 55). Por la determinación in vitro, el índice glicémico varió entre 40.1±0.02 (barras) y 40.6±0.05 (harina). El tenor de fibra alimentaria encontrado fue del 42.6% ± 0.49 a 42.9% ± 0.68, sin diferencias estadísticas entre las  uestras. Las barras de harina de algarroba pueden ser clasificadas como alimentos de bajo índice glicémico y de baja carga glucémica. La harina de algarroba presenta alto tenor de fibras alimentarias, sobre todo fibras insolubles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(1): 482-487, ene. 2015. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132632</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Respuesta glucémica de algarrobo (Ceratonia siliqua L) en sujetos sanos y con el índice de hidrólisis in vitro</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52203</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8523</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1812^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5824</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5566^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23102^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13990</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55451</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37656</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
