<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160411</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical perspectives on the management of bleeding in patients on oral anticoagulants: the DECOVER Study (DElphi Consensus on oral COagulation and therapy action reVERsal)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To evaluate the level of agreement between hematologists and emergency medicine physicians regarding the best clinical practices for managing bleeding and anticoagulant reversal. Methods. Nationwide Spanish multicenter Delphi method study with a panel of experts on anticoagulation and the management of bleeding. Two survey rounds were carried out between April and September 2015. Consensus was reached when more than 75% of the panelists scored items in the same tertile. Results. Fifteen hematologists and 17 emergency medicine specialists from 14 Spanish autonomous communities participated. Consensus was reached on the use of both hemodialysis and an activated prothrombin complex concentrate (PCC) to antagonize significant/major bleeding in patients taking dabigatran. Use of an activated PCC was considered sufficient for patients on rivaroxaban or apixaban. The panel did not consider any PCC to be both effective and safe. Tests for activated partial thromboplastin, thrombin, diluted thrombin, and ecarin clotting times were considered useful in patients treated with dabigatran. A specific anti-Xa activity assay was suggested for patients who developed bleeds while treated with rivaroxaban or apixaban. Specific antidotes for direct-acting oral anticoagulants would be useful when severe bleeding occurs according to 97% of the panelists. Such antidotes would substantially change current treatment algorithms. Conclusion. The points of consensus were generally in line with clinical practice guidelines, but the Delphi process revealed that there are aspects of the clinical management of bleeding that require unified criteria. The need for specific antidotes for direct-acting oral anticoagulants was emphasized (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Coll-Vinent, Blanca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Porras, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marco, Pascual</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suero, Coral</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roldán, Vanesa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camats, Míriam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soulard, Stéphane</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateo, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lecumberri, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Evaluar el grado de acuerdo entre hematólogos y urgenciólogos respecto a las mejores prácticas para el manejo de hemorragias y la reversión de la anticoagulación oral. Método. Estudio Delphi multicéntrico español con médicos expertos en anticoagulación y manejo de hemorragias. Se realizaron dos rondas de preguntas entre abril y septiembre de 2015. Se obtenía consenso cuando el 75% o más de los panelistas puntuaban en el mismo tercil. Resultados. Se encuestó a 15 hematólogos y 17 urgenciólogos de 14 comunidades autónomas. La hemodiálisis y la administración de concentrados de complejo protrombínico (CCP) activado fueron tratamientos consensuados para antagonizar una hemorragia relevante/mayor en pacientes tratados con dabigatrán. Para rivaroxabán y apixabán solo se consideró el CCP. El panel no valoró ningún CCP como eficaz y seguro a la vez. Los tiempos de tromboplastina parcial activado, trombina, ecarina y de trombina diluido se indicaron para pacientes tratados con dabigatrán y la actividad anti-Xa específica para los tratados con rivaroxabán y apixabán cuando presentan una hemorragia. Disponer de un antídoto específico para el tratamiento de los anticoagulantes orales de acción directa (ACOD) sería útil en caso de hemorragia grave (97%) y supondría un cambio sustancial en el algoritmo de tratamiento actual (97%). Conclusiones. Los resultados estuvieron en general alineados con las guías de práctica clínica, pero mostraron que existen áreas de mejora en la unificación de criterios sobre el manejo de los pacientes con hemorragias, y destacan la necesidad de disponer de antídotos específicos para ACOD (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);29(1): 18-26, feb. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160411</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perspectivas clínicas del manejo de la hemorragia en el paciente tratado con anticoagulante oral: estudio DECOVER</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d938^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55911^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4711</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55927^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
