<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101315</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Guillain-Barré syndrome: clinical presentation and prognosis in children under six years-old</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Guillain-Barré syndrome (GBS) is an acute polyneuropathy that is difficult to diagnose in young children.   Objectives: To review the form of presentation of GBS in children under six years-old at the time of onset and the symptoms they had until the diagnosis, the findings in the complementary tests, and the progression and prognosis.                       Patients and methods: All patients less than 6 years-old who fulfilled the Asbury et al criteria for the diagnosis of GBS were reviewed.                               Results: Eight patients with a mean age of 3.4years were included. Of those 75% recorded a previous infection. The symptoms prior to the diagnosis were very heterogeneous which entailed a wide differential diagnosis with many complementary examinations. The mean time to diagnosis was 8.5 days. All of them (100%) had motor involvement in the lower limbs, 75% in the upper limbs and 12% in the respiratory muscles. Sensory and cranial nerve involvement was observed in 62.5% and 25%, respectively. Admission to intensive care was required for 25% of the patients. Albumino-cytological dissociation was observed in the CSF in 83.3% and all the electrophysiological tests were positive with different patterns. The prognosis was excellent in all patients.                                               Conclusions: GBS in children under 6 years-old is difficult to diagnosis due to the signs of onset often being unspecific. This entails a wide differential diagnosis, with the subsequent diagnostic delay. There is a good prognosis in all the electrophysiological sub-types in this age group(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Vico, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Lledó, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Gosálvez, F. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El síndrome de Guillain-Barré (SGB) es una polineuropatía aguda de difícil diagnóstico en la primera infancia.                                   Objetivos: Revisar la forma de presentación del SGB en niños menores de 6 años atendiendo al tiempo de evolución y sintomatología que presentaron hasta el diagnóstico, los hallazgos en las pruebas complementarias y la evolución y pronóstico.                                                Pacientes y métodos: Revisamos a todos los pacientes menores de 6 años que cumplieran los criterios de Asbury et al para el diagnóstico de SGB.                   Resultados: Se incluyó a 8 pacientes, con una media de edad de 3,4 años. El 75% se registró la presencia de un agente infeccioso previo. La sintomatología previa al diagnóstico fue de carácter muy heterogéneo, lo que conllevó un amplio diagnóstico diferencial y multitud de exploraciones complementarias. El tiempo medio al diagnóstico fue de 8,5 días. El 100% presentó afectación motora de miembros inferiores, el 75% de miembros superiores y el 12% de musculatura respiratoria. La afectación sensitiva fue del 62,5% y la de pares craneales del 25%. Requirieron ingreso en cuidados intensivos un 25%. Se objetivó disociación albúmino-citológica en el líquido cefalorraquídeo (83,3%) y positividad de todos los estudios electrofisiológicos con distintos patrones. El pronóstico fue excelente en todos los pacientes.                                 Conclusiones: El SGB en niños menores de 6 años es de difícil diagnóstico por la inespecificidad de las primeras manifestaciones en muchas ocasiones. Esto implica un amplio diagnóstico diferencial y retraso diagnóstico. Es relevante, el buen pronóstico en este grupo de edad de todos los subtipos electrofisiológicos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);76(2): 69-76, feb. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101315</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Guillain-Barré: presentación clínica y evolución en menores de 6 años de edad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9672^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9672^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11553^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34211^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34211^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11553^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4667^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34211^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34211^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4667^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34211^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
