<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141083</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The Act of Promotion of Personal Autonomy and Long-Term Care. Reflections and recommendations for better development</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present article provides a critical analysis of the state of affairs of the care of dependent individuals and proposals for reform of social protection systems for dependency &#150; especially the Act of Promotion of Personal Autonomy and Long-Term Care. The existing form of public coverage is linked to the theory of public finance. Against this background, a series of recommendations are made to achieve the goals of this important component of the welfare state (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Casasnovas, Guillem</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El análisis de situación y propuestas de reforma de los sistemas de protección social para la dependencia, y en especial para la ley española de dependencia, se entronca en este trabajo en la teoría de la hacienda pública en lo que atañe a la naturaleza de la intervención en el aseguramiento social de los cuidados de larga duración. Ello permite un conjunto de consideraciones introductorias que, de forma resumida, permiten mantener una guía para las proposiciones más descriptivas al respecto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;25(supl.2): 125-130, dic. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141083</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La Ley de autonomía y dependencia. Reflexiones y recomendaciones para su mejor desarrollo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50230</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5516</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31424^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13330^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36316</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13330^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31424^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50003</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
