<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91633</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hyperferritinemia, ferropenia and metabolic syndrome in a patient with a new mutation of gene TFR2 and another in gene FTL. A family study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objetives: Hyperferritinemia is a common finding in clinical practice. This condition can be congenital or acquired, although it is not always associated with iron overload. Genetic hyperferritinemia is associated with iron overload, hereditary hemochromatosis, or cataracts that progress without iron overload (hereditary hyperferritinemia-cataract syndrome). Metabolic syndrome is associated with hyperferritinemia and mild iron overload, with no increase in transferrin saturation. We report a family with hyperferritinemia. Patients and methods: We present the study of a family with dual hyperferritinemia (congenital and acquired) and an analysis of the genes involved in iron metabolism. Results: Patients with hereditary hyperferritinemia-cataract syndrome have the mutation c.-167C&gt;T in the FTL gene; patients with metabolic syndrome present a new mutation in the TFR2 gene (c.1259G&gt;A, p.Arg420His).Conclusions: The phenotypic and genotypic diversity of hyperferritinemia makes it a diagnostic challenge for clinicians. Basic research and clinical research should be combined to ensure better patient care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno Carralero, Maria Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>del Castillo Rueda, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuadrado Grande, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morán Jiménez, María Josefa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: La hiperferritinemia es un hallazgo común en la práctica clínica diaria que puede ser congénita o adquirida y no siempre se asocia con sobrecarga férrica. La hiperferritinemia genética puede acompañarse de sobrecarga, como en la hemocromatosis hereditaria, o cursar con cataratas sin sobrecarga, en ese caso es el síndrome hereditario de hiperferritinemia y cataratas. Por otra parte, el síndrome metabólico puede cursar con hiperferritinemia y sobrecarga leve-moderada pero sin aumento de saturación de transferrina. Presentamos una familia con hiperferritinemia.Pacientes y método: Estudio de una familia con hiperferritinemia dual, congénita y adquirida, con análisis de los genes implicados en el metabolismo del hierro. Resultados:Los pacientes con síndrome hereditario de hiperferritinemia y cataratas tienen la mutación c.-167C&gt;T en heterocigosis en el gen FTL. El paciente con síndrome metabólico presenta, además, una nueva mutación en heterocigosis en el gen TFR2 (c.1259G&gt;A, p.Arg420His). Conclusiones: La hiperferritinemia, habitualmente casual, supone para el clínico un reto diagnóstico por sus diversidades fenotípicas y genotípicas, siendo necesario aunar esfuerzos en investigación básica y clínica para la asistencia de los pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);137(2): 68-72, jun. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91633</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hiperferritinemia, ferropenia y síndrome metabólico en un paciente con una nueva mutación en el gen TFR2 y otra en el gen FTL. Estudio familiar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5402^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19035^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16595^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6582^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19330^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
