<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-27403</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spontaneous cerebral calcium embolism</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION: Calcium embolism is an uncommon cause of stroke which may not be diagnosed in cases which do not involve cardiac surgery or catheterization. The emboli may come from cardiac valves or calcified atheroma of the aortic or carotid arteries. CASE REPORTS: Two patients with cerebral infarcts secondary to spontaneous calcium embolism confirmed by neuro imaging. In both cases on CT scans there were dense points corresponding to calcified material within the middle cerebral artery or one of its branches. In the first case migration of the calcified point following the course of the artery was observed. CONCLUSIONS: Cranial CAT scans are essential for diagnosis of calcium embolism. Migration of the calcified point confirms the diagnosis. It is still not clear whether valve replacement is necessary in these patients and treatment with antiaggregants and/or anticoagulants is controversial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La embolia cálcica es una causa infrecuente de ictus que puede pasar desapercibida en los casos que no se asocian a cirugía o cateterismo cardíaco. Los émbolos pueden originarse en válvulas cardíacas o en ateromas calcificados de aorta o carótida. Casos clínicos. Dos pacientes con infarto cerebral secundario a embolismo de calcio espontáneo confirmado por neuroimagen. En ambos se apreciaron en la TAC puntos densos correspondientes a material cálcico dentro de la arteria cerebral media o alguna de sus ramas. En el primero además se observó la migración del punto cálcico siguiendo el trayecto de la arteria. Conclusiones. La TAC craneal es fundamental para el diagnóstico de embolismo cálcico. La migración del punto cálcico confirma el diagnóstico. La necesidad de recambio valvular en estos pacientes no se ha establecido suficientemente y el empleo de tratamiento antiagregante o anticoagulante es controvertido (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;34(4): 354-357, feb. 2002.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Embolismo cálcico cerebral espontáneo</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Gil-Néciga, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mir, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Fernández, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil-Peralta, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-27403</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d2591</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1953</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34257</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2148</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7163</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
