<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103765</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Determinants of poor mental health in people aged 16 to 64 residing in a large city</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Know what factors determine the poor mental health in the city of Madrid. Material and methods. Cross-sectional study Health Survey of the City of Madrid (ESCM&#146;05), analyzed 5746, persons aged 16 to 64 years, in the years 2004-2005. Dependent variable was obtained from the General Health Questionnaire (GHQ-12), was considered score above 2. Independent variables included sociodemographic factors, life style, health and environmental issues. The quality of life related to health (HRQOL) was measured with the questionnaire COOP / WONCA. Results. The overall prevalence of poor mental health was19.2%, p &lt;0.05 for gender, age group 16 to 24 years and lower social classes. The predictors most strongly associated with poor mental health in the multiple regression are: women OR=1.48 (1.23-1.78), minors OR=3.21 (2.40-4.29), immigrant economic OR=1.33 (1.06-1.68), smoking or drinking alcohol OR=1.22 (1.02-1.49) and 1.31 (1.09-1.57),chronic disease OR=1.47 (1.21-1.79), sleeping less 8 hours OR=1.41 (1.17-1.68), having fair or poor health status perception OR=1.65 (1.22-2.22), self-perceived poor quality of life OR=1.18 (1.15-1.22), and limited social activities OR=1.34 (1.07-1.69).Conclusions. The mental health problems are highly prevalent in this city. Being woman, young, economic migrant, worse lifestyles, poor quality of life refered or limited social activities are the factors that force to explain the association with poor mental health(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Esteban, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Cordero, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez García, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puerto, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Barrera, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil de Miguel, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. Conocer los factores que determinan la mala salud mental en la ciudad de Madrid. Material y métodos. Estudio transversal con la Encuesta de Salud de la Ciudad de Madrid (ESCM&#146;05), analizando 5.746personas de 16 a 64 años, en los años 2004-2005. La variable dependiente fue obtenida del Cuestionario General de Salud (GHQ-12), considerando la puntuación superior a 2. Las variables independientes incluyen factores sociodemográficos, hábitos de vida, salud y medio ambiente. La calidad de vida en relación con la salud (CVRS) se midió con el cuestionario COOP / WONCA. Resultados. La prevalencia general de mala salud mental fue del 19,2%, con p &lt;0,05 para sexos, grupo de edad de 16 a 24 años y clases sociales menos favorecidas. Los predictores más fuertemente asociados con mala salud mental en la regresión múltiple son: mujer OR=1,48 (1,23-1,78), menor de edad OR=3,21 (2,40-4,29), inmigrante económico OR=1,33 (1,06-1,68), fumar o beber alcohol OR=1,22 (1,02-1,49) y 1,31(1,09-1,57), tener una enfermedad crónica OR=1,47 (1,21-1,79),dormir menos de 8 horas OR=1,41 (1,17-1,68), tener regular o mala percepción del estado de salud OR=1.65 (1,22-2,22), autopercepción de mala calidad de vida OR=1,18 (1,15-1,22), y limitación en las actividades sociales OR=1,34 (1,07-1,69).Conclusiones. Los problemas de salud mental son muy prevalentes en esta ciudad. Ser mujer, joven, inmigrante económico, tener peores estilos de vida, referir mala calidad de vida o tener limitadas las actividades sociales, son los factores que más fuerza de asociación tienen para explicarla mala salud mental(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;35(2): 229-240, mayo-ago. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103765</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores que determinan la mala salud mental en las personas de 16 a 64 años residentes en una gran ciudad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28459</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
