<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-64633</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Correlation between clinical, dermatoscopic, and histopathologic variables in atypical melanocytic nevi</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Atypical melanocytic nevi are acquired melanocytic lesions that were described for the first time by Clark in studies of melanocytic nevi in patients with melanomas. Today, the use of dermatoscopy has made identification of this type of nevus much easier. Objective. Our aim was to study the correlation between the clinical, dermatoscopic, and histopathologic findings of melanocytic nevi and compare our findings with those of previous studies. We also aimed to investigate the value of dermatoscopy for identifying atypical melanocytic nevi. Material and methods. In this cross-sectional, observational study, 200 melanocytic lesions were analyzed in 166 patients examined between January 1, 2005 and December 31, 2005. We recorded the clinical, dermatoscopic, and histopathologic characteristics of each lesion and established the correlation between the different findings on a case-by-case basis. We then determined the agreement between diagnoses and assessed the value of dermatoscopy for identifying atypical melanocytic melanoma. Results. The clinical characteristics associated with atypical histology were a macular component (P &lt; 0.001), irregular borders, and presence of 3 or more colors. Asymmetry, diameter greater than 5 or 6 mm, and progression were not associated with atypical histopathologic characteristics (P &gt; 0.05). Agreement betweenclinical and histologic diagnosis was weak (kp = 0.38), whereas the agreement between dermatoscopic and histologic diagnosis was moderate (kp = 0.52). The area under the receiver operating characteristic curve for the model that included dermatoscopy was larger than that for the model that only included clinical data, and this difference was statistically significant. Conclusions. Atypical clinical features were not found to correspond to atypical histology. Dermatoscopy improved the accuracy of clinical diagnosis of atypical melanocytic nevus (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morales-Callaghana, AM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-García, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castrodeza-Sanz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peral-Martínez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miranda-Romero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los nevus melanocíticos atípicos (NMA) son lesiones melanocíticas adquiridas descritaspor primera vez por Clark en estudios de nevus melanocíticos (NM) en pacientes con melanomas. Actualmente, el uso de la dermatoscopia ha facilitado en gran medida la identificación de esta variante de nevus. Objetivo. Estudiar la correlación entre los hallazgos clínicos, dermatoscópicos e histopatológicos de los NM a estudio y comparar nuestros resultados con trabajos previos. Establecer el valor de la dermatoscopia para la identificación de NMA. Material y métodos. Estudio observacional, transversal de 200 lesiones melanocíticas correspondientes a166 pacientes, llevado a cabo desde el 1 de enero de 2005 hasta el 31 de diciembre de 2005. Describimos las características clínicas, dermatoscópicas e histopatológicas de cada lesión y establecimos la correlación entre los diferentes hallazgos obtenidos, caso por caso. Posteriormente determinamos la concordancia entre diagnósticos y establecimos el valor de la dermatoscopia para la identificación de NMA. Resultados. Las características clínicas que se asociaron a atipia histológica fueron componente macular (p &lt; 0,001), bordes irregulares y presencia de tres o más colores. La asimetría, diámetro mayor de 5 o 6 mm ola evolución no se correspondieron con atipia desde el punto de vista histopatológico (p &gt; 0,05). La concordancia entre diagnóstico clínico e histológico fue baja (índice kappa ponderado [kp]: 0,38), mientras que entre diagnóstico dermatoscópico e histológico fue moderada (índice kp: 0,52). Mediante curvas ROC (receiver operating characteristic) comprobamos que el modelo que contenía la dermatoscopia presentaba un incremento bajo la curva estadísticamente significativo respecto al modelo que sólo incluía los datos clínicos. Conclusiones. La atipia clínica no es equivalente a atipia histológica. La dermatoscopia mejora la precisión del diagnóstico clínico de NMA (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;99(5): 380-389, jun.-jul. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-64633</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de correlación clínica, dermatoscópica e histopatológica de nevus melanocíticos atípicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9695^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8714^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30694^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8714^s22071</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8714^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8714^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9695^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200807</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
