<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052195</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Extratesticular intraescrotal neurofibroma: case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: We report a rare case of    intrascrotal neurofibroma in an adult patient not affected by neurofibromatosis (NF1).    METHODS: Clinical diagnosis of asymptomatic right scrotal lipoma and left symptomatic inguinal hernia carried the    patient to the surgical treatment. After the first surgical step of left hernia repair, we proceeded to the excision by an inguinoscrotal approach of a voluminous whitish neoplastic mass occupying the whole left scrotum and not involving homolateral testis.    RESULTS/CONCLUSIONS: The histopathologic diagnosis was of neurofibroma, a benign neoplasm of peripheral nerves which rarely occurs at genital level</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Trovarelli, Stefano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miracco, Clelia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tripodi, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ponchietti, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tallis, Valeria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Presentamos un caso muy raro de neurofibroma localizado en la región genital a nivel intraescrotal en un paciente mayor que no estaba afectado por neurofibromatosis (NF1).    MÉTODOS: El diagnóstico clínico de lipoma escrotal derecho    asintomático y de hernia inguinal izquierda sintomática llevó al paciente al quirófano. Tras la primera intervención en la que se hizo la reparación de la hernia, se quitó una masa neoplástica de aspecto blanquecino y brillante que ocupaba el hemiescroto derecho procediendo a través de una incisión inguinoescrotal, sin sacrificar el testículo homolateral.    RESULTADOS/CONCLUSIONES: El examen anatomopatológico    etiquetó la masa quitada de neurofibroma, una neoplasia benigna de raro hallazgo a nivel genital</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;59(9): 905-908, nov. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052195</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neurofibroma intraescrotal extratesticular: aportación de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6711^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9647^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12992^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14115^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9647^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
