<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043138</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of the palmar pallor sign in the diagnosis of anemia in children in Bucaramanga (Colombia)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The prevalence of anemia in children from Santander (Colombia), is nearly 28 %. Economic conditions make it difficult to perform the hemoglobin test in all children with suspected anemia. The palmar pallor sign has been recommended by the World Health Organization (WHO) and the Pan-American Health Organization for the diagnosis of anemia in children aged less than 5 years old; however, the yield of the test has not been established in Colombian communities. The aims of the present study were to establish the efficiency of the test and to determine its reproducibility.                 Methods: The palmar pallor sign was evaluated in a sample of 167 children attending a low complexity hospital located in a deprived area of Bucaramanga city. Two pediatricians determined the presence of the sign, according to criteria from the "Integrated Management of Childhood Illness" strategy of the WHO and the Pan-American Health Organization. A hospital laboratory determined the concentration of hemoglobin in each of the children. Based on these data, the sensitivity, specificity, positive predictive value and negative predictive value were determined and the agreement between observers was established.                 Results: The prevalence of anemia in the sample evaluated was 28.74 %. Sensitivity was 33.33 %, specificity was 79.83 %, the positive predictive value was 40 % and the negative predictive value was 74.8 %. The reproducibility of the test was low. The yield of the test substantially improved when the hemoglobin cut-off point was reduced from 11 g/dl, which is the value proposed by the WHO, to 10.5 g/dl.                 Conclusions: Anemia is frequent in children aged less than 5 years old in Bucaramanga city. The Palmar pallor sign is a valuable tool for the diagnosis of severe anemia, but is much less useful in mild or moderate anemia. If the hemoglobin level proposed by the WHO were lower, the palmar pallor sign would be more useful</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cala Vecino, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sandoval Gómez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Latorre Latorre, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segovia Morales, O. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez Serrano, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedente: La prevalencia de anemia en niños de Santander (Colombia), está cercana al 28 %, pero las condiciones económicas dificultan la realización de hemoglobina en todos los niños sospechosos de padecerla. El signo de palidez palmar ha sido recomendado por la Organización Mundial de Salud (OMS) y Organización Panamericana de Salud (OPS) para el diagnóstico de anemia en menores de 5 años; sin embargo, el rendimiento de la prueba no se ha establecido en poblaciones de nuestro país. Los objetivos del estudio fueron establecer el rendimiento de dicha prueba y determinar su reproducibilidad.                 Métodos: El signo de palidez palmar fue evaluado en 167 niños, usuarios de un hospital de baja complejidad, en una zona económicamente deprimida de la ciudad de Bucaramanga. Dos pediatras determinaron la presencia del signo, según los criterios de la estrategia Atención Integrada a las Enfermedades Prevalentes de la Infancia, propuestos por la OMS y la OPS. El laboratorio de la institución determinó la concentración de hemoglobina de cada uno de ellos. A partir de estos datos se obtuvieron los valores de sensibilidad, especificidad, valor predictivo positivo y valor predictivo negativo. También se estableció la concordancia entre los observadores.                 Resultados: La prevalencia de anemia, en la muestra evaluada, fue el 28,74 %, la sensibilidad fue del 33,33 %, la especificidad del 79,83 %, el valor predictivo positivo del 40 % y el valor predictivo negativo del 74,80 %. La reproducibilidad de la prueba fue baja. El rendimiento de la prueba mejoró de manera sustancial cuando el punto de corte, en concentración de hemoglobina, se disminuyó de 11 g/dl, que es el propuesto por OMS, a 10,5 g/dl.                 Conclusiones: La anemia es frecuente en niños menores de 5 años de la ciudad de Bucaramanga (Colombia). El signo de palidez palmar es un recurso valioso para el diagnóstico de anemia grave pero, en los grados leve y moderado, carece de la concordancia y tiene poco rendimiento. Si se aceptan valores de corte inferiores, en las cifras de hemoglobina para la determinación de anemia, mejora la utilidad clínica del signo</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);63(6): 495-501, dic. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043138</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación del signo de palidez palmar para diagnóstico de anemia en niños de Bucaramanga (Colombia)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3137</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10354</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11241</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
