<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125188</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pre-operative training induces changes in the histomorphometry and muscle function of the pelvic floor in patients with indication of radical prostatectomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the efficacy of preoperative pelvic floor muscle training (PFMT) on histomorphometry, muscle function, urinary continence and quality of life of patients undergoing radical prostatectomy (RP). Material and methods: A prospective intervention clinical study was designed in 16 patients with indication of RP who were randomized into two groups. The Control Group received routine pre-surgical education (hygienic-dietary measures). The intervention group received a training session with supervised PFMT, three times a day, for four weeks, 30 days before the PR. Muscle function of the external urethral sphincter, contraction pressure of the levator ani, urinary continence and quality of life related to health (HRQoL) were evaluated before and after the intervention. At the end of the intervention and day of the surgery, samples of residual muscle tissue were obtained from the external sphincter muscle of the urethra for histomorphometric analysis. Results: After the intervention, those participants who carried out PFMT showed an increase in the cross-sectional area of the muscle fibers of the external urethral sphincter (1.313 ± 1.075 &amp;#956;m2 vs. 1.056 ± 844 &amp;#956;m2, p = 0.03) and higher pressure contraction of the levator ani (F = 9.188; p = 0.010). After catheter removal, 62% of patients in the experimental group and 37% in the control group showed no incontinence. After removal of the catheter, 75% of the experimental group did not require any pad compared to 25% in the control group (p = NS). There were no significant differences between the two groups in any of the HRQoL domains studied. Conclusions: Pre-surgical PFMT in patients with RP indication induces changes in the histology and function of the pelvic floor muscles, without changes in urogenital function and HRQoL. These results provide new evidence regarding the benefit of PFMT in preventing RP associated complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Hung, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ocampo-Trujillo, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, C. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez-Vélez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carbonell-González, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Blanco, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar el efecto del entrenamiento preoperatorio del suelo pélvico (EPSP) en la histomorfometría, función muscular, continencia urinaria y calidad de vida de pacientes con indicación de prostatectomía radical (PR). Material y métodos: Estudio prospectivo de intervención en 16 pacientes con indicación de PR aleatorizados en 2 grupos. Grupo control: educación prequirúrgica de rutina (medidas higiénico-dietéticas). Grupo de intervención: EPSP intensivo, 3 veces al día durante 4 semanas, 30 días previo a la PR. Antes y después de la intervención se evaluó la función del músculo esfínter externo de la uretra, presión de la contracción de los elevadores del ano, continencia urinaria y calidad de vida relacionada con la salud (CVRS). Al final de la fase de intervención y el día de la cirugía se tomaron muestras de tejido muscular residual del músculo esfínter externo de la uretra para análisis histomorfométrico. Resultados: Después de la intervención los participantes que realizaron EPSP presentaron un incremento en el área transversal de las fibras musculares del músculo esfínter externo de la uretra (1.313 ±1.075 &amp;#956;m2 vs. 1.056 ±844 &amp;#956;m2, p = 0,03) y mayor presión de la contracción de los elevadores del ano (F = 9,188; p = 0,010). Posterior a la retirada del catéter el 62% de los pacientes en el grupo experimental y el 37% del grupo control no presentaron incontinencia. El 75% de pacientes del grupo experimental después del entrenamiento no requirió el uso de protectores, con respecto al 25% del grupo control (p = NS). No se encontraron cambios en la CVRS por grupos en ninguno de los dominios estudiados. Conclusiones: El EPSP prequirúrgico en pacientes con indicación de PR induce cambios en la histología y función de los músculos del suelo pélvico, sin modificaciones en las funciones urogenitales y en la CVRS. Estos resultados proporcionan nuevas evidencias del beneficio del FMPP en la prevención de las complicaciones asociadas a la PR (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;38(6): 378-384, jul.-ago. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125188</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El entrenamiento preoperatorio induce cambios en la histomorfometría y función de los músculos del suelo pélvico en pacientes con indicación de prostatectomía radical</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20180^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54529^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
