<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111126</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Systemic lupus erythematosus. A case report with cutaneous presentation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pediatric Systemic lupus erythematosus is a multisystem chronic autoimmune disease with complex clinical manifestations. The clinical presentation has a cyclic nature. The initial symptoms are nonspecific. It affects multiple organs with specific symptoms depending on their location. Its skin manifestation may or may not occur with systemic manifestation. It is the great mimic that can simulate other diseases. The heterogeneous nature of lupus makes it a diagnosis medical challenge. Since there is not an only symptom or finding leading to the diagnosis of the disease, the American College of Rheumatology has established some criteria for the evaluation of suspicion of lupus. Treatment depends on the clinical manifestations, on the presence/absence of vital organs affectation and its approach must be multidisciplinary. The survival has improved in the last decade due to its early diagnosis and treatment. However, his prognosis continues to be serious. We present the clinical case of a 10 year old diagnosed girl with this condition (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Moya, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olmedo Sanlaureano, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente Cuevas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El lupus eritematoso sistémico pediátrico es una enfermedad autoinmunitaria crónica multisistémica con manifestaciones clínicas complejas. Presentación clínica de carácter cíclico. Los síntomas iniciales son inespecíficos. Afecta a múltiples órganos con síntomas específicos según su localización. Su manifestación cutánea puede presentarse junto con la manifestación sistémica o no. Es el gran imitador que puede simular otras enfermedades. La naturaleza heterogénea del lupus hace que sea un reto médico diagnóstico. Debido a que no existe un síntoma o hallazgo exclusivo para hacer el diagnóstico de la enfermedad, la American College of Rheumatology ha establecido unos criterios para su evaluación ante la sospecha de lupus. Su tratamiento depende de las manifestaciones clínicas, de la presencia/ausencia de afectación de órganos vitales y su abordaje debe ser multidisciplinar. Su supervivencia ha mejorado en la última década gracias a su diagnóstico y tratamiento precoz. Sin embargo, su pronóstico continúa siendo grave. Presentamos el caso clínico de una niña de diez años, diagnosticada de esta enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;15(57): 55e5-55e9, ene.-mar. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111126</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lupus eritematoso sistémico. A propósito de un caso clínico con presentación cutánea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8356^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8356^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8356^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4977^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4977^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4977^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12917^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12917^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
