<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166625</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Using consumer panels in public health observational studies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Consumer panels are a market research method useful for gathering information about low-frequency or difficult-access customers. The objective of this field-note is to explain our experience using this method in a cross-sectional public health study on the use of electronic cigarettes. After taking into account other non-probabilistic sampling techniques to obtain a huge sample of electronic-cigarette users (n=600), in the end we decided to use consumer panels (recruiters) because of the relative short duration of the field work and the high representativeness of the sample (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ballbè, Montse</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matilla Santander, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Sánchez, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lidón Moyano, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Esteve</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Sánchez, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fu, Marcela</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los paneles de consumidores son una técnica de investigación de mercados de gran utilidad para obtener información sobre clientes poco frecuentes o de difícil acceso. El objetivo de esta nota de campo es exponer nuestra experiencia usando esta técnica para un estudio transversal de salud pública sobre el uso de cigarrillos electrónicos. Después de valorar diferentes técnicas de muestreo no probabilístico para obtener una muestra elevada de usuarios de cigarrillos electrónicos (n=600), se ha optado por el uso del panel de consumidores debido al tiempo relativamente corto para obtener el gran tamaño muestral requerido para el estudio y una buena representatividad de la muestra (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;31(5): 436-438, sept.-oct. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166625</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso de paneles de consumidores en estudios observacionales de salud pública</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d55767^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29815^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3277</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3275^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37697</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
