<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126659</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of the intervention to quit smoking in people with mental illness</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: A high proportion of those seeking help to quit smoking have psychiatric disorders. The aim of this work is to analyze the effectiveness of those group smoking cessation programs who are usually employed in Primary Care and to compare their results to those obtained with non psychiatric patients. Methods: A descriptive longitudinal study with a one-year follow-up that evaluated smoking cessation groups conducted in a Primary Care setting between 2006 and 2011. Nineteen groups were carried out and 267 smokers were included; 36.3% had been diagnosed with a psychiatric disorder. The program consisted of five 90 minutes sessions (up to six weeks after abstinence) with telephonic follow-up for a year. Abstinence was verified by cooximetry at the end of the program and by self-declaration afterwards. Quantitative and qualitative variables were described, and the association between variables analyzed through binary logistic regression. Results: Self-declared continuous abstinence rate at 12 months of was 39.7%, being slightly higher, not in a non significant way, in women (43.1% vs. 35.1%; p: 0.18). Smokers with no history of psychiatric illness showed better abstinence rates, although without significant differences (42.9% vs. 34.0%; p: 0.16). There was no significant interaction between sex and psychiatric pathology. Those with a psychiatric disorder relapsed in a significantly higher rate during the first six weeks after abstinence [23.7% vs. 10.6%, p: 0.019; OR:1.90(1.08-3.36)]; relapse rates were similar afterwards (44,1% vs. 42,5%; p&gt; 0,8). Conclusions: This group intervention program for smoking cessation is effective. Although smokers with a present or previous history of psychiatric disorder may find abstinence harder to attain, they benefit from the intervention (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ayesta, F. Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Otero, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amo, Mónica del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Bardeci, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: Una alta proporción de quienes solicitan ayuda para dejar de fumar padecen trastornos psiquiátricos. El objetivo del trabajo es conocer si las intervenciones grupales recomendadas para la atención de personas fumadoras son efectivas en pacientes con antecedentes de patología psiquiátrica y si ello supone un factor pronóstico negativo. Métodos: Estudio descriptivo longitudinal con un año de seguimiento. Se evaluaron los grupos de deshabituación realizados en atención primaria durante el período 2006-11, incluyendo a 267 fumadores, 97 de ellos con antecedentes personales de patología psiquiátrica. Se realizaron cinco sesiones presenciales de 90 minutos (hasta 6ª semana abstinencia) y seguimiento telefónico posterior de 12 meses. La abstinencia fue comprobada por cooximetría en las sesiones presenciales y auto-declarada posteriormente. Análisis estadístico: descripción de variables cualitativas y cuantitativas, análisis comparativo de las mismas entre los dos grupos y regresión logística binaria según cesación. Resultados: La tasa de abstinencia continua declarada al año fue 39,7%, en mujeres del 43,1% y en hombres 35,1%; p: 0,18). Las personas fumadoras sin historia psiquiátrica presentaron tasas de abstinencia del 42,9% y las que sí la tenían del 34,0% (p: 0,16). No hubo interacción entre las variables sexo y patología psiquiátrica. Quienes presentaban antecedentes psiquiátricos recayeron en las 6 primeras semanas tras la abstinencia en el 23,7% y quienes no los tenían:10,6% [(p:0,019; OR:1,90 [LC95%:1,08-3,36)]; a partir de entonces las tasas de recaída fueron similares recayendo el 44,1% y un 42,5%, respectivamente (p&gt;0,8). Conclusiones: Las personas con patología psiquiátrica asociada o previa parecen encontrar más dificultades para dejar de fumar pero la intervención es efectiva en ambos grupos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;82(6): 629-638, nov.-dic. 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126659</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de una intervención para dejar de fumar en personas con enfermedad mental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23925</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29815</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36377</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
