<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041408</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Challenge in the treatment for pathological gambling</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper deals with the new developments in the treatment for pathological gambling, as well as with the challenges for further research. Assessment tools currently available, such as self-reports (SOGS or ASI) or clinical interviews (NODS) have many limitations. Reviewed studies about treatment of pathological gambling show that this disorder improves significantly with proposed therapies, with a success rate ranging from 50% to 80% of treated patients in a long-term follow-up. However, the choice treatment appears to be stimulus control and in vivo exposure with response prevention, followed by a cognitive-behavioral intervention in relapse prevention. Psychopharmacological therapy may have incremental benefit when patients have comorbid depression or high impulsivity. Responsible gambling may be a therapeutic option for young gamblers or people without a severe dependence. Further information is required about women gamblers and about the most convenient programs for them. The relevance of this review for clinical practice and future research in this field, as well as the unsolved problems, are commented upon</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Echeburúa, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se señalan los principales avances y los retos de futuro en el tratamiento de la ludopatía. Los instrumentos de evaluación del juego patológico actualmente disponibles, específicos (autoinformes, como el SOGS, o entrevistas clínicas, como el NODS) o más generales, como el ASI referido a la ludopatía, son aún muy limitados. Los estudios referidos a la terapia del juego patológico prueban que este cuadro clínico responde bien a los tratamientos ofertados, con unas tasas de éxito entre el 50% y el 80% de los casos tratados en un seguimiento a largo plazo. En concreto, la terapia de elección parece ser el control de estímulos y la exposición en vivo con prevención de respuesta, seguida por una intervención cognitivo-conductual en prevención de recaídas. La terapia psicofarmacológica puede ser complementaria cuando los pacientes tienen un estado de ánimo deprimido o un elevado nivel de impulsividad. El juego controlado puede ser una alternativa terapéutica para los jugadores jóvenes o que no presentan aún una dependencia severa. Se requiere aún más información sobre las mujeres jugadoras y sobre los programas terapéuticos más específicos para ellas. Se comentan las implicaciones de esta revisión para la práctica clínica y para las investigaciones futuras en este campo, así como las limitaciones actualmente existentes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);17(1): 11-16, ene. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041408</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Retos de futuro en el tratamiento del juego patológico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29633</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5855^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11417^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51780^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51780^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11417^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
