<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114148</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endoscopic treatment of orbital cellulitis in pediatric patients: Transethmoidal approach</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Orbital cellulitis is a septic process of the soft tissues behind the orbital septum and is the most frequent cause of the monolateral exophthalmos in pediatrics. Approximately 90% of the orbital cellulitis in pediatrics are associated to acute ethmoiditis. From the 01.01.2001 to 31.12.2010 we treated 36 patients, less than 18 years-old affected by Chandler stage II, III or IV orbital cellulitis. The inflammation was resolved medically in 6 patients. In the 30 cases that showed no improvement in 48-72 h, an endoscopic drainage of the pus was performed by the transethmoidal route. In children, an adenoidectomy should be included, in order to eliminate eventual infections of this lymphatic organ. Endoscopic treatment has resulted in rapid resolution of disease without any complications. In addition, postoperative discomfort is minimal, with a rapid return to daily activities (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Volino, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parente, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iemma, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cavaliere, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Troisi, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La celulitis periorbitaria es un proceso séptico de los tejidos blandos orbitarios y representa la causa más frecuente de exoftalmos unilateral en la infancia. Aproximadamente el 90% de los casos de celulitis periorbitaria en edad pediátrica se asocian a etmoiditis aguda. En el periodo 1.° de enero de 2001&#150;31 de diciembre de 2010 se han tratado 36 pacientes menores de 18 años con celulitis periorbitaria en los estadios II, III, IV de Chandler. Seis pacientes consiguieron la resolución de la inflamación con el tratamiento farmacológico. En 30 casos que no demostraron una mejoría en un período de 48 a 72 h, se efectuó un drenaje quirúrgico endoscópico del moco-pus con abordaje por vía transetmoidal. En los niños es muy importante no olvidar el tratamiento quirúrgico de la adenoiditis crónica que, con toda probabilidad, se presentará simultáneamente. La cirugía endoscópica permite una rápida resolución de la enfermedad sin ninguna complicación. Además, el malestar postoperatorio es mínimo, permitiendo un rápido regreso a las actividades cotidianas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;88(7): 271-275, jul. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114148</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento endoscópico de la celulitis orbital en la infancia: abordaje transetmoidal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13233^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24631^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52600^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13233^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13233^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52600^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
