<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95344</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of Giardia duodenalis assemblage B in humans in Zaragoza and León, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives To study Giardia duodenalis assemblages circulating in the health areas of two hospitals in Zaragoza and León (Spain).Method sA total of 211 stool samples with Giardia were genotyped by PCR of the tpi gene. Results Assemblage B was the most prevalent, both in Zaragoza (84,7%) and León (95,1%). The remaining isolates were identified as AII+B. Conclusions We detected the spread of G. duodenalis assemblage B in Zaragoza and in León, with an increase in its prevalence in Zaragoza compared to previous studies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aldana, Débora Esmeralda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seral, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Goñi, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Clavel, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Remacha, María Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción Se estudiaron los grupos genéticos (genotipos) de Giardia duodenalis circulantes en las áreas sanitarias de 2 hospitales de Zaragoza y León (España).Métodos Se genotiparon 211 muestras de Giardia mediante PCR del gen tpi. Resultados El genotipo B fue más prevalente tanto en Zaragoza (84,7%) como en León (95,1%). Los restantes aislados fueron identificados como AII+B. Conclusiones Predominó G. duodenalis genotipo B en Zaragoza y León, con aumento de su prevalencia en Zaragoza respecto a estudios anteriores  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;28(10): 710-712, dic. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95344</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de Giardia duodenalis genotipo B en humanos en Zaragoza y León, España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5974</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10459^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6011^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29400^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31670</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
