<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053786</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New case of an intra-abdominal testicular seminoma in an adult</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To present a new case of an Intra-abdominal Testicular Seminoma in an adult.    Methods/results: We report a 30 year old patient with cryptochidism, that after consulting to the emergency    service due to abdominal pain, was diagnosed an Intra-abdominal Testicular Seminoma.    Discussion: The incidence of testicular cancer in cryptorchidic testis is 3 to 48 times higher than in general    population. The existence of maldescended testis in adult population is rare in developed countries, due    to the normal practice of elective orchidopexia in children under 2 years old and orchiectomy in maldecended    testis in postpuberal pacients. In spite these measures of prevention, there are still isolated cases of    Intra-abdominal testicular tumors in adults</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cristóbal, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cristián Palma, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maccioni, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Presentar un nuevo caso de Seminoma de Testículo Abdominal en un paciente adulto y una    revisión de la literatura.    Observación clínica: Presentamos a un paciente de 30 años con criptorquidia, que luego de consultar    por dolor abdominal en el servicio de urgencias, es diagnosticado un Seminoma de testículo abdominal.    Discusión: La incidencia de cáncer testicular en testículos no descendidos es de 3 a 48 veces mayor que    en la población general. La existencia de testículos no descendidos en la población adulta es rara en los países    desarrollados debido a la práctica sistemática de orquidopexia electiva antes de los 2 años de vida y    orquiectomía en pacientes postpuberes con testículos no descendidos. A pesar de estas medidas de prevención,    aún se encuentran casos aislados de tumores testiculares abdominales en adultos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;31(2): 140-143, feb. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053786</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seminoma de testículo abdominal en un paciente adulto: reporte de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31051^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14115^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3473^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
