<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-65705</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-2597</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Food allergy has a great prevalence in children and sometimescan lead to potentially life-threatening situations. Thegreater prevalence in childhood than in adulthood reflectsboth the increased development of sensitizations in the firstyears of life and the possible loss of the same food sensitivitiesover time. Most of food allergies are acquired in thefirst 1 or 2 years of life whereas the development of immunologictolerance is a far more variable process dependingon both the individual child and the responsible food. The clinical spectrum of food allergies in children is verywide. Immediate reactions such as urticaria, angioedema oranaphylaxis are likely to be IgE-mediated and can usuallybe detected by cutaneous testing or measuring of specificserum IgE levels. Delayed-onset reactions such as atopicdermatitis or gastrointestinal allergic disorders, usually nonIgE-mediated, are more difficult to diagnose and often requirecomplex elimination or challenge protocols.More than 90% of IgE-mediated food allergies in childrenare caused by some few foods and can be classifiedin those probably transient (milk, egg, soy, wheat) and thoseprobably persistent (dry fruits, fish and shellfish).The key of diagnosis and management of food allergiesis correct identification and avoidance of offending antigen.This article provides a review of the natural history, diagnosisand evolutive management of the most common childhoodfood allergies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Berciano, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Caro, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La alergia a alimentos es un proceso de elevada prevalenciay posible riesgo vital en el niño. La mayor prevalenciaen la infancia que en la edad adulta es reflejo del desarrollode sensibilizaciones en los primeros años de vida yde la posible pérdida de las mismas a lo largo del tiempo.La mayoría de las alergias alimentarias se originan durantelos primeros 1 ó 2 años de vida, mientras que el desarrollode tolerancia es un proceso mucho más variabledependiendo de características individuales y del alimentoimplicado.El espectro clínico de la alergia a alimentos en el niño esmuy amplio. Por un lado las reacciones de tipo inmediatocomo urticaria, angioedema o anfilaxia son habitualmentemediadas por IgE y pueden ser fácilmente identificadasmediante pruebas cutáneas o determinación de IgE específica.Por otro lado las reacciones de tipo retardado como ladermatitis atópica o los trastornos alérgicos gastrointestinaleshabitualmente reconocen un mecanismo mixto o noIgE mediado y su diagnóstico es más difícil, basándose enprotocolos de eliminación y provocación.Más del 90% de las alergias alimentarias IgE mediadasen el niño son causadas por unos pocos alimentos. De ellas,unas son probablemente transitorias (leche, huevo, soja ytrigo) y otras probablemente persistentes (frutos secos, pescadosy mariscos).La clave para el diagnóstico y el tratamiento de la alergiaa alimentos es la correcta identificación y evitación delantígeno responsable.En este artículo se revisa la historia natural, el diagnósticoy el manejo evolutivo de las alergias alimentarias máscomunes en la infancia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Bol. pediatr;48(203): 21-36, ene.-mar. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-65705</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5651^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5651^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5651^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5651^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28219</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5651^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
