<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116555</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">EAU Guidelines on Surgical Treatment of Urinary Incontinence</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Context: The European Association of Urology (EAU) guidelines on urinary incontinence published in March 2012 have been rewritten based on an independent systematic review carried out by the EAU guidelines panel using a sustainable methodology. Objective: We present a short version here of the full guidelines on the surgical treatment of patients with urinary incontinence, with the aim of dissemination to a wider audience .Evidence acquisition: Evidence appraisal included a pragmatic review of existing systematic reviews and independent new literature searches based on Population, Intervention, Comparator, Outcome (PICO) questions. The appraisal of papers was carried out by an international panel of experts, who also collaborated in a series of consensus discussions, to develop concise structured evidence summaries and action-based recommendations using a modified Oxford system. Evidence summary: The full version of the guidance is available online (www.uroweb.org/guidelines/online-guidelines/). The guidance includes algorithms that refer the reader back to the supporting evidence and have greater accessibility in daily clinical practice. Two original meta-analyses were carried out specifically for these guidelines and are included in this report. Conclusions: These new guidelines present an up-to-date summary of the available evidence, together with clear clinical algorithms and action-based recommendations based on the best available evidence. Where high-level evidence is lacking, they present a consensus of expert panel opinion (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tubaro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burkhard, F. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Turner, W. H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pickard, R. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nambiar, A. K</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ridder, D. J. M. K. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Madden, T. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bosch, R. J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Neisius, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lucas, M. G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Contexto: Se ha vuelto a escribir la guía clínica de la Asociación Europea de Urología (EAU) sobre la incontinencia urinaria publicada en marzo de 2012, basándose en una revisión sistemática independiente llevada a cabo por el panel de guías clínicas de la EAU utilizando una metodología sostenible. Objetivo: Presentamos una versión resumida de la guía clínica completa sobre el tratamiento quirúrgico de pacientes con incontinencia urinaria, con el objetivo de difundirla a un público más amplio. Adquisición de la evidencia: La valoración de la evidencia incluyó una revisión pragmática de las revisiones sistemáticas existentes y nuevas búsquedas bibliográficas independientes, basadas en cuestiones sobre población, intervención, comparador, resultados (PICO). La evaluación de los trabajos fue realizada por un panel internacional de expertos, quienes también colaboraron en una serie de debates de consenso, para desarrollar breves resúmenes de evidencia estructurada y recomendaciones basadas en la acción utilizando un sistema modificado de Oxford. La versión completa de la guía clínica está disponible online (http://www.uroweb.org/guidelines/online-guidelines/). La guía clínica incluye algoritmos que remiten de nuevo al lector a la evidencia de apoyo, y son más inmediatamente utilizables en la práctica clínica diaria. Se llevaron a cabo 2 metaanálisis específicamente para esta guía clínica que se incluye en este informe. Conclusiones: Esta nueva guía clínica presenta un resumen actualizado de la evidencia disponible, junto con claros algoritmos clínicos y recomendaciones basadas en la acción fundamentadas en la mejor evidencia disponible. Cuando dicha evidencia no existe, presentan un consenso de opiniones de expertos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;37(8): 459-472, sept. 2013. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116555</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Guía clínica de la Asociación Europea de Urología sobre el tratamiento quirúrgico de la incontinencia urinaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13901^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
