<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99579</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pressure ulcers and chronic wounds: review of scientific evidence on their treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pressure ulcers (PU) and other chronic wounds (HC) is a health problem thoroughly studied. Numerous etiopathogenic theories attempt to justify the use of physical treatments, pharmacological or surgical, as well as different measures. The discussion about the most effective dressings can illustrate the statement. Clinical guidelines recommend several interventions, but few are the recommendations of level A. To clarify the highest quality scientific evidence underlying the variability in the  treatment of PU/HC have made a search of existing reviews in the Cochrane Library as well as third party sources. In the assessment of the various revisions have been able to conclude that overall the thousands of clinical trials on UPP and HC suffer from a lack of rigor in many cases preventing the realization of meta-analysis. High heterogeneity, use of intermediate variables, inadequate sample sizes, not by intention to treat analysis or selection bias, are the main disadvantages. Perhaps this can justify the small number of interventions that are supported with evidence of Grade A: 1) in UPP hydrocolloid dressing,  2) high compression, iodine cadexomer, pentoxifylline or double-layer graft venous ulcers, 3) stimulating Factor granulocyte colony-or hydrogel dressings in diabetic foot HC. Particularly striking is the lack of evidence for measures widely recommended by the guidelines as the use of postural changes, alternating air mattresses or surgical debridement (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Farouk Allam, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Berchez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Otero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oritz Arjona, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las úlceras por presión (UPP) y otras heridas crónicas (HC) son un problema de salud abundantemente estudiado. Numerosas teorías etiopatogénicas intentan justificar el uso de tratamientos físicos, farmacológicos o quirúrgicos, así como distintas medidas complementarias. La discusión sobre los apósitos más eficaces puede ilustrar la afirmación. Las Guías Clínicas recomiendan numerosas intervenciones pero escasas son las recomendaciones de nivel A. Para clarificar las evidencias  científicas de máxima calidad que sustentan la variabilidad en el tratamiento de las UPP/HC hemos realizado una búsqueda de las revisiones existentes en la Biblioteca Cochrane Plus así como en terceras fuentes. De la valoración de las diferentes revisiones hemos podido concluir que en líneas generales los miles de ensayos clínicos sobre UPP y HC adolecen de falta de rigurosidad impidiendo en muchas ocasiones la realización de metanálisis. Alta heterogenicidad, uso de variables intermedias, muestras de tamaño inadecuado, no análisis por intención de tratar o sesgos de selección, son los principales inconvenientes. Quizás esto pueda justificar el escaso número de intervenciones que encontramos respaldadas con una evidencia  de grado A: 1) Apósitos hidrocoloides en UPP; 2) Compresión elevada, yodo de cadexómero, pentoxifilina o los injertos de doble capa en ulceras venosas; 3)Factor estimulador de las colonias de granulocitos o los apósitos de hidrogel en las HC del pié diabético. Llama la atención la falta de pruebas para medidas ampliamente recomendadas por las guías como la utilización de cambios posturales, los colchones de aire alternante o el desbridamiento quirúrgico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;14(4): 229-235, oct.-dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99579</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Úlceras por presión y heridas crónicas: revisión de las evidencias científicas sobre su tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53366^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3664^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38828^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54277^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
