<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049047</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Congenital aniridia keratopathy treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To attempt to review the aniridia keratopathy        pathogenesis and establish a treatment protocol        according to the severity of the symptoms.        Methods: Personal experience in aniridic keratopathy        management and a bibliography review.        Results: The ocular manifestations of this anomaly        include defects of the cornea, glaucoma, lens subluxation,        cataracts, hypoplasia of the iris, fovea and        optic nerve, amblyopia and nystagmus. The keratopathy        occurs in a 20% of patients with aniridia. The        correct PAX6 expression is necessary for normal        corneal development, limbal stem cell activity and        correct corneal epithelial cell migration and adhesion.        Conclusions: The management of ocular surface        diseases due to limbal stem cell deficiency in aniridia        is complex but has changed in recent years, as        an understanding of the limbal stem cells and their        microenvironment has modified the therapeutic        approach. The use of autologous serum eye drops,        amniotic membrane transplantation, limbal transplantation        or cultivated limbal cell transplantation        have all been reported as a treatment for several ocular surface diseases</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rivas, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-García, J. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Lozano, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Garchitorena, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Revisar la patogenia de la queratopatía        por aniridia y establecer un protocolo de tratamiento        según su gravedad.        Métodos: Revisión bibliográfica y experiencia personal        en el manejo de pacientes con queratopatía        por aniridia.        Resultados: Las manifestaciones oculares de esta        anomalía incluyen defectos a nivel corneal, glaucoma,        subluxación del cristalino y cataratas, hipoplasia        de iris, fóvea y nervio óptico, ambliopía y nistagmus.        La queratopatía por aniridia ocurre en un        20% de los pacientes. La correcta expresión del gen        PAX6 es necesaria para el normal desarrollo corneal        y actividad de las células limbares así como la        correcta migración y adhesión de las células epiteliales.        Conclusiones: El manejo de los trastornos oculares        debidos a la deficiencia limbal asociada a la aniridia        es complejo pero ha cambiado en los últimos años.        El concepto de célula madre limbal y de su microambiente        ha modificado la aproximación terapéutica        de estos pacientes. El empleo del suero autólogo,        trasplante de membrana amniótica, trasplante de limbo o trasplante de células limbares cultivadas        han sido utilizados en el tratamiento de distintos        trastornos de la superficie ocular</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;81(8): 435-444, ago. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049047</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo terapéutico de la queratopatía asociada a aniridia congénita</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3333^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3334^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29361</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3334^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24520^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3333^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3334^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24520^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24520^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
