<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036834</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-3465</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New aspects on oral rehydration</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Infectious diarrhea in childhood continues to be a    major health problem worldwide. The morbidity and    mortality associated to this result from dehydration.    The discovery that sodium and glucose transport is    coupled in the small intestine was the scientific basis    of oral rehydration development. Oral rehydration    is safe and effective in the treatment of dehydration    attributable to diarrhea, but it does not reduce    the fecal fluid loss and the duration of diarrhea.    There have been attempts to improve the oral rehydration    solution in order to reduce the amount of    diarrhea. Most of these efforts have focused on the    enhancement of small-bowell absorption of fluids by    using hypo-osmolar solutions, the inclusion of aminoacids    or rice as substrates to stimulate sodium    absorption and the addition of non-digestible carbohydrates    or probiotics</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Román, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La diarrea infecciosa sigue siendo un problema    de salud importante en la edad infantil en todo el    mundo con una morbilidad y mortalidad asociada    secundaria a la deshidratación que produce. La evidencia    de un transporte de sodio acoplado al transporte    activo de glucosa en el intestino ha constituido    el fundamento de la rehidratación oral. Esta es segura    y efectiva en el tratamiento de la deshidratación,    pero no disminuye las perdidas fecales ni la    duración de la diarrea. Por ello se investigan nuevas    soluciones de rehidratación oral que disminuyan la    diarrea. Se ha buscado el aumento de la absorción    de fluidos por el intestino delgado mediante la disminución    de la osmolaridad de la solucion, la sustitución    de la glucosa por otros transportadores como    arroz o aminoácidos, y la adición de carbohidratos    complejos no digeribles o probióticos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediátrika (Madr.);25(3): 116-120, mar. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036834</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevos conceptos en rehidratación oral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1717^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36832^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5574^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24857^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13598^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3995^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6091^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3694^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
