<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157237</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Revascularisation pattern of ruptured flexor tendon grafts in anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction: a histological study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. For successful anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) reconstruction, revascularisation and histological maturation are necessary, as their failure can cause graft rupture. Purpose. The purpose of this study was to describe differences in the histological maturation of early failed plasty (less than 12 months after surgery) and late failed plasty (more than 12 months after surgery) in patients with re-rupture after ACL reconstruction with hamstring tendons. Material and methods. A descriptive observational study was conducted on a consecutive series of 20 patients whose ACL reconstruction had failed. Graft biopsy samples were obtained during the revision surgery from the proximal, medial, and distal graft remnants. The samples were evaluated by light microscopy, and the vascularity and maturation of the samples were established by histological scoring. Results. The most common aetiology of reconstruction failure (86.6%) was a specific event with non-contact mechanism. The patients with re-rupture of their ACL plasty less than 12 months after surgery had substance vessels that were less deep. The distal segment of the graft in those patients showed a delay in histological maturation with fewer collagen fibres. Conclusion. In patients whose ACL grafts failed less than 12 months after surgery, a lower distribution of blood vessels and collagen fibres was found that were less ordered in the distal graft. These results indicate a delay in maturation, which leads to a higher risk of graft failure (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Figueroa, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallegos, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaisman, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Scheu, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Para la reconstrucción exitosa del ligamento cruzado anterior (LCA) son necesarias la revascularización y la maduración histológica del injerto. Fallos en este proceso pueden causar la rotura del neoligamento. Objetivo. Describir las diferencias en la maduración histológica de plastias fallidas precoces (menos de 12 meses poscirugía) y tardías (más de 12 meses poscirugía) en pacientes con rerrotura de reconstrucción de LCA con tendones flexores. Materiales y métodos. Estudio observacional descriptivo. Serie consecutiva de 20 pacientes con fallo en la reconstrucción de LCA con tendones flexores. Muestras obtenidas mediante biopsia de los remanentes del injerto (porción proximal, corporal y distal) durante la cirugía de revisión. Las muestras fueron evaluadas por microscopia de luz y la vascularización y la maduración fueron establecidas mediante un puntaje histológico descrito en la literatura. Resultados. La causa más común de fallo de reconstrucción (86,6%) fue un evento identificable sin mediar traumatismo directo. Los pacientes con rotura precoz de la plastia del LCA presentaron vasos sanguíneos más superficiales en comparación con los con rotura tardía. El segmento distal del injerto en los pacientes con roturas precoces mostró una menor maduración histológica con menor número de fibras de colágeno. Conclusión. En los pacientes que presentaron fallos en las reconstrucciones de LCA precoces (dentro de los 12 meses poscirugía) encontramos una distribución menor de vasos sanguíneos y fibras de colágeno en la región distal del injerto. Estos resultados indican un retraso en la maduración, pudiendo generar mayor riesgo de fallo del injerto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);60(6): 372-377, nov.-dic. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157237</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patrón de revascularización de injertos de tendones flexores rotos en reconstrucción de ligamento cruzado anterior: un estudio histológico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36299^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28861^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14088^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14088^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28861^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14086^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9041^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14086^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
