<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038550</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-1375</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fulfilment of the activities of prevention and health promotion in a haemodialysis unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Prevention and health promotion activities are dealt with in the general population by the Programme of Preventive Activities and Health Promotion (PAPPS).Given their high joint morbility and immunological alteration, patients in haemodialysis (HD) should be highly compliant. The aim of our work was to use a transversal observational study on 72 patients in out patientHD to see the fulfilment of some activities of the adult sub-programme of the PAPPS. Results. Recommendations on lifestyle: smoking, 19.4% smoked an average 14.78 cigarettes/day. Alcohol, 41.7% were consumers of an average106.08+/-87.1 g/week in men and 79.6+/-91 g/week in women. Cancer prevention programme: breast cancer, average overall fulfilment was 54.4%; 42.8% completely, 35.7% incompletely and 21.4%had no mammography. Cervical cancer, average overall fulfilment was 59%; 56.2% fulfilling 100%, 43.7%incompletely and 18.75% of patients had had no kind of cervico-vaginal cytology. Infectious disease prevention programme: 19.4% were vaccinated against pneumococo; 22.2% against tetanus-diphtheria; 73.6% against influenza and 97.7% against Hepatitis B. Activities to prevent alternations in the vision of the elderly: average fulfilment was30.34%; 13.6% completely; 52.3% incompletely and34.1 % had no ophthalmologic revision. Compliance with the recommendations of the PAPPS in HD is low. Nursing should take an active role in increasing these activities</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gruss Vergara, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Mangas, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marco García, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gálvez Serrano, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Horna, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrés Vázquez, M. del Mar de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gago Gómez, M. del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piña Simón, Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Gómez, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernando Lucio, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las actividades de prevención y promoción de la salud son abordadas en la población general por el Programa de Actividades Preventivas y de Promoción de la Salud (PAPPS). Los pacientes en hemodiálisis (HD), por su elevada comorbilidad y alteración inmunológica deberían tener un elevado cumplimento de las mismas. El objetivo de nuestro trabajo fue conocer mediante un estudio observacional transversal en 72 pacientes en HD extrahospitalaria el cumplimiento de algunas actividades del subprograma del adulto de los PAPPS. Resultados. Recomendaciones sobre el estilo de vida: tabaquismo, el 19.4% fumaban una media de 14.78 cigarrillos/día. Alcohol, el 41.7% eran consumidores con una media de 106.08+/-87.1gr/semana en varones y 79.6+/-91 gr/semana en mujeres. Programa de prevención del cáncer: cáncer de mama, la media de cumplimiento global fue del 54.4%; el 42.8% de forma completa, el35.7% de forma incompleta y el 21.4% no tenía ninguna mamografía. Cáncer de cerviz, la media de cumplimiento global fue 59%; el 56.2% con cumplimiento del 100%, el 43.7% de forma incompleta y el 18.75% de pacientes no se había realizado ninguna citología cervico-vaginal. Programa de prevención de enfermedades infecciosas: un19.4% estaban vacunados frente al neumococo;22.2% frente al tétanos-difteria; 73.6% frente a la gripe y el 97.7% frente a la Hepatitis B. Actividades preventivas de alteraciones de la visión en los mayores: la media de cumplimiento fue del30.34%; el 13.6% de forma completa; el 52.3% deforma incompleta y el 34.1 % no tenía ninguna revisión oftalmológica. El cumplimiento de las recomendaciones de lo sPAPPS en HD es bajo. Enfermería debería tomar un papel activo en el incremento de estas actividades</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Enferm. Nefrol;8(1): 19-22, ene.-mar. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038550</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cumplimiento de las actividades preventivas y de promoción de la salud en un centro de hemodiálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6587^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
