<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046303</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Post-treatment effect of the foot reflexology in blood pressure and heart rate. A pilot study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Foot reflexology is a technique based on the treatment of zones on the feet that correspond to different body parts. Objective. Value the systemic modifications after foot reflexology treatment on healthy subjects. Experimental design. Pilot study, cuasi-experimental a blind. Method. A total of 34 subjects divided in two groups, an experimental and control group, received a 25 minute treatment that consisted in foot reflexology for the experimental group and a placebo application in the control group. A before and after treatment measure was made for the blood pressure and heart rate values. Results. The experimental group, that received the foot reflexology treatment, presented a highly statistic decrease in the heart rate value (p = 0,002) en comparison to the control group; as for the systolic (p = 0,434) and diastolic (p = 0,264) blood pressure values there were no statistic differences found. Conclusion. According to the obtained results, foot reflexology is a technique that produces a heart rate decrease and inducts relaxation. For this reason, we suggest that foot reflexology can be used in various clinic applications. However, more studies are needed to clarify the physiologic effects of this technique</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Linares Fernández, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Angulo Díaz-Pardeño, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>La Touche Arbizu, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escalante Raventós, K</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La reflexoterapia podal es una técnica que se basa en el tratamiento de zonas reflejas de todo el organismo que se encuentran ubicados en los planos musculares plantares y dorsales del pie. 0bjetivo. Valorar las modificaciones sistémicas pos-tratamiento con reflexoterapia podal en sujetos sanos. Diseño experimental. Estudio piloto cuasi-experimental a ciego. Método. Un total de 34 sujetos divididos en dos grupos, un grupo experimental que se le aplicó reflexoterapia podal durante 25 minutos y un grupo control con tratamiento placebo durante 25 minutos. Se realizó una medición pre-test y post-test de la tensión arterial y frecuencia cardiaca (FC) en ambos grupos. Resultados. El grupo experimental, al cual se le aplicó la reflexoterapia podal, presentó una disminución altamente significativa de la variable de FC (p = 0,002) en comparación con el grupo control, mientras que la tensión arterial sistólica (TAS) y diastólica (TAD) no presentaron cambios estadísticamente significativos (TAS, p = 0,434/TAD, p = 0,264). Conclusión. De acuerdo a los resultados obtenidos, se puede afirmar que la reflexoterapia podal es una técnica que influye directamente en la disminución de la FC y, a su vez, este mecanismo forma parte de la inducción a la relajación; por esta razón, se sugiere que esta técnica podría utilizarse en algunas aplicaciones clínicas determinadas, sin embargo, se necesitan realizar más investigaciones que aclaren los efectos fisiológicos de esta técnica</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);28(3): 125-132, may. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046303</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto pos-tratamiento de la reflexoterapia podal en la tensión arterial y la frecuencia cardiaca. Estudio piloto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1821^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1822^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12485^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8577^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6493^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
