<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99271</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Infantile Behçet&#146;s disease: an actual case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Behçet&#146;s disease is a small vessel vasculitis that attends in the form of recurrent outbreaks of fever and increase of acute phase reactants. The diagnosis is clinical and their significance is in the possible development of neurological or ocular involvement. We present the case of a Moroccan child of 3 years of age whose final diagnosis was the infantile Behçet's disease because the child presented repeated episodes of fever, recurrent oral ulcers, rash on the trunk and uveitis. The clinical evolution was on the whole good after several immune modulating drugs, but with severe ocular damage, pending approval of treatment with anti-TNF drugs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carceller Lechón, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Villena, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Ruiz, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castaño de la Mota, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Pérez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad de Behçet es una vasculitis de pequeño vaso que cursa en forma de brotes recurrentes de fiebre y aumento de reactantes de fase aguda. Su diagnóstico es clínico y su importancia está en la posible aparición de complicaciones graves, como la afectación neurológica u ocular. Se presenta el caso de un niño marroquí de 3 años de edad, cuyo diagnóstico final fue el de enfermedad de Behçet infantil tras presentar episodios repetidos de fiebre, aftas orales, exantema en el tronco y uveítis. Su evolución clínica, en general, fue buena después de la administración de varios fármacos inmunomoduladores, pero presentó un daño ocular severo, pendiente de aprobación de fármacos anti-TNF para su tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;69(11): 523-524, dic. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99271</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Behçet infantil: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28255^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38737^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7336^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22307^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
