<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157729</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tri-dimensional filling: a key factor in the outcome of endodontic treatment: case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The quality of the root canal filling is currently recognized as a factor that influences the outcome of the endodontic treatment (ET). Cone beam computerized tomography (CBCT) can be used to confirm a diagnosis of root canal morphology and is indicated in the evaluation of post-treatment complications, when conventional radiographic examination does not provide sufficient information. Recent studies with micro-CT present anatomic variations which can be implicated in the ET failure. Clinicians should be aware of the teeth&#146;s morphological variations and of the advantages of using CBCT in specific situations. This case report aims to highlight the importance of a tri-dimentional filling in the success of the ET (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barros, Joana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferreira, Manuel Marques</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferreira, Inês</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaz, Irene Pina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La calidad de la obturación del conducto radicular está considerada en la actualidad como un factor de gran influencia en el resultado del tratamiento endodóncico (TE). La tomografía computerizada de haz cónico (CBCT) puede ser utilizada para confirmar un diagnóstico sobre la morfología del conducto radicular, y está indicada en la evaluación de complicaciones post-tratamiento, cuando el examen radiográfico convencional no aporta suficiente información. Estudios recientes realizados con micro-CT muestran variaciones anatómicas que pueden estar implicadas en el fracaso del TE. Los clínicos deben tener en cuenta las variaciones anatómicas de los dientes y las ventajas de utilizar el CBCT en situaciones específicas. Este caso clínico pretende resaltar la importancia de una obturación tridimensional en el éxito del TE (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);34(3): 165-170, jul.-sept. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157729</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Obturación tridimensional: un factor clave en el pronóstico del tratamiento endodóncico: caso clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10676^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10676^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29816^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14190^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4790^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4790^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12764^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29816^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12764^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4790^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12764^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12764^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4790^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14190^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10676^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10676^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
