<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88087</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Polymyalgia rheumatica: do we think of it?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Polymyalgia rheumatica (PMR) is a chronic inflammatory disease which is generally diagnosed in primary care in patients older than 50 years. The diagnosis is based on clinical findings, analytical tests and the response to corticoids. Clinical findings are symmetrical pain and stiffness affecting shoulders, hips and cervical spine. There are several diagnostic criteria of PMR, with Bird¿s Criteria being the most sensitive. PMR differential diagnosis is made with rheumatic, infectious, autoimmune and osteoarticular diseases. There is a special interest in the relationship between PMR and giant cell arteritis as this association is not uncommon. The treatment of choice for PMR is corticoid therapy, showing a sharp clinical improvement, but its maintenance period is unknown, and should be determined empirically. Some studies show that other immunomodulatory drugs, such as methotrexate and infliximab can be added to reduce the length of the corticoid treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lafarga-Giribets, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodrigo-Claverol, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juanós-Lanuza, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Miguel, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La polimialgia reumática (PMR) es una enfermedad inflamatoria crónica que se diagnostica generalmente en las consultas de atención primaria a pacientes mayores de 50 años. El diagnóstico se basa fundamentalmente en el cuadro clínico, pruebas analíticas y la respuesta terapéutica a los corticosteroides. La clínica se caracteriza por dolor simétrico y rigidez de cintura escapular y pelviana y en columna cervical. Existen diferentes tablas de criterios diagnósticos de PMR, aunque se considera que los criterios de Bird son los que poseen mayor sensibilidad. El diagnóstico diferencial se realiza con enfermedades reumatológicas, infecciosas, autoinmunes y traumatológicas. Especial interés presenta la relación entre PMR y arteritis de células gigantes, dado que hay veces que coexisten. El tratamiento debe realizarse con corticosteroides, que proporcionan una pronta mejoría, aunque se desconoce el tiempo de duración de este. También se han realizado estudios con metotrexato e infliximab para disminuir el tiempo y las dosis de corticosteroides (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);37(5): 258-262, mayo 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88087</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Polimialgia reumática: ¿pensamos en ella?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1189^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11548^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11548^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12306</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11548^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11548^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14078^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22622^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14078^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14078^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13966^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14078^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201105</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
