<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118662</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bacterial acute gastroenteritis requiring hospital admission in children under 5 years</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Acute gastroenteritis (AGE) is a common cause of hospitalization in the pediatric age. Although viral etiology is predominant, bacteria can occupy an important place at certain times of the year. Between January 2005 and December 2010 a descriptive and prospective survey was carried out analyzing AGE of bacterial origin requiring hospital admission, in children younger than five years in a hospital of a suburban area of Madrid. Bacterial etiology is responsible for 9.3% of revenue by AGE in less than five years, with an hospitalized incidence of 0.9 per thousand under the age of 5, having a decrease from 2005 to the rest of their years studied. Most frequently bacteria isolated was Salmonella spp. We didn't found clinical parameters to distinguish clearly between bacterial or viral gastroenteritis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zafra Anta, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Arata, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrio Torres, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivero Martín, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Román Riechmann, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto Gabuccio, N. N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La gastroenteritis aguda (GEA) es una causa frecuente de hospitalización en la edad pediátrica. Aunque la etiología viral es la predominante, las bacterias pueden ser un agente importante en algunas épocas del año. Se lleva a cabo un estudio descriptivo prospectivo de las GEA de origen bacteriano que requirieron hospitalización en niños menores de 5 años en un hospital de un área suburbana de Madrid, desde enero de 2005 hasta diciembre de 2010. La etiología bacteriana es responsable del 9,3% de los ingresos por GEA en menores de 5 años, con una incidencia de 0,9 ingresos a causa de una GEA bacteriana por 1.000 menores de 5 años, aunque se ha constatado un descenso en 2005 respecto al resto de los años de estudio. El germen más frecuentemente implicado fue Salmonella spp. No se han encontrado parámetros clínicos que diferencien claramente las gastroenteritis bacterianas de las víricas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;71(10): 218-221, nov. 2013. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118662</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hospitalización por gastroenteritis aguda de etiología bacteriana en menores de 5 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12857^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33283^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2711^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1447^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201311</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
