<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-62122</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">MIS vs. standard total hip arthroplasty: a comparative study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To prospectively evaluate the results of minimally invasive surgery (MIS) vs. thetraditional approach in total hip arthroplastyMaterials and methods: We prospectively studied 70 consecutive patients subjected tototal hip replacement with a posterolateral approach. In 49% of them, a traditional Mooreapproach was used and in 51% a minimally invasive approach (an incision of less than 10cm); patients were distributed into the two groups randomly. We used hydroxyapatitecoatedcups and stems. Patients were reviewed at 6 months. Quantitative variables wereassessed using Student¡¯s ¡°t¡± test, whereas categorical variables were compared with thechi square test.Results: Comparison of our two groups revealed that OR time and hospital stay werelonger with the standard approach, although this difference was not statisticallysignifi cant. Stem malpositioning (placing them in varus or valgus) was signifi cantly higherin the MIS group (p=0.018). The results of the SF-12 questionnaire and the Harris hip scorewere better with the standard approach.Conclusions: In our experience, minimally invasive surgery for total hip replacement hasnot improved the results obtained with the traditional approach in terms of blood loss,pain or time to recovery. Better results are however obtained in terms of OR time andlength of hospital stay, although this is overshadowed by a greater incidence of varusstem malpositioning and a poorer life quality at 6 months (SF-12 questionnaire)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Crusi, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valera, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vergara, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trullols, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sancho, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: evaluar de forma prospectiva los resultados de la técnica de abordaje mínimamente invasiva (MIS) frente al abordaje tradicional en la artroplastia total de cadera. Material y método: se estudió, de forma prospectiva, a 70 pacientes consecutivos intervenidos de artroplastia total de cadera por vía posterolateral, el 49% mediante abordaje tradicional de Moore y el 51% mediante abordaje reducido (menos de 10 cm) distribuidos aleatoriamente. Se emplearon cotilos y vástagos con recubrimiento de hidroxiapatita y se revisó a los pacientes a los 6 meses. Las variables cuantitativas se evaluaron mediante la prueba de la t de Student, mientras que las variables categóricas fueron comparadas mediante la prueba de la X2. Resultados: partiendo de 2 grupos comparables estadísticamente, el tiempo quirúrgico y los días de ingreso fueron mayores en el abordaje estándar, aunque sin signifi cación estadística. La mala posición de los vástagos (colocación de éstos en varo o valgo) fue signifi cativamente mayor en el grupo MIS (p = 0,018). El test SF-12 y el test de Harris a los 6 meses fueron mejores en el abordaje estándar. Conclusiones: en nuestra experiencia, el abordaje reducido para artroplastia total de cadera no ha mejorado los resultados de la técnica tradicional en pérdidas hemáticas, dolor o rapidez de recuperación. Presenta una mejoría en el tiempo quirúrgico y en los días de hospitalización, con una presencia de vástagos posicionados en varo signifi cativamente mayor y una peor calidad de vida a los 6 meses (test SF-12) de los pacientes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);53(2): 76-82, mar.-abr. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-62122</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Artroplastia total de cadera mediante mini abordaje frente al abordaje est¨¢ndar: estudio comparativo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33577^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33577^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31497^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d81^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
