<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-16210</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">An unusual etiology of upper airway resistance syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present the case of a thirty-eight years-old man bearing of frequent crisis of asphyxiating wakefulness and breathnessless whenever he was asleep. There also were excessive daytime sleepiness and a strong snore before every wakefulness, but not for the rest of sleep. A polysomnographic study revealed normal values in the oxygen desaturation index, minimum oxygen saturation, an sleep structure alteration with a decrease of III-IV stages, high arousals index and RDI &lt; 5. Pharyngeal diameters measured by mean of TC were normal, but sleepiness degree detected in the Epworth scale was high. Nasal fiberoptic endoscopy study allowed to see a swinging epiglottis that closed totally the upper airway during forced inspiration. The lack of desaturation episodes with numerous wakefulness along the sleep and excessive daytime sleepiness drove to the diagnosis of upper airway resistance syndrome (UARS). Treatment whit C-PAP just provoked an impairment in symptoms, but a CO2-laser partial epiglottectomy improved them. Patophysiological aspects of UARS, as well as its follow-up and therapeutic alternatives are commented (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sanidad y Ediciones (SANED, S.L.)</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos el caso de un hombre de 38 años que consultó por presentar frecuentes crisis de despertar asfícticas con sensación de ahogo siempre que dormía. Asociaba además somnolencia excesiva diurna y un ronquido intenso antes de cada despertar, pero no durante el resto del sueño. El estudio polisomnográfico evidenció valores normales en el índice de desaturaciones de O2, en la mínima saturación de O2, una desestructuración de la arquitectura del sueño, con mínimos porcentajes de los estadios IIIIV, un índice elevado de arousals y un RDI &lt;5. Los diámetros faríngeos medidos mediante TC resultaron normales, pero el grado de hipersomnia detectado en la escala de Epworth fue muy elevado. El estudio nasofibroscópico objetivó una epiglotis basculante que en inspiración forzada ocluía totalmente la vía aérea. La ausencia de episodios de desaturación con numerosos despertares durante el sueño y somnolencia diurna excesiva condujeron al diagnóstico de síndrome de resistencia de las vías aéreas superiores (SRVAS). El tratamiento con C-PAP condicionó empeoramiento de los síntomas, pero la epiglotectomía parcial con láser CO2 fue resolutiva de los mismos. Se comentan los aspectos fisiopatólogicos del SRVAS, así como su monitorización y alternativas terapéuticas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;53(9): 701-706, nov. 2002. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Una etiología infrecuente de síndrome de resistencia de las vías aéreas superiores</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Esparcia Navarro, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Callejo, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morant, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferris, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marco, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Julián, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orts, MH</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-16210</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d30611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4905^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4905^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34202^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34202^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200211</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
