<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147677</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Definition, etiology, classification and presentation forms</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Osteoarthritis is defined as a degenerative process affecting the joints as a result of mechanical and biological disorders that destabilize the balance between the synthesis and degradation of joint cartilage, stimulating the growth of subchondral bone; chronic synovitis is also present. Currently, the joint is considered as a functional unit that includes distinct tissues, mainly cartilage, the synovial membrane, and subchondral bone, all of which are involved in the pathogenesis of the disease. Distinct risk factors for the development of osteoarthritis have been described: general, unmodifiable risk factors (age, sex, and genetic makeup), general, modifiable risk factors (obesity and hormonal factors) and local risk factors (prior joint anomalies and joint overload). Notable among the main factors related to disease progression are joint alignment defects and generalized osteoarthritis. Several classifications of osteoarthritis have been proposed but none is particularly important for the primary care management of the disease. These classifications include etiological (primary or idiopathic forms and secondary forms) and topographical (typical and atypical localizations) classifications, the Kellgren and Lawrence classification (radiological repercussions) and that of the American College of Rheumatology for osteoarthritis of the hand, hip and knee. The prevalence of knee osteoarthritis is 10.2% in Spain and shows a marked discrepancy between clinical and radiological findings. Hand osteoarthritis, with a prevalence of symptomatic involvement of around 6.2%, has several forms of presentation (nodal osteoarthritis, generalized osteoarthritis, rhizarthrosis, and erosive osteoarthritis). Symptomatic osteoarthritis of the hip affects between 3.5% and 5.6% of persons older than 50 years and has different radiological patterns depending on femoral head migration (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mas Garriga, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La artrosis se define como un proceso degenerativo articular, consecuencia de trastornos mecánicos y biológicos que desestabilizan el equilibrio entre la síntesis y la degradación del cartílago articular, estimulando el crecimiento del hueso subcondral y con la presencia de sinovitis crónica. Actualmente se considera a la articulación como una unidad funcional que integra diferentes tejidos, principalmente el cartílago, la sinovial y el hueso subcondral, todos ellos implicados en la patogenia de la enfermedad. Se han descrito diferentes factores de riesgo relacionados con su aparición: los generales no modificables (edad, sexo y genética), los generales modificables (obesidad y factores hormonales) y los locales (anomalías articulares previas y sobrecarga articular), mientras que entre los principales factores relacionados con su progresión destacan los defectos de alineación articular y la artrosis generalizada. Se han propuesto diferentes maneras de clasificar la artrosis, aunque ninguna de ellas tiene gran relevancia para su manejo por el médico de atención primaria: la etiológica (formas primarias o idiopáticas y formas secundarias), la topográfica (localizaciones típicas y atípicas), la de Kellgren y Lawrence (repercusión radiológica) y la del American College of Rheumatology para la artrosis de manos, caderas y rodillas. La artrosis de rodilla tiene una prevalencia del 10,2% en España y muestra una importante disociación clinicorradiológica. La artrosis de manos, con una prevalencia de afectación sintomática de alrededor del 6,2% puede adoptar diferentes formas de presentación (artrosis nodal, artrosis generalizada, rizartrosis y artrosis erosiva). La artrosis sintomática de cadera afecta entre el 3,5 y 5,6% de los mayores de 50 años y tiene diferentes patrones radiológicos en función de la migración de la cabeza femoral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;46(supl.1): 3-10, ene. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147677</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Definición, etiopatogenia, clasificación y formas de presentación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201401</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
