<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167044</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Actinic keratosis: New concept and therapeutic update</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Actinic keratosis (AK) is a common reason for consultation in both Primary Care and Specialised Care. It is the third or fourth most common reason for consultation in dermatology, accounting for up to 5-6% of patients attended. It has also been observed that its prevalence has been increasing in the last 10 years, compared to other dermatoses. This is also expected to continue to increase due to longer life expectancy, and by the changes in sun exposure habits since the middle of the last century. The aim of this article is to update the concepts of AK, cancerisation field and to present the currently available therapeutic tools (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santos-Alarcón, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lucas-Truyols, Sofía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateu-Puchades, Almudena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carmena-Ramón, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La queratosis actínica (QA) es motivo de consulta frecuente tanto en atención primaria como en atención especializada. Supone el tercer o cuarto motivo más frecuente de consulta en dermatología, llegando a representar hasta un 5-6% de los pacientes atendidos. Además, se ha observado que esta prevalencia ha ido en aumento en los últimos 10 años, en comparación con otras dermatosis, y se prevé que seguirá aumentado por la mayor esperanza de vida y por los cambios de hábitos de exposición solar acontecidos desde mediados del siglo pasado. El objetivo de este artículo es actualizar los conceptos de QA y de campo de cancerización, y exponer las herramientas terapéuticas disponibles actualmente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;49(8): 492-497, oct. 2017. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167044</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Queratosis actínica: nuevo concepto y actualización terapéutica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11665^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2337^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10987^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53062^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5602^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31536^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4671^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28018^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34640^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
