<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165479</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neonatal glaucoma associated with juvenile xanthogranuloma: Case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case Report: The case concerns a 22 day-old male child with juvenile xanthogranuloma (JXG), which manifested as a unilateral glaucoma and with fibrinous haemorrhagic exudate in the anterior chamber affecting the angle of the right eye. Despite a high level of suspicion, the definitive diagnosis was not possible until the infant reached the age of 10 months, after the appearance of the skin lesions typical of this condition and histopathological study of them.Conclusion: JXG is a rare disease, characterised by yellowish skin lesions on the trunk, neck, or head. Up to 10% of cases will have ocular involvement, which is the most common extracutaneous manifestation of the disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ayet Roger, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serra Castanera, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Suárez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Varón de 22 días con xantogranulomatosis juvenil (XGJ) que comenzó con glaucoma unilateral y exudado fibrinohemorrágico que invadía ángulo en su ojo derecho. Pese a un alto nivel de sospecha, el diagnóstico definitivo no pudo realizarse hasta los 10 meses de vida tras la aparición y estudio anatomopatológico de las típicas lesiones cutáneas. Conclusión: La XGJ es una enfermedad poco frecuente caracterizada por lesiones cutáneas amarillentas en tronco, cuello o cabeza. Hasta el 10% de casos pueden presentar afectación ocular siendo la manifestación extracutánea más frecuente de la enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;92(8): 394-397, ago. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165479</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Glaucoma neonatal secundario a xantogranuloma juvenil: caso clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24587^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28053^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28204^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23041^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28053^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30445^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30445^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
