<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100534</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Needs for Health Education in the Second Cycle of Secondary Education</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims: This article addresses the aims of analyzing the needs felt and perceived by students and teachers of second cycle of ESO in terms of Health Education (HE) and to develop and validate a questionnaire designed to measure students&#146; perceived needs in the second cycle of ESO regarding this matter. Methodology: We develop a descriptive study of ecological design that analyzes a cross-section. Cronbach&#146;s &amp;#945; gives a final result of 0.70. KMO and Bartlett&#146;s test invites us to make factor analysis to test the construct validity. Qualitative variables are dealt with are frequencies and percentages for each variable and hypothesis testing using Chi-square test (&amp;#945; error of 5%). Findings: Statistical analysis has validated a questionnaire to measure students&#146; perceived needs in HE. The topics students wish to learn about are food, drugs, exercise, alcohol and obesity and/or weight problems. Moreover, among teachers 2 difficulties of providing HE were raised: lack of knowledge and having to develop additional teaching material. The best person to inform HE teachers and students is the community nurse. Conclusions: The knowledge of the HE needs of students and teachers of this cycle promotes the work of the community nurse when delivering HE in the institutes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mena Tudela, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pina Romero, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: En este artículo se plantean los objetivos de analizar las necesidades sentidas y percibidas por alumnos y profesores de segundo ciclo de la ESO en cuanto a Educación para la salud (EpS); y elaborar y validar un cuestionario que permita medir las necesidades sentidas por los alumnos de segundo ciclo de la ESO respecto a esta materia. Metodología: Se desarrolla un estudio observacional descriptivo de diseño ecológico que analiza una corte transversal. La alpha de Cronbach que aporta un resultado de final de 0,70. KMO y prueba de Bartlett nos invita a realizar el análisis factorial para comprobar la validez de constructo. Las variables cualitativas se tratarán con: frecuencias y porcentajes para cada variable y un contraste de hipótesis mediante la prueba de Chi-cuadrado (error &amp;#945; del 5%). Resultados: El análisis estadístico ha permitido la validación de un cuestionario para medir las necesidades sentidas por los alumnos respecto a EpS. Los temas que quieren conocer estos en EpS son: alimentación, drogas, ejercicio físico, alcohol y obesidad y/o problemas de peso. Por otro lado, entre el profesorado destacan 2 dificultades a la hora de impartir EpS: la falta de conocimientos y tener que desarrollar material adicional para impartirla. La persona más indicada para llevar a cabo la EpS tanto profesores como alumnos es la enfermera comunitaria. Conclusiones: El conocimiento de las necesidades de alumnos y profesores de este ciclo en cuanto a EpS, favorece el trabajo de la enfermera comunitaria a la hora de impartir EpS en los institutos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;11(26): 102-116, abr. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100534</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Necesidades de Educación para la Salud en el Segundo Ciclo de Educación Secundaria Obligatoria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3183^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3183^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
