<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166095</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Qualitative Research in Pharmaceutical Care: Observatorio Farmacéutico Social experience, a proposal in community pharmacy with a pedagogical and social approach</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The Observatorio Farmacéutico Social (OFS) is a research proposal in community pharmacy with a pedagogical and social approach. The OFS seeks to investigate on cultural usage of drugs, medicinal plants, health education and disease prevention, particularly, in vulnerable populations. In Colombia, the information related to this issue is limited. Aim: To document life experiences and knowledge related to the usage of drugs and medicinal plants in a population of community leaders, among whom participation is voluntary, through the OFS proposal. Method: It was carried out a qualitative research proposal based on Participatory-Action-Research (PAR) methodology. For the fieldwork some Interactive Qualitative Research Methodologies were used. The results&#146; interpretation was made from the critical and reflexive researchers&#146; eye, following the technical and scientific recommendations about the appropriate usage of medications. Results: It was structured an OFS proposal that allowed the participation of 46 women. The main findings in the OFS experience were about the knowledge and myths associated with the usage of drugs, confidence in medical care, adherence to treatments and defense of medicinal plants&#146; usage. Conclusions: Currently there is no information documenting the availability of an observatory with these features. For this reason, is considered necessary to progress in the structure and operation of the OFS as a popular education proposal in the appropriate usage of drugs and medicinal plants and, thus, contribute to the achievement of positive and safe results in the pharmacological therapy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cifuentes Posada, LM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Restrepo Lara, PA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estrada Cano, W</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Henao Molina, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amariles Muñoz, PJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El Observatorio Farmacéutico Social (OFS) es una propuesta investigativa en farmacia comunitaria con enfoque pedagógico y social. Indaga sobre el uso cultural de medicamentos, plantas medicinales, educación para la salud, promoción de la salud y prevención de la enfermedad, especialmente, en poblaciones vulnerables. En Colombia la información sobre este tema es limitada. Objetivo: Documentar experiencias de vida y conocimientos relacionados con el uso de medicamentos y plantas medicinales en una población de adultos líderes comunitarios, de participación voluntaria, utilizando la propuesta de OFS. Método: Propuesta de corte cualitativo, basada en la metodología participativa de Investigación-Acción-Participación. Para el trabajo de campo se utilizaron algunas Metodologías interactivas de la investigación cualitativa. La lectura de los resultados se realizó desde la mirada crítico-reflexiva de los investigadores, acorde con recomendaciones técnicas y científicas relacionadas con el uso adecuado de medicamentos. Resultados: Se estructuró una propuesta de OFS, que permitió la participación de 46 mujeres. Los principales hallazgos se dieron sobre conocimientos y mitos asociados al uso de medicamentos, confianza en la atención médica, adherencia a los tratamientos y defensa por los saberes ancestrales relacionados con el uso de plantas medicinales. Conclusiones: Actualmente no se encuentra información que documente la disponibilidad de un observatorio con estas características; por ello, se considera necesario continuar la estructuración y funcionamiento del OFS como una propuesta de educación popular en el uso adecuado de medicamentos y plantas medicinales y, así, contribuir al logro de resultados positivos en la terapia farmacológica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;19(4): 184-204, 2017. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166095</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Investigación Cualitativa en Atención Farmacéutica: Experiencia del Observatorio Farmacéutico Social, una propuesta en farmacia comunitaria con enfoque pedagógico y social</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4422^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3275</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3137</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50249^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
