<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157303</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">V-Y advancement flaps for extensive perianal defect repair</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: Some perianal pathologies require aggressive surgery that will need techniques to allow to re-establish the integrity of the perianal region. The purpose is to analyze short and long term results after perineal reconstruction with V-Y flaps. Objectives: Some perianal pathologies require aggressive surgery that will need techniques to allow to re-establish the integrity of the perianal region. The purpose is to analyze short and long term results after perineal reconstruction with V-Y flaps. Methods: A retrospective review of prospectively collected database was conducted at Virgen de la Arrixaca&#146;s Hospital in Murcia (España) between January 2000 and December 2013. The study includes all patients who underwent a perineal reconstruction with V-Y flaps. Demographic and surgical data and short-/long- term morbidity was recorded. Results: 10 patients were included, 6 males and 4 females. The average age was 58,1±17,4 years. Surgical indication included both malignant and benign pathologies. Operating time was 143,5±41,3 min. R0 resection was performed in all cases although histopathological analysis showed involvement of the deeper margin in 3 cases. Length of hospital stay was 7,8±7,6 days. Regarding complications: 6 patients had partial dehiscence of the flap. None of the patients lost the flap completely. The most frequent late complication was anal stenosis (n=4). Follow up showed total continence in 7 patients. Two patients had variable fecal and/or flatus incontinence. A colostomy was made in one case due to severe incontinence. Conclusions: V-Y flaps are an effective and feasible technique to cover large perianal defects after aggressive surgeries. However, this technique is not free of postoperative morbidity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Abrisqueta, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parrilla, Pascual</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luján, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibañez, Noelia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, Quiteria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Algunas enfermedades perianales precisan cirugías agresivas que crean la necesidad de recurrir a técnicas reparadoras para reconstruir la integridad de esta región. El objetivo de este estudio es analizar los resultados a corto y largo plazo tras reconstrucción perianal con colgajos V-Y. Método: Se ha revisado retrospectivamente nuestra base de datos institucional prospectiva (2000&#150;2013), y se ha incluido en el presente análisis a todos los pacientes a los que se ha realizado una reconstrucción perianal con colgajo V-Y, tras escisión amplia perianal por enfermedad benigna o maligna. Se recogieron datos demográficos, quirúrgicos y la morbilidad a corto y largo plazo. Resultados: Se analizó a un total de 10 pacientes, 6 varones y 4 mujeres, con edad media de 58,1±17,4 años. El tiempo quirúrgico fue 143,5±41,3 min y la estancia hospitalaria media tras la cirugía 7,8± 7,7 días. En 8 pacientes aparecieron complicaciones postoperatorias: dehiscencia parcial del colgajo (n = 6) y estenosis anal tardía (n = 4). En ningún caso se produjo la pérdida del colgajo. Siete pacientes presentaron buenos resultados en cuanto a la continencia anal, 2 pacientes incontinencia variable y en un caso se realizó una colostomía terminal por incontinencia grave. Conclusión: Los colgajos V-Y son una técnica factible y efectiva para cubrir grandes defectos tras cirugías perianales agresivas; sin embargo, no están exentos de morbilidad postoperatoria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);94(9): 525-530, nov. 2016. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157303</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El colgajo V-Y como método de reparación de defectos perianales extensos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1938^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d708^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55182^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
