<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164251</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors involved in the burden of the primary caregiver of cancer patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The aim of the study was to identify the factors involved between burden in the primary caregiver of cancer patients and their quality of life. Material and methods. A cross-sectional study was conducted in a secondary level hospital on 100 primary caregivers of cancer patients. The level of burden was determined using the Zarit scale and the perception of quality of life using the World Health Organisation Quality of Life questionnaire. Quality of life was categorised as high or low and compared between groups according to their level of burden. Descriptive statistics were performed on the study variables, and differences between groups were analysed according to their level of burden. Results. In assessing the overload, it was found that 31% of caregivers had burden. A good quality of life was perceived by 76% of caregivers, while the remaining 24% perceived it as poor. To identify association between these two variables Chi squared (X2) was used to determine whether there was any association between quality of life and overloading of the primary caregiver, giving a P&amp;#8804;.05. A Spearman correlation was also performed, obtaining an r-value of .321 with a P&amp;#8804;.05, finding a slightly positive correlation. Conclusions. The factors that have a bearing on a good quality of life despite having burden were: being married, dedicated to the home, and kinship (to be immediate family: spouse, parents and children). Conversely, the type of cancer, sleep hours, and hours of care influence the perception of a poor quality of life (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Juárez-Romero, K</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Cruz, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortes-Campero, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero-Figueroa, MS</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valencia, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meza-Osnaya, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Paredes, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Ovalle, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chino-Hernández, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Identificar los factores que intervienen en la sobrecarga y calidad de vida del cuidador primario del paciente con cáncer. Material y métodos. Se realizó un estudio transversal en un hospital de segundo nivel de atención que incluyó 100 cuidadores primarios de pacientes con cáncer. Se determinó el nivel de sobrecarga con la escala de Zarit, y la percepción de calidad de vida con el cuestionario World Health Organization Quality of Life. Se categorizó la calidad de vida como alta o baja y se comparó entre grupos según su nivel de sobrecarga. Se realizó estadística descriptiva para las variables de estudio y se analizaron las diferencias entre grupos según su nivel de sobrecarga. Resultados. Al evaluar la sobrecarga se encontró que el 31% de cuidadores presentó sobrecarga. El 76% de los cuidadores percibió una buena calidad de vida, mientras que el 24% restante la percibió como mala. Para identificar la asociación entre estas 2 variables se utilizó la Chi cuadrado, encontrando una asociación con una p&amp;#8804;0,05. Para identificar correlación entre calidad de vida y sobrecarga del cuidador primario se realizó una correlación de Spearman, obteniendo un valor r de 0,321 con una p&amp;#8804;0,05, encontrando una correlación levemente positiva. Conclusiones. Los factores que inciden en mayor medida para una buena calidad de vida a pesar de tener sobrecarga fueron: el ser casado, el dedicarse al hogar y el parentesco (ser familiar directo: cónyuge, padres e hijos). De manera contraria el tipo de cáncer, las horas de sueño y las horas de cuidado influyen en la percepción de una mala calidad de vida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;32(4): 221-225, jul.-ago. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164251</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores que intervienen en la sobrecarga del cuidador primario del paciente con cáncer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
