<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159626</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spasmolytic effect of Jasonia glutinosa on rodent intestine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Jasonia glutinosa is an endemic plant species of the Iberian Peninsula and Southern France traditionally used in infusions as a spasmolytic; this plant is also known as &#147;té de roca&#148; (rock tea) but there is no scientific evidence about the effects of this plant. Aim: To evaluate the spasmolytic effect of rock tea. Methods: We have studied the in vitro effect of a rock tea extract on rat duodenum spontaneous contractions and the in vivo effect on mice gastrointestinal transit. Results: Rock tea extract reduced the spontaneous contractions of rat duodenal smooth muscle, inhibited KCl-induced contractions and blocked the contractions invoked by both extracellular Ca2+ and the agonist of L-type calcium channels Bay K8644. This inhibitory effect was similar to the one observed after the addition of the antagonist of L-type calcium channels verapamil. Rock tea did not modify gastrointestinal transit in healthy mice. However, after the treatment with dextran sulfate sodium, an inducer of colitis, rock tea extract reverted the increase in the gastrointestinal transit associated with this treatment. Conclusion: Rock tea extract relaxed duodenal smooth muscle via L-type calcium channels and normalized gastrointestinal transit in a model of colitis. These results may validate the traditional use of Jasonia glutinosa in patients with gastrointestinal alterations. Thus, rock tea may be used as a spasmolytic agent to treat gastrointestinal disorders (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Plaza, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giménez, Mariano Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murillo, María Divinia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Les, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valero, Marta Sofía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trejo, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: Jasonia glutinosa es una planta utilizada en la Península Ibérica y en el sur de Francia por su efecto espasmolítico, pero sin evidencia científica sobre ello. Objetivo: examinar el efecto espasmolítico de un extracto de té de roca. Métodos: estudiamos el efecto de dicho extracto sobre las contracciones espontáneas en duodeno de rata in vitro y sobre el tránsito gastrointestinal en el ratón in vivo. Resultados: el extracto de té de roca redujo las contracciones espontáneas en el músculo liso longitudinal del duodeno de rata, inhibió las contracciones inducidas por KCl, bloqueó la contracción causada por la entrada de Ca2+ extracelular y la contracción inducida por el Bay K8644, agonista de los canales de Ca2+ tipo L. El efecto inhibitorio del extracto de té de roca fue similar al del verapamilo, inhibidor de los canales de Ca2+ tipo L. El té de roca no modificó el tránsito gastrointestinal total en ratones sanos. Sin embargo, tras el tratamiento con dextrano sulfato de sodio, un inductor de colitis, el extracto de té de roca revirtió el aumento del tránsito gastrointestinal asociado a dicho tratamiento. Conclusión: el extracto de té de roca relajó el músculo liso duodenal a través de canales de Ca2+ tipo L y normalizó el tránsito gastrointestinal en un modelo de colitis. Estos resultados validan el uso tradicional de Jasonia glutinosa en alteraciones digestivas. Así, el té de roca podría ser utilizado como espasmolítico en el tratamiento de diversas patologías gastrointestinales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;108(12): 785-789, dic. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159626</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto espasmolítico de Jasonia glutinosa en intestino de roedores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8994</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22901^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8686^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23506^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23177^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10465^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23177^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5910^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10465^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11626^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33297</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9320^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
