<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99225</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">New peritoneal dialysis solutions have attracted interest in recent years, as shown by the number of publications. Overall, the most salient aspects refer to the potential clinical benefits achieved using such solutions. Reports on such benefits are sometimes conflicting. The improved preservation of kidney function seen with a biocompatible bicarbonate solution is not seen with biocompatible lactate or bicarbonate/lactate solutions. Lower CRP levels are seen with biocompatible solutions; however, other studies report similar levels. Peritoneal local inflammation parameters suggest that less inflammation occurs with new solutions as compared to the standard solutions. The decreased incidence of peritonitis achieved with a solution in the long term is not achieved with other solutions in the short term. There is no agreement as to whether UF is lower with biocompatible solutions, a well designed study did report a lower ultrafiltration (UF) with the new solutions. The higher the concentration of glucose degradation products in dialysis solutions, the higher will also be inperitoneal fluid and blood, as has brilliantly been reported. Also, the higher the concentration of glucose degradation products, the greater the generation of advanced glycosilation products. All authors conclude that further controlled studies are required to obtain more convincing evidence about the clinical benefits of the new solutions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montenegro, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las nuevas soluciones de diálisis peritoneal han tenido interés en los últimos años, si tenemos en cuenta el número de publicaciones.  Los  aspectos más  destacados  se  refieren  en conjunto a los posibles beneficios clínicos conseguidos con el uso de las mismas, a veces contradictorios. La función renal mejor preservada con una solución biocompatible de bicarbonato, no se observa con soluciones biocompatibles con lactato o bicarbonato/lactato. La PCR es más baja con las soluciones  biocompatibles,  sin  embargo  en  otros  trabajos  los niveles son semejantes. Los parámetros de inflamación local peritoneal apuntan que hay menos inflamación con las nuevas soluciones que con  las soluciones estándar. La disminución del índice de peritonitis conseguido con una solución alargo plazo, no se consigue con otras a corto plazo. No hay acuerdo si la UF es inferior con las soluciones biocompatibles, sigue habiendo diferencias: unos trabajos no encuentran diferencias significativas entre las dos soluciones, mientras otro trabajo  bien  diseñado  sí  observa  una menor  ultrafiltración(UF)  con  las  soluciones  nuevas. A mayor  concentración  de productos de degradación de la glucosa en las soluciones dialíticas, mayor concentración en el líquido peritoneal y en sangre,  como brillantemente  se ha descrito. También, a mayor concentración  de  productos  de  degradación  de  la  glucosa mayor generación de productos avanzados de glicoxilación. Todos los autores concluyen que son necesarios más estudios controlados para lograr una evidencia más convincente acerca de los beneficios clínicos con las nuevas soluciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;28(supl.5): 59-65, ene.-dic. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99225</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Soluciones de diálisis peritoneal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6063^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10728^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23606^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23497^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7852^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
