<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140369</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality of life in obese patients and change after bariatric surgery medium and long term</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Morbid obesity has grown enormously in recent decades, representing a serious public health problem. It is characterized by the accumulation of body fat and the presence of diseases associated with it, which affects the physical, psychological and social level. It has been considered bariatric ciguría as the most effective treatment for weight loss, getting the welfare of the obese person in the above-described drawings. Objective: To evaluate the impact on the quality of life of obese people before and after bariatric surgery be tapped using the technique of laparoscopic gastrectomy (GVL) in a follow short, medium and long term. Method: The study population are all people with morbid obesity and are candidates for surgery, presenting at Torrecárdenas Bariatric Surgery Hospital (Almería). The design is a descriptive, longitudinal study, prospective. Results: After evaluation of the obese patients a year, two years and five years after surgery, there has been decrease in weight, therefore decrease in BMI and the degree of obesity, improvement or disappearance of comorbidities and increased CV variables. Discussion: The GVL gets reduce excess weight and therefore BMI and the degree of obesity, as well as the number of obesity-associated diseases, thus increasing the CV (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alcaraz García, Aurora María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer Márquez, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parrón Carreño, Tesifón</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La obesidad mórbida ha crecido enormemente en las últimas décadas, representando un grave problema de Salud Pública. Se caracteriza por el acúmulo de grasa corporal y la presencia de enfermedades asociadas a ella, que repercute en el plano físico, psíquico y social. Se ha considerado a la ciguría bariátrica como el tratamiento más eficaz para la pérdida de peso, consiguiendo el bienestar de la persona obesa en los planos anteriormente descritos. Objetivo: Evaluar el impacto en la calidad de vida de las personas obesas antes y después de ser intervenidas de cirugía bariátrica, mediante la técnica de gastrectomía vertical laparoscópica (GVL) en un seguimiento a corto, medio y largo plazo. Metodo: La población de estudio son todas las personas con obesidad mórbida y son candidatos a cirugía, que acuden al Servicio de Cirugía Bariátrica del Hospital Torrecárdenas (Almería). El diseño es un estudio descriptivo, longitudinal, prospectivo. Resultados: Tras la evaluación del pacientes obeso al año, a los dos años y a los cinco años de la cirugía, se ha observado disminución del peso, por tanto, descenso en el IMC y en el grado de obesidad, la mejoría o desaparición de las comorbilidades y un aumento en las variables de CV. Discusión: La GVL consigue disminuir el exceso de peso y por tanto el IMC y el grado de obesidad, al igual que el número de enfermedades asociadas a la obesidad, aumentando asi la CV (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(5): 2033-2046, mayo 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140369</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida en los pacientes obesos y su cambio tras cirugía bariátrica a medio y largo plazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51221^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51716</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23862</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
