<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118443</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anthropometric evaluation of adult coeliac patients from de Valencian Community (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The objective of this work is to evaluate the nutritional status of a group of celiac patients from the Valencian Community through their anthropometric characteristics. A cross-sectional study was designed, in which all patients followed a yet without gluten during at least six months. Material and methods: The sample was constituted by 2000 members of the Association of Celiacs of the Valencian Community (ACECOVA) of both sexes and different age ranges were passed to the questionnaires. The three provinces, Castellón, Valencia and Alicante were included. Finally, anthropometric data of 139 people with celiac disease were evaluated, between adults and children. Among the 84 adults, 77.4% were women. All participants were summoned to measure their weight and height in the laboratory of Anthropometries of the Faculty of Pharmacy of the University of Valencia. The following anthropometric measures were selected: body weight, height and body mass index. Results: 12% of the adult celiac population presents overweight and 5% obesity, much smaller proportions than in the general population and in the Valencian Spanish in particular. However, the proportions of (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Soriano del Castillo, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mañes Vinuesa, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pelegrí Calvo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El objetivo de este trabajo es evaluar el estado nutricional de un grupo de pacientes celíacos de la Comunidad Valenciana a través de sus características antropométricas. Se diseñó un estudio transversal en el cual todos los pacientes llevaban más de seis meses en tratamiento con dieta sin gluten (DSG). Material y métodos: El universo muestral lo constituyeron 2000 asociados de la Asociación de Celíacos de la Comunidad Valenciana (ACECOVA) de ambos sexos y diferentes rangos de edad a los que invitó a participar. Se incluyeron las tres provincias, Castellón, Valencia y Alicante. Finalmente, se evaluaron los datos antropométricos de 139 sujetos celíacos entre adultos y niños. De los 84 adultos, el 77,4% fueron mujeres. Todos los participantes fueron citados para medir su peso y altura en el laboratorio de antropometrías de la Facultat de Farmàcia de la Universitat de València. Se seleccionaron las siguientes medidas antropométricas: peso corporal, talla e índice de masa corporal (IMC) y percentil de peso y de altura. Resultados: El 12% de la población celíaca adulta presenta sobrepeso y el 5% obesidad, proporciones mucho menores que en la población española en general y en la valenciana en particular. Sin embargo, las proporciones de peso insuficiente en el 9% de los celíacos y de normopeso en el 74% superan las de la población sana. Conclusiones: Habría que investigar el cumplimiento de la DSG en celíacos tratados con el fin de obtener menores proporciones de peso insuficiente que pueden relacionarse con desnutrición (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;33(3): 18-22, dic. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118443</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación antropométrica de celíacos adultos de la Comunidad Valenciana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53326^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2481^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
