<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148996</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Experience with BMP-7 in the treatment of infected pseudarthrosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze the results of the use of bone morphogenetic protein-7 (BMP-7) in infected pseudarthrosis. Material and methods: We performed a descriptive, retrospective study of 45 patients with septic pseudarthrosis who were treated with BMP-7 between 2003 and 2006. Bone consolidation was confirmed through radiographic studies in four projections at 2, 4, 6, 8 and 12 months after the intervention. In all patients, five intraoperative cultures were taken and were included among the study variables in the data collection sheet used in the statistical analysis. Results: Bone consolidation was achieved in 70% of the patients at a mean of 5 months. In the remaining 30%, more than 60% of the patients continued to show active infection. Conclusions: BMP-7 is a good osteoinducer under rigid selection criteria. Active infection blocks its effectiveness (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mut Oltra, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cervelló López, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Colado Domínguez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar los resultados del uso de la BMP-7 en seudoartrosis infectadas. Material y métodos: Estudio descriptivo y retrospectivo de 45 pacientes con seudoartrosis sépticas en los que se aplicó la BMP-7 entre los años 2003 y 2006. El estudio de la consolidación ósea se confirmó mediante estudios radiográficos en cuatro proyecciones 2, 4, 6, 8, 10 y 12 meses tras la intervención. Se tomaron en todos los casos cinco cultivos intraoperatorios, incluidos entre las diferentes variables en estudio en la hoja de recogida de datos que se analizaron estadísticamente. Resultados: Se obtuvo la consolidación en el 70% de los pacientes con una media de 5 meses. En el 30% restante, más del 60% de los pacientes continuaban con la infección activa. Conclusiones: La BMP-7 es un buen osteoinductor óseo si se sigue estrictos criterios de selección. La infección activa impide que funcione correctamente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);54(supl.1): 24-30, mayo 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148996</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia con BMP-7 en el tratamiento de las seudoartrosis infectadas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1886^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11981^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53134^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10199^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
