<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044514</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prostate cyst at the midline in a patient with a renal transplantation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cystic lesions at the midline of the prostate are uncommon and they are considered as congenital disorders. Is generally accepted that active treatment should be instituted only in symptomatic patients and watchful waiting in asymptomatic ones. The most common active treatment is minimally invasive surgery by puncture-aspiration or endoscopic unroofing. We are attaching an inmunosupressed patient because of a renal transplantation in which we provided an active treatment by puncture-aspiration of the cystic lesion in spite of being asymptomatic</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Cózar, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flores Ginés, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fariñas Varo, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González García, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soto Villalba, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Tenorio, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las lesiones quísticas localizadas en la línea media de la próstata son poco frecuentes y se consideran alteraciones congénitas. Se acepta generalmente que el tratamiento activo se realiza sólo a los pacientes sintomáticos, haciendo observación a los asintomáticos. El tratamiento activo más común es la cirugía mínimamente invasiva por medio de punción-aspiración o la decorticación endoscópica. Aportamos un caso de un paciente inmunosuprimido por un trasplante renal, circunstancia que nos hizo optar por el tratamiento activo con punción aspiración del mismo, a pesar de ser asintomático</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;28(6): 452-454, jun. 2004. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044514</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Quiste prostático de línea media en paciente trasplantado renal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11910^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11910^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29431^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11910^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
