<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61070</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1473</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Giant cerebral cavernous malformation in a child less than 1 year old: case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cerebral cavernous malformations are rarely described in children. Giant cavernous malformations are exceptional in this group of patients.The authors reports a case of an eleven months boy, who begins at the sixth month of life with epilepsy. Medical therapy was advised and imagenological studieswere carried out. An IRM was performed, and shows a giant cavernous malformation in the right parietal lobe. Surgery was carried out, with complete resection of the lesion. In the postoperative period and at more thana year of follow up, he was free of crisis.We report the case because of the rarity of a giantcavernous angioma in a patient less than a year old (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carminatti, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prinzo, H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los angiomas cavernosos son poco frecuentes en niños, y son menos frecuentes aún los angiomas cavernosos gigantes. Describimos el caso clínico de un niño de 11 mesesque consultó por un cuadro de crisis epilépticas de 5 meses de evolución. Los estudios de imagen (IRM) evidenciaron un angioma cavernoso gigante parietal derecho. Se realizó una resección total de la lesión con controlde las crisis. Se reporta el caso dado lo excepcional de la lesión descrita en un paciente menor de un año (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurocirugia (Astur);20(1): 54-56, ene.-feb. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61070</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Angioma cavernoso cerebral gigante en paciente menor de un año: descripción deun caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34179^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34179^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34179^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34179^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
