<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112422</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hôtel-Dieu in Paris; origins and appearance of the first religious nurses of the history</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of the present study is to discover and disclose the history of the Hôtel-Dieu in Paris and, at the same time, the history of the Agustinian´s Sisters, nurses of the mentioned hospital. The methodology used to carry out the study was an extensive literature research, translation, reading, analysis and discussion of the documents we find during the research. The conclusions tell us about the difficulties of the occupation, about how long one-person could take to complete studies and to became fully professional in this area (up to 26years), and also talks about how the functions between some occupations and others was delimitated (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garcia Berrocal, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Teresa Morales, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente estudio es descubrir y dar a conocer la historia del Hôtel-Dieude Paris y la historia paralela al mismo de las Hermanas Agustinas, cuidadoras de los enfermos de dicho hospital. El método usado para llevar a cabo el estudio ha sido una amplia búsqueda bibliográfica, traducción, lectura, análisis y reflexión de los documentos encontrados. Las conclusiones de este estudio nos hablan de la dureza de la ocupación, de cómo podían llegar a tardar en formarse para ejercer plenamente, hasta, veintiséis años y de cómo estaban de delimitadas las funciones entre unos cuerpos y otros (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;17(35): 42-54, ene.-abr. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112422</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hôtel-Dieu de París; orígenes y aparición de las primeras enfermeras religiosas de la historia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29425^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6835</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6825</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9929^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10486</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38876</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6917^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12490</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
