<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74161</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Determinant factors of blood lead levels in children of 7-8 years old in the Autonomous Community of Madrid, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Lead is a toxic heavy metal. Exposure to it has been reduced by the ban on leaded petrol and, now, other sources such as drinking water are more relevant. The aims of this study are to determine the blood lead levels of children in the second year of primary education living within the Autonomous Community of Madrid, and to establish the relationship between these levels and the lead concentration in the drinking water consumed by the children. Methods: A cross-sectional study including 515 children selected from public primary schools and those private ones that received partial public funding in the Autonomous Community of Madrid. The children of each primary school were transferred by bus to a hospital, where blood collection and a basic clinical examination were carried out. Parents filled out a self-completion questionnaire and, following certain guidelines, collected a water sample from home. Water samples were also taken at each primary school. Results: The values for the blood lead levels of the children ranged between 1.0 &#131;Êg/dL and 11.5 &#131;Êg/dL, with a geometric mean of 3.8 &#131;Êg/dL (standard deviation: 0.1 &#131;Êg/L). Blood lead levels were significantly associated with age, certain oral habits, business sector of the father, smoking by the mother, geographical location and age of the family residence, and the presence of certain pets. Conclusions: The geometric mean of blood lead concentrations in children in the Autonomous Community of Madrid is 3.8 !g/dL, below that of 10 !g/dL defined by the Centers for Disease Control. Two children had levels of 11.5 &#131;Êg/dL. The relationship between the blood lead level, consumption of drinking water and other socioeconomic factors is statistically significant (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ordóñez Iriarte, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aránguez Ruiz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aparicio Madre, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivero Cuadrado, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: El plomo es un metal pesado toxico. La exposición al mismo se ha visto reducida por la prohibición de las gasolinas con plomo, y hoy en día son más relevantes otras fuentes, como el agua de bebida. El objeto de este estudio es determinarlos niveles de plomo en sangre que presentan los niños de segundo curso de Educación Primaria que residen en la Comunidad de Madrid, y establecer la relación entre dichos niveles y la concentración de plomo en el agua de bebida que ingieren. Métodos: Estudio transversal, para el que se seleccionaron 515 niños de 23 colegios públicos y/o concertados de la Comunidad de Madrid. Los niños de cada colegio eran trasladados en autobus a un centro hospitalario, donde se procedía a una extracción sanguínea y a una exploración clínica basica. Los padres rellenaban una encuesta autocumplimentada y recogían una muestra de agua del domicilio, siguiendo unas directrices determinadas. También se muestreo el agua del colegio. Resultados: Los valores de plomo en sangre de los niños se situaron entre 1,0 y 11,5 &#131;Êg/dL, con una media geométrica de3,8 &#131;Êg/L (con una desviación estandar de 0,1). Los niveles de plomo en sangre estuvieron asociados de forma significativa a la edad, a ciertos hábitos de oralidad, al sector de trabajo de los padres, al consumo de tabaco de las madres, a la ubicación geográfica y la antigüedad de las viviendas, y a la presencia de mascotas en el domicilio. Conclusiones: La concentración de plomo en sangre en los niños de la Comunidad de Madrid presento una media geométrica de 3,8 !g/dL, nivel que se situá por debajo de los 10 !g/dL definidos por los Centers for Diseases Control and Prevention. Dos niños tuvieron niveles de 11,5 &#131;Êg/dL. Resulta significativa la relación existente entre el plomo en sangre, el consumo del agua de bebida y otras variables sociodemograficas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;67(4): 173-181, abr. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74161</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores determinantes de plomo en sangre en niños de 7-8 años de la Comunidad de Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34355^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34355^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34355^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
