<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154006</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4603</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Laryngectomized voice rehabilitation: handicap, perception and acoustic analysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Laryngectomized patients have a very important limitation when they lose the vocal function. Voice rehabilitation is fulfilled by means of the esophageal voice or by means of a phonatory prosthesis. Both methods are useful but they have evident differences concerning the vocal quality obtained. Objective. Determine how rehabilitated voice is perceived with both methods by patients and observers, completing the study with its acoustic analysis. Material and method. Laryngectomized patients (n = 18) with rehabilitated voice by means of esophageal voice (n = 10) and phonatory prosthesis (n = 8). A study was made through the VHI-30, acoustic analysis (F0, TMF,HNR, «speech rate», intensity and spectrogram) and perceptual evaluation (GRBAS and CAPE-V). Results. VHI-30 displays similar values in both types of rehabilitated voice. The acoustic analysis shows differences between both types of rehabilitated voices and the usual laryngeal voice. The perceptual study presents a higher degree of affectation on the esophageal voice than on the PF one. There is no relation between what the patient perceives and what the observer values. The acoustic and perceptual studies show closer values to normality in the phonatory prosthesis voice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Granda Membiela, Carla María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sirgo Rodríguez, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Marcos, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Gutiérrez, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santamarina Rabanal, Liliana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mamolar Andrés, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los pacientes laringectomizados tienen una limitación muy importante al perder la función vocal. La rehabilitación de la voz se realiza por erigmofonía o prótesis fonatoria. Ambos procedimientos son útiles pero tienen diferencias evidentes en la calidad vocal obtenida. Objetivo. Determinar cómo es percibida la voz rehabilitada con ambos procedimientos por los pacientes y observadores, completando el estudio con su análisis acústico. Material y método. Pacientes laringectomizados (n = 18) con voz rehabilitada con erigmofonía (n = 10) y prótesis fonatoria (n = 8). Estudio por medio de VHI-30, análisis acústico (F0, TMF, HNR, «speech-rate», intensidad y espectrograma) y evaluación perceptual (GRBAS y CAPE-V). Resultados. El VHI-30 presenta valores similares en ambos tipos de voz rehabilitada. El análisis acústico muestra diferencias importantes entre ambos tipos de voces, siendo los valores obtenidos con prótesis fonatoria más parecidos a los de la voz laríngea. La evaluación perceptual indica mayor grado de afectación en la voz erigmofónica que en la prótesis fonatoria. No se observa relación significativa entre lo percibido por los pacientes con ambos tipos de voces rehabilitadas y lo valorado por el observador. Los estudios acústicos y perceptuales muestran valores más próximos a la normalidad en la voz de prótesis fonatoria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. logop. foniatr. audiol. (Ed. impr.);36(3): 127-134, jul.-sept. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154006</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La voz del laringectomizado: incapacidad, percepción y análisis acústico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8004^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8004^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8004^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28150^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13445^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28150^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11916^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28150^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
