<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87067</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of the antiretroviral therapy cover in Spanish patients with HIV/AIDS in 1999</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Late diagnosis, irregular access of some patients to medical care and bad treatment adherence reduce the effi cacy of the HIV/ AIDS Medical Care Programs. The antiretroviral therapy cover could be an indicator of the effi cacy of these Programs. Objectives: To evaluate the antiretroviral therapy cover of the Spanish patients with HIV/AIDS in 1999. Material and Methods: We calculate the cost of providing antiretroviral drugs to the HIV/AIDS patients multiplying the number of patients by the average yearly cost of the therapy. The therapeutic cover is the quotient of the expenses incurred and the expenses needed, expressed as a percentage. Results: In Spain in 1999 the antiretroviral therapy cover would have been 33% (24-46 %) for all HIV-infected persons and 44% (35-57%) for the patients with an established AIDS  diagnosis. Discussion: To optimize the HIV/AIDS healthcare services would mean to treble the prescription of antiretroviral drugs in Spain. A more effi cient and less costly alternative would be the research and development of the HIV vaccine. Conclusions: The study of the antiretroviral therapy cover reveals the ineffi ciency of the antiretroviral therapy as a tool for controlling the HIV/AIDS epidemic (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cascante Burgos, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cascante Burgos, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El diagnóstico tardío, el acceso errático de algunos pacientes a los Servicios Sanitarios y la mala adherencia a los tratamientos restan efi cacia a los Programas de Asistencia Sanitaria del VIH/SIDA. La Cobertura de Terapéutica Antirretroviral podría ser un indicador de la efi cacia de estos Programas. Objetivos: Evaluar la Cobertura de Terapéutica Antirretroviral de los Pacientes Españoles VIH/ SIDA en el año 1999. Material y Métodos: Calculamos el Gasto que sería Necesario hacer para proporcionar medicación antirretroviral a los pacientes VIH/SIDA multiplicando el número de pacientes por el Coste medio anual del Tratamiento. La Cobertura Terapéutica es el  cociente entre el gasto realizado y el gasto necesario, expresado en porcentaje. Resultados: En España, en 1999, la Cobertura de Terapéutica Antirretroviral habría sido del 33% (24%-46%) para el conjunto de todos los infectados por VIH y del 44% (35%-57%) para los pacientes con diagnóstico de VIH/SIDA establecido. Discusión: Optimizar el funcionamiento de los Servicios Asistenciales del VIH/SIDA implicaría triplicar el Consumo de Antirretrovirales en España. Una alternativa más efi caz y menos costosa sería la Investigación y el Desarrollo de la Vacuna del VIH. Conclusiones: El estudio de la Cobertura de Terapéutica Antirretroviral desvela la inefi cacia de los Tratamientos Antirretrovirales  como herramientas de control de la epidemia de VIH/SIDA (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;66(1): 7-15, ene.-mar. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87067</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la Cobertura de Terapéutica Antirretroviral en los pacientes españoles VIH/SIDA, en 1999</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29364^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16855^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29364^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50207</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35395^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
