<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053271</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The reliability of non-invasive diagnostic tests in recurring deep vein thrombosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The clinical signs and symptoms of recurring deep vein thrombosis (RDVT) can be very anodyne,    and may easily be confused with the symptomatology produced by a post-thrombotic syndrome. Diagnostic errors have    very important effects because false positives mean carrying out a possibly indefinite treatment with anticoagulant    drugs and false negatives expose the patient to new episodes of RDVT and/or a pulmonary embolism. Development. In    this review the pathophysiological mechanisms of RDVT will be discussed and we will also evaluate the different    diagnostic tests and their reliability</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Orgaz Pérez-Grueso, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benito, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flores Herrero, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leal, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Doblas Domínguez, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fontcuberta García, Juan M. </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermúdez, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los síntomas y signos clínicos de la trombosis venosa profunda recurrente (TVPR) pueden ser    muy anodinos, confundiéndose con la sintomatología producida por un síndrome postrombótico. Los errores diagnósticos    tienen gran trascendencia, ya que los falsos positivos suponen realizar un tratamiento posiblemente indefinido con    anticoagulantes, y los falsos negativos exponen al paciente a nuevos episodios de TVPR y/o a un embolismo pulmonar.    Desarrollo. En esta revisión se discutirán los mecanismos fisiopatológicos de la TVPR y se realizará una valoración de    los diferentes tests diagnósticos y su fiabilidad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;59(2): 155-172, mar.-abr. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053271</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fiabilidad de los tests diagnósticos no invasivos en la recurrencia de la trombosis venosa profunda</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23418^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31994^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33361^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11420^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3979^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
