<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-12952</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationships between personality styles and life domains satisfaction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study examines the relationship between personality styles and life domains satisfaction across the evaluation of 215 university students. Two personality profiles are interpreted. The relationship between satisfaction in life domains satisfaction for each one of the profiles are studied from a constructivist approach. In this way, we have used the Millon Inventory Personality Styles Inventory (Millon, 1994) and one scale of satisfaction in life domains (study, family, spare time, friends, classmates, physical health, psychological health, standard of living and emotional life). The results show that the personality profiles modulate relationship s of the life domains satisfaction, being significant the number and type of related domains. This result indicate that the representation the satisfaction is different according to the personal characters (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez López, M. Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Morales, Juan Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este trabajo se analizan las relaciones entre los estilos de personalidad y la satisfacción en diferentes áreas vitales en un grupo de 215 estudiantes universitarios. Se interpretan dos perfiles de personalidad y se estudian las relaciones entre la satisfacción en diferentes áreas vitales para cada uno de los perfiles desde una perspectiva constructivista. Se ha utilizado el Inventario Millon de Estilos de Personalidad (Millon, 1994) y una escala de satisfacción por áreas vitales (estudios, familia, tiempo libre, amigos, compañeros de clase, salud física, salud psicológica, nivel de vida y vida emocional). Los resultados indican que las características de personalidad modulan las relaciones en la satisfacción de diferentes áreas vitales, siendo significativo el número y tipo de áreas relacionadas, lo que indica que la representación de la satisfacción es diferente según las características personales. (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);14(1): 100-105, ene. 2002. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-12952</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relaciones entre estilos de personalidad y satisfacción autopercibida en diferentes áreas vitales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10742^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1248</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10746^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200201</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
