<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036731</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Role of microvasculature in the development of acute lung injury induced by mechanical ventilation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pulmonary wedge pressure is one of the determinants of pulmonary edema and in addition favors the development of pulmonary injury induced by mechanical ventilation (PIMV). Accordingly, in the critically ill patients subject to mechanical ventilation (MV), the precise determination of pulmonary wedge pressure gain in importance. Vascular flow is also a decisive factor in acute pulmonary injury, and its increase favors a more intense pulmonary injury. The increase of these physiological variables determines an increment in mechanical stress on the cells of pulmonary capillary endothelium, and this stress can induce an endothelial inflammatory response with appearance or worsening of acute pulmonary injury. Accordingly, reducing pulmonary vascular stress can diminish acute lung injury in experimental models</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villagra García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piacentini, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Aguilar, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hotchkiss, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanch Torra, Ll</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáenz-Valiente, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murias, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La presión capilar pulmonar es uno de los determinantes de la formación de edema pulmonar y además favorece el desarrollo de lesión pulmonar inducida por la ventilación mecánica (VILI). En consecuencia, en los enfermos críticos sometidos a ventilación mecánica (VM), la determinación ajustada de la presión capilar cobra mayor relevancia. El flujo vascular también es un factor determinante de la lesión pulmonar aguda, cuyo incremento favorece una mayor lesión pulmonar. El aumento de estas variables fisiológicas determina un incremento del estrés mecánico sobre las células del endotelio capilar pulmonar, lo que puede inducir una respuesta inflamatoria endotelial y favorecer la aparición o el empeoramiento de la lesión pulmonar aguda. En consecuencia, reducir el estrés vascular pulmonar puede disminuir la lesión pulmonar aguda en modelos experimentales</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);29(4): 226-235, mayo 2005. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036731</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papel de la microcirculación en el desarrollo de la lesión pulmonar aguda inducida por la ventilación mecánica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12549^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9022^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13702</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8345^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27781</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
