<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043999</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1473</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of dexmedetomidine on intracranial hemodynamics in severe head injured patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Dexmedetomidine, an alpha2 adrenergic agonist, with distinctive characteristics when compared to traditional plans, namely: conscious sedation, sympatholysis and lack of respiratory depression, represents an attempt to improve the sedoanalgesia of critically ill patients.Objective. To study dexmedetomidine´s effect on intracranial hemodynamic and hemometabolic parameters in severe head injured patients. Material and methods. Prospective study on the effect of Dexmedetomidine on twelve severe head injured patients (Glasgow Coma Scale score &lt;= 8) admitted to an intensive care unit, with intracranial pressure &lt; 20 mmHg and O2 saturation monitoring of blood from jugular bulb. The drug was perfused intravenously during 3 hours, in progressive doses (0.2, 0.4 y 0.7 ug/kg/h). All other sedo-analgesia medication had been previously withdrawn. Results. No significant differences were found in intracranial pressure, mean arterial pressure and cerebral hemometabolic parameters after infusion of dexmedetomidine in relation to basal values. Cerebral perfusion pressure showed a trend to decrease during the drug infusion (marginal effect, p =.058). Cardiac frequency decreased significantly after the drug administration. Conclusions. At the doses utilized, dexmedetomidine was safe, and it was not associated with significant changes in intracranial hemodynamics, nor in cerebral hemometabolic parameters, in a group of severe head injured patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miraballes, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fariña, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Biestro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grille, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La dexmedetomidina, un agonista adrenérgico selectivoalfa2, constituye un intento de mejorar la sedoanalgesia de los pacientes críticos, por sus efectos distintivos en comparación a los planes tradicionales como son: sedación consciente, simpaticolisis y ausencia de depresión respiratoria. Objetivo. Estudiar el efecto de la dexmedetomidina, un nuevo agonista alfa28, sobre la hemodinámica intracraneal y sobre los parámetros hemometabólicos cerebrales en un grupo de pacientes con trauma craneoencefálico grave. Material y métodos. Estudio prospectivo de los pacientes con lesión encefálica traumática grave (Glasgow Coma Scale &lt;= 8) ingresados en un Centro de Tratamiento Intensivo (CTI) que recibieron monitorización de la presión intracraneal (PIC) y monitorización de saturación de O2 del bulbo yugular (SjO2). Se realizó una perfusión intravenosa de la droga durante 3 horas, en dosis progresivas (0.2, 0.4 y 0.7 ug/kg/h), previa suspensión de otros sedantes y analgésicos. Resultados. Se estudiaron 12 pacientes sin hipertensión intracraneal. No se encontraron diferencias significativas entre los valores de PIC y presión arterial media (PAM) tras la infusión de la droga en relación con los valores basales. La presión de perfusión cerebral (PPC) mostró una tendencia a disminuir durante el estudio (efecto marginal, p=0.058). Se encontró un descenso significativo de la frecuencia cardíaca (FC) (p&lt;0.0001) en relación a los valores basales. No se hallaron diferencias significativas en los parámetros hemometabólicos cerebrales (SjO2 y CEO2).Conclusión. A las dosis utilizadas, la dexmede-tomidina fue segura, no asociándose a alteraciones significativas de la hemodinámica intracraneal ni del metabolismo sanguíneo cerebral en pacientes en la etapa aguda del trauma craneoencefálico grave (TECG)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurocirugia (Astur);16(5): 411-418, jun. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043999</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de la dexmedetomidina sobre la hemodinámica intracraneal en pacientes con lesión encefálica traumatica grave</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6410^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7170^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34395^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24697</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6410^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6410^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12461^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24219^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6590^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34395^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1821^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d319^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2599^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d319^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32371^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32371^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6493^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7170^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
