<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114889</identifier>
<setSpec>0377-4732</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Financial exploitation and undue influence in the elderly</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Older adults are at especial risk of financial exploitation and its achievement by a specific dynamic called undue influence. It is imperative that services and professionals who work with the elderly learn how to prevent, detect, and manage these cases. The detection and successful prosecution of these situations is dependent on the ability of family, friends and professionals to interpret the signs of abuse and the ability of forensic professionals to evaluate it. Effective assessment, by the use of the different models described hereby, can prevent needless emotional and financial losses of the victims and help them maintain their autonomy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Richards, Danielle</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Durán, Esperanza L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blum, Bennett</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las personas de avanzada edad resultan especialmente vulnerables al abuso económico y a su consecución mediante la dinámica específica denominada influencia indebida. Es imperativo que los servicios y los profesionales que trabajan con personas mayores aprendan a prevenir, detectar y manejar estos casos. La detección y el éxito en el enjuiciamiento de estas situaciones dependen en gran parte de la capacidad de interpretar los signos de abuso por parte de los familiares, amigos y profesionales que contactan con el anciano y la habilidad de los profesionales forenses en la evaluación del cuadro. Una evaluación eficaz, mediante los diferentes modelos que describimos, puede evitar innecesarias pérdidas emocionales y económicas a las víctimas y ayudarlas a mantener su autonomía (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. med. legal;39(2): 63-69, abr.-jun.2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114889</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abuso financiero e influencia indebida de las personas de avanzada edad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d16665</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5688^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17556^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28416^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5688^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28470</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50238</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38400^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
