<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116480</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Axillary approach for surgical closure of atrial septal defect</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Mid-line sternotomy is the routine approach for surgical repair of congenital heart diseases. However, its noticeable scar is a constant reminder of having undergone heart surgery. Several alternative approaches have been developed for simple cardiac conditions to hide the scar. Our series, consisting of 26 patients with axillary closure of atrial septal defect, is presented. The median age was 5.45 years (range 3-13), and median weight was 19.84 Kg. (range 13-37). The defect was closed directly in 13 cases, and with an autologous pericardial patch in the other 13. The number of surgical steps and time taken were the same as in median sternotomy. Functional recovery, intensive care unit stay, and hospital discharge were also standard. The cosmetic result, assessed both by patients and relatives, was excellent (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zabala, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuenca, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Picazo, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil-Jaurena, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conejo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La esternotomía media es el acceso habitual para la corrección quirúrgica de las cardiopatías congénitas. Sin embargo, la cicatriz visible recuerda siempre que se trata de un cardiópata. Diversos abordajes alternativos han sido explorados en afecciones simples con objeto de ocultar la cicatriz. Presentamos una serie de 26 pacientes intervenidos de comunicación interauricular por vía axilar. La media de edad fue de 5,45 años (rango 3-13) y de peso 19,84 kg (rango 13-37). En 13 casos el defecto se cerró directamente (sutura) y en los 13 restantes, mediante parche de pericardio propio. Los pasos y los tiempos quirúrgicos son superponibles a la técnica clásica. La recuperación funcional, estancia en cuidados intensivos y planta hospitalaria hasta el alta han sido estándar. El resultado estético, valorado por pacientes y familiares, ha sido excelente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);79(2): 108-111, ago. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116480</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incisión axilar para el cierre quirúrgico de la comunicación interauricular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1377^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6496^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5211^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53703^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
