<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-059033</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Surgical treatment of Duane´s syndrome type I by recession of the medial rectus of the afected eye and faden operation of the contralateral medial rectus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: Different surgical approaches have        been described for the treatment of Duane&#146;s syndrome.        The purpose of our study is to report the        results of patients undergoing recession of the        medial rectus (MR) muscle of the affected eye        and placement of contralateral MR faden posterior        fixation sutures.        Methods: Retrospective study of 11 patients treated        by a 4-7 mm recession of the MR of the affected        eye and 13 mm faden posterior fixation suture        of the contralateral MR in order to correct abnormal        head position and esotropia in primary position.        Results: After surgery, there was no torticolis in        81.8% of patients, with less than 10º of torticolis in        the remainder. In all patients, postoperative esotropia        was less than 5 prismatic dioptres. Conclusion: This is a safe and effective procedure        in Duane&#146;s syndrome type I to treat moderate esotropia        and torticolis</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-Manrique, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Caballero, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Sánchez, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puerto-Hernández, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Contreras, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Se han descrito numerosos tratamientos        quirúrgicos para el síndrome de Duane (SD) tipo I.        El objetivo de este trabajo es comunicar los resultados        obtenidos en pacientes diagnosticados de SD        tipo I sometidos a retroinserción del recto medial        (RM) del lado afecto y operación de faden del RM        contralateral.        Métodos: Estudio retrospectivo sobre once pacientes        con SD tipo I a los que se les realiza una retroinserción        del RM del lado afecto de entre 4 y 7 mm y faden        a 13 mm del RM contralateral para resolver el tortícolis        y la endotropía presentes en posición primaria.        Resultados: Tras la cirugía, el tortícolis desapareció        en el 81,8% de los pacientes, siendo menor de        10º en el resto. En todos los pacientes la endotropía        postquirúrgica fue menor de 5 dioptrías prismáticas. Conclusión: Esta técnica es un procedimiento        seguro y efectivo para el tratamiento de endotropías        y tortícolis moderados en el SD tipo I</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;83(2): 113-116, feb. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-059033</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento quirúrgico del síndrome de Duane, tipo I mediante retroinserción del recto medial del lado afecto y faden del recto medial contralateral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24809^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24809^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13889^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27992^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200802</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
