<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159788</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Autoadhesive bandage on comprehensive treatment and rehabilitation of burned hand</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and Objective. Hand burns constitute pathology with very difficult management and which functional sequelae are hugely important. The treatment of these burns has to include an early debridement followed by a focused rehabilitation process, with splints, physiotherapy and pressotherapy. In our Burns Unit we employ Coban(TM) 3M bandage as early pressure therapy. This is a proven technique from the rehabilitation of lymphedema, which applied to burns reduces the prolonged edema (causal agent of numerous complications and functional impairment), as well as hypertrophic healing. Patients and Methods. We conduct a retrospective study with 14 patients with 2º deep grade and 3rd grade in hand, to analyze their demographic features, burn characteristics, chronology of Coban bandage usage and performance of other therapies, complications rate and functional recovery rate. Furthermore, we detail the application method of this bandage. Results. The application of Coban(TM) bandage was performed in average of 17.93 days after burns coverage or healing by 2nd intention, keeping its application for 75.54 days in average, with low complication rate (mild hypertrophic scars: 28.57 %; pain: 7.14%; edema: 7.14%: itching: 7.14%; infection: 0), as well as high functional recovery rate (complete recovery in 64.28%, with mild impairment in 14.28%). From the data collected in our study we show that the application of Coban(TM) rehabilitation treatment of burns showed a low rate of complications, which were mostly minor, accompanied by high rates of functional recovery (64.28% full recovery and 14.28% with slight limitation). To our knowledge, there are no references in the literature that detail an application protocol of this bandage on burn patients. Conclusions. Based on the results of our study, we believe that early application of self-adhesive bandage Coban(TM) 3M as an additional tool in the comprehensive treatment of burns may be interesting as it reduces levels of edema and the incidence of hypertrophic healing. Our study shows low complication rates and high levels of functional recovery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Simón Sanz, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esteban Vico, Juan Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Klenner Muñoz, Cristhian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villaverde Doménech, Eloísa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Del Caz, Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes y Objetivo. Las quemaduras en las manos constituyen una patología de muy difícil manejo y cuyas secuelas son de vital importancia desde el punto de vista funcional. Su tratamiento debe incluir un desbridamiento precoz seguido de un proceso de rehabilitación temprana con férulas, fisioterapia y presoterapia. En nuestra Unidad de Quemados empleamos la venda Coban(R) 3M como inicio temprano de presoterapia. Se trata de una técnica probada procedente del tratamiento rehabilitador del linfedema, que aplicada a las quemaduras permite reducir el edema prolongado (agente causal de múltiples complicaciones y de la pérdida funcional) y la cicatrización hipertrófica. Pacientes y Método. Realizamos un estudio retrospectivo sobre 14 pacientes con quemaduras de 2º grado profundo o de 3er grado en mano, analizando sus características demográficas, características de la quemadura, cronología del empleo del vendaje Coban(R) 3M y uso de otras terapias, índice de complicaciones y tasa de recuperación funcional. Explicamos también de forma detallada el método de aplicación del vendaje. Resultados. Aplicamos el vendaje a una media de 17.93 días tras la cobertura o cierre por segunda intención de las quemaduras, manteniéndolo durante una media de 75.54 días, con bajas tasas de complicaciones (cicatrización hipertrófica leve: 28.57%; dolor: 7.14%: edema: 7.14%; prurito: 7.14%; infección: 0), así como altas tasas de recuperación funcional (completa: 64.28%; limitaciones leves: 14.28%). Observamos que la aplicación de este tipo de vendaje en el tratamiento rehabilitador de quemaduras presentó una baja tasa de complicaciones, mayoritariamente menores, y altas tasas de recuperación funcional (64.28% de recuperación completa y 14.28% con limitación leve). Hasta donde hemos podido comprobar, no existe ningún trabajo en la literatura que detalle un protocolo similar de aplicación de este vendaje en pacientes quemados. Conclusiones. En base a los resultados de nuestro estudio, consideramos que la aplicación precoz del vendaje autoadherente Coban(R) 3M como herramienta adicional en el tratamiento integral de las quemaduras, puede resultar interesante ya que reduce los niveles de edema y la incidencia de cicatrización hipertrófica. Nuestro estudio presenta unas bajas tasas de complicación y altos niveles de recuperación funcional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;42(4): 347-353, oct.-dic. 2016. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159788</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vendaje autoadherente en el tratamiento integral y rehabilitador de la mano quemada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15343</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2088^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7796^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30787^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1480^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9964^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14403^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33888</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6382^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
