<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147163</identifier>
<setSpec>1697-641X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Lower second molar endodontic retreatment with complex anatomy. Endodontic Retreatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study is to present the clinical management of an endodontic retreatment in a case in which the tooth presented a complex anatomy, broken file and a filling material that was difficult to bypass. We present a case in which a patient refers pain in an endodontically treated 37. Diagnostic tests indicate the presence of apical periodontitis due to the failure of the previous treatment as a result of its complex anatomy and subobturation of the canals. Cavity access revealed the existence of an extra root containing a broken file. The distal root was filled using a composite like a filling material. Due to the broken files, ledge, filling materials used and so forth, it took three appointments to reach the working length for the entire root canal system. The irrigation protocol consisted of 4.25% hypochlorite, 17% EDTA and 4.25% hypochlorite activated with Endoactivator®. The B&amp;L® system was used for filling. 1 year follow-up showed healing of the previous apical periodontitis. Moreover, the tooth presented adequate function and esthetic. In conclusion, a profound knowledge of the internal anatomy of the teeth and the possible variations is critical. Separated instruments and changes to the original anatomy are the primary obstacles that must be overcome in order to achieve success in endodontic retreatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Flores García, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estévez Luaña, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valencia de Pablo, Óliver</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Ruiz, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cisneros Cabello, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo es presentar el manejo de un retratamiento con una anatomía compleja, con presencia de un instrumento separado y material de obturación difícil de permeabilizar. Presentamos el caso de una paciente que acude con dolor en un 37 tratado endodónticamente. Las pruebas diagnósticas indican la presencia de periodontitis apical por fracaso del tratamiento previo debida a una anatomía compleja y a una subobturación de los conductos. Al realizar la apertura, se comprobó la existencia de una raíz extra, en la que se encontró una lima separada, y un material similar al composite utilizado para obturar la raíz distal. Alcanzar la longitud de trabajo de todo el sistema de conductos y su instrumentación, debido limas rotas, escalones, material de obturación... costó tres citas. Se hizo un protocolo de irrigación con hipoclorito 4,25%, EDTA 17% e hipoclorito 4,25% activado con Endoactivator®. Se obturó con el sistema B&amp;L®. El control 13 meses después muestra un curación de la periodontitis apical previa y el diente se mantiene en función y estética satisfactorias. Como conclusión, es esencial un profundo conocimiento de la anatomía interna de los dientes y sus posibles variaciones. Los instrumentos separados y las alteraciones de la anatomía original son los principales obstáculos para lograr el éxito en un retratamiento endodóntico, que debería ser la primera opción ante un fracaso del tratamiento inicial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cient. dent. (Ed. impr.);12(3): 51-58, sept.-dic. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147163</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Retratamiento de un segundo molar inferior con anatomía compleja. Retratamiento Endodóntico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32617^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12765^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12764^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3801^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33109^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9153</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
