<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124967</identifier>
<setSpec>2014-9832</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Methodologies and materials in gross human anatomy learning. Perceptions by digital native medical students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To know the opinion of the first students generation that has grown up under the information and communication technology about the methodologies currently used in the teaching-learning of gross human anatomy in medical studies. Subjects and methods. The study was based on the data provided by an anonymously answered survey. Seventy-four students of the second year medical students at the University of Las Palmas de Gran Canaria answered the survey. Results and conclusions. The methodologies better considered for learning gross human anatomy were the study of cases and the recognition of anatomic structures in fixed human material (prosections and dissection). The students considered the main advantage of the last, the recognition of tridimensional anatomical structures and the consolidation of anatomical knowledge, and the main disadvantage was the unpleasant odour due to the fixing process. Students considered the study of cases, the recognition and identification of structures in fixed human material and the surface anatomy sessions, the methodologies that better suited to acquire skills in clinical anatomy and the lectures and the study of fixed human material the most appropriate methodologies to obtain knowledge about descriptive and functional anatomy. Plastic anatomical models and computing resources were considered the worst methods to study gross human anatomy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mompeó-Corredera, Blanca</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer la opinión de los estudiantes de la primera generación que ha crecido bajo el imperio de las tecnologías de la información y comunicación sobre las metodologías utilizadas actualmente en el proceso de enseñanza-aprendizaje de la anatomía humana en los estudios de medicina. Sujetos y métodos. Se realiza un estudio a partir de los datos aportados por una encuesta contestada anónimamente por 74 estudiantes de segundo curso de la titulación de medicina en la Universidad de Las Palmas de Gran Canaria. Resultados y conclusiones. En general, las metodologías mejor consideradas para el aprendizaje de la anatomía humana fueron el estudio de casos y el reconocimiento de estructuras en material humano fijado (prosecciones y disección), siendo la principal ventaja de esta última el reconocimiento tridimensional de las estructuras anatómicas y la consecuente consolidación de los conocimientos anatómicos, y su principal desventaja es el olor desagradable, debido a los procesos de fijación. Para la adquisición de habilidades en anatomía clínica se consideraron como las metodologías más adecuadas el estudio de casos, el reconocimiento e identificación de estructuras en material humano fijado y las sesiones de anatomía de superficie, mientras que las que mejor se adaptaban a la adquisición de conocimientos de anatomía descriptiva y funcional eran las clases magistrales y el estudio del material humano fijado. Los métodos peor considerados para estudiar anatomía fueron la utilización de modelos anatómicos plásticos y los recursos informáticos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Fund. Educ. Méd. (Ed. impr.);17(2): 99-104, jun. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124967</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Metodologías y materiales para el aprendizaje de la anatomía humana. Percepciones de los estudiantes de medicina 'nativos digitales'</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13724^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d727^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4572^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9143</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14043</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
