<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149010</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Disorders of executive functions. Diagnosis and treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Different contributions to the scientific literature made over the last few decades have confirmed the prefrontal cortex as the neurobiological basis of the executive functions. Today, both the evaluation protocols for carrying out diagnoses and the structuring of the treatment and neurocognitive stimulation plans must interpret each of the prefrontal syndromes (dorsolateral, medial or of the anterior cingulate, and orbitofrontal) involved in the aetiopathogenesis of the different neurodevelopmental and adult disorders in which the executive functions are affected. Aims. To report on the latest advances in diagnosis and treatment of the executive functions and to stress the importance of identifying and understanding the three syndromes of prefrontal dysfunction in the phase of diagnosis and in neurocognitive rehabilitation. Development. The authors carry out a review of the literature on the latest advances in neuroscience as regards the neurobiological and neuropsychological foundations of the executive functions and their diagnosis and treatment. Conclusions. Every day, the scientific community confirms the importance of identifying and understanding the brain circuits in the diagnostic stage, especially the prefrontal dysfunction syndromes involved in the neuropsychological deficits of the different neurodevelopmental and adult disorders, so as to be able to establish effective neurocognitive stimulation protocols (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Etchepareborda, Máximo C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Mejía, Iván D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los diferentes aportes de la literatura científica ratifican, desde hace un par de décadas, a la corteza prefrontal como base neurobiológica de las funciones ejecutivas. En la actualidad, tanto los protocolos de evaluación para la realización del diagnóstico como la estructuración de los planes de tratamiento y estimulación neurocognitiva deben hacer la lectura de cada uno de los síndromes prefrontales (dorsolateral, medial o del cíngulo anterior, y orbitofrontal) implicados en la etiopatogenia de los diferentes trastornos del neurodesarrollo y del adulto en los que se ven afectadas las funciones ejecutivas. Objetivos. Exponer los últimos avances sobre diagnóstico y tratamiento de las funciones ejecutivas y resaltar la importancia de identificar y comprender en la fase diagnóstica y en la rehabilitación neurocognitiva los tres síndromes de disfunción prefrontal. Desarrollo. Se realiza una revisión bibliográfica sobre los últimos avances neurocientíficos alrededor de las bases neurobiológicas, neuropsicológicas, diagnóstico y tratamiento de las funciones ejecutivas. Conclusión. Cada día la comunidad neurocientífica ratifica la importancia de identificar y comprender en la etapa diagnóstica los circuitos cerebrales, específicamente los síndromes de disfunción prefrontal implicados en los déficits neuropsicológicos de los diferentes trastornos del neurodesarrollo y del adulto para poder establecer protocolos eficaces de estimulación neurocognitiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;57(supl.1): s95-s103, 6 sept. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149010</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos de las funciones ejecutivas. Diagnóstico y tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30601^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13448^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1951^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1541</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2699^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53744^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5761^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2699^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6330^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13448^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13448^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2699^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
