<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052688</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nutrition alterations in internal medicine. Body composition analysis with bioelectrical impedance</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To determine the prevalence of malnutrition in patients in Internal Medicine. To describe the changes of corporal composition depending on body mass index (BMI). To evaluate validity of the different screening tools for the estimation of body composition.                 Material and methods. Prospective observational cross-sectional study of the prevalence of malnutrition in 300 patients (sample 1); these were chosen 136 patients (sample 2), classifying in four groups: BMI  30: 30 patients. In the patients of sample 2, we carried out a protocol of nutritional evaluation with anthropometry, laboratory and bioelectrical impedance analysis.                 Results. The prevalence of desnutrition was 9.3% and the obesity was 22.3%. In undernourished patients, the measure of body compartments with bioelectrical impedance, expressed in percentage of body weight, were: fat mass 20.5%, fat-free mass 79.4% and total body mater 58.3%. The body composition in obeses was: fat mass 40.1%, fat-free mass 60.6% and total body water 44.3%. The patients with normal BMI, the meta index (impedance at 50 kHz/BMI) was 25.9 ± 5.21; in undernourished the index was higher (36.7) and obeses lower (15.5). The meta index (30-20) estimates desnutrition-obesity with high sensibility and specificity. The prevalence of desnutrition varies from 6% to 69% and obesity from 23% to 74%, using different methods and criterions for the estimation of body composition.                 Conclusions. In Internal Medicine, the overweight (BMI &gt; 25) is the most prevalent nutritional alteration. The bioelectrical impedance analysis helps for estimation of body composition and meta index is a very useful indicator of malnutrition (desnutrition-obesity)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Sánchez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castuera Gil, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez de Oteyza, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo Lasso de la Vega, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Determinar la prevalencia de alteraciones de la nutrición en pacientes ingresados en Medicina Interna. Describir los cambios en la composición corporal según el índice de masa corporal (IMC). Evaluar la utilidad de los diferentes métodos de medición de la composición corporal.                 Material y métodos. Se realizó un estudio prospectivo observacional transversal para determinar la prevalencia de malnutrición por IMC en 300 pacientes (muestra 1); de éstos se seleccionaron 136 pacientes (muestra 2), que se distribuyeron en cuatro grupos según el IMC: desnutridos (IMC  30): 30 pacientes. A todos los pacientes de la muestra 2 se les realizó un estudio de valoración nutricional con antropometría, laboratorio y análisis de impedancia bioeléctrica.                 Resultados. La prevalencia de desnutrición en los 300 pacientes fue del 9,3% y de la obesidad del 22,3%. El valor de los componentes corporales medidos por impedancia bioeléctrica, expresados en porcentaje del peso corporal, fue en los pacientes desnutridos: 20,5% de masa grasa, 79,4% de magro y 58,3% de agua corporal total. En los obesos: 40,1% de masa grasa, 60,6% de magro y 44,3% de agua corporal total. El índice meta (impedancia a 50 kHz/IMC) en los pacientes con IMC normal fue 25,9 ± 5,21; los desnutridos presentaron los valores más altos (36,7) y los obesos los más bajos (15,5). El índice meta (30-20) identifica desnutrición-obesidad con una alta sensibilidad y especificidad. La prevalencia de desnutrición varió entre un 6% y un 69% y la de obesidad entre un 23% y un 74%, dependiendo de los parámetros y criterios utilizados.                 Conclusiones. El exceso de peso (IMC &gt; 25) fue la alteración del estado nutricional más prevalente en Medicina Interna. El análisis de impedancia bioeléctrica facilita la medición de los componentes corporales y el índice meta es un indicador muy útil de malnutrición (desnutrición-obesidad)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;207(1): 6-12, ene. 2007. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052688</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alteraciones de la nutrición en Medicina Interna. Análisis de la composición corporal por impedancia bioeléctrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7553</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
