<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143397</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Rupture of a superior mesenteric artery aneurysm in pediatric age: case report and literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Splanchnic artery aneurysms are rare in children. High mortality from rupture justifies its treatment, with various therapeutic options among which stand out surgery and recently, endovascular treatment. Case report. A 11 year old girl presented with abdominal pain and sudden drop in hematocrit. The urgent abdominal CT angiography showed a saccular aneurysm of the superior mesenteric artery (SMA) at 4 cm from the ostium with dissection and active bleeding. A selective angiography was performed which confirmed the dissection. A self-expanding stent was placed in the main trunk of the SMA and a transcatheter coil and onyx embolization of the aneurysm was performed. The control angiogram showed no evidence of residual perfusion of the false lumen and demonstrated proper vascularization of the distal jejunumileal branches. Dual antiplatelet therapy with aspirin and dipyridamole was begun. After 24 months of follow-up the patient is asymptomatic. Comments. Endovascular treatment of a SMA aneurysm is effective in the pediatric patient, even in emergency situations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bueno, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gander, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lloret, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segarra, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lara, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los aneurismas esplácnicos son excepcionales en la edad pediátrica. La elevada mortalidad por rotura justifica su tratamiento, existiendo diversas opciones terapéuticas entre las que destacan la cirugía y, recientemente, el tratamiento endovascular. Caso clínico. Paciente de 11 años que presentó dolor abdominal súbito y caída del hematocrito. La angio-TC abdominal urgente mostró un aneurisma sacular de la arteria mesentérica superior (AMS) a 4 cm del ostium con disección de la luz y signos de sangrado activo. Se realizó una angiografía que confirmó el aneurisma. Se colocó un stent autoexpandible en el tronco principal de la arteria mesentérica superior con repleción del aneurisma con microcoils y Onyx, sin evidenciar perfusión residual de la falsa luz y comprobando una adecuada vascularización tanto distal como de las ramas yeyuno-ileales. Se instauró doble antiagregación con AAS y dipiridamol. Tras 24 meses de seguimiento se encuentra asintomática. Comentarios. El tratamiento endovascular es efectivo en el paciente pediátrico, incluso en situaciones de emergencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;28(1): 40-44, ene. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143397</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rotura de un aneurisma de arteria mesentérica superior en edad pediátrica: caso clínico y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d794^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30855^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22965^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30657^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54238^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
