<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145321</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Children as receptors of living donors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The most import nt fact or in lif e expectancy for children on renal replacement therapy (RRT) is to have a  unctioning graft when they reach adult hood (63 years on transplantation vs 37 years on dialysis). The pediat ric recipient is very suitable for a living donor transplantation (LDT), with few contraindications. There are several reasons that make LDT the most recommended RRT in children: pre-emptive transplant avoiding dialysis, good renal mass, minimal cold ischaemia time, better HLA-matching and the possibility to programt he time of surgery. Long term graft survival in LDT is significantly better than in cadaveric donor transplant at ion (CDT) (81.3% LDT vs 60.8 % CDT at 10 years follow -up). Calculat ed half -lif e graft survival for recipient s aged 2-5 years reaches 27.5 years in some series, making LDT t he ideal opt ion for these children. Adolescent recipient s (12-17 years) have an excellent early graft survival, but the worst long term out come compared with the rest of pediatric population. However, preempt ive LDT has a 70% of graft survival at 10 years. Late rejections episodes associated w it h non-adherence factors are f ound in all series (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Navarro Torres, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espinosa Román, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La esperanza de vida del niño con enfermedad renal terminal (ERT) depende de un trasplante funcionante (trasplante 63 años frente a diálisis 37 años). El receptor pediátrico es muy adecuado para un injerto de donante vivo, y las contraindicaciones son muy escasas. La posibilidad de evitar la diálisis, elegir el momento del trasplante, proporcionar una buena masa renal, con mínimo tiempo de isquemia fría y mejores identidades en muchos casos hacen del trasplante de donante cadáver una elección idónea. La supervivencia del injerto de donante vivo a largo plazo es significativamente mejor que la de donante cadá- ver (donante vivo 81,3% frente a donante cadáver 60,8% a 10 años). La vida media calculada de donante vivo en receptores de edades comprendidas entre 2 y 5 años es de 27 años, por lo que es el donant e idóneo en menores de 5 años. Los adolescentes (12-17 años) tienen una excelente supervivencia del injerto precoz, pero la peor de todas las edades a largo plazo. Episodios tardíos de rechazo tardío asociados a incumplimiento terapéutico son los factores encontrados en t odas las series publicadas. Sin embargo, el trasplante con donante vivo prediálisis tiene una supervivencia del injerto a 10 años del 70% . Los resultados con donante vivo no emparentado en receptores pediátricos son de difícil interpretación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;30(supl.2): 85-93, feb. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145321</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El receptor infantil de donante vivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
