<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159400</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reverse shoulder arthroplasty in 3 and 4 part proximal humeral fractures in patients aged more than 65 years: results and complications</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The treatment of 3 and 4 part proximal humeral fractures in elderly patients is still controversial. The frequent co-existence of poor quality bone and rotator cuff abnormalities in patients with multiple clinical conditions and with difficulties for physical rehabilitation leads to disappointing clinical results, even when the radiological images are acceptable. Objective. To evaluate the clinical, radiological, and functional results in patients over 65 years old with complex proximal humerus fractures treated with reverse shoulder arthroplasty. Material and methods. A prospective review was carried out on 30 patients (26 women and 4 men) with proximal humeral fractures treated with reverse shoulder arthroplasty in our department. The mean age was 74.9 years (SD=6.3), and the mean follow-up was 34.5 months (SD=19.3). Results. Clinical and functional results were acceptable, with a mean forward flexion of 124° and a mean external rotation of 13°. The mean abbreviated Constant abbreviated score was 49.1 (SD=14.1), 27 (SD=6.3) in the UCLA scale, and 32.2 (SD=19.2) in the QuickDASH questionnaire. The large majority (80%) of the patients are pain free, and they do not need medication to do daily activities. The complication rate was 13.3%. Conclusions. We consider that reverse shoulder arthroplasty is a valid option to treat 3and 4 part proximal humeral fractures in elderly patients. The surgical goals should include the anatomical reconstruction of the tuberosities, avoiding enlargement of the operated arm greater than 2cm (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villodre-Jiménez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estrems-Díaz, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bru-Pomer, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diranzo-García, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El tratamiento de las fracturas en 3 y 4 fragmentos de húmero proximal en el paciente anciano resulta controvertido. La frecuente coexistencia de un hueso de mala calidad y la afección del manguito rotador con dificultades para el tratamiento rehabilitador en pacientes pluripatológicos conlleva, en muchas ocasiones, resultados clínicos decepcionantes, aun cuando el resultado radiológico sea aceptable. Objetivo. Evaluar los resultados clínicos, radiológicos y funcionales obtenidos en el tratamiento de las fracturas de húmero proximal complejas con prótesis inversa en pacientes mayores de 65 años de nuestro servicio. Material y métodos. Revisión prospectiva en la que incluimos a 30 pacientes con fractura de húmero proximal intervenidos en nuestro servicio con prótesis total inversa de hombro. De ellos, 26 eran mujeres y 4 hombres. La edad media fue de 74,9 años (DE=6,6). El seguimiento medio fue de 34,5 meses (DE=19,3). Resultados. El resultado clínico y funcional ha sido aceptable, con una antepulsión activa media de 124° y una rotación externa media de 13°. La puntuación media en la escala abreviada de Constant fue de 49,1 puntos (DE=14,1), en la escala UCLA fue de 27 puntos (SD=6,3) y en el cuestionario QuickDASH de 32,2 puntos (DE=19,2). El 80% de los pacientes están libres de dolor sin precisar analgesia para la realización de sus actividades habituales. El 95% de los pacientes estaban satisfechos o muy satisfechos tras la intervención. La tasa de complicaciones fue del 13,3%. Conclusiones. Consideramos la artroplastia total inversa como una opción válida en el tratamiento de las fracturas en 3 y 4 fragmentos de húmero proximal en pacientes mayores de 65 años. Los objetivos de la cirugía deben incluir la reconstrucción anatómica de las tuberosidades, evitando incrementos de la longitud del miembro intervenido superiores a 2cm (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);61(1): 43-50, ene.-feb. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159400</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de las fracturas de húmero proximal en pacientes mayores de 65 años con prótesis inversa: resultados y complicaciones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1877^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1185^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6962^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1185^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6962^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
