<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84159</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Isolated avulsion of the distal femoral biceps. Results in three cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: An analysis is made of an infrequent lesion, isolated avulsion of the distal femoral biceps tendon, in three elite category (league first division) soccer players. Material and methods: Three professional soccer players of the Spanish national league (first division) presented isolated avulsion of the distal femoral biceps tendon, produced by different mechanisms during sports activity. The injuries were treated by anatomical reinsertion of the biceps tendon in the fibular head, with the application of a specific rehabilitation protocol. Isokinetic controls were made 3, 6 and 12 months after the operation. Results: The clinical results were satisfactory. The end mobility range of the knee was complete in all cases, and full recovery of muscle strength and resistance was confirmed by the serial isokinetic tests. The patients were able to fully return to their sports activity after an average of 14 weeks. Conclusions: In elite athletes, surgical recovery through reinsertion of the biceps muscle in the fibular head restores the normal anatomy and function of the knee (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín Buenadicha, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez García, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leyes Vence, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silberberg Muiño, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miranda Mayordomo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Analizar la avulsión aislada del tendón del bíceps femoral distal, una lesión poco frecuente, en tres futbolistas de primera división nacional. Material y métodos: Tres jugadores de fútbol profesionales de primera división española, presentaron una avulsión aislada del tendón del m. bíceps femoral distal durante la práctica deportiva con diferentes mecanismos de producción que fueron intervenidos mediante reinserción anatómica del tendón del m. bíceps en la cabeza de peroné siguiendo un protocolo rehabilitador específico. Efectuamos un control isocinético a los 3, 6 y 12 meses de la intervención. Resultados: La valoración clínica fue satisfactoria en todos los casos, el rango de movilidad articular final de la rodilla fue completo y la recuperación de fuerza y resistencia muscular completa fue confirmada con el estudio isocinético seriado. Los pacientes se incorporaron a su actividad deportiva a pleno rendimiento en un tiempo medio de 14 semanas. Conclusiones: En deportistas de alto nivel, la reparación quirúrgica mediante la reinserción bicipital en la cabeza de peroné, restablece la anatomía y la función normal de la rodilla (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);20(3): 177-180, jul.-sept. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84159</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Avulsión aislada de bíceps femoral distal. Resultados en tres casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5495^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7893^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7893^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1273^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7893^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5495^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1273^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1273^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14086^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14086^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5495^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7893^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
