<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039420</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-0921</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Geriatric assessment: the Day Hospital View</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Integral Geriatric Assessment is the basic and fundamental tool in theprioritization of problems and supervision in the care of the frail elderly.Independent of whatever the level of care is, it permits the realization ofan exhaustive analysis of the physical and functional capabilities, thenutritional state, the sense organs, the state of mind and the social andfamily environment that surrounds each patient. In the same way, theneeds, the will and the wishes of the patient are taken into account.Therefore, only through it can we coordinate between the differenthealth professionals and levels of care to prioritise the broaching of thehealth problems and offer quality integral care</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fontecha Gómez, Benito J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Valoración Geriátrica Integral es la herramienta básica y fundamentalen la priorización de problemas e intervención en la atención alanciano frágil. Independientemente de cuál sea el nivel asistencial,permite realizar un análisis exhaustivo de las capacidades físicas,funcionales, del estado nutricional, de los órganos de los sentidos, delestado de ánimo y del entorno sociofamiliar que envuelve a cadapaciente. De la misma manera, tiene en cuenta las necesidades, lavoluntad y los deseos del paciente. Por este motivo, sólo a través deella, podemos coordinarnos entre los diferentes profesionales de lasalud y niveles asistenciales para priorizar el abordaje de los problemasde salud y ofrecer una asistencia integral de calidad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. multidiscip. gerontol;15(1): 23-25, ene. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039420</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración geriátrica: visión desde el Hospital de Día</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32782^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3648^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28940^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24693^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
