<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146982</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-0618</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Study characteristics physical-chemical of the waters of the Spa</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The waters of the Spa La Villa de Olmedo (Valladolid) have special characteristics; are high salinity waters declared as water "Thermal and Minero-medicinal water&#148; in June 2005 by the Community of Castilla-León. These hypothermic waters have a pH around 8.0 and are characterized by high mineralization, with a high residue content of five grams per liter. Sodium content stand out among the elements that form the salts, which along with high chloride content gives rise to sodium-chloride waters. In addition, the sulphate content is high and the concentrations of calcium and magnesium are low, which these waters are not noted for heir hardness, so they are considered as soft waters (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tenorio Sanz, Mª Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torija Isasa, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Mata, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Colón, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las aguas del balneario de La Villa de Olmedo (Valladolid) tienen características especiales; son aguas de alta salinidad que fueron declaradas como agua "Termal y Mineromedicinal" en junio de 2005 en la Comunidad de Castilla-León. Se trata de aguas hipotermales, con un pH en torno a 8, de alta mineralización, con un elevado residuo superior a los cinco gramos por litro. Destaca el elevado contenido de sodio que, junto a un alto contenido de cloruros, da origen a aguas clorurado-sódicas. El contenido de sulfatos es elevado y presentan concentraciones bajas de calcio y magnesio, por lo que no destacan por su dureza, considerándolas blandas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Real Acad Farm;81(5): 33-44, 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146982</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de las características físico&#150;químicas de las aguas del balneario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d850^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23127^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23461^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9088^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23127^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9088^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54761^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11634^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d850^s22065</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9088^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54761^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23461^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9094</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
