<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151937</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hospitalisation as a risk for functional decline in older adults</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Functional decline: (FD) is a risk associated with hospital admission in older people, due to its high prevalence (35-70%) and its serious consequences. Aim: To determine the incidence of FD in the elderly after hospital admission at the Geriatric and Internal Medicine wards of a tertiary teaching hospital (Albacete, Spain). Method: A cohort study has been designed, whose primary focus was FD, defined as the loss of independence to perform the activities of daily living between preadmission status and discharge. Demographic characteristics, comorbidity, length of hospital stay and cognitive status have been analysed. Data collection was performed by interviews with patients and caregivers during hospitalization and after discharge (by phone), as well as by revision of clinical records. Results: 104 patients were evaluated, of which 51.9% were female; the average age was 79.97 years (dt = 7.89) IC 95% [78.43, 81.5] and the average length of stay was 10.11 days (dt = 7.65) IC 95% [8.62,11.6]. The proportion of patients who showed a normal cognitive status on the first in-hospital day was 41.4% (43 patients). FD was present in 60 (57.7%) patients in the first day of hospitalisation; when discharged, 32.6% of 92 patients who could be evaluated showed FD. 19% of patients who were previously independent in activities of daily living developed a serious dependence after discharge. FD was associated statistically with age and a history of previous falls. Conclusions: FD takes place in a high percentage of the elderly patients. Among the previously independent patients, 19% remains in a situation of dependence after discharge (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Pallarés, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Mansilla, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Serrano, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saiz-Vinuesa, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herreros-Sáez, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Córcoles-Jiménez, María Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-García, María Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calero-Yáñez, Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El deterioro funcional es un riesgo asociado a la hospitalización en las personas mayores, con elevada prevalencia (35&#150;70%) y graves consecuencias. Objetivo: Determinar la incidencia del deterioro funcional relacionado con la hospitalización (DFH) en personas mayores ingresadas en el Área Médica del Complejo Hospitalario Universitario de Albacete. Método: Se ha realizado un estudio de cohortes, cuya variable principal ha sido el DFH (pérdida de capacidad para realizar actividades cotidianas durante el ingreso y tras el alta); se han incluido otras variables (demográficas, relacionadas con el ingreso, patologías asociadas, estado cognitivo). Los datos se recogieron por entrevista presencial al paciente y cuidadores, llamada telefónica tras el alta y revisión de historia clínica. Resultados: Se incluyeron 104 pacientes, de los que un 51,9% eran mujeres; la edad media fue 79,97 años (dt = 7,89), IC 95% [78,43; 81,5] y la estancia media de 10,11 días (dt = 7,65) IC 95% [8,62; 11,6]. El primer día del ingreso 43 (41,4%) pacientes presentaban estado mental intacto. Se produjo DFH en las primeras 24 horas en 60 (57,7%) pacientes; tras el alta hospitalaria, el deterioro existía en un 32,6% de los 92 pacientes que pudieron ser evaluados. En pacientes que antes del ingreso eran independientes para las actividades cotidianas, un 19% quedó con dependencia importante. El DFH se relacionó de forma estadísticamente significativa con los antecedentes de caídas y la edad. Conclusiones: El DFH se produce en un porcentaje elevado de los mayores de 65 años; entre los previamente independientes, casi la quinta parte queda en situación de dependencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);26(2): 121-128, mar.-abr. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151937</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Deterioro funcional asociado a la hospitalización en pacientes mayores de 65 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d212^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53744^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
