<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101741</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical experience of treatment with onabotulinumtoxin A in patients with refractory migraine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To analyse our experience in the treatment of refractory chronic migraine, episodic frequent refractory migraine  (&amp;#8805; 10 days/month), with onabotulinumtoxin A (OnabotA).  Patients and methods. Retrospective analysis of patients with refractory migraine who underwent, at least two sessions  of OnabotA pericranial injections following the PREEMPT protocol between 2008 and 2012. The efficacy of OnabotA was  evaluated comparing the basal situation with 12-16 weeks after the second session. We analysed the subjective improvement   f the patients, number of days with headache, preventive and abortive drugs consumption, and adverse effects.  Results. Forty-one patients (37 women, 4 male) were identified. 65.8% patients experienced subjective improvement after  OnabotA treatment. 36.58% responded (reduction of &gt; 50% in headache days). Differences between days with headache  before the first session (24.5 ± 7.3), and 12-16 weeks after the second session (17.4 ± 11.6), as well as the differences  between the number of abortive drugs taken before the first session (26.8 ± 23.1) and 12-16 weeks after the second session  (16.7 ± 19.3), were statistically significant (p &lt; 0.001). Subgroups analysis showed that all differences were significant,  xcept for the reduction of the number of days with headache in patients with episodic frequent refractory migraine.  Conclusion. Our work shows that treatment with OnabotA is safe and useful in patients with episodic and chronic refractory   migraine, including those patients with medication overuse headache (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferández Torrón, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Cubero, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palma, José A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luqín, M. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Irimia, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riverol, Mario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Villa, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Mostrar nuestra experiencia en el tratamiento de onabotulinumtoxin A (OnabotA) en pacientes con migraña  refractaria, tanto crónica como episódica frecuente (&amp;#8805; 10 días/mes).  Pacientes y métodos. Análisis retrospectivo de pacientes con migraña refractaria que habían recibido al menos dos infiltraciones de OnabotA siguiendo el protocolo PREEMPT entre los años 2008 y 2012. Se evaluó la eficacia de OnabotA comparando la situación basal y transcurridas entre 12-16 semanas después de la segunda infiltración, determinando: mejoría  subjetiva de los pacientes, número de días con cefalea, consumo de fármacos preventivos y analgésicos, y efectos adversos.  Resultados. Se identificaron 41 pacientes (37 mujeres, cuatro varones). Un 65,8% de los pacientes encontró mejoría subjetiva tras el tratamiento. Un 36,58% respondió al tratamiento con OnabotA (reducción &gt; 50% en los días de cefalea).   La diferencia entre los días al mes de cefalea antes de la primera infiltración (24,5 ± 7,3) y después de la segunda infiltración (17,4 ± 11,6), y la diferencia entre la dosis de analgésicos al mes antes de la primera infiltración (26,8 ± 23,1) y la  de después de la segunda infiltración (16,7 ± 19,3) fueron significativas (p &lt; 0,001). En el análisis por subgrupos, todas  las diferencias fueron significativas, salvo en el caso de pacientes con migraña episódica frecuente refractaria, donde la  reducción en los días al mes de cefalea no alcanzó la significación. Conclusión. El tratamiento con OnabotA es útil en pacientes con migraña refractaria crónica, y podría ser también beneficioso en migraña refractaria episódica frecuente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;54(12): 105-711, jun. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101741</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia clínica del tratamiento con onabotulinumtoxin A en pacientes con migraña refractaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50485^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9068^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33081^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
