<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114416</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evolution of the frequency of congenital defects in newborn infants and fetuses from terminations of pregnancy after prenatal diagnosis in the period 1982-2009</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: The study of congenital defects (CD) must include termination of pregnancy (TOP) for CD and evaluate risk factors that modify their frequency. Patients and methods: Consecutive series of 517 newborn and 202 TOP with CD among 38,191 childbirths, between 1982-2009 years. Results: The mean frequency for newborns with CD is 13.54&#137; and for newborn and TOP with CD is 18.73&#137;. Single CD are 61.12% in newborns and 52.17% in TOP. The 18.37% of CD in newborn and 40.58% of TOP are syndromic. Mean gestational age for TOP is 17.92 weeks. Overall frequency of anencephaly is 2.62&#137; for newborns and 6.77 for 10,000 for newborns and TOP. Spina bifida is 3.14 for 10,000 newborns and 5.99 for 10,000 newborns and TOP. Overall frequency of Down syndrome (DS) is 10.74 for 10,000 newborns and 22.14 for 10,000 newborns and TOP. The percentage of foreign mothers was 35.9% in 2009 and the mean maternal age significantly increased in this period. Conclusion: We observe a significant decrease of CD in newborns but not in their conception. We have not detected primary prevention for neural tube defects. The decrease in DS in newborns is not statistically relevant but ethnic diversity and maternal aging may be modifying the frequency. The 53% of CD were TOP in the period 2007-2009. It is mandatory a complete study for CD in TOP in order to offer serious reproductive counseling (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Roselló Sastre, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermejo Sánchez, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcover Barrachina, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanchis Calvo, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escandón Alvarez, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balanzá Chancosa, Reyes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcos Puig, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Ebri, María Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camarasa Lillo, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: El estudio de la frecuencia de los defectos congénitos (DC) requiere incluir interrupciones voluntarias del embarazo (IVE) por DC y evaluar los factores que influyen en aquella. Pacientes y método: Serie consecutiva de 517 recién nacidos (RN) y 202 IVE con DC en 38.191 nacimientos entre 1982-2009. Resultados: La frecuencia media de RN con DC es 13,54&#137; y la de RN + IVE por DC de 18,73&#137;. Los DC aislados suponen el 61,12% en RN y el 52,17% en IVE. El 18,37% de los DC en RN y el 40,58% en IVE son sindrómicos. La media de edad gestacional en IVE es 17,92 semanas. La frecuencia global de anencefalia es 2,62 y 6,77 por 10.000, respectivamente, en RN y en RN + IVE. La de la espina bífida es 3,14 y 5,99 por 10.000, respectivamente. La frecuencia global de síndrome de Down es 10,74 por 10.000 RN y 22,14 por 10.000 RN + IVE. El porcentaje de madres extranjeras en nuestra maternidad alcanza el 35,9% en 2009. La media de edad materna asciende significativamente a lo largo del tiempo. Conclusiones: Observamos una disminución estadísticamente significativa de DC en RN, pero no en su concepción. No detectamos prevención primaria de anencefalia ni espina bífida. El descenso de síndrome de Down en RN no alcanza significación estadística. La diversidad étnica y la mayor edad materna pueden estar modificando la frecuencia. El 53% de los casos (RN + IVE) con DC del trienio 2007-2009 fueron IVE. Se precisa el estudio completo de IVE por DC para ofrecer consejo reproductivo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);141(4): 152-158, ago. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114416</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Defectos congénitos en recién nacidos y fetos procedentes de interrupción del embarazo tras diagnóstico prenatal en el período 1982-2009</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29127^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5950^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d770^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
