<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143075</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tuberous sclerosis and its oral manifestations. A clinical case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Tuberous sclerosis (TS) is a congenital anomaly in the development of the embryo which is transmitted through the autosomal dominant gene. It has various forms of clinical expression. It is classified as one of what are known as Phacomatoses (phakos stain and oma tumour), which are development anomalies that can originate tumours and/or hamartomas in the nervous system. Lesions in the nervous system are nearly always accompanied by cutaneous anomalies. In this study we introduce the case of a woman patient aged 55, diagnosed several years earlier with Tuberous Sclerosis, who attended for intraoral lesions which were clinically compatible with fibromata. These lesions of fibrous appearance occurred above all on the lower lip and in both cheeks' mucous membra-nes, little mentioned in the literature as a site for such a manifestation of TS. The pathological anatomy suggested lesions compatible with Angiomyolipoma.In addition, the data referring to TS are reviewed; its implications for the mouth are described; and histopathological results are used to examine the significance of the word Angiomyolipoma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Chimenos Küstner, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez de Rivera Campillo, Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López López, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marques Soares, M. Sueli</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Finestres Zubeldia, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roselló Llabrés, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La esclerosis tuberosa (ET) es una anomalía congénita del desarrollo embrionario que se transmite de forma autosómica dominante y tiene diferentes formas de expresión clínica. Se clasifica dentro de las denominadas facomatosis (phakos "mancha" y oma "tumor"), que son anomalías del desarrollo, susceptibles de originar tumores y/o hamartomas del sistema nervioso. Es importante destacar que las lesiones del sistema nervioso se acompañan, prácticamente siempre, de anomalías cutáneas. En este trabajo presentamos el caso de una paciente de 55 años de edad, diagnosticada desde hace años de esclerosis tuberosa, que cursa con lesiones intraorales compatibles clínicamente con fibromas. Estas lesiones de aspecto fibromatoso se presentan sobre todo en el labio inferior y en ambas mucosas yugales, localización poco referenciada para esta manifestación en la enfermedad de base que nos ocupa. La anatomía patológica sugiere lesiones compatibles con angiomiolipoma. También repasamos los datos referentes a la ET, se describen las implicaciones orales de la misma y en base al resultado histopatológico obtenido se revisa el significado del término angiomiolipoma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);9(3): 216-223, mayo-jul. 2004. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143075</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Esclerosis tuberosa y manifestaciones orales. Caso clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31654^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5486^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14804^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9252^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34313^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200407</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
