<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80752</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Macronutrients intake and caloric profile as dietetic conditioners in depression in elderly</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Depression is a common disease inelderly. Nutrition, as in cognitive disorders and disability,plays an important role in the origin and/or evolutionof the affective disorders. The aim of this studyhas been to analyze the macronutrients intake and caloricprofile as dietetic conditioners in depression in agroup of institutionalized elderly people. Methods: 176 institutionalized subjects (&amp;#8805;65 years)of 4 nursing-homes from Madrid were studied. Dieteticdata was evaluated using a precise individual weighingfor 7 days. Also an anthropometric study also was realized.Affective capacity was valued by Yesavage´sGeriatric Scale Depression (GDS) (punctuation &gt;5 is indicativeof depression).Results: The affective capacity valued by GDS was5.36±3.48, average indicative result of depression. Thecaloric intake was similar in the depressed elders (D)and not depressed (ND), though the elders D presenteda caloric profile more unbalanced than the eldersND, with a major energy contribution on the part of thelipids and a minor contribution of carbohydrates, differencesthat determine in the elders D a major withdrawalof their caloric profile with regard to the nutritionalobjectives marked as advisable (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Sobaler, Ana María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navia Lombán, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Rodríguez, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Anta, Rosa María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aparicio Vizuete, Aránzazu</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: La depresión es una enfermedadcomún en las personas de edad avanzada. La nutrición,al igual que en los trastornos cognitivos y motores,juega un importante papel en el origen y/o evoluciónde los trastornos afectivos. El objetivo del estudioes analizar las diferencias en la ingesta de macronutrientesy en el perfil calórico de la dieta en función delestado afectivo de un colectivo de ancianos institucionalizados.Métodos: Se ha estudiado a un grupo de 176 personasde edad avanzada, institucionalizadas en 4 residenciasde la Comunidad de Madrid, mayores de 65años a los que se les realizó un estudio dietético mediantepesada precisa individual durante 7 días consecutivos.También se les realizó un estudio antropométricoy de capacidad afectiva valorada por la aplicaciónde la Escala de Depresión Geriátrica de Yesavage(GDS), cuya puntuación superior a 5 puntos es indicativade depresión.Resultados: La capacidad afectiva valorada a travésdel GDS, fue de 5.36±3.48, resultado medio indicativode depresión. La ingesta calórica fue similar enlos ancianos deprimidos (D) y no deprimidos (ND),aunque los ancianos D presentaron un perfil calóricomás desequilibrado que los ancianos ND, con un mayoraporte de energía por parte de los lípidos y un menoraporte de hidratos de carbono, diferencias quecondicionan en los ancianos D un mayor alejamientode su perfil calórico respecto a los objetivos nutricionalesmarcados como aconsejables (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;29(2): 24-30, mayo-ago. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80752</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ingesta de macronutrientes y perfil calóricocomo condicionantes dietéticos de depresión en ancianos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50311</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
