<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039300</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Xanthogranulomatous pyelonephritis in childhood. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Xanthogranulomatous pyelonephritis is an uncommon chronic inflammatory renal disorder. Most cases have been described in middle aged women and it is extremely rare in children. We report a case of a 4 years old girl who suffered from recurrent urinary tract infection and antibiotic therapy resistance. She had low growth-rate and palpable left renal mass on examination and was confirmed by radiological findings. We performed left kidney partial resection and then histological examination showed focal xanthogranulomatous pyelonephritis. The focal form of the disease may respond to antibiotic treatment although usually an enucleation or partial resection must be performed. In conclusion xanthogranulomatous pyelonephritis should be considered in the differential diagnosis of a renal mass and recurrent urinary tract infection in childhood (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Pérez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrero Candau, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Pérez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campoy Martínez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Argüelles Salido, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Resina, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La pielonefritis xantogranulomatosa es una rara inflamación crónica del parénquima renal. Predomina en mujeres de edad media y es extremadamente rara en niños. Presentamos el caso de una niña de 4 años de edad, con infecciones del tracto urinario de repetición y mala respuesta a tratamiento médico. La paciente tenía retraso pondo-estatural y una masa en hemiabdomen izquierdo a la exploración y en las pruebas de imagen. Se realizó heminefrectomía superior izquierda, con posterior confirmación histopatológica de pielonefritis xantogranulomatosa focal. El tratamiento más frecuente de la forma focal es la nefrectomía parcial, aunque a veces responde a tratamiento antibiótico. Como conclusión la pielonefritis xantogranulomatosa debe ser considerada dentro de un diagnóstico diferencial de un niño con un riñón aumentado de tamaño e infecciones recurrentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;29(6): 596-598, jun. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039300</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pielonefritis xantogranulomatosa en la infancia. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19556^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19556^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7849^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19556^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7849^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
