<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161330</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Campbell Scale for pain assessment in Hospital Emergency Units. The case of Turkana, Kenya</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to study the feasibility of a pain assessment scale that considers behavioural features and that can provide the healthcare staff with an assessment not only based on the interpretation of their pain by patients, in the rural area of Turkana.  Method: a descriptive observational study was conducted. People between 18 and 65-year-old were selected, from the Turkana culture, with pain in emergency situations, and they were divided into two groups. For Group 1, the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) and the Faces Pain Scale (FPS) were used, while the Campbell Scale was used for Group 2. The correlation between the three scales was analyzed through the Spearman Index.  Results: the study included 48 adult patients: 32 in Group 1 and 16 in Group 2. While the VAS and FPS maintained a good 0.667 correlation between them, the Campbell Scale offered values of 0.245 and 0.36 respectively, with each of the other scales; therefore, there did not seem to be an association between this scale and each of the other scales.  Conclusions: assessment with scales based on the association with a number or a face will present failures, while the result of a combined use of these scales with a scale such as the Campbell Scale will be more satisfactory (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Riera, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Climent Rubio, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Higón, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: estudiar la viabilidad de una escala de valoración del dolor que contemple rasgos conductuales que ofrezcan al personal sanitario una valoración no solo basada en la interpretación del paciente de su dolor en la zona rural de Turkana (Kenya).  Método: se realizó un estudio descriptivo observacional. Se seleccionaron personas de entre 18 y 65 años pertenecientes a la cultura turkana con dolor en situaciones de urgencia, y se dividieron en dos grupos. En el Grupo 1 se aplican la escala visual analógica (EVA) y la escala con caras (FPS), y en el Grupo 2 la escala Campbell. Mediante el índice Spearman se analizó la correlación entre las tres escalas. Resultados: se estudiaron 48 adultos, 32 en el Grupo 1 y 16 en el Grupo 2. Mientras las escalas EVA y FPS mantienen una buena correlación de 0,667 entre ellas, la escala Campbell con cada una de ellas ofrece unos valores de 0,245 y 0,36, respectivamente, por tanto, no parece existir relación entre esta con cada una de las otras.  Conclusiones: la valoración con escalas basadas en la asociación de un número o una cara muestran deficiencias, mientras que el resultado de un uso combinado de estas con una escala como la escala Campbell es más satisfactorio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;20(2): 12-17, mar. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161330</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La escala Campbell para la valoración del dolor en urgencias/emergencias. El caso de Turkana, Kenya</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4711^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19283^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
