<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107566</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neurological syndromes associated with drug use. Frequency and characterisation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The need for safe health care, in which the care and treatment of the patient does not cause any injuries in addition to those already arising from their baseline disease, hasled to the present study. Our objective has been to determine the frequency and describe the  neurological syndromes attributable to drugs, their preventability and the levels of medical care involved. Methods: Observational study. Cohort of subjects referred from Primary and Specialized Care between December 2008 and January 2010 due to neurological symptoms attributable to drugs, and previously known neurology patients who began to have symptoms other than those of the baseline disease, also caused by drugs. The notifications were recorded in a questionnaire. Frequency distributions, central tendency measurements, X2 or Fisher tests and non-parametric tests were performed. Results: The prevalence of adverse neurological events was 0.586% of the total sample. Of  the 105 patients selected, the most frequent adverse events were: 25.7%, akinetic-rigid syndrome, 18.1%, dyskinetic syndrome, 11.4% neuro-psychiatric symptoms, and 10.5% confusional syndrome. The most commonly recorded pharmacological groups were, in decreasing order: anti-epileptic, dopaminergic, antidepressant, neuroleptic, antivertiginous and prokinetic drugs. We describe the most susceptible population and the statistically significant relationships between the presence of certain pharmacological groups and neurological syndromes. Conclusions: The low prevalence detected may be due to the study design, although adverse neurological events accounted for 2.84% of the admissions to a Neurology Unit. Understanding the epidemiology should help to identify the safest approaches, apply them correctly to the population at a higher risk, and reduce healthcare needs and consumption of medical resources (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández González, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Del Real Francia, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gudín Rodríguez-Magariños, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrasco Garíca de León, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Soria, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez Alonso, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaamonde Gamo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallardo Alcáñiz, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flores Barragán, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La necesidad de una asistencia sanitaria segura en la que los cuidados y tratamientos no supongan da&#152;nos diferentes a los derivados de la enfermedad de base, ha motivado este estudio. Nuestro objetivo ha sido determinar la frecuencia y describir los síndromes neurológicos atribuibles a fármacos, su evitabilidad y los niveles asistenciales implicados. Métodos: Estudio observacional. Cohorte prospectiva de todos los sujetos derivados desde atención primaria y especializada, en el período de diciembre de 2008 a enero de 2010, por síntomas neurológicos atribuibles a fármacos y enfermos neurológicos conocidos con clínica distinta o agravada de la enfermedad de base causada por fármacos. Las notificaciones quedaron reflejadas en un cuestionario. Se realizaron distribuciones de frecuencias, medidas de  tendencia central, pruebas de la  2 o Fisher y pruebas no paramétricas correspondientes. Resultados: La prevalencia de efectos adversos neurológicos respecto a la muestra total fue 0,586%. De los 105 pacientes seleccionados, los principales efectos adversos fueron: 25,7% síndrome rígido-acinético; 18,1% discinético; 11,4% síntomas neuropsiquiátricos, y 10,5% síndrome confusional. Los grupos farmacológicos más registrados fueron, en orden decreciente: antiepilépticos, dopaminérgicos, antidepresivos, neurolépticos, antivertiginosos y procinéticos. Describimos la población más susceptible y las asociaciones estadísticamente significativas  entre la presencia de determinados grupos farmacológicos y síndromes neurológicos concretos.Conclusiones: La baja prevalencia detectada puede deberse al dise&#152;no del estudio, aunque  los efectos adversos neurológicos suponen el 2,84% de los ingresos en una unidad de neurología.Conocer la epidemiología permitirá identificar los abordajes más seguros, aplicarlos   correctamente a la población de mayor riesgo y reducir necesidades asistenciales y recursos médicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;27(9): 547-559, nov.-dic. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107566</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndromes neurológicos asociados al uso de medicamentos. Frecuencia y caracterización</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9687^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2527^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
