<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73959</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Arthroplasty of the wrist and hand</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The hands are the main organ for physicalmanipulation of the setting and primary source of tactile informationon the surroundings. The specialization of thecerebral hemisphere has determined that there is dominanceof one hand for activities of skills, aptitudes and/or force overthe other hand in the human being.Hand surgery is one of the branches of surgery with thefastest development since the Second World War, as othermedical and surgical knowledge. The history of arthroplastiesis linked to treatment of pain and attempt to recover functionalityof the joints and in the case of the hands, to the seriousdeformations, secondary to chronic, invalidating inflammatorydiseases such as rheumatoid arthritis or traumaticsequels.The indication of arthroplasty in the hand (IPJ, PIP, MCP,TMJ) and wrist, entails great complexity due to the close functionalrelationship existing between the joints. The function ofa joint depends on the others and thus any procedure performedin a joint affects the activity of the others and also thedelicacy of the soft tissues (tendons, ligaments, etc.) significantlycomplicates the likelihoods of adequate rehabilitation.Rehabilitation and post-operative cares play a very importantrole in the success of the arthroplasty. The fundamentalpurpose is to achieve early protected mobility.Based on the joint and type of arthroplasty performed, differenttherapeutic procedures are indicated(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herraiz-Gastesi, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García y García, E. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña-Giménez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar-Franco, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Villén, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las manos son el principal órgano para lamanipulación física del medio y la principal fuente de informacióntáctil sobre el entorno. La especialización de los hemisferioscerebrales ha determinado que en el ser humano seproduzca la dominancia de una mano para actividades de destreza,habilidad y/o fuerza sobre la otra.La cirugía de la mano es una de las ramas de la cirugía quecon mayor rapidez se ha desarrollado desde la Segunda GuerraMundial, como tantos otros conocimientos médicos yquirúrgicos. La historia de las artroplastias está ligada al tratamientodel dolor y al intento de recuperar la funcionalidadde las articulaciones y, en el caso de las manos, a las gravesdeformaciones, secundarias a enfermedades inflamatoriascrónicas invalidantes, como la artritis reumatoide (AR), o secuelastraumáticas.La indicación de artroplastia en la mano (interfalángicaproximal, interfalángica distal, metacarpofalángica y trapeciometacarpiana)y la muñeca entraña una gran complejidad, porla estrecha relación funcional existente entre las articulaciones.La función de una articulación depende de las demás, ypor lo tanto cualquier procedimiento practicado en una articulaciónincide en la actividad de las otras, y además la delicadezade los tejidos blandos (tendones, ligamentos, etc.)complica notablemente las probabilidades de una rehabilitaciónadecuada.La rehabilitación y los cuidados postoperatorios desempeñanun papel muy importante en el éxito de la artroplastia.El objetivo fundamental es conseguir una movilidad precozprotegida.En función de la articulación y del tipo de artroplastiapracticada se indican distintos procedimientos terapéuticos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);41(6): 266-272, nov.2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73959</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Artroplastia de muñeca y mano</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15352^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1185^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33888</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12467^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33582^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50364^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
