<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129227</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Erectile function in men with failed hypospadies repair</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: While efforts have been made to study erectile function in patients with urethral stricture, very few prior investigations have specifically assessed erectile function in men with failed hypospadias surgery. We set forth to assess the baseline erectile function of men with hypospadias failure presenting for urethroplasty as adults. METHODS: Retrospective data was analyzed on 163 adult patients with prior failed hypospadias repair who presented for urethroplasty from 2002-2007 at two sites in the United States and Italy. All patients had completed the International Index of Erectile Function (IIEF) pre-operatively. Standard IIEF-6 categories were used to assess baseline level of erectile dysfunction (ED) defined as none (&amp;#8805;26), minimal (18-25), moderate (11-17), and severe (&amp;#8804;10). A subset of 13 hypospadias patients prospectively completed the IIEF questionnaire pre and post-operatively. RESULTS: The mean age at presentation for urethroplasty was 39.7 years. Based on IIEF-6 scores, 54% of patients presented with some degree of ED with 22.1%, 3.7%, and 28.2% reporting severe, moderate and mild ED respectively. While the oldest patient population (&gt;50) had the highest incidence of severe ED (38.9%), the youngest age group (&amp;#8804;30) had a 60% rate of ED with 18% classified as severe (Table I). Subset analysis of 13 failed hypospadias patients following urethroplasty revealed that 11 (85%) patients had the same or improved erectile function following surgery. CONCLUSIONS: Patients presenting for repair after hypospadias failure often require complex penile reconstruction impacting both urinary as well as sexual quality of life. Among these patients there appears to be a high baseline prevalence of ED. Older patients had a higher incidence of more severe ED; however, the majority of younger patients still presented with some form of ED and a significant number with severe ED. Urethroplasty does not appear to negatively impact erectile function in men with previous hypospadias failure; however a disease specific questionnaire is needed to fully address this issue (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barbagli, Guido</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Stein, Daniel M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Madonia, Massimo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sansalone, Salvatore</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gonzalez, Chris M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cimino, Sebastiano</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Aunque se han hecho esfuerzos para estudiar la función eréctil en pacientes con estenosis de uretra, muy pocas investigaciones previas han evaluado específicamente la función eréctil en varones en los que ha fracasado la cirugía del hipospadias. Buscamos evaluar la función eréctil basal de los varones con fracaso de la reparación del hipospadias que acuden para uretroplastia en edad adulta. MÉTODOS: Análisis retrospectivo de los datos de 163 pacientes adultos con fallo de reparación previa de hipospadias que consulta para uretroplastia entre los años 2000-2007 en dos centros en los Estados Unidos de América e Italia. Todos los pacientes habían rellenado el IIEF (índice internacional de función eréctil) en el preoperatorio. Las categorías del IIEF-6 Standard se utilizaron para evaluar el nivel basal de disfunción eréctil (DE) definido como nada (&amp;#8805;26), mínima (18-25), moderada (11-17) y grave (£10). Un subgrupo de 13 pacientes con hipospadias completaron el cuestionario IIEF de forma prospectiva antes y después de la cirugía. RESULTADOS: La edad media de los pacientes en el momento de la consulta era 39,7 años. En base a los resultados del IIEF-6, el 54% de los pacientes presentaban algún grado de DE con 22.1%, 3.7% y 28.2% comunicando DE grave, moderada y leve respectivamente. Mientras que la población de pacientes más mayor (&gt;50) tenía la incidencia más alta de DE grave (38,9%), el grupo de edad más joven (&amp;#8804;30) tenía una tasa de DE del 60% con el 18% clasificada como grave (Tabla 1). El análisis del subgrupo de 13 pacientes con hipospadias fallidos después de uretroplastia reveló que 11 (85%) de los pacientes tenían la misma función eréctil o mejor después de la cirugía. CONCLUSIONES: Los pacientes que consultan para reoperación después del fracaso de la cirugía del hipospadias con frecuencia requieren reconstrucciones peneanas complejas que tienen impacto sobre la calidad de vida urinaria y sexual. Entre estos pacientes parece existir una alta prevalencia de DE. Los pacientes más mayores tienen una incidencia mayor de DE más grave; sin embargo, la mayoría de los pacientes más jóvenes también presentan algo de DE y un número significativo DE grave. La uretroplastia no parece impactar negativamente la función eréctil en hombres con cirugía de hipospadias previa fallida; sin embargo es necesario un cuestionario específico de la enfermedad para tratar completamente este problema (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;67(1): 152-156, ene.-feb. 2014. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129227</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Función eréctil en hombres tras fracaso de reparación del hipospadias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7200^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14924^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13901^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
