<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159882</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Specialized rheumatology clinic in an emergency department: A year of the rheumatology and musculoskeletal emergencies clinic (RMSEC) experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. In October 2013, the emergency department of our hospital started up a rheumatology and musculoskeletal emergencies clinic (RMSEC) with the participation of three specialists in Rheumatology. The purpose of this study was to describe the experience gained in the first year since the beginning of our activity. Method. A descriptive study of healthcare activity of the RMSEC throughout its first year of operation was performed. Results. 1788 assessments on 1663 patients were performed. The range of age was 7 to 67 years. 1530 (85.57%) assessments were performed in patients of the healthcare area of our hospital. Of all the assessments made, 633 (35.4%) were related to inflammatory processes and the remaining 1155 (64.6%) to mechanical or degenerative joint or soft tissue processes. According to the topography of the complaint, 435 (24.3%) patients consulted for a process related to the knee, 362 (20.3%) with axial lumbar region and 336 (18.8%) with the shoulder. Conclusion. Our results denote an intense clinical activity that could have a positive impact on the management of rheumatic and musculoskeletal general emergency (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villarejo-Botija, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boteanu, Alina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blázquez-Cañamero, María Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antonio Guillén-Astete, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En octubre de 2013, el servicio de urgencias de nuestro hospital implementó una consulta de urgencias reumatológicas y musculoesqueléticas (URMES) atendida por 3 especialistas en Reumatología. El propósito del presente estudio es describir la experiencia acumulada en el primer año desde el inicio de la actividad de esta consulta. Método. Se realizó un estudio descriptivo de la actividad asistencial de la URMES a lo largo de su primer año de funcionamiento. Resultados. Se realizaron 1.788 atenciones a un total de 1.663 pacientes. La media de la edad de los pacientes atendidos fue de 67años (DE 7); 1.530 (85,57%) valoraciones se realizaron en pacientes correspondientes al área de influencia de nuestro hospital. De todas las valoraciones realizadas, 633 (35,4%) correspondieron a juicios clínicos relacionados con procesos inflamatorios y el resto, 1.155 (64.6%), a procesos mecánicos o degenerativos, articulares, paraarticulares o de partes blandas. De acuerdo con la topografía del motivo de consulta, 435 (24,3%) pacientes consultaron por un proceso relacionado con la rodilla, 362 (20,3%) con la región axial lumbar y 336 (18,8%) con el hombro. Conclusión. Nuestros resultados denotan una intensa actividad asistencial que parece repercutir positivamente en el manejo de las urgencias reumatológicas y musculoesqueléticas en general (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);13(1): 21-24, ene.-feb. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159882</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La consulta especializada de reumatología en un servicio de urgencias: un año de experiencia con la unidad de urgencias reumatológicas y musculoesqueléticas (URMES)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28302^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7764^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7764^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30392^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30392^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30392^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30392^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
