<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148538</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vascular and tissue calcifications in haemodialysis patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Atherosclerosis is the principal cause of myocardial infarction, stroke, and peripheral vascular disease, accounting for nearly half of all mortality in developed countries. The excessive growth of vascular smooth muscle cells is an important component in the development of atherosclerotic lesion. The direct effect of calcitriol and vitamin D analogs on the VSMCs proliferation is not clear. In this study we have analysed if calcitriol, Paracalcitol (19-nor-1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D2) and EB1089 (experimental analog used as anticancerous) modify proliferation and the expression of vitamin D receptor (VDR) gene that is regulated at the transcriptional level by itself in the VSMCs. VSMCs proliferation was analysed by BrdU incorporation and VDR gene expression using RT-PCR. VSMCs proliferation was stimulated when calcitriol was added to the culture. VSMCs proliferation was significantly lower with analogs at the same dose. With regard to the functional study, the expression of VDR gene was upregulated by calcitriol at a concentration of 100 nM. There were no changes in this expression with the analogs. In conclusion, calcitriol, do not modify VSMCs proliferation. Therefore, Paracalcitol could have a minor proliferating effect on the wall of vessels that vitamin D (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muray, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cardús, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aldea, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marco, MP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parisi, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Existen datos experimentales contradictorios respecto al comportamiento de las células de músculo liso vascular (CMLV) expuestas al calcitriol. Determinar el efecto del calcitriol y de sus análogos a nivel vascular tiene una considerable trascendencia clínica ya que la proliferación de las CMLV está implicada en el mecanismo patogénico de la arteriosclerosis y de la resistencia tras angioplastia. En este trabajo demostramos mediante incorporación de BrdU que el calcitriol estimula la proliferación en las CMLV. La proliferación es menor al añadir al medio de cultivo Paracalcitol o EB1089 a dosis equimolar. En concordancia con estos hechos, también observamos que el calcitriol induce la expresión del mRNA VDR mientras que no existe este efecto con ninguno de los análogos estudiados. En conclusión, el calcitriol tiene un efecto directo estimulador de la proliferación de las CMLV que no se observa con el Paracalcitol y EB1089 a concentración equimolar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;23(supl.2): 117-121, 2003. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148538</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto diferencial de los análogos de la vitamina D en la proliferación de células de músculo liso vascular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31134^s22007</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2151^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2512^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2151^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30579</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2490^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1016^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13655</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28048^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31134^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4329^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33872</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14550^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22282^s22007</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36347</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9321^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9321^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200300</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
