<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125782</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">My little Dora</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This work compares the Dora case with that of nine years old girls with conversión symptoms. Freud worked with Dora through dreams, while the author works with the girl through games, understanding such games as a language of the psyche enabling a translation of all its symbolizations, the same way as dreams do. Both the histories and the parts of the treatment are told through four facets: 1) About the parents and the failures in the maternal object´s early support. 2) A body that talks unveils the symptoms as a whistle-blower of a psychic conflict. 3) Secretes and lies show the unreliable aspects of both histories, which are trying to hide some unseen truths, and 4) Mirror, mirror, who am I? meaning the multiple identifications in hysteria. Being more than one hundred years apart, the similarities between both cases are pointed out, stressing the concepts of trauma, sexuality, conversion, surrogate parenting and identity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mora Febres, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo compara el caso Dora con el caso de una niña de nueve años con síntomas conversivos. Freud trabaja con Dora a través de los sueños, la autora trabaja con la niña a través del juego, entendido éste como un lenguaje del psiquismo, que al igual que los sueños permite traducir toda su simbolización. Ambas historias y partes del tratamiento son contadas a través de cuatro vertientes: 1) Sobre los padres y las fallas en el apuntalamiento precoz del objeto materno. 2) Un cuerpo que habla revela el síntoma como delator de un conflicto psíquico. 3) Secretos y mentiras que muestran aspectos poco veraces de ambas historias, que intentan ocultar verdades encubiertas y 4) Espejito, espejito, ¿quién soy yo?, alude a las múltiples identificaciones de la histeria. Con más de 100 años de diferencia, se plantean las similitudes entre ambos casos, y se hace hincapié en los conceptos de traumatismo, sexualidad, conversión, cesión de los hijos e identidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(67): 165-179, nov. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125782</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mi pequeña Dora</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7227^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201211</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
