<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136673</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5274</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Social well-being and psycho-social trauma: An alternative approach to posttraumatic stress disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Traditionally, clinical psychology has addressed mental health with a focus on the individual, irrespective of his/her environment. On the contrary, a psychosocial approach has underlined the need to address conditions foregoing the trauma, beyond individual&#146;s skin. If we are to understand mental health and mental disorders we have to consider the socio-historical coordinates within which the trauma takes place, i.e., the pre-traumatic situation, interpersonal and inter-group involvement, even the political frame, etc. A mental health view lies behind all these determinants, which takes into account individual-environment relationships. In line with this concept of health and disorder or trauma, Psychology is a science pursuing individual well-being (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz, Darío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, Amalio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Psicología clínica tradicional ha abordado el trastorno y la salud mental tomando como marco de referencia y unidad de análisis a un sujeto aislado de su medio. Frente a esa concepción, la perspectiva psicosocial ha mostrado la necesidad de atender aquellas condiciones, situadas más allá de la piel del individuo, que anteceden al trauma. Se trata de condiciones de un individuo inserto dentro de unas determinadas coordenadas socio-históricas. Desde ahí retomamos el concepto de trauma psicosocial como un trastorno situado dentro de un determinado contexto interpersonal, social, económico, político, etc., al que subyace una visión de la salud mental entendida como un asunto que incumbe a las relaciones del sujeto con diversos elementos de su medio. Detrás de las concepciones de salud, trastorno o trauma se encuentra la idea de la Psicología como una ciencia al servicio del bienestar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. salud;15(3): 227-252, sept.-dic. 2004.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136673</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bienestar social y trauma psicosocial: una visión alternativa al trastorno de estrés prostraumático</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12075^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
