<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86367</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Benign transient hyperphosphatasemia of infancy: a condition to be considered</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Benign transient hyperphosphatasemia of infancy (BTHI) is a condition where disproportionately high levels of serum alkaline phosphatase are observed, without clinical or biochemical evidence of bone, liver, renal or metabolic disease. We report a case of an eight months old patient presenting with fever and important increase of serum alkaline phosphatase. The HTBI is a frequent entity to be considered in order to avoid unnecessary investigations. If a patient has high alkaline phosphatase level, with physical examination, calcium, phosphate and liver normal profile, he/her should be monitored clinically and by measuring alkaline phosphatase levels until normalization. If high level persists after 3 months, the origin of the isoenzymes and a family study should be investigated (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Colino Gil, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Luzardo, M. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Calcines, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hiperfosfatasemia transitoria benigna infantil (HTBI) es una entidad en la que se observan marcadas elevaciones de fosfatasa alcalina sérica, sin evidencia clínica, bioquímica ni en exámenes complementarios de patología ósea, hepática, renal o endocrinometabólica. Se presenta el caso de una paciente de ocho meses ingresada por un cuadro febril y elevación importante de fosfatasa alcalina. La HTBI es una entidad frecuente que debe tenerse en cuenta para evitar preocupaciones y exploraciones innecesarias. Si un paciente tiene elevación de fosfatasa alcalina, con exploración física, calcio, fosfatos y perfil hepático normales, se le debe controlar clínicamente y continuar midiendo los niveles de fosfatasa alcalina hasta la normalización. Si persiste elevada tras tres meses, debería investigarse el origen de las isoenzimas y estudiar a familia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;13(49): 107-111, ene.-mar. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86367</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hiperfosfatasemia benigna transitoria de la infancia: una entidad a tener en cuenta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1873^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8281^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25525^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1873^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7694^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d471^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d471^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
