<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97053</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of the Mediterranean traditional diet in overweight and obese children after one year of intervention</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: the preventive and therapeutic strategy for obesity offers a poor development in the health care system. There is not enough evidence to determine what diet is the most efficient. The purpose of the study was to evaluate the effect of an intervention based on a Traditional Mediterranean diet. Methods: the study was conducted in overweight and obese children aged 2 to 14 years through the nutrition education program "Learning to eat". Anthropometric measurements and Mediterranean diet tests were used. There was neither calorie restriction nor physical activity promotion nor was cognitive-behavioral therapy. Mediterranean diet was promoted throughout the family environment. Priority was given to natural, perishable and seasonal foods. Results: the study was completed by 98 children; 61.2% showed a normal weight at the end of the intervention. At the end of the study, 73.1% and 82.6% were no longer obese or overweight. The proportion of fat mass decreased 18.66%, lean mass increased properly, and KidMed diet quality index was optimal in 95% after the intervention. Conclusions: opposed to low-calorie and low glycemic index diets, we propose a diet based on the Mediterranean Traditional Diet and from Primary Care. The observed decrease in Body Mass Index is clinically relevant, with a significant decrease in the proportion of overweight and obesity. The percentage of body fat mass decreased significantly. The Traditional Mediterranean Diet is easy to complete and along with the nutritional education program proposed, we consider it as the main pillar of the study(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gallego Fernández-Pacheco, J. G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calatayud Moscoso del Prado, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calatayud Sáez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la estrategia preventiva y terapéutica de la obesidad ofrece un escaso desarrollo en el sistema asistencial. No hay evidencia suficiente para determinar qué dieta es la más eficiente. El objetivo del estudio fue valorar el efecto de una intervención basada en una dieta mediterránea/tradicional. Pacientes y métodos: se realizó en niños de 2 a 14 años con sobrepeso y obesidad a partir de un programa nutricional denominado "Aprendiendo a comer". Se tomaron medidas antropométricas y se utilizaron test de calidad nutricional. No hubo restricción calórica, no se promovió actividad deportiva ni hubo tratamiento cognitivo-conductual. Se promocionó en todo el ámbito familiar. Se dio prioridad a los alimentos naturales, perecederos y de temporada. Resultados: noventa y ocho niños completaron el estudio. El 61,2% presentó normopeso al finalizar la intervención. Dejaron de ser obesos y de tener sobrepeso el 73,1% y el 82,6%, respectivamente. La pérdida de masa grasa fue del 18,7%, la masa magra aumentó adecuadamente y el índice de calidad nutricional KidMed fue óptimo en el 95% al finalizar la intervención. Conclusiones: frente a las dietas hipocalóricas y de bajo índice glucémico, proponemos una dieta basada en la dieta mediterránea/tradicional y desde Atención Primaria. La disminución observada en el percentil del índice de masa corporal es clínicamente relevante, con un descenso importante de niños con sobrepeso y obesidad. El porcentaje de masa grasa corporal disminuyó de forma significativa. La dieta que proponemos es fácil de cumplimentar y, junto con el programa de educación nutricional, consideramos que es el pilar fundamental del estudio(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;13(52): 553-569, oct.-dic. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97053</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de una dieta mediterránea tradicional en niños con sobrepeso y obesidad tras un año de intervención</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37656^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37653^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37653^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37653^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
