<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112149</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The role of stress of therapy dog handlers in animal-assisted therapy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We investigated the relationship between dog handlers&#146; perceived stress and therapy dog &amp;#8203;&amp;#8203;team performance in a dog assisted therapy program to improve emotional management in adolescents. The objectives were to analyze the relationship between dog handlers&#146; perceived stress and (a) patients&#146; evaluation of the handlers&#146; management, (b) patients&#146; evaluation of the dogs&#146; performance, and (c) stress identified in therapy dogs by their handlers. Nine handlers reported perceived stress in themselves and their dogs, and participants assessed the management and performance of the team. Results showed a significant negative correlation between handlers&#146; stress and the stress they identified in their dogs, which suggests that stress during the animal-assisted therapy sessions was negatively associated with the therapy team performance, and this was also identified by participants (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Ramírez, Mónica Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Jiménez, Xóchitl Angélica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Landero Hernández, René</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se investigó la relación entre estrés percibido del guía de perros de terapia y el desempeño del binomio en un taller de terapia asistida con perros para mejorar el manejo de emociones en adolescentes. Los objetivos fueron: analizar la relación entre el estrés percibido del guía y (a) la evaluación de los participantes sobre el manejo del perro; (b) la evaluación de los participantes sobre el desempeño del perro; (c) el estrés identificado en su perro. Se evaluó mediante autoinforme el estrés percibido de 9 guías de perros de terapia y el manejo y desempeño de los binomios fue evaluado por los participantes en el taller. Los resultados mostraron una relación negativa y significativa entre el estrés del guía y el estrés que ellos identificaron en su perro; y sugieren que altos niveles de estrés durante las sesiones de terapia asistida con animales están asociados a un peor desempeño de los binomios, lo cual es incluso identificado por los participantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;19(1): 1-10, jun. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112149</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El rol del estrés del manejador de perros de terapia en la terapia asistida con animales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53694^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d836^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
