<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058077</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Blood pressure findings in spanish dyslipidemic primary-care patients. LIPICAP­PA study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives. Despite the well-known significant relationship between blood pressure and cardiovascular mortality, few data are available on the blood pressure characteristics of dyslipidemic patients. The aims of this study were to determine the blood pressure characteristics of dyslipidemic patients being treated in primary care, and to identify factors associated with poor blood pressure control. Methods. This multicentre cross-sectional study involved patients of both sexes aged &amp;#8805;18 years who were diagnosed with dyslipidemia (i.e., hypercholesterolemia, hypertriglyceridemia, mixed dyslipidemia, or a low high-density lipoprotein cholesterol level) in the 17 Spanish autonomous regions. Blood pressure was measured according to standard procedures, and was considered well-controlled if it was &lt;140/90 mm Hg (or &lt;130/80 mm Hg in patients with diabetes, nephropathy or cardiovascular disease). Results. In total, 7054 patients were studied (mean age 61.3 [11.2] years, 50.8% male). Mean systolic and diastolic blood pressures were 134.6 [14.2]/79.8 [8.9] mm Hg, with significant differences (P&lt;.001) between hypertensives (140.8 [14.6]/82.8 [9.0] mmHg) and normotensives (128.5 [10.7]/76.9 [7.7] mm Hg). Good blood pressure control was observed in 47.4% (95% confidence interval, 46.3­48.5%) of subjects overall, in 29.3% of hypertensives, and in 12.8% of hypertensive diabetics. Poor control was associated with an increased cardiovascular disease risk (hazard ratio [HR]=2.89), poor control of low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HR=1.43), a higher body mass index (HR=1.06), and older age (HR=1.02). Conclusions. Fewer than half of dyslipidemic primary-care patients in Spain had good blood pressure control. Poor control was associated, in particular, with increased cardiovascular risk and poor control of the low-density lipoprotein cholesterol level (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lou, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrios, Vivencio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llisterri, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matalí, Arantxa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Roca, Gustavo C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Banegas, José R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Moreno, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Aunque la presión arterial se ha relacionado significativamente con la mortalidad cardiovascular, se dispone de escasa información sobre sus características en los pacientes dislipémicos. Los objetivos de este estudio fueron conocer las características de la presión arterial en una población dislipémica asistida en atención primaria y los factores que se asocian con el mal control tensional. Métodos. Estudio transversal multicéntrico en el que se analizó a individuos &amp;#8805; 18 años de ambos sexos diagnosticados de dislipemia (hipercolesterolemia, hipertrigliceridemia, dislipemia mixta o bajas concentraciones de colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de alta densidad) en las 17 comunidades autónomas de España. La presión arterial se midió siguiendo normas estandarizadas y se consideró bien controlada cuando era &lt; 140/90 mmHg (&lt; 130/80 mmHg en pacientes con diabetes, nefropatía o enfermedad cardiovascular). Resultados. Se analizó a 7.054 pacientes (edad media 61,3 ± 11,2 años; 50,8% varones). Los valores medios de presión arterial sistólica/diastólica fueron de 134,6 ± 14,2/79,8 ± 8,9 mmHg, con diferencias significativas (p &lt; 0,001) entre hipertensos (140,8 ± 14,6/82,8 ± 9,0 mmHg) y normotensos (128,5 ± 10,7/76,9 ± 7,7 mmHg). Se halló buen control de la presión arterial en el 47,4% (intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 46,3-48,5) del total de sujetos, en el 29,3% de los hipertensos y en el 12,8% de los hipertensos diabéticos. El mal control tensional se asoció con la elevación del riesgo cardiovascular (odds ratio [OR] = 2,89), el mal control del colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de baja densidad (cLDL) (OR = 1,43) y los incrementos del índice de masa corporal (OR = 1,06) y la edad (OR = 1,02). Conclusiones. Menos de la mitad de los dislipémicos españoles asistidos en atención primaria tiene bien controlada la presión arterial. El mal control tensional se asocia especialmente con el aumento del riesgo cardiovascular y el mal control del cLDL (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;60(8): 825-832, ago. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058077</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características de la presión arterial en una población dislipémica española asistida en atención primaria. Estudio LIPICAP­PA</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1822^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d963^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
