<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99725</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cardiovascular disease, osteoporosis and risk of fracture</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A 60-year-old man, who did administrative work, consulted for evaluation of the presence of osteoporosis. He smoked ten cigarettes a day and drank alcohol occasionally. Eight years ago he suffered a Colle's fracture in his right arm after an incidental fall, which resolved without complications. His mother had a hip fracture when she was 78 years old. The patient weighed 89.4 kg and his height was 165cm (BMI 38 kg/m2). The DXA showed a T-score &#150;2.4 at lumbar spine and &#150;1.9 at femoral neck. He had suffered a myocardial infarction one year ago and is presently taking statin, a beta-blocker and enalapril. In summary, this is a male with a background of fracture due to fragility, with lumbar BMD close to those established as diagnostic of osteoporosis and he also has cardiovascular disease. How should this patient be evaluated and treated?(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rozas-Moreno, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyes-García, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Torres, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Hombre de 60 años, administrativo, que consulta para valoración de posible osteoporosis. Fumador de 10 cigarrillos/día y bebedor esporádico. A los 52 años y tras una caída accidental presentó una fractura de Colles en muñeca derecha, que curó sin complicaciones. Su madre padeció a los 78 años una fractura de cadera. El enfermo pesaba 89,4 kg y medía 165cm (IMC: 32,8 kg/m2). La densitometría ósea mostró en columna lumbar T-score &#150;2,4 (CL) y en fémur T-score &#150;1,9. Hace un año tuvo un infarto agudo de miocardio, por lo que sigue tratamiento con una estatina, beta-bloqueante y enalapril. En resumen, se trata de un varón con antecedente de fractura por fragilidad, con valores de densidad mineral ósea (DMO) lumbar cercanos a los establecidos como diagnósticos de osteoporosis y que además presenta enfermedad cardiovascular. ¿Cómo debe ser evaluado y tratado este enfermo?(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;212(4): 188-192, abr.2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99725</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad cardiovascular, osteoporosis y riesgo de fractura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15208^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32988^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28261^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5057^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5059^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
