<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149846</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Qualitative research about euthanasia concept, between Spanish doctors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives. The decriminalisation of euthanasia and assisted medical suicide has generated a continuous debate. The terminological confusion is one of the main difficulties in obtaining medical practice consensus. The objective of this study was to determine whether the terms of Euthanasia and physician assisted suicide are used with the same meaning by doctors in Extremadura (Spain). Material and method. A qualitative study was conducted using two focus groups in which doctors from different specialties who attended a large number of terminal patients participated. No other focus group was required due to saturation. The sessions were tape recorded and transcribed by two experts in qualitative methodology. Atlas.ti software was used for the analysis. We were advised by the &#147;Health Care at the end of life&#148; Group of the Organizacion Médica Colegial of Spain. Results. Terminological confusion was verified in: 1) The mixture of etymological, functional and social concepts, 2) the term Passive Euthanasia, 3) the association between euthanasia and physician assisted suicide, 4) the confusion with the equivalent &#147;wish to hasten death&#148;, and 5) the difficulty of differentiating sedation with Euthanasia. There was consensus on some aspects: a) Full voluntariness, b) the condition of terminal illness, and c) the condition of unbearable symptoms. Conclusions. Conceptual variability persists in relation to the concept of Euthanasia, and is particularly noticeable in the persistence of the concept of passive euthanasia. It would be desirable to achieve a common language to assign a precise meaning to these words to help doctors in their professional practice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Altisent Trota, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rocafort Gil, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuervo Pinna, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Sancho, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivos. La despenalización de la eutanasia y el suicidio médicamente asistido genera un debate continuo. La confusión terminológica constituye una de las principales dificultades a la hora de consensuar prácticas médicas. El objetivo de este trabajo fue conocer si los términos de «eutanasia» y «suicidio médicamente asistido» son empleados con el mismo significado por los médicos de Extremadura. Material y método. Se llevó a cabo una investigación cualitativa a través de 2 grupos focales en la que participaron médicos de diferentes especialidades que atendían a un gran número de pacientes en situación terminal. No se realizó ningún otro focal, pues se objetivó saturación con solo 2 grupos. Las sesiones fueron grabadas en audio y transcritas por 2 expertos en metodología cualitativa. Se utilizó para la explotación de los datos el programa informático Atlas.ti. El grupo de «atención médica al final de la vida» de la Organización Médica Colegial de España actuó como grupo asesor del estudio. Resultados. Se constató confusión terminológica en: 1) la mezcla de conceptos etimológicos, funcionales y sociales; 2) el término de eutanasia pasiva; 3) la equiparación de eutanasia con suicidio médicamente asistido; 4) la confusión con el equivalente: «deseo de adelantar la muerte»; y 5) la dificultad de diferenciar sedación de eutanasia. Hubo consenso en ciertos aspectos tales como: a) la plena voluntariedad; b) la condición de enfermedad terminal; y c) el padecimiento de síntomas insoportables. Conclusiones. Persiste la variabilidad conceptual relacionada con la eutanasia, especialmente llamativa al observar la pervivencia del concepto de eutanasia pasiva. Parece conveniente que exista un lenguaje común que asigne a las palabras un significado preciso para ayudar a los médicos en su práctica profesional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;31(1): 18-26, ene.-feb. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149846</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Investigación cualitativa sobre el concepto de eutanasia, entre médicos españoles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28008^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32415^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32415^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32415^s22082</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32415^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28008^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
