<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037509</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vascular tumors arising in the chest wall: 25 years' experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Seventy-three interventions for chest wall tumors were performed at our hospital from 1978 through 2003. Six(8.2%) tumors were vascular. Four of them were soft tissue tumors, and two involved bone. The histologic diagnoses were hemangio endothelioma (1), low-grade angio sarcoma (1),and hemangioma (4). The diagnosis was established after surgery in all cases except one that had been previously diagnosed during an attempted resection before the patient came to our hospital. Fine needle aspiration carried out in 4 patients was inconclusive in all cases. Complete tumor resection with amargin greater than 3 cm was performed in each patient. Embolization followed by ligation of the intercostal vessels was performed prior to tumor resection in 1 patient with arterio venous fistula and diffuse angiomatosis. Chest wall reconstruction after tumor removal was carried out using autologous tissues except in 1 case in which a Marlex mesh(CR Bard Inc., Burlington, USA) and a metallic prosthesis was inserted to prevent deformity in the lower costal arch. All patients have been followed and have survived with no evidence of recurrence after follow up ranging from 2 to 25 years</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Sánchez Girón, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corpa Rodríguez, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casillas Pajuelo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Agero Álvarez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santiago Recuerda, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Pelillo, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el período de 1978 a 2003 realizamos 73 intervenciones en tumores de la pared del tórax, de los cuales 6 eran tumores vasculares, un 8,2%. Cuatro eran tumores de partes blandas y 2 tenían afectación ósea. El diagnóstico histológico fue de 4 hemangiomas, un hemangioendotelioma y un angiosarcoma de bajo grado. En todos el diagnóstico se estableció tras la cirugía, excepto en un caso que había sido diagnosticado previamente en un intento de resección antes de llegara nuestro servicio. A 4 enfermos se les realizó una punción-aspiración con aguja fina, que no fue concluyente en ningún caso. Se practicó resección completa del tumor en todos los pacientes, con un margen superior a 3 cm. En un enfermo con fístula arteriovenosa y angiomatosis difusa se practicó embolización con posterior ligadura quirúrgica de los vasos intercostales antes de la resección tumoral. La reconstrucción parietal del defecto tras la extirpación del tumor se llevó a cabo con tejidos propios, excepto en un caso en que utilizamos placa de Marlex y prótesis metálica para evitar la deformidad de la arcada costal inferior. Hemos realizado seguimiento de todos los enfermos, que en la actualidad están vivos y sin signos de recidiva, entre2 y 25 años tras la cirugía</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;41(1): 53-56, ene. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037509</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia de 25 años en tumores vasculares de la pared torácica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d36507</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32581^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32581^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
