<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73646</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Detection of bullying victims in a Primary Care site</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION. "Bullying" refers to abuse at school. The studies published up to date have been conducted in schools. They show that there are consequences for the health of those bullied, so that this work analyzes the detection of school bullying victims in a primary health care center. MATERIAL AND METHODS. The target population is 1256 teenagers aged between 13 to 16 years assigned to a Primary Care Center located in the Madrid suburbs. A cross-sectional, descriptive study was made using a random sample of 90 teenagers, the inclusion criteria being in school and having given written consent. The exclusion criteria were not knowing how to read or write, not being able to speak Spanish, suffering any kind of mental illness or those who could not be contacted via telephone. The variables gathered were: gender, age, nationality, living environment, whether they had repeated a year, body mass index (BMI), previous diseases, instances of being a victim of school violence or other forms of harassment, self-esteem problems, smoker, drinker and drugs use. RESULTS. A total of 37.8% of the persons surveyed indicated that had experienced some form of physical, verbal or psychological abuse and a relationship was found with BMI. A total of 3.3% of the people met the criteria of bullying, 12.2% were smokers, 11.1% drank alcohol and 3.3% took drugs and 16.7% had self-esteem problems. This last point was more frequent among women. CONCLUSIONS. Detection of bullying victim in this work-place is similar to those found in schools. Thus, the approach to this problem should be interdisciplinary and the family doctor should be involved (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Olivares Ortiz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedraz Garcá, MI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguel Vicenti, M de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benito Ortiz, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyes Fernández, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Redondo, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">INTRODUCCIÓN. El término bullying hace referencia al acoso escolar. Los estudios publicados hasta ahora se han realizado en centros escolares. Artículos publicados demuestran que ser víctima de bullying tiene consecuencias en la salud, por lo que este trabajo analiza la detección de víctimas de acoso escolar en un centro de Atención Primaria. MATERIAL Y MÉTODOS. La población diana son los 1.256 adolescentes de 13 a 16 años pertenecientes a un centro de salud de la periferia de Madrid. Se hace un estudio descriptivo transversal de una muestra aleatorizada de 90 adolescentes, siendo los criterios de inclusión estar escolarizado y dar consentimiento escrito, y los criterios de exclusión no saber leer o escribir, no hablar castellano, padecer algún tipo de enfermedad mental o no disponer de teléfono de contacto. Las variables recogidas fueron: sexo, edad, nacionalidad, núcleo de convivencia, repetidor, índice de masa corporal (IMC), patología previa, víctima de violencia escolar, criterios de ser víctima de acoso escolar, problema de autoestima, fumador, bebedor y consumo de drogas. RESULTADOS. El 37,8% de la muestra alguna vez habían sido agredidos física, verbal o psicológicamente, encontrando relación con el IMC. El 3,3% cumplía criterios de ser víctima de acoso escolar. El 12,2% eran fumadores, el 11,1% bebían alcohol y el 3,3% consumían drogas. Un 16,7% tenían problema de autoestima, siendo esto más frecuente en las mujeres. CONCLUSIONES. El estudio demuestra que si preguntamos en la consulta por este problema, la detección de víctimas de bullying es similar a la de los centros escolares. Por lo tanto, el abordaje de este problema debe ser interdisciplinar, y en él se debe implicar el médico de familia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);34(8): 375-378, oct. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73646</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Detección de víctimas de bullying en un centro de Atención Primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d297</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7773^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
