<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-11976</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Computed tomography appearance of Kikuchi-fujimo to's disease (histiocytic necrotizing lymphadenitis)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Histiocytic necrotizing lymphadenitis, Kikuchi Fujimoto's disease (KFD) is characterised by fever and lymphadenopathy,usually large cervical, unilateral lymph nodes. Such clinical presentation demands a work-up to exclude serious medical conditions like malignancy and infections. Foci of necrosis with lymphocytic Histiocytic predominance in association with scarce polymorphonuclear cells on lymph node examination, confirm the diagnosis of KFD. Many different patterns of computed tomographyc (CT) appearance of KFD have been reported. We describe the CT scan finding in two patients with this disease. All our cases showed, after two and three weeks of evolution respectively, enlarged lymph nodes with hypodense centres and peripheral ring enhancement. These radiological alterations correlated with the central lymph node necrosis found in the anatomopathologycal studies. In conclusion, KFD should be considered in patients with fever, cervical lymph node enlargement and CT scan showing hypointense centres and peripheral ring enhancement (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Arán Ediciones, S.A.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Linfadenitis necrotizante histiocitaria o enfermedad de Kikuchi (EK) es una rara enfermedad caracterizada por fiebre y linfoadenopatías habitualmente unilaterales y cervicales. Su presentación clínica obliga a descartar serias enfermedades que incluyen infecciones y enfermedades malignas. Los hallazgos característicos anátomo-patológicos en ganglios con focos de necrosis con infiltración linfocítica-histiocítica y pobreza de neutrófilos posibilitan su diagnóstico. Apariencias variables mediante estudio de Tomografía computerizada (TC) ha sido descritas en esta entidad lo que nos lleva a describir nuestras observaciones mediante esta técnica en dos pacientes con EK. En los dos casos a las dos y tres semanas de evolución, respectivamente, constatamos datos radiológicos de centro hipodenso y realce anular que correlacionan bien con las alteraciones anátomo-patológicas apreciadas en la biopsia ganglionar, que consistieron fundamentalmente en necrosis central. Creemos de la E.K. debe ser incluida en el diagnóstico diferencial de adenopatías láterocervicales, máxime si en los estudios mediante TC se demuestran las características radiológicas descritas en nuestros dos casos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;19(4): 183-185, abr. 2002.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Linfadenitis necrotizante histiocitaria o enfermedad de Kikuchi. Apariencia radiológica mediante TC</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Martínez Cueto, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuente J. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López,   A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Vázquez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sopeña, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilariño, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-11976</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33774</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
