<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107113</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Digitalis poisoning: the basis for treatment with antidigoxin antibodies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Digitalis poisoning, particularly in persons under long-term digoxin therapy, is a reason for repeated visits to Spanish emergency departments. Acute poisoning is rare but may occur as a result of attempted suicide or the intake of plants that contain cardiac glycosides. Kidney failure modifies digoxin pharmacokinetics and is an important trigger for severe adverse reactions to the drug. Clinical manifestations are nonspecific but usually include gastrointestinal events (nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, and abdominal pain) along with circulatory effects (hemodynamic instability, dizziness or lightheadedness, and syncope). Bradycardia (slow atrial fibrillation, conduction blocks) is common and may cause systole. Tachyarrhythmias may lead to ventricular fibrillation. In acute digitalis poisoning, hyperkalemia is a risk factor for cardiac arrest. The digoxin plasma concentration can indicate the severity of the poisoning, provided the tissue-to plasma ratio is at steady state. To treat acute poisoning, administer activated charcoal within the first few hours after digitalis intake. In such cases, or in poisoning during long-term digoxin therapy, continuous electrocardiographic monitoring is essential and potassium and magnesium concentrations should be brought within the normal range. The first-line treatment for bradycardia is atropine. Ventricular arrhythmias are treated with phenytoin or lidocaine. In life threatening situations, antidigox in antibodies must be used. They should be available in all referral or high-level tertiary care facilities and are administered according to the total digoxin body load (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cino, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puiguriguer, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Civeira, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burillo, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soy, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dueñas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nogué, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corominas, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La intoxicación digitálica, sobre todo asociada a un tratamiento crónico con este fármaco, es un motivo recurrente de consulta a los servicios de urgencias españoles. La intoxicación aguda es excepcional y podría presentarse tanto en una tentativa de suicidio como por la ingesta de plantas presentes en nuestro medio y que contienen glucósidos digitálicos. La insuficiencia renal, al modificar la cinética de la digoxina, es un importante factor precipitante de reacciones adversas y graves a este medicamento. Las manifestaciones clínicas son inespecíficas, y predominan las digestivas (náuseas, vómitos, diarreas, dolor abdominal) y circulatorios (inestabilidad, mareos, síncope, lipotimia). Las bradiarritmias (fibrilación auricular lenta, bloqueos de conducción) son frecuentes y pueden acabar en asistolia. Las taquiarritmias podrían conducir a la fibrilación ventricular. En las intoxicaciones agudas, la hiperpotasemia es un factor de riesgo de parada cardiaca. La concentración plasmática de digoxina permite evaluar la gravedad de una intoxicación, siempre y cuando se haya alcanzado el equilibrio de distribución entre las concentraciones plasmáticas y tisulares. El tratamiento de la intoxicación aguda precisa la administración de carbón activado en las primeras horas tras la ingesta. En las intoxicaciones agudas o por tratamiento crónico, es necesaria la monitorización electrocardiográfica continua y normalizar, en caso necesario, las concentraciones de potasio y magnesio. Las bradiarritmias se tratan con atropina como fármaco de primera elección y las arritmias ventriculares con fenitoína o lidocaína. Las situaciones de riesgo vital requieren eluso de anticuerpos antidigital, y se recomienda la disponibilidad de este antídoto en loshospitales considerados de referencia o alta tecnología, el cual deberá dosificarse en función de la carga corporal total de digoxina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);24(6): 462-475, dic. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107113</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de la intoxicación digitálica. Bases para el uso de los anticuerpos antidigital</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d938^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4110^s22025</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d916^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4116^s22025</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
