<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124821</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-1285</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of dry mouth. New trends</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Decreased saliva affects patients quality of life, that can improve changing certain health habits like hydration, usin groom humidifiers, avoid toxics and healthy behaviors, including frequent visits to the dentist. Prevention in patients who are going to be irradiated and modify xerostomizing drugs where possible contribute to the welfare of these patients. Different salivary stimulation methods, both pharmacological (acid, pilocarpine) and non-pharmacological (mechanical, electrical, laser, acupuncture or hyperbaric oxygen) and the use of salivary substitutes help maintain oral moisture better. In the future, the development of organic components from stem cells will probably be a valid line of treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jané Salas, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estrugo Devesa, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayuso Montero, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López López, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La disminución de saliva afecta la calidad de vida de los pacientes, que pueden mejorar cambiando ciertos hábitos de salud general como hidratación, uso de humidificadores ambientales, evitar tóxicos y conductas saludables, incluyendo visitas frecuentes al dentista. La prevención en los pacientes que van a ser irradiados, la modificación de los fármacos xerostomizantes en los casos posibles contribuyen al bienestar de estos pacientes. Los diferentes métodos de estimulación salivar tanto farmacológicos (ácidos, pilocarpina) como no farmacológicos (mecánicos, eléctricos, láser, acupuntura u oxígeno hiperbárico) y el uso de sustitutos salivales ayudan a mantener mejor hidratación bucal. En el futuro, el desarrollo de componentes orgánicos a partir de células madre será probablemente una posibilidad de tratamiento efectiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av Odontoestomatol;30(3): 135-138, mayo-jun. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124821</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de la boca seca. Nuevas tendencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52861^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15386^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4387</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11295^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54220^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12839^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
