<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054825</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of overweight and hunger among Mexican children from migrant parents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: To assess the prevalence of risk of overweight, overweight, and the perception of hunger among Mexican children from Indian and migrant parents over the periods of 2001 and 2003 &amp;#8232;Method: A total of 1,200 and 1,452 children were measured to assess anthropometric status and their perception of hunger experience. Results: There was no difference between 2001 and 2003 in the total prevalence of risk of overweight and overweight in either boys or girls. The prevalence of abdominal obesity is higher in the 2003 group than in the 2001 group among girls older than 9y (p &lt; 0.001). During 2003, the risk of hunger was higher (58%) than in 2001 (46%). Conclusion: The prevalence shown in our study is alarming since these children suffering from food insecurity have higher risk to develop obesity and diabetes during adulthood, particularly if they show rapid catchup fat after periods of economic recession (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Cruz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bacardí Gascón, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Valorar la prevalencia de riesgo de sobrepeso, de sobrepeso y de percepción de hambre en niños mexicanos hijos de padres migrantes indígenas durante el 2001 y 2003.  Método: Durante 2001 y 2003, un total de 1.200 y 1.452 niños fueron medidos para valoración antropométrica y percepción de hambre. Resultados: No se observó diferencia significativa en la prevalencia de riesgo de sobrepeso y sobrepeso en niños y niñas durante los dos períodos. La prevalencia de obesidad abdominal fue superior en el grupo del 2003 y en las niñas mayores de nueve años (P &lt; 0,001). Durante 2003, el riesgo de hambre fue superior (58%), cuando se compara con 2001 (46%). Conclusión: La prevalencia presentada en este estudio es alarmante, ya que los niños que sufren inseguridad alimentaria (hambre) tienen mayor riego de desarrollar obesidad y diabetes en la etapa adulta, particularmente si presentan períodos de recuperación grasa posterior a una recesión económica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;22(1): 85-88, ene.-feb. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054825</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de sobrepeso y sensación de hambre en niños mexicanos de padres migrantes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9951</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29426</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4716</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
