<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161557</identifier>
<setSpec>1577-0354</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acute effects of exercise on mood and HRV</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to analyze the acute effects of exercise on mood and on heart rate variability (HRV), in active and sedentary people. This involved 30 undergraduates classified into Active and Non active participants. In a single session participants performed a submaximal exercise test (UKK), answered the Profile of Mood States (POMS) and performed before and after the exercise a test of HRV at rest. The participants improved their mood state, by increasing Vigor and Fatigue factors and decreased Tension and Depression after the exercise test. Moreover, Active participants presented a significant higher decrease in Depression after exercise than Non active. HRV analysis also showed differences between Active and Non active participants in the frequency domain parameters LFnu2 and HFnu2 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Capdevila, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonet, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parrado, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del estudio es analizar los efectos agudos del ejercicio físico sobre el estado de ánimo y la variabilidad de la frecuencia cardíaca (HRV), en personas activas y sedentarias. Para ello participaron 30 estudiantes clasificados en Activos y No activos. En una sola sesión realizaban una prueba de esfuerzo submáximo (UKK), cumplimentando el Perfil de Estados de Ánimo (POMS) y realizando un test en reposo de la HRV antes y después del ejercicio. Los resultados indican una mejora en el estado de ánimo, aumentando en los factores de Vigor y Fatiga y disminuyendo en Tensión y Depresión después del ejercicio. Se encontraron diferencias significativas en función del nivel de ejercicio físico de los participantes en el nivel de Depresión, al observarse una mayor disminución después del ejercicio en los Activos. La HRV también mostró diferencias entre Activos y No activos en los parámetros de dominio frecuencial, LFnu2 y HFnu2 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. int. med. cienc. act. fis. deporte;17(65): 85-100, mar. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161557</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos agudos del ejercicio físico sobre el estado de ánimo y la HRV</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5325^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11240^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6493^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1349^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
