<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88876</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychogenic Non-Epileptic Seizures: a case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Psychogenic Non-Epileptic Seizures (PNES) are paroxysmal episodes of altered behavior that superficially resemble epileptic seizures but lack both the expected electroencephalographical epileptic changes and the association to dysfunction of central nervous system. They account for 17 to 30% of the population admitted to epilepsy units of tertiary hospitals for evaluation of seizures refractory to the pharmacological treatment. These episodes include most of the paroxysmal non epileptic events and diverse studies have found a high prevalence of multiple psychiatric disorders during the lifetime. The simultaneous presence of 2 or more psychiatric disorders has even been observed in 70% of the patients. When there is evidence on the absence of real epileptic seizures, the first step is to slowly suppress the antiepileptic treatment. After, adequate psychopharmacological treatment should be initiated in relationship with the psychopathological state of the patient. The different emotional and psychological variables that may be affecting the appearance and perpetuation of PNES must be identified and then resolved with psychological treatment. The aim of the present case report is to present the difficulties of differential diagnosis between epilepsy and PNES, emphasizing the great importance of both neurological and psychiatric management in the treatment of these clinical symptoms (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-González, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sierra-Acín, Ana C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pintor-Pérez, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Becerra-Cuñat, Juan L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las crisis no epilépticas psicógenas (CNEP) son episodios paroxísticos de alteración conductual, que superficialmente parecen crisis epilépticas verdaderas, pero sin los cambios electroencefalográficos esperables ni la asociación a disfunción del sistema nervioso central. Suponen entre un 17 y un 30% de la población atendida en unidades de epilepsia de hospitales de tercer nivel para evaluación de crisis refractarias al tratamiento farmacológico. Estas crisis comprenden la mayoría de eventos paroxísticos no epilépticos y diversos estudios han encontrado una alta prevalencia a lo largo de la vida de múltiples trastornos psiquiátricos, incluso se ha observado la presencia simultánea de 2 o más diagnósticos psiquiátricos en el 70% de los pacientes. Ante la evidencia de ausencia de crisis epilépticas verdaderas, el primer paso es suprimir lentamente el tratamiento anticomicial. Posteriormente se debe iniciar un adecuado tratamiento psicofarmacológico en relación con las alteraciones psicopatológicas que muestre el paciente. Es preciso identificar las diversas variables emocionales y psicológicas que pueden estar incidiendo en la aparición y perpetuación de las CNEP y abordarlas mediante tratamiento psicológico. El objetivo de presentar este caso clínico es el de plantearlas dificultades que suele entrañar el diagnóstico diferencial entre epilepsia y CNEP, destacando la gran importancia del abordaje conjunto, neurológico y psiquiátrico, en el tratamiento de estos cuadros (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;39(3): 191-195, mayo-jun. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88876</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Crisis No Epilépticas Psicógenas: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14873^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14873^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30325^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30325^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30325^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30325^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
