<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77564</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Rowell&#146;s syndrome or systemic lupus erythematosus and erythema multiforme. Association or coincidence?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Rowell&#146;s syndrome is characterized by the association of systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) and erythema multiforme-like lesions with the presence of immunological markers such as antinuclear antibodies with speckled pattern, anti-La antibodies and rheumatoid factor. We present the case of a 22-year-old woman with a diagnosis of SLE and erythema multiforme and discuss the possibility of distinguishing these entities from Rowell&#146;s síndrome(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tirado Sánchez, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de Rowell se caracteriza por la asociación de lupus eritematoso sistémico (LES) y lesiones de tipo eritema multiforme con la presencia de marcadores inmunológicos como son los anticuerpos antinucleares con patrón moteado, anticuerpos anti-La y factor reumatoide positivo. Presentamos el caso de una paciente del sexo femenino de 22 años de edad con diagnóstico de LES y eritema multiforme y planteamos una posibilidad para distinguirlo de un síndrome de Rowell(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);2(3): 155-157, mayo-jun. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77564</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Rowell o lupus eritematoso sistémico y eritema multiforme: ¿correlación o concomitancia?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28231^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22562^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22622^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29421^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8356^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
