<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055119</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Consultations and hospitalizations from an arranged hemodialysis center population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The hemodialysis (HD) population continues growing and aging, reason why        they are required to adapt the human, economic and materials resources to be taken care of. Objective: To analyze the distribution of the consultations and the        times of admissions in the different Hospital services of which an peripheral arranged        HD Center depends. Method: We analyzed all the consultations to the Hospital        Urgencies Departments and Hospitable admissions of all the patients who        received HD in the arranged Center Ponfedial (sanitary area Ponferrada of 150,000        inhabitants) in period 01/12/02 to the 31/05/05. Results: We prospectively examined        a population of 87 HD patients (71,0 ± 12,5 years, 77,9 % male, 31,4%        diabetics) time in HD 21,0 ± 22,7 months. They were a total of 286 (9,5/month)        consultations in the Service of Urgencies (2,31 consult/patient/year), 37,4% of        them did not motivate admissions. The most frequent consultation (28,9%) was        the complications of vascular access (70,9% of them required positioning a transitory        catheter; 1,1 complication of catheter/months), cardiac causes 10,3%, acute        pulmonar edema: 9,3%, infectious: 8,4% and traumatologic: 8,4%. There were        179 admissions (5,9/month; 1,44 hospitalizations/patient/year; 4,0 ± 14,2 days of        admissions): cardiovascular cause: 37,4%, by vascular access: 18,4%, infectious        disease: 17,0%, digestive: 6,7%, traumatologic: 3,9% and by other causes: 11,0%.        The cardiovascular group takes 46,5% (60,8% of them by vascular peripheral disease)        of the total of days of hospitalizations, infectious 16,7%, neoplasic 8,4%        and vascular access 7,6%. The neoplasic causes were the greater average with        36,0 ± 21,6 days of hospitalization, by amputations 23,0 ± 38,1 days, by stroke        14,5 ± 10,6 days, infected ulcers of lower extremities members 10,0 ± 19,0, other        vascular treatments 10,0 ± 4,7, ischemic heart disease 8,5 ± 20,3 and heart failure        7,5 ± 5,2 days. Our prevalent population of 49,5 patients needed 3 to 7 hospitable        beds, 0,33 temporal catheter, 1 tunneled permanent catheter and 1 fistulography        per month. Conclusions: The cardiovascular causes, the accesses and the        infectious ones are the main causes of consultations, hospital admissions and time        of hospitalizations</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Reichert, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La población en hemodiálisis (HD) continúa creciendo y envejeciendo, por lo que        se requieren adecuar los recursos humanos, materiales y económicos para ser atendida.        Objetivo: Analizar la distribución de las consultas, los ingresos y los tiempos de        estancia hospitalaria en los distintos Servicios Hospitalarios de los que depende un        Centro de HD concertado. Método: Analizamos todas las consultas al Servicio de        Urgencias (SºU) e ingresos hospitalarios de todos los pacientes que recibieron HD        en el Centro concertado Ponfedial (área sanitaria Ponferrada de 150.000 habitantes)        en el período 01/12/02 al 31/05/05. Resultados: Se dializaron 87 pacientes (media        de 49,5 pacientes/año, edad media de 71,0 ± 12,5 años, 77,9% masculinos, 31,4%        diabéticos) tiempo en HD 21,0 ± 22,7 meses. Fueron un total de 286 consultas en        el SºU (2,31 consultas/paciente/año), de ellas 37,4% no motivaron internaciones. La        consulta más frecuente 28,9% fueron las complicaciones del acceso (de ellas 70,9%        requirieron colocación de catéter transitorio; 1,1 complicación de catéter/mes), causas        cardíacas 10,3%, edema pulmonar: 9,3%, infecciosas: 8,4% y traumatismos:        8,4%. Fueron 179 ingresos (1,44 hospitalizaciones/paciente/año; 4,0 ± 14,2 días de        estancia hospitalaria): causa cardiovascular 37,4%, por angioacceso 18,4%, infecciosas        17,0%, digestivas 6,7%, traumatológicas 3,9% y por otras causas 11,0%. El        grupo cardiovascular se lleva el 46,5% (60,8% de ellas por vascular periférico) del        total de días de ingreso, las infecciosas 16,7%, neoplásicas 8,4% y angioacceso 7,6%.        Las causas neoplásicas tuvieron la media mayor con 36,0 ± 21,6 días de estancia        hospitalaria, por amputaciones 23,0 ± 38,1 días, por accidente cerebro vascular 14,5        ± 10,6 días, úlceras infectadas de miembros inferiores (MMII) 10,0 ± 19,0, otros tratamientos        vasculares 10,0 ± 4,7, coronariopatías 8,5 ± 20,3 y descompensación cardíaca        7,5 ± 5,2 días. Fueron de 3 a 7 camas/mes ocupadas por nuestros pacientes        hospitalizados. Conclusiones: Las causas cardiovasculares, los accesos y las infecciosas        son las principales causas de consultas, ingresos y estancias hospitalarias</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;27(1): 53-61, ene.-feb. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055119</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consultas e ingresos hospitalarios de una población de un centro de diálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2446^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6587^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
