<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-70096</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Tyrosinemia type I is a rare hereditary disease caused by an enzymatic defect in the metabolic pathway of the tyrosine. The detection of succinylacetone in the urine as toxic metabolite is a pathognomonic sign. High levels of alpha-fetoprotein are also frequent. There is an efficient treatment, the 2-(2 nitro-4-trifluoro-methylbenzoyl)-1,3-cyclohexanedione (NTBC), whose action mechanism consists on the inhibition of the enzyme 4-hydroxyphenylpyruvate dioxygenase. We have revised a total of six cases of tyrosinemia type Icontrolled in the Children&#146;s Hospital La Fe. One of our cases was detected through a neonatal screening test, five presented as acute hepatic failure and three of them showed proximal tubular dysfunction, with the clinical manifestations of our series coinciding with those described in literature. An excellent response to the NTBC is seen, improving the hepatic function in just a few days with hardly any toxic effects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dalmau Serra, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solera Navarro, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calzado Agrasot, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La tirosinemia tipo I es una enfermedad hereditaria infrecuente causada por un fallo enzimático en la vía metabólica de la tirosina. La detección de succinilacetato en orina como metabolito tóxico es un hallazgo patognomónico. También son habituales unas cifras elevadas de alfafetoproteína. Existe un tratamiento eficaz, la 2-(2 nitro-4-trifluorometilbenzoil)-1,3-ciclohexanodiona (NTBC), cuyo mecanismo de acción consiste en la inhibición de la enzima 4-hidroxifenilpiruvato dioxigenasa. Hemos revisado un total de seis casos de tirosinemia tipo Icontrolados en el Hospital Infantil «La Fe». Uno de ellos se detectó mediante test de cribado neonatal, cinco pacientes debutaron en forma de fallo hepático agudo y tres de ellos presentaron disfunción tubular proximal, concordando la clínica de nuestra serie con la descrita en la bibliografía. Se constata una excelente respuesta a la NTBC, mejorando en unos pocos días la función hepática sin prácticamente efectos tóxicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;66(9): 455-458, oct. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-70096</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34235^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34235^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4877^s22007</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35288^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34235^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35288^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34235^s22050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8272^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4877^s22015</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8272^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8272^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35288^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
