<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111252</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors related to patient satisfaction with hospital emergency services</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives To determine the perceived quality variables related to satisfaction and to identify the influence of sociodemographic factors on user satisfaction with hospital emergencies. Methods A telephone survey was conducted with a specifically designed questionnaire for use in a sample of 3,600 users of hospital emergency services in nine public hospitals in 2008 and 2009.ResultsThe adjusted model including all perceived quality and sociodemographic variables explained 47.1% of the variance (adjusted R2). Of all the independent variables included, only eight were significant in predicting the level of patient satisfaction. These variables were related to the patient's opinion of the relationship with medical staff (p = 0.041), nurses&#146; and porters&#146; professionalism (p = 0.010 and 0.022), infrastructure (cleanliness and comfort) (p = 0.033 and 0.008), information received at discharge (p = 0.000), waiting time in the emergency department (p = 0.000) and the perception of treatment-diagnosis without failure (p = 0.028).Conclusions The variables influencing emergency patients&#146; satisfaction were determined, allowing areas where corrective action could be introduced to be identified. In addition, possible confounding factors that should be controlled for when comparing results among distinct hospitals were identified. The emergency satisfaction questionnaire is a useful instrument to evaluate and improve quality of care(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Más Castillo, Adelia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hidalgo Montesinos, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parra Hidalgo, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermejo Alegría, Rosa María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gomis Cebrián, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calle Urra, José Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos Conocer las variables de calidad percibida que se relacionan con la satisfacción e identificar la influencia de los factores sociodemográficos en el grado de satisfacción del usuario de las urgencias hospitalarias. Métodos Encuesta telefónica con cuestionario de elaboración propia a una muestra de 3600 usuarios de los servicios de urgencias de nueve hospitales públicos durante los años 2008 y 2009.ResultadosEl modelo ajustado que incluye todas las variables de calidad percibida y las variables sociodemográficas explicó el 47,1% de la varianza (R2 corregida). De todas las variables independientes incluidas, sólo ocho resultaron significativas para predecir la satisfacción del paciente. Estas variables hacen referencia al trato del personal médico (p = 0,041), la profesionalidad del personal de enfermería (p = 0,010) y del celador (p = 0,022), la infraestructura (limpieza y confort) (p = 0,033 y 0,008), la información recibida al alta (p = 0,000), el tiempo pasado en urgencias (p = 0,000) y la percepción de tratamiento-diagnóstico sin fallos (p = 0,028).Conclusiones Los resultados obtenidos con la aplicación del cuestionario permitieron identificar las áreas donde implantar acciones correctoras mediante la identificación de las variables que influyen en la satisfacción del paciente de urgencias, así como la identificación de posibles factores de confusión a controlar para su utilización en la comparación de resultados entre diferentes hospitales. El cuestionario de satisfacción en urgencias es un instrumento útil para evaluar y mejorar la calidad asistencial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;26(2): 159-165, mar.-abr. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111252</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores relacionados con la satisfacción del paciente en los servicios de urgencias hospitalarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
