<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057651</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality of life as reported by palliative cancer patients. Relationship with medical report and emotional state</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: to analyse the clinical usefulness of data regarding quality of life (QL) as reported by oncology patients in a palliative situation.     Subjects and Method: 107 patients from the cancer department of Cabueñes Hospital in Gijón (Spain) completed the questionnaires QL-CA-Afex, HAD and Duke-UNC and a clinical protocol. In a second evaluation, the subjects were assigned at random to different assessment groups (one, two, three or six months). Correlation coefficients were used to analyse the relationship between the QL and the clinical situation, emotional state and social support. The ANOVA was used to study the differences in the QL with regard to the variables analysed.     Results: The quality of life did not diminish as the disease progressed. The aspects most closely related to the QL were the symptoms of illness and, secondly, psychological aspects. The validity of the QL-CA-Afex when distinguishing between groups of patients formed according to various clinical variables was tested</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez, Marino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gracia, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peláez, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padierna, Celina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amigo, Isaac</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: analizar la utilidad clínica de los datos acerca de la calidad de vida (QL) informada  por pacientes oncológicos en situación paliativa.      Sujetos y Método: 107 pacientes del Servicio de Oncología del Hospital de Cabueñes de Gijón (España) cumplimentaron los cuestionarios QL-CA-AFex, HAD y Duke-UNC y un protocolo clínico. Los sujetos se asignaron aleatoriamente a distintos grupos de seguimiento (uno, dos, tres o seis meses). Se utilizaron coeficientes de correlación para analizar la relación entre la QL y la situación clínica, estado emocional y apoyo social. Se empleó el ANOVA para estudiar las diferencias en la QL en función de las variables analizadas.      Resultados: la QL no se deterioró con la progresión de la enfermedad. Los aspectos más relacionados con la QL fueron los síntomas y, en segundo lugar, los aspectos psicológicos. Se comprobó la capacidad del QL-CA-AFex  para discriminar entre grupos de pacientes realizados en función de diversas variables clínicas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;15(52/53): 30-34, 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057651</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida informada por pacientes oncológicos paliativos. Relaciones con el informe médico y estado emocional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28598^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
