<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60224</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perinatal listeriosis. A presentable disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Listeria monocytogenes is a Gram positive bacillus widelay distributed in the environment whose main host is the pig, ovine and bovine cattle, being able to be present in foods like non-pasteurized milk, soft cheeses, meats badly cooked or vegetables. This germ is a rare cause of disease in the general population. Nevertheless in newborn, pregnant women, old or inmunocompromissed patients it could produce a severe infection with bacteremia or meningoencephalitis. Although most of the cases are sporadic, several outbreaks have been related to contaminated food. In this article we report a case for sepsis by Listeria monocytogenes in a preterm, and we review the epidemiology, clinical picture and management of the infections by this germ in the perinatal period, making special emphasis in the hygienic measures destined to diminish the rates of infection by this pathogen in such period (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Iglesias González-Nicolás, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soto Insuga, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muro Brussi, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Movilla, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Pelegrina, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Listeria monocytogenes es un bacilo gran positivo ampliamente distribuido en el entorno cuyo reservorio principalmente distribuido en el entorno cuyo reservorio principal es el ganado porcino, ovino y bovino, pudiendo estar presente en alimentos, como la leche no pasteurizada, quesos blandos, carnes mal cocidas o verduras. Este germen es una causa poco frecuente de enfermedad en la población general. Sin embargo, en neonatos, gestantes, ancianos o inmunodeprimidos puede producir una infección grave con bacteriemia o meningoencefalitis. Aunque la mayoría del los casos son esporádicos se han descrito brotes epidémicos relacionados con el consumo de diversos alimentos. En este artículo describimos, un caos de sepsis por Listeria monocytogenes en un recién nacido pretérmino, y revisamos la epidemilogía, cuadro clínico y manejo de las infecciones por este germen en el período perinatal, haciendo especial hincapié en las medidas higiénicas destinadas a disminuir las tasas de infección por este patógeno en dicho período (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;64(4): 297-300, jul.-ago. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60224</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Listeriosis perinatal. ¿Una enfermedad prevenible?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7410^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30071^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7410^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8262^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8261^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30071^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8261^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8262^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8261^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8262^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200808</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
