<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98332</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-755X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Why a Master&#146;s in Educational Psychology?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Psychology has experienced significant development in recent years, as well as achieving an increased presence in various fields of professional activity, including education. In Spain, however, progress in Educational Guidance has been unfortunately slow. This has been due to, among other factors, its pseudo-professionalized state. The purpose of this article is to highlight the need for specialized training to correct the imbalance between the training currently received by these workers and the professional skills and competences which are required today of the educational psychologist. Specifically, it presents a proposal that supports the need for a specific master´s degree in Educational Psychology, rather than existing Teacher Training specializing in Educational Guidance (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Solis, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Psicología ha experimentado en las últimas décadas un importante desarrollo y una creciente implantación en diversos ámbitos de actuación profesional, entre ellos el educativo. En España, no obstante, la Orientación Educativa ha sufrido un lamentable retroceso, favorecido entre otros factores por la seudo-profesionalización. El objeto de este artículo es poner de manifiesto la necesidad de una formación especializada que corrija el desajuste existente entre la oferta de formación y las capacidades y competencias profesionales que la sociedad requiere del psicólogo educativo. En concreto, se presenta una propuesta en la que se defiende la necesidad de un Máster específico en Psicología Educativa, frente al existente de Formación del Profesorado, en la especialidad de Orientación Educativa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. educ. (Madr.);17(1): 101-114, ene.-jun. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98332</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Por qué un Máster en Psicología Educativa?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4568^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4563^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35237</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36312</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12025^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32270^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
