<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102829</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">BSID-I Bayley Scales versus BSID-II as an assessment tool in early intervention</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study aimed to test whether developmental assessment using the version of the Bayley&#146;s Scales of Infant Development (BSID-I, 1977) overestimated the capabilities of infants born at term and preterm, compared with those obtained by applying a most recent version of these scales (BSID-II, 1993). 83 children participated in this study, 68 term infants (39 boys and 29 girls) and 15 preterm infants (9 boys and 6 girls) with less than 36 weeks gestation and/or less than 2500 grams of weight. The infants born at term were evaluated at two different ages (6 and 12 months of chronological age), while preterm infants were assessed at 6 months of age corrected. The results indicate that the use of scales BSID-I overestimated the abilities of children and suggest using more sensitive assessment tools to the processes of change and development of infants (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Fuentes, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Herrero, Ángela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brito, Alfredo G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Caravaca, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casbas-Gómez, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Rego, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-López, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente trabajo fue comprobar si las valoraciones del desarrollo mediante la versión de las escalas Bayley del desarrollo infantil (BSID-I, 1977) sobreestiman las capacidades de niños nacidos a término y prematuros, en comparación con las que obtendrían aplicando una versión más reciente de dichas escalas (BSID-II, 1993). 83 niños tomaron parte en este estudio, 68 nacidos a término (39 niños y 29 niñas) y 15 niños (9 niños y 6 niñas) con menos de 36 semanas de gestación y/o menos de 2500 gramos. Cada niño nacido a término fue evaluado en dos edades diferentes (6 y 12 meses de edad cronológica), mientras los niños prematuros fueron evaluados al alcanzar la edad corregida de 6 meses. Los resultados indican que el uso de las escalas BSID-I sobrevalora las capacidades de los niños y sugieren utilizar instrumentos de evaluación más sensibles a los procesos de cambio y desarrollo de los niños (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;28(2): 484-489, mayo-ago. 2012. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102829</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las escalas Bayley BSID-I frente a BSID-II como instrumento de evaluación en Atención Temprana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54849^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54849^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
