<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88921</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Systemic or intrasacular methotrexate in the treatment of cervical pregnancy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present a case of cervical ectopic pregnancy diagnosed in the sixth week of gestation. The speed of diagnosis and good clinical status of the patient allowed conservative treatment to be applied. Two doses of systemic methotrexate were required to decrease human chorionic gonadotrophin (BetaHCG) values followed by the use of intrasaccular methotrexate due to the persistence of the ultrasound image. Medical treatment with systemic and/or intrasaccular methotrexate is a highly effective measure to achieve low morbidity. This option allows more aggressive techniques to be reserved for patients unresponsive to this treatment or those with complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pallarés Ayuso, María del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos Pinel, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez López, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maldonado Ezequiel, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Partal Lorente, Ana Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Martí, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta el caso de una gestante a la que se le detectó un embarazo ectópico cervical en la sexta semana de gestación. La rapidez del diagnóstico y el buen estado clínico de la paciente permitieron la instauración de tratamiento conservador, siendo preciso el uso de dos dosis de metotrexato sistémico para que disminuyeran las cifras de la beta gonadotropina coriónica humana, y posteriormente el empleo de metotrexato intrasacular, debido a la persistencia de la imagen ecográfica. El tratamiento médico con metotrexato sistémico y/o intrasacular es una medida altamente eficaz para conseguir una escasa morbilidad, reservando otras técnicas más agresivas para aquellos casos que no respondan a este tratamiento o si aparecen complicaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);54(6): 306-309, jun. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88921</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Metotrexato sistémico o intrasacular en el tratamiento del embarazo cervical</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24738^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11694^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24738^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11694^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11694^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28169^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
