<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61709</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fibrous dysplasia of bone in a young male</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Fibrous dysplasia of bone is a skeletal disease due to a specific mutation in theGNAS1 gene with a broad spectrum of clinical presentations ranging from isolated monostotic and polyostotic forms to associations with other extra-skeletalmanifestations (McCune-Albright syndrome). The main complications are bone pain, deformities and fractures and sometimes cranial nerve compression and the development of bone sarcomas. Traumatologic surgery represents the principal approach in complicated lesions. Currently, the efficacy of pharmacological therapies is fairly limited. Cyclicadministration of intravenous biphosphonates is the most effective approach to achieve symptomatic improvement and to lower the risk of fractures, although more evidence from well-designed randomized clinical trials evaluating the safety and efficacy of these treatments is still required. We present a case of polyostotic fibrous dysplasia of bone in a 19-year-old male (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Torres, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La displasia ósea fibrosa es un trastorno esquelético originado por una mutación del gen GNAS1 con un amplio espectro de presentaciones clínicas. Hay formas monostóticas y poliostóticas puras y relacionadas con trastornos extraesqueléticos (síndrome de McCune-Albright). Lamorbilidad está determinada por el desarrollo de deformidades, fracturas y dolor óseo y, en ocasiones, compresión de nervios craneales y degeneración sarcomatosa. La cirugía traumatológica representa el abordaje principal de las lesiones complicadas y actualmente las posibilidades de tratamientos farmacológicos eficaces son bastante limitadas. La administración de bisfosfonatos intravenosos en ciclos es la intervención más justificada para la mejoría sintomática y la disminucióndel riesgo de fracturas, aunque son necesarios estudios clínicos controlados que evalúen la eficacia y la seguridad de estos tratamientos. Presentamos un caso clínico de displasia ósea fibrosa poliostótica en un varón de 19 años (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;56(4): 195-200, abr. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61709</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Displasia ósea fibrosa en un varón joven</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5493^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9601^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34482^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4220^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50518^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5494^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5493^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
