<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79054</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Heat stroke. Standarized treatment plan</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Heat stroke, or sun stroke, is defined as an emergency situation characterized by an increase in central body temperature above 40ºC and alterations in the central nervous system where encephalopathy predominates and coma is typical [1]. A precocious diagnosis is essential and if the initial opportune measures are not taken, the death rate is very high, up to 70%. Due to climate changes, the number of heat stroke cases has increased since the 2003 heat wave  [2-4]. Although at first symptoms these cases are treated in hospital emergency wards or outpatient wards, when the severity of a person stricken by heat stroke becomes life-threatening or advanced medical care is warranted, patients are placed in Intensive Medical Care Wards. Even though cases of heat stroke are low, its lethalness converts it to a serious life-threatening circumstance due to thermal regulation deterioration, adverse neurological effects, and secondary multi-organ dysfunction(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Monzón Ferrer, Adrián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Velasco Sánchez-Morago, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El golpe de calor se define como una emergencia sanitaria caracterizada por un incremento de la temperatura corporal central por encima de 40 ºC y alteraciones del sistema nervioso central donde predomina la encefalopatía y es típico el coma [1]. Resulta fundamental un diagnóstico precoz y, si no se toman las medidas iniciales oportunas, la tasa de mortalidad es muy alta (hasta el 70%). Con los cambios climáticos su incidencia ha aumentado desde la ola de calor del año 2003 [2-4]. Aunque inicialmente estos casos se atienden en los Servicios de Urgencias Hospitalarios (SUH) o Extrahospi-talarios, cuando la gravedad compromete la vida del paciente o precisan de tratamiento médico avanzado ingresan en los Servicios de Medicina Intensiva (SMI). Aunque la incidencia del golpe de calor es baja, su morbimortalidad se convierte en alta debido al deterioro termorregulador, neurológico, y a la disfunción multiorgánica secundaria(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;31(5): 354-358, mayo 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79054</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Golpe de calor. Plan de cuidados estandarizados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1953^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6509^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3159^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9294^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6509^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200805</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
