<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76784</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-811X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prenatal diagnosis trend for structural birth defects in Asturias (Spain). Period 1990-2004</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To asses the impact of prenatal diagnosis(PD) on structural birth defects.Methods. Over 15 years (1990-2004) the Registro deDefectos Congénitos de Asturias (RDCA) collected informationon birth defects (BD). The RDCA is a populationbasedregistry that includes all diagnosed cases whetherabortions, stillbirths, or live birth until the age of five.Data obtained were analyzed for the defects of the neuraltube closure (DNT), diaphragmatic hernia (DH), omphalocele,gastroschisis, and congenital heart disease, and theevolution of PD in these defects.Results. 3,035 BD were diagnosed (2.9% of totalbirths), of which 560 were prenatally (18.5%). They wererecorded 126 cases of DNT with an average of PD equalto or exceeds 90% in the periods studied, mainly due toultrasound diagnosis. There were 45 cases of DH, with asubstantial increase in the PD (68% the last years). Omphaloceleand gastroschisis, also show an increase in thefrequency of PD, especially in gastroschisis, being diagnosedthe 90% of them prenatally. 10.6% of congenitalheart diseases were diagnosed prenatally, and the eightvalues harsher and more structurally complex PD barelyreaches 20% (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García López, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mosquera Tenreiro, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Dehli, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ariza Hevia, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. Evaluar el impacto del diagnóstico prenatal(DP) en los defectos congénitos estructurales (DCE).Métodos. Durante 15 años (1990-2004) el Registro deDefectos Congénitos de Asturias (RDCA) recogió informaciónsobre defectos congénitos (DC). El RDCA es un registrode base poblacional que incluye todos los diagnósticos yasean abortos, mortinatos, o nacidos vivos hasta los cincoaños de edad. Se analizaron datos obtenidos de los defectosde cierre del tubo neural (DTN), hernia diafragmática (HD),onfalocele, gastrosquisis, y cardiopatías congénitas, y la evolucióndel DP de estos defectos.Resultados. Se diagnosticaron un total de 3.035 DC(2,9 % sobre el total de nacimientos), siendo 560 los diagnósticosprenatales (18,5 %). Se registraron 126 casos deDTN con un porcentaje de DP igual o superior al 90 % en losperíodos estudiados, principalmente a expensas del diagnósticoecográfico. Hubo 45 casos de HD, con un incrementosustancial en el DP (68 % en los últimos años). En elcaso del onfalocele y la gastrosquisis, también se produjouna mejoría en la frecuencia del DP, especialmente en elcaso de las gastrosquisis, siendo diagnosticadas el 90%prenatalmente. El 10,6 % de las cardiopatías congénitas sediagnosticaron antes de nacer, y analizando las ocho másseveras y estructuralmente más complejas el DP apenas llegaal 20 % (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. diagn. trat. prenat. (Ed. impr.);21(1): 8-14, ene.-mar. 2009. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76784</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución del diagnóstico prenatal de los defectos congénitos estructurales en Asturias. Período 1990-2004</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6707^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6713^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6707^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33760^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9629^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
