<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134269</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-6581</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Twelve hours of a compression sleeve is not enough to improve the muscle recovery of an exercise-damaged upper arm</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the efficacy of a compression sleeve worn for a short-time period (12 h) on the recovery from the symptoms of exercise-induced upper arm muscle damage. Methods: A randomized controlled study was conducted on thirteen healthy young men using a standardized and exercise-induced upper arm muscle damage protocol, and they were immediately placed into two groups: TREATED (n = 7) and CONTROL (n = 6). Isometric elbow flexion strength, upper arm circumference, and muscle soreness measurements were taken before and at 24, 48, 72 and 96 h after the damaging exercise, and were used as criteria of exercise-induced muscle damage. Group comparisons were made for each variable using a two-way ANOVA design (2 groups × 5 measurements), and with a significance level of P &lt; .05. Results: A significant impairment (P &lt; .001) was observed in muscle strength (&amp;#8764; 43% and &amp;#8764; 34%, for CONTROL and TREATED groups, respectively, 24 h after exercise), as well as a significant increase (P &lt; .001) in upper arm circumference (UAC) and muscle soreness (F4,55 = 6.49 for UACand F4,55 = 6.95 for muscle soreness) among the measurements after exercise for both groups, with no significant differences between them. Conclusions: These results, together with previous findings, suggest that the use of a compression garment for 12 h is not enough to improve the recovery from exercise- induced muscle damage in the upper arm, and longer periods of compression may be necessary to achieve positive outcomes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santos Borges, Lucio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dos Santos Rocha, José Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva Pirôpo, Uanderson</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos Cerqueira, Mikhail</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereira, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lupato Conrado, Luis Augusto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brito Andrade, Helder</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la eficacia de la manga de compresión usada durante un período de tiempo corto (12 h) en la recuperación de los síntomas de daño muscular inducido por el ejercicio de los músculos del brazo. Métodos: En un estudio aleatorizado controlado, 13 hombres jóvenes sanos realizaron un protocolo de ejercicio estandarizado para inducir daño muscular para los flexores del codo y se dividieron inmediatamente en 2 grupos: tratados (n = 7) y control (n = 6). Se tomaron medidas de la fuerza isométrica de flexión del codo, la circunferencia del brazo (CB) y la percepción del dolor muscular antes y 24, 48, 72 y 96 h después del ejercicio, y se utilizaron como criterios de daño muscular inducido por el ejercicio. Comparaciones entre grupos se hicieron para cada variable con un ANOVA de 2 vías (2 grupos × 5 medidas) y con un nivel de significación de p &lt; 0,05. Resultados: Se observó una reducción significativa (p &lt; 0,001) de la fuerza muscular (&amp;#8764;43% y &amp;#8764;34% para el grupo control y tratados, respectivamente, 24 h después del ejercicio) y un aumento significativo (p &lt; 0,001) en la circunferencia del brazo y dolor muscular (F4,55 = 6,49 para CB y F4,55 = 6,95 para dolor muscular) a lo largo de las medidas después del ejercicio en ambos grupos, sin diferencias significativas entre ellos. Conclusiones: Nuestros resultados, junto con los hallazgos previos, sugieren que el uso de la manga de compresión durante 12 h no es suficiente para mejorar la recuperación de los síntomas de daño muscular inducido por el ejercicio de los músculos del brazo, y para lograr resultados positivos son necesarios largos períodos de compresión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apunts, Med. esport (Internet);50(185): 23-28, ene.-mar. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134269</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El uso de manga de compresión durante 12 horas no es suficiente para mejorar la recuperación muscular del brazo tras el daño inducido por el ejercicio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30732</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1138^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1138^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38830^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
