<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143285</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">High prevalence of antibodies against hepatitis E virus in HIV-infected patients with unexplained liver disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To look for evidence of hepatitis E virus (HEV) exposure in HIV-infected patients with unexplained elevations of liver stiffness (LS). Methods: Case&#150;control study conducted in 31 HIV-infected patients with unexplained elevations of LS and in 31 HIV-controls with normal LS, matched by age, sex and CD4 cell-counts. Serum HEV antibodies were tested by two ELISA procedures and by Immunoblot. We defined exposure to HEV as the detection of serum HEV antibodies by at least one of the two ELISA assays, provided that it was confirmed by Immunoblot. A real-time PCR RNA assay was conducted in all plasma samples to identify subjects with active HEV infection. Results: Exposure to HEV was demonstrated, according to the criteria used in this study, in 9 (29%) of the cases, whereas it was shown in 5 (16%) of the controls (p = .3). Serum HEV RNA was detected in none of the controls and in only in one case. This patient had a documented chronic hepatitis E with progression to cirrhosis. Conclusions: HEV antibodies are frequently found in HIV-infected patients with unexplained liver disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Merchante, Nicolás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pineda, Juan A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivero, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parra-Sánchez, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Navarro, Elisabet</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivero-Juárez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cifuentes, Celia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macías, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Dueñas, Loreto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camacho, Ángela</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la existencia de exposición previa al virus de la hepatitis E (VHE) en pacientes infectados por el VIH con elevaciones inexplicadas de rigidez hepatica (RH). Métodos: Estudio caso-control realizado en 31 pacientes con infección por el VIH y elevaciones inexplicadas de RH y 31 controles infectados por el VIH con RH normal, apareados por edad, sexo y recuento de células CD4. Se investigó la presencia de anticuerpos en suero frente al VHE mediante dos técnicas de ELISA y por Inmunoblot. La exposición previa al VHE se definió como la detección de anticuerpos séricos mediante al menos una de las dos técnicas de ELISA que se confirmó posteriormente mediante Inmunoblot. En todos los pacientes se realizó una PCR en tiempo real para identificar a aquellos pacientes con infección activa por el VHE. Resultados: Se demostró la presencia de exposición previa al VHE, de acuerdo a los criterios usados en el estudio, en 9 (29%) de los casos y en 5 (16%) de los controles (p = 0.3). La PCR en tiempo real confirmó la presencia de RNA del VHE en el suero de uno de los casos y en ninguno de los controles. Este paciente presentó una hepatitis crónica por VHE documentada con progresión a cirrosis. Conclusiones: Los pacientes infectados por VIH con enfermedad hepática de origen inexplicado presentan una frecuencia elevada de anticuerpos frente al VHE  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;33(8): 532-535, oct. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143285</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia elevada de anticuerpos frente al virus de la hepatitis E en pacientes infectados por el VIH con enfermedad hepática de origen incierto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30054^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54468^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30862^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24206^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30053^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
