<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59464</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Survey of anesthesiologists&#146; practice in treating spontaneous aneurysmal subarachnoid hemorrhage</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: To evaluate the participation of Spanishanesthesiology departments in the management ofpatients hospitalized for spontaneous aneurysmalsubarachnoid hemorrhage.MATERIAL AND METHODS: Chiefs of anesthesiologydepartments of hospitals listed in the Spanish NationalCatalog of Hospitals of the Ministry of Health andConsumer Affairs were sent a questionnaire with 30items covering protocols for the management of patientswith spontaneous aneurysmal subarachnoid hemorrhage.Items asked about the participation of anesthesiologistsduring both admission and the perioperative period.RESULTS: The questionnaire was sent to 132 hospitals,of which 18 (13.6%) responded. Forty-six percent ofanesthesiology departments do not participate in theinitial resuscitation. Only 4 reported having a protocolfor treating these patients. The initial diagnosis wasreportedly made by cranial computed tomography in allcases. Endovascular treatment was the most commonprocedure reported (66%) and it was given within thefirst 48 hours (66%). Basic monitoring was used morethan nervous system monitoring. Total intravenousanesthesia was used for craniotomy in 53% of thehospitals and for endovascular treatment in 64%.Complications reported most often were vasospasm(100%) and hydrocephalus (69%).CONCLUSIONS: Even though few questionnaires werereturned, the results reveal scarce use of protocols forthe treatment of spontaneous aneurysmal subarachnoidhemorrhage by anesthesiologists. It was also evident thatthe participation of anesthesiology department staff inthe treatment of this condition takes place almostexclusively in the intraoperative period and that the useof nervous system monitoring is scarce. Endovasculartreatment is increasing in our practice settings (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fàbregas, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rama-Maceiras, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Palazón, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ingelmo, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVOS: Evaluar la participación de los Serviciosde Anestesiología de nuestro país en el manejo de lospacientes ingresados por hemorragia subaracnoideaaneurismática (HSA) espontánea.MATERIAL Y MÉTODOS: A partir del Catálogo Nacionalde Hospitales del Ministerio de Sanidad y Consumo, seremitió a los Jefes de Servicio de Anestesiología unaencuesta con 30 preguntas sobre la participación de losanestesiólogos en el manejo y la protocolización terapéuticade los pacientes con HSA, durante el ingreso y elperiodo perioperatorio.RESULTADOS: La encuesta se envió a 132 hospitales. Contestaron18 (13,6%). El 46% de los Servicios de Anestesiologíano participan en la reanimación inicial. Sólo 4 tienen protocolizadasu actuación ante estos pacientes. El diagnósticoinicial se realiza mediante tomografía computarizada cranealen el 100%. El tratamiento es mayoritariamente endovascular(66%) y en las primeras 48 horas (66%). La monitorizaciónbásica fue la más empleada frente a la neuromonitorización.La técnica anestésica utilizada tanto para la craneotomíacomo para tratamiento endovascular fue la intravenosatotal en el 53 y 64%, respectivamente. Las complicacionesseñaladas con mayor frecuencia por los encuestados fueron elvasoespasmo (100%) y la hidrocefalia (69%).CONCLUSIONES: A pesar del reducido número deencuestas contestadas, los datos obtenidos muestran unaescasa protocolización de la asistencia del anestesiólogoen esta patología, así como una participación casi exclusivade los Servicios de Anestesiología en el periodointraoperatorio, en el que la neuromonitorización utilizadaes todavía escasa. Al igual que ocurre en nuestroentorno, comprobamos que el tratamiento endovascularse está imponiendo a la cirugía (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;56(1): 15-21, ene. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59464</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Encuesta sobre la práctica y actuación de los anestesiólogos ante unahemorragia subaracnoidea aneurismática de origen no traumático</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13733^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33550^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30855^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30855^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13733^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33118^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200901</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
