<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-12145</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality of life, psychological and social aspects in patients with advanced HIV disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The advanced HIV infection carries an important physical, psychological and quality of life deterioration for patients. The introduction of new treatment strategies probably implies a global benefit for HIV patients. We carried out this study in order to know in HIV advanced patients; the clinical situation, the prevalence of psychological alterations (anxiety and depression), the quality of life and the impact of the introduction of new antiretroviral drugs about these variables. Methods: This is a prospective observational study carried out between January of 1996 and June of 1997 with 52 advanced HIV patients (CD4 cells less than 200 /µl). We carried out 2 clinical interviews with an interval of 12 months being introduced after the first one a change of strategy of antiretroviral treatment. For evaluating the quality of life, the MOS SF-36 was used. The valuation of the anxiety and depression were carried out with the instruments STAI and Beck respectively. Results: An important physical deterioration was found at the beginning of the study with 84.6% of polisymptomatic patients. We found a high prevalence of anxiety (76.9%) and depression (86.6%) that reaches criteria of graveness respectively in 75% and 25% of the cases. The quality of life was severely affected involving most of the dimensions of the SF-36 scale preserving the social function. The introduction of the change of therapeutic strategy produces a reduction of polisymptomtics patients to 54.8% (p=0.05), of the graveness of the anxiety (p=0.009) and depression (p=0.05) and improving in the perception of general health (p=0.03) and alterations of physical role (p=0.02). Conclusions: The advanced HIV infection carries a high symptomatic load with a high prevalence of psychological dysfunctions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Arán Ediciones, S.A.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: La infección VIH avanzada conlleva un importante deterioro físico, psíquico y de calidad de vida para el paciente. La introducción de nuevas estrategias de tratamiento probablemente impliquen un beneficio global para los pacientes. Se realiza este estudio con el objetivo de estudiar en pacientes VIH avanzados; la situación clínica, la prevalencia de alteraciones psicológicas(ansiedad y depresión), la calidad de vida y el impacto sobre estas variables de la introducción de nuevos fármacos antirretrovirales. Métodos: Estudio observacional prospectivo realizado entre enero de 1996 y junio de 1997 con 52 pacientes VIH avanzados (recuentos CD4 menores de 200 cel/µl). Se realiza 2 entrevistas clínicas con un intervalo de 12 meses introduciéndose tras la primera un cambio de estrategia de tratamiento antirretroviral. Para la valoración la calidad de vida se utiliza el MOS SF-36. Para la valoración de la ansiedad y depresión se utilizaron el STAI y la escala de Beck respectivamente. Resultados: Existe una importante deterioro físico al inicio del estudio con un 84,6 por ciento de pacientes polisintomáticos. Encontramos una elevada prevalencia de ansiedad (76,9 por ciento) y depresión (86,6 por ciento) que alcanza criterios de gravedad en el 75 por ciento y 25 por ciento de los casos respectivamente. La calidad de vida se ve comprometida severamente con afectación de la mayoría de las dimensiones del SF-36 conservándose la función social. La introducción del cambio de estrategia terapéutica produce una reducción de polisintomáticos a 54,8 por ciento (p=0,05), de la gravedad de la ansiedad (p=0,009) y depresión (p=0,05) y mejoría en la percepción de salud general (p=0,03) y alteraciones de rol físico (p=0,02).Conclusiones: La infección VIH avanzada conlleva una alta carga sintomática con una elevada prevalencia de trastornos de la esfera psicológica y deterioro de la calidad de vida. Las nuevas estrategias de tratamiento antirretroviral inducen una mejoría global a los pacientes, pero hace necesario un abordaje de los trastornos psicológicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;19(8): 396-404, ago. 2002.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida, aspectos psicológicos y sociales en pacientes con infección VIH avanzada</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Cano Monchul, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pujol de la Llave, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuesta, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguayo Canela, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Suárez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez de Ayala, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-12145</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35395</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
