<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165458</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cognitive techniques and language: A return to behavioral origins</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: the main purpose of this study is to offer an alternative explanatory account of the functioning of cognitive techniques that is based on the principles of associative learning and highlights their verbal nature. The traditional accounts are questioned and analyzed in the light of the situation of psychology in the 1970s. Method: conceptual analysis is employed to revise the concepts of language, cognition and behavior. Several operant- and Pavlovian-based approaches to these phenomena are presented, while particular emphasis is given to Mowrer&#146;s (1954) approach and Ryle (1949) and Wittgenstein&#146;s (1953) philosophical contributions to the field. Conclusions: several logical problems are found in regard to the theoretical foundations of cognitive techniques. A combination of both operant and Pavlovian paradigms based on the above-mentioned approaches is offered as an alternative explanatory account of cognitive techniques. This new approach could overcome the conceptual fragilities of the cognitive standpoint and its dependence upon constructs of dubious logical and scientific validity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Froján Parga, María Xesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual Verdú, Ricardo de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez de Prado Gordillo, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: el objetivo de este trabajo es proponer una alternativa explicativa al funcionamiento de las técnicas cognitivas basándonos en los procesos de aprendizaje asociativo y destacando su carácter verbal; se cuestionan las explicaciones tradicionales, que se analizan a la luz de la situación de la psicología en los años 70 del siglo pasado. Método: se emplea el análisis conceptual para revisar los conceptos de lenguaje, cognición y conducta y se presentan las propuestas desarrolladas para su estudio desde planteamientos operantes y pavlovianos, haciendo especial hincapié en las aportaciones de Mowrer (1954) y en los planteamientos filosóficos de Ryle (1949) y Wittgenstein (1953). Conclusiones: se detectan una serie de problemas lógicos en los fundamentos de las terapias cognitivas. La combinación de los paradigmas operante y pavloviano y su soporte filosófico en las propuestas señaladas suponen una superación de dichas flaquezas y permiten una explicación del funcionamiento de las técnicas cognitivas sin necesidad de recurrir a constructos de dudosa validez lógica y científica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);29(3): 352-357, ago. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165458</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Técnicas cognitivas y lenguaje: un regreso a los orígenes conductuales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37555^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3240</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7981</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
