<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109277</identifier>
<setSpec>2174-5544</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Congenital heart defects and chromosomal anomalies in fetal life: should a chromosomal study always be offered?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To assess the relationship between congenital heart defects (CHD) and chromosomal abnormalities in fetal life. Methods: This is a retrospective study undertaken at a tertiary care referral center. Our database was queried for cases of CHD prenatally diagnosed between 1990 and 2011, with postnatal diagnostic verification, as well as information available as regards the karyotype. The recommendation for performing fetal invasive procedures relied upon the type of CHD and the presence of associated high-risk factors of chromosomal disease. Results: A total of 1,384 CHD were retrieved and analyzed. The karyotype was studied prenatally in 848 (61.3%) and in the rest was either studied postnatally (172, 12.4%) or the presence of chromosomal disease was clinically ruled out given the absence of suggestive clinical markers (364, 26.3%). Chromosomal defects were diagnosed in 363 CHD (26.2%). The diagnosis was made prenatally in 324 (89.3%), and after birth in 39 (10.7%). In most of these cases (n = 28) the parents refused fetal invasive testing. We found that atrioventricular septal defect was the CHD most associated with chromosomal abnormalities (66.7%). On the contrary, we did not observe any chromosomal defect in CHD, such as transposition of large arteries or single ventricle. Similarly, there was no abnormal karyotype in isolated tricuspid atresia or in heterotaxy syndromes presenting without anomalies other than those typically included in the disease. Conclusions: Karyotype analysis is highly relevant in fetuses with CHD, given its impact in the parental decision-making process and patient outcome. Nevertheless, the recommendation of performing fetal invasive testing should be based on the individual characteristics of any given case, and in many cases the risks associated with the invasive procedure could be avoidable(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno Izquierdo, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escribano Abad, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Martínez, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galindo Izquierdo, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Arriaga, Paula Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Rodríguez, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herraiz García, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Analizar la relación entre las cardiopatías congénitas (CC) y las cromosomopatías en vida fetal. Método: Estudio retrospectivo realizado en un centro terciario de referencia. Seleccionamos las CC diagnosticadas prenatalmente entre 1990 y 2011, con verificación posnatal del diagnóstico y con información disponible del cariotipo. La recomendación de realizar técnica invasiva prenatal para estudio del cariotipo dependió del tipo de CC y de la existencia de otros factores de riesgo de cromosomopatía. Resultados: Se analizaron 1.384 CC. El cariotipo se estudió prenatalmente en 848 (61,3%) y en el resto o se estudió posnatalmente (172; 12,4%) o se excluyó clínicamente la presencia de cromosomopatía por la ausencia de marcadores clínicos indicativos de aquella (364; 26,3%). Existía una cromosomopatía en 363 CC (26,2%). El diagnóstico fue prenatal en 324 (89,3%) y posnatal en 39 (10,7%). En estos casos no se realizó el estudio prenatal del cariotipo principalmente por la negativa de los padres (n = 28). La CC que mostró mayor asociación con cromosomopatías fue el canal aurículo-ventricular (66,7%). Esta asociación fue nula en algunas CC como la transposición de grandes arterias o el ventrículo único. Lo mismo sucedió en la atresia tricúspide aislada y en los síndromes de heterotaxia sin anomalías ajenas a las que forman parte del síndrome. Conclusiones: Aun siendo enormemente relevante la información del cariotipo en los fetos con CC para la toma de decisiones de los padres y el pronóstico del paciente, la recomendación de dicho estudio ha de individualizarse según las características de cada caso, pudiendo evitarse los riesgos de la técnica invasiva diagnóstica en muchos casos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Diagn. prenat. (Internet);24(1): 15-22, ene.-mar. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109277</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cardiopatías congénitas y cromosomopatías en vida fetal: ¿siempre cariotipo?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7789</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28105^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34293^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34293^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
