<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043740</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Viral hepatitides infections in transplant recipients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hepatitis C (HCV) and hepatitis B (HBV) ­related end-stage liver disease are the most common indications for liver transplantation (LTx) in our area. Recurrent HCV infection is universal after LTx and although histological recurrence is variable, the rate of disease progression is more rapid than in non-immunosupressed patients and this impact graft and patient survival. All anti-HCV treatment strategies have shown limited efficacy so, at the present time, HCV reinfection after LTx represents the most important clinical problem in the follow-up. Regarding HBV, the most important factor in viral recurrence in the allograft is the presence of active viral replication at the time of LTx. The best patient selection (in non-replicative phase), the indefinite use of hiperinmune anti-hepatitis B immunoglobulin and the use of the new antiviral drugs have made possible a significant improvement in graft and patient survival (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castells, Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La infección por el virus de la hepatitis C (VHC) y en menor frecuencia por el virus de la hepatitis B (VHB) son las causas más frecuentes de enfermedad hepática crónica en los pacientes candidatos a trasplante hepático. La recurrencia del VHC postrasplante es universal y esta se asocia con una mayor agresividad que en los pacientes no inmunodeprimidos, lo que condiciona la supervivencia de los pacientes. Las diferentes estrategias terapéuticas han mostrado una escasa eficacia, por lo que la reinfección por VHC postrasplante representa el mayor problema clínico. En relación al VHB, el factor más importante en la recurrencia por VHB en el injerto, es la presencia de replicación viral activa previamente al trasplante. La mejor selección de los candidatos (en fase no replicativa), el uso indefinido de inmunoprofilaxis con inmunoglobulina hiperinmune antihepatitis B y la utilización de los nuevos fármacos antivirales han condicionado una mejora espectacular en el pronóstico de estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;24(2): 118-128, feb. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043740</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infección por los virus de la hepatitis en el paciente trasplantado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30351^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30351^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6664^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6664^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29476</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
