<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143922</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reconstruction of oral cavity defects with FAMM (facial artery musculomucosal) flaps. Our experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: The facial artery musculomucosal (FAMM) flap is a good option for covering small and medium-sized defects in the oral cavity because of its similar tissue characteristics and easy implementation. Methods: We reviewed our results using this flap between 2006 and 2014. A total of 20 patients were included and 25 FAMM flaps were performed, 16 right (64%) and 9 left (36%) flaps. Five patients had simultaneous bilateral reconstructions. The indications for flap surgery were reconstruction after resection of tumours in the floor of the mouth (8 cases, 40%), tumours in other sites of the oral cavity (4 cases, 20%), mandibular osteoradionecrosis (4 cases, 20%), oroantral fistula (3 cases, 15%) and postoperative ankyloglossia (one case, 5%). Results: Reconstruction was successful in 92% of cases (n = 23). Total flap necrosis occurred in one case and dehiscence with exposure of bone in another. Oral function and ingestion were satisfactory in all patients. Conclusions: The facial artery musculomucosal flap is reliable and versatile for reconstruction of small and medium-sized intraoral defects. It allows functional reconstruction of the oral cavity with a low risk of complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sumarroca, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Masià, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quer, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Bauzà, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: El colgajo músculo-mucoso de arteria facial (FAMM) es un buen recurso para la cobertura de defectos intraorales de pequeño y mediano tamaño debido a sus características tisulares y a su facilidad de realización. Métodos: Revisión retrospectiva de los resultados obtenidos con el colgajo, realizados en nuestro centro durante el periodo 2006-2014. Se intervino a un total de 20 pacientes sobre los que se realizaron 25 colgajos tipo FAMM, 16 derechos (64%) y 9 izquierdos (36%). El colgajo se utilizó de forma bilateral y simultánea en 5 pacientes. Las indicaciones para la realización de los colgajos fueron: reconstrucción tras exéresis de neoplasias del suelo de la boca (8 casos; 40%), neoplasias en otras localizaciones de cavidad oral (4 casos; 20%), osteorradionecrosis mandibular (4 casos; 20%), fístula oroantral (3 casos; 15%) y anquiloglosia posquirúrgica (un caso; 5%). Resultados: El colgajo consiguió una reconstrucción satisfactoria en el 92% de los casos (n = 23). Se produjo una necrosis del colgajo en una ocasión, y una dehiscencia con exposición de hueso subyacente en otra ocasión. Se consiguió una ingesta y función oral satisfactoria en la totalidad de los pacientes. Conclusiones: Dada su fiabilidad y versatilidad, el colgajo músculo-mucoso de arteria facial es una técnica adecuada para la reconstrucción de defectos orales de pequeño y mediano tamaño. Permite una reconstrucción funcional adecuada de la cavidad oral con escaso riesgo de complicaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;66(5): 275-278, sept.-oct. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143922</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reconstrucción de defectos de cavidad oral con colgajos tipo FAMM (colgajo músculo-mucoso de arteria facial). Nuestra experiencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9259</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5255</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10206</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22570^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22570^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29496</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24351^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13896</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2337^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24351^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9284</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9254</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2337^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
