<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91430</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Language and executive functioning skills of students with attention deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD), and in reading comprehension difficulties (RCD)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this work was to study the specificity of deficits in linguistic and executive functioning of students with ADHD and with RCD and to determine the profile of deficits in the comorbid group (ADHD+RCD). Participants in the study were 84 students, ages 12-16 years divided into four groups with an equal number of subjects (N= 21): ADHD, RCD, ADHD+RCD and comparison group (without ADHD and without RCD). We measured vocabulary, oral comprehension, lexical access, verbal and visual working memory, inhibition and attention. The results show that the ADHD+RCD group presents the most important linguistic deficits, followed by the RCD group. On the other hand, the three clinical groups (ADHD, RCD and ADHD+RCD) display greater performance problems in working memory than the comparison group, whereas the two groups with ADHD had more problems in attention and inhibition. These results suggest the dissociation of linguistic and executive deficits that affect the RCD group and ADHD group to a greater extent, respectively. Lastly, the comorbid group showed deficits both in language and in executive skills. We discuss the implications of these findings for designing interventions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miranda Casas, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Castellar, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Colomer Diago, Carla</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Andrés, María Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roselló Miranda, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo fue estudiar la posible especificidad de déficits en el funcionamiento lingüístico y ejecutivo de estudiantes con TDAH y con DCL y conocer el perfil de déficits del grupo comórbido (TDAH+DCL). Participaron en el estudio 84 chicos entre 12 a 16 años divididos en cuatro grupos con un número igual de sujetos (N= 21): TDAH, DCL, TDAH +DCL, y grupo de comparación (sin TDAH y sin DCL). Se midió el vocabulario, comprensión oral, acceso al léxico, memoria verbal y espacial, atención e inhibición. Los resultados indican que el grupo TDAH+DCL presenta los déficits lingüísticos más importantes seguido del grupo con DCL. Por otro lado, los tres grupos con problemas muestran peor rendimiento en memoria de trabajo que el grupo de comparación, mientras que los dos grupos con TDAH experimentan más problemas en atención e inhibición. Esto sugiere una cierta disociación de los déficits lingüísticos y ejecutivos que afectan en mayor grado al grupo con DCL y al grupo con TDAH, respectivamente. Finalmente, el grupo comórbido experimenta déficits tanto en habilidades del lenguaje como ejecutivas. Se comentan las implicaciones de estos hallazgos en el terreno práctico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);23(4): 688-694, oct.-dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91430</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Habilidades lingüísticas y ejecutivas en el Trastorno por Déficit de Atención (TDAH) y en las Dificultades de Comprensión Lectora (DCL)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7985</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37623^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8212^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8212^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29986^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
