<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043709</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-1375</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Incidence of peritonitis caused by oxacillin-cephazolin resistant germs in peritoneal dialysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Coagulase-negative Staphylococcus and Staphylococcus aureus continue to the germs most often responsible for peritonitisin patients treated using peritoneal dialysis. A variableportion of these germs have developed resistance to antibiotics such as oxacillin, cephazol in and glycopeptides. A total of 75 cases of peritonitis occurring in the last 5 years in 38 patients were analysed, to determine the percentage of gram positive germs resistant to oxacillin-cephazolinand to describe the evolution of these cases of peritonitis with empirical treatment with teicoplanine-cephtazidime, investigating the distinctive characteristics with respect to cases of peritonitis caused by germs that are sensitive to these antibiotics. The results of the cultures were: sterile 15%, coagulase negative Staphylococcus 37%, Staphylococcus aureus 8%, gram negatives 23%, other gram positives 13% and others 4%. No resistance to teicoplanine was found in any of the gram positive germs, nor to cephtazidime in the gram negatives; however, 50% of Staphylococcus were resistant to oxacillin and cephazolin. The percentage curation rate was over 90%, it not being possible to determine any distinguishing characteristics. In conclusion, the high curation rate in gram positive peritonitis treated with teicoplanine-cephtazidime is a further argument in favour of validating this treatment as the choice in peritoneal dialysis peritonitis</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Tristancho, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Ainsua, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Machado Guzmán, Visitación</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez Benítez, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los estafilococos coagulasa-negativos y dorados siguen siendo los germenes responsables más frecuentes de las peritonitis en pacientes tratados con diálisis peritoneal. Una porción variable de estos gérmenes han desarrollado resistencia a antibióticostales como oxacilina, cefazolina y glicopeptidos. Se analizan un total de 75 peritonitis acontecidas durante los 5 últimos años en 38 pacientes, para determinar el porcentaje de gérmenes gram positivos resistentes a oxacilinacefazolina y describir la evolución de dichas peritonitis contratamiento empírico con teicoplanina-ceftazidima, investigando las características distintivas con respecto a las causadas por gérmenes sensibles a estos antibióticos. Los resultados de los cultivos fueron: esteriles 15%, estafilocococoagulasa-negativo 37%, estafilococo dorado 8%,gram negativos 23%, otros gram positivos 13% y otros 4%.No se observó resistencia a la teicoplanina en ninguno delos gérmenes gram positivos, ni a la ceftazidima en los gramnegativos; sin embargo, un 50% de estafilococos fue resistente a la oxacilina y cefazolina. El porcentaje de curación fue superior al 90% no permitiendo distinguir características entre ellas. En conclusión, la alta tasa de curación de las peritonitis por gram positivos tratados con teicoplanina-ceftazidima se suman a los argumentos a favor de validar este tratamiento como elección en las peritonitis en diálisis peritoneal</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Enferm. Nefrol;8(3): 227-230, jul.-sept. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043709</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incidencia de peritonitis por gérmenes resistentes a oxacilina-cefazolina en diálisis peritoneal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6244^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10728^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10728^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6241^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28583</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24244</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10244^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2473^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
