<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127927</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patients with cancer in the intensive monitoring unit. New perspectives</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In recent years, there has been a significant improvement in the survival of patients with cancer in intensive care units (ICUs). Advances in medical and surgical treatments and better selection of patients has helped improve the life expectancy of this type of patient. An appropriate and early resuscitation in the ICU, without initial limitations on the life support techniques, has been shown to also decrease the mortality of patients with cancer. At present, we should not deny admission to the ICU based only on the underlying neoplastic disease. However, the mortality rate for patients with cancer in the ICU, especially those with hematologic disease, remains high. In some cases, an ICU admission test (ICU test) is required for at least 3 days to identify patients who can benefit from intensive treatment. We would like to propose a decision algorithm for ICU admission that will help in making decisions in an often complex situation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Prieto del Portillo, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Polo Zarzuela, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pujol Varela, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Durante los últimos años, se ha evidenciado una mejoría significativa en la supervivencia de los pacientes con cáncer en las unidades de cuidados intensivos (UCI). Tanto el avance en el tratamiento médico y quirúrgico, como una mejor selección de pacientes, han influido en la mejoría de las expectativas vitales de estos enfermos. En la UCI una resucitación adecuada y precoz, sin limitaciones iniciales a técnicas de soporte vital, ha demostrado disminuir también la mortalidad en los pacientes con cáncer. Actualmente, no debemos denegar el ingreso en UCI solo por la enfermedad neoplásica de base. Aun así, la mortalidad del paciente con cáncer en la UCI, especialmente el hematológico, sigue siendo alta y en algunos casos es necesario realizar una prueba de ingreso en UCI (test de UCI) de, al menos, 3 días para diferenciar a los pacientes que se estén beneficiando de un tratamiento intensivo. Proponemos un algoritmo de decisión al ingreso en la UCI que nos ayude en una situación, a veces, compleja (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;214(7): 403-409, oct. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127927</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El paciente con cáncer en la unidad de vigilancia intensiva. Nuevas perspectivas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9691^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9294^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
