<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054708</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reliability assessment of the EUROTEST</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The EUROTEST is a valid and useful instrument for detecting cognitive impairment and dementia. Our aim was to assess the test-retest reliability (TRTR) and the inter-rater reliability (IRR) of this instrument.         Methods. We assessed the TRTR by means of a cross-sectional repeated measures design in 30 subjects with no cognitive impairment. The IRR was determined through the blind assessment of 10 test administrations by 20 independent observers. In both instances we calculated the intra-class correlation coefficient and we compared those coefficients with the ones of the semantic Verbal Fluency Test (sVFT) obtained with the same samples and procedures.        Results. There were not significant differences concerning the characteristics of the subjects included in this study and those of previous studies on the EUROTEST. The EUROTEST showed a significantly higher TRTR (0.94 [95% CI: 0.87-0.97]) than the sVFT (0.51 [95% CI: 0.17- 0.74]), but there was not significant difference in IRR between the EUROTEST (0.91 [95% CI: 0.82-0.97]) and the sVFT (0.96 [95% CI: 0.91-0.99]).        Conclusions. The EUROTEST shows high TRTR and IRR; therefore, this instrument is appropriate for the longitudinal assessment of subjects with dementia and their response to treatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carnero Pardo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gurpegui, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montoro Ríos, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Cantalejo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Camello, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guardado-Santervás, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El EUROTEST es un instrumento válido y útil para la detección de deterioro cognitivo y demencia. Nuestro objetivo fue evaluar la fiabilidad test-retest (FTR) y la fiabilidad interobservador (FIO) de este instrumento.         Métodos. La FTR se evaluó mediante un diseño transversal de medidas repetidas en una muestra de 30 sujetos sin deterioro cognitivo; la FIO se determinó mediante la evaluación a ciegas de 10 aplicaciones del test por 20 observadores independientes; en ambos casos se utilizó el coeficiente de correlación intraclase y los resultados se compararon con los obtenidos con las mismas muestras y los mismos procedimientos por el Test de Fluidez Verbal semántica (TFVs).        Resultados. No hay diferencia significativa en las características de los sujetos de este estudio y las de estudios previos del EUROTEST. La FTR del EUROTEST (0,94 [IC 95%: 0,87-0,97]) fue significativamente superior a la del TFVs (0,51 [IC 95 %: 0,17-0,74]); no hubo diferencia significativa, en cambio, entre la FIO del EUROTEST (0,91 [IC 95 %: 0,82- 0,97]) y la del TFVs (0,96 [IC 95%: 0,91-0,99]).        Conclusiones. El EUROTEST tiene altas FTR y FIO; por tanto, es un instrumento adecuado para seguir evolutivamente a sujetos con demencia y evaluar su respuesta al tratamiento</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;22(3): 153-158, abr. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054708</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la fiabilidad del EUROTEST</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7985</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13448^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28387</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24807</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13448^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
