<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79967</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-6045</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Health-related quality of life after a community program of hydrokinesis therapy for pregnant women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine how the quality of life of pregnant women who participate in a community program of hydrokinesis therapy for pregnant women (PHTPW) changes. Material and methods. Quasi-experimental, pre-post intervention study. This study was conducted in a community center for physical activity and health promotion. A total of 26 pregnant women, who took part in a community program of hydrokinesis therapy for pregnant women twice a week, were included. Inclusion criteria: provide medical authorization. Exclusion criteria: women who exceeded 24 weeks of pregnancy, who did not provide authorization or who refused to participate in the study. The SF-12 and EuroQol questionnaires were used as specific instruments to measure the variations of quality of life and general health status of the participants. Results. The participants had a mean age of 32±4.09. The results obtained were: general physical health condition 1.73 (95% CI &amp;#8722;3.00 to 6.46); mental health condition &amp;#8722;2.19 (&amp;#8722;6.67 to 2.29), EuroQol_5D &amp;#8722;0.01 (&amp;#8722;0.10 to 0.07) and EuroQol_VAS 0.29 (&amp;#8722;7.39 to 7.97). Conclusions. An 8-week long community program of hydrokinesis therapy for pregnant women may stop the normal decrease in health-related quality of life in pregnant women (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-Sánchez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuesta-Vargas, A. I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar cómo cambia la calidad de vida de mujeres embarazadas que realizan un programa comunitario de hidrocinesiterapia para embarazadas (PCHCE). Material y método. Estudio cuasi experimental pre-post intervención. Estudio realizado en un centro comunitario de promoción de salud y actividad física. Veintiséis mujeres embarazadas, la cuales, durante 8 semanas realizaron un programa comunitario de hidrocinesiterapia para embarazadas 2 veces por semana. Criterios de inclusión: aportar autorización facultativa. Criterios de exclusión: mujeres que superasen las 24 semanas de gestación, que no portasen dicha autorización o que rechazasen participar en el estudio. Fueron utilizados los cuestionarios SF-12 y EuroQol como instrumentos específicos para medir las variaciones de la calidad de vida y el estado general de salud de las participantes. Resultados. Con una edad media de 32±4,09 en las participantes. Los resultados obtenidos fueron: estado general de salud física 1,73 (IC 95% &amp;#8722;3,00&#150;6,46); estado de salud mental &amp;#8722;2,19 (&amp;#8722;6,67&#150;2,29), EuroQol_5D &amp;#8722;0,01 (&amp;#8722;0,10&#150;0,07) y EuroQol_EVA 0,29 (&amp;#8722;7,39&#150;7,97). Conclusiones. Un programa comunitario de hidrocinesitareapia para embarazadas de 8 semanas de duración puede frenar el normal descenso de la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud en mujeres embarazadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. iberoam. fisioter. kinesiol. (Ed. impr.);13(1): 22-28, ene.-jun. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79967</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida relacionada con la salud tras un programa comunitario de hidrocinesiterapia para embarazadas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37736</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37617^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36319^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
