<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149021</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychopedagogical intervention in attention deficit hyperactivity disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Children with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) present alterations in both their attentional mechanisms and their inhibitory control processes (impulsiveness and hyperactivity), which have different effects on their academic, socio-emotional and behavioural achievement. Therefore it is essential to have access to intervention strategies in the field of psychopedagogics that can have a favourable effect on the developmental course of the patients. Aim. To review the psychopedagogical foundations underlying interventions in cases of ADHD, bearing in mind the relation between the functional anatomy and the clinical symptoms and the corresponding programmes of intervention. Development. Three syndromes stand out above the rest: orbitofrontal, dorsolateral and in the cingulate at the medial level. The phases of psychopedagogical intervention should cover both the child and his or her family and school. Neurocognitive training is focused on the child, and is based on programmes for training the executive functions and on interventions involving the academic, behavioural and socio-affective spheres. Behavioural modification programmes are complementary and on many occasions improve the compromised behaviour in children with ADHD. Psychopedagogical guidance at school must be considered necessary for an effective intervention in the academic environment. Conclusions. Psychopedagogical interventions in children with ADHD must include personalised treatment within a multidisciplinary methodology that takes into account all the contexts in which the child is developing, his or her cognitive performance and the appropriate pharmacological intervention in each case (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herrero Liadró, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abad Mas, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Madrid, Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suay Nicolás, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Andrés, Rosalía</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los niños con trastorno por déficit de atención/hiperactividad (TDAH) presentan alteraciones en los mecanismos atencionales y en los procesos de control inhibitorio (impulsividad e hiperactividad), que afectan de distinta manera a su rendimiento académico, socioemocional y conductual, por lo que es fundamental la consideración de estrategias de intervención en el ámbito psicopedagógico que puedan incidir de forma favorable en el curso evolutivo de los afectados. Objetivo. Revisar las bases psicopedagógicas en la intervención sobre el TDAH, considerando la relación de la anatomía funcional con la sintomatología clínica y los correspondientes programas de intervención. Desarrollo. Se destacan los tres síndromes preferentes: orbitofrontal, dorsolateral y en el cíngulo a nivel medial. Las fases de la intervención psicopedagógica deben abarcar tanto al niño como a la familia y el colegio. El entrenamiento neurocognitivo se centra en el niño, basado en programas de entrenamiento de las funciones ejecutivas y en las actuaciones sobre el ámbito académico, conductual y socioafectivo. Los programas de modificación de conducta son complementarios y en muchas ocasiones mejoran el comportamiento comprometido en los niños con TDAH. Las orientaciones psicopedagó- gicas en la escuela deben considerarse necesarias para una intervención eficaz en el entorno académico. Conclusiones. La intervención psicopedagógica de los niños con TDAH debe contemplar la individualización del tratamiento dentro de una metodología multidisciplinar, teniendo en cuenta todos los contextos en los que se desarrolla el niño, su rendimiento cognitivo y las intervenciones farmacológicas apropiadas en cada caso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;57(supl.1): s193-s203, 6 sept. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149021</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervención psicopedagógica en el trastorno por déficit de atención/hiperactividad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7353</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8601</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30601^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4589^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15354</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32270</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5761^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14043</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6330^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1541^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8037^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2699^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2699^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
