<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115701</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0973</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Therapeutic communities as treatment for drug dependencies: a systematic review of short-term follow-up</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive. The therapeutic communities (TC) constitute one of the most extensive treatments for the drug dependencies; however, its investigation is scarce. The aim to do a systematic review to know the methodological elements of the short term follow-up studies and, at the same time, describe the consequences of the TC. Material and method. It was applied the &#147;Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic reviews and meta-Analyses&#148; (PRISMA) for the search in Medline, PsycINFO, PsycARTICLES and PsycCRITIQUES, in order to locate short-term follow-up studies of TC between 1980 and 2010. Results. The follow-up consists in an initial register and, at least, another to half year of treatment; the minimum sample contains 60 users with a greater prevalence of single men; 50% continues in follow-up and/or reaches the abstinence. Conclusion. The TC seem to be beneficial for the adjustment of the consumption and other psychosocial aspects, although lacking information difficult the comparability of these findings (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Claver, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lopez-Fernandez, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Román-Jiménez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castello-Cullell, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Las comunidades terapéuticas (CT) constituyen uno de los tratamientos más extensos para las drogodependencias; sin embargo, su investigación es escasa. El objetivo fue realizar una revisión sistemática para conocer los elementos metodológicos de los estudios de seguimiento a corto plazo y, a su vez, describir las consecuencias de las CT. Material y método. Se aplicó el "Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic reviews and meta-Analyses" (PRISMA) para la búsqueda en Medline, PsycINFO, PsycARTICLES y PsycCRITIQUES de estudios de seguimiento a corto plazo de CT entre 1980 y 2010. Resultados. El seguimiento consiste en un registro inicial y, al menos, otro al medio año de tratamiento; la muestra mínima contiene 60 usuarios con una mayor prevalencia de hombres solteros; el 50% continúa en seguimiento y/o alcanza la abstinencia. Conclusión. Las CT parecen ser beneficiosas para el ajuste del consumo y otros aspectos psicosociales, aunque la falta de información dificulta garantizar la comparación de estos hallazgos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trastor. adict;14(4): 118-125, oct.-dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115701</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las comunidades terapéuticas como tratamiento para las drogodependencias: una revisión sistemática del seguimiento a corto plazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14186</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
