<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135625</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: Carcinosarcoma is a neoplasia with malignant epithelial and mesenchymal differentiation. Carcinosarcoma of the urinary tract is a rare neoplasm. It is an extremely rare entity in the ureter. METHODS/RESULTS: We report one case of carcinosarcoma arising from the ureter in a 69-year-old male patient who underwent total ureterectomy. CONCLUSION: Carcinosarcomais a malignant neoplasia associated with poor prognosis, probably resulting from the advanced stage at diagnosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jurado, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Porras, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lara, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: El carcinosarcoma se caracteriza por ser un tumor con componente epitelial y mesenquimal maligno. Se trata de una neoplasia poco frecuente en la vía urinaria y su localización en uréter es excepcional. MÉTODOS/RESULTADOS: Describimos un caso de carcinosarcoma de uréter en un paciente de 69 años de edad al que se le practica tumorectomía con resección ureteral. CONCLUSIÓN: Los carcinosarcomas son tumores malignos con mal pronóstico, probablemente por ser lesiones diagnosticadas en estadio avanzado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;60(10): 1213-1215, dic. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135625</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Carcinoma de ureter. Descripción de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2340^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14915^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
