<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156577</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Infection by Human Papillomavirus (HPV) in women bearers of HIV/AIDS</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Verify the predominance of HPV in women bearers of HIV/AIDS, and know the social demographic, clinic and behavior characteristics of this population. Methods: Documental, exploratory, descriptive and quantitative study that included the promptuary of 32 women with HIV/AIDS in the CERDI system and that were submitted to the Papanicolaou test during the period of study. Results: HPV lesions were found in (15.6%) of the women, having the classification of LSIL low grade (60%) of these. Age varied between 18 to 39 (62.5%), married or in common-law marriage (75.1%) and the majority hasn&#146;t finished middle school (37.5%). Regarding to family income, 46.9% informed income same or lower to the minimum wage. They started their sexual activity with age lower than 17 (62.5%), had less than four sexual partners in their life (56.3%) and only one partner during the last year (96.9%). No women referred to the regular use of condoms before the diagnosis of HIV, after the diagnosis, 62.5% started to use in all their sexual relations. Sexual diseases prior history were reported by (40.6%), probable way of virus transmission were by sexual means (93.8%) and the diagnosis of infection was done over five years for the majority (56.3%). Most of them also make use of TARV (65.6%) and presented a CD4 cell count same or over 500 cells/ml (59.4%) in the last test. Conclusions: There were prevalence of HPV in 15.6%, similar to other studies. The need of a periodic Papanicolaou test to detect early alterations is highlighted to avoid cervical cancer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santos, Silvânia Paiva dos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodrigues, Bianca Gonçalves</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Holzmann, Ana Paula Ferreira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, Amanda Gesiele Pereira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lima, Cássio de Almeida</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gonçalves, Renata Patrícia Fonseca</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Verificar la prevalencia del VPH en mujeres viviendo con VIH/AIDS, y conocer las características sociodemográficas, clínicas y comportamentales de esa población. Métodos: Estudio documental, exploratorio, descriptivo, cuantitativo, que incluyó los historiales de 32 mujeres viviendo con VIH/AIDS registradas en el CERDI y que realizaron el examen de Papanicolaou en el período de estudio. Resultados: Se encontraron lesiones de VPH en (15,6%) de las mujeres, siendo clasificada como LSIL bajo grado (60%) de estas. La edad varió de 18 a 39 años (62,5%), casadas o vive en unión estable (75,1%) y la mayoría tiene bachillerato incompleto (37,5%). En cuanto a la renta familiar, 46,9% informó renta igual o inferior a un sueldo mínimo. Iniciaron actividad sexual con edad inferior a 17 años (62,5%), tuvieron menos de cuatro parejas sexuales en la vida (56,3%) y pareja única en el último año (96,9%). Ninguna mujer se refirió al uso regular de preservativos antes del diagnóstico de VIH, siendo que, tras el diagnóstico, 62,5% pasaron a usar el insumo en todas las relaciones sexuales. Historia anterior de DST fue relatada por (40,6%), probable forma de transmisión del virus fue la vía sexual (93,8%) y el diagnóstico de la infección se realizó hace más de cinco años (56,3%) para la mayoría. La mayoría también hace uso de TARV (65,6%) y presentó recuento de células CD4 igual o mayor que 500 células/mL (59,4%), en el último examen realizado. Conclusiones: Hubo prevalencia de VPH de 15,6%, semejante a otros estudios. Se destaca la necesidad de examen de Papanicolaou periódico para detectar precozmente alteraciones, evitándose el cáncer cervical (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;15(44): 1-12, oct. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156577</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infección por el Virus del Papiloma Humano (VPH) en mujeres con VIH /SIDA</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2623^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2623^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55350^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35997^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55350^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55350^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35997^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
