<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86337</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Infective endocarditis in octogenarian patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Our aims were to investigate the clinical features and prognosis of endocarditis in octogenarian patients (aged&gt;79 years) and in comparison with those in younger elderly patients (aged 65-79 years) and young patients (aged&lt;65 years). Octogenarian subjects more frequently were male and had a community-acquired infection, mitral valve disease, and chronic anemia. Their clinical course was more insidious and benign: they presented less often with fever or new heart murmurs. When heart failure was present, it tended to be less severe. The most frequently isolated microorganisms were streptococci. The detection rate for vegetation on transesophageal echocardiography was lower in octogenarians. Octogenarians had shorter periods of hospitalization, needed surgery less frequently, and had lower mortality. Mortality in those undergoing surgery was not higher in elderly patients. Age was not an independent predictor of in-hospital mortality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Manchado, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Wolf, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarriá, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Revilla, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Román, José A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilacosta, Isidre</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Nuestro objetivo es valorar las manifestaciones clínicas y el pronóstico de la endocarditis en pacientes octogenarios (edad &gt; 79 años) comparándolos con ancianos de menor edad (65-79 años) y pacientes jóvenes (edad &lt; 65 años). Los octogenarios fueron con mayor frecuencia varones, con infección adquirida en la comunidad, afección mitral y anemia crónica. Su cuadro clínico fue más insidioso y benigno y tuvieron con menor frecuencia fiebre y nuevos soplos. En los casos de insuficiencia cardiaca, esta tendió a ser de menor gravedad. Los estreptococos fueron los microorganismos más frecuentemente aislados. La tasa de detección de vegetaciones mediante ecocardiografía transesofágica fue menor entre octogenarios. Los octogenarios tuvieron una estancia hospitalaria más corta, necesitaron cirugía con menos frecuencia y su mortalidad fue menor. La mortalidad en pacientes operados no fue mayor en los ancianos. La edad no fue factor predictor independiente de mortalidad intrahospitalaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;64(4): 329-333, abr. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86337</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Endocarditis infecciosa en pacientes octogenarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4777^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4777^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30047^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4777^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4777^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
