<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048442</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of a program of constructed training in Hipopressive Gymnastic on the vertebral cervical and dorsolumbar statics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Try to target the effects of a training of Gymnastic Hipopressive (GH) of 10 meetings on the statics of the dorsolumbar column. Material. Different instruments of measurement were used: plummet, metric tape; as well as a camera Nikon Coolpix 5200, which images were treated with the computer software "Image Tool". Methods. A double blind study, where the population were of the same age. Twenty nine students, divided in 2 groups: the first group was trained with GH for an hour a week during ten weeks, with standardization of the exercises; while the second one followed only a postural training. To all of them a series of test were realized before the study and also later: flexibility of the vertebral column, muscular extensibility and enclosed pose measurements static and dynamic; so that every parameter was compared statistically by means of the test Student-Newman-Keuls. Results. We have found significant variations in the group of study with regard to the controls: in the static of the spine (cervical arrow: p = 0.002; dorsal p = 0.0001; lumbar p = 0.006) in the position of the occipital axis (p = 0.04); as well as also in the measurements of flexibility of the column, above all, in the flexion of trunk parameters (p = 0.005). And also in the isometric strength of the expanding muscles: Sorensen-Biering test (p = 0.02). Conclusions. The GH has an effect on the statics of the dorsolumbar column and believe that these results are very encouraging and must be considered, nevertheless, the research must continue</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Snoeck, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fanzel, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caufriez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Mostrar los efectos de un entrenamiento de Gimnasia Abdominal Hipopresiva (1sesión semanal/10 semanas), sobre la estática de la columna dorsolumbar. Material. Se utilizaron como instrumentos de medición: plomada, cinta métrica; así como una cámara fotográfica Nikon Coolpix 5200, cuyas imágenes fueron tratadas por ordenador (software "Image Tool"). Métodos. Estudio simple ciego cuya población inicial fue de 29 estudiantes divididos en 2 grupos: al primero se le realizó un entrenamiento de 1 hora semanal durante 10 semanas de gimnasia abdominal hipopresiva, con estandarización de los ejercicios; y el segundo siguió sólo un entrenamiento postural. A todos se les realizó una serie de tests previos y posteriores al estudio: de flexibilidad de la columna vertebral, de extensibilidad muscular y mediciones posturales estáticas y dinámicas; de forma que cada parámetro fue comparado estadísticamente mediante el test Student-Newman-Keuls. Resultados. Hemos encontrado variaciones significativas en el grupo de estudio con respecto a los controles: en la estática vertebral (flecha cervical: p = 0,002; dorsal p = 0,0001; lumbar p = 0,006) en la posición del eje occipital (p = 0,04); y en las mediciones de flexibilidad de la columna, sobre todo en la flexión de tronco (p = 0,005). También hay un aumento de la fuerza isométrica de los músculos extensores del tronco: test de Sorensen-Biering (p = 0,02). Conclusiones. La gimnasia abdominal hipopresiva tiene incidencia en la estática de la columna dorsolumbar y creemos que estos resultados son muy alentadores y deben ser considerados; pero antes de poder ser aplicada con éxito en la reeducación dorsolumbar, debe proseguirse esta vía de investigación</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);28(4): 205-217, jul. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048442</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de un programa de entrenamiento estructurado de Gimnasia Abdominal Hipopresiva sobre la estática vertebral cervical y dorsolumbar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29507^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13505^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30961^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6324^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
