<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108871</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adherence to a mediterranean diet and its relantionship to body mass index in Galician university</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Mediterranean diet (MD) is probably one of the healthiest dietary patterns. This diet is characterised by a diet profile based foods typical of the Mediterranean region and in your lifestyle. The aim of this study was to determine the degree of adherence to the MD in the Galician university diet and their relationship the body mass index (BMI). The participants were students of University of Vigo. We measured the height and weight of each participant and BMI was calculated. To determine the adherence to the MD KidMed test was used. A total of 266 university participate (67.7% female and32.3% male) aged 18 to 25 years. Majority of students(79-83%) were normal weight, but we found a relatively large percentage of overweight children (18.6%) and low prevalence of obesity in both sexes (2,3%). The mean KidMed score was 6.35 ± 2.20 and these index did not differ between girls and boys. Only 33% of the participants had a high KidMed score. Underweight girls and normal weight boys presented the highest adherence. In conclusion, it was evidenced need to change the eating habits of this population towards healthier patterns (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montana, J. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cobas, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodriguez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La dieta Mediterránea (DM) es, probablemente, uno de los modelos dietéticos más saludables. Esta dieta se caracteriza por un perfil dietético basado en alimentos típicos de la región mediterránea y en su estilo de vida. El objetivo de este trabajo es conocer el grado de adhesión a la DM de la dieta de estudiantes universitarios gallegos y su relación con el índice de masa corporal(IMC). Los participantes fueron universitarios del Campus de Ourense. Se determinó el peso y la estatura de cada participante y se calculó el IMC. Para determinar el grado de adhesión a la DM se utilizó el test KidMed. Participaron 266 universitarios (67,7% mujeres y 32,3% hombres) de edades comprendidas entre18 y 25 años. La mayoría de los estudiantes eran normo peso(79-83%), aunque se encontró un porcentaje relativamente importante de chicos con sobrepeso(18,6%) y una baja prevalencia de obesidad, en ambos sexos. La puntuación media del KidMed fue de6,35±2,20 y éste índice no difiere significativamente entre chicas y chicos. Solo el 33% de los participantes presentaron una dieta de alta adhesión a la DM. Las chicas con bajo peso y los chicos normo peso fueron los que presentaron los porcentajes más elevados de dietas (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;32(3): 72-80, sept.-dic. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108871</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adherencia a la dieta mediterranea y su relación con el índice de masa corporal en universitarios de Galicia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37653^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5657</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
