<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112069</identifier>
<setSpec>2014-9832</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Design and development of clinical simulation scenarios: analysis of courses for anesthesiologists</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Simulation is integrating into the residency programs and for continuing medical education (CME). The aim of this article is identify and standardize the best practices to design and develop clinical simulation scenarios for training exercises. Materials and methods: We analyze the courses for Anesthesia and Critical Care performed in Valdecilla Virtual Hospital from September 2008 to June 2011. Results: A total of 104 scenarios were reviewed, related to 14 CME and 13 resident courses. The resultant phases followed to design, build and refine a clinical simulation scenario, and the criteria utilized to make the  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Maestre, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojo, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rábago, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sancho, Rodrigo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moral, Ignacio del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La simulación se está integrando en los programas docentes de los residentes y en la formación continuada de los especialistas. El objetivo de este artículo es identificar y estandarizar las mejores prácticas para diseñar e implementar un escenario de simulación clínica. Materiales y métodos: Se analizan los cursos realizados para la especialidad de Anestesiología y Reanimación en el Hospital Virtual Valdecilla durante el período septiembre 2008-junio 2011. Resultados: Se revisan un total de 104 escenarios correspondientes a 14 cursos de formación continuada de médicos especialistas, y 13 realizados para el programa de integración de la simulación clínica en el programa  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Fund. Educ. Méd. (Ed. impr.);16(1): 49-57, ene.-mar. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112069</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diseño y desarrollo de escenarios de simulación clínica: análisis de cursos para el entrenamiento de anestesiólogos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30213^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29901</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d787^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34600^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
