<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102952</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Emotional intelligence and engagement in San Camilo Centre workers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">For some time organizations are committed with health promotion and workers welfare. Under this concern this study has been conducted; the aim was to describe and analyse the existing associations between emotional intelligence and engagement variables. The population were 150 workers from San Camilo Centre. The assessment instruments used were the scale of Emotional Intelligence (EIE-33), the scale of Emotional Intelligence (EIE-25), the Trait Meta-Mood Scale (TMMS-25) and the questionnaire of Utrecht Work Engagement Scale (UWES). It is a descriptive correlational study. In San Camilo Centre workers there is association between emotional intelligence and engagement. Emotional intelligence, understood as the capacity to acquire skills or competencies for the adaptation to professional demands thus enhances a positive mental state work-related and this affects the quality of care and the assisted population health (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carabias Maza, M. Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermejo Higuera, José Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Martínez, M. Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villacieros Durbán, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Borrego, M. Aurora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Liébana Presa, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las organizaciones están comprometidas desde hace tiempo con la promoción de la salud y del bienestar de los trabajadores. Con este referente se realizó el presente estudio; el objetivo fue describir y analizar las asociaciones que existen entre las variables inteligencia emocional y engagement. La población fueron 150 trabajadores del Centro San Camilo. Los instrumentos de evaluación utilizados son la escala de Inteligencia Emocional (EIE-33), la escala de Inteligencia Emocional (EIE-25), el Trait Meta-Mood Scale (TMMS-24) y cuestionario de Utrecht Work Engagement Scale (UWES). Es un estudio descriptivo correlacional. En los trabajadores del Centro San Camilo existe asociación entre la inteligencia emocional y el engagement. Así la inteligencia emocional, entendida como la capacidad para adquirir habilidades o competencias para la adaptación de las demandas profesionales, potencia un estado mental positivo relacionado con el trabajo y ello repercute en la calidad asistencial y en la salud de la población atendida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);23(2): 63-68, Jun. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102952</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inteligencia emocional y vínculo laboral en trabajadores del Centro San Camilo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53742</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
