<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042568</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Satisfaction among hospitalized patients as an indicator of quality of care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To study general satisfaction among hospitalized patients and to evaluate their satisfaction with nursing care both during their hospital stay and after discharge. Method. We performed an observational, descriptive, prospective study at the Josep Trueta Hospital in Girona (Spain). Patient satisfaction was evaluated through the SGEM, CEP and LOPSS 12 scales. Results. We studied 150 patients with medical and surgical neurological diseases. A high level of satisfaction was expressed. Among the least valued aspects were physical space, catering, and the quality of information. No association was found between any of the sociodemographic variables and patient satisfaction. The most highly valued aspects were the quality of the care received (among the most dependent patients), the advice given (among patients who were university graduates), and technical procedures (among patients with complications). No significant differences were observed between satisfaction scores during hospitalization and scores measured after discharge. Conclusions. We highlight the need to improve communication with inpatients and the information given to them</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bertrán-Noguer, Carme</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suñer-Soler, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hortal-Gasull, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Algans-Coll, Lluisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baró-Ministral, Núria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pujiula-Masó, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grau-Martín, Armand</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estañol-Posas, Francesca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mascort, Zaida</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puigdemont-Guinart, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Estudiar la satisfacción general de los pacientes hospitalizados y su satisfacción con los cuidados de enfermería durante su estancia hospitalaria. Método. El diseño del presente estudio es observacional, descriptivo y prospectivo, desarrollado en el Hospital Universitario Dr. Josep Trueta de Girona en la unidad de neurología medicoquirúrgica. La satisfacción de los pacientes se ha valorado con las escalas de satisfacción SGEM, CEP y LOPPS 12. Resultados. Se han estudiado 150 pacientes con patología neurológica médica y quirúrgica, que han expresado altos niveles de satisfacción. Entre los aspectos peor valorados destacan la información, el espacio físico y la hostelería. No se ha hallado asociación entre ninguna variable sociodemográfica y la satisfacción de los pacientes. Los más dependientes valoraron más la calidad de los cuidados recibidos, los pacientes con estudios universitarios apreciaron más los consejos y los que presentaron alguna complicación valoraron más la asistencia técnica. Tampoco se observan diferencias significativas entre las puntuaciones de satisfacción realizadas en la hospitalización con las realizadas ya en el domicilio. Conclusiones. Se destaca la necesidad de mejorar la comunicación y la información con los pacientes hospitalizados</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);16(1): 19-26, ene. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042568</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La satisfacción de los pacientes hospitalizados como indicador de la calidad asistencial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32094^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9924^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
