<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98786</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-0559</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of the psychomotor aptitude and intelligence required in driving in the Drivers evaluation centres</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Goals, analysis of the aspects on intelligence and perceptive-motor aptitudes according to the Spanish Driver model test. Material and methods, through observation of the analysed variables of the applied norm since locomotion started in Spain and the current protocols of evaluation recommended by the Direction General of Traffic and The Ministry of Health. Conclusions, the considerated variables have served the preventive models of each time period, currently their goal is to attend the prevention needs of the current social habits. The evaluated aspects have hardly changed in the last few years. The evaluation system and data collection have being developed with the standardization of psycotechnical devices in 1988. Remaining unchanged until the present. The protocolized intervention is without question an effective system to determine the driving attitude (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz, M. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Civera, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montoro, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ozcoidi, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos, análisis de los aspectos considerados en la valoración de las aptitudes perceptivo-motoras y la inteligencia según el Modelo Español de reconocimiento de conductores. Material y Métodos, mediante la observación de variables analizadas en las normativas aplicadas desde que se inicia la locomoción en España y los protocolos actuales de valoración recomendados por la Dirección General de Tráfico y El Ministerio de Sanidad. Conclusiones, las variables consideradas han servido a los modelos preventivos de cada época, actualmente pretenden atender a las necesidades de prevención de los hábitos sociales actuales. Los aspectos valorados, apenas han sufrido variaciones, en los últimos años. El sistema de evaluación y registro de datos evolucionó con la normalización de los aparatos psicotécnicos en 1988, permaneciendo sin modificaciones hasta la actualidad. La actuación protocolizada es sin duda un sistema eficaz para determinar la actitud para conducir (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Interv. psicosoc;17(1): 23-32, ene.-abr. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98786</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración de la aptitud psicomotora y la inteligencia requerida para conducir en los Centros de Reconocimiento de Conductores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1339</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10662</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1340^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
