<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048772</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical, functional and quality of life differences in patients of different gender with essential tremor</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Essential tremor (ET) is a chronic disease with important variability in its clinical manifestation, discapacity and quality of life (QoL) affectation. As previous reports have described differences in clinical manifestations of ET according to gender, this study proposes to check its existence in the Spanish population and to detect the presence of discapacity or alterations in QoL between different gender.    Methods. Patients with ET attended in the neurology clinic of a sanitary area were evaluated in a prospective consecutive way. Their clinical characteristics were recorded and discapacity and QoL were assessed through the Fahn and Tolosa scale for ET and the SF-36 health questionnaire. Comparisons between groups of both genders have been established.    Results. 104 patients with ET were evaluated (46 males and 58 females). Clinically there were differences concerning the localization and type of tremor. Although the intensity and the presence of discapacity were similar in both genders, women showed a lower QoL compared to men in the «physical role» dimension.    Conclusions. There are differences in the clinical expression and in the affectation of QoL in patients with ET of different gender. Women had a lower score in the «physical role» dimension of QoL in comparison to their reference population, meaning lesser satisfaction with their performance capacity of their usual activities. QoL, thus, does not appear in this study as something only related with the degree of discapacity, but rather as having other determinant factors</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Navas Vinagre, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López del Val, L. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintana Riera, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Oriz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El temblor esencial (TE) es una enfermedad crónica con importante variabilidad respecto a sus manifestaciones clínicas, discapacidad y afectación de calidad de vida (CdV). Dado que estudios previos describen diferencias en las manifestaciones clínicas del TE según el sexo, se plantea este estudio para comprobar su existencia en población española y detectar la presencia de discapacidad o alteraciones en CdV en los diferentes sexos.    Métodos. Se han evaluado de forma prospectiva consecutiva pacientes con TE atendidos en las consultas de neurología de un área sanitaria, registrándose sus características clínicas y valorando discapacidad y CdV mediante la escala de TE de Fahn y Tolosa y el cuestionario de salud SF-36. Se han establecido comparaciones entre ambos sexos.    Resultados. Participaron 104 pacientes con TE (46 varones y 58 mujeres). Clínicamente hubo diferencias en cuanto a localización y tipo de temblor. Aunque la intensidad del temblor y la presencia de discapacidad fue similar en ambos sexos, las mujeres manifestaron menor CdV respecto a los hombres en la dimensión de «rol físico».    Conclusiones. Existen diferencias en la expresión clínica y en la afectación de CdV de pacientes con TE de diferentes sexos. Las mujeres presentaron menos puntuación en la dimensión «rol físico» de CdV respecto a su población de referencia, indicando un menor grado de satisfacción con la capacidad de realización de sus actividades habituales. La CdV, por tanto, no aparece en este estudio como un aspecto relacionado solamente con el grado de discapacidad, sino que puede tener otros factores determinantes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;21(2): 60-67, mar. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048772</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias clínicas, funcionales y de calidad de vida en pacientes con temblor esencial de ambos sexos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34288^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34288^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d212</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
