<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132467</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Amelanotic anorectal melanoma metastatic to the thyroid gland. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Despite its rich vascular supply, metastases to the thyroid gland are rare. Renal, colorectal, lung and breast carcinomas are the most frequent sources of metastases. We report the case of a 75-year-old woman who presented with a rapid nodular enlargement of the thyroid gland, for which she underwent a partial thyroidectomy. She had a history of advanced amelanotic anorectal melanoma surgically treated one year previously. Histopathologically, the thyroid lobe showed diffuse infiltration by an amelanotic melanoma. Although a few cases of metastases of melanoma to the thyroid gland have been reported, the majority are derived from a cutaneous primary; to the best of our knowledge, this is the first reported case of an anorectal melanoma with metastasis to the thyroid gland (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gonzales Jordán, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Klock, Clovis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paulo Barbieri-Cella, Rudinei</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rehbein, Paulo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rigatti, Rosie Augusta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Faturi, Daliane</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A pesar de su rico aporte vascular, las metástasis en la glándula tiroides son eventos raros. Los carcinomas renales, colorectales, de pulmón y mama son las fuentes más frecuentes de metástasis. Presentamos el caso de una mujer de 75 años de edad, con el antecedente de un melanoma anorrectal amelanótico avanzado, operado un año antes, que se presentó con un crecimiento nodular rápido de la glándula tiroides, por lo que fue sometida a una tiroidectomía parcial. Histopatológicamente, el lóbulo tiroideo mostró una infiltración difusa por melanoma amelánico. Aunque se han publicado algunos casos de metástasis de melanoma en la glándula tiroides, la mayoría de ellos son de origen cutáneo por lo que, a nuestro entender, nosotros presentamos el primer caso de un melanoma anorrectal con metástasis a la glándula tiroide (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;48(1): 48-51, ene.-mar. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132467</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Un melanoma amelanótico con metástasis a la glándula tiroides. Descripción clinico-patológica de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3267^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3267^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22696^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14353^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31313^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31313^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31313^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14349^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22696^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
