<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84412</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reconstruction of the anterior cruciate ligament</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The current techniques for reconstruction of the anterior cruciate ligament restore normal knee function, reduce the risk of gonarthrosis, and offer satisfactory clinical results in over 90% of all cases. The technique used exerts a decisive influence upon the success of treatment, which in turn is intimately linked to biological graft response. Most failures are due to error in performing the tunnels or in fixing plasty. Careful evaluation of patients who are dissatisfied despite a perfectly executed technique should contribute to improve this surgery even further, in order to more closely reproduce the biomechanics of the native anterior cruciate ligament (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Forriol Campos, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo Haro, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero Martín, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las técnicas actuales de reconstrucción del ligamento cruzado anterior restauran la función normal de la rodilla, disminuyen el riesgo de gonartrosis y presentan resultados clínicos satisfactorios en más de un 90% de los casos. La técnica influye de forma decisiva en el éxito, estando íntimamente relacionada con la respuesta biológica del injerto. Los fracasos en su mayoría se deben a errores en la realización de los túneles o la fijación de la plastia. El estudio detenido de los pacientes insatisfechos a pesar de una técnica impecable nos debe de llevar a mejorar aún esta cirugía en un futuro para acercarnos más a la biomecánica del LCA nativo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);19(supl.1): 22-38, 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84412</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reconstrucción del ligamento cruzado anterior</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28861^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33759^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7893^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33759^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5727^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10162^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10162^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28861^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5727^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32668^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1721^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1721^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28861^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7893^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200800</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
