<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149276</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-1342</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of reduced visual acuity on precision of two-dimensional tracing movements</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: We intended to assess consequences of reduced visual acuity for performance in a natural simple motor task (tracing) using objective kinematic performance measures. Specifically, we intended to elucidate the kind of relationship between the task performance and best corrected binocular visual acuity and to determine the threshold of visual acuity when task performance starts to deteriorate. Methods: Ninety-five individuals with different best corrected visual acuity participated in the study (age 49±12 years, mean±SD, 27 men and 68 women). The participants manually traced maze-like visual patterns of different spatial complexity presented on the screen of a portable notebook computer using Clinical Kinematic Assessment Tool software. Tracing error was computed as performance measure in each trial with a spatial pattern matching technique &#150; rigid point set registration method. Results: The segmented linear regression analysis showed that the relation between visual acuity and tracing errors was best described with a regression function having a break point between two data segments. Tracing performance was unaffected by values of visual acuity below 0.2 on logMAR scale, but when logMAR values increased above this critical limit (i.e. when visual acuity is further reduced), tracing errors linearly increased. The rate of the increase of the tracing error correlated with the complexity of visual stimulus shape. Conclusion: Testing of fine motor functions with objective kinematic measures during visuomotor tasks may help differentiating between actual effects of reduced visual acuity on eye&#150;hand coordination in individuals with similar levels of impairment of visual acuity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zetterlund, Christina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Richter, Hans O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domkin, Dmitry</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lundqvist, Lars-Olov</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Tratamos de evaluar las consecuencias de la reducción de la agudeza visual sobre el desempeño de una tarea motora simple y natural (trazado) utilizando mediciones cinemáticas y objetivas del desempeño. De manera específica, tratamos de esclarecer el tipo de relación entre el desempeño de la tarea y la agudeza visual binocular mejor corregida, así como determinar el umbral de la agudeza visual a partir del cual el desempeño de la tarea comienza a deteriorarse. Métodos: Participaron en el estudio noventa y cinco personas con diferente agudeza visual mejor corregida (edad 49±12 años, media±DE, 27 hombres y 68 mujeres). Los participantes trazaron manualmente patrones visuales de tipo laberíntico de diferente complejidad espacial, presentados en la pantalla de un ordenador portátil utilizando el software Clinical Kinematic Assessment Tool. El error de trazado se computó como medición del desempeño en cada ensayo, con una técnica de correspondencia del patrón espacial: el método de registro del conjunto de puntos rígidos. Resultados: El análisis de la regresión lineal segmentada reflejó que la relación entre la agudeza visual y los errores de trazado se describía mejor con una función de regresión con un punto de ruptura entre los dos segmentos de datos. El desempeño del trazado no se vio afectado por valores de agudeza visual inferiores a 0,2 en una escala logMAR (superior a 0,63 en una escala decimal), pero cuando los valores de logMAR superaban este límite crítico (es decir, cuando la agudeza visual empeoraba aún más), los errores de trazado se incrementaban de modo lineal. La tasa de incremento del error de trazado se correlacionó con la complejidad de la forma del estímulo visual. Conclusión: Las técnicas de medición objetiva del desempeño motor durante las tareas visomotoras en personas con diferente agudeza visual pueden aportar un punto de corte ecológicamente válido y preciso para la definición de la discapacidad debida a la disfunción visual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>J. optom. (Internet);9(2): 93-101, abr.-jun. 2016. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149276</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de la reducción de la agudeza visual sobre la precisión de los movimientos bidimensionales de trazado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10660^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15197^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12452^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24366^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9241</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
