<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-28239</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Williams syndrome: memory. visuospatial and visuoconstructive functions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Williams syndrome (WS) is a dominant autosomal genetic syndrome resulting from a microdeletion on chromosome 7. This deletion gives rise to certain characteristic physical traits, systemic pathologies and a cognitivebehavioural pattern that is characterised by the relative preservation of linguistic abilities with very striking visuospatial deficits. Case reports. We describe the neuropsychological features of three patients with WS, diagnosed by means of a cytogenetic study, and their mnemonic functions and visuospatial skills are explored. Conclusions. The results obtained in the study of these three patients reinforce the idea, already acknowledged in the literature, of the marked visuospatial difficulties. They also account for the need for an early diagnosis and an extensive knowledge of the cognitive profile of these patients so as to allow the planning of a stimulation that strengthens the cognitive possibilities of children suffering from this syndrome as much as possible (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El síndrome de Williams (SW) es un síndrome genético autosómico dominante, resultado de una microdeleción del cromosoma 7. Esta deleción da lugar a unos rasgos físicos característicos, una patología sistémica y un patrón cognitivoconductual que se caracteriza por una relativa preservación de las habilidades lingüísticas con unos déficit visuoespaciales muy marcados. Casos clínicos. Se describen las características neuropsicológicas de tres pacientes con SW diagnosticados mediante estudio citogenético. Se exploran sus funciones de memoria y sus habilidades visuoespaciales. Conclusiones. Los resultados obtenidos en el estudio de estos tres pacientes apoyan la idea, reconocida en la literatura, de las marcadas dificultades visuoespaciales, y justifican la necesidad de un diagnóstico precoz y de un conocimiento a fondo del perfil cognitivo de estos pacientes, con el fin de planificar una estimulación que potencie al máximo las posibilidades cognitivas de los niños que padecen este síndrome (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;37(9): 826-830, nov. 2003. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Williams: memoria, funciones visuoespaciales y funciones visuoconstructivas</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Rigau Ratera, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estévez González, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Artigas Pallarés, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Sánchez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Nonell, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-28239</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d13420</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32574</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200311</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
