<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138507</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Age, period, and cohort effects on mortality from ischemic heart disease in southern Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives:  Ischemic heart disease is the leading cause of death and one of the top 4 causes of burden of disease worldwide. The aim of this study was to evaluate age-period-cohort effects on mortality from ischemic heart disease in Andalusia (southern Spain) and in each of its 8 provinces during the period 1981-2008. Methods: A population-based ecological study was conducted. In all, 145 539 deaths from ischemic heart disease were analyzed for individuals aged between 30 and 84 years who died in Andalusia in the study period. A nonlinear regression model was estimated for each sex and geographical area using spline functions. Results: There was an upward trend in male and female mortality rate by age from the age of 30 years. The risk of death for men and women showed a downward trend for cohorts born after 1920, decreasing after 1960 with a steep slope among men. Analysis of the period effect showed that male and female death risk first remained steady from 1981 to 1990 and then increased between 1990 and 2000, only to decrease again until 2008. Conclusions: There were similar age-period-cohort effects on mortality in all the provinces of Andalusia and for Andalusia as a whole. If the observed cohort and period effects persist, male and female mortality from ischemic heart disease will continue to decline (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mayoral-Cortés, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Olmedo, Piedad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco-Reina, Encarnación</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Ajuria, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ocaña-Riola, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Cantalejo, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: La cardiopatía isquémica es la primera causa de muerte y una de las cuatro principales causas de carga de enfermedad en el mundo. El objetivo de este trabajo es evaluar los efectos edad-periodo-cohorte la mortalidad por cardiopatía isquémica en Andalucía (sur de España) y en cada una de sus provincias durante el periodo 1981-2008. Métodos: Se realizó un estudio ecológico poblacional. Se analizaron las 145.539 defunciones por cardiopatía isquémica ocurridas en Andalucía durante el periodo de estudio a edades comprendidas entre 30 y 84 años. Se estimó un modelo de regresión no lineal con funciones spline para cada sexo y área geográfica. Resultados: En la tasa de mortalidad masculina y femenina a partir de 30 años de edad se observa tendencia a aumentar. El riesgo de muerte para varones y mujeres fue descendiente para las cohortes nacidas después de 1920 y con una pendiente más pronunciada después de 1960 entre los varones. El análisis del efecto periodo mostró que el riesgo de mortalidad masculina y femenina se mantuvo estable desde 1981 hasta 1990, aumentó entre 1990 y 2000 y volvió a disminuir desde 2000 hasta 2008. Conclusiones: Los efectos edad-periodo-cohorte en la mortalidad fueron similares en todas las provincias de Andalucía y el conjunto de la comunidad autónoma. Si los efectos cohorte y periodo persisten, la mortalidad masculina y femenina por enfermedad isquémica cardiaca continuará disminuyendo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;68(5): 373-381, mayo 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138507</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de la edad, el periodo de defunción y la cohorte de nacimiento en la mortalidad por enfermedad isquémica del corazón en el sur de España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28637</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
