<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055547</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Caring with laughs and good humour</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Laughing and health are two concepts historically thought to be interrelated. Science is demonstrating that good humour and laughing can be very positive elements:    laughing is healthy for our physical, psychological social and spiritual health. The aim of this article is to present a retrospective examination on the origin and    evolution of &#147;laughter therapy&#148; and to present the available scientific evidence on the effects of laughing, with a description its indications. A second aim is to describe how laughing and good humour could become a part of nursing care. In our setting, the application of laughing and good hum or must be carried out in an    intelligent manner and at the right time, creating a beneficial framework for the therapeutic relationship and constituting a powerful therapeutic tool that reinforces other forms of therapy. Given the closeness established between patient and nurse, it is the nurse who holds the key for the implementation of this therapeutic modality</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Medina, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Risa y salud son dos conceptos sobre los que históricamente se intuye relación. La ciencia está demostrando que el humor y la risa pueden ser elementos muy positivos: reír es saludable para la salud física, psicológica, social y espiritual. El presente artículo tiene como propósito hacer una recorrido sobre el origen y la evolución de la risoterapia, así como sobre la evidencia científica en torno a los efectos de la risa, para pasar a exponer sus indicaciones y por último cómo la risa y el humor podrían formar parte de los cuidados enfermeros. En nuestro ámbito, la aplicación de la risa y el humor se debe hacer de forma inteligente y en el momento adecuado, creando un marco beneficioso para la relación terapéutica y siendo a su vez una poderosa modalidad terapéutica que ayuda a otras formas de terapia. Por nuestra cercanía con el paciente, es la enfermera la pieza clave para su uso</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;10(3): 26-30, abr. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055547</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuidar con risa y humor. Cuidar con risa y humor</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d36277^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8024^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
