<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143249</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reversion of oral anticoagulation in emergency surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bleeding is the most serious adverse effect of oral anticoagulants. Emergency surgery requires the rapid reversion of coagulation disorder though the use of such products as prothrombin complex, vitamin K, or activated recombinant factor VII. We analyze the cases of 5 patients on oral anticoagulants (vitamin K antagonists) who required emergency surgery in our hospital in the past year. We describe patient characteristics, laboratory findings before and after correction of anticoagulant effects, preoperative treatment of coagulation disorder, surgical interventions, and outcomes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gomez Ara, Ana Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valenzuela Martinez, Maria Jose</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martinez Ubieto, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz Lopez, Ana Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hemorragia es el efecto adverso mas grave secundario al tratamiento con anticoagulantes. Es necesario revertir rápidamente la anticoagulacion en enfermos que van a ser intervenidos de urgencia. Para la reversion se utilizan productos como complejo protrombinico, vitamina K y factor VII activado recombinante. En el ultimo ano, en nuestro hospital han sido intervenidos cinco pacientes que necesitaban una cirugia urgente y estaban en tratamiento con anticoagulantes orales (antagonistas de la vitamina K). Presentamos sus datos demograficos, la analitica antes y despuesde corregir los efectos anticoagulantes, el tratamiento preoperatorio de la anticoagulacion, las intervenciones quirúrgicas y los resultados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);27(5): 316-318, oct. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143249</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reversión de la anticoagulación oral en cirugía de urgencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28875^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22270^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
