<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126899</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-9895</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Dermatofibrosarcoma protuberans (DFSP) is a neoplasm of soft tissue of intermediate malignancy, initially localized in the skin developing in the deep layers of skin. Clinically it is characterized by its presentation as a nodule or indurated plaque on the trunk and proximal extremities.Initial treatment is local surgical excision, and an inadequate surgical removal is themayor risk for recurrence. There are few reports of metastases described in the literature; the lung is the most common site of metastasis. Immunohistochemical study is characterized by the expression of vimentin and CD34, and by a reciprocal chromosomal translocation, t(17;22). The treatment is a complete surgical excision, followed by radiotherapy and chemotherapy in advanced cases. Therefore, although metastases are extremely rare, the presence of a lung mass should be included in the differential diagnosis of a patient with a history of DFSP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Arévalo, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Punter, R. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Castillo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Pérez, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Riolobos, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Espinosa, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El dermatofibrosarcoma protuberans (DFSP) es una neoplasia de partes blandas de malignidad intermedia localizada inicialmente en la piel, desde donde invade tejidos más profundos. Clínicamente se caracteriza por su presentación como un nódulo o placa indurada en tronco o extremidades. El tratamiento inicial es la extirpación quirúrgica local, siendo el factor de mal pronóstico más reconocido una extirpación quirúrgica inadecuada. Hay pocos casos de metástasis descritos en la literatura siendo la localización pulmonar la más frecuente. El estudio inmunohistoquímico se caracteriza por la expresión de vimentina y CD34, y el estudio genético-molecular por la presencia de translocación de cromosomas 17 y 22. El tratamiento de elección es la extirpación quirúrgica completa, seguida de radioterapia y quimioterapia en los casos avanzados. Por tanto, aunque las metástasis son extremadamente raras, la presencia de una masa pulmonar debe incluirse en el diagnóstico diferencial de un paciente con antecedentes de un DFSP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. patol. respir;17(3): 98-100, jul.-sept. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126899</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dermatofibrosarcoma protuberans metastásico: una causa poco frecuente de masa pulmonar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32848^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15150^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14570^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31514^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
