<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133161</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Does the family of origin influence unplanned pregnancy in teenagers and young adults?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine whether there is a relationship between family characteristics and unplanned pregnancy in women under 25 years old. Subjects and Methods. A descriptive, cross-sectional study was performed in 583 young persons (13-24 years old) treated in 2012 in the Contraceptive Office for Young People. Bivariate analysis, chi-squared test, odds ratio and multivariate analysis were performed through binary logistic regression. Results. Of the 583 participants, 174 (29.8%) had an unplanned pregnancy. The risk was higher if the father was unemployed [OR: 3.569 (95% CI 1.669-7.630)], if the family structure differed for parents and siblings [OR: 3.022 (95% CI 1.447-6.311)], if the mother had had a child during adolescence [OR: 2.815 (95% CI 1.115-3.397)] and if there were problems in the household [OR: 1.946 (95% CI 1.115-3.397)]. Discussion. To improve unplanned pregnancy rates among young women, it is important to consider the influence of the family environment and the socio-economic level of families and to detect and attend to problems in the household (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Yago Simón, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomás Aznar, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Conocer las características familiares relacionadas con el embarazo no planificado en mujeres jóvenes. Sujetos y métodos. Estudio descriptivo, transversal. Jóvenes atendidas durante el año 2012, en Consulta Joven de Anticoncepción, 583 jóvenes (13-24 años). Análisis bivariante, pruebas de la chi al cuadrado, odds ratio y multivariante, mediante regresión logística. Resultados. De 583 jóvenes, 174 (29,8%) tuvieron embarazo no planificado. El riesgo aumentó si el padre no trabajaba (OR: 3,569 [IC del 95%, 1,669-7,630]), si la estructura familiar era diferente de padres y hermanos (OR: 3,022 [IC del 95%, 1,447-6,311]), si su madre había sido madre en la adolescencia (OR: 2,815 [IC del 95%, 1,115-3,397]) y si tenían problemas de convivencia (OR: 1,946 [IC del 95%, 1,115-3,397]). Discusión. Para mejorar los índices de embarazos no planificados entre las jóvenes, hay que considerar la influencia del entorno familiar, el nivel socioeconómico de las familias y detectar y atender problemas de convivencia familiar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);58(3): 118-124, mar. 2015. `btab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133161</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Influye la familia de origen en el embarazo no planificado de adolescentes y jóvenes?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11709^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23905^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11695^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11695^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38863^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
