<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121222</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perioperative management of atrial fibrillation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Atrial fibrillation is a frequent complication in the perioperative period. When it appears there is an increased risk of perioperative morbidity due to stroke, thromboembolism, cardiac arrest, myocardial infarction, anticoagulation haemorrhage, and hospital readmissions. The current article focuses on the recommendations for the management of perioperative atrial fibrillation based on the latest Clinical Practice Guidelines on atrial fibrillation by the European Society of Cardiology and the Spanish Society of Cardiology. This article pays special attention to the preoperative management, as well as to the acute perioperative episode. For this reason, the latest recommendations for the control of cardiac frequency, antiarrhythmic treatment and anticoagulation are included (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arguis, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Regueiro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matute, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galán, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabaté, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gomar, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fita, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sierra, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rovira, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arbelo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mont, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roux, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La fibrilación auricular es una complicación frecuente en el periodo perioperatorio, y cuando aparece se incrementa el riesgo de morbimortalidad perioperatoria debido a ACV, tromboembolismo, fallo cardiaco, IAM, hemorragia debida a anticoagulación y reingresos hospitalarios. En el presente artículo se recogen las recomendaciones para el manejo de la fibrilación auricular perioperatoria basándose en las últimas Guías de Práctica Clínica de la fibrilación auricular publicadas por la Sociedad Europea de Cardiología y la Sociedad Española de Cardiología, prestando atención tanto a su optimización preoperatoria, como al manejo del episodio agudo perioperatorio. En este sentido se incluyen las últimas recomendaciones para control de la frecuencia cardiaca, control del ritmo y anticoagulación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;61(5): 262-271, mayo 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121222</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo perioperatorio de la fibrilación auricular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54247^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54247^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d902^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
