<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138543</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Drug prescriptions study in the outpatient setting: assessment of off-label uses in children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to evaluate the prescription profile and to assess the off-label and unlicensed uses of medicines among non-hospitalised pediatric patients. Design: cross-sectional study. Setting: pediatric units in two urban health centers and general emergency room (Hospital Materno-Infantil, Málaga). Main measurements: sociodemographics variables, reasons for consultation and information about therapeutic medications. The classification of prescriptions was established according to information requirements contained in the Summary of Products Characteristics (SPC). Results: A total of 388 children were included (a subsample of 105 treated in the emergency room). Four hundred sixty-two prescriptions (involving 74 different active ingredients) were evaluated. Each infant received and average of 1,7 drugs (95% CI: 1,6-1,9). The most prescribed medicines were ibuprofen, paracetamol, amoxicillin-clavulanate and budesonide. The therapeutic group with the greatest variety of drugs was the respiratory group. 27,4% (95% CI: 23,5-31) of prescriptions were off-label and the main cause was different age (60%; 95% CI: 54,1-63), followed by different dose (21,5%; 95% CI: 18-25), different indication (12%; 95% CI: 9,2-15) and different route of administration (7%; 95% CI: 5,4-10). Conclusions: The rate of off-label uses presents intermediate figures. Around one third of the paediatric outpatients in our sample are exposed to at least one off-label or unlicensed prescription. We should, however, point out that such usage is based on scant official, quality information, although it is not necessarily incorrect. Evidence-based medicine should be encouraged to improve drug therapy in children, as well as following the rules on drugs in special situations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blanco-Reina, Encarnación</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega-Jiménez, M. Auxiliadora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ocaña-Riola, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez-Romero, Elisa Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bellido-Estévez, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar el perfil de prescripción y los usos off-label (fuera de ficha técnica [FT]) y unlicensed(medicamentos no autorizados específicamente para niños) de medicamentos a nivel ambulatorio. Diseño: Estudio transversal. Emplazamiento: Consultas de pediatría de 2 centros de salud urbanos y sala de urgencia general del Hospital Materno-Infantil de Málaga. Participantes: Niños de 0-14 años que acudiesen a consulta y se les prescribiese al menos un medicamento. Mediciones principales: Variables sociodemográficas, motivo de consulta y medicación. Clasificación de las prescripciones según información contenida en FT. Resultados: Se incluyeron un total de 388 niños, una submuestra de 105 (27%) atendidos en urgencias, y se valoraron 462 prescripciones, que involucraron 74 principios activos diferentes. Cada niño recibió un promedio de 1,7 fármacos (IC 95%: 1,6-1,9), siendo los más prescritos ibuprofeno, paracetamol, amoxicilina-clavulánico y budesonida. El grupo terapéutico más empleado y con mayor variedad de fármacos fue el respiratorio. El 27,4% de las prescripciones (IC 95%: 23,5-31) fueron off-label, constituyéndose como causa más frecuente el uso del fármaco para una edad distinta de la autorizada (60%; IC 95%: 54,1-63), seguida de distinta dosis (21,5%; IC 95%: 18-25), diferente indicación (12%; IC 95%: 9,2-15) y el 7% por distinta vía de administración (IC 95%: 5,4-10). Conclusiones: La tasa de usos off-label presenta cifras intermedias, pudiendo recibir este tipo de prescripciones una tercera parte de los niños. Esto no significa que sean prescripciones incorrectas, pero es recomendable respaldarlas con la mejor evidencia, así como seguir las directrices de la normativa sobre medicamentos en situaciones especiales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;47(6): 344-350, jun.-jul. 2015. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138543</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de las prescripciones farmacológicas en niños a nivel de atención primaria: evaluación de los usos off-label o fuera de ficha técnica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53689</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11742</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2700</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28462</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
