<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143849</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Glycemic and lipid metabolic disorders in diabetic and non-diabetic patients bmi &lt; 35 or &gt; 35 before gastric bypass</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Obesity and diabetes are diseases with high prevalence worldwide. There is currently no effective medical treatment for combat the weight gain. It is precursor of diseases such as diabetes or metabolic syndrome. It is necessary to know if weight gain has cumulative effects on the glycemic and lipid metabolism as precursors of complications or comorbidities. Patients and methods: We studied 131 patients (78 nondiabetic and 53 diabetic), 37 BMI &amp;#8804; 35 (3 BMI &lt; 25, 18 BMI 25-29.9, 16 BMI 30-34.9) and 94 BMI &amp;#8805; 35 (81 BMI 35-49.9 and 13 BMI &amp;#8805; 50).We analyzed BMI, gender, diabetes and the time of evolution. Lipid profile, glucose, HbA1c and C-peptide evaluated after 12-hour fasting. Results: Diabetic and diabese patients showed high triglycerides. Non-diabetics have impaired glucose (58% BMI &lt; 35 and 36% BMI &gt; 35). The 20% of non-diabetics BMI &lt; 35 had high C-peptide, and 19% of BMI &gt; 35 had high levels. The 5% of diabetics BMI &lt; 35 had low Cpeptide and 36% of BMI &gt; 35 had high levels. HbA1c was higher in 40% of non-diabetic patients BMI &lt; 35 compared to 13% BMI &gt; 35. Conclusions: Glucose and triglycerides increase with age and years of development of T2DM. Age of 51 and more, and men are more affected. The weight increase has cumulative effect by altering the metabolism favoring the onset of diabetes and comorbidities. Despite having intensive control treatment of diabetes, it continues its deleterious effects on patients through the years (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Toval-Mata, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyes-Ortiz, Alexander</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Moreno, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garciacaballero, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La obesidad y la diabetes son enfermedades de alta prevalencia a nivel mundial. Actualmente no existe un tratamiento médico eficaz para combatir el aumento de peso. La obesidad es precursora de enfermedades tales como la diabetes o el síndrome metabólico. Es necesario saber si el aumento de peso tiene efectos acumulativos sobre el metabolismo de la glucemia y los lípidos como precursores de complicaciones o comorbilidades. Pacientes y métodos: Se estudiaron 131 pacientes (78 no diabéticos y 53 diabéticos), 37 IMC &amp;#8804; 35 (3 IMC &lt; 25, 18 IMC 25-29,9, 16 IMC 30-34,9) y 94 IMC &amp;#8805; 35 (81 IMC 35- 49,9 y 13 de IMC &amp;#8805; 50). Se analizó el IMC, el género, la diabetes y su tiempo de evolución. El perfil lipídico, glucosa, HbA1c y el péptido C fueron evaluados después de un ayuno de 12 horas. Resultados: Los pacientes diabéticos y diabesos mostraron niveles altos de triglicéridos. Los pacientes no diabéticos tienen alteración de la glucosa (58% IMC 35). El 20% de los no diabéticos IMC 35 tenían niveles altos. El 5% de los diabéticos IMC &lt; 35 tenía bajos niveles de péptido C y 36% de IMC &gt; 35 tenían niveles altos. HbA1c fue mayor en 40% de pacientes no diabéticos IMC &lt; 35 frente al 13% de IMC &gt; 35. Conclusiones: La glucosa y los triglicéridos aumentan con la edad y los años de evolución de la DMT2. La edad de &amp;#8805;51 años y los hombres son los más afectados. El aumento de peso tiene efecto acumulativo alterando el metabolismo favoreciendo la aparición de la diabetes y sus comorbilidades. A pesar de tener un tratamiento de control intensivo de la diabetes, esta continúa con sus efectos nocivos sobre los pacientes a través de los años (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;29(5): 1095-1102, mayo 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143849</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos del metabolismo glicémico y lipídico en pacientes diabéticos y no diabéticos con imc &lt; 35 ó &gt; 35 antes de bypass gástrico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52151^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53702</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23640^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38060^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
