<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84161</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Development of a self-report instrument to measure disability in mobility activities (DIMA)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To develop a questionnaire to measure perception for disability in International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health (ICF) subdomains of mobility activities, that can be used in outpatients with musculoskeletal problems. Material and methods: The questionnaire was developed by a three-step process involving a 718 outpatients with musculoskeletal problems from three physiotherapy setting and 24 experts in disability issues. The item-generation process utilized input from relevant literature, experts and outpatients. Initial item reduction utilized researchers and the same experts and outpatients. Final item reduction was achieved by FA and tests for unidimensionalidad of identified factors. Results: The final questionnaire, called DIAM, is a 22-item self-administered questionnaire with five response categories. Results of AF provided two unidimensional factors in subdomain «Changing and maintaining body position » (1. Involving the standing; 2. Involving only sitting and/or lying down position), two in subdomain «Carrying, moving and handling objects» (1. Using hand and shoulder; 2. Using hand and/or forearm), and one factor in subdomain «Walking and moving» (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jimeno-Serrano, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baño-Aledo, M. E. del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrios Coines, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina- Mirapeix, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliveira-Sousa, S. L. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sobral Ferreira, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escolar-Reina, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro-Pujalte, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Arnaldos, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montilla-Herrador, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Desarrollar un instrumento basado en el auto-informe para medir la discapacidad en cada uno de los subdominios de las actividades de movilidad de la Clasificación internacional del Funcionamiento, de la Discapacidad y de la Salud (CIF), que pueda ser usado en pacientes ambulatorios con problemas musculoesqueléticos. Material y métodos: El cuestionario se desarrolló en tres etapas implicando a 718 pacientes ambulatorios con problemas musculoesqueléticos de tres centros con Fisioterapia, y a 24 expertos en discapacidad. El proceso de generación de ítems utilizó aportaciones de literatura relevante, expertos y pacientes. La reducción inicial se logró con las aportaciones de investigadores, expertos y pacientes. La reducción final se realizó usando análisis factoriales (AF) y pruebas de comprobación de la unidimensionalidad de cada factor identificado. Resultados: Se obtuvo un cuestionario (DIAM) de 22 ítems con cinco opciones de respuesta. Los resultados de los AF produjeron dos factores unidimensionales en el subdominio «cambiar y mantener la posición del cuerpo» (1. Implicando bipedestación; 2. Implicando sólo sedestación y/o decúbito), dos en el subdominio «llevar, mover y usar objetos» (1. Usando la mano y el hombro; 2. Usando la mano y/o antebrazo), y un factor en el subdominio «andar y moverse» (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);20(3): 184-193, jul.-sept. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84161</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desarrollo de un instrumento basado en el auto-informe del paciente para medir la Discapacidad en las Actividades de Movilidad (DIAM)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29507^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30935^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36319</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28397</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50525</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30935^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
