<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162526</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The role of chemotherapy in advanced oral cavity cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To evaluate the role of chemotherapy in advanced cancer of the oral cavity by assessing its influence on the survival of patients receiving palliative care and its ability to improve the expectations of curative surgery. Patients and method. Ninety-nine consecutive patients were analyzed to assess their course, the prognostic factors for tumour progression, and overall survival after treatment with two different chemotherapy regimes: cisplatin plus bleomycin (n=45) or cisplatin plus 5-fluorouracil (n=52). For the analysis, patients were split into groups depending on the treatment intention: palliative (n=41) or neo-adjuvant (n=56). Results. The response rate was 56.7%. The response was greater in the neo-adjuvant group (73.2%) than among the palliative patients (36.6%) (P &lt;0 001 greater with the bleomycin regime 73 3 than 5-fluorouracil 44 2 P=0.003); and greater in patients with stage III (77.8%) than stage IV (50%) ( P=0.021). Survival was higher among patients receiving bleomycin than in those on 5-fluorouracil (P=0.019) and among those with stage III than stage IV (P=0.013). In the palliative treatment group, the response was associated with greater survival (P &lt;0 001). In the neo-adjuvant group, 30 patients (53.6%) underwent surgery, with complete resection in 26 of them (86.7%). Sixteen cases (61.5%) presented recurrence. Chemotherapy response was not associated with operability. Survival was higher in the group with complete tumour resection (P &lt;0 041). Conclusions. The response to chemotherapy in oral cavity tumours was greater in patients with stage III and in those receiving bleomycin. Chemotherapy may improve survival in palliative cases. In neo-adjuvant cases, no great influence was seen in the conversion of doubtful cases into candidates for surgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grau, Juan J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casellas, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanch, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernal-Sprekelsen, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Valorar el papel de la quimioterapia en el cáncer avanzado de cavidad oral valorando su influencia en la supervivencia de los pacientes considerados como paliativos y su capacidad para mejorar las expectativas de cirugía curativa. Pacientes y método: Noventa y nueve pacientes consecutivos fueron analizados para valorar su evolución, los factores pronósticos de la progresión del tumor y la supervivencia global después del tratamiento con dos regímenes diferentes de quimioterapia: cisplatino más bleomicina (BLM) (n ¼ 45) o más 5-fluorouracilo (5-FU) (n ¼ 52). El análisis se realizó dividiendo los pacientes de acuerdo con la finalidad del tratamiento: paliativo (n ¼ 41) o neoadyuvante (n ¼ 56). Resultados: La tasa de respuesta fue del 56,7%. La respuesta fue mayor en el grupo neoadyuvante (73,2%) que en el grupo paliativo (36,6%) (po 0,001), mayor con el régimen de BLM (73,3%) que con 5-FU (44,2%) (p ¼ 0,003) y mayor en pacientes con estadio III (77,8%) que IV (50%) (p ¼ 0,021). La supervivencia fue mayor en pacientes que recibieron BLM que en los que recibieron 5-FU (p ¼ 0,019) y en el estadio III que en el IV (p ¼ 0,013). En el grupo paliativo, la respuesta se asoció a una mayor supervivencia (po0,001). En el grupo neoadyuvante, 30 pacientes (53,6%) fueron intervenidos y la resección fue completa en 26 de ellos (86,7%). Dieciséis casos (61,5%) presentaron una recidiva. La respuesta a la quimioterapia no se asoció a la operabilidad. La supervivencia fue mayor en el grupo con una resección completa del tumor (p ¼ 0,041). Conclusiones: La respuesta a la quimioterapia en los tumores de cavidad oral fue mayor en los pacientes con estadio III y en los que recibieron BLM. La quimioterapia puede mejorar la supervivencia en casos paliativos. En los casos neoadyuvantes no se demostró una gran influencia para convertir casos dudosos de cirugía en tributarios para cirugía (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;60(4): 260-267, jul.-ago. 2009. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162526</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El papel de la quimioterapia en el cáncer de la cavidad oral avanzado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2971^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5602^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1786^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22570^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d974^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22570^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
