<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141793</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-1342</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diurnal versus office-hour intraocular pressure fluctuation in primary adult onset glaucoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To evaluates the role of measuring intraocular pressure (IOP) outside office-hour in primary adult onset glaucoma. Methods: This retrospective study included 100 cases of primary adult onset glaucoma. IOP readings obtained with Goldmann applanation tonometry between 7 am and 10 pm were compared to office-hour readings. Results: One hundred patients were enrolled (mean age: 58.64±10.98 years) in the study. Overall, mean diurnal IOP was significantly higher than mean office IOP (p&lt;0.05). Two-thirds of the patients had peak IOP measurements outside office-hour. Mean diurnal IOP fluctuation (7.03±2.69mm Hg) was significantly higher than mean office IOP fluctuation (4.31±2.6mm Hg) (p&lt;0.003). There was a significant correlation between baseline IOP and fluctuation in IOP (r=0.61, p&lt;0.001). Conclusion: The mean diurnal IOP and IOP fluctuations were higher than office-hour readings in patients with primary adult onset glaucoma. Diurnal monitoring may be particularly useful in patients with high baseline IOP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arora, Vishal</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jindal Bali, Shveta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dada, Tanuj</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Panda, Anita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Wadhwani, Meenakshi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arora, Tarun</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la función de la medición de la presión intraocular (PIO) fuera del horario de consulta en el glaucoma de reciente aparición en edad adulta. Métodos: Este estudio retrospectivo incluyó 100 casos de glaucoma primario en adultos. Se compararon las mediciones de la PIO obtenidas mediante tonometría de aplanación de Goldmann entre las 7:00 y las 22:00, con los valores en horario de consulta. Resultados: Se incluyó a cien pacientes (edad media: 58,64±10,98 años). Globalmente, la PIO media diurna fue significativamente superior que la PIO media en horario de consulta (p&lt;0,05). Dos tercios de los pacientes reflejaron unos valores elevados de la PIO fuera del horario de consulta. La fluctuación de la PIO media diurna (7,03±2,69mm Hg) fue considerablemente superior que la fluctuación de la PIO media en horario de consulta (4,31±2,6mm Hg) (p&lt;0,003). Se produjo una correlación significativa entre la PIO basal y la fluctuación de PIO (r= 0,61, p &lt;0,001). Conclusión: Las fluctuaciones de la PIO media diurna y la PIO fueron superiores a los valores medidos en horario de consulta en pacientes con glaucoma primario de aparición en la edad adulta. La supervisión diurna puede resultar particularmente útil en pacientes con una elevada PIO basal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>J. optom. (Internet);8(4): 239-243, oct.-dic. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141793</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de la fluctuación de la presión intraocular diurna y en horario de consulta en pacientes con glaucoma primario de aparición en la edad adulta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d25631^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28204^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1822^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24698^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
