<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166519</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Postural deformities of the skull. Advantages of protocolization in its treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Since 2007, we have examined in our medical practice children with cranial deformities. The increasing demand and lack of professionals dedicated to it has forced us to assume the treatment of this disease. We present our experience. Material and methods. Retrospective study of patients with cranial deformities treated from 2010 to 2015. We collected data as age at the first visit and at discharge, sequential measurements of the skull and cranial index, type of treatment prescribed (postural, orthosis or both) and consultation requested to other specialties. In the first stage (2010-2012), each surgeon prescribed the treatment he considered appropriate. Since November 2012 a protocol has been implemented, it includes guideline sheets for the surgeon and parents with information on postural therapy and graphs to record the measurements. Results. We have treated 261 patients. Two were diagnosed with craniosynostosis. From the rest, only 151 possessed complete quantitative data and were included in the study with 105 men and 46 women and a mean age of 5.8 months (± 1.9 months). There were 23 pure brachycephaly, 126 mixed forms and 2 pure plagiocephaly. A significant disparity between observers&#146; measurements was noticed. All patients underwent a protocolized postural treatment. In 36 patients who did not improve with postural treatment, cranial orthosis was prescribed with good response: 66.8% became mild forms. Those who maintained only postural treatment also improved to milder forms in 64.4%. Conclusions. The implementation of a protocol has enabled us to unify the care and follow-up of these patients. Cranial measurement techniques should be more precise and reproducible. Good postural treatment and empathy with the family reduce the use of orthosis in carefully selected cases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pisón Chacón, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Martín, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina Caballero, AY</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayuso González, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Martínez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Desde 2007 hemos valorado en consulta a niños con deformidades craneales. La creciente demanda y la falta de profesionales dedicados nos obligaron a asumir el tratamiento de esta patología. Presentamos nuestra experiencia. Material y métodos. Estudio descriptivo retrospectivo de los enfermos con deformidades craneales atendidos desde 2010 a 2015. Recopilamos datos sobre edad en la primera visita y al alta, medidas secuenciales del cráneo, tipo de tratamiento prescrito (postural, ortesis o ambos) e interconsulta a otras especialidades. En la primera etapa (2010-2012), cada cirujano prescribía el tratamiento que consideraba oportuno. Desde noviembre de 2012 se implementó un protocolo que incluye una hoja de actuación para el cirujano y otra para los padres con información sobre medidas posturales y gráficas para anotar las mediciones. Resultados. Hemos atendido a 261 pacientes afectos de deformidades craneales. Dos fueron diagnosticados de craneosinostosis. Del resto, solo 151 disponían de datos cuantitativos completos y se incluyeron en el estudio. Fueron 105 varones y 46 mujeres con edad media de 5,8 meses (± 1,9 meses). Veintitrés presentaban una braquicefalia pura, 126 formas mixtas y 2 presentaban plagiocefalia pura. Existía una importante disparidad entre observadores en la toma de medidas. Todos fueron sometidos a un tratamiento postural protocolizado. En 36 enfermos que no mejoraban se pautó ortesis craneal con buena respuesta: 66,8% pasaron a formas más leves. Los que se mantuvieron solo con tratamiento postural también mejoraron evolucionando a formas más leves en el 64,4%. Conclusiones. La introducción de un protocolo asistencial nos ha permitido unificar la atención y el seguimiento de estos enfermos. Las técnicas de medición craneal deben ser más precisas y reproducibles. Un buen tratamiento postural y empatía con la familia reducen la utilización de ortesis a casos muy seleccionados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;30(2): 105-110, abr. 2017. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166519</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Deformidades craneales posturales. Ventajas de la protocolización en su tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32938^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10166^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28264^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3414^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38614^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32938^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
