<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79712</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish version of the revised movement image questionnaire (MIQ-R): psychometric properties and validation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this study was twofold: first to evaluate the factors and distribution of the items in the Spanish version of the Movement Imagery Questionnaire-Revised (MIQ-R) and second, to determine internal consistency and its correlation with other measures of imagery ability. A total of 201 undergraduate students were given the Spanish version of the MIQ-R and the factorial analysis revealed that the questionnaire consisted of two factors corresponding to the visual and kinaesthetic subscales, which together explained 66.11% of the total variance. Test consistency was satisfactory in terms of the total test score and both subscales. The MIQ-R had a correlation of -.34 with the Vividness of Movement Imagery Questionnaire (VMIQ), and -.26 with the Vividness of Visual Imagery Questionnaire (VVIQ). The Spanish version of the MIQ-R is a good instrument for measuring movement imagery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González, María Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En esta investigación deseábamos saber los factores que tenía la versión española del Cuestionario-Revisado de Imagen del Movimiento (MIQ-R), y cómo se distribuían los ítems. También deseábamos conocer la consistencia interna y cómo correlacionaba con otras medidas de habilidad de imagen. Para ello aplicamos la versión española del MIQ-R a una muestra de 201 estudiantes universitarios, y encontramos, mediante análisis factorial, que el cuestionario consta de dos factores, que juntos explican el 66.11% de la varianza total. Estos dos factores corresponden a la subescala visual y a la subescala cinestésica. La consistencia del test fue satisfactoria, tanto la consistencia de la puntuación total del test, como la de cada una de las dos subescalas. El MIQ-R correlacionó -.34 con el Cuestionario de Viveza de Imagen del Movimiento (VMIQ), y -.26 con el Cuestionario de Viveza de Imagen Visual (VVIQ). La versión española del MIQ-R se considera una buena medida de imagen del movimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;19(2): 265-275, jul.-dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79712</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Versión española del cuestionario-revisado de imagen del movimiento (MIQ-R): validación y propiedades psicométricas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
