<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054751</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mobbing: a meta-analysis and integrative model of its antecedents and consequences</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Although mobbing has been extensively studied, empirical research has not led to firm conclusions regarding its antecedents and consequences, both at personal and organizational levels. An extensive literature search yielded 86 empirical studies with 93 samples. The matrix correlation obtained through meta-analytic techniques was used to test a structural equation model. Results supported hypotheses regarding organizational environmental factors as main predictors of mobbing</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Depolo, Marco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Topa Cantisano, Gabriela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Domínguez, J. Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Pese a que el acoso laboral ha sido extensamente estudiado, la investigación empírica no ha llegado a conclusiones firmes relativas a sus antecedentes y consecuencias personales y organizacionales. Una extensa búsqueda de la literatura arroja 86 estudios empíricos con 93 muestras que son sometidos a técnicas meta-analíticas. La matriz de correlaciones obtenida por técnicas metaanalíticas ha sido usada para probar un modelo de ecuaciones estructurales. Los resultados apoyan las hipótesis relativas a los factores del ambiente organizacional como predictores del acoso</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);19(1): 88-94, feb. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054751</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acoso laboral: meta-análisis y modelo integrador de sus antecedentes y consecuencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23790</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30967</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13700</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16629</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
