<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146349</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Disability-adjusted life years lost to ischemic heart disease in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. The health indicator disability-adjusted life years combines the fatal and nonfatal consequences of a disease in a single measure. The aim of this study was to evaluate the burden of ischemic heart disease in 2008 in Spain by calculating disability-adjusted life years. Methods. The years of life lost due to premature death were calculated using the ischemic heart disease deaths by age and sex recorded in the Spanish National Institute of Statistics and the life-table in the 2010 Global Burden of Disease study. The years lived with disability, calculated for acute coronary syndrome, stable angina, and ischemic heart failure, used hospital discharge data and information from population studies. Disability weights were taken from the 2010 Global Burden of Disease study. We calculated crude and age standardized rates (European Standard Population). Univariate sensitivity analyses were performed. Results. In 2008, 539 570 disability-adjusted life years were lost due to ischemic heart disease in Spain (crude rate, 11.8/1000 population; standardized, 8.6/1000). Of the total years lost, 96% were due to premature death and 4% due to disability. Among the years lost due to disability, heart failure accounted for 83%, stable angina 15%, and acute coronary syndrome 2%. In the sensitivity analysis, weighting by age was the factor that changed the results to the greatest degree. Conclusions. Ischemic heart disease continues to have a huge impact on the health of our population, mainly because of premature death. The results of this study provide an overall vision of the epidemiologic situation in Spain and could serve as the basis for evaluating interventions targeting the acute and chronic manifestations of cardiac ischemia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández de Larrea-Baz, Nerea</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morant-Ginestar, Consuelo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gènova-Maleras, Ricard</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Martínez, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Catalá-López, Ferrán</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Los años de vida ajustados por discapacidad aúnan en una medida consecuencias mortales y no mortales de las enfermedades. El objetivo fue cuantificar la carga de enfermedad de la cardiopatía isquémica en España en 2008 mediante el cálculo de años de vida ajustados por discapacidad. Métodos. Años perdidos por muerte prematura calculados a partir de defunciones por cardiopatía isquémica por edad y sexo del Instituto Nacional de Estadística y tabla de vida del estudio de carga global de enfermedad 2010. Años vividos con discapacidad calculados para el síndrome coronario agudo, la angina estable y la insuficiencia cardiaca isquémica, con datos del registro de altas hospitalarias y de estudios poblacionales, y pesos de discapacidad del estudio de carga global de enfermedad 2010. Se calcularon tasas brutas y estandarizadas por edad (población estándar europea). Se realizaron análisis de sensibilidad univariantes. Resultados. En 2008 se perdieron en España 539.570 años de vida ajustados por discapacidad por cardiopatía isquémica (tasa bruta: 11,8/1.000; estandarizada: 8,6/1.000). El 96% correspondía a años perdidos por muerte prematura y el 4% por discapacidad. De estos últimos, el 83% por insuficiencia cardiaca, el 15% por angina estable y el 2% por síndrome coronario agudo. En el análisis de sensibilidad, el factor que más modificó los resultados fue la ponderación por edad. Conclusiones. La cardiopatía isquémica sigue teniendo un gran impacto en la salud de la población, principalmente por mortalidad prematura. Los resultados aportan una visión global de la situación epidemiológica y pueden servir para evaluar intervenciones sobre las manifestaciones agudas y crónicas de la isquemia cardiaca (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;68(11): 968-975, nov. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146349</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Años de vida ajustados por discapacidad perdidos por cardiopatía isquémica en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30935^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28397</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54536^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
