<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158819</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Profilactic surgery of digestive tumors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Prophylactic surgery is analogous of the preventive medicine. Before the development of anaesthesia, prophylactic surgery was virtually non-existent, except for circumcision; however, since the end of the 20th century, a significant practice of general surgery is prophylactic, the majority related with cancer. Due to the high incidence of cancer, have proposed protocols and clinical pathways for the detection and monitoring of injuries with potential neoplastic. This article checked the genetic basis of the highlight and prophylactic surgery, in your case, with special attention to the hereditary neoplastic syndromes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Montes, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La cirugía profiláctica es la análoga de la medicina preventiva. Antes del desarrollo de la anestesia, la cirugía profiláctica virtualmente era inexistente, excepto para la circuncisión; sin embargo, desde finales del siglo XX una significativa práctica de la cirugía es profiláctica, la mayoría relacionada con el cáncer. Debido a la alta incidencia de cáncer, se han propuesto protocolos y vías clínicas para la detección y seguimiento de lesiones con potencial neoplásico. En este artículo se revisan las bases genéticas, los aspectos más destacados y la cirugía profiláctica de estas lesiones, en su caso, con especial atención a los síndromes neoplásicos hereditarios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;19(4): 175-182, 2016. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158819</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cirugía profiláctica de los tumores digestivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19258^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11665^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1493^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55687^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32787^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5911^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
