<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-36170</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-1285</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Surgical treatmen of a fibrous hyperplasia located in the cauncula of opening of Estenon´duct</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The fibrous hyperplasia is an exofitic injury circumscribed and formed by dense fibrous conective weave, covered by epithelio squamous stratified. lt is located with more frequency in the buccal mucosa, gingiva, tongue and soft palate, generally zones where greater rubbing takes place, since his etiopathogenia seems to be related to chronic irritatives or traumatic repeated factors. The treatment is based in the surgical extirpation and the elimination of the local irritating factors. We present a case of unilateral tumor of fibrous aspect of ten years of evolution located in left buccal mucosa, that included caruncula of opening of Estenon's duct. The treatment consisted of the canalization of the duct to preserve its integrity, surgical extirpation of the injury with cold scalpel and positioning of an active intraoral drainage. The histopathologic study of the sample confirmed the diagnosis of fibrous hyperplasia. After one year follow-up, the patient has not presented any recurrence, and the drainage of the left parotid gland is functioning normally (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ediciones Avances, S.L.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hiperplasia fibrosa es una lesión exofítica circunscrita y formada por tejido conectivo fibroso denso, cubierto por un epitelio escamoso estratificado. Se localiza con más frecuencia en la mucosa yugal, encía, lengua y paladar blando, generalmente zonas donde se produce mayor roce, ya que su etiopatogenia parece estar relacionada con factores irritativos crónicos o traumáticos repetidos. El tratamiento consiste en la extirpación quirúrgica y la eliminación de los factores irritantes locales. Presentamos un caso de tumoración unilateral de aspecto fibroso de diez años de evolución localizada en mucosa yugal izquierda, que incluía la carúncula de desembocadura del conducto de Estenon. El tratamiento consistió en la canalización del conducto para preservar su integridad, extirpación quirúrgica de la lesión con bisturí frío y colocación de un drenaje activo intraoral. El estudio histopatológico de la muestra confirmó el diagnóstico de hiperplasia fibrosa. Tras un año de seguimiento, el paciente no ha presentado ninguna recidiva, y el drenaje de la glándula parótida izquierda se mantiene normal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av Odontoestomatol;20(5): 227-231, sept.-oct.  2004. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento quirúrgico dé una hiperplasia fibrosa localizada en la desembocadura del conducto de Estenon. Descripción de la técnica</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Bermejo Fenoll, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Jornet, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saura Inglés, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camacho Alonso, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-36170</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d7144^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10094^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12841^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13896^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32615^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22570^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12841^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32615^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
