<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95265</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-9476</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this article general information is exposed on the mictional dynamics and on the Stop-Test, a technique defended by many people butdenied by many others, for the training of the Kegel, exercises, at present generates controversy among different health professional groups.The dictionary defines the controversy as a long and repeated discussion. It is produced in the best of the cases for a lack of reliable information,but also obeys on occasions to personal interests, economicist, social, etc. How many controversies have been seen and keep being seen inrelation to the vaccination recommendations, without talking necessarily about the A Flu? Gregory Benford, in 1980, commented in his knownLaw of Controversy: «The passion is inversely proportional to the quantity of available real information»! (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Rodríguez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Milla España, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se expone información general sobre la dinámica miccional y sobre el Stop-test; una técnica, tan defendida por unos comonegada por otros, para el aprendizaje de los ejercicios de Kegel, y que en la actualidad genera controversia entre distintos colectivos sanitarios.El diccionario define la controversia como una discusión larga y reiterada. Se produce en el mejor de los casos por una falta de información fidedigna, pero también obedece en ocasiones a intereses personales, economicistas, sociales, etc. ¿Cuántas controversias se han visto y sesiguen viendo en relación a las recomendaciones vacunales, sin hablar necesariamente de la gripe A? Gregory Benford, en 1980, comentó ensu llamada Ley de Controversia: «La pasión es inversamente proporcional a la cantidad de información real disponible». (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>ENFURO: Rev. Asoc. Esp. A.T.S. Urol;(113): 19-23, ene.-mar. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95265</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La controversia del Stop-test en la reeducación uroginecológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9309^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14954^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
