<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75817</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Carotid stenting. Review of the evidence</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION. In the current moment a total agreement does not exist on the treatment of choice in the carotid stenosis, both therapeutic existing options are carotid thromboendarterectomy and carotid stent. In this review we have wanted to analyze the results of the studies published in the last years and the scientific existing evidence at present. MATERIAL AND METHODS. There was realized a bibliographical search of Native Library of Medicine (PubMed). The key words introduced to realize the above mentioned search were carotid stenosis, stent, and thromboendarterectomy. The articles were included published from2006 until 2008, in English and Spanish. RESULTS. With the limits mentioned previously, we found 225 articles and 24reviews, 14 of them were relating to the topic. CONCLUSION. There are several controversies because the studies are heterogeneous(different patients, technicals and duration of follow-up) and five of them were interrupted early by the high index of stroke/death of the endovascular treatment. The scientific evidence on the treatment of the carotid stenosis by means of angioplasty/stent, does not support a change in the clinical practice opposite to carotid thromboendarterectomy , except in groups of selected patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez, V. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carpintero, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cenizo, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Fajardo, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Del Río, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mengíbar, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Pedrosa, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Norberto, E. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvador, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Del Blanco, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrera, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brizuela, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Revilla, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">INTRODUCCIÓN. En el momento actual no existe un total acuerdo sobre el tratamiento de elección en la estenosis carotidea, las dos opciones terapéuticas existentes son la tromboendarterectomia (TEA) carotidea y el stent carotideo. En esta revisión hemos querido analizar los resultados de los estudios publicados en los últimos años y la evidencia científica existente en la actualidad. MATERIAL Y MÉTODOS. Se realizó una búsqueda bibliográfica de la Nacional Library of Medicine (PubMed). Las palabras clave introducidas para realizar dicha búsqueda fueron carotid stenosis, stent, y thrombo endarterectomy. Se incluyeron los trabajos publicados desde 2006 hasta 2008, en inglés y español. RESULTADOS. Con los límites citados anteriormente se encontraron 225 artículos y 24 revisiones, de los cuales eran referentes al tema 14 de ellos. CONCLUSIONES. Los datos son difíciles de interpretar porque los ensayos son heterogéneos (diferentes pacientes, técnica y duración de seguimiento) y cinco ensayos se interrumpieron anticipadamente por el elevado índice de stroke/muerte del tratamiento endovascular. La evidencia científica sobre el tratamiento de la estenosis carotídea mediante angioplastia/stent, no apoya un cambio en la práctica clínica frente a la tromboendarterectomía carotídea, salvo en grupos seleccionados de pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;12(1): 40-43, ene.-mar. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75817</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Stent carotídeo. Revisión y puesta al día</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30956^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4772^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30211^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
