<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158358</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-3334</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Inclusion in schools has been a topic of great interest because the statistics demonstrate a low level of educational inclusion. Therefore, this study aims to understand the subjective experiences of students with Mild Cognitive Disability, parents, peers and teachers to the process of school inclusion in the Educational Institution from the city of Neiva. It is a qualitative ethnographic study, used participant observation and the free drawing in 27 people in 6 groups (government agencies, support groups, teachers, parents, students with disabilities and peers). The results demonstrate that Governmental Entities are responsible for ensuring the right to education and school inclusion from the normativity recognizing that there are difficulties in implementing these programs. The other people involved in the process need to be very commitment to inclusion that can be carried out in an environment of equality that allows the construction of life project. Students with Cognitive Disabilities are feeling good because they have the opportunity to start a process of socialization with peers which have accepted them, welcomed and established equality treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gil Vargas, Isabel Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ríos Gallardo, Ángela Magnolia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Vanegas, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermeo Losada, María Alejandra</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La inclusión del alumnado con algún tipo de discapacidad es uno de los retos pendientes en el ámbito escolar. El presente estudio tiene como objetivo comprender las experiencias subjetivas de los estudiantes con discapacidad cognitiva leve, padres de familia, pares y docentes, frente al proceso de inclusión escolar en una institución educativa de la ciudad de Neiva. Es un estudio cualitativo-etnográfico que utilizó la observación participante y el dibujo libre en 27 personas distribuidas en 6 grupos (entidades gubernamentales, grupo de apoyo, profesores, padres de familia, estudiantes con discapacidad e iguales). Los resultados evidencian que son las entidades gubernamentales las encargadas de garantizar el derecho a la educación y a la inclusión escolar desde la normatividad reconociendo que existen dificultades en la implementación de estos programas. Las demás personas involucradas en el proceso requieren tener mucho compromiso para que la inclusión pueda realizarse en un ambiente de igualdad que permita la construcción del proyecto de vida. Los estudiantes con discapacidad cognitiva se sienten bien ya que tienen la oportunidad de iniciar un proceso de socialización con los pares los cuales los han aceptado, acogido y establecido un trato con igualdad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apuntes psicol;33(2): 83-92, 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158358</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hacer realidad un derecho: una experiencia de inclusión de alumnado con discapacidad cognitiva en una institución educativa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d17557</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50296</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12955^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33920^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33552^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4589^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
