<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81277</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0367</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hallucination versus representation. From anánké to poiesis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article deals with the concepts of perception and representation, and the many aspects and facets with which both recreate themselves in the person&#146;s inner world. Following the methodology of a rigorous hermeneutics, they are contrasted with the schizophrenic hallucinations, experienced as imposed phenomena, repetitive or anankastic, seemingly revealing an automatization of neurological process defined by some authors as zombie modes or «previous global representations», which claim  independence from subjective will and ego-based consciousness. On the contrary, the process of representations refers to a dominion of the ego where reality is constantly resemantiziced in the consciousness. There, the creative thinking, poiesis and reason find a privileged ground, giving access to the complexity and freshness inherent to healthy behavior (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rojas Malpica, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villaseñor Bayardo, Sergio Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente trabajo se propone abordar el problema de las percepciones y representaciones, así como los matices con que ambas se recrean en el mundo interior. Por el método de una rigurosa hermenéutica se contrastan con las alucinaciones esquizofrénicas, vividas como fenómenos impuestos, anancásticos o repetitivos; que parecen revelar una automatización de procesos neurofisiológicos definidos por algunos autores como zombie modes o «representaciones globales previas», que se independizan de la voluntad subjetiva y de la conciencia del yo. Por el contrario, el  proceso de las representaciones, remite a un dominio del yo, donde la realidad es permanentemente resemantizada en la conciencia. Allí el pensamiento creador, la poiesis y la razón encuentran un lugar privilegiado, dando acceso a la complejidad y frescura propios del comportamiento saludable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. psiquiatr;71(1): 1-14, ene.-mar. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81277</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alucinación frente a representación. De la anánké a la poiesis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6365</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10663</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12946</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
