<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129493</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-5434</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Etiological and epidemiological particularities of ovine contagious agalactia: similarities and differences with goats</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Contagious agalactia (CA) is an infectious syndrome caused by several species of Mycoplasma spp. which affects small ruminants. The aim of this review is to describe the main differences noted between the disease in sheep and goats, especially with regard to its etiologic and epidemiological peculiarities. Thus, the presence of asymptomatic auricular carriers of CA-causing mycoplasmas and the stud&#146;s role in the transmission of the disease are well known in goats, but scarcely evaluated in sheep. Further studies are needed to determine if these differences are real or if they are due to the shortage of scientific work in this matter (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fe, C. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Contreras, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paterna, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prats-van der Ham, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amores, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Martín, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tatay-Dualde, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corrales, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo describe las diferencias existentes en la presentación de la agalaxia contagiosa, síndrome infectocontagioso causado por varias especies del genero Mycoplasma spp., en el ganado ovino y caprino. Las particularidades etiológicas y epidemiológicas de la infección crónica en la cabra, y la ausencia de datos similares en el ovino, evidencian la necesidad de realizar nuevos trabajos que determinen si las diferencias observadas en referencia a la presencia de portadores auriculares en los rebaños o la participación de los sementales en la difusión de la enfermedad son fruto de la escasez de trabajos científicos o por el contrario, establecen verdaderas diferencias sobre las que desarrollar estrategias dirigidas de control en función de la especie de rumiante afectada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. vet. Murcia;29: 39-48, ene.-dic. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129493</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Particularidades etiológicas y epimediológicas de la agalaxia contagiosa ovina: similitudes y diferencias con el caprino</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9367^s22069</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9367^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28582^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37949^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28582^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28582^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28582^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9367^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
