<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119922</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Primary tuberculosis of the glans penis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: Tuberculosis of the penis is an extremely rare disease with few cases reported in the literature. CLINICAL CASE: We present the case of a 64 year-old man with a whitish papular-ampullary eruption in the glans penis. After antibiotic/antimycotic therapy and several topical ointments for 3 months without response he was referred to our Department. Biopsy of the ulceration edge was performed and pathology result showed a chronic granulomatous inflammatory necrotizing lesion with granulomatous vasculitis lesions, without tumor infiltration. Systemic examination to rule out other tuberculosis foci was negative. With de suspicion of primary tuberculosis of the glans penis, anti tuberculosis therapy with Isoniazid and Piridoxine was started. RESULTS: Within a period of five months the ulceration healed significantly. Currently, the patient is still asymptomatic without glans penis lesions. CONCLUSIONS: Primary glans penis tuberculosis is a rare disease, but we must consider it (both primary and secondary forms) to try to avoid diagnostic delays that may cause prejudice for the patient. This condition promptly responds to anti tuberculosis therapy as evidenced by our case and many other reports (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Parra, José David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Bandrés, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Varas, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García García, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Calvo, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sotil Arrieta, Amaia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVOS: Aportar un nuevo caso de tuberculosis primaria de pene dada su infrecuente incidencia, con pocos casos descritos en la literatura. MÉTODO: Presentamos el caso de un varón de 64 años de edad, sin antecedentes urológicos de interés, que acude a consulta de dermatología por aparición de lesión ampollosa blanquecina en glande de tres meses de evolución que no mejora con antibióticos-antimicóticos tópicos (Médico de Atención Primaria). Se realiza biopsia de glande con resultado anatomopatológico de inflamación granulomatosa necrotizante con lesiones de vasculis granulomatosa, sin infiltración tumoral. Tras descartar posibles focos tuberculosis a nivel sistémico comienza tratamiento con Isoniazida más Piridoxina. RESULTADOS: A los cinco meses de evolución el paciente presenta gran mejoría clínica, con disminución de la lesión peneana y asintomático desde el punto de vista urológico. CONCLUSIONES: La tuberculosis primaria de pene es una patología infrecuente aunque debemos tenerla en mente (tanto formas primarias como secundarias), para así intentar evitar el retraso diagnóstico con el consecuente perjuicio para el paciente. El inicio de una terapia antituberculosa muestra respuestas favorables en la mayoría de los casos de forma relativamente precoz (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;67(2): 203-206, mar. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119922</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tuberculosis primaria a nivel de glande</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14790^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29286^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10603^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d999^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
