<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148767</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Inferior vertical nystagmus: is magnetic resonance imaging mandatory?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The presentation of a down-beating nystagmus force to discard vascular pathology of brain and cervical joint with magnetic resonance imagine (MRI). Recent studies support the low profitability of this study and is subjected that this oculomotor sign has a peripheral origin especially when the patient has a benign paroxysmal positional vertigo (BPPV) with affection of the superior semicircular canal. Aim. To evidence the profitability of MRI in a population of patients with positional down-beating nystagmus. Patients and methods. We present a retrospective study with 42 consecutive patients. A complete clinical history and physical examination was performed. All of them perform vestibular tests (caloric and rotatory), cranial and cervical MRI. Results. Fifty-two percent of patients present clinical manifestations and physical exploration compatible with BPPV. MRI was normal in 67%. We found spondylopathy in 26% and vascular cerebral pathology in 5%. Prevalence of type I ArnoldChiari malformation was 9% in our population. None of them was founded when the main symptom was suggestive of BPPV. Results obtained of vestibular tests didn&#146;t contribute additional information to give an ethiologic diagnosis. Conclusion. The profitability of vestibular tests and MRI in our population with down beating nystagmus was very low. We must evaluate the real necessity of this test with the clinical context (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz Fernández, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esteban Sánchez, Jonathan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Sanz, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rueda Marcos, Almudena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La aparición de un nistagmo vertical inferior clásicamente obliga a descartar una patología vascular o de la unión craneocervical mediante resonancia magnética (RM). Estudios recientes demuestran una baja rentabilidad de esta prueba, ya que sugieren que este signo oculomotor puede tener una causa vestibular periférica, sobre todo cuando el paciente presenta un vértigo posicional paroxístico benigno (VPPB) del canal semicircular superior. Objetivo. Comprobar la rentabilidad de la RM en una población de pacientes con nistagmo de posición vertical inferior. Pacientes y métodos. Estudio retrospectivo de 42 pacientes consecutivos a los que se les realizó una historia clínica, exploración física, y pruebas vestibulares calóricas y rotatorias. A todos ellos se les practicó una RM craneal y cervical. Resultados. El 52% de los pacientes con nistagmo de posición vertical inferior presentaba una clínica y exploración física compatibles con VPPB del canal semicircular superior. La RM fue normal en un 67%, un 26% mostraba datos de espondilopatía y un 5% de microangiopatía cerebral no relacionados con la clínica del paciente. La prevalencia de malformación de Arnold-Chiari de tipo I fue de un 9% en la población estudiada, sin que nadie tuviera un antecedente reciente de VPPB. Los resultados obtenidos en las pruebas complementarias vestibulares no aportaron información adicional para llegar a un diagnóstico etiológico. Conclusión. En los pacientes con un VPPB, la RM craneal y las pruebas vestibulares tienen una baja rentabilidad diagnóstica, y se debe evaluar la necesidad real de esta prueba con el contexto clínico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;62(3): 107-112, 1 feb., 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148767</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nistagmo vertical inferior: ¿es obligada la resonancia magnética?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1143^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4656^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21041^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27888^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1143^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15128^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15129^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27888^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4656^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15128^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27888^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13267^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
