<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110556</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Alternatives to pharmaceutical distribution and reimbursement</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In Spain pharmaceutical distribution is carried out mainly thorugh the 20,000 independent pharmacies located throughout the country. This situation contrasts with that in other countries where other health care providers play a major role in drug dispensation or where pharmacies form part of industrial conglomerates or commercial chains. We describe the pharmaceutical distribution chain in Spain &#150;wholesale and through the pharmacies&#150; and place particular emphasis on five aspects of relevance when considering alternatives: ownership of the pharmacy and norms of professional service, criteria for setting up a pharmacy, monopoly on dispensing, automatic ageement with the Spanish national health system and reimbursement system. Several alternatives found in comparable countries are described: mail order and on-line distribution, sale of over-the counter pharmaceutical products in establishments other than pharmacies, the estabilishment of pharmaceutical chains, dispensing by providers, the repercussions of electronic prescribing and the possibilities of the still-emerging «Pharmacuetical Care». The characteristics of pharmacy reimbursement systems are also reviewed. We recommend modification of limitations on ownership of pharmacies, the establishment of optional agreements between pharmacies and the Spanish national health system and the authorization of alternative or complementary channels of distribution for some products. We propose a mixed model of reimbursement that would include: a) a ficed price for dispensing; b) almost total  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Meneu, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La distribución de medicamentos en España se articula mayoritariamente alrededor de las 20.000 oficinas de farmacia (OOFF) independientes radicadas en el territorio. Esta situación contrasta con la de otros países en que otros proveedores sanitarios desempeñan un papel primordial en la dispensación de fármacos, o con la de aquellos cuyas farmacias forman parte de conglomerados industriales o cadenas empresariales. Se presenta una descripción de la cadena de distribución del medicamento española &#150;mayoristas y OOFF&#150;, destacando 5 aspectos relevantes para la consideración de alternativas: titularidad de la farmacia y actuación profesional, criterios de radicación, monopolio de dispensación, concierto automático con el Sistema Nacional de la Salud (SNS) y sistema de retribución. Se consideran algunas alternativas existentes en países de nuestro entorno: distribución a distancia, venta de especialidades farmacéuticas publicitarias en establecimientos distintos de las OOFF, constitución de cadenas farmacéuticas, dispensación por proveedores, repercusiones de la prescripción electrónica y las posibilidades de la aún emergente atención farmacéutica. Asimismo se revisan las características de los sistemas de retribución de las farmacias. Se proponen la modificación de las limitaciones a la propiedad de las OOFF, el establecimiento de convenios de libre aceptación entre éstas y el SNS, y la autorización de canales alternativos o complementarios para la distribución de algunos productos. En  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;16(2): 171-181, mar.-abr. 2002.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110556</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alternativas a la distribución de medicamentos y su retribución</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51455</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54846</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51469</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53206^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30152</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4424^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
