<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045633</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Migraine in childhood: a trivial condition?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Migraine is seen as being a trivial disease, and more so in childhood, but in many cases it has adetrimental effect on the patient&#146;s quality of life. Patients and methods. Prospective study. All the patients were evaluated by thesame neuropaediatrician and all of them satisfied diagnostic criteria for migraine. 127 children were examined. The mean agewas 9.4 years, with an interval of 3-14 years; there were no differences between sexes. 67 males and 60 females. Results. Themean length of time the episodes lasted was 22.5 h. The most frequently observed clinical features were: hemicraniallocalisation, 44.4%; throbbing, 74.4%; photophobia, 74.8%; phonophobia, 83.5%; nausea-vomiting, 63.5%; and aura, 14.3%;with predominance of acutely intense visual and sensory symptoms (74%), functional repercussions in 87% and absence fromschool in up to 36.9% of cases. 16% of patients have had episodes of status migrainous. At the time of the visit 46% had severalattacks a week; 13.7% once a week; 16.1% fortnightly; 13.7 % monthly; 5.6% every three months; and others, 4.8%. 48.7% ofthe patients were given preventive treatment, which was wholly effective in 48%, partially effective in 35% and not at alleffective in 15.4%. Conclusions. Migraine in childhood is not a trivial pathology. It is disabling: it interferes with their dailylife in 85% of cases, causes them to miss school in almost 40% of patients and nearly 50% of them have several episodes aweek. A similar figure required prophylactic treatment that was seen to be very effective</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Menéndez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinel-González, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La jaqueca se considera una enfermedadbanal, más aún en la infancia, pero lo cierto es que en muchos casosresta calidad de vida. Pacientes y métodos. Estudio prospectivo.Todos los pacientes fueron evaluados por el mismo neuropediatra.Cumplían criterios diagnósticos de jaqueca. Se evaluó a 127niños. La edad media fue de 9,4 años (intervalo: 3-14 años), sindiferencias entre sexos. 67 varones y 60 mujeres. Resultados. Laduración media de la crisis fue de 22,5 h. Las características clínicasmás frecuentes recogidas fueron: localización hemicraneal,44,4%; pulsátil, 74,4%; fotofobia, 74,8%; fonofobia, 83,5%; náuseas-vómitos, 63,5%, y aura, 14,3%, con predomino de síntomasvisuales y sensitivos, de intensidad aguda (74%), con repercusiónfuncional en el 87% y provocación del absentismo escolar hasta enel 36,9%. Un 16% sufrió episodios de estado jaquecoso. En el momentode consultar el 46% tuvo varias crisis a la semana; el13,7%, semanal; el 16,1%, quincenal; el 13,7 %, mensual; el 5,6%,trimestral; y otros, el 4,8%. El 48,7% recibió tratamiento preventivocon eficacia completa en el 48%, parcial en el 35% y nula en el15,4%. Conclusiones. La jaqueca en la infancia no es una patologíabanal. Es incapacitante: interfiere con la vida diaria en más del85%, provoca faltas escolares en casi un 40% de los casos y cercadel 50% sufre varios episodios a la semana. Una cifra similar requiriótratamiento profiláctico, que resultó muy eficaz</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;42(11): 643-646, jun. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045633</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La jaqueca en la infancia: ¿una patología banal?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15241^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34334^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9517^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6412^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9068^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9068^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
