<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72680</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of the demand for neurological health care generated by primary care in a geographical area within the districts of Girona</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To perform a descriptive analysis of the outpatient activity in a neurological department in terms of thefrequency and type of neurological diseases that were attended. Patients and methods. A retrospective and cross-sectional study was conducted involving patients referred to the neurology outpatients department. The cases that visited for the first time during the years 2006 and 2007 were recorded consecutively. Medical information was evaluated based on computerisedhospital registers and the following data were collected: health referral area, date of visit, age, sex and diagnosis according to the International Classification of Diseases, 9th edition, clinical modification (CIE-9-MC), reconverted into the InternationalClassification of Diseases, 10th edition (CIE-10). Results. The mean age was 60.6 ± 20.9 years (range: 4-95 years) and 61.4% were females. The rate of frequency of visits was 4.3  requests/1000 inhabitants for the year 2006 and 3.9 for the year2007; an increase was observed with age for the neurodegenerative diseases. As far as the CIE-10 is concerned, the diseases were classified as episodic and paroxysmal (25%), degenerative and demyelinating (18.6%), organic mental disorders (14.7%), extrapyramidal syndromes (10.5%), diseases affecting cerebral circulation (3.5%), stress-related disorders and somatomorphs (3.5%) and diseases of the inner ear (3.3%). The remaining pathologies did not reach 3% of the total. Diseases of the central nervous system were observed in 61% of the patients and psychiatric disorders were found in 20.3%. The mostcommon diseases were cognitive disorders (31.5%), headaches (18.6%) and movement disorders (11.7%), followed by psychiatric diseases, epilepsies, cerebrovascular diseases and neuropathies(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Pousa, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar-Barberà, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pericot-Nierga, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Turon-Estrada, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garre-Olmo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coll-De Tuero, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monserrat-Vila, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caja-López, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilalta-Franch, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Turbau-Recio, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Turró-Garriga, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Análisis descriptivo de la actividad ambulatoria en un servicio de neurología en relación con la frecuenciay tipo de enfermedades neurológicas atendidas. Pacientes y métodos. Estudio retrospectivo y trasversal de los pacientesremitidos a la consulta ambulatoria de neurología. Se registraron consecutivamente los casos visitados por primera vez durantelos años 2006 y 2007. Se evaluó la documentación médica a partir de los registros hospitalarios informatizados, recogiéndose:zona de salud de referencia, fecha de visita, edad, sexo y diagnóstico según la Clasificación Internacional de Enfermedades,9.ª edición, modificación clínica (CIE-9-MC), reconvertida a la Clasificación Internacional de Enfermedades, 10.ªedición (CIE-10). Resultados. La media de edad fue de 60,6 ± 20,9 años (rango: 4-95 años) y el 61,4% fueron mujeres. El índicede frecuentación fue de 4,3 solicitudes/1.000 habitantes para el año 2006 y de 3,9 para el año 2007, y se observó unincremento con la edad para las enfermedades neurodegenerativas. Respecto a la CIE-10, las enfermedades se clasificaroncomo episódicas y paroxísticas (25%), degenerativas y desmielinizantes (18,6%), trastornos mentales orgánicos (14,7%), síndromesextrapiramidales (10,5%), enfermedades de la circulación cerebral (3,5%), trastornos relacionados con el estrés y somatomorfos(3,5%) y enfermedades del oído interno (3,3%). Las demás patologías no alcanzaron el 3%. El 61% de los pacientespresentó enfermedades del sistema nervioso central y el 20,3%, trastornos psiquiátricos. Las enfermedades más frecuentesfueron los trastornos cognitivos (31,5%), las cefaleas (18,6%) y los trastornos del movimiento (11,7%), seguidas delas enfermedades psiquiátricas, epilepsias, enfermedades cerebrovasculares y neuropatías(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;49(6): 288-294, sept. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72680</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la demanda asistencial neurológica generada por la atención primaria en una área geográfica de las comarcas de Girona</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7165^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10481^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4640^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9672^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9672^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10481^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4640^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7165^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
