<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036411</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutations in patients with familial breast cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE: Familial breast (BC) and ovarian cancer (OC) has been associated withgerm-line mutations in the cancer susceptibility genes BRCA1 and BRCA2. The mutational spectravary depending on the study populations and the criteria applied for patient selection. The present study reports the mutations found in 48 families of the Valencian Community studied in the University Hospital La Fe of Valencia (Spain). PATIENTS AND METHOD: We analysed the BRCA1 and BRCA2 genes of 48 families (55 patients) with a family history of BC an/or OC. The method consists of DNA extraction, followed by a polymerase chain reaction, mutational analysis by hetero duplex formation in conformation-sensitive-gel electrophoresis and sequencing of the hetero duplex detected. RESULTS: We report eight different deleterious mutations, four in BRCA1 and four in BRCA2 and four unclassified variants (UV). We also identified the presence of the BRCA1 3889_3890 de lG mutation for the first time in the Spanish population. In BRCA2,we report two mutations not described in the brest cancer information care, the 5025 del T which iscompletely new and the 9206_9219 del 14, which has already been described in Spanish population. We also describe for the first time the presence of UV 8038C&gt;T in this gene. CONCLUSIONS: The mutational spectra and the presence of new mutations in the limited number of patients give support to the relevance of the study population in the mutational spectra</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bolufer, Pascual</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santaballa, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Munárriz, Blanca </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velasco, Eladio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lerma, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barragán, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">FUNDAMENTO Y OBJETIVO: El cáncer de mama y el de ovario familiares se ha encontrado asociado con las mutaciones en los genes BRCA1 y BRCA2. El espectro de las mutaciones depende de la población estudiada y de los criterios de selección delos pacientes. En el presente estudio se presentan las mutaciones detectadas en familias de la Comunidad Valenciana procedentes del Hospital Universitario La Fe de Valencia. PACIENTES Y MÉTODO: Se han analizado las mutacionesen los genes BRCA1 y BRCA2 en 48 familias 55 pacientes) con historia familiar de cáncer de mama y de ovario. Se efectuó la extracción del ADN, seguida de técnicas de reacción en cadena de la polimerasa (PCR), análisis de hetero dúplex mediante electroforesis en geles sensibles al cambio conformacional y secuenciación. RESULTADOS: Se han encontrado 8 mutaciones patogénicas diferentes (4 en BRCA1 y 4 en BRCA2) y 4 variantes de efecto desconocido. Se describe por vez primera en población española la mutación 3889_3890de lAG de BRCA1. En el gen BRCA2 se han identificado 2 mutaciones no descritas en el Breast Cancer Information Core, la 5025 del T, que es completamente nueva, y la 9206_9219 del 14,que ya se había descrito en la población española. También se describe por primera vez en este gen la variante missense de efecto desconocido 8048C&gt;T (T2607I). CONCLUSIONES: Las mutaciones detectadas y la presenciade nuevas mutaciones en el limitado número de pacientes indican la influencia de la población estudiada en el espectro mutacional</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);124(1): 10-12, ene. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036411</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mutaciones en BRCA1 y BRCA2 en pacientes con historia familiar de cáncer de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9346</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33161</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28468</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22880</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36331</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
