<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129501</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Physiopathology and recording techniques of ocular movements</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A number of functional systems are involved in the control of eye movements. The vestibulo-ocular and optokinetic reflexes are automatic responses that compensate for the movements of the head and those of the visual environment in order to stabilize the retinal image on a given fixation point. The saccadic movements are quick displacements of fixation from one to another point in the visual field. The smooth pursuit movements consist in the gaze following a moving target. Finally, there are some involuntary movements of very small amplitude during fixation maintenance. Each functional modality of movement depends on specific neuronal circuits that work in a coordinated manner for encoding the contraction of the oculomotor muscles to reach an adequate position at every moment. These neuronal systems can be altered by many neurological processes of different kinds and localizations, causing a broad variety of oculomotor disturbances. The most salient aspects of the physiopathology and the recording systems of eye movements are reviewed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gila, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villanueva, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabeza, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el control de la motilidad ocular intervienen varios sistemas funcionales. Los reflejos vestíbulo-oculares y optocinéticos son respuestas automáticas para compensar los movimientos de la cabeza y del entorno visual y poder estabilizar la imagen retiniana sobre un determinado punto de fijación. Los movimientos sacádicos son rápidos desplazamientos de la fijación de un punto a otro del campo visual. Los movimientos de persecución lenta consisten en el seguimiento de estímulos móviles con la mirada. Finalmente, existen movimientos involuntarios de muy escasa amplitud que se producen durante el mantenimiento de la fijación. Cada modalidad funcional de movimiento depende de circuitos neuronales específicos que trabajan coordinadamente para codificar la contracción de los músculos oculomotores correspondiente a la posición adecuada en cada momento. Estos sistemas neuronales pueden verse alterados por múltiples procesos neurológicos de diferente naturaleza y localización dando lugar a una variada gama de trastornos oculomotores. Se revisan los aspectos más destacados de la fisiopatología y de los sistemas de registro de los movimientos oculares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;32(supl.3): 9-26, sept.-dic. 2009. tab, graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129501</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fisiopatología y técnicas de registro de los movimientos oculares</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9262^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30636^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5235^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2525^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34315^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10485^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24809^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38389</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5539^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
