<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130779</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-2841</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: Determining the impact of the implementation of the ventilator bundle in the ICU of the Hospital of Sant Joan d'Alacant in terms of variation of the incidence density of mechanical ventilation associated pneumonia (MVAP). Material and Methods: Intervention study before-after, the Preventive Medicine Service organized training activities aimed at improving the compliance with the «ventilator bundle» of the IHI (Institute for Healthcare Improvement). Daily vigilance by means of ICU visits (medical history review) was carried out. Statistic analysis with SPSS 15.0. Calculation of the incidence and incidence density of MVAP in 1000 days of ventilation and bundle compliance percentage. Results: During the period before the intervention (2008) 91 patients with mechanical ventilation were monitored and 20 MVAPs were diagnosed, what meant an annual accumulated incidence of MVAP of 22%, IC 95% (13,5%-30,5%) and an incidence density of 21,6 per-mille, IC 95% (12,1 per-mille - 31,1 per-mille). The intervention started in 2009 (first semester), this year 611 patients were monitored and 14 MVAPs were diagnosed. The MVAP incidence in 2009 was of 10,9%, IC 95% (5,5%- 16,2%), less than in 2008, and the MVAP incidence density of 20,4 per-mille, IC 95% (9,7 per-mille - 31,1 per-mille). Considering as postintervention period the second semester of 2009 and the first semester of 2010, 599 patients were monitored, 10 MVAP were diagnosed, incidence of 9,3% , IC 95% (3,8% - 14,9%). The MVAP incidence density was 12,1 per-mille, IC 95% (4,6 per-mille - 19,5 per-mille). Discussion: After the bundle implantation in our hospital, both the MVAP incidence and incidence density are reduced, an incidence rise is observed in the postintervention period of the second semester of 2009, what could point out the need of continuous training systems for professionals. Conclusions: The bundle or «measures packages» have proven to be an effective tool for the prevention of hospital-acquired infection and MVAP in the ICU. Enabling its widespread implementation in our ICUs while developing continuous training programs for professionals and vigilance systems to assess compliance, would contribute to the continuous improvement process of welfare quality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gea, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antón, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Requena, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aranaz, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Determinar el impacto que la introducción del bundle ventilador en la UCI del Hospital Sant Joan d'Alacant puede tener en términos de variación de la densidad de incidencia de la neumonía asociada a ventilación mecánica (NAVM). Material y método: Estudio de intervención antes-después, el Servicio de Medicina Preventiva organizó actividades de formación para mejorar el cumplimiento del 'bundle ventilador' del IHI (Institute for Healthcare Improvement). Se realizó vigilancia diaria mediante visitas a UCI (revisión de historias clínicas). Análisis estadístico con SPSS 15.0. Cálculo de la incidencia y densidad de incidencia de NAVM por 1.000 días de ventilación y el porcentaje de cumplimiento del bundle. Resultados: Durante el periodo previo a la intervención (2008) se siguieron 91 pacientes con ventilación mecánica y se diagnosticaron 20 NAVM, lo que supuso una incidencia acumulada anual de NAVM del 22%, IC del 95% (13,5%-30,5%) y una densidad de incidencia de 21,6 por mil, IC del 95% (12,1 por mil - 31,1 por mil). La intervención se inició en 2009 (primer semestre), este año se siguieron 611 pacientes y se diagnosticaron 14 NAVM. La incidencia de NAVM en 2009 fue de 10,9%, IC 95% (5,5%-16,2%), inferior al 2008, y la densidad de incidencia de NAVM, de 20,4 por mil, IC 95%(9,7 por mil - 31,1 por mil). Considerando periodo postintervención el segundo semestre de 2009 y primer semestre 2010, se siguieron 599 pacientes, se diagnosticaron 10 NAVM, incidencia de 9,3%, IC 95% (3,8%- 14,9%). La densidad de incidencia de NAVM fue de 12,1 por mil, IC 95% (4,6 por mil -19,5 por mil). Discusión: Tras la implantación del bundle en nuestro hospital, se reduce la incidencia y la densidad de incidencia de NAVM, se observa un ascenso de incidencia en el periodo postintervención del segundo semestre de 2009, lo cual puede indicar la necesidad de sistemas de formación continuada a los profesionales. Conclusiones: Los bundle o «paquetes de medidas» han demostrado ser una herramienta eficaz para la prevención de la infección nosocomial y de la NAVM en la UCI, posibilitar su instauración de forma generalizada en nuestras UCIs y a su vez desarrollar programas de formación continuada a profesionales y sistemas de vigilancia que permitan evaluar el cumplimiento contribuiría al proceso de mejora continua de la calidad asistencial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. prev;20(1): 15-20, ene.-mar. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130779</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicación del 'bundle ventilador' en la unidad de críticos de un hospital universitario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24402^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50259</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52093^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
