<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057420</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Importance of hepatology in the current Spanish health environment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To find out the impact of hepatic diseases on care activity at national and autonomous region level, and in a tertiary hospital with a Hepatology Department. Material and methods: An anlaysis was carried out on BMDS data (Basic Minimum Data Set) from 1999 to 2003. In the study of cases from the Gregorio Marañón Hospital, Madrid, data bases from the years 2000-2004 were used, and indicators were calculated, such as the percentages of digestive diseases of the total hospital discharges, of digestive diseases that were admitted into the Digestive Diseases Department, and of the total discharges form this Department that originated from hepatic diseases. Results: Hepatic diseases represented around 23% of the hospital discharges generated by gastroenterology at national level and about the same at autonomous regional level. Hepatocellular carcinoma shows a slow and sustained increase, reaching 22.7% of discharges, due to hepatic disease, in 2003. The mortality specifically due to hepatic disease was around 12% in the year 2003. In the study carried out in a tertiary hospital, 21.2% of the total hospital discharges were due to digestive diseases, in the last year analysed. Only 12.48% of these had been admitted to the Digestive Diseases Department and more than 50% were attributed to Hepatology. Conclusions: Hepatology is a very important area of health care within Gastroenterology, showing a sustained growth in the last few years</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Clemente, Gerardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, Ana Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vigil, Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Paz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matilla, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Conocer el impacto que las enfermedades hepáticas tienen sobre la actividad asistencial en los ámbitos nacional y autonómico, y en un hospital de tercer nivel con sección de hepatología. Material y métodos: Se ha procedido al análisis de los datos del Conjunto Mínimo Básico de Datos (CMBD) desde 1999 hasta 2003. En el estudio de los casos pertenecientes al Hospital Gregorio Marañón se han utilizado las bases de datos de los años 2000-2004, y se han calculado ciertos indicadores, como el porcentaje de casos de enfermedades digestivas sobre el total de altas hospitalarias, de los pacientes con enfermedades digestivas ingresados en el servicio de aparato digestivo, y sobre el total de altas de dicho servicio las que proceden de enfermedades hepáticas. Resultados: Las enfermedades hepáticas representan alrededor del 23% de las altas producidas en los servicios de gastroenterología a nivel nacional y de forma similar a nivel autonómico. El hepatocarcinoma presenta un incremento lento y sostenido que alcanza el 22,7% de las altas por enfermedades hepáticas en el año 2003. La tasa de mortalidad específica por enfermedades hepáticas se sitúa en el 12% en el año 2003. En el estudio realizado en un hospital de tercer nivel, durante el último año analizado, el 21,2% del total de las altas hospitalarias se debe a una enfermedad digestiva; de estos pacientes, había ingresado en el servicio de aparato digestivo sólo el 12,48%. De las altas del servicio de aparato digestivo, más del 50% se atribuye al área de hepatología. Conclusiones: La hepatología representa un área de atención asistencial de gran importancia dentro de la gastroenterología, y ha presentado un crecimiento sostenido en los últimos años</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;30(5): 255-262, may. 2007. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057420</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Importancia de la hepatología en el entorno sanitario, español, actual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8281^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8287^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17212</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28585</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
