<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047985</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Importance of pharmacovigilance in the family doctor&#146;s clinical practice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pharmacovigilance is a public health activity in which the clinicians are legally and medically involved. The authors describe these implications and provide some definitions of terms that may be useful when evaluating and reporting suspicion of adverse drug reaction. The type of information that the clinicians should provide, if possible, together with some useful instructions to evaluate the causality relationship, are mentioned. Finally, some quantitative procedures for signal generation and some concepts of risk management in pharmacovigilance are explained</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Souto Pais, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borja Villegas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La farmacovigilancia es una actividad de salud pública en la que los clínicos se hallan implicados a nivel médico y legal. Los autores describen dichas implicaciones y proporcionan algunas definiciones de términos que pueden ser útiles a la hora de evaluar y notificar una sospecha de reacción adversa. También se menciona el tipo de información que los clínicos deben proporcionar, si ello es posible, junto con algunas directrices útiles para evaluar la relación de causalidad. Por último, se exponen algunos procedimientos cuantitativos de generación de señales y algunos conceptos de gestión del riesgo en farmacovigilancia</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);32(7): 334-338, ago. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047985</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Importancia de la farmacovigilancia en la práctica del médico de familia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4404^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11253</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32286</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
