<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110787</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparison between VAMA(R) and Berman(R) cannulas for fibroscopic orotracheal intubation in anaesthetised patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. In fibroscopic intubation, the fact of achieving a direct view in real time does not guarantee the correct advance of the endotracheal tube (ET) to its intratracheal position. The use of oral cannulas helps in achieving a free airway in order to pass the fibroscope and the ET. This study compares the VAMA® (V) and Berman® (B) cannulas as regards the time required for the intubation, fibroscopic view, and the ease in positioning the ET. Patients and methods. 90 patients with no signs of difficult airway were randomised into 2 groups, Berman(R) (B) and VAMA(R) (V), depending on the type of cannula employed. After inducing general anaesthesia, they were intubated using a flexible fibroscope. The fibroscope and intubation times were recorded, as well as the quality of the fibroscopic view, and the level of difficulty in positioning the ET. Results. No statistically significant differences were observed between the cannulas, although the intubation time (P=.292) and the difficulty found in positioning the ET were slightly less (P=.447) in the VAMA® group compared to the Berman® group. The vision quality was good with both devices, with only some degree of obstruction being encountered in only 22% of the patients. In no case was there complete obstruction, thus all the patients could be intubated correctly. Conclusions. The VAMA® cannula is an effective alternative to the classic cannulas for fibreoptic assisted intubation. Furthermore, the novel design provides advantages for the correct orientation of the fiberscope and the withdrawal of the cannula after intubation(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castañeda Pascual, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dorronsoro Auzmendi, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Vizcaíno, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Unzué Rico, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murillo Jaso, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Batllori Gastón, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. En la intubación fibroscópica, el hecho de gozar de una visión directa y en tiempo real, no nos asegura el correcto avance del tubo endotraqueal (TET) hasta su posición intratraqueal. El empleo de cánulas orales ayuda a la consecución de una vía aérea libre para el paso del fibroscopio y el TET. Comparamos la cánula VAMA(R) y la cánula Berman(R) en cuanto a tiempo necesario para la intubación, visión fibroscópica y facilidad de paso del TET. Pacientes y método. Noventa pacientes sin criterios de vía aérea difícil fueron randomizados en dos grupos, B y V, según el tipo de cánula empleada. Tras inducir anestesia general, se procedió a la intubación con fibroscopio flexible, midiendo tiempos de fibroscopia e intubación, intentos de fibroscopia, calidad de visión fibroscópica y grado de dificultad en el paso del TET. Resultados. No se obtuvieron diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre ambas cánulas, si bien, la tendencia apuntaba a menores tiempo de intubación (p=0,292) y menor dificultad al paso del TET (p=0,447). Con ambos dispositivos, la calidad de visión fue buena, encontrando únicamente algún grado de obstrucción en la vía aérea en el 22% de los pacientes. En ningún caso esta obstrucción fue total, por lo que todos los pacientes pudieron ser intubados correctamente. Conclusiones. La cánula VAMA® representa una alternativa eficaz a las clásicas cánulas de intubación fibroasistida. Además, su novedoso diseño ofrece ciertas ventajas para la correcta orientación del fibroscopio y la retirada de la cánula tras la intubación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;60(3): 134-141, mar. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110787</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de las cánulas VAMA(R) y Berman(R) para la intubación fibroscópica orotraqueal en pacientes anestesiados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d405^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7603^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d405^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d405^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7603^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7601^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7601^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
