<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143058</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cost-effectiveness analysis of universal screening for thyroid disease in pregnant women in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the cost-effectiveness of universal screening for thyroid disease in pregnant women in Spain as compared to high risk screening and no screening. Methodology: A decision-analytic model comparing the incremental cost per quality-adjusted life year (QALY) of universal screening versus high risk screening and versus no screening. was used for the pregnancy and postpartum period. Probabilities from randomized controlled trials were considered for adverse obstetrical outcomes. A Markov model was used to assess the lifetime period after the first postpartum year and account for development of overt hypothyroidism. The main assumptions in the model and use of resources were assessed by local clinical experts. The analysis considered direct healthcare costs only. Results: Universal screening gained .011 QALYs over high risk screening and .014 QALYS over no screening. Total direct costs per patient were &#128;5,786 for universal screening, &#128;5,791 for high risk screening, and &#128;5,781 for no screening. Universal screening was dominant compared to risk-based screening and a very cost-effective alternative as compared to no screening. Use of universal screening instead of high risk screening would result in &#128;2,653,854 annual savings for the Spanish National Health System. Conclusions: Universal screening for thyroid disease in pregnant women in the first trimester is dominant in Spain as compared to risk-based screening, and is cost-effective as compared to no screening (incremental cost-effectiveness ratio of &#128;374 per QALY). Moreover, it allows diagnosing and treating cases of clinical and subclinical hypothyroidism that may not be detected when only high-risk women are screened (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Hernández, Julia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Alcántara, Ferrán</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Polanco Sánchez, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balsa Barro, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Donnay Candil, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo Palomo, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la relación coste-efectividad del cribado universal para la enfermedad tiroidea en mujeres embarazadas frente al cribado selectivo y no realizar cribado. Metodología: Modelo analítico de decisión para embarazo y periodo posparto que compara los años de vida ajustados por la calidad (AVAC) obtenidos gracias a la realización de un cribado universal frente al cribado de alto riesgo y no realizar cribado. Se consideraron las probabilidades de los ensayos aleatorios controlados para los resultados obstétricos adversos. Se utilizó un modelo de Markov para valorar el período de vida tras el primer año después del parto y considerar la posible progresión a hipotiroidismo clínico. Los principales supuestos del modelo, así como el uso de recursos fueron evaluados por expertos clínicos. Se consideraron únicamente los costes sanitarios directos. Resultados: Realizar un cribado universal produce 0,011 AVAC más que el cribado selectivo y 0,014 AVAC más que la alternativa de no realizar cribado. Los costes totales directos por paciente fueron de 5.786 &#128; para el cribado universal, 5.791 &#128; para cribado por riesgo y de 5.781 &#128; sin cribado. El paso del cribado selectivo por riesgo al cribado universal puede ahorrar 2.653.854 &#128; al sistema sanitario español. Conclusiones: El cribado universal de enfermedad tiroidea durante el primer trimestre de gestación es una estrategia dominante frente al cribado selectivo y coste-efectiva con respecto al no cribado (ratio coste-efectividad incremental de 374 &#128; por AVAC), que permite además diagnosticar y tratar casos de hipotiroidismo clínico y subclínico que podrían no ser detectados al cribar solo mujeres con alto riesgo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;62(7): 322-330, ago.-sept. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143058</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis coste-efectividad del cribado universal de la enfermedad tiroidea en mujeres embarazadas en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7160^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14348^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14347^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7217^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
