<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043650</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Low carbohydrate diets versus low fat diets</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The substantial increase in the prevalence of the obesity in the Western world over the past few decades has prompted the creation of strategies to help control this problem. The real effectiveness of any medical therapy will depend on adherence to the treatment prescribed. In the case of obesity, adherence will depend on the patient's motivation to lose weight and on the intrinsic characteristics of the reducing diet, and will be reinforced by positive results. In recent years, low carbohydrate diets have been proposed as an alternative to the traditional low energy and low fat diets. Since 2003, several randomized studies lasting more than 6 months have assessed their efficacy by comparing them with other nutritional strategies. In conclusion, independently of other metabolic considerations, weight loss at 12 months was no greater with low carbohydrate diets than with other alternatives, fundamentally because of low adherence to the diet itself</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ballesteros-Pomar, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano-Rodríguez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Corral, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguado, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El importante aumento de la prevalencia de la obesidad durante las últimas décadas en el mundo occidental impulsa la creación de estrategias terapéuticas que ayuden a su control. La eficacia real de cualquier tratamiento médico dependerá de su cumplimiento. En el caso de la obesidad, el cumplimiento dependerá de la motivación del paciente para perder peso y de las características intrínsecas del propio plan dietético y se reforzará con la eficacia del propio tratamiento. Los tratamientos con dietas bajas en hidratos de carbono se han propuesto como alternativa en los últimos años a las tradicionales hipocalóricas y hipograsas. Desde 2003, varios estudios aleatorizados de más de 6 meses de duración abordan su eficacia comparándolas con otras estrategias nutricionales. Como conclusión, independientemente de otras consideraciones metabólicas, se constata que la disminución ponderal lograda a los 12 meses no es superior con las dietas bajas en hidratos de carbono respecto a otras alternativas, fundamentalmente por no estimular la adherencia al plan dietético</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;53(3): 209-217, mar. 2006. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043650</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dietas bajas en hidratos de carbono frente a dietas bajas en grasas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32288^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4071^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
