<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129328</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Women-and Child-Friendly Institutional Strategies with an integral approach in Colombia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It is uncommon to implement and document a maternal and child healthcare strategy on a territorial and institutional level is infrequent. Therefore, we aimed to describe the experience of a consulting team composed of two physicians, two nurses and two nutritionists, whose purpose was to support the introduction of the Women- and Child-Friendly Institutional Strategy with an integral approach in 25 healthcare institutions in three Colombian departments (Cauca, Huila and Nariño), according to unmet basic needs. The Women- and Child-Friendly Institutional Strategy, considered a senior management strategy, promotes a specific method that allows monitoring of institutions during the implementation of a health and nutritional care strategy for women and children, and offers them the possibility of voluntarily becoming accredited as a Women- and Child-Friendly Institutions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Farías-Jiménez, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Botero-Uribe, Inés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trujillo-Ramírez, Kenny Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arocha-Zuluaga, Gina Paola</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Implementar y documentar una estrategia de atención en salud materna e infantil de ámbito territorial y de las instituciones de salud no es frecuente. Por esta razón, el objetivo es presentar la experiencia realizada por un equipo consultor (dos médicos, dos nutricionistas y dos enfermeras), cuyo propósito era apoyar la implementación de la Estrategia Instituciones Amigas de la Mujer y la Infancia con enfoque integral en 25 instituciones prestadoras de salud de tres departamentos de Colombia (Cauca, Huila y Nariño), seleccionados según necesidades básicas insatisfechas. Considerada una estrategia de alta gerencia, plantea una metodología concreta que permite seguir a las instituciones una ruta exitosa, para implementar una estrategia de atención en salud y nutrición materna e infantil, y les ofrece la posibilidad de acreditarse voluntariamente como una Institución Amiga de la Mujer y la Infancia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;28(4): 326-329, jul.-ago. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129328</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrategia Instituciones Amigas de la Mujer y la Infancia, con enfoque integral en Colombia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3285^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23060^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2710^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3137</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6424^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3222^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
