<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98306</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-755X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Autism is a disorder of unknown origin. Its heterogeneous symptoms, together with the disparity of criteria used in its research, make its study difficult. Several etiological models have been proposed, which have generated various hypotheses. However, a clear and definitive explanation about its genesis has not yet proved possible. The aim of this article is to evaluate a variety of theoretical postulates that are intended to identify the pathogenic mechanisms by correlating autism?s variable and heterogeneous characteristics with different events (medical, genetic, social, family, perigestational, and neurological events, among others). In this regard, it is concluded that the most adequate explanation for the etiology of autism suggests a biological predisposition originating from both environment and physical condition, together with a number of risk and protection factors that still remain unidentified (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Taboada Ares, Eva María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Gómez, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivas Torres, Rosa María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El autismo es un trastorno de causa desconocida. Sus manifestaciones heterogéneas, junto con la disparidad de criterios utilizados en las investigaciones, dificultan su estudio. Se han propuesto diversos modelos etiológicos que han generado distintas hipótesis. Sin embargo, sigue sin poder ofrecerse una explicación clara y definitiva sobre su génesis. El objetivo de este artículo es valorar los diferentes postulados teóricos que tratan de identificar los mecanismos patogénicos correlacionando las características inconstantes y heterogéneas del autismo con acontecimientos de distinta naturaleza -médicos, genéticos, sociofamiliares, perigestacionales, neurológicos, entre otros-. Al respecto, puede concluirse que la explicación más acertada en la etiología del autismo apunta a una predisposición biológica que proviene del propio entorno y de la constitución personal así como un, todavía no identificado, número de factores tanto de riesgo como protectores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. educ. (Madr.);15(2): 127-121, jul.-dic. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98306</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Etiología del Autismo: un Tema a Debate</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4258^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
