<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76512</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-1375</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of an educational programme aimed at school children on donating organs</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There are two aspects that play a part in organ donation:one is the refusal of the family and the other is the cultural level of the families. Over eight years, our hospital unit has developed health information and dissemination campaigns aimed mainly at sensitising the population on the importance of organ donation for the community. These campaigns have been carried out through an Educational Programme aimed at school children from 16 to 18.The aim of the study is to evaluate the Educational Programme since its beginnings in 1997 to the present day and to transmit our experience in giving health education to the community from the hospital area. An observational, descriptive study has been done and two aspects have been borne in mind:1. The demand from Schools for these sessions, which have included them as an extra-curricular activity.2. The replies to a questionnaire with three questions that teachers completed in the months of February-March 2005 and which scored on a scale of one toten.268 educational sessions were performed among a total3,758 pupils over 8 years, with an annual average of33.5 (ranging from 31 to 36 sessions). Pupils came from31 Schools with an annual average participation of 18.5centres. The mean score on the content was 9.06 (ranging between 7 and 10 points). The average score on the dynamics used was 8.84 (ranging from 6 to 10points). The average score for the reception of the Educational Programme by the pupils was 8.65 (ranging from 5 to 10 points).The results obtained indicate that the Educational Programme was well received and can be considered a good strategy to reach a certain sector of population, which in turn is an excellent transmitter of information among relatives and friends (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Matamala Gastón, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luque Vadillo, Emilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Jansana, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Quintana, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Villalba, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barroso Ortín, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferret Piñera, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Hay dos aspectos que influyen en la donación de órganos: uno es la negativa familiar y el otro, es el nivel cultural de las familias. A lo largo de ocho años, desde nuestro ámbito hospitalario se han desarrollado campañas de información y divulgación sanitaria canalizadas, fundamentalmente, a sensibilizar a la población sobre la importancia que tiene la donación de órganos para la comunidad. Estas campañas se han llevado a cabo mediante la realización de un Programa Educativo orientado a escolares de 16 a 18 años. El objetivo de este estudio es evaluar el Programa Educativo desde su inicio en 1997 hasta la actualidad y transmitir nuestra experiencia de realizar educación sanitaria a la comunidad desde el ámbito hospitalario. Se ha realizado un estudio descriptivo observacional y se han tenido en cuenta dos aspectos: 1. La demanda por parte de los Centros Escolares de estas sesiones que las han incluido como actividad extraescolar.2. La respuesta a un cuestionario con tres preguntas que los profesores han cumplimentado durante los meses de febrero-marzo del año 2005 y que han puntuado con una escala del uno al diez. Se realizaron 268 sesiones educativas a un total de3.758 alumnos durante 8 años, siendo la media anual de 33,5 (rango de 31 y 36 sesiones). Concurrieron los alumnos de 31 Centros Escolares con una media de participación anual de 18,5 centros. La puntuación media sobre el contenido fue 9,06 (rango de 7 y 10 puntos).La puntuación media sobre la dinámica utilizada fue 8,84 (rango de 6 y 10 puntos). La puntuación media sobre la acogida del Programa Educativo por los alumnos fue 8,65 (rango de 5 y 10 puntos).Los resultados obtenidos indican que el Programa Educativo está bien valorado y se puede considerar una buena estrategia para llegar a un determinado grupo de población que a su vez resulta ser excelente transmisor de la información entre sus familiares y amigos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Enferm. Nefrol;9(3): 177-181, jul.-sept. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76512</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de un programa educativo sobre la donación de órganos dirigido a escolares</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14408^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28461</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16836</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19279^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
