<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165723</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Childhood excess weight in Spain from 2006 to 2012. Determinants and parental misperception</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: Due to the high prevalence of childhood obesity in Spain, we analyzed changes in its prevalence from 2006 to 2007 and from 2011 to 2012, as well as diet, sleep, and sedentary habits in 5- to 14-year-olds and parental misperceptions about their children's excess weight. Methods: The sample was from the Spanish National Health Surveys for 2006 to 2007 (n = 5590) and for 2011 to 2012 (n = 3601). Data were collected by trained personnel through telephone interviews with parents/guardians. Weight and height were self-reported and the International Obesity Task Force cutpoints were used to define overweight and obesity. Results: The prevalence of childhood excess weight was 30.1% from 2006 to 2007 and 29.7% from 2011 to 2012, while that of childhood obesity was 9.6% and 9%, respectively. Parental misperception of childhood excess weight increased from 60.8% to 71.4% (P &lt; .001). Daily consumption of vegetables increased by 7.8%, while that of soft drinks and snacks decreased. This decrease was greatest in children from families with a low socioeconomic status, who also decreased their consumption of sweets and fast food. Adherence to sleep recommendations decreased by 5%, but adherence to recommended sedentary time did not change. Conclusions: High childhood overweight and obesity rates remained stable in Spain from 2006 to 2007 and from 2011 to 2012, but there was an increase in parental misperception of childhood excess weight. Despite reduced consumption of soft drinks and snacks, there was low adherence to dietary recommendations, hours of sleep, and sedentary habits (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz Barbero,  Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramiro González, María D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Royo Bordonada, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: Dada la gran prevalencia de obesidad infantil en España, se analiza su evolución entre 2006-2007 y 2011-2012, junto con dieta, hábitos de sueño y sedentarismo en la población de 5-14 años y la percepción parental del exceso de peso infantil. Métodos: La muestra procede de las Encuestas Nacionales de Salud de 2006-2007 (n = 5.590) y 2011-2012 (n = 3.601). Las encuestas se realizaron mediante entrevista telefónica a los padres/tutores por personal entrenado. La información sobre peso y talla es la declarada por los encuestados, y se aplicaron los puntos de corte de sobrepeso/obesidad de la International Obesity Task Force. Resultados: La prevalencia de exceso de peso fue del 30,1% en 2006-2007 y del 29,7% en 2011-2012, y la de obesidad, del 9,6 y el 9% respectivamente. La percepción errónea del exceso de peso pasó del 60,8 al 71,4% (p &lt; 0,001). La ingesta diaria de verdura aumentó un 7,8% y la de refrescos y aperitivos disminuyó. Esta caída fue mayor en menores de clase social baja, que también redujeron el consumo de dulces y comida rápida. Mientras el cumplimiento de las recomendaciones sobre horas de sueño disminuyó un 5%, el de las relativas al tiempo máximo de actividad sedentaria no varió. Conclusiones: Las altas cifras de obesidad y sobrepeso infantil permanecieron estables en España entre 2006-2007 y 2011-2012. El error perceptivo del exceso de peso aumentó entre los padres. Aunque disminuyó el consumo de refrescos y aperitivos, se observó un bajo cumplimiento de las recomendaciones dietéticas y las relativas a horas de sueño y ocio sedentario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;70(8): 656-663, ago. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165723</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Exceso de peso infantil en España 2006-2012. Determinantes y error de percepción parental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55220^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15295</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
