<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145114</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-6581</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship of chronological age and sexual maturity with skeletal maturity by magnetic resonance imaging of the distal radial epiphysis in adolescent football players</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Although the grade of fusion of the left distal radial epiphysis (LDRE) observed by magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) has been linked to chronological age (CA), its relationship to Tanner stage of the genitals in the Latin American population is unknown. Objective: To evaluate the relationship of CA and sexual maturity with skeletal maturity (SM) determined by MRI of the LDRE in adolescent football players from Medellin, Colombia. Materials and methods: Cross-sectional study that included 60 male football players with certified legal age between 12 and 18 years. Medical evaluation and MRI of the LDRE using a 1.5 T scanner was performed according to a described protocol. The image reading was performed by 3 blinded evaluators. SM was classified as: A: immature; B: developing; C: mature, and interand intra-observer variability was assessed. Results: Among the football players included in the study, the average body mass index and body fat were 19.6 ± 2.0 kg/m2 and 11.1 ± 1.2%, respectively. A correlation of CA and the Tanner stage of genital maturity with SM (Kendall&#146;s Tau b 0.686 and 0.693, respectively; P &lt; .001) was found. All players classified as stage C were 17 or older and Tanner stage V. The inter-observer and intraobserver agreement showed a kappa index of 0.36 (P &lt; .001) and 0.60 (P &lt; .001), respectively (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bolívar, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sandoval, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallo, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Osorio, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dib, Gabriel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Aunque el grado de fusión de la epífisis del radio distal izquierdo (ERDI) por resonancia magnética nuclear (RMN) se ha relacionado con la edad cronológica (EC), se desconoce su relación con el Tanner genital en población latinoamericana. Objetivo: Evaluar la relación de la EC y la maduración sexual con la maduración ósea (MO) por RMN de la ERDI en futbolistas adolescentes de la ciudad de Medellín, Colombia. Materiales y métodos: Estudio transversal que incluyó 60 futbolistas hombres con edad legal certificada entre 12 y 18 años. Se realizó una evaluación médica y una RMN de la ERDI con un resonador de 1.5 T según un protocolo descrito. La lectura de la imagen fue realizada por 3 evaluadores cegados. Se determinó la MO en tres estadios (A: inmaduros; B: en desarrollo; C: maduros) y se evaluó la variabilidad inter e intra-observador. Resultados: Entre los futbolistas incluidos, se encontró un promedio de índice de masa corporal y porcentaje de grasa corporal de 19,6 ± 2,0 Kg/m2 y 1,1 ± 1,2%, respectivamente. Se encontró correlación de la EC y el estadio de maduración por Tanner genital con la MO (Tau_b de Kendall 0,686 y 0,693, respectivamente; p &lt; 0,001). Todos los jugadores clasificados en el grado C tenían 17 o más años y Tanner estadio V. La concordancia inter-observador e intra-observador, mostró un índice kappa de 0,36 (p &lt; 0,001) y 0,60 (p &lt; 0,001), respectivamente. Conclusión: Se encontró relación de la EC y la maduración sexual con la MO por RMN de la ERDI en futbolistas adolescentes. La clasificación por grados de MO en 3 categorías, podría ser más práctica y tener implicaciones para la competencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apunts, Med. esport (Internet);50(188): 129-137, oct.-dic. 2015. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145114</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación de la edad cronológica y la maduración sexual con la maduración ósea por resonancia magnética nuclear de la epífisis del radio distal en futbolistas adolescentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23151</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13121^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4918^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38865^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
