<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058355</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cognitive impairment and basic personal autonomy in old age adults</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study pretends to meet the mental condition of aged and what activities of the basic personal autonomy area part of its repertoire, comparing these variables, attending to sex and age. Also it has wanted to be investigated on the degree of relation between the cognitive impair-ment in the major persons and his level of autonomy in basic activities The purpose of this investigation ist to detect the most deficit areas, which could be the object in the future for psichological, social and sanitary interventions in this field.    The results of this investigation provide us with a reliable knowledge, till now unknown, about the real situation of these persons, aged between 60 and 102</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Hernández, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sicilia Molina, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio pretende conocer el estado mental de personas mayores y qué actividades de la autonomía personal básica forman parte de su repertorio, comparando estas variables en función del sexo y la edad. También se ha querido investigar sobre el grado de relación entre el deterioro cognitivo en las personas mayores y su nivel de autonomía en actividades básicas (vestirse, lavarse, comer&#133;). El propósito de la presente investigación es el de detectar las áreas más deficitarias que pudieran ser objeto de futuras intervenciones psicosociosanitarias en este sector. Los resultados obtenidos en esta investigación nos proporcionan un conocimiento fiable, hasta ahora inexistente, sobre las necesidades básicas que presentan estos sujetos, con edades comprendidas entre los 60 y los 102 años</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;23(2): 272-281, dic. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058355</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Deterioro cognitivo y autonomía personal básica en personas mayores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8300^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1079^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36316</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28628</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
