<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044689</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nutrition intake of Cuban type 2 diabetics differs from recommendations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Several studies have demonstrated theefficacy of lifestyle interventions (targeting diet andexercise) in reduction of risk of type 2 diabetes.Objective: To document the daily intake of energy,macronutrients and selected antioxidant micronutrientsof Cuban type 2 diabetics and compare them with theCuban and the ADA recommendations.Methods: 3-day food diaries from 56 non-obese type 2diabetics were obtained. Nutrient analysis was performedby the nutritional software CERES based on the CubanFood Composition Table. The contribution of 10 foodgroups to total energy intake, total fats, saturated, polyunsaturatedand essential fatty acids were calculated andgraphically represented.Results: A high proportion of diabetics exceeded therecommendations for total and saturated fats and did notreach the recommendations for carbohydrates, fiber,vitamin E and zinc.Conclusions: We advise to decrease total and saturatedfat intakes by reducing the intake of chicken with skin,pork and its derivatives. Fish consumption should beadvised as it is a good source of zinc. Since eggs are richin vitamin E and zinc, their consumption should beincreased under certain limits. Fat rich diets should bereplaced by low glycaemic load diets rich in complexcarbohydrates and fiber</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Enriquez, Yanik</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Christophe, Armand B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: Múltiples estudios han demostrado laeficacia de intervenciones en el estilo de vida (dirigidoshacia la dieta y el ejercicio) en la reducción del riesgo desufrir diabetes mellitus tipo 2.Objetivo: Documentar la ingestión diaria de energía,macronutrientes y micronutrientes antioxidantes seleccionadosde diabéticos tipo 2 cubanos y compararlascon las recomendaciones cubanas y de la ADA.Métodos: Se aplicaron encuestas dietéticas de 3 días a56 diabéticos tipo 2 no obesos. Las mismas fueronanalizadas a través del programa CERES, basado en laTabla Cubana de Composición de Alimentos. Se calculóy graficó la contribución relativa de 10 grupos de alimentosa la energía total, las grasas totales, saturadas,poliinsaturadas y esenciales.Resultados: Una gran proporción de los diabéticos excediólas recomendaciones para las grasas totales y saturadaspero no las alcanzó para los carbohidratos, fibra,vitamina E y cinc.Conclusiones: Aconsejamos disminuir la ingestión degrasas totales y saturadas reduciendo el consumo depollo con piel, carne de cerdo y sus derivados. Debeaconsejarse el consumo de pescados y huevos al serfuentes ricas en cinc y vitamina E. Las dietas ricas engrasas deben ser sustituidas por dietas con baja cargaglicémica ricas en carbohidratos complejos y fibra</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;10(4): 178-185, oct.-dic. 2004. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044689</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La ingestión de nutrientes de diabéticos tipo 2 cubanos difiere de las recomendaciones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d16525^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32687^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d979^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32415</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32687^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4499^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2181^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13841^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13841^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3482^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
