<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162777</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Detection of high biliary and fecal viral loads in patients with chronic hepatitis C virus infection</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The life cycle of the hepatitis C virus (HCV) is closely associated with lipid metabolism.  Recently, NPC1L1 (a cholesterol transporter) has been reported to function as an HCV receptor. This receptor is expressed in the hepatocyte canalicular membrane and in the intestine; serving as a key transporter for the cholesterol enterohepatic cycle. Objectives: We hypothesized that HCV might have a similar cycle, so we aimed to study the presence of HCV in bile and stools of infected patients. Materials and methods: Blood, feces, and duodenal bile samples were collected from patients infected with HCV. The biliary viral load was normalized to the bile salt concentration of each sample and the presence of HCV core protein was also evaluated. A total of 12 patients were recruited. HCV RNA was detected in the bile from ten patients. Results: The mean viral load was 2.5log10IU/60mg bile salt. In the stool samples, HCV RNA was detected in ten patients (mean concentration 2.7log10IU/g of feces). Conclusions: HCV RNA is readily detectable and is present at relatively high concentrations in the bile and stool samples of infected patients. This may be relevant as a source of infection in men who have sex with men. Biliary HCV secretion may perhaps play a role in the persistence of viral infection via an enterohepatic cycle of the virus or intrahepatic spread (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Labbé, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soza, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miquel, Juan Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monrroy, Hugo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pino, Karla</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Lastra, Marcelo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Angulo, Jenniffer</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El ciclo de vida del virus de la hepatitis C (VHC) está estrechamente ligado al metabolismo lipídico. Recientemente, se ha descrito que el NPC1L1 (un transportador del colesterol) actúa como un receptor del VHC. Este receptor se expresa en la membrana canalicular de los hepatocitos y en el intestino, y actúa como uno de los principales transportadores durante la circulación enterohepática del colesterol. Objetivos: Planteamos la hipótesis de que el VHC podría tener un ciclo similar, por lo que nuestro objetivo fue estudiar la presencia del VHC en la bilis y en las heces de pacientes infectados. Materiales y métodos: Se obtuvieron muestras de sangre, heces y bilis duodenal de pacientes infectados por el VHC. La concentración vírica en la bilis se normalizó respecto a la concentración de sales biliares de cada muestra y también se evaluó la presencia de la proteína central del VHC. Se reclutaron un total de 12 pacientes. Se detectó el ARN del VHC en la bilis de 10 pacientes. Resultados: La media de la concentración vírica fue 2,5log10UI/60mg de sales biliares. En las muestras de heces, se detectó el ARN del VHC en 10 pacientes (media de la concentración 2,7log10UI/g de heces). Conclusiones: El ARN del VHC es fácilmente detectable y está presente en concentraciones relativamente elevadas en las muestras de bilis y heces de pacientes infectados. Esto puede tener importancia como foco de infección en varones que mantienen relaciones sexuales con otros varones. Es posible que la secreción biliar del VHC pueda desempeñar un papel en la persistencia de la virosis a través de la circulación enterohepática del virus o la propagación intrahepática (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;40(5): 339-347, mayo 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162777</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Detección de concentraciones víricas elevadas en la bilis y en las heces de pacientes con infección crónica por el virus de la hepatitis C</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33344^s32386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31852^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1671^s32386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33344^s22069</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33123</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5346^s32386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
