<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84155</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Coracoclavicular joint. Case report and review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: A literature review is made in reference to the presentation of a case of coracoclavicular joint. Clinical case: A 56-year-old male presented with left scapulohumeral luxation. The X-ray study moreover revealed the presence of a left coracoclavicular joint. Discussion: The described anomaly is present in 0.6-30% of all cases, depending on the literature source. Discussion focuses on whether the joint is congenital or acquired, and on whether certain morphometric characteristics of the clavicle and scapula predispose to its development. The condition is generally asymptomatic, and constitutes a casual radiological finding, though symptoms can also develop. Symptomatic cases are treated with infiltrations, and resection is rarely necessary. Conclusion: A coracoclavicular joint is not a rare anomaly (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramberde, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Presentar un caso de articulación coracoclavicular. Se hace una revisión bibliográfica sobre el tema. Caso clínico: Varón de 56 años que presenta una luxación escapulohumeral izquierda que presentaba además una articulación coracoclavicular izquierda. Discusión: Es un anomalía presente en el 0,6&#150;30% de los casos y se discute si es congénita o adquirida o si determinadas características morfométricas de la clavícula y de la escápula pueden predisponer a su desarrollo. Generalmente es asintomática y se descubre casualmente con la imagen. Los casos sintomáticos se tratan con infiltraciones y raramente será necesaria su extirpación. Conclusión: La articulación coroclavicular no es una anomalía infrecuente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);20(3): 161-163, jul.-sept. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84155</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Articulación coracoclavicular. Caso clínico y revisión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d179^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13167^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13163^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d179^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2992^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33758^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d179^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13163^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d179^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d179^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13167^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13167^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13163^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
