<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76128</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Obesity and metabolic syndrome in adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In spite of the lack of a uniform definition for metabolic syndrome in pediatry, recent studies have shown that it develops during childhood and is highly prevalent among children and adolescents who suffer from obesity. In light of the current epidemic of obesity in this age category in western countries, and specifically in Mexico, it becomes essential to know the means to prevent, detect and treat this syndrome. Nurses play an important role in promoting childhood health with regards to metabolic syndrome. To put into practice the strategies which resolve underlying problems related with this syndrome is a priority for the well-being of this age group. These strategies should include the application and management of public policies; the collaboration by health services, social services and schools; but, furthermore, the prevention and the management of this syndrome require a family commitment, while the changes in living habits benefit the entire family. This review article proposes to introduce prevention, diagnostic and treatment strategies which nursing personnel can carry out while dealing with metabolic syndrome in adolescents(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cortés Castell, Ernesto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cárdenas Villarreal, Velia Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rizo-Baeza, Maria M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A pesar de la falta de una definición uniforme del Síndrome Metabólico (SM) en pediatría, estudios recientes han demostrado que se desarrolla durante la niñez y es altamente prevalente entre los niños y adolescentes con obesidad. En vista de la actual epidemia de obesidad en esta franja etaria en los países occidentales, y en concreto en México, es de suma importancia conocer las directrices de prevención, detección y tratamiento. La enfermera tiene un rol importante en la promoción de la salud infantil en el síndrome metabólico, poner en práctica las estrategias que resuelvan problemas de las causas subyacentes relacionados con él es una prioridad para el bienestar de esta población. Las estrategias deben incluir aplicación y gestión de políticas públicas, colaboración de los servicios sanitarios, sociales y escuelas pero, más aún, la prevención y el manejo del síndrome constituyen una cuestión de la familia, y los cambios de la forma de vida beneficiarán a toda ella.  El presente trabajo de revisión tiene como propósito dar a conocer las estrategias de prevención, diagnóstico y tratamiento que puede realizar el personal de enfermería en relación al síndrome metabólico en los adolescentes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;32(3): 186-192, mar. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76128</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Obesidad y síndrome metabólico en adolescentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
