<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038894</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Climate change and Kyoto protocol. Science and strategies. Obligations for Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article presents climate change as the major environmentalproblem of our time. A result of the so-called "greenhouse effect", climatechange is caused by certain gases, the concentrations in theatmosphere of which are growing exponentially. The consequences ofthese gases are going to be felt throughout the entire biosphere, fromweather phenomenon to humans, creating a uncertain panoramawhich is going to be requiring some fast-paced adaptation on the partof all species. This is not, however, an irreversible process, takingaction thus being possible and necessary, by combining education andlawmaking measures brought into being within the timeframes and tothe extents set forth under the 1997 Kyoto Protocol. Spain will be oneof the most highly-affected countries, and its strategy may thereforemean a highly-valuable tool for correcting the deviations caused andcontributing to the urgent control of global emissions</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Velázquez de Castro González, Federico</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El artículo presenta el cambio climático como el principal problemaambiental de nuestro tiempo. Consecuencia del llamado efectoinvernadero, el cambio climático es provocado por determinadosgases cuyas concentraciones atmosféricas crecen con perfil exponencial.Sus consecuencias se dejarán sentir en toda la biosfera, desdelos fenómenos meteorológicos al ser humano, creando un panoramaincierto que exigirá una rápida adaptación de todas las especies.No es, sin embargo, un proceso irreversible por lo que la actuación esposible y necesaria, combinando la educación y las medidas legislativas,manifestadas en los plazos y cantidades establecidas por elProtocolo de Kioto de 1997. España será uno de los países más afectadosy por ello su estrategia puede suponer un instrumento valiosoque corrija las desviaciones producidas y contribuya al urgente controlde las emisiones globales</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;79(2): 191-201, mar.-abr. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038894</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambio climático y protocolo de Kioto. Ciencia y estrategias. Compromisos para España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3266^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7555</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31430</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31494</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
