<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039176</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Calcium intake in Spanish women aged between 45 and 65 years old</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine whether the current diet of Spanish women provides adequate calcium intake to prevent osteoporosis and whether calcium supplements are used by gynecologists as prophylaxis and/or treatment of osteopenia/osteoporosis. Women living in a coastal region (Valencia) and an interior region (Madrid) were studied. Material and method: We performed an open study in 250 postmenopausal women to determine dietary calcium intake. Eighty-eight gynecologists were surveyed to determine their opinion of dietary calcium intake and the use of calcium supplements in osteoporosis prevention and/or treatment. Results: Seventy-three percent of the gynecologists surveyed believed calcium intake in women aged between 45 and 65 years old was insufficient to prevent osteoporosis. Only 51% prescribed calcium for prophylaxis while 85% used calcium supplements together with antiresorptive drugs and bone-forming agents in the treatment of osteopenia/osteoporosis. Seventy percent did not refer women to rheumatology clinics and 67% included densitometry in the protocol of menopausal women. Conclusions: Gynecologists believe that dietary calcium intake in Spanish women aged 45-65 years old and living in the areas studied was insufficient to prevent osteoporosis. Consensus is lacking on whether dietary calcium supplements can produce remission of bone loss; 50% prescribed calcium as prophylaxis in women in this age group. Calcium supplementation was usually accompanied by an antiresorptive drug. The most widespread opinion was that calcium inhibits bone resorption and consequently that it can be useful in the treatment of bone diseases causing substantial resorption such as postmenopausal osteoporosis</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arévalo, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olleros, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grandas, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rebollo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arriaza, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer si la dieta actual de la mujer española aporta la cantidad de calcio necesaria para prevenir la osteoporosis y si los suplementos de calcio son empleados por los ginecólogos como profilaxis y/o tratamiento de la osteopenia/osteoporosis. Para ello, se estudiaron mujeres de una zona costera (Valencia) y una zona del interior (Madrid). Material y método: Estudio abierto de 250 mujeres posmenopáusicas para conocer el consumo de calcio en su dieta y en el que 88 ginecólogos opinan sobre el consumo de calcio en la dieta de las mujeres posmenopáusicas, y el empleo de suplementos de calcio en la prevención y/o tratamiento de la osteoporosis. Resultados: El 73% de los médicos encuestados opina que las mujeres de edades comprendidas entre 45 y 65 años no consumen en su dieta la cantidad de calcio necesaria para prevenir la osteoporosis. Sólo el 51% de los ginecólogos prescribe calcio de forma profiláctica, mientras que el 85% emplea suplementos de calcio junto con fármacos antirresortivos o agentes de formación ósea en el tratamiento de la osteopenia/osteoporosis. El 70% no deriva a las mujeres al reumatólogo y el 67% de los médicos incluye la densitometría en el protocolo de la mujer menopáusica. Conclusiones: Los ginecólogos opinan que las mujeres españolas de las zonas estudiadas con edades entre 45 y 65 años no consumen en su dieta la cantidad de calcio necesaria para prevenir la osteoporosis. Un 50% prescribe calcio de forma profiláctica a las mujeres en edades comprendidas entre 45 y 65 años, al no haber acuerdo en si un aporte suplementario de calcio en la dieta es una medida terapéutica que puede lograr una remisión del deterioro óseo. De forma mayoritaria el calcio acompaña a cualquier fármaco antirresortivo. La opinión más generalizada es que el calcio inhibe la resorción ósea y que, consecuentemente, puede ser de utilidad en el tratamiento de las enfermedades óseas que cursan con mayor resorción como sucede con la osteoporosis posmenopáusica</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);48(7): 338-344, jul. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039176</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consumo de calcio por la mujer española de entre 45 y 65 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24502^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28261^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24823^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1876^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24823^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23096^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24543^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1876^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30227^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
