<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108998</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The autistic syndrome or the autism spectrum disorders: a case of Becker muscular dystrophy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The autism spectrum disorders (ASD) are a heterogeneous group of diseases with many possible causes (mostly of genetic origin, that today are known in many cases) but usually (80-90%) remain unidentified, it is not possible to identify the cause. We report the case of a man initially diagnosed with idiopathic ASD, who eventually was diagnosed with the disease in the origin of his autistic disorder, in this case a Becker muscular dystrophy. The associated theoretical aspects are also discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Amor Salamanca, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los trastornos del espectro autista (TEA) forman un heterogéneo grupo de patologías con muchas posibles causas (mayoritariamente de origen genético, de las que en la actualidad se conoce un gran número) pero que habitualmente (80-90%) quedan sin filiar, al no identificarse dicha causa. Presentamos el caso de un varón inicialmente diagnosticado de TEA idiopático, en quien finalmente pudo encontrarse la patología originaria de su trastorno autista, en este caso una distrofia muscular de Becker. Después se comentan los aspectos teóricos asociados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);19(4): 139-141, oct.-dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108998</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El síndrome autista o los trastornos del espectro autista: a propósito de un caso de distrofia muscular de Becker</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9415^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9415^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9415^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1714^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1714^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
