<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145242</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Associated factors to eating disorders in first year students of biomedical careers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The prevalence of eating disorders varies depending on the studied group, being important the one found on students of biomedical careers. Objective: To determine the relation between the presence of the symptoms of eating disorders (anorexia nervosa and bulimia nervosa) and the studied factors, in undergraduates of first year of biomedical careers from a private university of Arequipa. Methods: An analytical cross-sectional study was performed. We used The Eating Disorder Inventory 2 and The Cisneros Student Questionnaire on School Bullying. Other variables were professional career, type of school, extracurricular activities, religion, academic performance in high school, number of lovers, weekly hours watching television and daily hours employed in a social network. We evaluated 226 subjects. Results: The multiple linear regression analysis found that symptoms of eating disorders are associated with studying Obstetrics, having performed extracurricular academic activities in the last year, the number of daily hours spent in a social network and bullying. Discussion: Obstetrics students would be at risk because of female predominance (predisposing factor) and maybe the body dissatisfaction. The use of social networks (by generating social pressure or discrimination) and bullying (by causing body dissatisfaction) would be precipitant factors. The extracurricular academic activities would act as risk factor or as consequence of perfectionism. Conclusion: In students of biomedical careers, symptoms of eating disorders were associated with studying Obstetrics (because of female predominance), extracurricular academic activities (by associated stress), use of social networks and bullying (by social pressure and body dissatisfaction) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Estefanero Meza, Jersson</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velarde Llerena, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Smedts, Connie</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suclla Velásquez, José A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murillo Yupanqui, Dania</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vera Rivera, Dayana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cáceres Huambo, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La prevalencia de los trastornos de la conducta alimentaria (TCA) varía dependiendo del grupo estudiado, siendo importante aquella encontrada entre estudiantes de biomédicas. Objetivo: Determinar la relación entre la presencia de síntomas de TCA (anorexia nerviosa y bulimia nerviosa) y los factores estudiados, en alumnos de primer año de carreras biomédicas de una universidad privada de Arequipa. Métodos: Se realizó un estudio transversal analítico. Se emplearon el Inventario de Trastornos de la Conducta Alimentaria 2 y el Cuestionario para Alumnado Cisneros sobre Acoso Escolar. Otras variables fueron carrera profesional, tipo de colegio, actividades extracurriculares, religión, rendimiento académico en Secundaria, número de enamorados(as), horas semanales viendo televisión y horas diarias empleadas en redes sociales. Se evaluaron 226 sujetos. Resultados: La regresión lineal múltiple encontró que los síntomas de TCA están asociados a estudiar Obstetricia, haber realizado actividades extracurriculares académicas el último año, el número de horas diarias empleadas en redes sociales y acoso escolar. Discusión: Las estudiantes de Obstetricia por su predominancia femenina (factor predisponente) y quizás por la insatisfacción corporal estarían en riesgo. El uso de las redes sociales, al generar presión social o discriminación, y el acoso escolar, al provocar insatisfacción corporal, serían factores precipitantes. Las actividades académicas extracurriculares actuarían como factor de riesgo o consecuencia del perfeccionismo. Conclusión: En estudiantes de biomédicas, los síntomas de TCA se asociaron con estudiar Obstetricia (por predominancia femenina), actividades académicas extracurriculares (por estrés asociado), uso de redes sociales y acoso escolar (por presión de grupo e insatisfacción corporal) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;35(3): 17-26, 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145242</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores asociados con trastornos de conducta alimentaria en estudiantes de primer año de carreras biomédicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24194^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51232^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1853</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24382^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13723^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
