<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051429</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Human papillomavirus vaccines: a new challenge for pediatricians</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Human papillomavirus (HPV) infections are the most common sexually transmitted infections in the world. This infection is a necessary cause of cervical cancer, has been related to other forms of anogenital, airway and digestive cancers, and also causes anogenital warts. The recent advances in HPV prophylactic vaccines and their imminent commercial availability will post a new challenge to pediatricians: the indication and administration of these vaccines for the prevention of HPV infection, and consequently, of cervical cancer and other HPV-related diseases. The present article reviews the essentials of HPV infection, its relationship with cervical cancer, the advances in prophylactic HPV vaccines, and the role of the pediatrician in this context</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Juan Martín, F. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez Domingo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garcés Sánchez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernaola Iturbe, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martinón-Torres, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Campderá, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baca Cots, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pineda Solas, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Picazo, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giménez Sánchez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La infección por virus del papiloma humano (VPH) es la enfermedad de transmisión sexual más frecuente en el mundo. Esta infección constituye una causa necesaria del cáncer de cérvix, se ha relacionado con otras formas de cáncer anogenital, de vía aérea y digestivo, y es además el origen de las verrugas anogenitales. Los avances recientes en la vacunación profiláctica frente al VPH y la inminente disponibilidad comercial de estas vacunas, colocan al pediatra ante un nuevo reto: la indicación y administración de estas vacunas para la prevención de la infección por VPH, y como consecuencia, del cáncer de cérvix y otras patologías relacionadas con el VPH. En este artículo se revisan los aspectos esenciales de la infección por VPH, su relación con el cáncer de cérvix, los avances en las vacunas profilácticas frente al VPH y el papel del pediatra en este contexto</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);65(5): 461-469, nov. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051429</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vacuna frente al virus del papiloma humano: un nuevo reto para el pediatra</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2623^s32386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29482^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2623^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35997^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11750^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35997^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11251</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
