<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129090</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Main biomarkers of inflammatory status and its relationship with obesity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The proinflammatory adipokines also known as  proinflammatory biomarkers are a heterogeneous group of biomolecules whose function is involved in inflammation processes. Taking into account that are synthesized by adipose tissue, its synthesis will vary according to degree of obesity of the subjects, those with decreasing protective  effects, such as adiponectin, and increasing those others with proinflammatory actions. The aim of this study was to review an update on major proinflammatory biomarkers currently known are regarded as connecting links between inflammation, obesity and its associated complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Ferre, Judit</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Jiménez, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las adipoquinas proinflamatorias también denominadas como biomarcadores proinflamatorios constituyen un grupo heterogéneo de biomoléculas cuya función será intervenir en los procesos de inflamación. Teniendo en cuenta que son sintetizadas por el tejido adiposo, su síntesis variará de acuerdo al grado de obesidad de los sujetos, disminuyendo aquellas con efectos protectores, como la adiponectina, y aumentando aquéllas otras con acciones proinflamatorias. El objetivo de este trabajo ha sido realizar una revisión actualizada sobre los principales biomarcadores  proinflamatorios conocidos que actualmente son  considerados como nexos de unión entre la inflamación, obesidad y sus complicaciones asociadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;17(2): 89-97, mar.-jun. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129090</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Principales biomarcadores de estado inflamatorio y su relación con la obesidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50570</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52799</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52657</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50570^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d280^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52657^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52657^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
