<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91529</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Functional outcomes after total wrist arthtroplasty. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The hand and wrist joints are among the most commonly affected by rheumatoid arthritis. The main indications for wrist surgery are pain, deformity and loss of overall function of the upper limb secondary to the baseline disease. Wrist arthrodesis has sufficiently demonstrated its success to provide stability and eliminate pain in the rheumatic wrist but at the expense of sacrificing its mobility. Wrist arthroplasty is proposed as an alternative to wrist arthrodesis in order to also provide pain relief, increased mobility and improved functionality(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pleguezuelos Cobo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guirao Cano, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sal Castells, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez García, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perucho Pont, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las articulaciones de la mano y la muñeca son unas de las más frecuentemente afectadas en la artritis reumatoide. Las principales indicaciones de la cirugía de la muñeca son el dolor, la deformidad y la pérdida de función global de la extremidad superior secundaria al proceso patológico de base. La artrodesis de muñeca ha demostrado suficientemente su éxito para proporcionar estabilidad y eliminar el dolor en la muñeca reumática, pero a expensas de sacrificar su movilidad. La artroplastia de muñeca se propone como alternativa a la artrodesis de muñeca para, además de proporcionar un alivio del dolor, incrementar la movilidad y mejorar así la funcionalidad(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);45(4): 348-351, oct.-dic.2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91529</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados funcionales tras artroplastia total de muñeca. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15351^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15351^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15353^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15353^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1185^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50364^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1185^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1178^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1182^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11916^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1185^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50364^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1182^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1185^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1178^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
