<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94422</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Return of the patient after hospital discharge: important factor to follow up the surgical wound</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It is becoming standard for patients to be discharged son after their surgery and for them to continue requiring wound care after discharge. The objective of this paper is to describe the experience of the patient who return for woundcare and follow up after discharge. Methodology: descriptive study with qualitative techniques carried out between july and september 2005, at the Fortaleza-Ceará district hospital. Data were compiled by means of a semi structured interview administered to eight patients at the time of their return to the hospital to have their wound examined. Results: data obtained from the patients responses were organised into categories based on the analysis and grouping of such data. Feelings of sadness, fear, insecurity and a feeling to run awaywere identified in the patients when faced with the existence of the wound. These feelings are counteracted by the sense of professionalism and availability of good technicalmeans and materials in the hospital setting. Nursing recommendations and advice are considered as important by the patient and incentivise self-care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mesquita Melo, Elizabeth</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elisàngela T Lima, Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>GLF Veras, Joelna Eline</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barbosa, Islene V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Comienza a ser habitual que los pacientes sean dados de alta hospitalaria precozmente y que continúen requiriendo cuidados de una herida después de la misma. El objetivo de este trabajo fue describir la experiencia del paciente que retorna al hospital para realizar la cura y el seguimiento de la herida. Metodología: estudio descriptivo con técnicas cualitativas realizado de julio a septiembre de 2005, en el hospital municipal Fortaleza-Ceará. Datos recogidos a través de un guión de entrevista semi-estructurada aplicada a ocho pacientes en el momento del retorno al hospital. Resultados: los datos referidos a las declaraciones de los pacientes fueron organizados en categorías a partir del análisis y la agrupación de los mismos. Identificamos en los pacientes sentimientos de tristeza, miedo, inseguridad y fuga frente a la existencia de la herida, que se contrarrestan con la percepción de profesionalidad y disponibilidad de buenos medios técnicos y materiales en el medio hospitalario. Las orientaciones de Enfermería son consideradas importantes por los pacientes e incentivan el autocuidado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;11(3): 50-53, abr. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94422</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Retorno del paciente post-alta hospitalaria: factor importante en el seguimiento de la herida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3285^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37737^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10545^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17193^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13032^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
