<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152702</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-0740</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The midwife as evaluating and managing digital content</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In recent years there has been a significant increase in the volume of information on the internet about health and particularly on pregnancy, postpartum and breastfeeding. This fact together with the emergence of a new archetype of more informed and critical pregnant but also more intransigent and demanding forces us to confront substantial changes in our relationship with the mother. The midwives currently have an important role in the education of pregnant women in the proper use of obstetric information the internet provides. In this article I propose to analyze in this role as information evaluators and managers and/or digital content must target the actions to be taken in three directions: a) teach locate reliable information published online; b) prescribe mobile applications tailored to the individual circumstances of the mother to monitor her pregnancy, and c) advise a new empowered pregnant in the use of social networks taking into account related to privacy and confidentiality of the information you share in them (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Aranda, María Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos años se ha producido un incremento importante del volumen de información existente en internet sobre salud, en especial sobre el embarazo, el puerperio y la lactancia materna. Este hecho, junto con la aparición de un nuevo arquetipo de gestante más informada y crítica, hace que tengamos que afrontar cambios sustanciales en nuestra relación con la mujer embarazada. Las matronas tenemos actualmente un papel importante en la educación para la salud de las gestantes en el buen uso de la información obstétrica que ofrece internet. En este artículo se propone profundizar en esta faceta de las matronas como evaluadoras y gestoras de información y/o contenidos digitales, cuyas actuaciones deben apuntar en tres direcciones: a) enseñar a localizar información fiable publicada en internet; b) prescribir aplicaciones móviles adaptadas a las circunstancias personales de cada mujer para el seguimiento de su embarazo, y c) aconsejar sobre la utilización de las redes sociales, teniendo en cuenta los aspectos relativos a la privacidad y la confidencialidad de la información que se comparte en ellas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Matronas prof;17(1): 20-27, 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152702</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La matrona como evaluadora y gestora de información digital</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17570^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51868</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55136^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36354</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
