<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151728</identifier>
<setSpec>2014-9832</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparison of learning styles of medical students obtained with a new questionnaire with those provided by the Honey-Alonso questionnaire (CHAEA)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. About the style term there are different definitions and a lot of questionnaires to determine them; moreover, rankings are heterogeneous and meaning of different styles is not coincident. Subjects and methods. In order to clarify some points, this paper presents a new tool (CESEA) and compares the results obtained with those provided by the CHAEA, one of the questionnaires most used in the Spanish-speaking world. Results. The results show differences mainly in regard with the active style. In general, the scores for the different styles are more homogenous and high in the new questionnaire. Conclusions. Given the reliability values found and the greater homogeneity of the same CESEA utilization is recommended to determine the learning styles of medical students in order to improve the less developed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guerra-Sánchez, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escanero-Marcén, Jesús F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva, Jackson</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soria, M Soledad</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Existe una gran diversidad de definiciones de estilo y numerosos cuestionarios para determinarlos; las clasificaciones son heterogéneas y el significado de los diferentes estilos no es coincidente. Sujetos y métodos. Con objeto de clarificar algunos puntos, este trabajo presenta una nueva herramienta, el cuestionario Escanero-Soria de estilos de aprendizaje (CESEA), y compara los resultados encontrados con los proporcionados por el cuestionario Honey-Alonso de estilos de aprendizaje (CHAEA), uno de los más utilizados en el ámbito hispanoparlante. Resultados. Los resultados muestran diferencias principalmente en lo que respecta al estilo activo, siendo más homogéneos y elevados en el nuevo cuestionario. Conclusiones. Dados los valores de fiabilidad encontrados y su mayor homogeneidad, se recomienda la utilización del CESEA para determinar los estilos de aprendizaje en los estudiantes de medicina con el objetivo de mejorar los menos desarrollados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Fund. Educ. Méd. (Ed. impr.);19(1): 19-26, ene.-feb. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151728</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de los estilos de aprendizaje de los alumnos de medicina obtenidos con un nuevo cuestionario con los proporcionados por el cuestionario Honey-Alonso (CHAEA)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13724^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
