<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86137</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of factors influencing the development of adverse effects in the external cephalic version</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To identify the association between the adverse effects of the external cephalic version (ECV) and several variables related to the technique. Material and method. We performed a prospective study in 180 pregnant women who delivered through the ECV. We analyzed fetal and maternal adverse effects and their association with the final result of the version, the experience of the obstetrician, the time used in the maneuver, the number of attempts performed in the same session, and the drug used as a uterine relaxant. Results. The ECV was successfully performed in 32.6% of primiparas and 79.19% of multiparas. The overall rate of adverse effects was 28.33%, and was higher in versions that failed, those with a greater number of failed attempts, those with longer duration and those in which ritodrine was used as a uterine relaxant. Conclusions. The factors increasing the probability of success and reducing the rate of adverse effects in ECV are a single attempt at the maneuver, total duration of the maneuver of less than 5minutes, and use of salbutamol as a uterine relaxant(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fandiño García, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Herrero, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrasco Gallego, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dueñas Díez, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Establecer la relación existente entre los efectos adversos de la versión cefálica externa (VCE) y diferentes variables relacionadas con la técnica. Material y método. Estudio prospectivo que incluyó a 180 gestantes a las que se realizó una VCE. Analizamos los efectos adversos fetales y maternos observados, y su relación con el resultado final de la versión, la experiencia del obstetra, el tiempo empleado en la maniobra, el número de intentos realizados en la misma sesión y el fármaco empleado como relajante uterino. Resultados. Se obtuvo el éxito de la VCE en el 32,6% de las primíparas y en el 79,19% en multíparas. La tasa global de efectos adversos fue del 28,33%, y fue superior en las versiones que fracasaron, en las de mayor número de intentos fallidos, las de mayor duración de la maniobra y en las que fue utilizado ritodrina como útero-relajante. Conclusiones. Se obtiene una mayor probabilidad de éxito y una menor tasa de efectos adversos en las VCE en las que se realiza un único intento, con una duración total de la maniobra inferior a 5min y empleando salbutamol como relajante uterino(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);54(2): 60-64, feb. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86137</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de los factores que influyen en la aparición de efectos adversos en la versión cefálica externa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9657^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12724^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15114^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12724^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15114^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15114^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d423^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
