<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106533</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vesicoureteral refulx in overactive bladder: medical resolution through botulin toxin injection</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: Overactive bladder may have a neurogenic or non neurogenic origin. Sometimes, as a result of detrusor overactivity, disorders of the upper urinary tract function may appear. One of these alterations may be the appearance of associated vesicoureteral reflux. The treatment of overactive bladder may be done with anticholinergic drugs and if there is not response the use of botulin toxin type A is approved.The aim of this case report is to demonstrate the effect of botulin toxin type A in the treatment of overactive bladder and vesicoureteral reflux secondary to the overactive bladder. METHOD: We present the case of a 10-year-old patient without significant past medical history. When he was one year old he had a urinary infection and voiding cystourethrogram showed grade 1 right vesicoureteral reflux. When he was 4 year old he presented several episodes of pyelonephritis and then he was diagnosed of severe bilateral vesicoureteral reflux, which did not respond to treatment with Macroplastic ® or Deflux ®. Urodynamic study was performed showing overactive bladder with decreased bladder compliance. RESULTS: We performed intravesical injection of 200 U of botulin toxin type A and vesicoureteral reflux disappeared and urodynamic study improved. One year later we reinjected botulin toxin type A (300 U) and we repeated the injection after one year (300 U). The patient is currently well, without changes in the urodynamic study and without vesicoureteral reflux. CONCLUSION: Repeated injections of botulin toxin type A has shown great efficacy in the treatment of overactive bladder in children with vesicoureteral reflux improved secondary(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arrabal-Polo, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nogueras-Ocaña, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palao-Yago, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Pacheco, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tinaut-Ranera, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zuluaga-Gómez, Armando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-León, Victor</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: La vejiga hiperactiva puede tener un origen neurogénico o no neurogénico. En ocasiones, como consecuencia de dicha hiperactividad del detrusor pueden producirse alteraciones en la funcionalidad del tracto urinario superior. Una de esas alteraciones puede ser la aparición de reflujo vesicoureteral asociado. El tratamiento de dicha vejiga hiperactiva puede hacerse con anticolinérgicos y en caso de no presentar respuestas, está aprobado el uso de toxina botulínica tipo A. El objetivo es demostrar el efecto de la toxina botulínica tipo A en el tratamiento de la vejiga hiperactiva y del reflujo vesicoureteral secundario a la misma. MÉTODO: Presentamos el caso de un paciente de 10 años sin antecedentes personales de interés que al año de vida presentó infección urinaria y en cistouretrografía miccional seriada tenía reflujo vesicoureteral derecho grado 1. A los 4 años de edad presentó varios episodios de pielonefritis diagnosticándose de reflujo vesicoureteral severo bilateral no respondiendo a tratamiento con macroplastic® ni deflux®. Se realizó estudio urodinámico observando vejiga hiperactiva con disminución de la acomodación vesical. RESULTADOS: Se realizó inyección intravesical de 200 U de toxina botulínica tipo A observando remisión del reflujo vesicoureteral y mejoría en el estudio urodinámico. Al año se vuelve a inyectar toxina botulínica tipo A (300 U) y se repite un año después la inyección de 300 U, estando actualmente el paciente bien, sin alteraciones en el estudio urodinámico y sin reflujo vesicoureteral. CONCLUSIÓN: La inyección repetida de toxina botulínica tipo A ha demostrado gran eficacia en el tratamiento de la vejiga hiperactiva en niños con mejoría del reflujo vesicoureteral secundario(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;65(9): 845-848, nov. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106533</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reflujo vesicoureteral en vejiga hiperactiva: resolución con inyección de toxina botulínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52129^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15123^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33081^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201211</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
