<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85095</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Multiple pilomatricomas. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pilomatricoma, or calcifying epithelioma of Malherbe, is a benign cutaneous tumour of ectodermal origin, relatively rare, although it is more common during childhood, especially in children under ten; it is normally unique and only 3.5% of the mare of multiple forms. They are usually small (0.5-3.0 cm) and the most usual location is the cephalic one. They are usually asymptomatic solitary subcutaneous nodules with a petreous consistency. The suspected diagnosis may be done with a very careful clinical examination; however preoperative diagnosis of pilomatricoma is often incorrect, mainly because the examining physician is not familiar with it. This event and the fact that multiple pilomatricomas are not very frequent are the reason for us to present this case report (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Abadi Abadi, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodicio García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valdés Tascón, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silveira Cancela, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lago Mandado, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrés Andrés, A. G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El pilomatricoma, o epitelioma calcificado de Malherbe, es un tumor cutáneo benigno de origen ectodérmico, relativamente raro, aunque es más común en la infancia, sobre todo antes de los 10 años; habitualmente es único y sólo el 3,5% de los casos son formas múltiples. Suelen ser pequeños (0,5-3 cm) y la localización más habitual es la cefálica. Se presentan como nódulos subcutáneos solitarios y asintomáticos, de consistencia pétrea. El diagnóstico de sospecha puede realizarse mediante una exploración clínica cuidadosa; sin embargo, con frecuencia el diagnóstico preoperatorio de pilomatricoma es incorrecto, fundamentalmente debido a la falta de familiaridad de los clínicos con este tumor. Este hecho y la poca frecuencia de los pilomatricomas múltiples nos motivaron a presentar este caso clínico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;68(3): 146-148, mar. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85095</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pilomatricomas múltiples. Presentación de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4542^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31178^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31178^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4542^s22023</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31178^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4542^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
