<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-MFM2-10866</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Organ donor management: Eight common recommendations and actions that deserve reflection</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Despite major advances in our understanding of the physiopathology of brain death (BD), there are important controversies as to which protocol is the most appropriate for organ donor management. Many recent reviews on this subject offer recommendations that are sometimes contradictory and in some cases are not applied to other critically ill patients. This article offers a review of the publications (many of them recent) with an impact upon these controversial measures and which can help to confirm, refute or open new areas of research into the most appropriate measures for the management of organ donors in BD, and which should contribute to discard certain established recommendations based on preconceived ideas, that lead to actions lacking a physiopathological basis. Aspects such as catecholamine storm management, use of vasoactive drugs, hemodynamic objectives and monitoring, assessment of the heart for donation, and general care of the donor in BD are reviewed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Cornejo, MS</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Ramírez, MR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Melgar, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chamorro-Jambrina, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A pesar de los avances en la comprensión de la fisiopatología de la muerte encefálica, existen controversias importantes sobre el protocolo más adecuado para el tratamiento del donante de órganos. En muchas revisiones recientes aparecen recomendaciones, a veces contradictorias, y a veces no aplicadas a otros pacientes críticos. Este artículo revisa publicaciones, muchas de ellas recientes, que tienen un impacto en estas medidas controvertidas y que pueden ayudar a confirmar, refutar o abrir nuevas áreas de investigación sobre las medidas más apropiadas para el tratamiento del donante y que deberían hacer olvidar algunas recomendaciones habituales basadas en ideas preconcebidas, que conducen a acciones carentes de una base fisiopatológica. Se revisan aspectos como: el control de la tormenta catecolamínica, el uso de fármacos vasoactivos y de hormonas, los objetivos hemodinámicos y su monitorización, la evaluación del corazón para donación y otros aspectos generales del tratamiento del donante en muerte encefálica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);41(9): 559-568, dic. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-MFM2-10866</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento del donante de órganos. Ocho recomendaciones y actuaciones habituales que merecen una reflexión</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
