<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037971</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Plastic bronchitis. A case report and review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Plastic bronchitis is a rare complication in which bronchial casts of lymphatic origin develop in the tracheobronchial    tree and cause airway obstruction. The main feature    is expectoration of bronchial casts. This condition    usually occurs in the postoperative period after the Fontan    operation for congenital heart disease. Treatment modalities    include mucolytics and chest physiotherapy, and in    the most severe cases bronchoscopy to remove the casts    and aerosolized urokinase or r-TPA. We describe a    12-year-old boy with pulmonary atresia with intact ventricular    septum and severely hypoplastic right ventricle    who underwent a modified Fontan operation at the age of    7 years. At the age of 12 years the patient started to present    frequent episodes of coughing, dyspnea, and desaturation    followed by difficult emission of white bronchial casts.    An extracardiac Fontan conversion was performed to improve    hemodynamics and symptoms. During the postoperative    period frequent episodes of airway obstruction    required bronchoscopy and finally improved with administration of aerosolized urokinase</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Galletti, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendoza Soto, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez de Quero, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velasco Bayón, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Casado, M. V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La bronquitis plástica es una rara manifestación consistente en la formación y expectoración de moldes bronquiales    de origen linfático que provocan obstrucción de la    vía respiratoria. Se asocia sobre todo al postoperatorio de    cardiopatías congénitas corregidas con la operación de    Fontan. Como tratamiento de base se han utilizado mucolíticos    y fisioterapia respiratoria y en los casos más graves    la extracción de los moldes por broncoscopia así como la    nebulización de urocinasa o activador tisular del plasminógeno    recombinante (rt-PA). Se presenta el caso de un varón    con atresia pulmonar con tabique íntegro y ventrículo    derecho hipoplásico operado a los 7 años con una intervención    de Fontan, que a los 12 años presentó episodios    frecuentes de tos, disnea y desaturación en los cuales el paciente    expectoraba moldes bronquiales de aspecto blanquecino.    Se realizó una conversión a Fontan extracardíaca    para mejorar la clínica y hemodinámica, presentando    en el postoperatorio frecuentes episodios de obstrucción    respiratoria por moldes bronquiales que requirieron extracción    mediante broncoscopia y mejoraron con la administración de urocinasa nebulizada</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);62(1): 72-75, ene. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037971</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bronquitis plástica. A propósito de un caso y revisión de los casos asociados a cirugía de Fontan</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32248^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2020^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
