<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037112</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Functional disorders of fof1-atpase in submitochondrial particles obtained from platelets of patients with a diagnosis of probable alzheimer&#146;s disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Recent studies indicate that decreased energy generation by mitochondria is a feature that is common across neurodegenerative diseases. Patients and methods. In order to obtain direct evidence that mitochondrial functioning is altered, we measured the hydrolytic activity of F0F1-ATPase and its capacity to generate a stable proton gradient in submitochondrial particles in 29 patients diagnosed with probable Alzheimer&#146;s disease (AD). Submitochondrial particles were obtained from platelets of patients with a diagnosis of probable AD and from clinically healthy controls. Results. Data revealed that the hydrolytic activity of F0F1-ATPase increases significantly in patients with probable AD (41.7 ± 4.3 nmol PO4 min-1[mg protein]-1, n = 29) as compared to the control subjects (29.1 ± 1.9 nmol PO4 min-1 [mg protein]-1, n = 29). It is important to note that, in the male population with probable AD, we found that hydrolytic activity of F0F1-ATPase increased as cerebral deterioration progressed. We also detected a lower pH gradient in the submitochondrial particles of patients with probable AD (0.28 ± 0.08 pH units, n = 25) as compared to the controls (0.5 ± 0.1 pH units, n = 20). Conclusions. Overall, these data point to an alteration in the functioning of the enzyme</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortiz-Genaro, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Cano, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pacheco-Moisés, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macías-Islas, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosales-Corral, SA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Nieto, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los estudios recientes indican que una disminución en la generación de energía de la mitocondria es una característica que unifica a las enfermedades neurodegenerativas. Pacientes y métodos. Para obtener evidencia directa que la función mitocondrial se altera, cuantificamos en 29 pacientes diagnosticados con probable enfermedad de Alzheimer (EA) la actividad hidrolítica de la F0F1-ATPasa y su capacidad para generar un gradiente estable de protones en partículas submitocondriales. Las partículas submitocondriales se obtuvieron de plaquetas de pacientes con diagnóstico probable de EA y de controles clínicamente sanos. Resultados. Los datos revelaron que la actividad hidrolítica de la F0F1-ATPasa se incrementa de manera significativa en los pacientes con la probable EA -41,7 ± 4,3 nmol PO4 min-1(mg proteína)-1, con n = 29- en comparación con los controles -29,1 ± 1,9 nmol PO4 min-1 (mg proteína)- 1, con n = 29-. De manera importante, encontramos que en la población masculina con probable EA, la actividad hidrolítica de la F0F1-ATPasa aumenta conforme progresa el deterioro cerebral. También detectamos un gradiente de pH menor en las partículas submitocondriales de los pacientes con probable EA (0,28 ± 0,08 unidades de pH, n = 25) comparados con los controles (0,5 ± 0,1 unidades de pH, n = 20). Conclusión. Estos datos, en conjunto, indican una alteración funcional en la enzima</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;40(2): 81-85, ene. 2005. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037112</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alteración funcional de la F0F1-ATPasa en partículas submitocondriales obtenidas de plaquetas de pacientes con diagnóstico de enfermedad de Alzheimer probable</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d262^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30922^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13754^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31728^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
