<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76372</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1780</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Organizational identification and psychological contract breach: its influences on employees&#146; motivation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The main purpose of this study has been showed the partial mediator role ofgroup, professional and organizational identification into the relationships between perceivedcontract breach and employees&#146; job satisfaction. Confirmative factor analysis with a sampleof employees (N= 133) showed hygienic and motivator job satisfaction factors&#146; as differentbut related dimensions. Through a structural equation model it has been proved thatdifferent focus of identification will be better predictor of different outcomes. Resultshave been discussed in order to their theoretical and practical implications(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Topa Cantisano, Gabriela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Domínguez, J. Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El principal objetivo de este estudio ha sido mostrar la mediación parcial de la identificacióngrupal, personal y organizacional en las relaciones entre la percepción de rupturade contrato psicológico y la satisfacción laboral de los empleados. El análisis factorialconfirmatorio con una muestra de empleados (N= 133) mostró los factores higiénicos ymotivadores de la satisfacción como dimensiones diferentes aunque relacionadas. A travésde un modelo de ecuaciones estructurales se prueba que los diferentes focos deidentificación serán predictores de diferentes resultados. Los resultados se discuten decara a sus implicaciones teóricas y aplicadas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int. j. psychol. psychol. ther. (Ed. impr.);7(3): 365-379, 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76372</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Identificación organizacional y ruptura de contrato psicológico: sus influencias sobre la satisfacción de los empleados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23790</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37687</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
