<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99980</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recognition of facial expression of emotions in Parkinson&#146;s disease: a theoretical review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Emotional facial expression is a basic guide during social interaction and, therefore, alterations in their expression or recognition are important limitations for communication. Aim. To examine facial expression recognition abilities and their possible impairment in Parkinson&#146;s disease. Development. First, we review the studies on this topic which have not found entirely similar results. Second, we analyze the factors that may explain these discrepancies and, in particular, as third objective, we consider the relationship between emotional recognition problems and cognitive impairment associated with the disease. Finally, we propose alternatives strategies for the development of studies that could clarify the state of these abilities in Parkinson&#146;s disease.  Conclusions. Most studies suggest deficits in facial expression recognition, especially in those with negative emotional content. However, it is possible that these alterations are related to those that also appear in the course of the disease in other perceptual and executive processes. To advance in this issue, we consider necessary to design emotional recognition studies implicating differentially the executive or visuospatial processes, and/or contrasting cognitive abilities with facial expressions and non emotional stimuli. The precision of the status of these abilities, as well as increase our knowledge of the functional consequences of the characteristic brain damage in the disease, may indicate if we should pay special attention in their rehabilitation inside the programs implemented (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso Redo, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Plasencia, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Rodríguez, Juan M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carvajal Molina, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Loeches Alonso, Ángela</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La expresión facial emocional constituye una guía básica en la interacción social y, por ello, las alteraciones en su expresión o reconocimiento suponen una importante limitación para la comunicación. Objetivo. Examinar las capacidades de reconocimiento de expresiones faciales y su posible deterioro en la enfermedad de Parkinson. Desarrollo. En primer lugar, se revisan las investigaciones sobre este tema y que no han encontrado resultados totalmente afines. En segundo lugar, se analizan los factores que pueden explicar estas divergencias y, en particular, como tercer objetivo, se valora la relación entre los problemas en el reconocimiento emocional y el deterioro cognitivo asociado a la enfermedad. Por último, se proponen estrategias alternativas para el desarrollo de estudios que contribuyan a clarificar el estado de estas habilidades en la enfermedad de Parkinson.  Conclusiones. La mayoría de los estudios indica deficiencias en el reconocimiento de expresiones, sobre todo en las de contenido emocional negativo. No obstante, es posible que dichas alteraciones estén relacionadas con las que también aparecen en otros procesos perceptivos y ejecutivos propios de la enfermedad. Para avanzar en esta cuestión, consideramos necesario diseñar estudios sobre reconocimiento emocional que impliquen diferencialmente a los procesos cognitivos mencionados o que contrasten la ejecución de los individuos con estímulos no emocionales y con expresiones faciales. Además de incrementar nuestro conocimiento sobre las consecuencias funcionales del deterioro cerebral característico de la enfermedad, estos estudios pueden indicarnos si debe prestarse atención adicional a su rehabilitación dentro de los programas que se aplican (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;54(8): 479-489, abr. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99980</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reconocimiento de expresiones faciales de emociones en la enfermedad de Parkinson: una revisión teórica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14181</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5250</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
