<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-16244</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Uconditioned logistic regression and sample size: a reference source review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Unconditioned logistic regression is a highly useful risk prediction method in epidemiology. This article reviews the different solutions provided by different authors concerning the interface between the calculation of the sample size and the use of logistics regression. Based on the knowledge of the information initially provided, a review is made of the customized regression and predictive constriction phenomenon, the design of an ordinal exposition with a binary output, the event of interest per variable concept, the indicator variables, the classic Freeman equation, etc. Some skeptical ideas regarding this subject are also included (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ministerio de Sanidad y Consumo</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La regresión logística no condicionada es un método de predicción de riesgo muy útil en epidemiología. En este artículo revisamos las diferentes soluciones que han dado diversos autores sobre la interfase entre el cálculo del tamaño muestral y la utilización de la regresión logística. A partir del conocimiento de las primeras aportaciones, se revisan los fenómenos de regresión a la media y de la constricción predictiva, el diseño de una exposición ordinal con una salida binaria, el concepto de evento de interés por variable, las variables indicadoras, la fórmula clásica de Freeman, etc. Recogemos también algunas ideas escépticas sobre este tema (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;76(2): 85-93, mar. 2002.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Regresión logística no condicionada y tamaño de muestra: una revisión bibliográfica</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Ortega Calvo, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cayuela Domínguez, Aurelio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-16244</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32037</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
