<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100226</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spinal arthrodesis. Basic science</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Spinal arthrodesis consists of a combination of a system of mechanical stabilisation of one or more vertebral segments with a biological substance that promotes osteoneogenesis, with aim of achieving the permanent fusion between areas more or less the same size of these segments. In spinal arthrodesis, the biological support par excellence is the autograft. However, obtaining this involves a high incidence of morbidity and, in cases of arthrodesis of more than one intervertebral space, the quantity available is usually insufficient. The extraction and implantation time prolongs the surgery, increasing the exposure to and risk of bleeding and infection. For these reasons, there is a search for substances that possess the properties of the autograft, avoiding the morbidity and added surgical time required to extract the autograft. The biomechanical-biological interaction in vertebral arthrodesis has been studied in this article (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Andrist, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrades, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerado, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cerván, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerado, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Becerra, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Una artrodesis vertebral consiste en la combinación de un sistema de estabilización mecánica de 2 o más segmentos vertebrales con una sustancia biológica que promueva la osteogénesis, con el objetivo de conseguir la fusión permanente entre zonas más o menos extensas de dichos segmentos. En una artrodesis vertebral, el aporte biológico por excelencia es el autoinjerto; sin embargo, su obtención genera una alta incidencia de morbilidad y, en casos de artrodesis de más de un espacio intervertebral, la cantidad disponible suele ser insuficiente. El tiempo de extracción e implantación prolonga la intervención quirúrgica, aumentando la exposición y riesgo a sangrado e infección. Por ello, actualmente hay una búsqueda de sustancias que posean las propiedades del autoinjerto evitando la morbilidad y tiempo de cirugía añadido que genera extraer el autoinjerto. En este trabajo se estudia la interacción biomecánica-biología en la artrodesis vertebral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);56(3): 227-244, mayo-jun. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100226</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Artrodesis del raquis. Ciencia básica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14573^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13505^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54432^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13620^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1696^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1182^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13515^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10191^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1182^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1182^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1182^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13515^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13505^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13505^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1182^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13505^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
