<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109968</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychiatric morbidity among young-adults cannabis users</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This cross-sectional study aims to determine lifetime prevalence of psychiatric disorders (including substance use disorders, -SUD and other non substance use disorders, &#150;Non-SUD) among 289 young (18-30 years) regular cannabis users, during the last year, in non-clinical settings in Barcelona. The Spanish version of the Psychiatric Interview for Substance and Mental Disorders (PRISM) was administered. Only 28% of the participants did not present any psychiatric disorder; while 65% had some SUD, the most common related to cannabis use (62%). Nearly 27% presented a non-SUD disorder. A younger age of initiation on alcohol use was associated with the presence of some SUD. Having consumed a greater number of &#147;joints&#148; in the last month was associated with the presence of both psychiatric disorders (SUD and non-SUD). While three quarters of subjects with non-SUD disorders had received some kind of treatment, only 28% of those with any SUD had received treatment. Given the low perception for need of treatment, there is a need for prevention strategies and to be able to offer therapies specifically tailored targeting young cannabis users(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torrens, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domingo-Salvany, Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Niubó, Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuenca-Royo, Aida M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suelves, Josep M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio transversal tiene como objetivo determinar la prevalencia vida de trastornos psiquiátricos (incluyendo los trastornos por uso de sustancias, &#150;TUS y los otros trastornos no por uso de sustancias, &#150;No-TUS) entre 289 jóvenes (18-30 años) consumidores regulares de cannabis durante el último año, reclutados fuera del entorno asistencial en Barcelona. Se administró la versión española de la Psychiatric Interview for Substance and Mental Disorders (PRISM). Sólo el 28% de los participantes no presentó ningún trastorno psiquiátrico, y el 65% tenía algún TUS, el más común relacionado con el cannabis (62%). Casi el 27% presentó trastornos no-TUS. Una edad de inicio más temprana en el consumo de alcohol se asoció con la presencia de algún TUS. Haber consumido un número mayor de &#147;porros&#148; en el último mes se asoció con la presencia de trastornos psiquiátricos (TUS y no-TUS).Mientras tres cuartas partes de los pacientes con trastornos no-TUS habían recibido algún tipo de tratamiento, sólo el 28% de las personas con cualquier TUS habían recibido tratamiento. Dada la baja percepción de necesidad de tratamiento, se hacen necesarias estrategias de prevención y poder ofrecer terapias adaptadas y dirigidas a los consumidores jóvenes de cannabis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);25(1): 45-54, ene.-mar. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109968</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comorbilidad psiquiátrica en jóvenes-adultos consumidores de cannabis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31511^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
