<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130649</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Microbiology of pressure and vascular ulcer infections</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Pressure ulcer (PU) infection is a significant clinical problem in many elderly patients. Material and methods. To determine the microbiology of PU and vascular ulcer (VU) infections by conducting a cross-sectional study of outpatients treated in a chronic wounds unit over an 18 month period. Results. Sixty six patients with PU infection and 159 patients with an infected VU were identified. The PUs were located below the knee in 36 patients (52%). Patients with pressure ulcers had a higher proportion of institutionalization, cognitive impairment, inability to walk, and sphincter incontinence. There was a greater number of infections caused by Enterobacteriaceae (52%, P=.002) and fewer S. aureus infections (24%, P&lt;.001) in patients with a PU compared to those with those with a VU. Forty-one percent of S. aureus strains isolated in all the patients were resistant to methicillin (MRSA). The proportion of Enterobacteriaceae infections was similar in patients with infection of pelvic girdle PU and in those located below the knee. Conclusions. PU patients suffer a higher rate of infection by enterobacteria. The most common pathogen in UV infections is S. aureus. The proportion of MRSA infection in patients with chronic wounds is high. The microbiology of the infection in the pelvic girdle PU is similar to those located below the knee (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Segovia Gómez, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Madero, Rodrigo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Romero, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Martínez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cantero Caballero, Miriea</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Balbuena, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La infección de úlceras por presión (UPP) supone un problema clínico relevante en los pacientes ancianos. Material y métodos. Para conocer la microbiología de las infecciones de las UPP y de las úlceras de origen vascular (UV) se realizó un estudio transversal de pacientes ambulantes durante 18 meses con infección de heridas crónicas (HC). Resultados. Se identificaron 69 pacientes con infección de UPP y 159 pacientes con infección de UV. Las UPP se localizaban por debajo de la rodilla en 36 pacientes (52%). Los pacientes con UPP presentaban una mayor proporción de institucionalización, deterioro cognitivo, incapacidad para la deambulación e incontinencia esfinteriana. Hubo un mayor número de infecciones producidas por enterobacterias (52%, p = 0,002) y un menor número de infecciones por S. aureus (24%, p &lt; 0,001) en pacientes con UPP en comparación con los que presentaban UV. El 41% de las cepas de S. aureus aisladas en el conjunto de los pacientes eran resistentes a meticilina (SARM). La proporción de infecciones por enterobacterias fue similar en los pacientes con infección de UPP supra o infrarrotulianas. Conclusiones. Los pacientes con UPP padecen una proporción mayor de infección por enterobacterias. El patógeno más frecuente en las infecciones de UV es S. aureus. Las infecciones por SARM son frecuentes en esta población. La microbiología UPP infectadas localizadas en la cintura pelviana es similar a las localizadas por debajo de la rodilla (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);50(1): 5-8, ene.-feb. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130649</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Microbiología de las infecciones de úlceras por presión y de origen vascular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15050^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53002^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15050^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53002^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15050^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4835^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13255^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13255^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13255^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
