<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038605</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship between LUTS (lower urinary tract symptoms) and quality of life</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: To evaluate the impact ofthe lower urinary tract symptoms (LUTS) included in theIPSS on the quality of life and to determine therelationship between quality of life or total IPSS scoreand treatment.METHODS: Retrospective review of the IPSS questionnairein 125 male patients who had consulted for LUTSbetween January 2001 and December 2003. Resultswere included in an Access database. Statistical analyseswere done with the SPSS 11.0 software.RESULTS: 17% of the patients showed severe symptomsin accordance to the IPSS score. In the quality of lifeevaluation grouped into two categories, 88% referredgood or indifferent quality of life. In the evaluation ofthe association between IPSS individual questions andquality of life there was a significant association for allquestions. Patients reporting worse quality of life had a6 times higher risk of receiving treatment. With a meanfollow-up of two years, 91% of patients who were noton treatment continued without it.CONCLUSIONS: The most severe symptoms are, theworse the quality of life. The independent parametersthat most influenced decision to start treatment werequality of life and total IPSS. Frequency, weak streamand hesitation may explain quality of life on eachpatient</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jalón Monzón, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Rodríguez, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Martínez, Juan Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Álvarez, Roberto Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Faba, Oscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Gómez, Jesús María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Mújica, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Regadera Sejas, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVOS: Evaluar el impacto de los síntomasdel tracto urinario inferior (STUI) referidos en elcuestionario IPSS sobre la calidad de vida y determinarla relación entre calidad de vida o puntuación total delIPSS con el tratamiento.MÉTODOS: Revisión retrospectiva del cuestionario IPSSde 125 hombres que habían consultado por STUI entreenero del 2001 y diciembre de 2003. La mediana deseguimiento fue de 24 meses. Los resultados fueronrecogidos en una base de datos Access. Para la evaluaciónestadística se utilizó la versión 11.0 del SPSS.RESULTADOS: Según la puntuación del IPSS total el17% de los pacientes presentaba síntomas severos. Enla evaluación de la calidad agrupada en 2 categorías,el 88% referían buena o indiferente calidad. Al evaluarla asociación entre los resultados del IPSS de cada preguntay la calidad, existió asociación significativa paratodas las preguntas. Los pacientes con STUI importantetenían un riesgo 6 veces mayor de mala calidad. Lospacientes que respondieron con peor calidad presentabanun riesgo 6 veces mayor de recibir tratamiento.Con un tiempo de evolución de más de 2 años demedia, el 91% de los que no tenían tratamiento seguíansin él.CONCLUSIONES: Cuanto más graves sean los síntomaspeor es la calidad de vida. Los parámetros independientesque más influyeron en la toma de decisiónpara iniciar un tratamiento fueron la calidad de vida yla puntuación total del IPSS. La polaquiuria, el chorrodébil y la vacilación inicial pueden explicar la calidadde vida de cada paciente</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;58(2): 109-113, mar. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038605</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre síntomas del tracto urinario inferior y calidad de vida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11913^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14955^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
