<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053452</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Functional dependency evaluation of hemofialysis patients. A multicentric study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: There has been a change in the hemodialysis population characteristics        over the last years with a progressive increase in patient,s age and associated comorbility        and mortality. This older hemodialysis population are more functionally and medically        dependent increasing the time taken to perform nursing work. The objective of this        study was to evaluate the degree of functional dependency on hemodialysis patients and        the need of care by nursing workload.        Methods: A transversal descriptive study was done during 1 month (april 2005) on 586        patients from 10 HD Units in Spain. No exclusion criteria were used. The Delta Test, who        was used to evaluate the patients dependency needs, is a workload measure instrument        base on three subscales: dependency, Physical Deficiency and mental deficiency. The indicators        are measure on a scale of one to three with each level representing an increasing        demand on nursing time. The results obtained from the Delta Test were analyzed taking        into account the following variables: age, average time in dialysis, Charlson comorbidity        Index, geographic location and HD unit.        Results: 46% of the patients show some degree of dependency, of these 12.8% were        moderated and 8.1% severe; the subscale analysis showed that 19.6% and 6.7% had,        respectively, a moderate to severe physical and mental health deficiency. The dependency        degree varied significantly between HD Units and geographic location with a range of 0%        to 59.8%. The degree of dependency were statistically associated with age and CCI. The        higher CCI (r: 0,21; p &lt; 0.001) and age (r: 0,26; p &lt; 0.001) the higher was the Delta        Test Score for dependency level. Patients times of initiation on dialysis were not associated        with an increase in the degree of dependency. The aspects evaluated by the Delta        Test that showed a higher score were those related to patients mobility. The patients assistance        requirements during the HD session are basically related to a lack of mobility due        to musculoskeletal disease and to a lesser extent to behavior alterations.        Conclusions: HD units are attending patients with an important degree of dependency        which impose and added workload to the healthcare personnel. In occasions, it is very difficult        to attend and give proper care with the current legally established nurse to patient        ratio which. This suggests the need to implement a better staffing policy. The Delta Test        provides an objective, adaptable and standardized instrument for measuring degree of dependency        of HD patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lacueva, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berdud, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Marcos, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arenas, MD</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Ude, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soriano, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antolín, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Angoso, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las características de los pacientes que se incluyen en hemodiálisis (HD)        han cambiado en los últimos años, habiendo aumentado la edad y la comorbilidad, lo que        tiene implicaciones sobre aspectos funcionales, dada la necesidad de ayuda que requieren        estos pacientes. El objetivo de este estudio ha sido analizar el grado de dependencia funcional        del paciente en HD.        Métodos: Estudio transversal y descriptivo en 586 pacientes dializados en abril de 2005        en 10 unidades de HD ubicadas en la Comunidad Valenciana, Andalucía y Castilla-León.        Para valorar el grado de dependencia se utilizó el «Test Delta», que consta de tres subescalas        que miden: Dependencia: (puntuación máxima 30), Deficiencia física: (puntuación        máxima 15) y Deficiencia psíquica: (puntuación máxima 15). Los ítems se puntúan de 0        a 3, de menor a mayor severidad. Se analizaron los resultados obtenidos de acuerdo con        las siguientes variables: Edad, tiempo medio en hemodiálisis, Índice de Comorbilidad de        Charlson (ICC), Provincias y Unidades.        Resultados: El 45,6% de los pacientes presentaba algún tipo de dependencia (un 12,8%        en grado moderado y un 8,1% en grado severo). El análisis por sub-escalas mostró una        Deficiencia física moderada-severa en el 19,6%, y en el 6,7% una Deficiencia psíquica.        Este grado de dependencia variaba significativamente de unas unidades a otras (0%-        59,8%), y según áreas geográficas. La edad y el ICC mostraron asociación estadísticamente        significativa con el grado de dependencia, de modo que a mayor edad (r: 0,26; p &lt;        0,001) y mayor puntuación en el ICC (r: 0,21; p &lt; 0,001) mayor grado de dependencia,        sin embargo el tiempo de permanencia en hemodiálisis no mostró asociación. Los aspectos        evaluados en el Test Delta que mostraron mayor puntuación fueron los relacionados        con la movilidad del paciente. Los requerimientos de ayuda se deben fundamentalmente a        falta de autonomía en la movilidad por alteraciones del aparato locomotor y, en menor medida,        a trastornos de conducta.        En conclusión, los centros de hemodiálisis están atendiendo a pacientes con un importante        grado de dependencia, lo que supone una mayor carga de trabajo para el personal sanitario        y muy especialmente el de enfermería. En ocasiones es imposible atender a este tipo de pacientes        con el ratio de personal asignado actualmente por los conciertos vigentes, y se requiere        una mayor dotación de enfermería. La existencia de parámetros que de manera objetiva        permitan valorar tales circunstancias, hacen aconsejable aprobar un instrumento de        valoración común, que sea sencillo, universal y rápido en la valoración y que, además, pueda        adaptarse a las necesidades cambiantes de la población a la que va destinado</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;26(5): 600-608, sept.-oct. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053452</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración del grado de dependencia funcional de los pacientes en hemodiálisis (HD): estudio multicéntrico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29745</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d212</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
