<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149299</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation a parenting skills pilot programme from a public health perspective</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective:  To evaluate the process and the results of the pilot phase of the Parenting skills development programme for families (PSP), an evidence-based strategy to promote positive parenting skills in socio-educational and community settings. Methods: Before-after quasi-experimental design without a control group for the evaluation of the pilot phase of the PSD carried out in Barcelona (Spain) between October 2011 and June 2013. Eleven groups were established with the participation of 128 parents and 28 professionals. The intervention consisted of 10 or 11 sessions. Information was collected through questionnaires for parents and in-depth individual or group interviews for professionals. Parenting skills were identified through a questionnaire with six dimensions. The situation before the intervention (T0) and immediately after (T1) was compared. Results: In T1 the number of participants decreased to 83 (retention=64.8%). Participants showed a high level of satisfaction with different dimensions of the program. On a maximum score of 10, the satisfaction of professionals was 8.7. Several key aspects and areas for improvement were identified for the future of the intervention. The quantitative analysis revealed improvements in all parenting skills dimensions and these improvements were consistent with the results of the qualitative analysis. Conclusions:  The results of the pilot phase of this program suggest that a universal intervention on parenting skills can improve wellbeing among parents (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vázquez, Noelia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Artazcoz, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pasarín, M Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar el proceso y los resultados de la fase piloto del Programa de desarrollo de habilidades parentales para familias (PHP), una estrategia de promoción de la parentalidad positiva basada en la evidencia y aplicable en contextos comunitarios y socioeducativos. Métodos: Diseño cuasiexperimental antes-después sin grupo control para la evaluación de la fase piloto del PHP implementada entre octubre de 2011 y junio de 2013 en Barcelona. Se condujeron 11 grupos en los que participaron 128 padres y madres y 28 profesionales. La intervención consistió en 10 u 11 sesiones. La información se recogió con cuestionarios a padres y madres y entrevistas en profundidad, individuales o grupales, a los/las profesionales. Las habilidades parentales se recogieron mediante un cuestionario con seis dimensiones. Se comparó la situación inmediatamente antes (T0) e inmediatamente después (T1) de la intervención. Resultados: El número de participantes en T1 se redujo a 83 (retención del 64,8%). El grado de satisfacción de los participantes con diversos aspectos del programa fue muy alto. Sobre una puntuación máxima de 10, la satisfacción de las personas moderadoras fue de 8,7. Se identificaron aspectos clave y áreas de mejora para el futuro de la intervención. En el análisis cuantitativo se observaron mejoras en todas las dimensiones de habilidades parentales que fueron consistentes con los resultados del análisis cualitativo. Conclusiones: Los resultados de la fase piloto de este programa apuntan a que una intervención universal de educación parental puede mejorar el bienestar de padres y madres (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;30(1): 37-42, ene.-feb. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149299</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de un programa piloto promotor de habilidades parentales desde una perspectiva de salud pública</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4573^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2719^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29907</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23661</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25783</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
