<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95417</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-2399</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Social skills in emergency and critical care professionals of a regional public hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To assess the social skills of health care professionals in the emergency and critical care units of the regional hospital Vega Baja and analyze the association between a series of sociodemographic and professionals variables and social skills. Aim A cross-sectional, descriptive study.Method Two evaluation tools were used. These included a sociodemographic and professional variables questionnaire, and the Elena Gismero's Social Skills Scale (SSS).Results A response rate of 82.6% was obtained. Considering the standards made by the author in SSS validation, it can be seen that the sample has obtained a medium-high score in each one of the aspects. Significant differences have been found when considering the sociodemographic variable gender as an independent variable with the complete score of SSS (F=6.555; p=0.013), and with the scale dimensions, self-expression in social situations (F=4.468; p=0.039) and making a demand (F=7.982; p=0.007). Conclusions In each one of the SSS dimensions, the sample has obtained a slightly higher score than the standard sample and it within the 50&#150;69 percentile. This indicates the existence of a medium-high level of Social Skill. The doctors score higher than the nurses, although these differences are not statistically significant (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Luján Cebrián, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Van-der Hofstadt Román, C. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer Villalonga, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leal Costa, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gascón García, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Determinar las habilidades sociales del personal sanitario de la Unidad de Urgencias y Cuidados Críticos del Hospital Comarcal «Vega Baja», y analizar la existencia de la asociación entre una serie de variables sociodemográficas y profesionales y las habilidades sociales. Diseño Estudio descriptivo transversal. Método Se emplearon dos instrumentos de evaluación: un cuestionario de variables sociodemográficas y profesionales, y la escala de habilidades sociales (EHS) de Elena Gismero. Resultados Se obtiene una tasa de respuesta del 82,6%. Teniendo en cuenta los baremos realizados por la autora en la validación de la EHS, podemos observar que la muestra obtiene una puntuación media-alta en cada una de las dimensiones. Se encuentran diferencias significativas al considerar como variable independiente la variable sociodemográfica sexo con la puntuación total de la EHS (F=6,555; p=0,013) y con las dimensiones de la escala autoexpresión en situaciones sociales (F=4,468; p=0,039) y hacer peticiones (F=7,982; p=0,007). Conclusiones En cada una de las dimensiones de la EHS la muestra obtiene una puntuación media ligeramente superior a la de la muestra de baremación y que se situaría en torno al percentil 50&#150;69, indicando la presencia de un nivel medio-alto de la habilidad social. Puntúan más alto los médicos que las enfermeras, aunque estas diferencias no son estadísticamente significativas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Intensiva;21(4): 136-141, Oct. - Dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95417</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Habilidades sociales en los profesionales de urgencias y cuidados críticos de un hospital público comarcal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23897</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30140^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9907</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
