<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136794</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Biochemical and neurobiological basis of alcohol dependence</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Recent advances in neuroscience have made it possible to deepen into the physiopathology of alcoholism at a biochemical and cellular level. There is now good evidence that acute effects of alcohol are mediated through interactions with amino acid neurotransmitters (mainly at GABAA and NMDA receptors) plus parallel changes in amines such as dopamine and noradrenaline. Neuroadaptative responses at amino acid receptors probably underlie significant components of the withdrawal syndrome and contribute to neuronal death found in chronic alcoholism. Although not so well understood, ethanol reinforcing properties appear to be mainly mediated by activation of GABAA receptors, release of opioid peptides, interaction with nicotinic receptors and indirect release of dopamine (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ayesta, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los últimos avances neurocientíficos han permitido profundizar en la fisiopatología del alcoholismo a nivel bioquímico y celular. Actualmente se sabe que los efectos agudos del etanol están fundamentalmente mediados por su interacción con neurotransmisores aminoácidos (primordialmente en los receptores GABAA y NMDA), así como cambios paralelos en determinadas aminas como la dopamina y la noradrenalina. Las respuestas neuroadpatativas en los receptores de aminoácidos subyacen probablemente en componentes importantes del síndrome de abstinencia, contribuyendo a la muerte neuronal que se encuentra en el alcoholismo crónico. Aunque no están tan bien comprendidas, las propiedades reforzadoras del etanol parecen estar mediadas fundamentalmente por la activación de receptores GABAA, la liberación de péptidos opioides, la interacción con receptores nicotínicos y la liberación indirecta de dopamina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);14(supl.1): 63-78, 2002. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136794</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bases bioquímicas y neurobiológicas de la adicción al alcohol</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32103^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29543^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30889^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31698^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13761^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200200</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
