<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107018</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevention and Detection of the Disorders of Food in Athletes of High Performance (CAR, CEARE and CTD)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this present paper we have analyzed the factors which determine the risks for an athlete to develop an Eating Disorder (ED). The level of a competition and the kind of sport practiced have been proved to influence the development of these risks. Among the athletes who seem to show an -apriori- bigger risk of developing the problems, we find those who compete in high performance competition, so, by means of this research paper we intend to detect using the Questionnaire for the eating habits in sportsmen and women (CHAD) sportsmen and sportswomen who are among those training in the Center of High Performance (CAR), the Center of Training and High Performance (CEARE) or the Center for the Sport Tech (CTD)that are more prone to the acquisition of an eating disorder and what influences this vulnerability, discovering that, in this precise case, it is women who practice a risky sport (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dosil Díaz, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Ceballos, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Fernández, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viñolas Ramisa, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este trabajo se analizan los factores que determinan el riesgo de que un deportista desarrolle un Trastorno de la Conducta Alimentaria(TCA). Se ha comprobado como el nivel de competición o el tipo de práctica puede influir en que ese riesgo aumente. Dentro de los deportistas que a priori presentan mayor riesgo se encuentran los que compiten en el alto rendimiento, por lo tanto, a través de este trabajo de investigación pretendemos detectar a través del Cuestionario de Hábitos Alimentarios del Deportistas- CHAD- quienes, de los deportistas que se encuentran en un CAR, CEARE o CTD, son los más vulnerables al desarrollo de un trastorno de alimentación y que influye en esta vulnerabilidad, encontrando, en este caso, que son las mujeres que practican deportes de riesgo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;12(1): 163-166, ene.-jun. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107018</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevención y detección de los trastornos de alimentación en deportistas de alto rendimiento (CAR, CEARE y CTD)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24382^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
