<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-67364</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Obesity can be considered as a low grade inflammatory disease, characterized by increased plasma levels of proinflammatory cytokines such as tumoral necrosis factor- alpha (TNF- alpha), and acute phase reactant proteins like C-reactive protein.  In this context, some cytokines of the interleukin-6 (IL-6) family have been involved in the inflammatory processes associated to obesity. In addition to IL-6, the IL-6 cytokine family includes IL-11, ciliary neurotrophic factor (cntf), cardiotrophin-1 (CT-1), cardiotrophin-like cytokine (CLC), leukemia inhibitory factor (LIF) y Oncostatin M (OsM). These proteins are also known as gp130 cytokines because all of them exert their action via the glycoprotein 130 (gp130) as a common transducer protein within their functional receptor complexes. However, their role in obesity and related disorders is controversial; thus, whereas some studies have described the involvement of gp130 cytokines in the development of obesity and its related cluster of pathophysiologic conditions like insulin-resistance, fatty liver and cardiovascular diseases, other trials have proposed the gp130 receptor ligands as therapeutic targets in the treatment of obesity and its related disorders. In fact, CNTF treatment has demonstrated to be effective in the reduction of body weight, by promoting the inhibition of food intake and the activation of the energy expenditure, together with an improvement of insulin sensitivity. This review analyzes the potential therapeutic role of some of the gp130 ligands in obesity and related diseases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marcos Gómez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Aliaga, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bustos, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La obesidad puede ser considerada como una patología inflamatoria crónica de bajo grado, caracterizada por una elevación de los niveles plasmáticos de citoquinas proinflamatorias como el factor de necrosis tumoral alfa (TNF-alpha), y proteínas reactantes de fase aguda como la proteína C reactiva. En este contexto, algunas de las citoquinas de la familia de interleuquina (IL-6) han sido también implicadas en el proceso inflamatorio asociado a obesidad y enfermedades relacionadas. Además de IL-6, pertenecen a esta familia citoquinas como IL-11, ciliary neurotrophic factor (CNTF), cardiotrophin-1 (CT-1), cardiotrophin- like cytokine (CLC), leukemia inhibitory factor (LIF) y oncostatin M (OsM). Todas ellas ejercen sus acciones biológicas mediante la interacción con un complejo receptor del que forma parte una molécula glicoproteica transductora de la señal denominada glicoproteína 130 (gp130), por lo que también se denominan citoquinas gp130.  Sin embargo, su papel en obesidad y sus complicaciones es controvertido; así, mientras que algunas han sido implicadas en el desarrollo de obesidad y enfermedades relacionadas como enfermedad hepática, insulino-resistencia y patología cardiovascular, otros estudios han llevado a proponer a los ligandos del receptor gp130 como potenciales agentes terapéuticos para el tratamiento de la obesidad y sus patologías asociadas. De hecho, el tratamiento con CNTF ha demostrado ser efectivo en la reducción del peso corporal, promoviendo la inhibición de la ingesta, la activación del gasto energético y la sensibilidad a la insulina. En esta revisión se analiza el potencial terapéutico de algunas de las citoquinas ligando del receptor gp130 en procesos de obesidad y enfermedades relacionadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;31(2): 113-123, mayo-ago.2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-67364</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8241^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33839^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10962</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28903^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10263^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28903</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31130^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200808</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
