<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133137</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Burnout syndrome and stress of nursing staff in a Ourense hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Set up the stress prevalence and burnout syndrome in different units of nursing staff of the Complexo Hospitalario Universitario de Ourense (CHUOU) and analyse which factors cause it. Materials and Methods. It has been designed a transversal, descriptive study by performing three assessment instruments: questionnaire of social-demographic variables; Maslach Burnout Inventory (MBI), and Nursing Stress Scale (NSS), to a 117 nursing staff of CHUOU as population. The average age was 39.23 years old and 83.8 % were women. Results. The average scoring in the emotional exhaustion dimension was 24.44, in the component of despersonalization was 7.58, and in the personal accomplishment was 34.50. Moreover, 89.7 % suffer stress related with work environment. The average score in the dimension of emotional exhaustion was 24.44, the depersonalization of 7.58 and the personal accomplishment of 34.50. The 89.7 % suffered from work-related stress. Conclusions. Nursing staff present high burnout syndrome and stress. It has been observed a higher vulnerability to the syndrome from subjects with temporary contract and rotary shift. There has been statistically significant differences in young nursing staff and less career seniority, whom present higher stress levels (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Soto-Rodríguez, Anxela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Fernández, M. Reyes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar la prevalencia del estrés y del síndrome de burnout en el personal de enfermería de distintas unidades del Complexo Hospitalario Universitario de Ourense (CHUOU) y analizar cuáles son los principales factores que lo causan. Material y Métodos. Se diseñó un estudio descriptivo transversal mediante la cumplimentación de tres instrumentos de evaluación: cuestionario de variables sociodemográficas; cuestionario Maslach Burnout Inventory (MBI), y cuestionario Nursing Stress Scale (NSS), a una población de 117 enfermeros del CHUOU. La edad promedio fue de 39.23 (± DT) años y el 83.8 % fueron mujeres. Resultados. La puntuación media obtenida en la dimensión de cansancio emocional fue de 24.44, en el componente de despersonalización de 7.58 y en el de realización personal de 34.50. Además, el 89.7 % sufría estrés relacionado con el ámbito laboral. Conclusiones. El personal de enfermería presentó altos índices de síndrome de burnout y estrés. Se observa que poseen una mayor vulnerabilidad al síndrome aquellos sujetos con contrato eventual y turno rotatorio. Existen diferencias estadísticamente significativas en los enfermeros de menor edad y con menor antigüedad tanto profesional como en el servicio actual, los cuales presentan mayores niveles de estrés (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;38(2): 101-106, feb. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133137</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de desgaste profesional (burnout) y estrés en personal de enfermería en un hospital de Ourense</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9926^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9926^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9926^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
