<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108647</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Available measurement methods of blood pressure at the community pharmacy for the screening and follow up of hypertension</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The blood pressure (BP) measurement in the physician&#146;s office has been for many years the gold standard for diagnosis, monitoring and making clinical decisions in the management of hypertension. On the other hand, few studies analyze the usefulness of the community pharmacy BP measurement method, which remains unknown in clinical practice. Home and ambulatory BP monitoring (HBPM and ABPM, respectively) have overcome many of the inherent limitations of the BP measurement at the physician&#146;s office, mainly providing multiple BP readings exempt from the white coat effect. Additionally, these methods have shown to be better predictors of end-organ damage and cardiovascular outcome than BP measured in the physician&#146;s offi ce. Finally, the use of HBPM or ABPM enables a more accurate assessment and an improved management of hypertension. This article provides an overview update on the interest of the different BP measurement methods available in the community pharmacy for the screening and monitoring of hypertensive patients(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sabater-Hernández, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fikri-Benbrahim, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fikri-Benbrahim, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Faus, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Azpilicueta, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La medida de la presión arterial (PA) en la consulta médica (PAC) ha sido durante muchos años el método de referencia para realizar el diagnóstico, seguimiento y tomar las decisiones clínicas en el manejo de la hipertensión arterial (HTA). Por otra parte, la medida de la PA en la farmacia comunitaria es un método poco estudiado y su utilidad en la práctica clínica es, cuando menos, desconocida. La aparición de la automedida domiciliaria de la PA (AMPA) y de la monitorización ambulatoria de la PA (MAPA) ha permitido superar muchas de las limitaciones inherentes a la medida de la PAC, principalmente al proporcionar múltiples medidas de PA exentas del efecto de bata blanca. Además, estos métodos han demostrado relacionarse más estrechamente que la medida de la PAC con el pronóstico cardiovascular y la lesión de órganos diana. En defi nitiva, la AMPA y la MAPA proporcionan una evaluación más precisa (p. ej., del riesgo cardiovascular o del efecto de los tratamientos antihipertensivos) y un mejor manejo del paciente con HTA. El presente artículo ofrece una visión actualizada sobre el interés de los distintos métodos de medida de la PA disponibles en la farmacia para el cribado y seguimiento del paciente hipertenso(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;13(3): 123-133, mayo-jun. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108647</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Métodos de medida de la presión arterial disponibles en la farmacia comunitaria para el cribado y seguimiento de la hipertensión arterial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55111^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
