<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156315</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Addressing bullous pemphigoid wounds in genital prolapse</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bullous and blistering diseases of the skin comprise a heterogeneous group of symptoms, which are essentially characterized by a common injury: blisters. Pemphigus and pemphigoid disorders are classified as blistering autoimmune diseases. The genital prolapse is the falling down or displacement of the pelvic organs through the vagina or towards the vulva, and which results from the loss of support structure and innervation and from a weak muscular tissue in both the urinary and intestinal system. What we are trying to show here is our experience and expertise in the care, management and topical treatment of bullous pemphigoid wounds in severe pelvic viscera prolapse, which used to make surgery difficult (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castro González, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barredo González, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro Fernández, Serafina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Palanca, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las enfermedades bullosas o ampollares comprenden un grupo heterogéneo de cuadros cuya lesión elemental común es la ampolla. Los pénfigos y los penfigoides pertenecen al grupo de las enfermedades bullosas de origen autoinmunitario. El prolapso genital es el descenso o desplazamiento de los órganos pélvicos, a través de la vagina y en dirección a la vulva, que se produce como consecuencia del fallo de sus elementos de suspensión y sustentación así como la inervación y musculatura del sistema urinario e intestinal. En este caso presentamos nuestra experiencia en el manejo y tratamiento tópico de lesiones por pénfigo ampolloso en prolapso visceropélvico total que dificultaban la cirugía (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);27(2): 80-84, jun. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156315</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abordaje de lesiones por pénfigo ampolloso en prolapso genital</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19270^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7225^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29576^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5967^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29502^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
