<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040953</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-2273</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sexuality and quality of life in the menopausal woman</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The sexuality is the expression of the privacy, and relationship whit physical, emotional, social, and spiritual dimensions of the persono A first step to obtain a satisfactory sexuality is to have an effective contraception that it releases the fear a non wished pregnancy at a time where maternal and perinatal complications are increased. The sexuality has a important repercussion in the quality of life and although this it is a subjective concept for each individual, is necessary actually clinical to have tools that aIlow to obtain an objective evaluation. With this idea the Cervantes scale was designed that allows the valuation of quality of life of the menopausal woman in our country and to state the possible changes produced after a therapeutic intervention</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cancelo Hidalgo, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La sexualidad es la forma de expresión de la intimidad, y en ella se manifiestan las dimensiones física, emocional, social y espiritual de la persona. Un primer paso para conseguir una sexualidad satisfactoria es disponer de una anticoncepción efectiva que libere el temor frente a un embarazo no deseado en una época donde las complicaciones maternas y perinatales están aumentadas. La sexualidad tiene una repercusión importante en la calidad de vida y aunque éste es un concepto subjetivo para cada individuo, resulta necesaria en la práctica clínica disponer de herramientas que permitan obtener una evaluación objetiva. Con esta idea se diseñó la escala Cervantes que permite la valoración de calidad de vida de la mujer posmenopáusiéa en nuestro medio y constatar los posibles cambios producidos tras una intervención terapéutica</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cienc. ginecol;9(6): 337-344, nov.-dic. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040953</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sexualidad y calidad de vida en la mujer menopáusica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11709^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22243^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3289</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32048^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22243^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11709^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
