<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057787</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Three techniques for measuring dorsal flexion of the ankle: Intra- and inter-observer reliability</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Ankle flexion is often measured in our field using different procedures; a lack of protocols for their use has been noted. The objective of our study is to estimate the reliability of the three most frequently employed methods in our environment.                 Material and methods. A randomized, single-blinded, descriptive, transversal study was performed in thirty volunteers without associated pathology. A goniometer and inclinometer (PLURIMETER-V) were used in addition to visual estimation. Measurements were obtained using the same assessment sequence in two separate sessions one week apart by two physicians from our department. The SPSS program was used to obtain the correlation and means of the intra- and inter-observer data to evaluate the reliability of the methods employed, with a 95 % confidence interval.                 Results. Intraobserver observations were moderately reliable for the use of the inclinometer; interobserver reliability was also moderate for the use of all three methods.                 Discussion. We would recommend the use of the inclinometer as the most reliable method and would emphasize the need for better management of the instruments used to evaluate dorsal flexion of the ankle</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-García de Velasco, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Torrico, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo-Guisado, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Borrego, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conejero-Casares, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La medición de la flexión del tobillo es una determinación frecuente en nuestro medio a través de diferentes procedimientos, habiéndose detectado una falta de protocolización en el uso de éstos. El objetivo de nuestro trabajo es la estimación de la fiabilidad de los tres métodos más usados en nuestro medio.                 Material y método. Estudio transversal descriptivo a simple ciego de treinta sujetos voluntarios elegidos al azar sin patología asociada. Se usó como instrumental un goniómetro y un inclinómetro PLURIMETER-V, además de la estimación visual. Se realizaron dos sesiones de mediciones separadas por una semana, siguiendo la misma secuencia de valoración por dos médicos del Servicio. Mediante el programa SPSS se obtuvieron la correlación y medias de los datos intra e interobservador para valorar la fiabilidad de los métodos usados, para un intervalo de confianza del 95 %.                 Resultados. Se determinó una fiabilidad moderada intraobservador con el uso del inclinómetro; siendo esta fiabilidad también moderada en el caso de la valoración interobservador con el uso de los tres métodos.                 Discusión. Se recomendaría el uso del inclinómetro como método más fiable y se destacaría la necesidad de un mejor manejo del instrumental usado para la valoración de la flexión dorsal de tobillo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);41(5): 200-206, sep.2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057787</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tres técnicas de medición de la flexión dorsal del tobillo: fiabilidad inter e intraobservador</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24807</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d857^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
