<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94564</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Working disability in multiple sclerosis: a propos of a case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A 34-year old woman, nurse, who arrives to the Medical Assessment Disability Unit of SSNI (Social Security National Institute) for to assess Temporary Disability (TD), she was diagnosed of Multiple Sclerosis(MS) 10 years ago, she had 6 outbreaks and because of that she was treated with Glatiramer Acetate and also her workstation was adapted. At the moment she has an EDSS (Expanded Disability Status Scale) of 1.0, and now she does not receive immunomodulator treatment With this case report we want to know the way that labour disability is evaluated for workers that complain of MS, also how the damage degree is determined according to EDSS and what labour aspects are taken into consideration (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Arcilla Conejo, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Chumbes, Gian C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Escribano, Marina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Enfermera de 34 años de edad que acude a la Unidad Médica de Valoración de Incapacidades del INSS (Instituto Nacional de Seguridad Social) para valoración de Incapacidad Temporal (IT); diagnosticada de Esclerosis Múltiple (EM) hace 10 años, presentó 6 brotes, por lo que requirió tratamiento con Acetato de Glatirámero y se le adaptó el puesto de trabajo. Actualmente tiene un EDSS (Expanded Disability StatusScale) estimado de 1,0, y actualmente no está con tratamiento inmunomodulador.Este caso clínico lo que busca es conocer de qué manera se valora la incapacidad laboral en los casosde trabajadores que padecen de EM, asimismo cómo se determina el grado de menoscabo en función del EDSS y qué aspectos laborales son tomados en consideración (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;56(221): 323-327, oct.-dic. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94564</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incapacidad laboral en esclerosis múltiple: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7336^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30459^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
