<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136754</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-695X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Changes in the metabolic control of type 2 diabetic patients in a health center</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To know the changes achieved in a period of four years in the control of diabetic patients, and the changes in the use of medication in routine practice. Study design:  Cross-sectional descriptive study. Setting: Primary Care Centre of Manzanares II (Manzanares &#150; Ciudad Real &#150; Spain). Participants: Diabetic patients of both sexes in the Health Zone. Measurements:  Sociodemographic data, cardiovascular risk factors, macro and microvascular impact of diabetes, blood pressure and analytical parameters (glucidic, lipidic), as well as drugs used in the treatment of diabetes and dyslipidemia, and antiplatelet/anticoagulant drugs were collected. These data were compared with those of the cross-sectional descriptive study conducted in 2010. Results: The metabolic control (HbA1C) has improved in 2014: 7.09 % (SD:1.17) with regard to 2010: 7.22 % (SD: 1.21), being significant in the percentage of higher values of HbA1C (&amp;#8805;8 % and &amp;#8805;10 %). The percentage of HbA1C &amp;#8804;7 % has increased from 50.5 % to 53.7 %. The largest decreases have occurred in the lipid parameters: total cholesterol   (p&lt;0.001), LDL-cholesterol (p &lt;0.001)) and microalbuminuria (p &lt;0.01). The percentage of HbA1C &amp;#8804;7 % and LDL-cholesterol &amp;#8804;100 mg/dl has increased from 13.1 % to 21.7 % (p &lt;0,01). The use of sulfonylureas has decreased (p &lt;0.01) and those of IDDP-4 (p &lt;0.001), statins (p &lt;0.05) and  acetyilsalicylic acid (p &lt;0.01) have increased. Conclusions:  The carbohydrate metabolic control has improved during a period of four years, with significant changes in lipid parameters. The use of sulfonylureas has decreased, and the use of IDPP-4, statins and acetylsalicylic acid has increased (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Sánchez-Migallón, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer los cambios producidos en un período de cuatro años en el control de los pacientes diabéticos y en el uso de la medicación en la práctica habitual. Diseño del estudio:  Estudio descriptivo, observacional, transversal. Emplazamiento:  Zona de Salud Manzanares II (Manzanares &#150; Ciudad Real &#150; España). Participantes:  Pacientes diabéticos de ambos sexos de la Zona de Salud. Mediciones principales: Se recogieron datos sociodemográficos, factores de riesgo cardiovascular, repercusión macro y microvascular de la diabetes, valores analíticos (glucídicos, lipídicos) y tensionales, así como los fármacos empleados en el tratamiento de diabetes, dislipemia y con efecto antiagregante/anticoagulante. Los datos fueron comparados con los del estudio observacional realizado en 2010. Resultados:  El control metabólico (HbA1c) ha mejorado en 2014: 7,09% (DE: 1,17) respecto a 2010: 7,22% (DE: 1,21), siendo significativo en el porcentaje de valores más elevados de HbA1c (&amp;#8805;8% y &amp;#8805;10%). El porcentaje de HbA1c &amp;#8804;7% ha pasado del 50,5% al 53,7%. Los mayores descensos se han producido en los parámetros lipídicos: colesterol total (p&lt;0,001), LDL-colesterol (p&lt;0,001) y microalbuminuria (p&lt;0,01). El porcentaje de HbA1c &amp;#8804;7% y LDL-colesterol &amp;#8804;100 mg/dl ha pasado del 13,1% al 21,7% (p&lt;0,01). Ha disminuido el uso de sulfonilureas (p&lt;0,01) y aumentado el de IDDP-4 (p&lt;0,001), estatinas (p&lt;0,05) y de ácido acetilsalicílico (p&lt;0,01). Conclusiones: En el periodo de cuatro años ha mejorado el control metabólico glucídico, siendo significativo el cambio en el patrón lipídico. Ha disminuido el uso de sulfonilureas y ha aumentado el uso de IDPP-4, estatinas y ácido acetilsalicílico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. clín. med. fam;8(1): 11-18, feb. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136754</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambios en el control metabólico de los pacientes diabéticos tipo 2 de un centro de salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22965^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52151^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d963^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52151^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
