<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165495</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-654X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Role of 18F-FDG PET/CT in primary brain lymphoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To study the usefulness of 18F-FDG PET/CT in the initial evaluation and in the response assessment in primary brain lymphoma. Material and methods: A retrospective analysis was carried out on 18 patients diagnosed with primary brain lymphoma, a histological subtype of diffuse large B-cell lymphoma, on whom an initial 18F-FDG PET/CT and MRI was performed, with 7 of the cases being analysed after the completion of treatment in order to assess response and clinical follow up. Results: Initial 18F-FDG PET/CT showed 26 hypermetabolic foci, whereas 46 lesions were detected by MRI. The average SUV maximum of the lesions was 17.56 with T/N 3.55. The concordance of both tests for identifying the same number of lesions was moderate, obtaining a kappa index of 0.395 (P&lt;.001). In the evaluation of treatment, MRI identified 16 lesions compared to 7 pathological accumulations observed by 18F-FDG PET/CT. The concordance of both tests to assess type of response to treatment was moderate (kappa index 0.41) (P=.04). In both the initial evaluation and the assessment of the response to treatment, PET/CT led to a change strategy in 22% of patients who had lesions outside the cerebral parenchyma. Conclusions: MRI appears to be the method of choice for detecting brain disease in patients with primary brain lymphoma, whereas 18F-FDG PET/CT seems to play a relevant role in the assessment of extra-cerebral disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Capote Huelva, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borrego Dorado, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Egea Guerrero, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández López, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonilla Damiá, Á de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz Vicente, F de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudiar la utilidad de la 18F-FDG PET/TC en la evaluación inicial y valoración de la respuesta al tratamiento en el linfoma cerebral primario. Material y métodos: Se analizaron retrospectivamente 18 pacientes diagnosticados de linfoma cerebral primario, subtipo histológico linfoma difuso de células grandes B, habiéndose realizado en todos ellos un estudio con 18F-FDG PET/TC y RM inicial y, en 7 casos, también tras la realización de tratamiento con el fin de valorar la respuesta. Resultados: La 18F-FDG PET/TC inicial detectó un total de 26 depósitos hipermetabólicos frente a un total de 46 lesiones de la RM. La media del SUV máximo de las lesiones fue de 17,56 y del T/N, de 3,55. La concordancia de ambas pruebas para identificar el mismo número de lesiones fue moderada, obteniendo un índice kappa de 0,395 (p&lt;0,001). En la valoración de la respuesta al tratamiento la RM identificó 16 lesiones frente a los 7 acúmulos patológicos de la 18F-FDG PET/TC. La concordancia de ambas pruebas para valorar el tipo de respuesta al tratamiento fue moderada (índice kappa 0,41) (p=0,04). Tanto en la evaluación inicial como en la valoración de la respuesta al tratamiento la PET/TC facilitó un cambio de estrategia en un 22% de los pacientes que presentaron lesiones fuera del parénquima cerebral. Conclusiones: La RM parece ser la técnica de elección en la valoración de la enfermedad cerebral en pacientes con linfoma cerebral primario, mientras que la PET/TC ha demostrado tener un papel importante en la valoración de la enfermedad extracerebral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. med. nucl. imagen mol. (Ed. impr.);36(5): 298-303, sept.-oct. 2017. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165495</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de la 18F-FDG PET/TC en el linfoma cerebral primario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8398^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4367</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22878^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35170^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1958^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38793^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33478^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33090^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
