<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058599</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Determinants of job satisfaction in long-term care facilities</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: the present study analyzed levels of job satisfaction among nurses and auxiliary nurses working with the elderly in public institutions in the Canary Islands. The effect of demographic and work-related variables on job satisfaction was also evaluated.                 Material and method: a descriptive correlational survey design was used in a sample of 227 participants who completed Font-Roja's job satisfaction questionnaire and another questionnaire on demographic and work-related variables. The association among variables was assessed using odds ratios and 95% confidence intervals. Adjustment for confounders was performed by logistic regression.                 Results: nurses showed a higher level of satisfaction than auxiliary nurses due to differences in the dimensions of work monotony and satisfaction with position. Overall, both groups scored lowest on physical environment and work-related strain. The best scores were for job content and position-related strain. Multivariate analysis revealed that the variables that best explained job satisfaction were the procedures used to assign work, shifts and job situation.                 Conclusions: improvements in human and material resources and modification of certain organisational aspects are proposed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fariña-López, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marrero-Medina, Carmen Delia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Marrero, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estévez-Guerra, Gabriel J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez-González, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: este trabajo evalúa el grado de satisfacción laboral de enfermeros/as y auxiliares de enfermería dedicados a la atención de personas mayores en instituciones públicas de Canarias. Asimismo, explora el impacto de variables demográficas y laborales en aquélla.                 Material y método: estudio descriptivo-correlacional. La muestra estuvo constituida por 227 trabajadores que contestaron al cuestionario Font-Roja de satisfacción laboral, y a otro de variables demográficas y laborales. Para cuantificar el grado de asociación utilizamos la odds ratio, y un intervalo de confianza del 95%. Los factores de confusión se ajustaron mediante regresión logística.                 Resultados: las enfermeras tienen mayor satisfacción que las auxiliares, y esta diferencia radica en las dimensiones monotonía laboral y satisfacción con el puesto. De forma general, ambos grupos presentan las puntuaciones más bajas en entorno físico y tensión relacionada con el trabajo. Por contra, las dimensiones contenido del trabajo y tensión relacionada con el puesto obtienen los mejores valores. El análisis multivariante pone de manifiesto que la forma de ser asignada al puesto de trabajo, el turno y la situación laboral son las variables que mejor explican la satisfacción laboral.                 Conclusiones: se proponen mejoras en recursos materiales y humanos, y la modificación de algunos aspectos organizacionales</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);42(5): 285-292, sept. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058599</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Determinantes de la satisfacción laboral en centros geriátricos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9914</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9926^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9926^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
