<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167296</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of an Xpert EV (Cepheid(R)) molecular diagnostic technique for enteroviral meningitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) assays have shown to be useful and quick for the diagnosis of enterovirus in aseptic meningitis. The aim of our study was to analyse the changes in clinical practice after the introduction of a real-time polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) technique using the Xpert EV (Cepheid(R)) assay for the qualitative detection of enterovirus RNA in cerebrospinal fluid specimens from children with suspected viral meningitis. Methods: A retrospective study was performed in children older than 1 year, diagnosed with enterovirus meningitis in a third level hospital from November 2006 to February 2013. The first period, before the availability of Xpert EV (Cepheid(R)) (Group 1, November 2006-August 2010) was compared with the later period (Group 2, September 2010-February 2013). Clinical characteristics, the mean length of stay, and the cost per inpatient cases, were compared between the 2 periods. Results: Forty-one patients (60.9% male) were included, with a median age of 64 months (interquartile range 28-96). Twenty-six patients (63.4%) were included in Group 2. There were non-statistically significant differences in the epidemiological, disease severity, and laboratory characteristics between both periods of study. A significant difference was observed in the mean length of stay, with it being shorter in Group2 (48 hours vs 40.5 hours, P = .039), and a significant lower inpatient cost per case (Euros 779.77 vs Euros 656.05, P &lt; .05). Conclusion: Xpert EV (Cepheid(R)) assay was useful for decreasing the length of hospital stay and the costs associated with hospitalisation in children with enterovirus meningitis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Torralba, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto Tato, Luis Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillén Martín, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Amador, José Tomás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Bermejo, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Pérez, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sagastizabal Cardelus, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las técnicas de biología molecular han demostrado ser útiles en la detección del enterovirus en niños con meningitis aséptica. El objetivo de nuestro estudio fue analizar cambios en la práctica clínica tras la introducción de una técnica de RT-PCR a tiempo real, ensayo Xpert EV (Cepheid(R)), para la detección de enterovirus en muestras de líquido cefalorraquídeo de niños con sospecha de meningitis vírica. Métodos: Estudio retrospectivo de los niños mayores de 1año diagnosticados de meningitis por enterovirus en un hospital de tercer nivel desde noviembre de 2006 a febrero de 2013. Se comparó el periodo previo a la introducción del ensayo Xpert EV (Cepheid(R)) (grupo1: noviembre 2006-agosto de 2010) con el periodo posterior (grupo2: septiembre 2010-febrero 2013). Se compararon las características clínicas, los tiempos de estancia media y los costes por hospitalización. Resultados: Se incluyeron 41 pacientes con una mediana de edad de 64 meses (rango intercuartílico, 28-96). En el grupo 2 se incluyeron 26 pacientes (63,4%). No hubo diferencias epidemiológicas, de gravedad, ni de laboratorio estadísticamente significativas entre los pacientes valorados en ambos grupos. Se observó una disminución significativa en la duración de estancia media hospitalaria en el grupo 2 (48 h vs 40,5 h, p = 0,039) y una disminución significativa en el gasto por paciente hospitalizado (779,77 Euros vs. 656,05 Euros, p&lt;0,05). Conclusiones: La incorporación de la técnica Xpert EV (Cepheid(R)) permitió disminuir la estancia y el gasto asociado a hospitalización en niños con meningitis por enterovirus (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);87(4): 201-205, oct. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167296</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de una técnica de diagnóstico molecular Xpert EV (Cepheid(R)) en la meningitis por enterovirus</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4849^s22043</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8752^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31734^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13513^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
