<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93440</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Benefits of blackberry nectar (Rubus spp. ) relative to hypercholesterolemia and lipid peroxidation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: In humans, the normal metabolic activity produces free radicals that constantly, along with other risk factors, including hypercholesterolemia may be responsible for the onset of degenerative diseases. Some bioactive compounds present in blackberry (Rubus spp.) have the ability to act as natural antioxidants can make the food to minimize effects on the body caused by reactive oxygen species. Objective: This study verified the benefits of blackberry nectar through the quantification of triglycerides, total and fraction cholesterol HDL (high density lipoprotein) and LDL-cholesterol (low density lipoprotein), blood glucose and lipid peroxidation in hypercholesterolemic hamsters. Methods: Two groups were treated with hypercholesterolemic diets (0.1% cholesterol), one of them receiving an additional 5 mL of nectar daily, and a third (control group) treated only with a standard diet. In the blood the quantification of lipids, blood glucose and lipid peroxidation was performed. In the brain, liver and small intestine the lipid peroxidation was determined and in other organs, histopathological evaluations were carried out. Results: The blackberry nectar reduced the triglycerides serum levels, total cholesterol and LDL-cholesterol in hypercholesterolemic hamsters, without influencing the HDL and blood glucose concentrations. A decrease in the initiation of lipid peroxidation reactions in the blood, brain and small intestine was also observed. Only the liver showed histopathological changes (steatosis), due to excess cholesterol, with no positive influence from the nectar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodrigues Machado, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva Rodrigues, R da</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gevehr Fernandes, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva Santos, V da</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferreira de Araujo, PR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En los seres humanos, la actividad metabólica normal produce radicales libres que constantemente, junto con otros factores de riesgo, incluyendo la hipercolesterolemia puede ser responsable de la aparición de enfermedades degenerativas. Algunos de los compuestos bioactivos presentes en mora (Rubus spp.) tienen la capacidad de actuar como antioxidantes naturales pueden hacer que los alimentos para minimizar los efectos sobre el cuerpo causados por las especies reactivas de oxígeno. Objetivo: Verificar los beneficios del néctar de mora a través de la cuantificación de triglicéridos, colesterol total y fracciones HDL (lipoproteína de alta densidad) y colesterol-LDL (liproteína de baja densidad), glucosa en la sangre y la peroxidación lipídica en hamsters hipercolesterolémicos. Métodos: Dos grupos fueron tratados con dieta hipercolesterolémica (0,1% de colesterol), que consumían diariamente, otros 5 mL de néctar, y un tercero (grupo control) tratados sólo con dieta estándar. En el sangre se realizo la cuantificación del lípidos, glucosa y la peroxidación lipídica. En el cerebro, el hígado y el intestino delgado se determinó la peroxidación lipídica y en otros órganos, evaluaciones histopatológicas. Resultados: El néctar de mora reduce los triglicéridos séricos, colesterol total y LDL-colesterol en hamsters hipercolesterolémicos, no influyen en los niveles de colesterol HDL y glucosa en la sangre. También se observo la disminución de las reacciones de iniciación de la peroxidación de lípidos en la sangre, el cerebro y el intestino delgado. El hígado, mostraron cambios patológicos (esteatosis), debido al exceso de colesterol, sin la influencia positiva de néctar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;26(5): 984-990, sept.-oct. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93440</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Beneficios del néctar de mora (Rubus spp.) en relación con la hipercolesterolemia y la peroxidación lipídica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29404</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8230^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5774</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5744^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d979^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37575</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
