<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-68422</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: high frequency and intensity of obsessive thinking and compulsive behaviour at a level which interferes with leading normal life are the characteristics of the Obsessive- compulsive disorder. Objective: the aim of this work is to analyze the main clinical characteristics in a group of patients of a Children and Youth Psychiatric Unit. Material and methods: descriptive observational study based on the systematic review of the clinical records of 11 patients. The most important factors related to clinical aspects, progression of the illness and treatment where evaluated and compared with the principal related publications. Results: the most frequent obsessions where fear of death and of illness, while the most frequent compulsions where cleanness and order. Fifty-five percent of the sample was suffering from other metal disorders and the parents of 65% of cases had some psychiatric diagnosis. All patients were treated with sertraline, in association with other psychotropic drugs when the progression of the illness was not adequate. Conclusions: most of the patients of this series show familiar records of mental disorders, comorbidity with other psychiatric illness and, sometimes require more than one psychotropic drug. Early detection is very important for a positive control and treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodrigues, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Godinho, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rocha, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Cortés, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: el trastorno obsesivo compulsivo se caracteriza por la presencia de ideas obsesivas y patrones conductuales compulsivos con la suficiente frecuencia e intensidad como para interferir en la vida normal de quien lo padece. Objetivo: realizar un análisis descriptivo de una serie de niños y adolescentes afectos de trastorno obsesivo compulsivo que acuden a una unidad de psiquiatría infantil y juvenil. Material y métodos: se realiza un estudio observacional descriptivo de 11 pacientes a partir de la revisión sistemática de sus historias clínicas. Se evalúan los condicionantes clínicos, evolutivos y terapéuticos más importantes y se contrastan con las publicaciones anteriores más relevantes. Resultados: las obsesiones más frecuentes son el temor a la muerte y a padecer una enfermedad, mientras que las compulsiones más frecuentes son la limpieza y el orden. El 55% de la muestra presentan comorbilidad con otras enfermedades mentales, y en el 65% de los casos alguno de los padres tiene un diagnóstico psiquiátrico. El tratamiento utilizado en todos los pacientes es la sertralina, unida a otros psicofármacos cuando la evolución no es adecuada. Conclusiones: la mayoría de los pacientes de la serie descrita presentan antecedentes familiares de trastornos mentales, comorbilidad con otras enfermedades psiquiátricas y en ocasiones requieren más de un psicofármaco. Es importante el diagnóstico precoz para un adecuado seguimiento y tratamiento posterior (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;10(39): 423-432, jul.-sept. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-68422</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38404</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200807</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
