<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045585</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ntwork review by the mental health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this article context we highlight the importance of family and personal relationships in the progress, development and treatment of persons who are in the care of us. These relationships may be formal or informal and they are a condition for a normal development. Methodological difficulties present at daily work are a handicap or an obstacle that may make difficult to have a clear and global view of contacts and relations of our patients. And we may have a difficulty for us to know what type of groups are better for the treatment, or what type of groups we can advise to be activated or not, as alcoholic groups for alcoholic people. Below we present concepts and basic instruments to be used by the nurse in an easy and practical way to represent both social network and individuals characteristics of the persons of the network, or at least those considered important by the professional. Our professional practice shows that this is a valuable instrument to represent in a clear way and concisely the social structure of the patient and his network relationships, and so it can make easier both psychological and social treatment, as the monitoring of his illness and the integration of the patient in the healthy networks</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Laborda, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Rodríguez, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo destacamos la importancia de las relaciones familiares y personales en el desencadenamiento, evolución y tratamiento de las personas a las que cuidamos, las relaciones tanto formales como informales que estos deben llevar a cabo para desenvolverse en la vida normal. Las dificultades metodológicas que se presentan en la actividad diaria de asistencia imposibilita o hace complicado tener una visión clara y global de los contactos y relaciones de nuestros pacientes, así como de que grupos de relaciones, desde la óptica del tratamiento, debemos aconsejar activar o desactivar, como es el caso de grupos de amigos alcohólicos en el caso de pacientes alcohólicos en tratamiento. A continuación presentamos los conceptos y instrumentos básicos, para que la enfermera tenga unos medios sencillos y prácticos, de representar tanto la red social como la caracterización de los individuos que la componen, o por lo menos de aquellos que la profesional considera mas importantes De la práctica que nosotros tenemos, se ha revelado como un instrumento valioso para la representación clara y concisa de la estructura social del paciente, y de su red de relaciones, lo que facilita tanto el tratamiento psicosocial, como del seguimiento de su enfermedad y de la integración de este en redes con estilos de vida saludables</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;14(48/49): 46-49, ene.-abr. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045585</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de red en Salud Mental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
