<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113859</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-2597</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cerebral arteriovenous malformation as a cause of congestive heart failure in a newborn</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Arteriovenous malformation of the vein of Galen represents a very uncommon congenital vascular anomaly. This patology occurs preferably in neonatal period, and can cause severe morbi-mortality. Clinical presentation is variable. Association of cranial murmur and heart failure are frequent presentations in neonatal period. The degree of heart failure associated represents the main prognostic factor and determinant of the treatment, which consists, first, in the symptomatic treatment of the same, and secondly, in the treatment of the vascular lesion, either by surgery, or by intravascular access, method that has improved results in recent years. We report the case of a male neonate with prenatal diagnosis of aneurysmal dilatation of the vein of Galen, that was confirmed in the postnatal period and developed congestive heart failure that does not respond to treatment initiated, and died at four days old (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lareu Vidal, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montes Granda, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Sánchez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bueno Pardo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solís Sánchez, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Montes, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La malformación arterio-venosa de la vena de Galeno representa una anomalía congénita vascular muy infrecuente. Esta patología se presenta de forma preferente en el periodo neonatal pudiendo causar una importante morbi-mortalidad. La forma de presentación clínica es muy variable, siendo la asociación de soplo craneal e insuficiencia cardiaca la forma de presentación más frecuente en el periodo neonatal. El grado de insuficiencia cardiaca asociada constituye el principal factor pronóstico y condicionante del tratamiento, que consistirá, en primer lugar en el tratamiento sintomático de la misma, y en segundo lugar, en el tratamiento de la lesión vascular, bien mediante cirugía, o mediante acceso intravascular, método que ha mejorado los resultados en los últimos años. Se presenta el caso de un neonato varón con diagnóstico prenatal de malformación aneurismática de la vena de Galeno que se confirmó en el periodo postnatal, y que desarrolló insuficiencia cardiaca congestiva refractaria al tratamiento instaurado, siendo éxitus a los cuatro días de vida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Bol. pediatr;53(223): 37-40, ene.-mar. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113859</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Malformación arterio-venosa cerebral causante de insuficiencia cardiaca congestiva en un neonato</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19099^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2569^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52606^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54238^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52590^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
