<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041920</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Legal Medicine of Primary Care Pediatrics (I). Medico-legal documents: clinical history and injury report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the present study, the most interesting aspects of legal medicine that may arise formedical staff in the practice of basic pediatric attention are studied, for example the fillingin of the medical history and the issuing of the injury report.The legislation in force regarding these questions is examined and discussed: the PenalCode, the Law of Penal Procedure, the General Health Law, the Ethical and DeontologicalMedical Code and the basic law that regulates the autonomy of the patient and his/herrights and obligations in relation to information and clinical documents</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pastor Bravo, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodes Lloret, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se abordan en el presente trabajo los aspectos médico-legales de mayor interés, que sele pueden plantear al pediatra, en el ejercicio de su profesión en Atención Primaria, como esla cumplimentación de la historia clínica y la emisión del parte de lesiones.Se revisa y se discute, asimismo, la legislación vigente a este respecto: Código Penal,Ley de Enjuiciamiento Criminal, Ley General de Sanidad, Código de Ética y DeontologíaMédica y Ley 41/2002, básica reguladora de la autonomía del paciente y de derechos yobligaciones en materia de información y documentación clínica</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;7(27): 489-503, jul.-sept. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041920</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Medicina legal de la asistencia pediátrica en Atención Primaria (I). Documentos médicolegales: historia clínica y parte de lesiones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28219^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5082</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2710^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17550</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
