<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129461</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Necrotic eschar and neck lymphadenopathy after tick bite: TIBOLA</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Tick-borne lymphadenopathy (TIBOLA) is an emerging dise­ase caused by Rickettsia slovaca. It is a zoonoses transmitted to humans by Dermacentor marginatus tick-bite. Patients presents with a necrotic eschar surrounded by a perilesional erythematous halo on the scalp and painful regional lymphadenopathies. We present a case of a 4-years old girl with necrotic eschar on the scalp and painful cervical lymphadenopathy after tick bite (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Flor Parra, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Croche Santander, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tena, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez Santos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tort Pérez, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La linfadenopatía por picadura de garrapata (TIBOLA, por sus siglas en inglés: tick-borne lymphadenopathy) es una enfermedad emergente causada por Rickettsia slovaca. Es una zoonosis transmitida por la picadura de la garrapata Dermacentor marginatus. Los pacientes afectados presentan una escara necrótica rodeada de un halo eritematoso en el cuero cabelludo, así como adenopatías regionales dolorosas. Presentamos el caso de una niña de 4 años de edad con escara necrótica y linfadenopatías cervicales dolorosas tras una picadura de garrapata (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;72(8): e285-e287, sept. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129461</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Escara necrótica y linfadenopatías cervicales tras una picadura de garrapata: TIBOLA</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8383^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8383^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8383^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8383^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8383^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52156</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24377^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
