<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137535</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Insect bites in Spain. Pediatric guideline for Primary Care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Insect bites are a common reason for consultation in primary care. There are enough pediatric guidelines and protocols for treating children appropriately. However, stings are heavily influenced by lore. Because of this, pediatricians could change their performance sometimes, mainly if they are guided by customs and practices based on unscientific treatments. A review on the subject is presented with the aim of recommending a general attitude to treat insect bites in children. Several comments about some particular cases are also carried, such as spiders, scorpions and ticks, always taking into account the real possibilities in the Spanish territory, regardless of tropical or exotic insects. Preventive measures against stings and hypersensitivity phenomena are also covered in this document (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Piñeiro Pérez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carabaño Aguado, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las picaduras de insecto constituyen un motivo habitual de consulta en Atención Primaria. Existen suficientes guías clínicas pediátricas y protocolos para atender de forma apropiada a los niños. Sin embargo, se trata de situaciones clínicas muy influenciadas por la tradición popular. Esto, en ocasiones, puede incluso alterar la actuación del pediatra, si se deja guiar por costumbres, prácticas y tratamientos basados en divulgación no científica. Se presenta una revisión sobre el tema con el objetivo principal de recomendar una actitud general para tratar las picaduras de insecto en niños. Se realizan además una serie de apreciaciones sobre algunos casos en particular, como por ejemplo arañas, escorpiones y garrapatas, siempre valorando las posibilidades reales en territorio español, sin considerar insectos tropicales o exóticos. También se abordan medidas preventivas frente a las picaduras y aspectos relativos a fenómenos alérgicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;17(66): 159-166, abr.-jun. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137535</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo práctico de las picaduras de insecto en Atención Primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d721^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d721^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7473^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7473^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6792^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d714^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1101^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1101^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1101^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55228^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55227^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d721^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55228^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55227^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
