<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93292</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Association of insulin resistance to different anthropometric measures and cardiovascular risk factors in a non-diabetic population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and Objective: Insulin resistance (IR) has been directly related to obesity, particularly central obesity, and to other cardiovascular risk factors (CVRFs). Direct IR quantification is difficult in clinical practice, and indirect methods such as HOMA (homeostasis model assessment) have therefore been developed. The aim of this study was to assess the association ofI R, as measured by HOMA, with different anthropometric measures and some CVRFs. Materials and Methods: A cross-sectional, observational study was carried out in a general population sample older than 18 years in the province of Albacete, Spain. Sample size was678 subjects. Participants completed a survey and underwent physical examinations and laboratory tests. Obesity measures included body mass index, waist perimeter, and sagittal abdominal diameter. Data analysis was performed using SPSS 15.0 software. Results: Mean values of obesity measures were higher in males as compared to females and increased with age. IR prevalence was 39.8%. All assessed anthropometric measures, decreased HDL (high density lipoprotein) cholesterol and increased non-HDL cholesterol were independently associated to the risk of IR. Conclusions: A clear association exists between different anthropometrical measures and IR in the general population. There is also an association between lipid profile cahnges and the risk of experiencing IR (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grupo de Enfermedades Vasculares de Albacete (GEVA)</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes y objetivo: La resistencia a la insulina (RI) se ha relacionado directamente con la obesidad, especialmente la obesidad central, y con otros factores de riesgo cardiovascular(FRCV). La cuantificación de la RI de forma directa es difícil en la práctica clínica, por lo que se han desarrollado métodos indirectos como el índice homeostasis model assessment (HOMA).El objetivo de este estudio fue valorar la asociación existente entre la RI, medida por índice HOMA, con diferentes medidas antropométricas y algunos FRCV. Material y métodos: Se trata de un estudio observacional transversal realizado en una muestra de población general mayor de 18 años de la provincia de Albacete. El tamaño muestral fue de 678 sujetos. Se realizaron encuesta, exploración física y analítica a los participantes. Las medidas de obesidad valoradas fueron índice de masa corporal, perímetro de cintura y diámetro sagital abdominal. El análisis de datos se realizó con el programa SPSS 15.0.Resultados: Los valores medios de las medidas de obesidad fueron mayores en varones que en mujeres y aumentan con la edad. La prevalencia de RI fue del 39,8%. Todas las medidas antropométricas evaluadas, el descenso del colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de alta densidad(HDL) y el aumento del colesterol no unido a HDL se asocian de manera independiente con el riesgo de presentar RI. Conclusiones: Existe una clara relación entre diferentes medidas antropométricas y la RI en población general. También hay relación entre las alteraciones del perfil lipidio y el riesgo de presentar RI (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;58(9): 464-471, nov. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93292</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación de la resistencia a la insulina con diferentes medidasantropométricas y factores de riesgo cardiovascular en unapoblación no diabética</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201111</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
