<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101993</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">&#147;Time is brain&#148;: only in the acute phase of stroke?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objective: In Spain, stroke is the leading cause of death in women as well as the leading cause of disability in adults. This translates into a huge human and economic cost. In recent years there have been significant advances both in the treatment of acute stroke and in the neuro-rehabilitation process; however, it is still unclear when the best time is to initiate neurorehabilitation and what the consequences of delaying treatment are. To test the effect of a single day delay in the onset of neurorehabilitation on functional improvement achieved, and the influence of that delay in the rate of institutionalisation at discharge.Methods: A retrospective study of patients admitted to Parkwood Hospital's Stroke Neurorehabilitation Unit (UNRHI) (University of Western Ontario, Canada) between April 2005 and September 2008 was performed. We recorded age, Functional Independence Measurement (FIM) score at admission and discharge, the number of days between the onset of stroke and admission to the Neurorehabilitation Unit and discharge destination. Results: After adjustment for age and admission FIM, we found a significant association between patient functional improvement (FIM gain) and delay in starting rehabilitation. We also observed a significant correlation between delay in initiating therapy and the level of institutionalisation at discharge. Conclusions: A single day delay in starting neurorehabilitation affects the functional prognosis of patients at discharge. This delay is also associated with increased rates of institutionalisation at discharge (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortega-Cubero, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murie-Fernández, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meyer, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Teasell, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carmona-Abellán, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo: El ictus representa en España la primera causa de muerte por entidades específicas en mujeres, la primera causa de invalidez en los adultos y supone un enorme coste tanto humano como económico. En los últimos años se han producido avances importantes tanto en el tratamiento de la fase aguda como en el proceso neurorrehabilitador; sin embargo, continúa sin quedar claro cuál es el momento óptimo en el que debe iniciarse la neurorrehabilitación después de un ictus y cuáles son las consecuencias de retrasar este inicio. El objetivo de este estudio es comprobar el efecto que supone cada día de retraso en el inicio de la neurorrehabilitación en la recuperación funcional y su influencia en la tasa de institucionalización al alta.Métodos: Estudio retrospectivo en el que se incluyeron los pacientes ingresados entre abril de 2005 y septiembre de 2008, en la Unidad de Neurorrehabilitación de Ictus (UNRHI) del Hospital Parkwood (Universidad de Western Ontario, Canadá). Se obtuvo la edad, la puntuación FIM al ingreso y al alta, los días entre la aparición del ictus y el ingreso en la Unidad de Neurorrehabilitación y el destino al alta.Resultados: Después de ajustar por edad y FIM al ingreso, se encontró una asociación estadísticamente significativa entre la mejoría funcional de los pacientes (ganancia de FIM) y el retraso por cada día en comenzar la rehabilitación. Existe una correlación estadísticamente significativa entre el retraso en iniciar esta terapia y el grado de institucionalización al alta. Conclusiones: Por cada día que se retrase el inicio del tratamiento neurorrehabilitador empeora el pronóstico funcional de los pacientes al alta. Este retraso se relaciona también con una mayor tasa de institucionalización al alta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;27(4): 197-201, mayo 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101993</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">«Tiempo es cerebro», ¿solo en la fase aguda del ictus?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12033^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33888</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28397</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7499^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
