<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112879</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-3568</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">First and second naval steps. The Ship Patiño as a paradigm in the Endurance Freedom Operative</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">: The subsequent events following the tragic attemts of the september 11th, have derived to a new operative system into the AF,s and specially in the Navy. The reason for the present paper is to introduce the naval health activities done, during the Endurance Freedom (EF) operative, considering the warship Patiño as a paradigm, being a result of its implication as a naval first and second sanitary step, analysing many of the common and specific activities and actions of the naval health service. From all of these, we must make critical reflexions about the possible improvements and realizations to develop along the next naval operatives in Middle East and african coasts, also establishing a practical reference to the health officers from the first and second step (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz del Río Botas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Codesido Vila, P. I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los acontecimientos posteriores a los trágicos sucesos del 11 de septiembre han acarreado un nuevo ámbito de actuación dentro del seno de las FAS y concretamente de la Armada. El motivo del presente artículo es hacer una presentación de las actividades sanitarias navales realizadas durante la operación Libertad Duradera (LD) utilizando el BAC Patiño como paradigma debido a su implicación como primer y segundo escalón sanitario naval, lo que nos permite analizar muchas de las actividades y acciones comunes y específicas de la sanidad  naval. De todo ello extraeremos reflexiones críticas de las posibles mejoras y acciones a llevar a cabo en próximas misiones navales en Oriente Medio y costas africanas, estableciéndose además un referente práctico a tener en cuenta para oficiales destinados en primer y segundo escalón (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. mil;60(4): 251-255, oct.-dic. 2004. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112879</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Primer y segundo escalones navales. El BAC Patiño como paradigma en la operación Libertad Duradera</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6928^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51708^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9518^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28438^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9077</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
