<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056417</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Is capsule endoscopy useful in children with chronic abdominal pain?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Chronic abdominal pain is highly prevalent in school-aged children and is one of the most frequent disorders in our environment. The aim of the present study was to evaluate the usefulness of capsule endoscopy (CE) in patients with chronic abdominal pain. Sixteen patients (nine boys and seven girls), aged between 5 and 16 years old, with chronic abdominal pain for at least 12 months were studied. In all patients the results of hemograms, biochemical investigations, urine sediment test, Helicobacter pylori breath test and celiac serology were normal. In all children, gastroscopy, small bowel follow-through, abdominal ultrasound and colonoscopy were normal. All patients received CE by mouth. In 43.75 % of the patients studied (7/16), the capsule showed evidence of nodular lymphoid hyperplasia, mainly located in the ileum. In one girl, oxyuriasis was observed in the cecum and in another girl aphthous lesions were observed in the ileum. These lesions suggested small bowel Crohn's disease.                 CE mainly showed images compatible with nodular lymphoid hyperplasia, with unknown clinical significance. Consequently, we conclude that CE does not provide useful information in patients with abdominal pain without other symptoms</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romero Vázquez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Argüelles-Arias, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Argüelles Martín, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Montes, M. J </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrerías Gutiérrez, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pellicer Bautista, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caunedo Álvarez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Téllez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Yagüe, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El dolor abdominal crónico afecta a un alto porcentaje de niños en edad escolar, lo que la convierte en una de las patologías más frecuentes en nuestro medio. El objetivo es valorar si la cápsula endoscópica (CE) permite identificar lesiones intestinales en estos pacientes. Se han incluido 16 pacientes (9 niños y 7 niñas) con edades comprendidas entre los 5 y 16 años con dolor abdominal crónico de más de 12 meses de evolución. Todos tenían realizados hemograma, bioquímica, sedimento de orina, test de aliento para Helicobacter pylori y serología para enfermedad celíaca, que eran negativos. A todos se les había realizado una gastroscopia, y una colonoscopia que resultaron negativas, así como un tránsito gastrointestinal y una ecografía abdominal, sin hallazgos de interés. En el 43,75 % de los pacientes estudiados (7/16) la CE mostró imágenes compatibles con hiperplasia folicular linfoide localizadas en el íleon. En una niña se observaron oxiuros en ciego y en otra, lesiones aftosas ileales compatibles con enfermedad de Crohn.                 La CE muestra en la mayoría de los casos imágenes compatibles con hiperplasia nodular linfoide intestinal, con dudosa significación clínica, por lo que podemos concluir que la CE no aporta nada específico en niños con dolor abdominal crónico</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);67(4): 385-389, oct. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056417</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Es útil la cápsula endoscópica en niños con dolor abdominal crónico?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22901</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29396</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
