<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-27542</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical profiles and evolutive transitions in the spectrum of specific language impairment in childhood</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To test the clinical nature and diversity of specific language impairment (SLI) in Spanish individuals, in the framework of the neuropsycholinguistic model of Chevrie-Muller and the classification of Rapin and Allen. Patients and methods. Forty-two language impaired children with normal intelligence and audition have been followed during a mean period of 3 years 7 months in preschool and school ages; all of them have participated in an intervention program for language abilities. The evolutive neuropsychological evaluation at our hospital has comprised measurement of general cognitive abilities, formal (phonology, vocabulary, syntax) and pragmatic aspects of language. Results. Phonological and syntaxic abilities are the better evolutive predictors. The group clinical profiles, in general, fill into the clustering system proposed by Rapin and Allen, but mixed-transitional forms are observed in individuals. Also in six patients a transition from one to another clinical form have been observed; in these subjects, mixed phonological-syntactical syndrome is an obligate step during their evolutive changes; these changes can be attributed to natural evolutive processes and/or to effects of intervention. Conclusion. Our results permit hypothetize that the spectrum of SLI is an unique basic disorder whose clinical manifestations (interindividual and intraindividual during evolution) can be diverse in form and severity. This clinical interpretation is reinforced by the results of recent publications showing that members of the same familial group with identical genetic mutation had different forms of SLI (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Con la denominación trastorno específico del desarrollo del lenguaje (TEDL) o disfasia nos referimos al déficit que presentan algunos niños en el desarrollo de las habilidades para descodificar y codificar el lenguaje, teniendo unas capacidades sensoriales, cognitivas y motóricas no afectadas. Objetivo. Se pretende profundizar en la naturaleza del TEDL, así como sus características clínicas y evolutivas, siguiendo el modelo neuropsicolingüístico de Chevrie-Muller y la clasificación clínica de Rapin y Allen. Pacientes y métodos. En una muestra de extracción clínica formada por 42 niños disfásicos se ha estudiado el lenguaje en dos dimensiones: formal (fonología y morfosintaxis) y funcional (uso cognitivo y pragmático), a través de la evaluación neuropsicológica realizada en diferentes momentos evolutivos (media del tiempo de seguimiento: tres años y siete meses). Resultados. El desarrollo fonológico y el sintáctico se señalan como variables predictoras de la evolución de un sujeto. Se descubren los criterios homogéneos de clasificación y las transiciones diagnósticas, y se aportan los perfiles clínicos de cada uno de los subgrupos del TEDL, que constituyen un continuo en el espectro de esta patología. Conclusiones. En este estudio descriptivo se evidencia la unicidad del lenguaje y se considera que un sujeto con TEDL puede pasar de una categoría diagnóstica a otra, puesto que se tratan de distintas manifestaciones del mismo trastorno ligadas a variables evolutivas y de intervención psicopedagógica. (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;36(supl.1): 29-35, feb. 2003. graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfiles clínicos evolutivos y transiciones en el espectro del trastorno específico del desarrollo del lenguaje</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Crespo Eguílaz, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Narbona, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-27542</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7984</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
