<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77291</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-1375</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Waste management in peritoneal dialysis: present and future</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The environmental impact of waste is a cause for concern in our community. We have studied 26 patients undergoing Peritoneal Dialysis in order to find out their behaviour with regard to the waste generated in carrying out their treatment and their interest in collaborating in projects for improving this area in the future, as well as possible strategies to achieve this. A questionnaire was drawn up to obtain the necessary information and was completed through a voluntary and confidential personal interview. The patients&#146; behaviour in relation to waste was considered correct on the basis of the results obtained, except for the collection of sharp object (needles),as 46% (12) of the patients interviewed placed the needles properly covered in the exclusive bag for the collection of waste from Peritoneal Dialysis treatment. Most of the patients are willing to collaborate in waste treatment projects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salsamendi Ballesteros, M. Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilas Gómez,  Asier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Telleria Izaguirre, Amaia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivas Osés, M. Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Melero Múgica, Coro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zugasti Laquidain, M. Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El impacto medioambiental de los residuos es motivo de preocupación en nuestra comunidad. Hemos estudiado a 26 pacientes en tratamiento con Diálisis Peritoneal con el fi n de conocer el comportamiento de éstos con respecto a los residuos generados en la realización de su tratamiento y su interés en colaboraren proyectos de mejora en este campo en el futuro, así como posibles estrategias para conseguirlo. Se elaboró un cuestionario para obtener la información necesaria y se cumplimentó mediante entrevista personal, voluntaria y confidencial. El comportamiento de los pacientes con respecto a los residuos ha sido calificado de correcto a tenor de los resultados obtenidos, con la excepción dela recogida de los elementos punzantes (agujas),ya que el 46% (12) de los pacientes entrevistados los depositaba encapuchados en la bolsa de basura exclusiva para la recogida de residuos del tratamiento de Diálisis Peritoneal. La mayoría de los pacientes están dispuestos a colaborar en proyectos responsables con el tratamiento de residuos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Enferm. Nefrol;12(3): 189-194, jul.-sept. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77291</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gestión de residuos en diálisis peritoneal: presente y futuro</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31314^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5678</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
