<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136110</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ophthalmoscopic surveillance in treated patients with invasive Candida disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Invasive Candida disease (ICD) is the most common cause of endogenous endophthalmitis. There are two characteristic ocular signs: Candida chorioretinitis defined as retina and choroid lesions without vitreal involvement, and Candida endophthalmitis defined as chorioretinitis with extension into the vitreous with characteristic fluffy balls. The most common visual symptoms are blurred vision and floaters. Aims: To define in which patients with ICD a surveillance ophthalmoscopic examination should be done. Methods: We searched the PubMed/Medline data base Candida endophthalmitis in adult and paediatric patients with ICD. Results and conclusions: The need of ophthalmoscopic examination in patients with ICD is controversial, partly due to the fact that early antifungal treatment leads to a significant decrease of endogenous Candida endophthalmitis. Routine ophthalmoscopic examination seems of little value in patients with positive blood culture, with early implementation of antifungal treatment, without symptoms of ocular infection and without impairment of the level of consciousness during the episode. However, ophthalmoscopic examination should be performed in children with candidemia and critically ill patients with documented ICD, in the second week of treatment, especially in echinocandin treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Blázquez, Eugenio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: La enfermedad invasora debida a Candida (EIC) es la causa más común de endoftalmitis endógena. Las 2 formas características de presentación son la coriorretinitis candidiásica, que afecta a coroides y retina sin afectar al vítreo, y la endoftalmitis candidiásica, con presencia de lesiones vítreas redondeadas. Los síntomas visuales más habituales son la visión borrosa y las miodesopsias. Objetivos: Valorar en qué paciente con EIC debe realizarse una exploración oftalmológica y el momento más apropiado. Métodos: Revisión bibliográfica en la base de datos PubMed/Medline sobre endoftalmitis asociadas a EIC en población pediátrica y adulta. Resultados y conclusiones: Hay controversia en cuanto a la necesidad de realizar una exploración de fondo de ojo a todos los pacientes con EIC, debido a que la generalización del tratamiento temprano en estos pacientes ha supuesto una disminución marcada del número de infecciones oculares y de su gravedad. En un paciente con EIC tratado de forma temprana, sin síntomas oftalmológicos y sin alteración del grado de con- ciencia que le impida referir síntomas visuales durante el seguimiento, es muy dudosa la utilidad del estudio oftalmológico sistemático. Sin embargo, en pacientes sin posibilidad de referir ninguna alteración visual en la fase inicial de la infección ocular, como son los pacientes pediátricos con candidemia o los pacientes críticos con EIC, la exploración oftalmológica es obligada entre la primera y la segunda semanas de tratamiento, especialmente en los tratados con equinocandinas, por su baja penetración ocular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;26(1): 78-80, mar. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136110</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Importancia de la vigilancia oftalmológica durante el tratamiento de la enfermedad invasora por Candida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28297^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7410^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28268^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7410^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30095^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28268^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28297^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2209^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9691^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7410^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7410^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28297^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28268^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22228</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2209^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30095^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28268^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28297^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30040</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
