<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81285</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0367</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Depersonalization symptoms in psychiatric patients: the new Lifetime and Present Depersonalization Scale</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Depersonalization symptoms are not specific to depersonalization disorder and are frequently observed in other psychiatric disorders. The Lifetime and Present Depersonalization Scale represents a new method designed to measure past and present depersonalization symptoms in psychiatric samples. Methods: The Lifetime and Present Depersonalization Scale was tested in a sample of 44 psychiatric  inpatients. Test-retest measures were used to assess reliability. Correlations with Dissociative Experiences Scale (DES) and the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADs) were used to assess validity. Results: The Cronbach alpha coefficients for both life-time and present-time subscales were 0,935 and 0,92 respectively. Most items obtained a good to excellent intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC). Significant correlations were found for the scores obtained in the DES and HADS. Conclusions: The Lifetime and Present Depersonalization Scale is presented as an appropriate  instrument for identifying and measuring depersonalization symptoms in psychiatric samples (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sperry, Lily</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valls, Sergi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Santos, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berrios, German</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pailhez, Guillem</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bulbena, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bergé, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los síntomas de despersonalización están presentes no únicamente en el Trastorno por Despersonalización, sino también de forma importante en otros trastornos psiquiátricos con notable relevancia. Esta escala presenta una nueva metodología para medir los síntomas por despersonalización presentes y pasados en población psiquiátrica. Métodos: La escala fue testada en una muestra de 44 pacientes ingresados. Se realizó test-retest para evaluar la fiabilidad y se realizaron  correlaciones con la escala de Experiencias Disociativas (DES) y la Escala de Ansiedad y Depresión Hospitalaria (HADS). Resultados: Se obtuvieron coeficientes alfa de Cronbach de 0.935 y 0.910 para las dos subescalas de tiempo-vida y tiempopresente. La mayoría de los ítems obtuvieron una puntuación en el coeficiente de correlación intraclase (ICC) entre bueno y excelente. Se observan correlaciones significativas con las puntuaciones de la escala DES y la HADS. Conclusiones: La  nueva escala ha demostrado ser un instrumento adecuado para identificar y medir los síntomas de despersonalización en pacientes afectos de diversos trastornos psiquiátricos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. psiquiatr;72(1/4): 1-13, ene.-dic. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81285</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síntomas de despersonalización en pacientes psiquiátricos: la nueva escala de despersonalización presente-vida (DP-PV)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3881^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3881^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
