<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98514</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Measurement of the results of functional treatment of metatarsal fractures using the AOFAS scale and the duration of work incapacity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To demonstrate the effectiveness of functional treatment for the fractures of the metatarsal, which consisted of immediate or early weight bearing without immobilisation. Material and methodology. We prospectively studied 276 patients with simple or complex fractures of the metatarsal, treated with a functional method which consisted of immediate (before the 3rd day since the fracture) or early (between 3rd and 21st day) effective weight bearing. Inclusion criteria were patients aged 16-65, both sexes, diagnosed with isolated or multiple, closed or opened type I metatarsal fractures who did weight bearing exercises during the first 21 days. We analysed the effects of the steroid injection proposed for this treatment in the focus of the fracture, the days of weight bearing, rehabilitation and number of metatarsal fractures. Results were evaluated using AOFAS (American Orthopaedic Foot and Ankle Society) scores, days of work incapacity and complications of the treatment. Results. The AOFAS score for patients treated functionally was excellent and we found few complications with it. Discussion. The functional method is based on the function of ligaments and muscles of the forefoot and the aid of a rigid-soled shoe which allows early weight-bearing to avoid secondary displacement of the fractures. The results show that immediate weight bearing provides better results than delayed bearing. Injection of steroid does not appear to have any benefit. Conclusions. We propose the functional method for all closed displaced or non-displaced metatarsal fractures, except for the displaced fractures on the base of the fifth metatarsal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Úbeda Pérez de Heredia, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez de Renobales, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Otaño Aranguren, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Zapirain, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Díaz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Mostrar la efectividad del tratamiento funcional de las fracturas metatarsianas consistente en apoyo completo inmediato o precoz sin inmovilización. Material y método. Se estudian de manera prospectiva 276 individuos con fracturas metatarsianas simples o complejas tratadas con el método funcional, consistente en realizar apoyo sin inmovilización de manera inmediata (antes del tercer día de la lesión) o precoz (desde el 3.° al 21.° día de la fractura). Los criterios de inclusión fueron pacientes de 16 a 65 años, de ambos sexos, con fractura cerrada y abierta grado I de metatarsianos, aislada o múltiple, que realizaron carga efectiva en los primeros 21 días. Se analizaron los efectos de la inyección de esteroide en foco propuesta para este tratamiento, el tiempo de descarga, la rehabilitación, el tipo de trabajo desempeñado por el paciente y el número de metatarsianos fracturados. Los resultados se evaluaron mediante la escala AOFAS (American Orthopaedic Foot and Ankle Society), la duración de la incapacidad laboral y las complicaciones del tratamiento. Resultados. Se obtuvo una puntuación excelente en la escala AOFAS y un bajo grado de complicaciones. Discusión. Este método se fundamenta en la función de sostén del sistema músculo-ligamentario y el uso de un zapato con suela rígida, que permiten un apoyo precoz sin desplazamiento secundario. La carga inmediata proporciona mejor resultado que la diferida, y la infiltración de esteroide no aporta beneficios. Conclusiones. Proponemos el método funcional como tratamiento para todas las fracturas cerradas del metatarso desplazadas o no, excepto para las fracturas desplazadas de la base del quinto metatarsiano (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);56(2): 132-139, mar.-abr. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98514</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Medición de resultados del tratamiento funcional de las fracturas metatarsianas mediante la escala AOFAS y la duración de la incapacidad laboral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10221^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22943^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23375^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22943^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22943^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23375^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23375^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10221^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
