<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-AOT-2213</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A pilot study on the effectiveness of a training program in cardiopulmonary resuscitation for high school teachers in rural areas</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To evaluate the effectiveness of a training program in cardiopulmonary resuscitation, targeting high school teachers in rural areas for semi-automated external defibrillator management. Methodology. Quasi-experimental study using convenience sampling. The program lasted 10 hours, distributed among 4 sessions. At the beginning and end of the training program all participants answered a 5-issue questionnaire, which rated them as «suitable» or «unfit» to perform cardiorespiratory resuscitation. Participants. 15 high school teachers from Teruel province. LOCATION. The training sessions were conducted at the school premises. Main measurements. Program SPSS version 21 was used. The confidence interval was of 95 %. A descriptive analysis for quantitative (mean and SD ±) variables, qualitative variables, frequencies and percentages was performed. Results. 73.3 % of participants were women and 26.7 % men. The average age of participants was 44.8 years. For the pre-test questionnaire, 93.4 % of participants received «unfit» grades and only 6.7 % were rated as «suitable». In the posttraining evaluation questionnaire, 100 % of participants were graded as «suitable». Wilcoxon test established that the training program was highly efficient. Conclusions. Training programs make a difference in the capacity to correctly perform life-saving interventions. They also stimulate the development of new and better training programs. Such trainings are very effective and should be included as part of Spain&#146;s compulsory education (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Chárlez-Millán, Carmen María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano-Lamarca, Balbino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soria-Villanueva, Noelia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pellicer-García, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer-Buj, María Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Félez-Castro, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Evaluar la eficacia de un programa formativo en reanimación cardiopulmonar con manejo de desfibrilador externo semiautomático en docentes de un Instituto de Educación Secundaria en el medio rural. Metodología. Estudio cuasiexperimental mediante muestreo por conveniencia. La duración total del programa formativo fue de 10 horas repartidas en 4 sesiones. Al inicio y final del programa formativo se administró a todos los participantes un cuestionario con 5 preguntas. Participantes. 15 docentes de un Instituto de Educación Secundaria perteneciente a la provincia de Teruel. Emplazamiento. Las sesiones formativas se llevaron a cabo en el propio instituto. Mediciones principales. Se utilizó el programa SPSS versión 21, con un IC del 95 %. Se realizó un análisis descriptivo: para variables cuantitativas (media y DE±) y para variables cualitativas frecuencias y porcentajes. Resultados. Un 73.3 % de los participantes fueron mujeres y un 26.7 % hombres. La media de edad de los participantes fue de 44.8 años. En el cuestionario pretest se observó que un 93.4 % de los participantes obtuvieron calificaciones de «no apto» y tan solo un 6.7 % obtuvo una calificación de «apto». En el cuestionario de evaluación postest se observó que el 100 % de los participantes obtuvieron calificaciones de «apto». La prueba de Wilcoxon constata que el programa formativo consiguió una eficacia elevada. Conclusiones. Los programas formativos pueden servir para estimular el desarrollo de nuevos programas de formación. Este tipo de formaciones resultan efectivas y deberían formar parte en la educación obligatoria en España (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;40(12): 768-774, dic. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-AOT-2213</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad de un programa formativo en reanimación cardiopulmonar en docentes de educación secundaria en el medio rural. Estudio piloto</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
