<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87577</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Academic stressors perceived by University studies of health sciences</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study aimed to identify those situations within the academic context that are perceived as stress generators in a sample of university students of Health Sciences and the amount of their impact. We also analyzed the differences in the academic stressors perceived based on the variables of career and academic year. These were measured with the Academic Stress Questionnaire, which forms a part of the Academic Stress Questionnaire (ASQ). The results of this project show that Exams and Public Participation are, in this order, the academic stressors most perceived. These findings suggest that the situations that are most directly and clearly related with the evaluation are those that generate the most stress to the students. The result averages in the factors Student burden and Teacher methodological shortcomings  are very close to the above findings. We can consider that these four factors share the fact that they are external and uncontrollable in regards to the previous ones. In addition, there are significant differences among students groups of students established based on the career they are studying in the stressors Student burden, Low valuation of study and learning contents and Low academic self-concept. Regarding the academic year factor, our results show that there are significant differences in the following 3 stressors: Lack of control about own academic achievement, Exams and Impossibility of participating in decisions about one's own academic work. In these cases, second year students show, on average, the highest scores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Doniz, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Freire</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Cabanach, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Cervantes, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El propósito de esta investigación es identificar qué situaciones del contexto académico son percibidas como generadoras de estrés en una muestra de estudiantes de ciencias de la salud y en qué medida lo hacen. Adicionalmente, se analizan las diferencias en estos estresores académicos percibidos en función de las variables contextuales de la titulación y el curso. Para la medida de los estresores académicos ha sido empleada la escala de estresores académicos, que forma parte del cuestionario de estrés académico. Los resultados de este trabajo revelan que los exámenes y las intervenciones en público, por este orden, son las 2 situaciones académicas percibidas como más estresantes. Estos resultados sugieren que las situaciones más directas y claramente relacionadas con la evaluación son las que generan un mayor estrés a los estudiantes. Muy próximos se encuentran también los promedios resultantes en los factores sobrecarga del estudiante y deficiencias metodológicas del profesorado, factores que podemos considerar comparten la característica de externalidad e incontrolabilidad con respecto a los anteriores. Asimismo, existen diferencias significativas entre los grupos de estudiantes establecidos en función de la titulación que cursan en los estresores sobrecarga del estudiante, carencia de valor de los contenidos de aprendizaje y estudio y baja autoestima académica. Por lo que respecta a la variable curso, nuestros datos indican que existen diferencias significativas en los estresores falta de control sobre el propio rendimiento, exámenes e imposibilidad de participar en las decisiones respecto del propio trabajo académico, siendo el grupo de segundo el que obtiene la puntuación media más elevada en los 3 casos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);32(4): 151-158, Abr. -Ago. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87577</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estresores académicos percibidos por estudiantes universitarios de ciencias de la salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13723^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
