<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114140</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of criteria for referral of type 2 diabetes patients from primary care to specialized care in spain. A Pathways Study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To assess the reasons for referral of type 2 diabetes (T2DM) patients from primary care (PC) to specialized care (SC) in Spain. To assess the level of compliance with referral criteria established in national recommendations. Methods: Observational, cross-sectional, multi-centre national study, in PC and SC. Each physician provided, using a structured case report form, data on usual practice for T2DM patient referral and data about referral of 6 patients. Recommendations of the Spanish Society for Endocrinology and Nutrition (SEEN) and the National Health System (NHS) were used as reference documents to assess compliance. Data from clinical practice of 143 professionals of SC/641 general practitioners (GPs) and from referrals of 805 patients to PC/3,624 to SC are presented. Results: Almost one-third (31.8%) of GPs and 46.2% of SC professionals reported the existence of a coordination protocol with the other healthcare level. The most frequent communication tool for referrals to SC was a Consultation Report (89.2%), and the Medical History for referrals to PC. The referral criterion to SC most frequently declared was Metabolic Instability (80.5%) and to PC was Goal Achievement (96.5%). The most frequent cause for referral to SC among the patients studied was Reassessment (48.4%) and to PC Goal Achievement (91.6%). Almost half (46.8%) of GPs applied all NHS criteria in usual practice, and 3.9% all SEEN referral criteria. Conclusions: The number of reported coordination protocols is low, and the compliance with national guidelines is poor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Roldán, Cecilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Font, Beatriu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Javier Escalada, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ezkurra, Patxi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Conocer los motivos de derivación de pacientes con diabetes tipo 2 (DM2) entre atención primaria (AP) y atención especializada (AE). Analizar el grado de cumplimiento de las recomendaciones nacionales sobre motivos de derivación de pacientes con DM2. Material y métodos: Estudio observacional, transversal, multicéntrico nacional en AP y AE. Cada investigador debía aportar, mediante un cuaderno de recogida de datos estructurado, información sobre su práctica habitual en derivación de pacientes con DM2 y datos sobre derivación de 6 pacientes concretos. Los documentos de referencia para el análisis del cumplimiento fueron: Recomendaciones de la Sociedad Española de Endocrinología y Nutrición (SEEN) y Guía de Práctica Clínica del Ministerio de Sanidad y Consumo (MSC). Se analizaron datos sobre práctica habitual de 143 médicos de AE y 641 de AP y sobre derivaciones de 805 pacientes de AE y 3.624 de AP. Resultados: El 31,8% de los profesionales de AP y el 46,2% de AE declaran existencia de un protocolo de coordinación con el otro nivel asistencial. El método de comunicación más frecuentemente declarado para derivaciones hacia AE fue el parte interconsulta (89,2%) y hacia AP la historia clínica (53,5%). El criterio de derivación hacia AE más manejado en la práctica habitual fue «inestabilidad metabólica» (80,5%), y hacia AP, «consecución de objetivos» (96,5%). El motivo más frecuente en derivaciones concretas hacia AE fue «re-evaluación» (48,4%) y hacia AP «consecución de objetivos» (91,6%). El 46,8% de los profesionales de AP aplicaban todos los criterios MSC y el 3,9% todos los criterios SEEN. Conclusiones: Se observa una escasa implementación de protocolos de coordinación entre niveles asistenciales y un bajo grado de cumplimiento de las recomendaciones nacionales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;29(3): 60-67, mayo-jun. 2013. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114140</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis sobre los motivos de derivación de pacientes con diabetes mellitus tipo 2 entre atención primaria y atención especializada. Estudio Pathways</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
