<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130628</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-2074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Regression in young adults with Down&#146;s syndrome. A three cases review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A deterioration in some of their cognitive functions and adaptive skills has been observed in adolescents and young adults with Down&#146;s syndrome, which is similar to that observed in individuals who suffer from Alzheimer&#146;s disease, although at much earlier ages. Little is known of the etiology of these changes. In this work, 3 cases are presented on 3 young adults with Down&#146;s syndrome, who presented with a deterioration in their cognitive functions and a loss of, previously well attained, functional skills. Some medical and psychological risk factors that could be associated with this regression are examined. In all the cases, the loss of skills was associated with anxiety and depression symptoms (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Benejam, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garvía, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En algunos adolescentes y jóvenes con síndrome de Down (SD) se ha observado un deterioro en sus funciones cognitivas y en sus capacidades adaptativas similar al observado en personas que padecen la enfermedad de Alzheimer, aunque en edades muy tempranas. Se sabe muy poco sobre la etiología de estos cambios. En este trabajo se exponen tres casos de jóvenes con SD que presentaron un deterioro en sus funciones cognitivas y una pérdida de habilidades funcionales previamente bien adquiridas, y se examinan algunos de los factores de riesgo (médicos y psicológicos) que pueden estar asociados a dicho deterioro. En todos los casos, la pérdida de capacidades se acompañaba de síntomas de ansiedad y depresión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SD, Rev. med. int. Síndr. Down (Ed. castell.);18(3): 43-46, sept.-dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130628</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Regresión en adultos jóvenes con síndrome de Down. Revisión de tres casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33528^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50241</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33528^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3104</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22845</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9241^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30935^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33552^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
