<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-168006</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mesenteric edema as a prenatal ultrasound sign of poor prognosis in gastroschisis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction/Aim of the study. Gastroschisis is a congenital  malformation with an easy and early prenatal diagnosis, however, it has a variable post-natal outcome. Our aim was to determine if certain ultrasound markers or early delivery were related with a worse postnatal outcome. Patients and methods. Retrospective study of a cohort of patients with gastroschisis diagnosed between 2005-2014, with emphasis on prenatal ultrasounds, gestational age at delivery and post-natal outcome. Oligohydramnios, peel, mesenteric edema, fixed and dilated bowel with loss of peristalsis and small wall defect were considered ultrasonographic markers associated with poor prognosis. Outcome variables included: length-of-stay, complications, nutritional and respiratory factors. Non-parametric statistical analysis were used with p&lt; 0,05 regarded as significant. Results. Clinical charts of 30 patients with gastroschisis were reviewed (17M/13F). Gestational age at diagnosis was 20 (12-31) and at delivery 36 (31-39) weeks (33% of the patients over 36+3 weeks). A 73% of the patients presented at least one ultrasonographic marker factor during follow-up. Univariate analysis showed that mesenteric edema was associated with poor outcome variables: short-bowel syndrome (p= 0,000), PN-dependence (p= 0,007) and intestinal atresia (p= 0,02). The remaining risk factors analysed, including late delivery (&gt;36+3 weeks) were not associated with length-of-stay, ventilatory support, digestive autonomy, complications or mortality. Conclusions. Neither the presence of ultrasonographic markers classically associated with unfavorable outcomes, nor early delivery (&lt;36 weeks) resulted in worse postnatal outcome. Mesenteric edema was the only alarming ultrasound marker and that may suggest the need of closer follow-up (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dore Reyes, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Encinas Hernández, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alvarado Antolín, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Santamaría,  M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Cervantes, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Triana Junco, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bartha Rasero, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romo Muñoz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Galán, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez Cerezo,  V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Martínez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La gastrosquisis es una anomalía congénita de fácil diagnóstico prenatal y pronóstico postnatal variable. Nuestro objetivo es determinar si los signos ecográficos prenatales o el momento del parto se relacionan con peor pronóstico postnatal. Pacientes y métodos. Se realiza un estudio retrospectivo de la cohorte de pacientes con gastrosquisis diagnosticados entre 2005-2014, registrando las ecografías prenatales, edad gestacional al parto y evolución postnatal. Se valoraron los hallazgos ecográficos prenatales: oligohidramnios, peel, edema mesentérico, asas fijas, aperistálticas y/o dilatadas y defecto pequeño de pared. Se consideraron variables resultado: la estancia hospitalaria, complicaciones, mortalidad y factores nutricionales y respiratorios. Se utilizaron pruebas no paramétricas, considerándose significativo un valor p&lt; 0,05. Resultados. Se analizaron 30 pacientes con gastrosquisis (17V/13M). La edad gestacional al diagnóstico fue de 20 (12-31) y al parto de 36 (31-39) semanas (33% mayores de 36+3 semanas). El 73% de los pacientes presentaron al menos un signo ecográfico de mal pronóstico. El análisis univariante asoció el edema mesentérico al síndrome de intestino corto (p= 0,000), falta de autonomía digestiva (p= 0,007) y mayor incidencia de atresia (p= 0,02). El resto de los factores, incluyendo la edad gestacional &gt; 36+3 semanas, no tuvieron repercusión negativa en términos de estancia, asistencia respiratoria, autonomía digestiva, complicaciones o mortalidad.  Conclusiones. Ni la presencia de signos ecográficos considerados generalmente como desfavorables ni la tendencia a acercar el parto a la semana 36ª tienen repercusiones significativas en el curso postnatal. Únicamente el edema mesentérico parece un signo alarmante que sugiere la necesidad de aumentar la frecuencia de intervenciones (ecografías,  pruebas de bienestar fetal) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;30(3): 131-137, jul. 2017. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-168006</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El edema mesentérico como signo ecográfico prenatal de mal pronóstico en gastrosquisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4555</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4555^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8816</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31993^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d668</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31993^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33760</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201707</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
