<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-33300</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-1285</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Oral surgery in patients treated with anticoagulating therapy: experimental model for evaluation of fibrin glue efficiency</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim of the work: The authors emphasize how an effective emostatic method is extremely important in patients treated with anticoagulating therapy during oral surgery: it can avoid the risk of an excessive emorrhage and the necessity to alter the anticoagu- lating therapeutic regimen. The present study examines the fibrin glue emostatic ability as emostatic support in patients treated with anticoagulating therapy. It expresses the experiment results,based on standards of reference of surgical trauma and considers the anticoagulating therapy intensity. Materials and methods: 20 patients with anticoagulation therapy have been selected within the age of 44 and 79. Following the appropriate techniques extractions of teeth with one, two or three roots have been practiced. After the alveoloplasty a reabsorbable sponge of fibrine is placed and the suture is done. The surgical trauma has been classified by means of a quantitative scale which can express it without inaccuracy. The category of trauma for each patient is established by the total of the values obtained from each of the single procedures. It has been possible to evaluate the coefficient of relationship between the intensity of the anticoagulating effect (measured by the lNR) and the number of verified hemorrhagic complications; and also between the grade of surgical trauma and the number of complications. Results and conclusions: The authors demonstrate how the therapeutical usage of fibrin glue can be considered a valid support for the optimization of the haemostatis in patients with induced alterations of the coagulation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ediciones Avances, S.L.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En la práctica de cirugía oral en los pacientes bajo terapia anticoagulante, el empleo de un sistema eficaz de acción hemostática es de extrema relevancia, porque puede evitar la alteración del régimen terapéutico anticoagulante y el riesgo de un exceso de sangrado. En el presente trabajo se investiga la capacidad hemostática de la cola de fibrina como presidio hemostático en los pacientes bajo terapia anticoagulante, exponiendo los resultados de la experimentación sobre la base de un standard de referencia del trauma quirúrgico y de la intensidad de la terapia anticoagulante. Materiales y métodos: Han sido seleccionados 20 pacientes en terapia anticoagulante con una edad comprendida entre los 44 y 79 años, se han realizado, según las modalidades apropiadas, simples exodoncias o más complejas de dientes mono-, bi- y tri-radiculares. Tras la alveoloplastia se ha colocado una esponja de fibrina reabsorbible en forma de gel (Gingistat®) y se ha realizado la sutura. El trauma quirúrgico ha sido clasificado por medio de una escala cuantitativa que puede expresar de forma unívoca el grado de trauma. La categoría de trauma por cada paciente se establece por la suma de los valores obtenidos de cada uno de los procedimientos unitarios. Ha sido posible evaluar el coeficiente de relación entre la intensidad del efecto anticoagulante (medido por medio del INR) y número de complicaciones hemorrágicas que se han verificado, además de entre el grado de trauma quirúrgico y el número de complicaciones que se han presentado. Resultados y Conclusiones: Se demuestra que el uso terapéutico de la cola de fibrina puede ser considerado como un Válido soporte por la optimización de la hemostasis en los pacientes con alteraciones de la coagulación inducidas farmacológicamente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av Odontoestomatol;20(3): 139-146, mayo-jun. 2004. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cirugía oral en pacientes bajo terapia anticoagulante: modelo experimental para la evaluación de la eficacia de la cola de fibrina</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Denotti, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calzavara, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Papagna, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Taormina, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carini, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-33300</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d33208</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24653^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13896^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
