<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058609</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Minimal-change nephropathy in an elderly man as a manifestation of paraneoplastic syndrome from colorectal cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Tumors can be accompanied by a variety or paraneoplastic manifestations, such as nephrotic syndrome. We describe the case of a male patient with impairment of his general health status, cutaneous lesions, and nephrotic syndrome. Skin and renal biopsies indicated that the patient's manifestations were paraneoplastic, due to colorectal cancer, which was subsequently confirmed by colonoscopy</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blanco, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heras Benito, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Hernández, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Reyes Luis, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez González, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los tumores pueden acompañarse de diversas manifestaciones paraneoplásicas, entre ellas el síndrome nefrótico. Presentamos el caso de un varón con un deterioro del estado general, lesiones cutáneas y un síndrome nefrótico. Tras realizar biopsia cutánea y renal se llegó al juicio diagnóstico de que las manifestaciones que presentaba el paciente eran paraneoplásicas, debidas a un cáncer de colon que se confirmó posteriormente mediante colonoscopia</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);42(6): 361-363, nov.2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058609</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nefropatía de cambios mínimos en un anciano como manifestación paraneoplásica de un cáncer de colon</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3142^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3142^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9595^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9595^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31474</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
