<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113381</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The Spence Children´s Anxiety Scale (SCAS): reliability and validity of the Spanish version</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study examined the reliability and validity of the Spence Children&#146;s Anxiety Scale (SCAS) in a sample of 1,636 Spanish students 9-17 years old. The total-score internal consistency (Cronbach&#146;s alpha) was 0.92 and indices of subscales ranged from 0.81 (Panic-Agoraphobia) to 0.61 (Separation Anxiety and Physical Injury Fear). The test-retest reliability (intra-class correlation) was 0.61 and subscales ranged from 0.62 (Specific Phobias) to 0.51 (Panic-Agoraphobia). All scores decreased slightly from test to retest. SCAS scores showed convergent validity in their high correlation with general and specific anxiety measures. SCAS scores also showed divergent validity in their low correlation with several measures of non-anxiety disorders, including depression. It is concluded that the SCAS is a suitable tool to assess in Spanish children anxiety disorders as they are depicted in DSM-IV</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Godoy, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casado, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintero, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrillo, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gavino, Aurora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nogueira, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio ha sometido a examen la fiabilidad y la validez de la &#147;Escala de ansiedad infantil de Spence&#148; (Spence Children&#146;s Anxiety Scale, SCAS) en una muestra de 1636 estudiantes de 9 a 17 años de España. La consistencia interna (alfa de Cronbach) de la puntuación total ha sido de 0,92 y las de las subescalas han fluctuado entre 0,81 (pánico-agorafobia) a 0,61 (ansiedad de separación y miedo al daño físico). La fiabilidad test-restest (correlación intra-clase) de la puntuación total ha sido 0,61 y las de las subescalas han fluctuado entre 0,62 (Miedo al daño físico) y 0,51 (pánico-agorafobia). Todas las puntuaciones de la SCAS disminuyeron ligeramente del test al retest. Las puntuaciones de la SCAS han mostrado validez convergente al correlacionar alto con otras medidas de ansiedad, tanto generales como específicas de problemas concretos, y validez divergente al correlacionar bajo con medidas de trastornos distintos de la ansiedad, incluyendo la depresión. Se concluye que la SCAS es una prueba adecuada para evaluar en España los trastornos de ansiedad infanto-juveniles tal como aparecen en el DSM-IV (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;20(3): 529-545, sept.-dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113381</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">&#147;Escala de ansiedad infantil de Spence&#148; (Spence Children´s Anxiety Scale, SCAS): fiabilidad y validez de la versión española</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8519</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
