<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100908</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Agreement between five definitions of metabolic syndrome. Cartagena, Colombia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: During last decade the metabolic syndrome has been defined by five different guidelines. Discrepancies in such definitions could influence syndrome predictive ability over cardiovascular diseases. The aim of this study was to determine the degree of agreement between these five guidelines, in population from Cartagena (Colombia). Methods: A cross sectional study was conducted in adults from urban zone. Sample size was estimated based on 2005 DANE census, which included 670 individuals. The prevalence of metabolic syndrome was determined through the WHO (World Health Organization), AHA/NHLBI (American Heart Association/National Heart Lung and Blood Institute),ATP III (Adult Treatment Panel III), IDF (International Diabetes Federation) and JIS (Joint Interim Statement) guidelines. Frequencies obtained were compared through Cohen's kappa index Results: According to JIS, IDF, ATPIII, AHA/NHBLI and WHO guidelines, metabolic syndrome prevalence was 36.3% [32.6 &#150; 39.9], 35.1%, 30.3%, 24.2% and 4.9%. Agreement between JIS and IDF was 0.893, while index for these two guidelines with AHA/NHLBI was 0.778 y 0.750, respectively. ATPIII had a lower agreement with JIS and IDF (0.711 and 0.645, respectively), however withAHA/NHLBI agreement was 0.863.WHO presented a agreement with the others guidelines between 0.14 and 0.16. Conclusions: Significant agreement was found between the four most recent guidelines. Abdominal obesity cut-off points might support differences agreement differences(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salguedo Madrid, Germán</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Clason, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Alegría, Claudio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Camargo, Doris</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora García, Gustavo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alario Bello, Ángelo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fortich, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mazenett, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruíz Diaz, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: Durante la última década el síndrome metabólico fue definido en cinco diferentes guías. Con cada definición se modifica la capacidad predictiva del síndrome sobre la enfermedad cardiovascular. El objetivo del presente estudio fue determinar el grado de concordancia entre estas cinco guías en Cartagena (Colombia). Métodos: Se realizó un estudio de corte transversal en adultos. El tamaño mínimo de muestra se estimó con información del censo DANE 2005. Se realizó un muestreo por conglomerados bietápico que incluyó 670 individuos. Para estimar la prevalencia del síndrome se aplicaron las guías OMS (Organización Mundial de la Salud), AHA/NHBLI (Asociación Americana del Corazón), ATPIII (Panel de Tratamiento de Adultos), IDF (Federación Internacional de Diabetes) y JIS (Declaración Provisional Conjunta). La concordancia fue calculada con el índice Kappa de Cohen. Resultados: Según las guías JIS, IDF, ATPIII, AHA/NHBLI y OMS, la prevalencia de síndrome metabólico fue del 36,3%, 35,1%, 30,3%, 24,2% y 4,9% respectivamente. La concordancia entre JIS e IDF fue de 0,893 mientras que el índice entre estas guías y AHA/NHBLI fue de 0,778 y 0,750 respectivamente. El ATP III tuvo una concordancia más baja con JIS e IDF (0,711 y 0,645, respectivamente) pero con AHA/NHLBI la concordancia fue de 0,863. La OMS presentó un acuerdo con las demás guías de entre 0,14 y 0,16. Conclusiones: Existe concordancia significativa entre las cuatro guías más recientes. Los puntos de corte para obesidad abdominal podrían justificar las diferencias encontradas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;86(3): 301-311, may.-jun.2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100908</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Concordancia entre cinco definiciones de síndrome metabólico. Cartagena, Colombia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8657^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8657^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3137^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50514^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53563^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24538</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28408</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
