<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157343</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Extraoral surgical access for removal of intraparotid giant sialolith in young patient. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Sialolithiasis is one of the most common diseases of salivary glands. Sialoliths mainly develop in the submandibular gland with few cases described in the parotid and sublingual glands. They are more common in adults between the third and fourth decades of life, and can affect the elderly and rarely children and adolescents. In most cases, they are located in the ducts, but parenchymal location is unusual. Clinical signs of sialolithiasis are well known; however, they may appear in atypical sites, making it difficult to locate and diagnose them precisely. In these cases, the use of complementary imaging examinations, such as computerized tomography, is critical to delimit the lesion and determine the treatment plan. Therefore, the description of this clinical case of a parotid sialolith, with atypical location, in a 17-year-old patient, that was surgically removed by extraoral access after determining its correct location by using computerized tomography imaging is relevant and important (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Reis Oliveira, Marina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fabris Almeida Amarala, Lysandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mariano, Ronaldo Célio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carvalho Silva, Amanda de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La sialolitiasis es una de las enfermedades más frecuentes de las glándulas salivales. Los sialolitos pueden formarse en la glándula submandibular, y son pocos los casos que se describen en las glándulas parótida y sublingual. Son más comunes en los adultos entre la tercera y la cuarta décadas de la vida, y pueden darse en los ancianos y, excepcionalmente, en los niños y adolescentes. En la mayor parte de los casos, se encuentran en los conductos, y la localización parenquimatosa es poco habitual. Los signos clínicos de la sialolitiasis son bien conocidos; sin embargo, pueden aparecer en localizaciones atípicas, lo cual dificulta su localización y diagnóstico precisos. En tales casos, el uso de técnicas de imagen complementarias, como la tomografía computarizada es crucial para delimitar la lesión y determinar el plan de tratamiento. Así pues, la descripción de este caso clínico de un sialolito parotídeo con una localización atípica, en un paciente de 17 años, que se extrajo con un abordaje extraoral tras determinar su localización exacta mediante tomografía computarizada tiene interés e importancia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;38(4): 218-222, oct.-dic. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157343</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abordaje quirúrgico extraoral para la extracción de sialolito gigante intraparotídeo en un paciente joven. Presentación de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10496^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10496^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23821^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23821^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23821^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13750^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13896^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23821^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13896^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13750^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23440^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
