<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87408</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-7279</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In previous papers starts reviewing the contributions psychological, neuroscience and biological contributions perfor-med on the Relational Learning. They are considered the bases of the Protocol for the Neuropsychological Exploration of the Relational Learning-Child/Adolescent (PENpAR-IJ), designed by the first authoress and we work with in the Section of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry of the University Clinic Hospital Lozano Blesa of Zaragoza. It emphasizes the need to move towards integration of scientific knowledge about the mind. We review the contributions of the theory of mind in different mental disorders. And we conclude with the presentation of PENpAR-IJ (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Padilla, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Enríquez, Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montilla, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En  artículos anteriores se inicia la revisión de las aportaciones psicológicas, neurocientíficas y biológicas en las que se fundamenta el Protocolo de Exploración Neuropsicológica del Aprendizaje Relacional-InfantoJuvenil (PENpAR-IJ) diseñado por la primera autora y con el que se trabaja en la Sección de Psiquiatría Infanto-Juvenil del Hospital Clínico Universitario Lozano Blesa de Zaragoza. Se hace hincapié en la necesidad de in-tegrar conocimientos científicos vigentes sobre la mente. Se revisan así mismo, contribuciones sobre la teoría de la mente y las habilidades mentalistas en distintos trastornos mentales para concluir con una presentación del PENpAR-IJ (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Inf. psiquiátr;(197): 217-246, jul.-sept. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87408</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desde la emoción hacia la mente: fundamentación del protocolo de exploración neuropsicológica del aprendizaje relacional-infantojuvenil (Tercera parte)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2716</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d300</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35170</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
