<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139280</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Palliative peritoneal dialysis: Implementation of a home care system for patients treated with peritoneal dialysis in terminal situations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Patients undergoing peritoneal dialysis (PD) in a terminal situation are generally transferred to haemodialysis, given that they are incapable of carrying out the dialysis technique due to the fact that their functional capabilities are diminished. We present our experience with5 patients undergoing PD with pathology that constituted short-term threat to their lives. Their treatment was shared by the primary attention units and they were maintained in a PD mode adapted to their circumstances, which we have called Palliative Peritoneal Dialysis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rexach, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Teruel-Briones, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burguera Vion, Victor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quereda, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivera Gorrin, Maite</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los pacientes en Diálisis peritoneal (DP) en situación terminal suelen ser transferidos ahemodiálisis ya que son incapaces de realizarse la técnica dialítica a consecuencia de que sus capacidades funcionales están disminuidas. Presentamos nuestra experiencia con5 pacientes en DP con patología que amenazaba su vida a corto plazo, cuyo tratamiento fue compartido por las unidades de atención primaria y fueron mantenidos en una modalidad de DP adaptada a sus circunstancias a la que hemos denominado Diálisis Peritoneal Paliativa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;35(2): 146-149, mar.-abr. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139280</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diálisis peritoneal paliativa: implantación de un programa de atención domiciliaria a enfermos tratados con diálisis peritoneal (DP) en situación terminal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29408^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7851^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
