<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114565</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">An analysis of adherence to the «Recommendations for the treatment of human immunodeficiency virus-infected adults» in a penitentiary in Barcelona</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim To analyze the adherence to the &#147;Guidelines for the treatment of HIV-infected adults&#148; among HIV-infected prison inmates. Methods A cross-sectional study was conducted in 2010 in the Quatre Camins Prison (Barcelona, Spain). Epidemiological, clinical and therapeutic variables were collected. We verified whether antiretroviral therapy (ART) met the Guidelines and analyzed the variables associated with compliance using bivariate and multivariate analysis. Results There were a total of 202 HIV infected prison inmates, 83.2% of whom were on ART. An undetectable viral load (VL) was observed in 80.4% of treated patients. The large majority (86.1%) met the guidelines, and 42.9% of non-compliance to guidelines was because the patients refused ART. More undetectable VL (P = .001; ORA: 4,30, 95% CI: 1,85 to 10.0) was found in those patients following the guidelines. Conclusion Compliance with the guidelines is high, and is significantly associated with undetectable VL. We suggest evaluating the quality of prescriptions periodically, and to correct them if needed(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Puig, Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marco, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moruno, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Argüelles, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, Xosé Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Analizar en presos infectados por VIH-1 el cumplimiento de las «Recomendaciones para el tratamiento de adultos infectados por el VIH». Métodos Estudio transversal realizado en la prisión de Quatre Camins (Barcelona, España). Se recogen variables epidemiológicas, clínicas y terapéuticas. Se comprueba si el tratamiento antirretroviral (TAR) cumple las recomendaciones y se analiza, mediante un análisis bivariante y multivariante, las variables asociadas al cumplimiento y su impacto clínico. Resultados Se detectan 202 infectados, 83,2% con TAR. El 80,4% de los tratados presentaban carga viral (CV) indetectable. En el 86,1% se cumplían las recomendaciones. El 42,9% de los incumplimientos se debían al rechazo del paciente a realizar TAR. El cumplimiento de las recomendaciones se asoció a un mayor porcentaje de CV indetectable (p = 0,001; OR ajustada: 4,30, IC 95%: 1,85-10,0) en los casos de cumplimiento. Conclusión El cumplimiento de las «Recomendaciones» es alto en el entorno penitenciario y se asocia significativamente a conseguir una CV indetectable. Se aconseja evaluar periódicamente la calidad de las prescripciones y aplicar correcciones(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;31(6): 392-395, jun.-jul. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114565</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis del cumplimiento de las «Recomendaciones para el tratamiento de adultos infectados por el virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana» en un centro penitenciario de Barcelona</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11766</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
