<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98564</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Attitudes and behaviour of women towards cardiovascular disease prevention</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To find out the attitudes and behaviour of women towards preventive activities related to cardiovascular disease. Method Cross-sectional descriptive study, through a self-completion questionnaire, in three Health Centres in Toledo (Spain). A total of 539 women between 18 and 65 years old answered an ad hoc developed questionnaire that contained items on knowledge, attitudes, and behaviours in preventive practices. Results The mean age was 40.4 years age; 361 (66.7%) came from urban areas; 354 (65.4%) were married; 221 (40.8%) had university studies; 382 (70.8%) were working; 432 (83.2%) believed that the leading cause of death in women was cancer; 174 (32.4%) said they had annual preventive medical check-ups; 411 (76.8%) considered it very dangerous to smoke, but 159 (30.0%) currently smoked. Alcohol consumption was considered very dangerous by 232 (43.4%); 92 (17.2%) were regular consumers (almost every week). Only 128 (23.8%) did exercise one or more times per week. Only 127 (24.0%) followed some type of diet. At least one annual BP and laboratory tests (cholesterol and blood sugar) were measured in 68.4%, 64.1% and 53.9%, respectively. A total of 266 (51.7%) had been advised once on their lifestyle by a healthcare professional. Conclusions The impact of cardiovascular disease in women is underestimated. Our population seemed concerned about the risk of certain habits but this was not always translated into a healthy lifestyle. It seems that our advice may not change the behaviour of women in many cases, but it does increase the number of clinical and analytical controls. We must insist on the prevention of cardiovascular risk in women and improve the effectiveness of our interventions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ríos Germán, Peggy Paola</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Castro, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Martil, Carmen Amelia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López de Castro, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pizarro Losilla, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Conocer la actitud y el comportamiento de las mujeres hacia las actividades preventivas relacionadas con la enfermedad cardiovascular. Método Estudio descriptivo transversal, mediante encuesta autoadministrada sobre actitudes y comportamientos en prácticas preventivas, realizado en 3 centros de salud de Toledo, en 539 mujeres de 18-65 años. Resultados Edad 40,4 años. Proceden del medio urbano 361 (66,7%); 354 (65,4%) están casadas; 221 (40,8%) son universitarias; trabajan 382 (70,8%). Creen que la principal causa de muerte en las mujeres es el cáncer 432 (83,2%); 174 (32,4%) dicen realizarse anualmente un chequeo médico preventivo; 411 (76,8%) consideran muy peligroso fumar, pero fuman actualmente 159 (30,0%). El consumo de alcohol es considerado muy peligroso por 232 (43,4%); son consumidoras habituales (casi todas las semanas) 92 (17,2%). Sólo 128 (23,8%) hace ejercicio habitualmente. Hacen algún tipo de dieta 127 (24,0%). Se realizan al menos una vez al año una toma de PA y analítica (colesterol y glucemia) el 68,4, el 64,1 y el 53,9%, respectivamente. Recuerdan haber sido aconsejadas alguna vez sobre el estilo de vida por un profesional sanitario 266 (51,7%).Conclusiones La repercusión de las enfermedades cardiovasculares en la mujer está infravalorada. Nuestra población parece concienciada del riesgo de determinados hábitos, pero eso no se traduce siempre en un estilo de vida saludable. Parece que nuestros consejos no consiguen modificar la conducta de las mujeres en muchos casos, pero sí «medicalizar» su vida, aumentando la realización de controles analíticos y clínicos. Debemos insistir en la prevención del riesgo cardiovascular en la mujer y mejorar la efectividad de nuestras intervenciones(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);21(4): 196-201, jul.-ago. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98564</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actitud y comportamiento de la mujer frente a la prevención de la enfermedad cardiovascular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
