<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049613</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Brainstem auditory evoked potentials and vertex potentials in 5-year-old children with defective articulation of the phonemes /l/, /r/, /rr/ and /s/</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims. In children with articulatory defects it is important to evaluate the central auditory level. We compared theresults of the interwave intervals of brainstem auditory evoked potentials (BAEP) at 80 dB SPL (sound pressure level) and thelatencies of the waves of long latency auditory evoked potentials (LLAEP) (vertex) in 5-year-old children with articulatorydefects for /l/, /r/, /rr/ and /s/, and in controls. Subjects and methods. Fifty cases of 5-year-old children of both sexes wereevaluated; 25 had articulatory defects and 25 with no articulatory defects were used as controls. Melgar&#146;s articulation test wasapplied to both groups. The following aspects were considered in the two groups: normal bilateral audition by means of toneaudiometry, tympanometry and the revised Wechsler Intelligence Scale for preschool and primary school children, which werenormal; there was no history of neurological damage. Interwave intervals for waves I-III, I-V and III-V of the BAEP and thelatencies of the LLAEP (vertex) were evaluated. Results. Data were analysed using SPSS 12, and descriptive statistics andStudent&#146;s t test were carried out to appraise the differences between the two groups. No differences were found between thecontrol group and the study group. Conclusions. It is important to determine whether children with articulatory defects havealterations in the auditory receptor or in their central auditory function. It can be concluded that the variables analysed in thetwo groups behave in the same way; no significant differences were found, which suggests that neither the auditory receptor northe central auditory function are affected in the study group. Further studies are to be conducted to investigate the meaning ofthe difference in central nervous conduction between the two afferences in the study group</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Durand-Rivera, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peñaloza-López, Y. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Pedroza, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Uribe-Escamilla, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villarruel, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. En los niños con fallos articulatorios es importantevalorar el nivel auditivo central. Se comparan los resultadosde los intervalos interonda de los potenciales evocados auditivosde tallo cerebral (PEATC) a 80 dB SPL (nivel de presión sonora)y las latencias de las ondas de los potenciales evocados auditivosde latencia larga (PEALL) (de vértice) en niños de 5 años deedad con fallos articulatorios para /l/, /r/, /rr/ y /s/, y en controles.Sujetos y métodos. Se evaluaron 50 casos de niños de ambos sexos,de 5 años de edad; 25 con fallos articulatorios y 25 sin fallos articulatorios,como controles; a los dos grupos se les aplicó la pruebade articulación de Melgar. En ambos grupos se consideró: audiciónbilateral normal mediante audiometría tonal, timpanometría yescala de inteligencia de Wechsler para preescolar y primaria revisada,que fueron normales; ausencia de antecedentes de daño neurológico;se evaluaron intervalos interonda de las ondas I-III, I-V yIII-V de los PEATC y latencias de los PEALL (vértice). Resultados.Se analizaron los datos con el SPSS 12, y se realizó estadística descriptivay la t de Student para evaluar diferencias entre los grupos.No se encontraron diferencias entre el grupo control y el grupo deestudio. Conclusiones. Es importante descartar si los niños confallos articulatorios presentan alteraciones en el receptor auditivoo en su función auditiva central. Las variables analizadas en ambosgrupos se comportaron de la misma forma; no se hallaron diferenciassignificativas, lo cual sugiere que en el grupo de estudio noestá afectado su receptor auditivo ni su función auditiva central.Queda pendiente de investigar el significado de la diferencia de laconducción nerviosa central entre ambas aferencias del grupo deestudio</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;43(6): 330-334, sept. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049613</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Potenciales evocados auditivos de tallo cerebral y potenciales de vértice en niños de 5 años con fallos articulatorios para los fonemas /l/, /r/, /rr/ y /s/</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1191</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6462</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28929^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
