<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96794</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-6157</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The cases that we present are patients after dental treatment to improve the harmony of your facial contour drawing. The main objective is to show, through the presentation of both cases, the importance of conducting a study about the loss of volumen in these esthetics patients, which allows solving the problem with the implant material suitable, depending on this atrophy is soft or hard tissue and the degree of wrinkling and ptosis present (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torres Lagares, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Pacheco, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Recio, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz de León, Gonzalo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz de León, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los casos que presentamos son pacientes que tras su tratamiento odontológico quieren mejorar la armonía del dibujo de su contorno facial. El objetivo principal es mostrar, a través de la presentación de ambos casos, la importancia de realizar un estudio previo sobre la pérdida de volumen de estos pacientes de estética, que posibilítela resolución del problema con el material de implante adecuado, dependiendo de que esta atrofia sea de tejido duro o blando y del grado de arrugas y ptosis que presenten (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Dentum (Barc.);10(2): 61-63, abr.-jun. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96794</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Remodelación del ovalo facial: hidroxiapatita de calcio vs ácido poliláctico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32981^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1696^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12482</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31497^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
