<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-63988</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Arthrosis, or osteoarthrosis (OA) is the most common disease of the musculoskeletal system, generates the largest medical expense and is the main cause for disability or invalidity of all the chronic diseases. Its incidence is around 11 % in the Spanish population, bearing an important medical expense. It is an arthropathy characterized by degeneration and loss of the articular cartilage. Pain and and functional impotence are present, and can affect one or more joints. Nowadays the concept of the pathology of the disease has changed, giving more importance to the chondrocyte and the inflammatory response, looking for the possibility of acting pharmacologically on the chondrocyte, which would delay this degenerative process. Since the nineties there is an increasing interest in the so called chondroprotector or chondromodulating agents. They are known as SYSADOA (Symptomatic Slow Acting Drugs for Osteoarthritis). Clinical trials carried out with these substances have demonstrated a moderate improvement in the OA´s symptomatology, acting upon the slow onset symptoms. The European Society of Rheumatology 2003 Recommendations state the efficacy of glucosamine, chondroitin sulphate, diacerein and hyaluronic acid for the treatment of the disease, being recommended to improve the symptoms and as possible modifiers in the progression of the cartilage structural damage. The aim of this article is to provide information regarding these drugs, their mechanism of action, indication, dose and route of administration (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mongil, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arizaga, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Callejo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La osteoartrosis (OA) es la enfermedad más frecuente del aparato locomotor, la que genera mayor gasto sanitario y laprincipal causa de incapacidad o invalidez de todas las enfermedadescrónicas. Se estima una incidencia en la poblaciónespañola de un 11%, conllevando un importante gasto sanitario.Es una artropatía que se caracteriza por la degeneracióny pérdida del cartílago articular. Cursa con dolor e impotenciafuncional y puede afectar a una o más articulaciones. Actualmenteel concepto sobre la patogenia de la enfermedad seha modificado, dando más importancia al condrocito y a larespuesta inflamatoria, buscando la posibilidad de actuar farmacológicamentesobre el condrocito, lo que retrasaría esteproceso degenerativo.Desde la década de los 90 existe un creciente interés porlos llamados agentes condroprotectores o condromoduladores.Atendiendo se denominan: fármacos modificadores desíntomas de acción lenta SYSADOA (Symptomatic Slow ActingDrugs for Osteoarthritis). Los ensayos clínicos realizadoscon estas sustancias han demostrado una mejoría moderadaen la sintomatología de la OA, actuando sobre los síntomascon un comienzo de acción lento.En las recomendaciones del tratamiento de la osteoartrosisde la Sociedad Europea de Reumatología del 2003 se afirmala eficacia de la glucosamina, el condroitín sulfato, ladiacereína y el ácido hialurónico en el tratamiento de la enfermedad,siendo recomendados para mejorar los síntomas ycomo posibles modificadores de la progresión del daño estructuraldel cartílago. El objetivo de este artículo es aportarinformación acerca de estos fármacos, sobre su mecanismode acción, indicación, posología y formas de administración (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;13(7): 485-496, oct.2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-63988</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6972^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6088^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6088^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3706^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2857^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2857^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6972^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
