<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154912</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nutritional, anthropometrical and psychological aspects in rhythmic gymnastics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: There are frequent changes in the supply of female child population, especially in aesthetic sports athletes by pressure to maintain a body. Objectives: The aim was to evaluate nutritional, anthropometric and weight perception aspects of girls who perform rhythmic gymnastics. Methods: 25 gymnast girls were compared to 25 control girls (control). Anthropometric assessment was done by ISAK protocol and nutrition through a seven-day dietary record; as well as a quantitative and qualitative assessment of dietary intake by the DIAL software. Nutritional assessment was performed using a seven days dietary record. A quantitative and qualitative assessment of food intake was conducted, using DIAL software. An ad hoc questionnaire to assess their perception of weight was completed. Results: Anthropometric data showed no significant differences between the study groups except for skinfolds and fat percentage, which was statistically lower in gymnast girls. Energy intake (1,413 ± 283 kcal/day) of gymnasts was lower than recommended by the Food and Nutrition Board, according to their age. Distribution of macronutrients was in the range of normal values (10-30% proteins, 45-65% carbohydrates, 20-35% fat). 32% of gymnasts and 36.4% of control girls felt they should weigh less. Conclusion: Considering the activity carried out by gymnasts, their energy requirements should conform to it, as this will contribute to their development and growth, and also to better perform their activity. Gymnasts&#146; food consumption is far from a balanced diet. No different behaviors were observed in the perception of weight between the two groups (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garicano Vilar, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cevallos, Vanesa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pina Ordúñez, Diana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Mauro Martín, Ismael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: existen alteraciones frecuentes en la alimentación de la población infantil femenina, y especialmente en atletas de deportes estéticos por la presión ejercida para mantener un cuerpo. Objetivos: evaluar los aspectos nutricionales, antropométricos y la percepción del peso de niñas que realizan gimnasia rítmica frente a un grupo control. Métodos: estudio descriptivo comparativo. Se compararon 25 niñas gimnastas con 25 niñas no gimnastas (control). Se realizó una valoración antropométrica, mediante protocolo ISAK, y nutricional, mediante un registro dietético de 7 días; así como una valoración cuantitativa y cualitativa de la ingesta alimentaria, mediante el software  DIAL. Se rellenó un cuestionario de hábitos y sobre la percepción de su peso corporal. Resultados: los datos antropométricos no presentaron diferencias significativas entre ambos grupos, excepto en los pliegues cutáneos y el porcentaje de grasa, el cual era estadísticamente inferior en gimnastas. La ingesta energética (1.413 ± 283 kcal/día) de las gimnastas era inferior a la recomendada por la Food and Nutrition Board de acuerdo a su edad. La distribución de los macronutrientes cumplía con los valores normales establecidos (10-30% proteínas, 45-65% hidratos, 20-35% grasas). El 32% de las gimnastas y el 36,4% de las niñas control consideraron que les gustaría pesar menos. Conclusión: teniendo en cuenta la intensa actividad de las gimnastas, sus requerimientos energéticos deberían ajustarse a ello, ya que esto contribuirá a su desarrollo y crecimiento y a una mejor ejecución del ejercicio. En la muestra estudiada, el consumo de alimentos de las gimnastas se aleja de una alimentación equilibrada. No se observaron comportamientos diferentes en la percepción del peso entre ambos grupos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;33(4): 865-871, jul.-ago. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154912</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aspectos nutricionales, antropométricos y psicológicos en gimnasia rítmica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51387</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33926^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1076^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4499^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6324^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33926^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6324^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2181^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9936^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50311</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
