<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98762</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6709</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fe-Si biominerals in the Vilyuchinskie hot springs, Kamchatka Peninsula, Russia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The micromorphological structure of microbial mats (biomats) from the hot springs of the Vilyuchinskaya hydrothermal system, Kamchatka Peninsula, Russia, were investigated. The Vilyuchinskie hot springs had a discharge temperatureof 55&#150;56°C and Na-Ca-HCO3-type waters rich in silicic and boric acids. Water and biomats had high concentrations of Fe, Mn, Sr, and As. Enumeration of total bacterial abundance (TBA) demonstrated a low density of bacterial populations. However, the fractions of metabolically active bacteria and respiring iron-oxidizing bacteria in the hot-spring water were high, comprising 68 and 21% of TBA, respectively. Scanning electron microscopy equipped with an energy dispersive X-rayspectrometer (SEM-EDX) showed that unicellular rod-shaped bacteria about 5-&amp;#956;m long predominated in the brown biomats. The mineral capsules of these bacteria contained large amounts of Fe and Si. Extracellular and intracellular particles were observed by transmission electron microscopy. Fe-oxidizing bacteria were isolated from the biomats on agar plates with selective medium. Therefore, it can be concluded that microorganisms inhabiting the biomats of the Vilyuchinskie hot springs are essential for the deposition of Fe-minerals at neutral pH (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Okrugin, Viktor M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parfenova, Valentina V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Belkova, Natalia L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zakharova, Julia R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tazaki, Kazue</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se describe el estudio de la estructura micromorfológica de los tapetes microbianos (biomats) de las fuentes termales del sistema hidrotermal de Vilyunchinskaya, en la península de Kamchatka (Rusia). Las fuentes hidrotermales de Vilyichinskie tenían una temperatura de descarga de 55&#150;56ºCy sus aguas son del tipo Na-Ca-HCO3, ricas en ácidos silícico y bórico. El aguay los tapetes microbianos tenían una alta concentración de Fe, Mn, Sr y As. La enumeración de la abundancia total de bacterias (ATB) mostró una baja densidad de poblaciones bacterianas. Sin embargo, en el agua de las fuentes termales las fracciones de bacterias metabólicamente activas y de bacterias respiradoras oxidadoras de Fe eran elevadas, del 68 y el 21% de ATB, respectivamente. El estudio mediante el microscopio electrónico de barrido equipado con un espectrofotómetro de rayos X dispersor de energía (SEM-EDX) mostró que en los tapetes microbianos marrones predominaban las bacterias unicelulares en forma de bacilo de unos 5 &amp;#956;m. Las cápsulas minerales de estas bacterias contenían gran cantidad de Fe y Si. La observación con microscopía electrónica de transmisión reveló la presencia de partículas extracelulares e intracelulares. De los tapetes microbianos se aislaron bacterias oxidadoras  de Fe mediante placas de agar con medio selectivo. Por tanto, se puede concluir que los microorganismos de los tapetes microbianos de las fuentes termales de Vilyuchinskie son esenciales para el depósito de minerales de hierro a pH neutro (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int Microbiol;7(3): 193-198, sept. 2004. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98762</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Biominerales de Fe-Si de las fuentes termales de Vilyuchiskie, en la península de Kamchatka (Rusia)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d25416^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7668^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30888</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9088^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38366^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32342^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15275</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
