<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043046</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">efecctiveness of behavioral intervention in nocturnal enuresis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Nocturnal enuresis is a common, often misunderstood condition that affects millions of children. Although the rate of spontaneous resolution is 15 % per year, treatment is often required for social or psychological reasons.                 Objective: To determine the prevalence of nocturnal enuresis in a primary health care area, how was it diagnosed, which treatments were employed and treatment response.                 Material and methods: A retrospective study was performed that included all the medical records of children aged between 6 and 14 years old in a basic health area.                 Results: Twenty-seven children with a diagnosis of nocturnal enuresis were identified (4.3 %). Among these, 21 were boys (77.7 %) and six were girls (22.3 %). There was a family history of nocturnal enuresis in 15 patients (55.5 %). Nocturnal enuresis was not the reason for consultation in 24 of the 27 patients (88.8 %) but was diagnosed collaterally by anamnesis. All the children had simple primary nocturnal (monosymptomatic) enuresis. Five patients abandoned the treatment (18 %), 15 (55.5 %) recovered with behavioral intervention exclusively, the remaining seven children were treated with desmopressin, which was successful in three of them. The remaining four patients were still receiving treatment when the data were collected.                 Conclusions: The prevalence of nocturnal enuresis in this primary health area (4.3 %) is similar that reported in other series. In a high percentage (88.8 %) of patients, nocturnal enuresis was not the reason for consultation but was diagnosed during anamnesis. Behavioral intervention was effective in more than half (55.5 %) of the patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Monge Zamorano, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Nieto, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez Abad, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: La enuresis nocturna es un trastorno frecuente, no bien conocido, que afecta a millones de niños. Aunque su tasa de resolución espontánea es del 15 % anual, a veces es necesario instaurar tratamiento por motivos psicológicos o sociales.                 Objetivo: Determinar la prevalencia de enuresis nocturna en una zona básica de salud, la forma en que fue diagnosticada, los tratamientos empleados y la respuesta a los mismos.                 Material y métodos: Se realizó un estudio retrospectivo a partir de las historias clínicas, de los niños con edades entre 6 y 14 años pertenecientes a una zona básica de salud.                 Resultados: Se encontraron 27 niños con ese diagnóstico (4,3 %). De ellos, 21 fueron varones (77,7 %) y 6 niñas (22,3 %). Existían antecedentes familiares de enuresis en 15 de ellos (55,5 %). La enuresis nocturna no fue motivo de consulta en el 88,8 % de los casos (24 de 27), sino que se obtuvo ese dato en la anamnesis. Todos los niños presentaban enuresis nocturna primaria simple (monosintomática). Durante el tratamiento, 5 pacientes abandonaron (18,5 %), 15 (55,5 %) consiguieron la curación con terapia conductual exclusivamente y en los otros 7 casos se empleó tratamiento con desmopresina, con éxito en tres de ellos. Los cuatro restantes continuaban en tratamiento cuando se recogieron los datos.                 Conclusiones: La prevalencia de enuresis nocturna en esta zona básica de salud (4,3 %) es similar a la publicada en otras series. En un elevado porcentaje (88,8 %) no fue un problema consultado sino obtenido por anamnesis dirigida. El tratamiento conductual se mostró muy eficaz en más de la mitad de pacientes (55,5 %)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);63(5): 444-447, nov. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043046</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia del tratamiento conductual en la enuresis nocturna</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4855^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1541^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
