<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117406</identifier>
<setSpec>2014-9832</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of an educational intervention in the clinical management of cardiovascular risk factors in primary healthcare. Experiment with the Project Globe Consortium in Russia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Cardiovascular diseases are the main cause of morbimortality and of burden of disease in both developed and developing countries. Therefore the appropriate management of cardiovascular risk factors (CVR) in primary and secondary prevention is highly relevant. The role of continuing medical education and continuing professional development on performance improvement has been questioned. An educational intervention addressed to primary care physicians as continuing professional development as well as to their patients with CVR was devised. Principles of therapeutic education were used. The objective was to evaluate the impact of both educational interventions on cognitive and attitudinal parameters of CVR, as well as the impact on their surrogate markers of disease progression. Subjects and methods. 30 primary care physicians from outpatient clinics in the Moscow metropolitan area were invited to the educational intervention (lectures, seminars, workshops for a total of 72 h during one month). Afterwards 600 patients with CVR attending the same clinics received education on CVR (12 sessions over 3 months). Patients were clinically evaluated on quarterly bases during one year of follow up. Results. A significant reduction in surrogate markers of CVR was observed (blood pressure, serum lipids, weight, smoking, etc.) among the patient cohort as a probable consequence of leveraged therapeutic adherence. Likewise, the knowledge and attitudes improved significantly both in physicians and their patients. Conclusions. A sequential education of physicians and their patients with CVR seems to have a favorable impact upon surrogate markers of risk. Further controlled studies are needed to confirm these preliminary results (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Silva, Honorio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Shurandina, I. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vartanyan, Felix</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borisov, K. N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Thomson, Tom</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Avtandilov, A. G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pukhaeva, A. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pulido, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las enfermedades cardiovasculares son la principal causa de morbimortalidad y de carga de enfermedad global. Por ello, el manejo apropiado de sus factores de riesgo (FRCV) en la prevención primaria y secundaria del daño cardiovascular es de primordial importancia. Se ha cuestionado el papel de la educación médica continuada en mejorar el desempeño profesional. Diseñamos una intervención educativa destinada tanto a médicos de atención primaria bajo el contexto de desarrollo profesional continuo como a sus pacientes, utilizando principios de educación terapéutica en un diseño abierto no controlado. El objetivo fue evaluar su impacto en parámetros cognitivos y actitudinales, y su efecto en marcadores de riesgo. Sujetos y métodos. 30 médicos de policlínicas ambulatorias en el área metropolitana de Moscú fueron invitados a participar en un programa de actualización sobre el manejo de FRCV (72 h). Posteriormente, 600 pacientes con FRCV participaron en 12 sesiones educativas durante un periodo de tres meses. Los pacientes fueron evaluados clínicamente de forma trimestral durante 12 meses. Resultados. Se observó una reducción significativa de los FRCV (hipertensión arterial, hipercolesterolemia, peso corporal, hiperlipidemia, tabaquismo) durante el periodo de evaluación, acompañados de cambios en el estilo de vida probablemente como reflejo de una mejor adherencia al tratamiento. La evaluación cognitiva y las actitudes hacia el control de FRCV tuvieron mejores calificaciones tanto en los médicos como en sus pacientes. Conclusiones. La educación secuencial de médicos y de sus pacientes en el manejo de FRCV parece tener un impacto favorable en la evolución clínica de sus marcadores, pero se precisan estudios controlados para confirmar estos hallazgos preliminares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Fund. Educ. Méd. (Ed. impr.);16(3): 131-136, sept. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117406</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de una intervención educativa en el manejo clínico de los factores de riesgo cardiovascular en atención primaria de salud. Experiencia con Project Globe Consortium en Rusia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
