<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140817</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ultrasonography in Primary Care: State of the question</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Periodically, we question if introducing ultrasonography into Primary Health Care would be useful and suitable because it is a safe and rapid diagnostic procedure that could be used in our consulting room. This method can obtain quality diagnostic images comparable to more expensive and less accessible techniques. Material and methods. We have performed a review of the literature in INAHTA, Pubmed, and the websites of some scientific societies between the years 1996-2006 to find studies that would confirm whether performing ultra-sound in Primary Health Care was feasible and reliable in the field of diagnosis. Results. We only found a small number of articles on the subject that were of low quality and focused on partial issues. This contrasts with the intense activities of the scientific societies on this subject: work groups, accredited courses, etc. Conclusions. Performing ultrasound in Primary Care is feasible. However, its indications, training criteria of the medical practitioner and the legal considerations surrounding it still need to be defined (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vicente-Molinero, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aznar-Cantín, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yáñez-Rodríguez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Cíclicamente nos preguntamos si es útil y conveniente introducir la ecografía en Atención Primaria, al tratarse de un procedimiento diagnóstico inocuo y rápido realizable en nuestra consulta, y con la que se obtienen imágenes de calidad diagnóstica equiparables a técnicas más costosas y menos accesibles. Material y Métodos. Realizamos una revisión bibliográfica en INAHTA, Pubmed y las páginas web de distintas sociedades científicas, entre los años 1996-2006, buscando estudios que confirmasen si la realización de ecografías en Atención Primaria era factible y fiable en el terreno diagnóstico. Resultados. Encontramos un bajo número de artículos sobre la cuestión, con baja calidad y centrados en cuestiones parciales. Este hecho contrasta con una actividad intensa de las sociedades científicas en este tema: grupos de trabajo, cursos acreditados, etc. Conclusiones. La realización de la ecografía en Atención Primaria es factible, quedando por definir y reglamentar sus indicaciones, criterios de formación del médico de familia, y las consideraciones legales que la rodean (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);35(2): 58-61, feb. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140817</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ecografía en Atención Primaria: estado de la cuestión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33619^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37549^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11253^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37549^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11253^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11253^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11253^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33619^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
