<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92047</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Malignancy predictive factors in pancreatic intraductal papillary mucinous neoplasm</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective:Intraductal papillary mucinous neoplasm (IPMN) is a premalignant lesion of the pancreas. Its natural history is not well known. We evaluated the characteristics and predictor factors of malignancy of IPMN. Patients and method: A retrospective analysis was performed in 88 patients diagnosed with IPMN between January 1997 and December 2008. The diagnosis was done by abdominal computed tomography (CT), pancreatic-magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and/or endoscopic ultrasound (EUS). Gender, age, symptoms, origin, location, CA 19.9 serum levels, size of tumours and nodules by imaging techniques, type of surgery, malignancy and survival were evaluated. Nine pre-surgical variables were selected, and univariate and multivariate analysis to identify independent prognostic factors of malignancy were performed. Results: The mean age was 64years and 53% were men. 39% of tumours were incidental. 50% had their origin on the main pancreatic duct, 37% on collateral branchs and 13% were multifocal. 68% patients were operated: 42% had malignant neoplasms (32% carcinoma in situ and 68% invasive). Twelve patients died (1 benign, 1 in situ and 10 invasive). Univariate and multivariate analysis identified the symptoms and the tumour size (&amp;#8805; 22mm [median of our serie] and &amp;#8805; 30mm [size accepted in literature]) as independent predictor factors of malignancy. Conclusions: Many IPMN are incidental findings. The presence of symptoms and size of the tumour are independent prognostic factors of malignancy and they should be considered to decide therapeutic actions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miquel, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Feu, Faust</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castells, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Cruz, Laureano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayuso, Juan Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bombi, Josep Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ginés, Àngels</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Esparrach, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maurel, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Adet Caldelari, Ana Celia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: La neoplasia mucinosa papilar intraductal (NMPI) es una lesión pancreática premaligna cuya historia natural no es bien conocida. Se han analizado las características de las NMPI atendidas en nuestro hospital e identificado factores predictivos de malignidad.Pacientes y método: Análisis retrospectivo de 88 pacientes con NMPI diagnosticados por tomografía computarizada (TC), colangio-pancreatografía por resonancia magnética (CPRM) y/o ultrasonografía endoscópica (USE), de enero de 1997 a diciembre de 2008. Se evaluaron: edad, sexo, forma de presentación, origen, localización, CA 19.9 sérico, tamaño del tumor y existencia de nódulos según técnicas de imagen, tipo de cirugía, malignidad y supervivencia. Se seleccionaron nueve variables prequirúrgicas y se realizó un análisis uni y multivariante para identificar factores predictivos independientes de malignidad.Resultados: La edad media de los pacientes fue de 64 años y el 53% eran varones. El 39% fueron diagnosticados por un hallazgo casual. El 50% tenían su origen en el conducto de Wirsung, el 37% en ramas colaterales y un 13% eran mixtos. Fueron operados un 68%; de éstos, el 42% fueron tumores malignos (32% carcinoma &#147;in situ&#148; y 68% invasivos). Fallecieron 12 pacientes (1 benigno, 1 &#147;in situ&#148; y 10 invasivos). Los análisis uni y multivariante identificaron como factores predictivos independientes de malignidad la presencia de síntomas y el tamaño del tumor (&amp;#8805; 22mm [mediana de nuestra serie] y &amp;#8805; 30mm [tamaño aceptado en la literatura]). Conclusión: Muchas NMPI son hallazgos casuales. La presencia de síntomas y el tamaño del tumor son factores predictivos independientes de malignidad y deben tenerse en cuenta en el momento de decidir la actitud terapéutica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);137(14): 631-636, nov. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92047</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores predictivos de malignidad en la neoplasia mucinosa papilar intraductal de páncreas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31806^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33097^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38794^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10378^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201111</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
