<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74028</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Methodology and fieldwork logistics of a multilevel research study on the influence of neigbourdhood&#146;s characteristics on natives and ecuadorian&#146;s mental health in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The methodological design, characteristics and fieldwork stage ofa multilevel research study on the impact of the environmentalcharacteristics on mental health in an autochthonous and immigrantpopulation are described in this paper.Individual data were obtained using a core questionnaire 40minutes length from home interviews of Spanish and Ecuadorianadults from September 2006 to January 2007. A random sample of1186 people aged 18-55, with equal distribution of gender andnationality was obtained from Civil Registers of 33 areas(municipalities or neighbourhoods) of Madrid, Alicante, Almeria andMurcia, chosen by ethnic density and socioeconomic criteria.Previously, a pilot study was carried out. Socioeconomic indicators ofneighbourhoods and selected communities were obtained fromMunicipal Registers and other secondary sources.Finally, 1144 people were interviewed (96%). Each person wascontacted at home at two different times. The global response rate was61%, higher among Ecuadorians (69%), who presented more problemsof localisation (34%).Analyzing methods and fieldwork process the conclusion is thatsample strategies for this type of population studies should beevaluated using feasibility criteria given time and money constraints,against the need to obtain representative samples of the targetpopulations. There were serious shortcomings in the availability ofsocial integration indicators at the neighbourhood level(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-del Arco, Débora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Fulgueiras, ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mazarrasa Alvear, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jarrín Vera, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Pina, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Ortuzar, Visitación</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez-Rojo, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amo Valero, Julia del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Liria, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zunzunegui Pastor, María Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz del Peral, Domingo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Arenas, M. Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llácer Gil de Ramales, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se realizó una investigación multinivel sobre el impacto de lascaracterísticas ambientales de la zona de residencia en la salud mentalde población autóctona e inmigrante. El objetivo de este artículo esdescribir el planteamiento metodológico de la investigación, el trabajode campo, las tasas de respuesta correspondientes y discutir el diseñometodológico y las dificultades derivadas de su puesta en práctica.Los datos individuales se obtuvieron aplicando un cuestionarioestructurado de aproximadamente 40 minutos, mediante entrevistadomiciliaria a personas españolas y ecuatorianas de 18 a 55 años. Eltrabajo se realizó de septiembre de 2006 a enero de 2007 en una muestraestimada de 1.186 personas equiparada por sexo y nacionalidad,obtenida aleatoriamente de los Padrones Municipales de 33 áreas(municipios o barrios) de Madrid, Alicante, Almería y Murcia, seleccionadassegún criterios de densidad étnica y socioeconómicos. Previamentese realizó un estudio piloto (n=113)Los indicadores sociodemográficosde las áreas se obtuvieron a partir de fuentes secundarias. Seentrevistó a 1.144 personas (96%). La tasa de respuesta global fue del61%, superior entre ecuatorianos (69%), colectivo que presentó másproblemas de localización (34%). Las negativas a colaborar fueron másaltas entre españoles (21%).Se concluye que en este tipo de estudios sería conveniente revisarlas estrategias de muestreo para combinar criterios de eficiencia con lanecesidad de obtener una muestra representativa de la población diana.Se constata la dificultad de obtener datos inframunicipales de integraciónsocial(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;83(4): 493-508, jul.-ago.2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74028</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Metodología y logística de campo de un estudio multinivel sobre la influencia en España de las características medioambientales en la salud mental de población autóctona y ecuatoriana inmigrante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32466^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33954</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24535</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24872</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16665</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32485</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4716^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33155</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
