<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76911</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1473</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">High Resolution Microdialysis. Methodological issues and application to the study of inflammatory brain response</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cerebral microdialysis is a tool that provides veryrelevant information in the metabolic monitoring ofbrain injured patients. It is a particularly effective technique for the detection and analysis of small molecules,given that the pores of the dialysis membrane actas a barrier to restrict the transport of larger species,such as proteins and other macromolecules. The recentavailability of microdialysis catheters with membranepores of larger size, termed &#147;high resolution&#148; catheters,would widen the spectrum of molecules detectablein the dialisate. However, there are technical complicationsrelated to the use of these catheters for suchpurposes, and therefore, this potential capacity for therecovery of proteins needs to be validated, in order tobegin its application as a tool in studies of proteomicsassociated with brain injuries. The following reviewdepicts the basic principles of microdialysis, and describessome of the issues involved in the recovery ofmolecules in the dialisate, including the physical propertiesof the dialysis membrane and of the moleculesof interest (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sahuquillo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>De Los Rios, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Poca, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Expósito, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La técnica de microdiálisis (MD) cerebral es un instrumentoque proporciona información relevante en lamonitorización del metabolismo cerebral en pacientesneurocríticos. La MD es una técnica especialmente efectivapara la detección y análisis de pequeñas moléculas,puesto que el tamaño de los poros de la membranadializante actúa como barrera restringiendo el paso deespecies mayores, tales como proteínas u otras macromoléculas.La reciente disponibilidad de catéteres demicrodiálisis con poros de mayor calibre, denominadosde &#147;alta resolución&#148;, permite ampliar el rango de moléculasdetectables en el dializado. Sin embargo, existencomplicaciones técnicas relacionadas con la utilizaciónde estos catéteres para estos propósitos, por lo que estacapacidad potencial para la recuperación de proteínasnecesita ser validada antes de su aplicación como herramientapara estudios de proteómica asociados a la lesióncerebral. En esta revisión se contemplan los principiosbásicos de la microdiálisis y los diferentes factores queintervienen en los procesos de recuperación de moléculasen el dializado, tales como las características físicasde la membrana dializante, así como de las moléculasque se desea investigar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurocirugia (Astur);20(5): 433-448, sept.-oct. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76911</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Microdiálisis de alta resolución. Aspectos metodológicos y aplicación al estudio de larespuesta inflamatoria cerebral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28903^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6410^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6410^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10669</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9611^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4736^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8737</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11932</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28903^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1949</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6410^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23497</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4736^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31307^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31307^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38178^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32175^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38178^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
