<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045297</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New concepts in dietary treatment of metabolic syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Metabolic syndrome is a disorder having high prevalence in our society. It is characterized by different proatherogenic disorders (dyslipidemia, arterial hypertension, hydrocarbonated intolerance, prothrombotic and proinflammatory conditions) and predisposing factors (central obesity, sedentary life and genetic factors). There is much evidence in favor of the changes in the style of life in the control of metabolic and non-metabolic parameters that characterize this syndrome. The role of certain foods in the prevention and treatment of the manifestations of the metabolic syndrome, among others, coffee, vegetable and marine sterols, nuts, pod vegetables, eggs and olive oil, are presently the object of debate. Herein, the new dietary concepts for patients with metabolic syndrome and the scientific evidence supporting them are reviewed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pascual Fuster, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meco López, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome metabólico es un trastorno de elevada prevalencia en nuestra sociedad caracterizado por diversas alteraciones proaterogénicas (dislipidemia, hipertensión arterial, intolerancia hidrocarbonada, estados protrombótico y proinflamatorio) y factores predisponentes (obesidad central, sedentarismo y factores genéticos). Existen numerosas evidencias a favor de los cambios del estilo de vida en el control de los parámetros metabólicos y no metabólicos que caracterizan este síndrome. Actualmente es objeto de debate el papel de determinados alimentos en la prevención y tratamiento de las manifestaciones del síndrome metabólico, entre otros el café, los esteroles vegetales y marinos, los frutos secos, las legumbres, los huevos y el aceite de oliva. Aquí se revisan los nuevos conceptos dietéticos para pacientes con síndrome metabólico y las evidencias científicas que los apoyan</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;206(2): 100-102, feb. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045297</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevos conceptos en el tratamiento dietético del síndrome metabólico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8862^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37653</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22895^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
