<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108679</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">foundlings, nannies, attending sisters and hospitaller sisters: characters of a major public health problem between vintismo and  regeneração (1820-1852)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The practice of Pediatric and Child Health Nursing in Portugal is now clearly identified and differentiated. Nevertheless, it had a lengthy evolution in which we point out the existence and the role of nannies, attending sisters and hospitaller sisters in assisting foundlings. Our purpose is to highlight these characters as well as the political and institutional environment in which they lived between Vintismo and Regeneração (1820-1852). According to the historical method, we analyzed both the debates at Cortes Gerais e Extraordinárias (1821-1822) and the legislation produced between 1821 and 1839. We also consulted specific bibliography. We present the result of those debates, the principles stated in the project of the Regulamento da Saúde Pública as far as foundlings are concerned and the laws enacted in that period. A heavy legacy of the Antigo Regime, foundlings were one of the main Public Health problems for which all solving strategies failed. The problem persisted and expanded throughout the 19th century. From that time to modern Nursing, nannies and other «devoted women», as they attempted to prevent abandoned children from dying, did play a relevant caring and communitarian role in assisting children until the late 19th century (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Subtil, Carlos Lousada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vieira, Margarida</dc:creator>
<dc:language>pt</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En Portugal, las prácticas de salud infantil y enfermería pediátrica están bien identificadas y diferenciadas. Sin embargo, tuvieran una larga evolución que indica la existencia y el papel de las nodrizas y hospitalarias en la atención de los expósitos. Se pretende poner de relieve estos personajes y el entorno político e institucional en el que vivían, entre el Vintismo y la Regeneração (1820-1852), De acuerdo con la metodología histórica, se procedió à la análisis de los debates en las Cortes Generales y Extraordinarias (1821-1822), de la legislación producida entre 1821 y 1839 y a la consulta bibliográfica específica. Se presentan los resultados de estas discusiones, los principios esbozados en el proyecto de Reglamento de Salud Pública acerca de los expósitos y la legislación que se publicó durante este período. Los expósitos, un pesado legado del Antiguo Régimen, constituyen un problema importante de salud pública para el que ensayaron estrategias de resolución que han fracasado. El problema persistió y se ha ampliado durante el siglo XIX. En el trayecto que conduce a la enfermería moderna, las nodrizas y otras «mujeres consagradas», procurando tirar a la muerte muchos niños abandonados, desempeñaran hasta finales del siglo XIX, un significativo papel cuidativo y comunitario en la asistencia a los niños (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;15(31): 77-84, sept.-dic. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108679</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Expósitos, niñeras, hermanas asistentes y hermanas hospitalarias: figuras ante un problema de salud pública entre el vintismo y la regeneración (1820-1852)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2695</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2721^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6835</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10564^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
