<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123914</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-7546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Electromyographic study of bench press exercise at different angles of execution</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The objective of this was to evaluate of the peak maximum strength, and EMG activation (EMG) in the muscles clavicular portion of pectoralis major (CPPM), sternal portion of pectoralis major (SPPM), and anterior deltoid (AD) in the 3 different angles of the bench press. Method. They were selected 11 male subjects (23.7 ± 3.2 years, 75.1 ± 12.6 kg, 173.7 cm, 9.8 ± 3.6 % BF), experienced in strength training (2,8 ± 1.5 years, 3.2 ± 0.2 days of the week, 70 ± 8.9 minutes by session). The subjects were submitted to the tests of voluntary contraction maximum isometrics (CVIM), in the horizontal bench press (HBP: 90º), in the inclined bench press (IBP: 45º) and declined bench press (DBP: - 30º), being the three evaluations carried out respecting 48 hours of break between the same. Results. After the evaluations we identify the following results in the CVIM (162.65 ± 18.63 Kgf HPB, 155.02  ± 11.97 Kgf IPB and 163.90 ± 15.77 Kgf DPB) and we identify that do not statistically significant between exercises. When checking the differences recorded EMG to muscle the DA, in the exercises PBI and PBH, PBI and PBD. Conclusion. The results support, that the 2 portions of the greater pectoral muscle similarly are activated in the different angles of the press of banking, and that the IBP causes a greater activation of DA. © 2013 Revista Andaluza de Medicina del Deporte (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernandes da Silva, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calil e Silva, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinto da Silva, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereira Guimarãesa, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almeida Costa Campos, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El objetivo del estudio fue evaluar el pico de fuerza máxima, y la activación electromiográfica (EMG) del músculo pectoral mayor porción clavicular (PMC), pectoral mayor porción esternocostal (PME) y deltoides anterior (DA) en 3 diferentes ángulos del ejercicio press de banca. Método. Fueron seleccionados 11 sujetos del sexo masculino (23,7 ± 3,2 años; 75,1 ± 12,6 kg; 173,7 cm; 9,8 ± 3,6 %G), expertos en el entrenamiento de fuerza (2,8 ± 1,5 años; 3,2 ± 0,2 días de la semana; 70 ± 8,9 minutos por sesión). Los sujetos fueron sometidos a los tests de contracción voluntaria isométrica máxima (CVIM), en el ejercicio press de banca horizontal (PBH: 90º), press de banca inclinado (PBI: 45º) y press de banca declinado (PBD: - 30º), siendo hechas las tres evaluaciones respetando 48 horas de intervalo entre las mismas. Resultados. Después de las evaluaciones identificamos los siguientes resultados en la CVIM (162,65 ± 18,63 Kgf PBH, 155,02 ± 11,97 Kgf PBI y 163,90 ± 15,77 Kgf PBD), e identificamos que no hubo diferencias significativas entre los ejercicios. En la EMG registramos diferencias significativas en el músculo DA, en los ejercicio PBI y PBH, PBI y PBD. Conclusión. Los resultados soportan que, las 2 porciones del músculo pectoral mayor son similarmente activadas en los diferentes ángulos del press de banca, en cuanto que el PBI conlleva una mayor activación del DA (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. andal. med. deporte;7(2): 78-82, jun. 2014. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123914</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio electromiográfico del ejercicio press de banca en diferentes ángulos de ejecución</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7704^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4648^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32124^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
