<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93425</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1473</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Management and microsurgical treatment of infun-dibular dilatations of the posterior communicating artery. Series of nine cases and review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The infundibular dilatation (ID) of the posterior communicating (PCom) artery is defined as the conic, triangular or infundibular shaped, less than 3mm wide, origin of the PCom artery from the internal carotid artery. The purpose of this paper is to present the personal experience in the microsurgical manage­ment of the ID, to review the literature and to propose some algorithms to improve its clinical and microsurgi­cal management. Material and methods. Nine cases of ID have been operated on through a pterional approach. In four patients with subarachnoid hemorrhage (SAH) the ID was considered as the potential source of the bleeding; in four cases the ID was treated after a SAH due to the rupture of an aneurysm; finally, an ID was treated in patient with diagnosis of pseudoxantoma elasticum. Results. In eight cases the ID was clipped and the Pcom artery subsequently occluded and in the remai­ning case the ID was associated with a fetal PComA and the ID was reinforced. There were no complications excepting a transitory third cranial nerve paresis. The Glasgow Outcome Scale was 5 in all cases at discharge and one year later. Conclusions. The true significance of the ID remains unknown, but in some instances it is necessary to con­sider its management: 1. In patients with ruptured aneurysms submited to microsurgical clipping and with an ipsilateral ID, the lesion must be explored and treated; 2. In patients with ruptured aneurysms treated with endovascular procedures or harbouring an ID contralateral to a microsurgically treated aneurysm, the microsurgical indication will be done after conside­ring all risk factors; 3. In patients with SAH and an ID as the only potential source of the bleeding there would be an indication for microsurgical exploration; 4. The incidental finding of an ID should be indication for (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quilis-Quesada, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Verdú-López, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Darder, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La dilatación infundibular (DI) de la arteria comunicante posterior (AComP) se define como la dilatación cónica, triangular o en forma de embudo, menor de 3 mm, en el origen de la AComP de la arte­ria carótida interna. El propósito del presente trabajo es presentar la experiencia propia en el tratamiento microquirúrgico de la DI de la AComP, revisar la biblio­grafía y proponer algoritmos para optimizar su manejo clínico y microquirúrgico. Material y métodos. Se han estudiado nueve casos de DI intervenidos a través de un abordaje pterional. En cuatro pacientes con hemorragia subaracnoidea (HSA) la DI se consideró la única causa del sangrado; en otros cuatro pacientes la DI se intervino tras una HSA por ruptura de otra lesión aneurismática; finalmente, en un paciente con pseudoxantoma elástico la DI se intervino de forma preventiva. Resultados. En ocho casos se procedió al clipaje de la DI y cierre de la AComP y en uno al reforzamiento de la DI al tratarse de una AComP del tipo fetal. No aparecie­ron complicaciones salvo una paresia transitoria del III par. El Glasgow Outcome Scale al alta y al año fue de 5 en todos los casos. Conclusiones. La DI de la AComP es una lesión de significado no aclarado, pero que plantea la necesidad de considerar su tratamiento en algunas ocasiones: 1. En pacientes con aneurismas rotos sometidos a cirugía y DI homolateral se recomienda explorar y tratar la lesión;  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurocirugia (Astur);22(4): 301-309, ago. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93425</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo y tratamiento microquirúrgico de las dilataciones infundibulares de la arteria comunicante posterior. Serie de nueve casos y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11337^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23184^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13733^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13733^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30855^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2569^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3415^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
