<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055444</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of vitamine C in liposuction tumescent solution as lipolisis and fibrosis inductor. Experimental study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Liposuction does not always let to remove all the amount of adipose tissue which causes lipodistrophy, for that reason, it is recommended the necessity to improve that technique. We try to demonstrate that the use of vitamin C in the tumescence solution induces lipolysis and raises fibrosis. This article is a descriptive, prospective, experimental and comparative research of a sample of 30 mice of Sprague- Dawley type of both sexes, which were infiltrated with a tumescence solution in the subdermic inguinal region with vitamin C to the experimental group and with tumescence solution without vitamin C to the control group, for a further histological macroscopic as well as microscopic study. The results showed that 100% of the samples with vitamin C presented changes in the adipose tissue which suggested lipolysis, whereas 82% were evidence for the formation of young collagen. As a conclusion, vitamin C helps lipolysis and promotes synthesis of collagen when it is used as a part of the tumescence solution in experimental animals (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Romero, T. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antoniadis Petrakis, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Liposucción no permite siempre extraer todo el tejido adiposo causante de la lipodistrofia, por lo cual se plantea la necesidad de perfeccionar esta técnica. Nuestro objetivo es el demostrar que el uso de la vitamina C en la solución tumescente induce lipólisis y aumenta la fibrosis. El presente es un estudio descriptivo, prospectivo, experimental y comparativo de una muestra de 30 ratas Sprague-Dawley de ambos sexos, a las cuales se les infiltró solución tumescente en el tejido subdérmico de la región inguinal, con vitamina C al grupo experimental y con solución tumescente sin vitamina C al grupo control, para su posterior estudio histológico macroscópico y microscópico. El 100% de las muestras con vitamina C evidenciaron cambios a nivel del tejido adiposo sugerentes de lipólisis y en el 82% se evidenciaron cambios en el tejido conectivo sugerentes de formación de colágeno joven. Concluimos que la vitamina C favorece la lipolisis y promueve la síntesis de colágeno cuando se utiliza como parte de la solución tumescente en animales de experimentación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;33(2): 105-110, abr.-jun. 2007. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055444</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso de vitamina C en la solución tumescente de liposucción como inductor de lipolisis y fibrosis. Trabajo experimental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8241^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8241^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4255</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23742^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19167^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d280^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1212^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8235^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37575</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
