<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83200</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical results of femoropopliteal endovascular treatment in patients with critical limb ischaemia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Critical lower-limb ischaemia requires immediate treatment in order to preservethe threatened limb. The femoral and popliteal arteries are the most frequently affected.Besides the surgical procedures, endovascular therapy is also an option for this arterial segment.Objective. To analyse the clinical outcome of patients with critical limb ischaemia treated withfemoropopliteal angioplasty.Material and methods. A retrospective study was conducted that included 50 consecutivepatients with critical limb ischaemia who were treated with femoro-popliteal angioplasty (PTA)between 2006 and 2008.Results. PTA was technically successful in 94 %. Limb salvage rate was 75 % during the fi rst year,and amputation-free survival was 60 %. The factors related to limb salvage were the patency ofdistal vessels (p = 0.007) and the clinical situation of the contralateral limb (p = 0.03).Conclusion. Compared with other studies with similar characteristics, an acceptable limbsalvage rate was achieved, making endovascular treatment a therapeutic option that must betaken into account(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rivas Domínguez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Gay, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zanabili Al-Sibbai, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Julián, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortigosa Mateo, A. B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La isquemia crítica de las extremidades inferiores es indicación de tratamiento derevascularización para tratar de asegurar la preservación de la extremidad. El sector fémoro-poplíteo es el más frecuentemente afectado, y a las distintas posibilidades mediante cirugíaconvencional en ese sector, se suman las técnicas endovasculares.Objetivo. Determinar la evolución clínica de los pacientes con isquemia crítica tratados medianteangioplastia con colocación muy selectiva de stent en el sector fémoro-poplíteo y los parámetrosque infl uyen en los resultados.Material y métodos. Estudio retrospectivo en el que se recogen datos de 50 pacientes con isquemiacrítica de la extremidad tratados únicamente mediante angioplastia fémoro-poplítea, demanera consecutiva, entre los años 2006 y 2008.Resultados. El éxito técnico fue del 94 %. La tasa de salvamento de la extremidad fue del 75 % elprimer año, con una supervivencia libre de amputación del 60 %. Los factores predictores delsalvamento de la extremidad son: el número de troncos distales permeables hasta el pie(p = 0,007) y la situación clínica de la extremidad contralateral (p = 0,03).Conclusiones. En relación con estudios de características similares, se logra una aceptable tasade salvamento de la extremidad, por lo que constituye una opción terapéutica a considerar(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;62(3): 103-109, mayo-jun. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83200</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados clínicos del tratamiento endovascular sobre el sector fémoro-poplíteo en pacientes con isquemia crítica de la extremidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7678^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d686^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30853^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36500</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6590</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
