<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125843</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cholelithiasis in children. Report of 51 new cases and literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: With an overall prevalence of 0,13 to 1,9% in pediatric patients, gallstone disease differs from adult. Aim: To analyzed several epidemiological, clinical, diagnostic, etiologic and therapeutic aspects of this disease in our area and revise available casuistry. Method: Retrospective review of gallstone disease recorded at Jerez de la Frontera Hospital (Cádiz, Spain) between 1994 to 2011 in patients &lt;14 years of age. Patients &amp;#8804;24 months of age were analyzed separately. Results: Fifty-one patients with cholelithiasis were diagnosed in our department between 1994 and 2011 (29 male and 22 female). Idiophatic gallstone were found in 39.2%, infectious disease with or without antibiotic use in 35.2%, hemolytic disease, obesity, dyslipidemia or family history in 5.8% respectively. 64.7% were symptomatic and 13.7% had complicated disease (choledocholithiasis with cholestasis as more often). Conclusions: The therapeutic strategies were extremely heterogeneous. It depends on age, lithogenic disease, symptomatic and/or complicated disease associated (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Tardío, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Barrera, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio Santiago, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quirós Espigares, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La colelitiasis infantil, con una prevalencia entre el 0,13 y el 1,9%, cuenta con unas características propias que la diferencian de la enfermedad litiásica del adulto. Objetivos: Analizar los aspectos epidemiológicos, las formas de presentación clínica, los factores de riesgo asociados, las complicaciones y la terapéutica empleada en los casos de litiasis biliar infantil diagnosticados en nuestra área hospitalaria, así como revisar la casuística disponible. Método: Estudio retrospectivo de los casos de litiasis biliar diagnosticados entre los años 1994 y 2011 en el Hospital de Jerez de la Frontera (Cádiz). Los datos se han separado en &amp;#8804;24 o &gt;24 meses para su análisis. Resultados: Sumamos un total de 51 nuevos casos de litiasis biliar (29 varones y 22 mujeres). Un 39,2% de los casos fueron idiopáticos. Las infecciones con/sin uso de antibioterapia fueron el factor de riesgo asociado más frecuente (35,2%), seguido de la familiaridad, la enfermedad hemolítica, la obesidad o la dislipemia (en un 5,8% cada uno de ellos). El 64,7% de los pacientes presentó sintomatología, el 13,7% con formas complicadas, entre las cuales la coledocolitiasis con colestasis fue la más frecuente. Conclusiones: En más de la mitad de los casos encontramos algún factor de riesgo litogénico asociado, que, junto con la edad y la presencia de síntomas y/o complicaciones, determinan la actitud terapéutica en la mayoría de los casos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;72(6): e194-e201, jun. 2014. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125843</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Colelitiasis infantil: aportación de 51 nuevos casos y revisión bibliográfica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19612^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23190^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24011^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38038^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2829^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
