<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91002</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1582</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the results of fine needle aspiration (FNA) and core biopsy (CB) of breast lesions with pathologic diagnosis. Patients and methods: A retrospective, observational study of 144 patients in two years with FNA, CB and surgical specimen. Results: Pathological diagnosis of the 144 lesions were: 17 benign, 10 hyperplasia, 7 carcinoma in situ, 108 carcinoma and 2 others. In 2 of 17 benign cases, FNA and CB diagnosed carcinoma. These cases were treated with neoadjuvant chemotherapy with a complete response. In other case of hyperplasia in FNA and carcinoma in CB was totally excised by this technique. Ten of the 108 carcinomas were false negatives in CB (8 benign, 2 hyperplasia). In 4 cases FNA diagnosed carcinoma, 2 were suspicious of malignancy, 1 benign and in other there was no material for a diagnosis. In FNA there were 3 false negatives, 2 of them were diagnosed of carcinoma and benign by CB. The case diagnosed of benign by both techniques was a carcinoma arising in a mammary axillary gland. Conclusion: In this study the number of benign lesions is low because they were followed by image techniques. Also there are few hyperplasias and carcinomas in situ which are diagnosed by mammography for microcalcifications and they do not have cytological study. In the cases studied, FNA and CB are complementary techniques for the diagnosis of breast lesions(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Cid, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Masana, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fabra, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Travé, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pizarro, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Valorar los resultados de la punción aspiración con aguja fina (PAAF) y la biopsia por punción (BPP) de lesiones mamarias con estudio anatomopatológico de la pieza quirúrgica. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio retrospectivo y observacional de 144 pacientes durante dos años con PAAF, BPP y pieza quirúrgica. Resultados: Del total de 144 lesiones el diagnóstico anatomopatológico fue: 17 de benigno, 10 de hiperplasia, 7 de carcinomas in situ, 108 de carcinoma y 2 otros. En 2 de los 17 casos benignos la PAAF y la BPP diagnosticaron un carcinoma. Eran casos sometidos a quimioterapia neoadyuvante con respuesta total. En otro caso de hiperplasia por PAAF y carcinoma por BPP, la lesión se extirpó en su totalidad con esta técnica. De los 108 carcinomas, 10 casos fueron falsos negativos por BPP. En 8 el diagnóstico fue benigno y en 2 de hiperplasia. En 4 casos la PAAF indicó un carcinoma, en 2 fue sospechosa, 1 benigna y en otra no se obtuvo material celular. En la PAAF se detectaron 3 falsos negativos. En 2 de ellos la BPP diagnosticó carcinoma y en otro benignidad. El caso que fue diagnosticado de benigno por ambas técnicas era un carcinoma en glándula mamaria axilar. Conclusión: En el estudio hay un número bajo de lesiones benignas controladas por imagen y de hiperplasias y carcinomas in situ al no tener citología por presentarse con microcalcificaciones. En la casuística analizada, la PAAF y la BPP son técnicas complementarias para el diagnóstico de lesiones mamarias(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. senol. patol. mamar. (Ed. impr.);24(3): 95-99, 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91002</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados de la punción aspiración con aguja fina y la biopsia por punción con estudio anatomopatológico definitivo  en lesiones mamarias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d38338^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38338^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33861^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33861^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38338^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33861^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7144^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2148^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7144^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2148^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38338^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201100</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
