<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139754</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Maxillary sinus augmentation with bovine hydroxyapatite alone: A safe technique with predictable outcomes in patients with severe maxillary atrophy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Sinus augmentation is a preprosthetic technique for rehabilitating posterior sector of the atrophied maxilla with implant-supported prosthesis. We retrospectively analyzed 34 consecutive sinus augmentations performed using only bovine hydroxyapatite. The presurgical height in 92% of the cases was 4 mm or less. The success rate of the maxillary sinus augmentation was 100% for this technique. 13.4% of the implants were placed immediately with a success rate of implants placement of 93.9%. The non-osseointegrated implants were all successfully replaced. Follow-up period was 1268 days. The success rate obtained using bovine hydroxyapatite alone is similar to that using other types of materials, while avoids morbidity of the autologous bone donor area (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ochandiano Caicoya, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López López, Ana María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salmerón Escobar, José Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Planells del Pozo, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maza Muela, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Cuéllar, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La elevación del seno es una técnica preprotésica para la rehabilitación del sector posterior atrofiado del maxilar con una prótesis de implantación. Analizamos retrospectivamente 34 casos consecutivos de elevación del seno maxilar con el empleo de tan solo hidroxiapatita bovina sola. La altura prequirúrgica era de 4 mm o menos en el 92% de los casos. El porcentaje de éxitos de la elevación del seno maxilar con esta técnica fue del 100%. Un 13,4% de los implantes se colocaron inmediatamente, con un porcentaje de éxitos de la implantación del 93,9%. Los implantes no osteointegrados se sustituyeron todos con éxito. El periodo de seguimiento fue de 1268 días. El porcentaje de éxitos obtenido con el empleo de hidroxiapatita bovina sola es similar al de otros tipos de materiales, al tiempo que se evita la morbilidad en el área donante de hueso autólogo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;37(2): 87-92, abr.-jun. 2015. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139754</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Elevación del seno maxilar con hidroxiapatita bovina sola: Una técnica segura con resultados predecibles en pacientes con atrofia maxilar grave</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3771^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d541^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24600^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33348^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31497^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
