<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156178</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Large pterygium surgery: When coverage of the scleral bed justifies graft rotation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To perform a 12 month follow-up study to assess the safety and effectiveness of resection and conjunctival autograft fixed with Tissucol® in selected cases of large pterygium. The orientation of the graft was adapted to the morphology of the scleral bed for a better coverage free of traction, with limbal position being lost. Methods: A prospective, non-comparative study of 10 cases of grade II or superior pterygium (7 primary, 3 recurrent) with at least 8mm of limbal extension. A wide scleral bed was obtained after pterygium and Tenon resection, with larger grafts being required to cover the defects. A superior conjunctival autograft was harvested and fixed to bare sclera using Tissucol. The orientation was adapted to the morphology of the scleral bed and limbal position was lost. Patients were periodically assessed for recurrence and complications for a period of 12 months. Results: Minor complications occurred in 4 eyes. In one case a buttonhole was formed during dissection of the graft. Two presented with small limbal dehiscence, but epithelialisation was completed in the first week. In a third case, it was necessary to increase topical corticosteroids for pyogenic granuloma on the donor site, with secondary increased intraocular pressure (IOP). There were no recurrences after 12 months follow-up. Conclusions: A conjunctival graft of appropriate size adapted to the morphology of the scleral bed to ensure good coverage free of tension, provides good surgical results in selected cases of pterygium, regardless of the conservation the limbal orientation, with no recurrences after one year follow-up (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gargallo Benedicto, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olate Pérez, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Pérez, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Duch Samper, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Betancur Delgado, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cerdà Ibáñez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la eficacia y seguridad de la resección y autoinjerto conjuntival adherido con Tissucol® en casos seleccionados de pterigión de gran tamaño en los que la orientación del injerto se adapta a la morfología del lecho escleral para una mejor cobertura libre de tracción, perdiendo la orientación limbo-limbo, con un seguimiento de 12 meses. Método: Estudio prospectivo, no comparativo, de 10 casos de pterigión grado II o superior (7 primarios, 3 recurrentes) con al menos 8mm de extensión limbar. Después de la resección de la lesión se obtuvo un lecho escleral amplio, con necesidad de injerto grande para cubrir el defecto. Se disecó el autoinjerto conjuntival superior y se fijó a esclera mediante Tissucol®, adaptando la orientación a la morfología del lecho, perdiéndose la posición limbar. Se realizó seguimiento periódico de la recurrencia y complicaciones durante un año. Resultados: Se registraron complicaciones menores en 4 ojos. En un caso se formó un ojal al tallar el injerto. Dos presentaron una pequeña dehiscencia limbar, que epitelizó completamente durante la primera semana. En otro caso fue necesario aumentar los corticosteroides tópicos por granuloma piógeno en la zona donante, con aumento secundario de la presión intraocular (PIO). No hubo ningún caso de recurrencia después de 12 meses de seguimiento. Conclusiones: Un injerto conjuntival de tamaño adecuado adaptado a la morfología del lecho escleral que asegure una buena cobertura libre de tensiones proporciona buenos resultados quirúrgicos en casos de pterigión seleccionados, independientemente de la conservación de la orientación limbo-limbo, sin recidivas tras un año de seguimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;91(10): 469-474, oct. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156178</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cirugía del gran pterigión: cuando la cobertura del lecho justifica la rotación del injerto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6531</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14573^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3252^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21053^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3252^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3253^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13911^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13889^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21053^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13889^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
