<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162535</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-695X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Upper extremity pain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present the case of a 25-year-old woman with sudden onset pain in upper extremity. Acute peripheral arterial ischemia is the sudden interruption of the blood flow to an extremity, characterized by the appearance of intense pain, pallor, skin coldness, functional impairment, together with absence of distal pulses. It is a life-threatening emergency that requires early treatment of revascularization of the affected artery. The diagnosis of acute ischemia is based on clinical history review and physical examination. The severity of the clinical picture will be determined by the degree of obstruction, speed of onset, location, and presence of collateral circulation. Horner syndrome (oculosympathetic paresis) is characterized by the classic triad of palpebral ptosis, pupillary miosis and ipsilateral facial anhidrosis. The syndrome results from the interruption of sympathetic innervation to the eye and adnexa at various levels. It is a rare complication of cervical surgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Cano, Víctor Alexander</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Coronado, Jeny</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos el caso de una mujer de 25 años que consulta por dolor en miembro superior izquierdo de inicio súbito. La isquemia arterial periférica aguda es la interrupción brusca del aporte sanguíneo a una extremidad, caracterizado por la aparición de dolor intenso, palidez, frialdad cutánea, impotencia funcional, junto con ausencia de pulsos distales. Se trata de una urgencia vital que requiere tratamiento precoz de permeabilización de la arteria afectada. El diagnóstico de isquemia aguda se basa en la historia clínica y la exploración física. La gravedad del cuadro estará determinada por el grado de obstrucción, velocidad de instauración, localización y la existencia de circulación colateral. El síndrome de Horner (oculo-simpatoparesis) consiste en la clásica triada de ptosis palpebral, miosis pupilar y anhidrosis facial ipsilateral. El síndrome resulta tras la interrupción de la inervación simpática del ojo y de los anexos oculares a diferentes niveles, siendo una complicación poco frecuente de la cirugía cervical (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. clín. med. fam;10(1): 46-50, feb. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162535</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dolor en miembro superior</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7678^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30742^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14312^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28095^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36501^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d794^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d794^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
