<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76953</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Valuation of non-invasive tests to detect Helicobacter pylori infection in children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Helicobacter pylori infection is often acquired during childhood. Our objective was to determine the effectiveness and reliability of a rapid antigen test of H. pylori in faeces as an alternative to the breath test in children (criteria of non invasive reference).Patients and methods: The patients enrolled where children with suggestive symptoms of H. pylori infection who were attended in our service from June 2006 to April 2007. Tests of rapid detection of antibodies of immunoglobulin G versus H. pylori had been performed, breath test and rapid antigen test of H. pylori in faeces. Results: Our sample included a total of 94 children, 57% female; mean age 10.4 ± 2.9 years (2-16). By means of a breath test 39 (41.5%) of the children were infected with H. pylori. The faeces test diagnosed 28 (30%) infected children and serology showed 40 (42.5%). The overall sensitivity and specificity of the faeces test were of 54% and 87% and 74% and 80% for the serology test. The children were arranged in different groups of age 8 children less than 6 years old, 61 with ages between 7-12 years of age and 25 children above 12 years old. For the faeces test sensitivity it was 75, 57 and 29% and specificity was 100, 81 and 94%, for these three age groups respectively. Serology sensitivity was 50, 82 and 57%, respectively, and the specificity was 50, 82 and 83%.Conclusions: The faeces test sensitivity in our study is less than the results of prior publications. In our children population the faeces test is more specific than sensitive and it is more sensitive in younger children. The serological test is more sensitive and specific in children &gt;6 years old (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Húber, L. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Sánchez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo Medina, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendiola, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La infección por Helicobacter pylori se adquiere frecuentemente durante la infancia. Nuestro objetivo era determinarla eficacia y la fiabilidad del test rápido de detección del antígeno de H. pylori en heces como alternativa al test del aliento en niños (gold standard no invasivo).Pacientes y métodos: Se incluyeron pacientes con clínica sugerente remitidos a nuestra consulta entre junio de 2006 y abril de 2007. Se realizaron test de detección rápida de anticuerpos IgG frente a H. pylori, test del aliento y detección rápida del antígeno de H. pylori en heces. Resultados: Nuestra muestra fue de 94 pacientes (un 57% eran niñas), con una media de edad de 10,4 ± 2,9 años (rango:2-16). Mediante test del aliento, 39 niños (41,5%) fueron diagnosticados de infección actual. El test de detección en heces diagnosticó a 28 pacientes (30%) y la serología a 40 (42,5%). La sensibilidad y la especificidad del test de heces fueron del 54 y el 87%, y para el test serológico del 74 y el 80%, respectivamente. La distribución de los niños según grupos de edad fue la siguiente: 8 menores de 6 años, 61 de entre 7 y 12 años, y 25 mayores de 12 años. Para el test en heces la sensibilidad fue del 75, 57 y 29%, y la especificidad del 100, 81 y 94%, respectivamente para cada grupo. Para la serología, la sensibilidad fue del 50, 82 y 57%, y la especificidad del 50, 82 y 83%, respectivamente. Conclusiones: La sensibilidad del test de detección en heces resultó inferior a la publicada previamente. En nuestra población, este test es más específico que sensible, y es más sensible  cuanto menor es la edad del paciente. El test serológico resultó ser más sensible y específico en los niños &gt;6 años (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;67(7): 319-324, jul. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76953</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración de los test no invasivos en el diagnóstico de la infección por «Helicobacter pylori» en niños</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29157^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30037</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5346</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29156</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29157^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29157^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29157</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22669</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200907</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
