<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048759</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characteristics of status epilepticus in MELAS. Analysis of four cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Clinical characteristics of status epilepticus (SE) as a first manifestation in patients with MELAS who had not previously epileptic episode has been studied little in the literature.Objectives. Our aim was to analyse precipitating factors, clinical characteristics, EEG and difficulties in the treatment of SE in MELAS.Patients and methods. We studied four cases with ages between 27 an 41 years who began with SE and they had been diagnosed with MELAS during the episode. Case 3 was confirmed by autopsy. Cases 1, 2 and 4 showed a 3243 mtDNA mutation in the lymphocytes. Epileptic seizures had not been present in any previous status case. The precipitating factor in cases 1 and 3 was fever and in case 2 and 4 stress by headache. Moreover in case 2 second status was caused by stress in hyperglycaemic ketoacidosis. AlI cases were studied with EEG and a brain CT or MRI.Results. All patients started with epilepsia partialis continua that began with partial motor simple seizures, but sometimes progressed to partial complex seizures or secondary tonic clonic seizures. In two cases the initial symptom was migraine with aura, in two cases fever with cephalalgia and in one case diabetes mellitus decompensation. The EEG during a seizure presented a complex pseudoperiodic complex in the temporal-occipital contralateral region that spread to all hemisphere when myoclonus was increased.Conclusions. SE in MELAS appears in cell stress situation precipitated by hypermetabolic conditions and it provokes claudication in ill mitochondria. In fact, events such as fever, glycemic alterations, hypoxemia or headache that could change the normal mechanism of sequester mitochondrial calcium in the neuron are able to trigger SE. Optimal evolution depends on an improvement of basal metabolic conditions that could precipitate the status. Supplementary folic acid, riboflavin and coenzyme Q 10 can be useful</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribacoba, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salas-Puig, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Astudillo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El estado de mal epiléptico (EE) como primera manifestación en pacientes con MELAS que previamente no habían tenido crisis epilépticas ha sido escasamente analizado en la literatura.Objetivos. Nuestro propósito ha sido analizar los factores precipitantes, las características electroclínicas y las dificultades en el tratamiento del EE en el MELAS.Pacientes y métodos. Analizamos cuatro casos diagnosticados de MELAS, con edades comprendidas entre 27 y 41 años, que se inician con un EE y son diagnosticados de MELAS durante el episodio. El diagnóstico se realizó en los casos 1, 2 Y 4 analizando en una muestra de sangre periférica el ADN mitocondrial, obteniéndose en todos ellos la mutación 3243 en el ADN linfocitario. El caso 3 se confirmó por necropsia. Ninguno de los pacientes había presentado crisis epilépticas previamente. El factor desencadenante en los casos 1 y 3 fue la fiebre, mientras que los casos 2 y 4 se asociaron a migraña con aura. El estrés provocado por la hiperglucemia cetoacidótica desencadenó el segundo episodio en el caso 2. Todos los casos fueron estudiados con EEG, TC o RM craneal.Resultados. Clínica mente todos los pacientes empezaron con una epilepsia parcial continua que comenzó con crisis parciales motoras simples, pudiendo progresar a crisis parciales complejas o a crisis tonicoclónicas secundariamente generalizadas. En dos ocasiones se asoció a migraña con aura, en dos casos a fiebre con cefalea y en uno a descompensación diabética. El EEG durante las crisis mostraba complejos seudoperiódicos en la región temporo-occipital que se difundían a todo el hemisferio o contra lateralmente cuando se incrementaban las mioclonías.Conclusiones. El EE en el MELAS aparece en situaciones de estrés celular, desencadenado por situaciones hipermetabólicas que hacen claudicar a las mitocondrias enfermas. De esta manera efectos como fiebre, alteraciones de la glucemia o crisis migrañosas que puedan modificar el mecanismo habitual de secuestro del calcio mitocondrial en la neurona son capaces de desencadenarlo. El pronóstico dependerá en parte de la mejoría de las condiciones metabólicas basa les que lo han precipitado</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;21(1): 1-11, ene.-feb. 2006. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048759</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características del estado del mal epiléptico en MELAS. Análisis de cuatro casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30661^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4641</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30661^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30661^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24895</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13612^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13612^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30661^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1352</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
