<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108096</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5187</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Shiitake dermatitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Shiitake dermatitis was first described in 1977 in Japan by Nakamura and takes place after the intake of little cooked or raw shiitake mushrooms in certain persons. This condition is very characteristic for the presence of papules, plaques or vesicles, scattered highly pruritic that adopt a linear or flagellate disposal. We present a man of 38 years, submitted by pruritic eruption of 3 days duration, after questioning admitted some mushrooms eaten in a Chinese restaurant (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Manresa, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Río, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fraile Alonso, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viguri Díaz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez de Salinas, AM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almeida Llamas, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La dermatitis por shiitake fue descrita por primera vez en 1977 en Japón por Nakamura, y se desarrolla tras la ingesta de setas shiitake poco cocinadas o crudas en determinadas personas. Esta dermatitis es muy característica por la presencia de pápulas, placas o vesículas muy pruriginosas diseminadas que adoptan una disposición lineal o flagelada. Presentamos un varón de 38 años, remitido por erupción pruriginosa de 3 días de evolución, tras el interrogatorio reconoció haber comido unas se tasen un restaurante chino (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. cután. ibero-lat-am;40(6): 181-183, nov.-dic. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108096</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dermatitis shiitake</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30506^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5651^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28182^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34142</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
