<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96403</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The mediating role of self-regulation in cigarette smoking and alcohol use among young people</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This research explores the role of self-regulation in substance-use behaviours from a developmental perspective. We explore the influence of the peer group and parental competencies on self-regulation, in relation to substance use in young people, by means of two convenience samples, the first comprising 478 participants aged 10 to 20, the majority of whom were female, and the second made up of 311 youngsters aged 10 to 17, the majority being male. The instruments used were a Sociodemographic Questionnaire (ad hoc), a Smoking and Alcohol Use Questionnaire (ad hoc), the Adolescent Self-Regulatory Inventory &#150; brief version (ASRI-2r), the Parental Competencies Scale and the Peer Relations Questionnaire. The results confirm a relationship between gender and long-term self-regulation, whose level is higher among girls and young women. Those youngsters with friends who smoke or regularly drink alcohol score lower on the short-term self-regulation subscales. A moderate positive relationship is confirmed between long-term self-regulation and positive competencies in parents (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García del Castillo-López, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-del-Castillo, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Pérez, Julián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dias, Paulo César</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Esta investigación estudia el papel de la auto-regulación en los comportamientos de consumo, desde una perspectiva del desarrollo. Se explora la influencia del grupo de iguales y las competencias de los padres en la auto-regulación, en relación con el consumo de sustancias en jóvenes, mediante dos muestras de conveniencia, la primera compuesta por 478 jóvenes con edades comprendidas entre los 10 y los 20 años, siendo la mayoría del género femenino, y la segunda formada por 311 jóvenes, con edades comprendidas entre los 10 y los 17 años, siendo la mayoría del género masculino. Se utilizó un Cuestionario Sociodemográfico (ad hoc), un Cuestionario de consumo de tabaco y alcohol (ad hoc), el Inventario de Auto-regulación en la Adolescencia - versión reducida (IARA-2r), la Escala de Competencias de los Padres y el Cuestionario de Relación de Pareja. Los resultados confirman la existencia de una relación entre género y auto-regulación a largo plazo, más elevada en el género femenino. Los jóvenes con compañeros que fuman o consumen alcohol regularmente, presentan puntuaciones más bajas en las subescalas de auto-regulación a corto plazo. Se confirma una relación positiva moderada entre la auto-regulación a largo plazo y las competencias positivas de los padres (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;28(1): 1-10, ene.-abr. 2012. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96403</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El papel mediador de la auto-regulación en el consumo de tabaco y alcohol en población joven</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10538^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10538^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10538^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10538^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10538^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
