<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61963</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4603</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Manifestations of aphasia in Galician. Preliminary finding from Galician-Spanish bilingual patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present data from a preliminary study of manifestationsof aphasia in Galician, a language thatis spoken mainly in Galicia, N.W. of Spain. 17aphasic patients who are bilingual in Spanish(Castilian) and Galician participated in the studyand they were evaluated by the Bilingual AphasiaTest (BAT). Wilcoxon tests were carried out onfluency in spontaneous speech, comprehension ofcomplex commands, phonology (Verbal AuditoryDiscrimination and Repetition of Words), lexicon(Lexical Decision), morphology (Derivational Morphologyand Morphological Opposites) and syntax(Syntactic Comprehension, Grammaticality Judgments,Sentence Construction Correctness andSentence Construction Sense). Special attentionwas paid to the difficulties in understanding sentenceswith clitic pronouns, passives, negativesand topicalized subjects or objects. Results showeda similar performance on all the BAT subtests forthe two languages. In phonology the phonemicparaphasias that were produced respected the phonotacticrules of Galician. In syntax the sentencetypes that were worst understood relative to standardactive sentences were negative, the sentenceswith topicalized objects and those with cliticpronouns. These findings are discussed in relationto the main theories of agrammatism(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pereiro, AX</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Souto, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juncos-Rabadán, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presentan datos de un estudio preliminar sobre las manifestaciones de la afasia en gallego, una lenguahablada principalmente en el noroeste deEspaña. Participaron 17 pacientes afásicos bilingüesque hablaban gallego y castellano, evaluados con elTest de afasia en bilingües (BAT). Se analizó (testde Wilcoxon) el rendimiento en fluidez en el lenguajeespontáneo, comprensión de órdenes complejas,fonología (discriminación auditiva verbal yrepetición de palabras), léxico (decisión léxica),morfología (morfología derivacional y opuestosmorfológicos) y sintaxis (comprensión sintáctica,juicios de gramaticalidad, corrección en construcciónde oraciones y sentido en la construcción deoraciones) comparando especialmente el rendimientoen oraciones activas positivas, pasivas,negativas, oraciones con pronombres clíticos y oracionescon topicalización del sujeto y del objeto.Los resultados indicaron que el rendimiento entodos los subtest del BAT era similar para ambaslenguas. En fonología se producían parafasias fonémicaspero respetando las reglas fonotácticas delgallego. En sintaxis las oraciones que peor se comprendían,en relación a las activas estándar, fueronlas negativas, las oraciones con topicalización delobjeto y las que llevaban pronombres clíticos. Sediscuten estos resultados en relación a las principalesteorías del agramatismo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. logop. foniatr. audiol. (Ed. impr.);29(1): 21-29, ene.-mar. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61963</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manifestaciones de la afasia en gallego. Datos preliminares de pacientes bilingües gallego-castellano</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1043^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33194</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7985</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1045^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7984^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
