<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147266</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Last minute in NBA games</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Apparently the behavior during a basketball game, as in other team sports, shows tremendous variability manifested in both individual and collective ways. However, when a significant number of games are studied, we can observe the unpredictability that characterizes the game. The degree of complexity of the game is not stable. Patterns change during all the game time, but the last minute is completely different reality. Our aim was to test and evaluate the existence of these patterns and their apparent complexity, by analyzing the NBA games scoring and substitution dynamics. Therefore, we examined the difference between the last minute and the rest of the game from the collected scores (1, 2 and 3 points), substitutions and timeouts. The underlying chaotic behavior of nonlinear interactions is inherent in Complex Systems. The data showed the existence of symmetries and repeated patterns of play during basketball games of the NBA but the last minute, which can be considered a completely different game(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saá Guerra, Yves de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Manso, Juan Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valverde, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín González, Juan Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Aparentemente, el comportamiento del juego durante un partido de baloncesto, igual que en el resto de deportes de equipo, muestra una enorme variabilidad que se manifiesta tanto en las acciones individuales y en las colectivas. No obstante, cuando se estudia una cantidad significativa de partidos se detecta que, dentro de la impredecibilidad que caracteriza al juego, existen, al menos en el baloncesto NBA, patrones de comportamiento repetitivos que, frecuentemente, son libres de escala. El grado de complejidad del juego no es estable. Diferentes investigaciones muestran como los patrones cambian entre el primer y segundo tiempo del partido, así como, primer y tercer cuarto respecto al segundo y cuarto, o la parte inicial, mitad o final de cada cuarto. Nuestro objetivo fue comprobar y evaluar la existencia de estos patrones, y su aparente complejidad, analizando el final de los partidos de la NBA y comparando esta fase del encuentro con el final de cada uno de los cuartos. Los datos muestran la existencia de simetrías (fractalidad) y patrones repetidos de juego durante los partidos de baloncesto de la NBA (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;24(supl.1): 31-35, 2015. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147266</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Último mínuto en los partidos de la NBA</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32415^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32415^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34600^s22082</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34600^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32415^s22082</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34600^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34600^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32415^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
