<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-65192</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: To analize and compare differences in patients older than 80 years with Community acquired Pneumonia admitted in Internal Medicine or Pneumology of a General Hospital from the Emergency Room. Material and methods: Retrospective study of all the 277 patients above 80 years admitted into the Hospital in 2005 with the main diagnosis of Pneumonia. Results: 84% community-acquired, 16% from Institutions. Mean age: 85.8 y (48% men, 52% women). 19% FINE-3, 49% FINE-4, 32% FINE-5. Known etiology: 25% (Pneumococcal 19%, H. Influenzae and other Gram (-) 6%. 75% treated by Internists, 22% treated by Pneumologists. Standard Guidelines followed up by 30,5% a variant 60% (Equal by Internists or Pneumologists). Time door-1st antibiotic dose 6.6 hours. Global Mortality 16.7%. Women died at 87.4 y, men at 84.5 y (p = 0.035). Mortality FINE 3-4-5: 4.5, 12.4, 30% respectively. Mortality treated before 4 hours: 34.6%, after 4 hours: 11.5% (p = 0.01). Many more FINE 5 cases in Int. Medicine than Pneumology. Mortality by Internists 22%. Mortality by Pneumologists 3% (p = 0.001). Mortality similar following strict guidelines or variant. Conclusions: a) Internist receive patients sicker than Pneumologists ; b) Important mortality in these very old patients of 16.7%, and progressive according the FINE severiy index, in spite of correct therapy; c) Rapid initiation of Antibiotics did not decreased mortality; d) Mortality did not change following strict or variant Guidelines; and e) There are areas of quality improvement in our Hospitals</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zubillaga Azpíroz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zubillaga Garmendia, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benavente Claveras, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Haya, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zamarreño Gómez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarasqueta Eizaguirre, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ceciaga Elexpuru, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: analizar y comparar diferencias en pacientes mayores de 80 años con Neumonía Adquirida en la Comunidad (NAC) como diagnóstico de alta en pacientes ingresados desde Urgencias a servicios de Medicina Interna (MEDIN) y Neumología (NEUMO) de un Hospital General. Material y métodos: análisis retrospectivo de todos los 277 pacientes mayores de 80 años con ingreso hospitalario por NAC en el 2005. Resultados: 84% Comunitarios. 16% de Instituciones. Edad media: 85,8 años (52% mujeres). Severidad: 19% FINE-3. 49% FINE-4. 32%FINE-5. Etiología conocida 25% (Neumocócica 19%, H. Influenzae y otros Gram (-) 6%). 75% trata MEDIN, 22% NEUMO. Guías Clínicas de tratamiento estrictas 30&#146;5%, una variante 60% (Igual en MEDIN que en NEUMO). Tiempo puerta-1ª dosis antibiótico fue de 6,6 horas. Mortalidad:16,7%. Edad fallecidos mujeres: 87,4 a. mayor que hombres: 84,5a. (p = 0,035). Mortalidad FINE-3-4-5: 4,5, 12,4, 30% respectivamente. Mortalidad tratados antes de 4 horas: 34,6%, después de 4 horas: 11,5% (p = 0,01). Mucho más FINE-5 en MEDIN que en NEUMO. Mortalidad MEDIN: 22%, Mortalidad NEUMO: 3% (p = 0,001). Mortalidad igual siguiendo la Guía Clínica o variante. Conclusiones: a) MEDIN recibe pacientes más graves que NEUMO; b) mortalidad importante (16,7%) y progresiva en la escala FINE, a pesar de tratamiento correcto; c) la rápida administración de antibióticos no redujo la mortalidad; d) la mortalidad no varía aún con variantes de las Guías Clínicas; y c) hay areas de mejora en nuestros Servicios</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;25(3): 117-121, mar. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-65192</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11447^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11447^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28319^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28319^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
