<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101912</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Irrigation by negative pressure: Endovac to a case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There are a lot of techniques of irrigation that exist directed to obtaining free Canals of bacteria. At the end of 2004, one new irrigation technique is introduced; irrigation for negative pressure. It consists of depositing the irrigant in the pulpar chamber, and this one, by means of  a system introduced to length or work, is inhaled, favoring the cleaning in the apical third, and reducing the risks of extrusion of the sodium hypochlorite. Later we will explain held up this technique, and by means of the exhibition of a clinical case we will explain the clinical sequence of the Endovac ®, system patented by D iscus Dental, which uses as boss of irrigation the negative pressure (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín Escorial, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estévez Luaña, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gregorio González, C. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre de la Fuente, F de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aranguren Cangas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cisneros Cabello, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Son muchas las técnicas de irrigación que existen encaminadas a conseguir conductos libres de bacterias. A finales del 2004, una nueva técnica de irrigación es introducida: irrigación por presión negativa. Consiste en depositar el irrigante en la cámara pulpar, y éste, mediante un sistema introducido a longitud de trabajo, es aspirado, favoreciendo la limpieza en el tercio apical, reduciendo los riesgos de extrusión del hipoclorito de sodio al periápice. A continuación expondremos detenidamente esta técnica y mediante la exposición de un caso clínico explicaremos la secuencia clínica del Endova® sistema patentado por la casa Discus Dental, que emplea como patrón de irrigación, la presión negativa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);29(1): 19-26, ene.-mar. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101912</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Irrigación mediante presión negativa: Endovac, a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32617^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13358^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27987^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7674^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
