<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122149</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Social-health characteristics of subjects who make a living will</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The Living Will (LW) is well publicised, and still largely unknown to the general public and health professionals. Objective: To describe the characteristics of the subjects that formalize a LW related to sociodemographic situation, health status, degree of dependence, healthcare characteristics and psychosocial aspects. Method: Descriptive observational study conducted in the Health Area of Albacete including 123 people who formalized the LW in a Will Register in 2011. Study variables included: selfperceived health, functional status, morbidity, socio-demographic characteristics, use of health services, attitudes towards the LW, and psychosocial aspects. Results: Those that made an LW, were mainly women (64.2%), had a mean age of 53.3 years (SD: 14.5), higher levels of education (61% with at least secondary education), and a lifestyle other than living with a partner, and with children (67.5%). The majority were self-sufficient  for their daily living activities (98.4% to 94.3% for basic and instrumental), and suffered from chronic disease (73.2%). Despite lasting relationships with their physicians (9.4 years; SD: 7.9), there was very little talk about the end of life (18.3%). More than a half had a family member who had previously signed a document (54.5%). More than two-thirds (68.5%) considered this document useful in the death of a relative, and also a 56.7% had also served as a caregiver of a terminal patient. Conclusions: Middle-aged people, predominantly women, formalized an LW most often. They are usually chronic, but self-sufficient for their daily living activities, and are convinced that they can influence their health situation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gil, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Torres, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Simarro, M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rabanales, Joseba</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pozo, Katia del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El documento de voluntades anticipadas (DVA) cuenta con muy escasa difusión, siendo un gran desconocido para la población general y para los profesionales sanitarios. Objetivo: Describir las características de los sujetos que formalizan el DVA, referidas a la situación sociodemográfica, estado de salud y grado de dependencia, características de la atención sanitaria y aspectos psicosociales. Método: Estudio observacional descriptivo realizado en el Área Sanitaria de Albacete a 123 personas que formalizaron el DVA en un registro de voluntades anticipadas durante 2011. Se recogieron variables de salud autopercibida, situación funcional, morbilidad, características sociodemográficas, utilización de servicios sanitarios, actitudes hacia el DVA y aspectos psicosociales. Resultados: Los otorgantes, predominantemente mujeres (64,2%), presentaban una edad media de 53,3 a&#152;nos (desviación estándar [DE]: 14,5), niveles de instrucción elevados (61% con al menos estudios secundarios) y formas de convivencia diferentes a vivir en pareja y con hijos (67,5%). Mayoritariamente eran independientes para actividades de la vida diaria (98,4% para básicas y 94,3% para instrumentales) y presentaban alguna enfermedad crónica (73,2%). Pese a mantener relaciones duraderas con sus médicos (9,4 a&#152;nos; DE: 7,9), las conversaciones sobre el final de la vida eran escasas (18,3%). El 54,5% tenía algún familiar que había formalizado un documento previamente, el 68,5% lo consideraba útil ante el fallecimiento de un allegado y el 56,7% había ejercido como cuidador de algún enfermo terminal. Conclusiones: Personas de mediana edad y predominantemente mujeres son las que con mayor frecuencia formalizan un DVA. Suelen ser pacientes crónicos, independientes para realizar actividades de la vida diaria y, en su mayoría, están convencidos de poder intervenir en su situación de salud (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);40(3): 128-133, abr. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122149</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características sociosanitarias de quienes formalizan el documento de voluntades anticipadas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28849^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5703^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3487</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29008^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
