<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046676</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Autosomal dominant compelling helio-ophthalmic outburst syndrome (photic sneeze reflex). Clinical study of six Spanish families</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Sneeze is an ubiquitous phenomenon that happens to everyone. In spite of this, little attention has been paid to it, among medical literature in general, and even less in neurologic texts. A curious entity, called autosomal dominant compelling helio-ophthalmic outburst syndrome, has been scarcely described in the scientific literature. This reflex appears when subjects are exposed suddenly to intense sunlight and it consists of long incoercible sneeze bursts. There are no publications on this subject among the Spanish literature.    Objective. Io study the clinical and physiological features of the reflex in Spanish families.    Patients and method. Affected subjects were identified by personal interview and given a questionnaire drawn up for this study. Besides, they were instructed to give the questionnaire to their relatives.    Results. All the six families showed a high-penetrance, autosomal dominant inheritance. The reflex had a high consistency, a latency about 3 seconds, an intersneeze interval of 2 seconds and a frequency of 2-3 sneezes/burst. Refractory period was long.    Discussion. Our study suggest a higher consistency, shorter latency and lower age of onset of the reflex in our patients than general population, and that frequency and intensity increase with time</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gamero, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lucas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cid, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Moreno, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Páramo, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El estornudo es un fenómeno ubicuo que todo el mundo sufre, a pesar de lo cual ha recibido poca atención en la literatura médica en general y neurológica en particular. Una curiosa entidad, conocida como síndrome de estornudos heliooftálmicos compulsivo autosómico domi    nante (autosomal dominant compelling helio-ophthalmic    outburst syndrome), ha sido rara vez investigado de forma exhaustiva. Dicho reflejo consiste en la aparición de salvas de estornudos prolongadas e incoercibles en individuos expuestos súbitamente a la luz solar intensa. No existen referencias al tema en la literatura española.    Objetivo. Estudiar las características clínicas fisiológicas del reflejo en familias españolas.    Pacientes y método. Mediante una entrevista personal se detectaron sujetos que padecían el síndrome, a los cuales se les pasó un cuestionario elaborado al efecto y se les instruyó para que se lo pasaran al resto de la familia.    Resultados. Las seis familias estudiadas mostraron un patrón hereditario autosómico dominante con elevada penetrancia. El reflejo mostró una elevada consistencia, una latencia de unos 3 s, un intervalo interestornudo de 2 s, las salvas eran de dos-tres estornudas y el período refractario de unas 24 h.    Discusión. A diferencia de otros autores, nuestros encuestados refieren un reflejo con mayor consistencia, menor latencia y menor edad de aparición, que parece reforzarse con los años y cuya intensidad sonora es mayor que la del estornudo convencional</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;20(6): 276-282, jul.-ago. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046676</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de estornudos heliooftálmicos compulsivos autosómico dominante (reflejo fótico de estornudo). Estudio clínico de seis familias españolas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8203</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5939</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13293^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
