<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157300</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Development and pilot study of an essential set of indicators for general surgery services</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction:At present there is a lack of appropriate quality measures for benchmarking in general surgery units of Spanish National Health System. The aim of this study is to present the selection, development and pilot-testing of an initial set of surgical quality indicators for this purpose. Methods: A modified Delphi was performed with experts from the Spanish Surgeons Association in order to prioritize previously selected indicators. Then, a pilot study was carried out in a public hospital encompassing qualitative analysis of feasibility for prioritized indicators and an additional qualitative and quantitative three-rater reliability assessment for medical record-based indicators. Observed inter-rater agreement, prevalence adjusted and bias adjusted kappa and non-adjusted kappa were performed, using a systematic random sample (n = 30) for each of these indicators. Results: Twelve out of 13 proposed indicators were feasible: 5 medical record-based indicators and 7 indicators based on administrative databases. From medical record-based indicators, 3 were reliable (observed agreement &gt; 95%, adjusted kappa index &gt; 0.6 or non adjusted kappa index &gt; 0.6 for composites and its components) and 2 needed further refinement. Conclusions: Currently, medical record-based indicators could be used for comparison purposes, whilst further research must be done for validation and risk-adjustment of outcome indicators from administrative databases. Compliance results in the adequacy of informed consent, diagnosis-to-treatment delay in colorectal cancer, and antibiotic prophylaxis show room for improvement in the pilot-tested hospital (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martinez-Nicolas, Ismael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Angel-Garcia, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabezali Sanchez, Roger</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rebasa Cladera, Pere</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereira García, Luis Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soria-Aledo, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En la actualidad no se dispone de un conjunto adecuado de indicadores para benchmarking en las unidades de cirugía general del Sistema Nacional de Salud. Este trabajo presenta la selección, el desarrollo y los resultados del estudio piloto de un primer grupo de indicadores para esta finalidad. Métodos: Se realizó una selección y priorización de indicadores mediante un Delphi modificado con un grupo de expertos de la Asociación Española de Cirujanos. Los indicadores priorizados fueron sometidos a un estudio cualitativo de factibilidad y, para aquellos medidos por historia clínica, cuali-cuantitativo de fiabilidad en un hospital público. Se obtuvieron resultados de concordancia simple y estadístico kappa, ajustado y no ajustado por prevalencias y sesgos, para 3 evaluadores con un muestreo aleatorio sistemático de 30 casos por indicador. Resultados: De los 13 indicadores propuestos, 12 resultaron factibles (5 de historia clínica y 7 de bases de datos). De los 5 de historia, 3 resultaron fiables (concordancia interobservador &gt; 95% o índice kappa &gt; 0,6 para compuestos y subindicadores, o bien kappa ajustado por prevalencias y sesgos &gt; 0,6 en presencia de prevalencias extremas) y 2 necesitaron ser redefinidos a partir de los resultados obtenidos. Conclusiones: Los 5 indicadores de historia clínica podrán utilizarse para comparar unidades quirúrgicas, mientras que los 7 indicadores factibles de bases de datos necesitarán mayor validación y ajuste de riesgo para permitir comparaciones entre servicios. Los resultados del centro evaluado muestran áreas de mejora en algunos procesos de la atención (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);94(9): 502-510, nov. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157300</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desarrollo y estudio piloto de un conjunto esencial de indicadores para los servicios de cirugía general</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13885^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29453^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33549^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13883^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36300^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54376^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
