<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147173</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pediatric Extracorporeal Shock Wave Lithotripsy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Extracorporeal Shock Wave lithotripsy (ESWL) is the cornerstone of pediatric urolitiasis management. We evaluated its efficacy and complications in a series of children. Material and Methods. Children who were managed with ESWL between 2003 and 2012 were retrospectively reviewed. We studied etiology, clinical presentation, stonefree ratio and relevant complications. SPSS 17.0 software was used. Results.-90 children aged 0 to 10 years (median 2.9 years) were included in the study; that accounted for 122 stones and 162 ESWL sessions. Mean follow up was 20 months. Mean stone diameter was 12.2 mm. (range 4-25). Most prevalent clinical sign was urinary infection (55.6%, 50 patients). 75.4% of the lithiasis were found in renal pelvis or calices. A mean of 1.42 ESWL sessions per stone was performed. Stonefree status was reached in 80.3% (98) of the lithiasis. This rate was higher in patients below 5 years of age (86.1% vs., 69.8%, p=0.03), and worse in staghorn calculi (66% vs. 87.2%) and cystine ones (30% vs. 84.8%, p&lt; 0.001). We observed 17 complications (10.4% among 162 sessions), 6 UTIs, 6 episodes of fever and 6 episodes of UTI associated with steinstrasse. Almost all complications were associated with bigger size, staghorn calculi and struvite. Discussion. Best results are found in younger patients and small calculi. ESWL is a safe and efficient procedure in pediatric patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Ibieta, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alberola, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villavicencio, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caffaratti Sfulcini, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Corro, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonín, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bujons Tur, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La Litotricia Extracorpórea por Ondas de Choque (LEOC) constituye el pilar fundamental de la urolitiasis infantil. En este trabajo pretendemos objetivar la tasa de fragmentación y expulsión de cálculos mediante LEOC. Material y Métodos. Revisión retrospectiva de procedimientos de LEOC pediátricos, analizando etiología, clínica, tasa de éxito, factores asociados al mismo y complicaciones. Análisis: SPSS 17.0. Resultados. Se revisaron 90 niños (edad: 8 meses-10 años -mediana 2,9 años) que habían presentado 122 litiasis y precisaron 162 procedimientos de LEOC entre 2003 y 2012. Mediana de seguimiento: 20 meses. Diámetro medio del cálculo: 12,2 mm (rango 4-25 mm). La clínica más habitual fue Infección del Tracto Urinario (ITU) (55,6%, 50 niños). El 3,3% de los cálculos se localizaron en vejiga, el 21,3% en uréteres y el 75,4% en riñón. Se realizó una media de 1,41 LEOC por episodio litiásico. Se consiguió fragmentación y expulsión en el 80,3% (98) de los cálculos. Esta tasa fue mayor en niños menores de 5 años (86,1% vs. 69,8%, p=0,03) y en cálculos asociados a prematuridad y estancia prolongada en UCI (100% vs. 78,4%, p=0,19); y peor en cálculos coraliformes (66% vs. 87,2%, p=0,021), y en los de cistina (30% vs. 84,8%, p&lt; 0,001). Entre los 162 procedimientos, hubo 17 complicaciones (10,4%): (6 ITUs &#150;3,7%&#150;, y 5 ITUs asociadas a calle litiásica &#150;3%&#150;), todas relacionadas con cálculos grandes, coraliformes y/o de estruvita. Conclusión. Los mejores resultados en LEOC se objetivan en los pacientes de menor edad. La LEOC pediátrica es eficaz y segura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;28(2): 59-66, abr. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147173</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Litotricia extracorpórea en pacientes pediátricos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33180^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52133^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52124^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19612^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
