<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-70733</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Thyrotoxicosis factitia is defined as thyrotoxicosis resulting from exogenous ingestion of thyroid hormone, usually inpatients with a psychiatric disorder. Diagnosis can be difficult and this entity should be suspected in patients with highfree tiroxine (T4) concentrations, low or suppressed thyroglobulin concentrations, normal urinary iodide excretion and low or suppressed 131I uptake. To establish the differential diagnosis, thyrotoxicosisfactitia must be distinguished from several diseases with low 131I uptake, such as Graves&#146; disease, subacute thyroiditis, hyperthyroidism due to excessive iodineintake, struma ovarii and metastasis from thyroid cancer. Treatment is based on b blockers to reduce symptoms and avoidiatrogeny. We present a case of thyrotoxicosis factitia treated in our outpatient clinic (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Delgado del Rey, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Gallardo, Gema</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguirre Sánchez-Covisa, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La tirotoxicosis facticia se define como la causada por ingestión de hormona tiroidea exógena, normalmente en pacientes con trastornos psiquiátricos. El diagnóstico puede ser difícil y debemos sospecharla con concentraciones de tiroxina (T4) libre elevadas, tiroglobulina baja osuprimida, yoduria normal y gammagrafía con captación de 131I baja. Hay que hacer diagnóstico diferencial con otras causas de hipertiroidismo con gammagrafía con hipocaptación de 131I, como enfermedad de Graves, tiroiditis subagudas, struma ovarii, metástasis de cáncer de tiroides ehipertiroidismo inducido por yodo. El tratamiento se basa en bloqueadores beta para aminorar los síntomas y evitar riesgos iatrogénicos. Presentamos un caso de tirotoxicosis facticia atendida en nuestro servicio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;55(9): 436-438, nov. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-70733</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19366^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d322^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28071^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7160^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200811</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
