<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84581</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4008</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efectivity of antitransglutaminase antibodies IgA for the evaluation of gluten free diet in celiac patients. Evolution of hypertransaminasemia and iron deficiency</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze the validity of antitransglutaminase antibodies (tTGA) as a serological marker of response to the gluten-free diet (GFD) in celiac patients and to determine the outcome of hypertransaminasemia (HT) and ferropenia found at the time of diagnosis. Material and methods: We have retrospectively analyzed the data from 172 patients with celiac disease (CD) (141 children and 31 adults) following a GFD. We have collected clinical and diet information and also histological, biochemical and serological data. The tTGA was measured with a human recombinant antibody. Results: After a median follow-up time of 1.5 years in GFD, 114 (81%) of the children had normal levels of tTGA, 17 (12%) showed values in the &#145;&#145;grey zone&#146;&#146; and only 10 (7%) had elevated levels of this marker. This contrasts with the figures found in adults, corresponding to 15 (48.3%), 11 (33.5%) and 5 (17.2%), respectively. In our series we have performed 27 intestinal biopsies during follow-up (26 children and 1 adult). The concordance rate between the results of this biopsy and the tTGA determination was high, with a Kappa Index ¼ 0.898. We have detected dietary transgressions in 7 patients (4 occasional and 3 frequently) and 6 of these 7 patients showed high levels of tTGA. The GFD was correctly followed by children according to the international recommendations, but only 40% of the adults followed the GFD adequately. In both populations we have found a significant decrease in HTand normalization of the ferropenia found at diagnosis (Po0.001). Conclusions: tTGA is a useful indirect marker for evaluation of GFD in a pediatric population, with a high concordance between serum levels of the marker and histological findings in the intestinal biopsy. However, tTGA cannot substitute biopsy in cases of diet transgressions or unfavourable clinical evolution. In our environment it is still essential to increase the awareness of the adult population regarding the importance of diet in CD and also of the serious complications associated with untreated disease(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villanueva, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Criado, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguirregoicoa, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llorente, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sebastián, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: analizar la validez de los anticuerpos antitransglutaminasa (tTGA) como marcador de la respuesta a la dieta libre de gluten (DLG) en pacientes celíacos y valorar la evolución de la hipertransaminasemia (HT) y ferropenia detectadas en el diagnóstico. Material y métodos: se analiza a 172 celíacos (141 niños, 31 adultos) en DLG. Se realiza control dietético-clínico, histológico, serológico y bioquímico. La valoración de tTGA se realizó utilizando anticuerpo recombinante humano. Resultados: tras un período en DLG (mediana 18 meses), 114 (81%) niños mostraron concentración normal de tTGA, 17 (12%) se mantuvieron en la zona gris y 10 (7%), valores elevados. En adultos las frecuencias eran 15 (48,3%), 11 (33,5%) y 5 (17,2%). Se realizaron 27 biopsias intestinales (26 niños, 1 adulto). La concordancia histológica con la concentración de tTGA fue elevada; índice kappa = 0,898 (0,72¿0,98). Se detectan trasgresiones en 7 pacientes (4 ocasionales, 3 frecuentes), de los cuales 6 presentaron tTGA elevada. El control de la DLG se realizó conforme a las recomendaciones establecidas en los niños, mientras que el 30% de los adultos diagnosticados de EC carece del mismo. En ambas poblaciones observamos disminución significativa de la HT y normalización de la ferropenia detectada al diagnóstico (p&lt;0,001). Conclusiones: dado el acuerdo con los hallazgos histológicos, consideramos que la tTGA es un marcador indirecto útil para evaluar DLG al menos en población pediátrica. Sin embargo, no sustituye a la biopsia en casos de trasgresiones o de mala respuesta clínica. En nuestro medio es necesario concienciar al colectivo adulto de la importancia de la dieta y las complicaciones que conlleva su enfermedad sin tratar(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. lab. clín;1(3): 94-99, jul.-dic. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84581</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad de anticuerpos antitransglutaminasa IgA en la evaluación de la dieta sin gluten en pacientes celiacos. Evolución de la hipertransaminasemia y ferropenia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2481^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22202</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7582^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2481^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13078^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6127^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6127^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7576^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
