<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-168537</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Survey adaptation for bio-behavioural surveillance of HIV in Chilean female sex workers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To adapt a behavioural questionnaire for second-generation HIV/AIDS surveillance in female sex workers (FSWs) in the Metropolitan Region, Chile. Methods: Qualitative study of instruments validation. A Spanish instrument adapted in Catalonia was validated through a translation and back-translation of the original version. The content validity was determined through a modified Delphi method, via FSW and HIV experts representing community, political and institutional levels. Applicability aspects were determined by the application of the questionnaire to FSW in the Metropolitan Region. Results: The questionnaire, drafted in Spain, was successfully adapted to Chilean Spanish. The content validity process enabled sections to be created that address HIV in FSWs. The adapted questionnaire takes less than 15minutes to complete, which makes it usable in fieldwork. The 61 women surveyed came from different countries (all were Latin Americans) and had different educational levels; all this enabled potential applicability problems to be detected. Discussion: The adapted questionnaire for Chile contains all the UNAIDS indicators for FSWs, as well as the recommended indicators of Family Health International for bio-behavioural surveillance. Said questionnaire serves as a tool for second-generation HIV/other STD surveillance and further contributes to preventive policies in Chilean FSWs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carvajal, Bielka</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Folch, Cinta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manríquez, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Stuardo, Valeria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Belmar, Julieta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Adaptar un cuestionario conductual para la vigilancia de segunda generación del VIH/sida en mujeres trabajadoras sexuales (MTS) de la Región Metropolitana, Chile. Métodos: Estudio cualitativo de validación de instrumento. Se validó un cuestionario español adaptado en Cataluña (España) mediante traducción y retrotraducción del instrumento original. La validación de contenido se realizó a través de un grupo Delphi modificado, constituido por expertos en MTS y VIH, representantes de los ámbitos comunitario, político e institucional. Se evaluaron aspectos relacionados con la aplicabilidad del instrumento en terreno, encuestando a MTS de la Región Metropolitana. Resultados: El cuestionario, escrito en español de España, fue satisfactoriamente adaptado al español de Chile. En el proceso de validación de contenido se logró definir las secciones que abordan el VIH en la población MTS. El cuestionario adaptado tiene un tiempo de aplicación de menos de 15 minutos, por lo que es utilizable en terreno. Las 61 mujeres encuestadas presentan características diversas, tanto en país de origen (todas eran latinoamericanas) como en nivel de estudios, lo que permitió captar potenciales problemas en su aplicación. Discusión: El cuestionario adaptado para Chile contiene todos los indicadores para MTS recomendados por ONUSIDA, así como los recomendados por el Familly Health International para la vigilancia bioconductual. El instrumento definitivo emerge como una herramienta para la vigilancia de segunda generación del VIH y otras infecciones de transmisión sexual en Chile, y como un aporte al abordaje de políticas preventivas en la población de MTS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;31(6): 478-484, nov.-dic. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-168537</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación de una encuesta bioconductual para la vigilancia del VIH en mujeres trabajadoras sexuales chilenas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2722^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14567</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29172</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25783^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54843^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
