<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056386</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnosis and treatment of chronic urethritis in the Military health-care system with the change of the Century (XIX-XX)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: We can say that in military hospitals, pioneer institutions in health-care in our country,approximately 25% of the pathology over the second half of the 19th century would correspond to sexually transmitted diseases (STD), with hospital wards dedicated to these diseases, initially associated with genitourinary diseases. The "military drip" or blennorrhagic urethritis was a venereal disease with great incidence and prevalence in the pre-antibiotic era. This article reviews the diagnostic and therapeutic methods employed by Spanish military doctors during such period. METHODS: In the introduction we state the relationship between the knowledge of the time and the environment in which military doctors developed their professional activity. We make reference to military health-care journals, vehicle for their worries and demonstration of the level of theoretical and practical knowledge they were distinguished for. Based on their service records and publications we refer the urologists from the military health-care system that showed a greater interest in the field of urethral diseases, talking about the methodology they used for diagnosis and treatment of blennorrhagic urethritis. RESULTS AND CONCLUSIONS: Military health-care at the end of 18th century and the beginning of the 19th century joined a group of professionals who demonstrated talent and perseverance in the treatment of "military drip". To know the concepts for the diagnosis and treatment of urethritis improves our perspective in the knowledge of these pathologies, and confirms us in the evaluation of the advances available for us today, thanks to the addition of efforts of our predecessors</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lozano Lozano, Doroteo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Laborda y Bergasa, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Podemos afirmar que en los Hospitales Militares, instituciones pioneras dentro de la organización sanitaria del país, aproximadamente un 25% de la patología durante la segunda mitad del siglo XIX, correspondería a las Enfermedades Venéreas, existiendo salas dedicadas a este tipo de afecciones que inicialmente se asociaban a las Enfermedades del Aparato Genito-urinario. La "Gota Militar" o Uretritis Blenorrágica fue un padecimiento venéreo con gran incidencia y prevalencia en la era pre-antibiótica. En el presente trabajo revisaremos los métodos diagnósticos y terapéuticos realizados por los Médicos Militares Españoles durante el periodo indicado. MÉTODOS: Se realiza una introducción, interrelacionando los conocimientos de la época con el medio en que los Médicos Militares desarrollaban su actividad profesional. Se hace referencia a las Revistas de Sanidad Militar, vehículo de las inquietudes y demostración del nivel de conocimiento teórico y práctico que les distinguía. En base a sus Hojas de Servicio y a sus publicaciones, hacemos mención de los Urólogos originarios de la Sanidad Militar que más interés demostraron en el campo de la patología de la uretra, comentando la metodología que utilizaban en el diagnóstico y tratamiento de la Uretritis Blenorrágica. RESULTADOS Y CONCLUSIONES: La Sanidad Militar de finales del siglo XVIII y principios del XIX reunió a un grupo de profesionales que demostraron ingenio y perseverancia en el tratamiento de la "Gota Militar". Conocer los conceptos en el diagnóstico y manejo de las uretritis, mejora nuestra perspectiva en el conocimiento de estas patologías y nos confirma en la valoración de los avances de que hoy disponemos, gracias a la suma de esfuerzos de nuestros predecesores</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;60(8): 994-1002, oct. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056386</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico y tratamiento de la uretritis crónica en la sanidad militar con el cambio de siglo (XIX-XX)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14925^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14925^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9075^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9075^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23825^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14925^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7809^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7809^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24326^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52134^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6223^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6223^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38889</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52134^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38885</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
