<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84676</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Low cost simulator for acquiring basic laparoscopic skills</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction Laparoscopic surgery requires a different set of skills than conventional surgery. The aim of this study was to evaluate the usefulness of a low-cost simulator and camera for the acquisition of basic laparoscopic skills. Material and Methods This randomised trial involved 48 subjects (32 students and 16 surgeons). Two exercises were used, object transfer and cutting. Students were divided into two groups (n=8). One group performed the exercises in the operating theatre with the conventional laparoscopic camera. The second group performed the exercises in a classroom with a low cost micro-camera. Both groups were evaluated before and after five training sessions. Two groups of students were used as controls (n=8), and were evaluated two times without training. The surgeons were divided in two groups (n=8), one was evaluated in the theatre and the other one in the classroom. Results The trained groups showed significant improvements in the first exercise (P &lt;0.001) compared with non-trained groups. There were no differences in scores between the groups with different cameras. The surgeons had better scores than students (P &lt;0.001).Conclusions The improvements in laparoscopic skills on this simulator with a low-cost camera were not significantly different from those gained using the simulator with the conventional laparoscopic camera. This simulator was able to differentiate between experienced and inexperienced subjects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>del Castillo Déjardin, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrera Vilanova, Arancha</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morandeira Rivas, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabench Pereferrer, Fátima</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández González, Mercè</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción La cirugía laparoscópica requiere el conocimiento y tratamiento de un equipo e instrumental diferente al de la cirugía abierta. El objetivo de este estudio es observar si el entrenamiento con un simulador de bajo coste es de utilidad para adquirir habilidades en técnicas laparoscópicas básicas. Material y métodos Estudio aleatorizado en el que participaron 48 sujetos (32 estudiantes y 16 cirujanos). Se diseñaron 2 ejercicios, uno de prensión y otro de corte. Los estudiantes se dividieron en 2 grupos (n=8), el primer grupo realizó los ejercicios en quirófano con la cámara de laparoscopia habitual y el segundo en un aula con una microcámara de bajo coste. Ambos grupos realizaron una primera evaluación, varias sesiones de entrenamiento y una segunda evaluación. Se utilizaron 2 grupos control con estudiantes (n=8) que realizaron las 2 evaluaciones sin entrenamiento. Los cirujanos se dividieron en 2 grupos y realizaron una evaluación, un grupo en quirófano y otro en el aula. Resultados En los grupos con entrenamiento, la mejoría entre la primera evaluación y la segunda para el primer ejercicio fue significativamente mayor que en los grupos sin entrenamiento (p&lt;0,001). Los cirujanos presentaron una puntuación significativamente mejor que los estudiantes en su primera evaluación (p&lt;0,001).Conclusiones El entrenamiento con este simulador de bajo coste ha demostrado ser de utilidad, de forma similar al entrenamiento en el simulador con un sistema de laparoscopia convencional, para adquirir habilidades laparoscópicas básicas. Este sistema de entrenamiento fue capaz de discriminar entre los sujetos con y sin experiencia en cirugía laparoscópica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);87(1): 26-32, ene. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84676</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Simulador de bajo coste para el entrenamiento de habilidades laparoscópicas básicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9143</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3380</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201001</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
