<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041427</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8799</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Injuries and prevention in snowboard</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Recently there is a increasing of popularity of this sport. This is the reason why there are a lot of researches that are studying.The aim of this paper is to analyse researches in the scientific literature about this actual subject. Material were the review of articles during 2003 on Medline, Embase, CINHAL, PEDRO, Cochrane and MANTIS data base. Method will be described after (election of articles, search criteries...). The articles have to reach these chriteries: - Published in scientific review. - Published in English language. - The artic1e have to be a trial clinic or study with humans; studies with animal s were descarted. Results: Injuries are very important in these sports, so is very useful know their injury' s mechanisms, and the profile of this injuries. The new snowboarders, due to their general ignorance on the main aspects of snowboard, undergo great amount of injuries. Conclusions: prevention are very important to prevent posible injuries; so use of binding protectors are being introduced, as well as education and knowledge of techniques To emphasize that in addition to the knowledge of the basic and more important aspects of this sport, like the technique, lesional mechanism, is not either necessary to forget excellent aspects like the psychological condition, the nutrition, the type of snow... that can influence to a great extent in the possible injuries</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miñano Vigo, Juan G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos años está aumentando la popularidad de este deporte, y por ella se están sucediendo numerosos estudios relacionados con este tema, así como el interés por todo lo concerniente a ello.En este trabajo intentaremos referenciar estudios de diversos autores, acerca de este actual tema. El material ha sido los artículos revisados durante 2003 en las bases de datos Medline, Embase, CINHAL, PEDRO, Cochrane y MANITS . Los métodos se describen más adelante(elección de artículos, criterios debúsqueda...). Los artículos tenían que cumplir los siguientes criterios: - Haber sido publicado en una revista científica. - Estar publicado en lengua inglesa. - El artículo debía ser un ensayo clínico o un estudio con personas; los estudios con animales fueron descartados. Resultados: Las lesiones son muy frecuentes dentro de este deporte, y por ello hay que conocer su mecanismo. Los nuevos practicantes de este deporte, debido a su desconocimiento general sobre los principales aspectos del snowboard, sufren gran cantidad de lesiones.El perfil de lesión ha ido cambiando en los últimos años, debido la introducción de equipamiento nuevo, y a la educación sobre este deporte. Como conclusión, destacar el papel importantísimo de la prevención para evitar posibles lesiones, por ello el uso de los protectores obligatorios están siendo introducidos, así como la educación y el conocimiento de las técnicas de este deporte. Destacar que además del conocimiento de los aspectos básicos y más importantes de este deporte, como la técnica, mecanismo lesional, tampoco hay que olvidarse de aspectos relevantes como la condición psicológica, la nutrición, el tipo de nieve... que pueden influir en gran medida en las posibles lesiones</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. med. deporte;22(106): 129-137, mar.-abr. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041427</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lesiones y prevención en el snowboard</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13246^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1273^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1273^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1273^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33544^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37695^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37695^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13246^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
