<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114365</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of the PRIMUS scale to assess quality of life in a Spanish population of multiple sclerosis patients</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Mora, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introduction: Symptoms of multiple sclerosis (MS) are associated with significant and progressive functional disability and have a profound impact on patients&#146; quality of life (QoL). QoL and daily life activities are two areas that suffer major changes during the course of MS and there are currently no questionnaires specifically designed to evaluate these areas in MS patients. Purpose: To evaluate QoL of MS patients using the PRIMUS questionnaire and determine the possible relationship between QoL, duration of disease, and disability measured on the EDSS. Patients and methods: Multi-centre epidemiological and cross-sectional study including 261 patients with relapsing remitting MS (RRMS) or secondary progressive MS (SPMS) treated with interferon beta-1b for at least 6 months. The validated version of the PRIMUS questionnaire was used for patient reporting of changes in QoL and life activities. Results: Mean age of patients was 41.7 ± 10.3 years; 61.3% were women. Most had RRMS (83.9%). Mean time since MS diagnosis was 7.6 ± 5.8 years, and longer in the SPMS group (11.2 ± 7.4 vs 6.9 ± 5.2,P &lt; .0001). Mean EDSS score was 2.6 ± 1.75 (5.1 ± 1.3 in SPMS vs 2.1 ± 1.4 in RRMS, P &lt; .0001). Mean time since start of treatment was 5.5 ± 3.8 years. The PRIMUS QoL component was higher in the RRMS group: 18.3 ± 6.8 vs 9.9 ± 7.1 (P&lt;.0001); it also decreased with increases in both time since diagnosis (P &lt; .01) and disability scores (from 18.8 ± 6.6 in early stages [EDSS &lt; 3.5] to 8.4 ± 6.3 in advanced stages [EDSS &gt; 5], P &lt; .0001). The PRIMUS activity limitations component followed the same pattern: activity became more limited with increases in time since diagnosis (P &lt; .0001) and overall disability (P &lt; .0001). Conclusions: QoL in MS patients varies according to the disease type, and it worsens progressively over time and with increasing disability. The PRIMUS questionnaire is a good tool for assessing QoL and activity in patients with MS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;28(6): 340-347, jul.-ago. 2013. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114365</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la calidad de vida mediante cuestionario PRIMUS en población española de pacientes con esclerosis múltiple</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
