<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052806</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The intergenerational transmission of social exclusion and its detection in early childhood education</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this paper we analyse the relationship between the self-confidence manifested by 3-6 year old in the internal working model (evaluated by interview) and their adaptation to nursery environment observed by their teacher, along with the relationship between these variables and the social-economic disadvantage encountered by the families of the children. The study was carried out with 128 children (64 from families in deprived circumstances and 64 in the contrast group). The results show that children from families with serious problems of exclusion exhibit adaptation deficiencies in all of the assessed factors: competence and empathy, passiveness/isolation and antisocial behavior; in the interview, they also show less frequency of the secure model, and higher frequency in the destructured and avoidant models than in the contrast group. These differences can be interpreted as the origin of the exclusion and destructurisation that characterises the families in question</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Aguado Jalón, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Arias, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se analiza la relación entre la seguridad manifestada por los niños y las niñas de 3-6 años en el modelo interno de apego, evaluado través de una entrevista, y su adaptación a la escuela infantil observada por el educador, así como la relación entre ambas variables y la desventaja socioeconómica de sus familias. El estudio se ha realizado con N= 128, 64 del grupo en desventaja y 64 del grupo de comparación. Sus resultados reflejan que los sujetos de familias con graves problemas de exclusión tienen una peor adaptación escolar en todos los factores evaluados: competencia y empatía, pasividad/aislamiento y conductas antisociales; y manifiestan en la entrevista menor frecuencia de modelo seguro y mayor frecuencia de los modelos desestructurado y de evitación que los sujetos del grupo de comparación. Estas diferencias pueden ser interpretadas como el origen de la reproducción de la exclusión y desestructuración que caracteriza la vida de sus familias</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);18(3): 378-383, ago. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052806</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La reproducción intergeneracional de la exclusión social y su detección desde la educación infantil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9954</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23905</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d991^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12825^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10476</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
