<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140987</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Alternative to chronic wound closure by Reverdin grafts and growth factors in ambulatory surgery minor</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The closure of chronic wounds by secondary intention, is a high rate of nursing, especially in poorly healing wounds, for two main reasons, the lack of response to treatments, and the prevalence of this appeal process as claimed in primary health care centers and outpatient hospital. Also, the patient can lead to a delay in their total healing (medical discharge), which sometimes induce other incidents such as ambulance, delay in job placement, etc. It is necessary to find a method which reduces healing time in these cases and at the same time, avoid the complications inherent to conventional wet cure closing and in turn, be available to the media and resources available on our health system. The application of Platelets Rich Plasma (PRP), obtained by centrifugation of blood drawn directly to the patient, has been running for nearly twenty years in the health care setting. It is currently used as an alternative to traditional infiltration corticosteroid tendinopathies in gel state or as a clot, equivalent to a mesh of fibrin membranes capable of forming, filling in coverage or a particular area of tissue loss.  Already in 1869, coined the term Reverdin island of skin grafts, initially in treating injury due to burns. In this technique, the wound is covered partially with small fragments of healthy skin of the patient. This study combines the use of PRP and slips island, applied in 15 individuals with trauma with loss of substance, no relevant medical history and do not respond to conventional wet cure. The results show that after the first application of the gel of PRP shows the appearance of granulation tissue, which is susceptible to grafting or island nested.  The combination of both techniques shortens the healing time of wounds treated with equipment that is easily accessible in any health center, which is a very low level of spending and an expectation of success High cure, plus the procedure easily manageable by the nursing staff dedicated to program minor outpatient surgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo Penuelas, Jose Ramon</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dominguez Bermudez, Juan Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armario Hita, Jose Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro Maqueda, Guillermo de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perez Vega, Francisco Javie</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutierrez Vazquez, Maria Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cierre de heridas crónicas supone una alta tasa en cuidados de enfermería, sobre todo en heridas de difícil cicatrización, debido a la falta de respuesta a los tratamientos aplicados y a la elevada prevalencia del proceso. Es necesario encontrar un método que reduzca el tiempo de curación, evite las complicaciones inherentes al cierre por cura húmeda convencional y pueda realizarse con los recursos disponibles en cualquier medio sanitario. El plasma rico en plaquetas (PRP) autólogo se utiliza actualmente como alternativa a la infiltración tradicional con corticoesteroides o en estado gel, en la cobertura o relleno de una determinada zona con pérdida de tejido. El presente estudio combina el uso de PRP e injertos insulares descritos por Reverdin (1869), en 15 individuos que presentan traumatismos con pérdida de sustancia que no responden a la cura húmeda convencional. Los resultados muestran que, tras la primera aplicación de PRP, se aprecia la aparición de tejido de granulación, que es susceptible de recibir el injerto. La combinación de ambas técnicas acorta el período de cicatrización de las heridas tratadas, con equipos de fácil accesibilidad en cualquier centro sanitario, minimizando costes con una expectativa de curación elevada, sumado al procedimiento fácilmente asumible por el personal de enfermería dedicado a cirugía menor ambulatoria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);26(1): 28-33, mar. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140987</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alternativa al cierre de heridas crónicas mediante injertos de Reverdin y factores de crecimiento en cirugía menor ambulatoria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37364^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15343^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
