<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99468</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Drug delivery strategies based on the enhanced permeation and retention effect</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Current therapeutic strategies against diseases are primarily limited by the accessibility to the non healthy site, the risk of operating on a vital organ, and the lack of selectivity towards targeted cells. The association of active agents with colloidal delivery systems has been proposed to improve the efficacy of pharmacotherapy and to minimize the incidence of adverse side effects. This association is expected to result in: i) a specific drug accumulation into the targeted site; ii) a prolongation of the exposure of the cells to these molecules; and, iii) an improvement of the pharmacokinetic profile. However, drug nanoplatforms generally display in vivo a very significant interaction with the mononuclear phagocyte system (MPS).The development of long-circulating nanoparticles has allowed for many colloids to exploit structural abnormalities in the vasculature of particular pathologies, such as tumors, inflammatory and infectious sites. This leads to an enhanced accumulation of the drug dose into the targeted site. In this investigation, we evaluate the &#147;state of the art&#148; in the development of drug delivery nanoplatforms based on passive drug targeting strategies to targeted sites (through the enhanced permeation and retention, EPR, effect)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gallardo, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáez-Fernández, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Artacho, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Soler, G. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La nanotecnología permite el diseño de nanomateriales multifuncionales con una semivida plasmática prolongada (gracias a la incorporación superficial de cadenas poliméricas hidrófilas), necesaria para alcanzar de forma segura su objetivo y liberar específicamente la dosis de fármaco vehiculizada en el lugar deseado, aumentando al mismo tiempo la biodisponibilidad del agente activo en el tejido diana. En cuanto al tratamiento del cáncer, estas nanopartículas pueden alcanzar la región tumoral simplemente por acumulación o retención (transporte pasivo). Este fenómeno es el efecto de permeación y retención aumentada (efecto "EPR"). Este efecto es facilitado por las características diferenciales del entorno tumoral, donde el tejido vascular se encuentra alterado. Esto explica por qué se da una mayor acumulación de nanopartículas en la masa tumoral, en comparación con un tejido sano. En este trabajo analizamos el estado actual en el desarrollo de nanoplataformas transportadoras de fármacos basadas en estrategias de transporte pasivo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;51(supl.3): 113-116, jul. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99468</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrategias para el transporte de fármacos basadas en el efecto de permeación y retención aumentada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54318^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52498^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36473^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52498^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36473^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36473^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201007</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
