<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123012</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Preventive cardiology and cardiac rehabilitation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Prevention is the most effective and efficient way of tackling cardiovascular disease and, similarly, cardiac rehabilitation programs are the most effective and efficient means of secondary prevention. The main objective of the metabolic syndrome working group is to increase understanding of cardiovascular risk in Spain by studying the occurrence of various risk factors, and the connections and associations between them, in economically active individuals. The group&#146;s first study and, subsequently, the MESYAS (Metabolic Syndrome in Active Subjects) study have led to significant and informative new findings, and continue to be produce data that can be used to improve disease prevention in everyday clinical practice. Furthermore, cardiac rehabilitation and secondary prevention programs for cardiovascular disease provide the most effective means of decreasing morbidity and mortality. However, it is worrying to observe that, in cardiological practice, there are significant gaps incompliance with scientific society recommendations on secondary prevention. On request, the coordinator of the cardiac rehabilitation working group has provided a report on the latest data and findings from across the full spectrum of activity in this vital area of disease prevention (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Andrés-Esteban, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pablo-Zarzosa, Carmen de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Porrero, Esteban</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León-Latre, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La prevención es la herramienta más eficaz y eficiente en la enfermedad cardiovascular y, de igual forma, los programas de rehabilitación cardiaca son los más eficaces y eficientes en la prevención secundaria. Conocer la situación de riesgo cardiovascular en nuestro país a través del estudio de la presentación de los distintos factores de riesgo y de su relación y asociación en trabajadores españoles es el objetivo principal del grupo de trabajo de nuestra sección sobre síndrome metabólico. A través de su primero registro y luego estudio denominado MESYAS (MEtabolic SYndrome Active Subjets), nos ha ofrecido importantes e interesantes resultados y sigue produciendo datos que nos ayudan en nuestra práctica preventiva diaria. Por otra parte, los programas de rehabilitación cardiaca y de prevención secundaria de las enfermedades cardiovasculares son el método más eficaz para disminuir su morbimortalidad. Sin embargo, es preocupante observar que en la asistencia cardiológica hay importantes lagunas en cuanto al seguimiento de las recomendaciones de las sociedades científicas sobre esa prevención secundaria. Le hemos pedido al coordinador del grupo de trabajo de rehabilitación cardiaca que nos informe con los últimos datos y evidencias del panorama de esta importante actividad preventiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;63(supl.1): 40-48, 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123012</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cardiología preventiva y rehabilitación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12467^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
