<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74412</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacy of triple therapy with a proton pump inhibitor, levofloxacin, and amoxicillin as first-line treatment to eradicate Helicobacter pylori</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: triple therapy including a proton pump inhibitor, clarithromycin, and amoxicillin (PPI-CA) is the first-choice treatment used for H. pylori eradication. The efficacy of this treatment is declining of late, and alternative therapies are currently under evaluation. Objectives: to evaluate the efficacy, safety and compliance of a triple therapy with a PPI, amoxicillin and levofloxacin (PPI-LA) - replacing clarithromycin - for the eradication of H. pylori. Methods: the study included 135 patients (65% women), mean age 53 years, with dyspeptic symptoms and H. pylori infection proven by a positive urease rapid test, histological analysis, or C13-urea breath test. Diagnosis: non-investigated dyspepsia 48.9%, functional dyspepsia 36.3%, and ulcerative dyspepsia 14.8%. Treatment was indicated with a proton pump inhibitor at usual doses, amoxicillin 1 g, and levofloxacin 500 mg, administered jointly during breakfast and dinner for 10 days. We studied the performance of this triple therapy and its effects using a questionnaire, and effectiveness by the negativity of the C13-urea breath test after 6-8 weeks after treatment discontinuation. Per protocol, we compared the effectiveness of PPI-LA with a control group of 270 patients treated with PPI-CA for 10 days. Results: 130 patients (96.2%) could complete the treatment and follow-up protocol. Effectiveness (intention to treat) was 71.8% (97/135) and 74.6% (per protocol) (97/130). Sixteen patients (11.8%) had well-tolerated adverse effects, except for 5 subjects (3.7%) who dropped out. PPI-CA was effective (per protocol) in 204 patients out of 270 (75.5%) in the control group...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castro-Fernández, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero-Gómez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larraona, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pabón, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vargas-Romero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lamas, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aparcero, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Pastor, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la triple terapia con un inhibidor de la bomba de protones, claritromicina y amoxicilina (IBP-CA) es el tratamiento de primera elección más utilizado en la erradicación de H. pylori. La eficacia de este tratamiento está disminuyendo en los últimos años y se están valorando otras alternativas terapéuticas. Objetivos:valorar la eficacia, cumplimiento y seguridad de una triple terapia con un IBP, amoxicilina y levofloxacino, sustituyendo a la claritromicina, en la erradicación de H. pylori. Métodos: periodo de estudio: 2007-2008. Se incluyen 135 pacientes (65% mujeres), edad media de 53 años, con síntomas dispépticos e infección por H. pylori, constatada por positividad del test rápido de la ureasa, histología o prueba del aliento con urea-C13. Diagnósticos: dispepsia no investigada: 48,9%, dispepsia funcional: 36,3% y dispepsia ulcerosa: 14,8%. Se indica tratamiento con un inhibidor de la bomba de protones, a dosis habitual, amoxicilina 1 g y levofloxacino 500 mg (IBP-LA), administrados de forma conjunta en desayuno y cena, durante 10 días. Se valora el cumplimiento de la triple terapia y sus efectos adversos mediante interrogatorio y su eficacia mediante la negatividad de la prueba del aliento con urea-C13 practicada a las 6-8 semanas del término del tratamiento. Se compara la eficacia, por protocolo, del tratamiento con IBP-LA con la observada en un grupo control de 270 pacientes tratados con IBP-CA durante 10 días en los años 2006-2007. Resultados: 130/135 pacientes (96,2) del grupo de estudio completaron el tratamiento y el protocolo del seguimiento. La eficacia por intención de tratar fue del 71,8% (97/135) y por protocolo del 74,6% (97/130). Dieciséis pacientes (11,8%) presentaron efectos adversos bien tolerados, excepto en 5 pacientes (3.7%) que motivan el abandono del tratamiento. El tratamiento con IBP-CA resultó eficaz, por protocolo, en 204/270 (75,5%) pacientes del grupo control...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;101(6): 395-402, jun. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74412</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia de una triple terapia con un inhibidor de la bomba de protones, levofloxacino y amoxicilina, como primer tratamiento, en la erradicación de Helicobacter pylori</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29156^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52844^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29157^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d673^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23786^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d673^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23786^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32388</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
