<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050949</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acute pyelonephritis treated in a hospital at Home Unit. Ten years' experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. We present the experience of the Vitoria-Gasteiz Hospital at Home Unit in the treatment of acute pyelonephritis, including an analysis of potential predictors of failure. Patients and methods. A total of 369 episodes of acute pyelonephritis without septic shock or renoureteral obstruction are described. After initiating intravenous antibiotic therapy in the hospital emergency department, all patients were referred to the HH. We analyzed the characteristics of the cases and the relationship between several clinical factors and failure of HH care, defined as the need to readmit the patient to conventional hospitalization. Results. During the study period, 280 women and 89 men (age 16-88 years) met the inclusion criteria. Mean length of HH stay was 5 days and duration of intravenous therapy was 3 days. Sixteen of the 369 cases (4%) had to be readmitted to the hospital because of hypotension, vomiting, pain, fever, or signs of obstruction on ultrasound or because they requested it (four patients). Patients who were readmitted had a higher maximum temperature (mean 39.4 vs. 38.7 °C; p = 0.006) than those who remained at the HH. There were no differences between the groups with respect to the other clinical variables studied. The evolution of all 16 hospitalized patients was favorable; only one required a urological intervention. Conclusions. Hospital at home care was an effective alternative for managing acute pyelonephritis without shock in 96% of cases referred by the emergency department, and obviated conventional hospital admission, which is usually indicated for this disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Altuna, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cía, Juan M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Regalado, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aizpuru, Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendoza, Humberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Presentamos la experiencia de la Unidad de Hospitalización a Domicilio (HaD) de Vitoria-Gasteiz en el tratamiento de pielonefritis aguda, aportando además un análisis de posibles predictores de fracaso. Pacientes y método. Se estudian 369 casos de pielonefritis aguda sin shock séptico ni obstrucción renoureteral diagnosticados en el Servicio de Urgencias Hospitalarias (SUH), que tras iniciar en este servicio tratamiento antibiótico por vía intravenosa fueron remitidos a HaD. Se describen diferentes características de los casos y se analiza la relación entre diferentes variables clínicas y el fracaso de HaD, definido como necesidad de reenviar al paciente al hospital para ingreso convencional. Resultados. En el período estudiado, 280 mujeres y 89 varones de entre 16 y 88 años cumplieron los criterios de inclusión. La estancia media en HaD fue de 5 días, y 3 días fue la duración media del tratamiento intravenoso. Un total de 16 de los 369 casos ingresaron en el hospital. Cuatro por propia iniciativa y el resto remitidos por hipotensión, vómitos, dolor, fiebre o signos de obstrucción en ecografía. La temperaturas máximas alcanzadas en este grupo fueron significativamente mayores que en el de los pacientes no reingresados (media 39,4 °C frente a 38,7 °C; p &lt; 0,006). El análisis de otras diversas variables clínicas no muestra diferencias entre ambos grupos. La evolución durante el ingreso hospitalario de estos 16 casos fue favorable, y sólo uno requirió intervención urológica. Conclusiones. La asistencia en régimen de HaD de pielonefritis aguda sin shock diagnosticada en el SUH es una alternativa muy eficaz y evita el ingreso hospitalario convencional en el 96% de los casos derivados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;24(10): 629-633, dic. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050949</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pielonefritis aguda atendida en hospitalización a domicilio. Diez años de experiencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12140^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10553^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32196^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
