<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-6799</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-6585</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Microbiological study of the peri-implantitis: presentation of 9 clinical cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Peri-implantitis is an inflammatory process affecting the tissues around an osseointegrated implant in function, resulting in loss of supporting bone. The aim of this study was to evaluate the subgingival microbiota at dental implants associated with peri-implantitis treated in our service. A total of 16 implants of 9 patients were studied. In all cases implants were under functional conditions. Materials and Methods: We studied 16 peri-implantitis in 9 patients; in each patient subgingival bacterial samples were obtained using paper-points or inflammatory soft tissue, and subjected to microbiological analysis by culture. Each site was sample by serting paper points into the sulcus around the implant with peri-implantitis, in 14 implants, or by inflammatory soft tissue, in other 2 implants. Then the samples were grown in brain heart infusion broth. Results: We found Gram-negative anaerobic bacteria, Fusobacterium nucleatum, in one sample, Prevotella oralis, in one sample, Peptostreptococcus, in one sample, and Stomatococcus, in 3 samples. In 9 samples were impossible to found one predominant bacteria. Antimicrobial susceptibility of isolates was determined. Antibacterial activity of amoxicillin-clavulanate was significantly higher than with other antimicrobials tested like amoxicillin or metronidazole. Conclusions: This study found that microbiota associated with periimplantitis are Stomatococcus, Prevotella oralis, Peptostreptococcus and Fusobacterium nucleatum. Actinobacillus actinomycetemcomitans was not detected in any of the sampIes. Possible risk factors of peri-implantitis were hydroxyapatite, dental implants of 3,25 mm of diameter or distal position of implants in maxillary prosthetic superstructure (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ediciones Avances, S.L.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: La periimplantitis es un proceso inflamatorio de los tejidos que rodean a un implante sometido a carga que produce la pérdida de soporte óseo. En este trabajo se muestran los resultados del estudio microbiológico y del antibiograma realizado a partir del exudado y/o del tejido periimplantario de 16 implantes funcionales con periimplantitis de 9 pacientes que fueron tratados en nuestro servicio. Material y método: Se estudiaron 16 periimplantitis observadas en 9 pacientes; de 14 de ellas se obtuvieron muestras con puntas de papel estériles que se introdujeron en la bolsa periimplantaria. En 2 implantes las muestras procedían de tejido de granulación periimplantario. Inmediatamente después de ser obtenidas, se colocaban en placas de agar-chocolate con brain heart infusion para proceder a su cultivo. Resultados: Los especímenes bacterianos aislados fueron: Stomatococcus, Prevotella oralis, Peptostreptococcus y Fusobacterium nucleatum. En 9 muestras fue imposible aislar una bacteria predominante debido a la complejidad de la flora. Respecto al resto de muestras, la bacteria predominante fue Stomatococcus en 3, Prevotella oralis en 1, Peptostreptococcus en 1 y Fusobacterium nucleatum en 2. Los antibiogramas mostraron una mayor sensibilidad a la asociación de la amoxicilina con el ácido clavulánico, comparada con la amoxicilina, el metronidazol o una combinación de estos dos últimos antimicrobianos. Conclusiones: En este trabajo las bacterias asociadas más frecuentemente a la periimplantitis fueron: Stomatococcus, Prevotella oralis, Peptostreptococcus y Fusobacterium nucleatum. En ningún caso se aislaron cepas de Actinobacillus actinomycetemcomitans. Los posibles factores de riesgo asociados a periimplantitis en nuestra, serie fueron los implantes recubiertos con hidroxiapatita, implantes de 3,25 mm de diámetro y la localización más distal del implante en las prótesis que rehabilitaban extremos libres ed.éntulos superiores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. periodoncia implantol. oral;12(3): 137-150, dic. 2000. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio microbiológico de la periimplantitis: Presentación de 9 casos clínicos</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Gay Escoda, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Molina, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quinteros Borgarello, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Garcés, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berini Aytés, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-6799</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d24600^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32068^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10655^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30094^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31497^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10677^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
