<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049936</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9744</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Euthanasia and assisted suicide</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this report is to review the actualsituation around public debate about Euthanasiaand Assisted Suicide, analysing the argumentsagainst and pros for a permissive change in thepenal law. Also, a review over different law modelsis made, with special attention to the statesin which they are any kind of penal exemption(Nederland, Belgium, Switzerland, Oregon). TheSpanish Law is analysed, with evaluation of theimpact made for the new Registry of PreviousInstructions, a tool included in the new Law ofPatient&#146;s Autonomy (Law 41/2002). Finally, differentforms of Euthanasia are exposed, focusingethic problems derived from the application ofextraordinary measures (like sedative&#146;s use)which involve a &#147;double effect&#148; and the role ofthe Palliative Care Units in an overall sanitaryassistance</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bañón González, R. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El propósito del presente artículo es hacer unarevisión de la situación actual en torno al debatepúblico sobre la eutanasia y el suicidio asistido,analizando los argumentos a favor y en contrade modificar la legislación en un sentido permisivo.A continuación se hace una revisión de losdistintos modelos legislativos existentes, con especialatención de los estados que contemplanalgún modelo de exención penal en casos de eutanasia(Holanda, Bélgica, Suiza y Oregon) y seanaliza la legislación española y el impacto delregistro de Instrucciones Previas previsto en laLey de Autonomía del Paciente (Ley 41/2002).Por último se exponen las diferentes formas deeutanasia, los problemas éticos derivados de laaplicación de medidas (como la sedación) queconllevan un &#147;doble efecto&#148; y el papel de las Unidadesde Cuidados Paliativos en un sistema sanitariointegral</dc:description>
<dc:source>Geriátrika (Madr.);22(4): 151-156, abr. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049936</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eutanasia y suicidio asistido</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30490</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36358</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28008^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
