<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112728</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish normative studies in young adults ( NEURONORMA young adults project): norms for the Rey-Osterrieth Complex Figure (copy and memory) and Free and Cued Selective Reminding Test</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The Rey-Osterrieth Complex Figure (ROCF) and the Free and Cued Selective Reminding Test (FCSRT) are widely used in clinical practice. The ROCF assesses visual perception, constructional praxis, and visuo-spatial memory. The FCSRT assesses verbal learning and memory. Objective: In this study, as part of the Spanish normative studies project in young adults (NEURONORMA young adults), we present age- and education-adjusted normative data for both tests obtained by using linear regression techniques. Material and methods: The sample consisted of 179 healthy participants ranging in age from 18 to 49 years. We provide tables for converting raw scores to scaled scores in addition to tables with scores adjusted by socio-demographic factors. Results: The results showed that education affects scores for some of the memory tests and the figure-copying task. Age was only found to have an effect on the performance of visuo-spatial memory tests, and the effect of sex was negligible. Conclusions: The normative data obtained will be extremely useful in the clinical neuropsychological evaluation of young Spanish adults (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quintana, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casals Coll, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Benavides, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tamayo, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aranciva, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manero, R. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palomo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rognoni, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña Casanova, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El test Rey-Osterrieth Complex Figure (ROCF) y el Free and Cued Selective Reminding Test (FCSRT) son pruebas ampliamente utilizadas en la práctica clínica. El ROCF es de gran utilidad para la exploración de la percepción visual, la praxis constructiva y la memoria visuoespacial. El FCSRT evalúa aprendizaje y memoria verbal. Objetivo: En el presente estudio, que forma parte del proyecto de obtención de datos normativos españoles en adultos jóvenes (proyecto NEURONORMA jóvenes), se aportan datos normativos ajustados por edad y escolaridad para ambos test mediante la aplicación de regresiones lineales. Material y métodos: Se incluyó a 179 participantes sanos de entre 18 y 49 años de edad. Se aportan tablas para convertir las puntuaciones brutas en escalares, así como tablas de ajuste por los factores sociodemográficos. Resultados: Los resultados obtenidos muestran influencia de la escolaridad en diversas variables de memoria y en la copia de la figura. La edad únicamente afecta el rendimiento en memoria visuoespacial y el efecto del género es despreciable. Conclusiones: Las referencias obtenidas son de gran utilidad clínica para la evaluación neuropsicológica de población adulta joven española (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;28(4): 226-235, mayo 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112728</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudios normativos españoles en población adulta joven (proyecto NEURONORMA jóvenes): normas para las pruebas Rey-Osterrieth Complex Figure (copia y memoria) y Free and Cued Selective Reminding Test</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4592</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8738</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201305</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
