<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050578</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Selective digestive decontamination: the Getafe protocol</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The incidence of ventilator-associated pneumonia (VAP) among mechanically ventilated patients in intensive care units (ICUs) is 10-50%. Notable among preventive measures is selective digestive decontamination (SDD). In 1998, a protocol for SDD was developed and implemented in the ICU of the Hospital Universitario de Getafe. SDD is administered to patients admitted to the ICU who require mechanical ventilation for more than 72 hours and to those with diseases in which the efficacy of SDD has been demonstrated. SDD administration consists of: 1) a short course of systemic antibiotics; 2) oral administration of a solution of non-absorbable antibiotics and topical application in the oropharynx and nose of a non-absorbable antibiotic paste; 3) hygiene and isolation measures. Use of this protocol reduced the rate of VAP by 71% in medical-surgical patients and by 29% in burn patients, without producing a significant increase in multiresistant microorganisms</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arias-Rivera, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abella-Álvarez, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frutos-Vivar, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Entre el 10 y el 50% de los enfermos ventilados mecánicamente en las unidades de cuidados intensivos (UCI) presentan neumonía asociada a la ventilación mecánica (NAVM). Dentro de las medidas preventivas destaca el papel de la descontaminación digestiva selectiva (DDS). En 1998 se desarrolló el protocolo y se inició la aplicación de la DDS en la UCI del Hospital de Getafe. La DDS se aplica a los pacientes que van a requerir ventilación mecánica más de 72 h o con enfermedad en la que se ha demostrado la eficacia de la DDS. La DDS consiste en: 1) administrar un ciclo corto de antibióticos por vía intravenosa; 2) administración oral de antibióticos no absorbibles en forma de solución digestiva y pasta en orofaringe y nariz; 3) medidas de higiene y aislamiento. Con la implementación de esta técnica se ha reducido la tasa de NAVM en un 71% en pacientes medicoquirúrgicos y un 29% en pacientes quemados, sin aumento significativo de los microorganismos multirresistentes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);16(6): 336-339, nov. 2006. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050578</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Descontaminación digestiva selectiva: protocolo de Getafe</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10550^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9916^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
