<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152313</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endocrine disrupting chemicals exposure and other parental factors in hypospadias and cryptorchidism etiology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim of the study. To investigate the association between endocrine disrupting chemicals (EDC) exposure and other paternal factors in the etiology of hipospadias and cryptorchidism. Methods. A case-control study. Cases were infants between 0 and 6 years of age diagnosed with hypospadias or cryptorchidism in our pediatric urology and general pediatric surgery services during a period of 6 months, and controls were infants with the same range of age attending the same services without any urological problem. Several variables were collected by face-to-face interviews with both parents. After data abstraction, we compared the characteristics of both groups using parametric statistical tests. Main results. A total of 180 patients were studied, 90 cases (45 hypospadias/45 cryptorchidism) and 90 controls with a mean age of 2,37 ± 1.50 years [range 0,5-6]. Median of mother´s age was significantly greater in case group (34,40 ± 5,64 versus 31,74 ± 5,05; p= 0,001). Significant differences were observed between cases and controls in regard to maternal occupational exposure to EDC (mainly phthalates), adjusted Odds ratio (OR) was 3.67 [95% confidence interval (CI): 1.28- 10.51; p= 0,018] and regarding the paternal occupational exposure to EDC (mainly pesticides and herbicides), adjusted OR was 6.65 [95% CI: 2.60-17.02; p= 0,001]. Increased risk was also observed in smoking fathers and fathers who drink alcohol, adjusted Odds ratio were 2.36 [95% CI: 1.11-3.87; p= 0,029] and 2.50 [95% CI: 1.36-4.57; p= 0,003] respectively. Conclusions. This study represents a little contribution to the possible etiologic factors of hypospadias and cryptorchidism, further studies with higher statistical power would be needed to prove it (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gracia Romero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Atuan, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rihuete Heras, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bragagnini Rodríguez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Alvira, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estors Sastre, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Investigar la asociación entre la exposición a disruptores endocrinos (DE) y otros factores en el desarrollo del hipospadias y la criptorquidia. Material y métodos. Estudio de casos y controles. Consideramos como casos a los niños de entre 6 meses y 6 años de edad diagnosticados de hipospadias y/o criptorquidia que acudieron a las consultas de Urología/Cirugía durante un período de estudio de 6 meses y como controles, a los niños con mismo rango de edad que acudieron a las mismas consultas con otros diagnósticos. Recogimos las variables de interés mediante una encuesta epidemiológica y comparamos los resultados obtenidos en cada grupo mediante tests estadísticos paramétricos. Resultados. Estudiamos 180 pacientes, 90 casos (45 hipospadias/45 criptorquidias) y 90 controles, con edad media de 2,60 ± 1,72 años [rango 0,5-6]. Las medias de edad gestacional y peso al nacer fueron menores en el grupo-caso sin objetivarse diferencias significativas. La edad media materna fue significativamente mayor en el grupo-caso (34,40 ± 5,64 versus 31,74 ± 5,05; p= 0,001). Encontramos asociación significativa entre la exposición ocupacional materna a DE (ftalatos principalmente) y el grupo-caso siendo la Odds ratio (OR) de 3,67 (IC 95%: 1,28-10,51; p= 0,018) y también en la paterna (principalmente a pesticidas/herbicidas) con OR= 6,65 (IC 95%: 2,60-17,02; p= 0,001). Encontramos asociación significativa entre el consumo de tabaco y alcohol paternos y el grupo-caso: OR= 2,08 (IC 95%: 1,11-3,87; p= 0,029) y OR= 2,50 (IC 95%: 1,36-4,57; p= 0,003) respectivamente. Conclusiones. Este estudio supone una pequeña aportación respecto a los posibles factores etiológicos del hipospadias y la criptorquidia, y demuestra la necesidad de estudios ulteriores con mayor potencia estadística para aumentar la evidencia científica de nuestros hallazgos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;28(3): 128-132, jul. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152313</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Exposición a disruptores endocrinos y otros factores paternos en la etiología del hipospadias y la criptorquidia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51206^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3473^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7200^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32096^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32153^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
