<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117638</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Contributions of the conception of the link to interventions with families. Theoretical and technical aspects</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The author refers to the conception of the link in view of changes in the contemporary family. A review of the literature starts with Freud and continues with the works of different authors to explain how the notion of link enables understanding of phenomena the analyst aims to encompass in interventions with families. The point of departure is that psychic construction emerges as the product of an interweave of links. The author presents clinical material showing the process of factors that crisscross in family suffering and the effects they produce in the space-frame of the family cure (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Monserrat, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palacios, Elizabeth</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo se refiere a la concepción vincular ante los cambios de la familia contemporánea. Se realiza un recorrido partiendo de Freud a través de la obra de distintos autores, para dar cuenta de que la noción de vínculo posibilita una comprensión de los fenómenos que se intenta abarcar en las intervenciones con las familias. El punto de partida es que la construcción psíquica surge como producto de una trama vincular. Se presenta un material clínico donde se muestra el proceso de los factores que se entrecruzan en los padecimientos familiares y los efectos que se producen en el espacio marco de la cura familiar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(65): 99-114, jul. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117638</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aportes de la concepción vincular en la intervención con familias. Aspectos teóricos y técnicos y su aplicación en la clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12012^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13304</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28084</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5300^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201207</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
