<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76532</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-1375</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Approach to informal care of chronic renal patients in the Jaen hospital complex</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose was to discover the characteristics of the informal care that chronic renal patients receive in the dialysis programme of the hospital. To do so, we designed a transverse descriptive study carried out over two stages. We worked with professionals, patients and informal carers, heads of Service or Unit, supervisors and senior CAPD and teaching programme nurse. We obtained information through a questionnaire given to each professional and patient in the Dialysis Units. Another questionnaire was given to the main patient carers. The heads of Service, supervisors and senior CAPD nurse CAPD reported through a semi-structured interview. The results show that the demand for informal care concerns the need for help in: 1) using healthcare services; 2) dealing with issues and activities arising as a result of the kidney disease (medication, diet, control of intake of liquids and weight gain between dialysis sessions; 3) preparing dialysis sessions; 4) carrying out instrumental activities; 5) carrying out activities of daily life and 6) covering the needs of personal self-realization. Care is provided by the most immediate family, and the main carer is normally a woman. Almost half of them are unaware of the existence of social services providing help and90% never use them. The impact of the task of carer on the life of these people is important. A need can be seen to create infrastructures for the education of carers, and to increase and publicize resources and aid available for informal carers (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Ortega, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marchal Ocaña, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Jiménez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mengibar Yeguas, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Jurado, L. I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se ha pretendido conocer las características del cuidado informal que recibe el paciente IRC en programa de diálisis del CHJ. Para ello diseñamos un estudio descriptivo transversal realizado en dos etapas. Trabajamos con Profesionales, Pacientes y Cuidadores Informales, Jefes de Servicio o Unidad, Supervisores y Enfermera Responsable de Consulta y Programa de Enseñanza CAPD. Obtenemos la información mediante cuestionario entregado a cada profesional y paciente de las Unidades de Diálisis. Otro cuestionario se entregó a los cuidadores principales de pacientes. Los Jefes de Servicio, Supervisores y Enfermera Responsable de la Consulta de CAPD informaron mediante entrevista semiestructurada. Los resultados indican que la demanda de cuidados informales se corresponde con necesidad de ayuda para: 1) utilizar los servicios sanitarios;2) atender las cuestiones y actividades derivadas de la propia enfermedad renal (medicación, dieta, control de ingesta de líquidos y ganancia de peso interdiálisis; 3) preparación de las sesiones de diálisis; 4) realizar actividades instrumentales; 5) realizar actividades de la vida diaria y 6) cubrir las necesidades de autorrealización personal. Los cuidados se prestan por el núcleo familiar más cercano, siendo &#147;mujer&#148; quien normalmente ejerce de cuidadora principal. Casi la mitad no conoce la existencia de servicios sociales de ayuda y el90% no los utilizó nunca. Es importante el impacto que la tarea de cuidador ejerce sobre la vida de estas personas. Se desprende la necesidad de crear infraestructuras para facilitar la actividad educativa de los cuidadores, así como aumentar y difundir los recursos y ayudas para el cuidador informal</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Enferm. Nefrol;10(2): 55-64, abr.-jun. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76532</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aproximación a los cuidados informales de enfermos renales crónicos en el complejo hospitalario de Jaén</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6858^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
