<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166516</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">When should gestation of a gastroschisis be terminated?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. In gastroschisis pregnancies, a) to correlate prenatal ultrasound variables with postnatal outcome and b) to determine the ideal time for setting the delivery in order to achieve the best neonatal outcome. Material and methods. Retrospective review (2000-2015) of all available gastroschisis whose prenatal findings could be correlated with the neonatal outcome. Two study groups have been defined according to the complications present after birth: favorable gastrosquisis and complicated. Prenatal variables were compared by groups using McWhitney or Chi tests as needed. Results. Twenty-two gastroschisis fulfilled the requirement. Twelve cases had uneventful outcomes. Ten patients experienced complications, including death in five. In the complicated group there were 15 episodes of sepsis and 17 reoperations. Any single ultrasound parameter could predict a bad follow up. In thirteen cases, delivery was forced due to sudden changes on ultrasound bowel appearance. Nine of these patients had very good neonatal outcome. Conclusions. Finishing pregnancy when sudden changes on the fetal bowel were identified was the only strategy that leaded us to diminish the complication rate in gastroschisis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calvo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prat, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miró, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabrià, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castañón, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pertierra, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. En las gestaciones con gastrosquisis, a) valorar la presencia de algún dato ecográfico prenatal que pueda predecir la evolución postnatal de la gastrosquisis, y b) determinar el momento ideal del nacimiento de los pacientes con gastrosquisis que se relacione con una mejor evolución postnatal. Material y métodos. Revisión retrospectiva (2000-2015) de las gastrosquisis cuyos datos ecográficos prenatales hemos podido relacionar con las características de los pacientes y su evolución clínica posterior. Se han determinado dos grupos en función de la evolución favorable o complicada de la gastrosquisis. Todas las variables ecográficas prenatales se han comparado entre grupos según los test de McWitney o Chi cuadrado. Resultados. Veintidós gastrosquisis cumplieron el requisito anterior. Doce casos tuvieron una evolución sin incidencias significativas. Diez pacientes tuvieron una evolución complicada, de los cuales cinco fueron exitus. En este grupo hubo 15 episodios de sepsis y 17 reintervenciones. Ningún parámetro ecográfico prenatal predijo con fiabilidad una evolución desfavorable. En 13 casos se finalizó la gestación porque aparecieron cambios súbitos en la ecografía. Nueve de estos pacientes evolucionaron sin ninguna complicación. Conclusiones. Terminar la gestación cuando se produce un cambio súbito de la apariencia ecográfica de los intestinos fetales es la única estrategia que nos ha permitido disminuir la incidencia de complicaciones en los pacientes con gastrosquisis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;30(2): 89-94, abr. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166516</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Cuándo debe terminarse la gestación de una gastrosquisis?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12508^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3675</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33760^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11731^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29142^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
