<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116791</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Umbilical cord lactate and metabolic status in newborns with intrapatum fetal distress</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To relate lactate concentrations in umbilical cord blood and metabolic status in newborns with intrapartum fetal distress. Materials and methods: A portion of umbilical cord was obtained from term newborns to measure lactate concentrations in the umbilical artery, and pH and base deficit in theumbilical artery and vein. Results: Of 200 umbilical cords analyzed, 19 (9.5%) were from newborns with a diagnosis of nonreactive fetal status based on changes in cardiotocography (group A). Newborns without alterations were assigned to group B. Mean values of pH and base deficit of the umbilical artery and vein were significantly higher in group A than in group B (P&lt;.05). Lactate concentrations were 5.37 +/- 0.99 nmol/L in group A and 4.21 +/- 0.88 nmol/L in group B (P&lt;.05). In group A, a moderate, negative and significant association was found between lactate concentrations and base deficit in the umbilical vein (r = &#151;0,554; P&gt;,05). Conclusion: Lactate concentrations were higher in newborns with intrapartum fetal distress. These concentrations were correlated with base deficit in the umbilical vein in group A but not in group B (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aragon-Charris, Jhoan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mejia-Montilla, Jorly</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos-Bolívar, Joel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres-Cepeda, Duly</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyna-Villasmil, Nadia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyna-Villasmil, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Relacionar las concentraciones de lactato en sangre de cordón umbilical y el estado metabólico en recién nacidos con sufrimiento fetal intraparto. Materiales y métodos. Se obtuvo un segmento de cordón umbilical de recién nacidos a término para medir de las concentraciones de lactato de la arteria umbilical, el pH y el déficit de base, tanto de la arteria como de la vena umbilical. Resultados. De los 200 cordones umbilicales analizados, 19 (9,5%) pertenecían a recién nacidos con diagnóstico de estado fetal no reactivo debido a cambios en la cardiotocografía (grupo A). En el grupo B se ubicaron los recién nacidos, sin alteraciones. Los valores promedio de pH y déficit de base de la arteria y vena umbilical fueron significativamente más altos en los recién nacidos del grupo A que en los recién nacidos del grupo B (p &lt; 0,05). Las concentraciones de lactato en los recién nacidos con sufrimiento fetal (grupo A) fueron de 5,37 ± 0,99 nmol/L y en los recién nacidos sin sufrimiento fetal fue de (grupo B) fue de 4,21 ± 0,88 nmol/L (p &lt; 0,05). En los recién nacidos del grupo A, se encontró una correlación modera, negativa y significativa entre las concentraciones de lactato y el déficit de base de la vena umbilical (r = &#150;0,554; p &lt; 0,05). Conclusión. Los recién nacidos con sufrimiento fetal intraparto tienen concentraciones más elevadas de lactato y que existe una correlación entre las concentraciones y el déficit de base en la vena umbilical solo en este grupo de recién nacidos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);56(9): 447-452, nov. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116791</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lactato en sangre de cordón umbilical y estado metabólico en recién nacidos con sufrimiento fetal intraparto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7949^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5427^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14869^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14869^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5427^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7949^s22015</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25823^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25823^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14869^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25823^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201311</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
