<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99097</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To diminish inter centres variability in applied medical treatments, as well as in the results obtained with them, is one of the main challenges that Nephrology faces now a days. The systematic and planned use of Clinical Performance Measures (CPMs),Feedback and Benchmarking are tools that can help clinicians to reach such an objective. In this study we evaluate the consequences of applying those techniques in the results obtained in three haemodialysis units. Methods: We analyzed the results obtained in 311 patients dialyzed in the three units during the period 2006-2007. Established and evaluated objectives were as follows: 1.- To increase the percentage of patients with a serum calcium below 9,5mg/dl over 70%; 2.- To increase the percentage of patients with a serum phosphorus under 5,5 mg/dl over 80%; 3.- To increase the percentage of patients with a serum PTH in between 150 &#150;300 pg/ml over 40%; 4.- To diminish the percentage of patients with a serum ferritine below 100 ng/ml under 10%, in one of the units that at the beginning of the study was not accomplishing that objective. Every three months each unit received their own results as well as the results of the two other units. Results: The percentage of patients with serum calcium below9.5 mg/dl increased significantly in the three units (54.6%,56.1% and 55.6% at the beginning; 87.7%, 82.9% and 75.1%at the end of the study, respectively; p &lt; 0.001). The same was  observed for the percentage of patients with a serum phosphorus below 5,5 mg/dl (77.9%, 73.6% and 66.0% at the beginning; 81.7%, 78.0% and 85.9% at the end, respectively; p: not significant), and for the percentage of patients with PTH between 150-300 pg/ml (32.9%, 43.1% and 26.4% versus 47.5%, 41.4% and 39.5%, respectively; p: not significant). The percentage of patients with a serum ferritin below 100 ng/ml in unit B diminished from 30% to 5.3% (p &lt; 0.001), reaching results similar the the two other units. Mean erythropoietin (EPO) consumption during the year 2005 was 145.5 ± 13.2 U/kg/week in unit A; 226.2 ± 39.8 U/kg/week in unit B, and 175.5 ± 13.9 U/kg/week in unit C. At the end of year 2007, mean EPO consumption was significantly lower in unit B (144.2 ± 15 U/kg/week), and similar to the other two units (140 ± 14.2 in unit A and 135.1 ± 13.8 in unit C). Conclusion: The results of this study permit to conclude that the use of QPM´s and quality targets, combined with feedback and benchmarking, allows for the improvement of clinical results. Each centre should establish their own objectives, independently of the defined quality standards, so as to reach such standards or even to improve them. In this study, the three units showed a general improvement in their results, tending towards similar outcomes for the same clinical processes  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Malek, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arenas, MD</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Ude, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soriano, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moledous, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Uno de los retos a los que actualmente se enfrenta la Nefrología es conseguir reducir la variabilidad entre centros, tanto en la asistencia que se presta como en los resultados que obtenemos con la misma. La medición sistemática y planificada de Indicadores de Calidad, la retroalimentación(Feedback) y el Benchmarking son herramientas que nos pueden ayudar a conseguir dichos objetivos. En este estudio evaluamos la repercusión que la aplicación de esas técnicas tuvo en los resultados obtenidos en tres unidades de hemodiálisis. Métodos: Se han analizado los resultados obtenidos en311 pacientes de tres unidades de hemodiálisis, durante el periodo 2006-2007. Los objetivos establecidos y evaluados fueron: 1.- Aumentar el porcentaje de pacientes con calcio inferior a 9,5 mg/dl por encima del 70%. 2.- Aumentar el porcentaje de pacientes con fósforo inferior a 5,5 mg/dl por encima del 80%. 3.- Aumentar el porcentaje de pacientes con PTH entre 150-300 pg/ml por encima del 40%. 4.-Disminuir el porcentaje de pacientes ferropénicos (ferritina&lt; 100 ng/dl) por debajo del 10%, en una unidad que no cumplía este objetivo. Trimestralmente los resultados de los tres centros se enviaban a cada unidad. Resultados: En las tres unidades se observó un aumento significativo en el porcentaje de pacientes con calcio inferior a 9,5 mg/dl (54,6%, 56,1% y 55,6% al inicio y 87,7%,82,9% y 75,1% al final del estudio, respectivamente; p &lt;0,001). Igual sucedió con el porcentaje de pacientes con fósforo inferior a 5,5 mg/dl (77,9%, 73,6% y 66,0% al inicio y 81,7%, 78,0% y 85,9%, respectivamente; p: NS) y con el porcentaje de pacientes con PTH entre 150-300 pg/ml (32,9%, 43,1% y 26,4% frente a 47,5%, 41,4% y 39,5%, respectivamente; p: NS). En la unidad B el porcentaje de pacientes ferropénicos (ferritina &lt; 100 ng/ml) pasó del 30% a 5,3% (p &lt; 0,001), unificando los resultados con los de las otras dos unidades. El consumo medio de EPO en el año 2005 fue 145,5 ± 13,2 U/kg/semana en la unidad A, 226,2 ± 39,8 U/kg/semana en la unidad B y 175,5 ± 13,9 U/kg/semana en la unidad C; al final del año 2007 se obtuvo un consumo medio de EPO significativamente inferior en la unidad B (144,2 ± 15 U/kg/semana), similar al de las otras dos unidades (140 ± 14,2 en la unidad A, y 135,1 ± 13,8 en la unidad C). En el periodo de estudio el Índice de Resistencia a la Eritropoyetina disminuyó de 26,1 a 11,3 en la unidad B. En conclusión, este estudio demuestra que una actitud activa, basada en el uso de indicadores de calidad y el establecimiento de objetivos, la retroalimentación y el benchmarking, permite conseguir una mejora de los resultados. Independientemente de los estándares de calidad definidos, cada centro debería marcarse unos objetivos, bien para alcanzar dicho estándar o bien para mejorarlo. En general las tres unidades tendieron a mejorar sus resultados, así como a igualar los correspondientes al mismo proceso asistencial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;28(4): 397-406, jul.-ago. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99097</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Es posible mejorar nuestros resultados en hemodiálisis? Establecimiento de objetivos de calidad, retroalimentación (Feedback) y Benchmarking</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6587^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33549^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d72</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200808</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
