<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82585</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Management of high blood pressure in children and adolescents: Recommendations of the European Society of hypertension</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hypertension in children and adolescents has been gaining ground in cardiovascular medicine, mainly due to the advances made in several areas of pathophysiological and clinical research. These guidelines arose from the consensus reached by specialists in the detection and control of hypertension in children and adolescents. Furthermore, these guidelines are a compendium of scientific data and the extensive clinical experience it contains represents the most complete information that doctors, nurses and families should take into account when making decisions. These guidelines, which stress the importance of hypertension in children and adolescents, and its contribution to the current epidemic of cardiovascular disease, should act as a stimulus for governments to develop a global effort for the early detection and suitable treatment of high pressure in children and adolescents. J Hypertens 27:1719-1742 Q 2009 Wolters Kluwer Health | Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dillon, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kuznetsova, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Wühl, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schaefer, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Invitti, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruickshank, J. K</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lurbe, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mancia, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zanchetti, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rascher, W</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laurent, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Stergiou, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Redon, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferreira, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales-Olivas, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seeman, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cifkova, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hipertensión en niños y adolescentes ha ido ganando terreno en la medicina cardiovascular, gracias a los avances producidos en distintas áreas de la investigación fisiopatológica y clínica. Estas guías nacen del consenso al que han llegado los especialistas en la detección y control de la hipertensión en niños y adolescentes. Por otra parte, dichas guías son un compendio de los datos científicos y la extensa experiencia clínica con la que se cuenta, y constituyen la información clínica más completa que los médicos, enfermeras y familiares deberían tener en cuenta a la hora de tomar decisiones. Estas guías, que hacen hincapié en la importancia de la hipertensión en niños y adolescentes, así como en el papel que desempeña en la actual epidemia de enfermedades cardiovasculares, deberían constituir un estímulo para que los gobiernos desarrollaran un esfuerzo global para una detección precoz y un tratamiento adecuado de la hipertensión arterial en niños y adolescentes. J Hypertens 27:1719-1742 Q 2009 Wolters Kluwer Health | Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);73(1): 51-51[e1-e28], jul. 2010. tab, graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82585</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo de la hipertensión arterial en niños y adolescentes: recomendaciones de la Sociedad Europea de Hipertensión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1822^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201007</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
