<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78135</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Lymphangioleiomyomatosis in a post-menopausal women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Lymphangioleiomyomatosis is a rare disease characterised by pulmonary cysts with abnormal proliferation in the lymphatic system. It occurs almost exclusively in women of fertile age due to a hormonal influence, for this reason it is extremely rare in post-menopausal patients. In these cases it is usually associated to hormone replacement therapies. It is known that this diseases is strongly associated with other conditions, such as tuberous sclerosis and renal angiomyolipomas.We present a case of a post-menopausal patient suffering from lymphangioleiomyomatosis, with no history of hormone therapy, in whom were also detected renal angiomyolipomas and clinical signs indicative of a probable tuberous sclerosis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Clemente-Andrés, Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cendra-Morera, Eulalia de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soler-Ferrer, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Custal-Teixidor, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Colomer-Pairés, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Lozano, albert</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La linfangioleiomiomatosis es una enfermedad rara caracterizada por quistes pulmonares con proliferación anómala del sistema linfático. Se presenta casi en exclusiva en mujeres en edad fértil debido a una influencia hormonal, por lo que resulta sumamente infrecuente en pacientes posmenopáusicas. En estos casos suele tener relación con tratamientos hormonales sustitutivos. Es conocido que esta enfermedad tiene un alto grado de asociación con otras afecciones como la esclerosis tuberosa y los angiomiolipomas renales.Presentamos el caso de una paciente posmenopáusica afecta de linfangioleiomiomatosis, sin ningún antecedente de tratamientos hormonales, en la que se detectaron, además, angiomiolipomas renales y criterios clínicos indicativos de esclerosis tuberosa en grado de probable(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;46(3): 148-150, mar. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78135</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Linfagioleiomiomatosis en mujer posmenopáusica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31364^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11805^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31161^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14010^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2026^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31364^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31364^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
