<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104074</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sex differences in the relationship between vigorous vs. moderate intensity exercise and risk markers of overweight and obesity in healthy adults</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Several studies have extensively documented the bene&amp;#64257;ts of moderate intensity physical training for reducing the risk of cardiovascular death in the management of overweight and obesity. However, the bene&amp;#64257;ts of vigorous intensity training are small. Objective: To examine sex differences in the relationship between vigorous vs. moderate intensity exercise and risk markers for overweight and obesity in healthy adults. Methods: A cross-sectional, descriptive study in 304 healthy subjects (n = 218 men, n = 86 women). The short version of the International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ)was used to stratify exercise intensity into two categories, moderate and vigorous. Body mass index (BMI) and percent body fat (%BF) were calculated, and waist circumference (WC) was measured as risk markers of overweight and obesity. Results: No signi&amp;#64257;cant differences were found in risk markers of overweight and obesity in the male group depending on exercise intensity. As compared to women training at moderate intensity, those making vigorous exercise had lower BMI (25.7 ± 3.0 kg/m2vs.22.5 ± 1.7 kg/m2),WC (79.2 ± 6.8 cm vs. 76.0 ± 3.1 cm), and BF (33.5 ± 2.6% vs. 28.1 ± 5.3%) levels (P &lt; 0.05 forall).Conclusions: Vigorous intensity training is associated with lower values of markers of overweight and obesity in women, but not in men (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García, Sophya</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez-Vélez, Robinson</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Ruíz, Katherine</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agredo-Zúñiga, Ricardo Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción Varios estudios han documentado en forma extensa los beneficios del entrenamiento físico de moderada intensidad en la reducción del riesgo de morir por enfermedades cardiovasculares, en el control del sobrepeso y la obesidad. Sin embargo, los beneficios del entrenamiento a intensidades vigorosas son escasos. Objetivo Examinar las diferencias por sexo de la relación entre el ejercicio de intensidad vigorosa vs. intensidad moderada y marcadores de riesgo de sobrepeso y obesidad en adultos saludables. Métodos Estudio descriptivo, transversal en 304 sujetos saludables (n=218 hombres; n=86 mujeres). Se aplicó la versión corta del International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ) para estimar la intensidad de ejercicio en 2 categorías: intensidad moderada e intensidad vigorosa. Se calculó el índice de masa corporal (IMC), el porcentaje de grasa corporal (%GC) y se midió la circunferencia de cintura (CC), como marcadores de sobrepeso y obesidad. Resultados Respecto a la intensidad del ejercicio, no se encontraron diferencias significativas en los marcadores de sobrepeso y obesidad en el grupo de hombres. En comparación con el entrenamiento de moderada intensidad, las mujeres que se entrenaban a intensidad vigorosa presentaron menores valores en el IMC (25,7±3,0kg/m2 vs. 22,5±1,7kg/m2), en la CC (79,2±6,8cm vs. 76,0±3,1cm), y en el %GC (33,5±2,6% vs. 28,1±5,3%) respectivamente, P&lt;0,05.ConclusionesEl entrenamiento de intensidad vigorosa se relaciona con menores valores en los marcadores de sobrepeso y obesidad en mujeres pero no en hombres (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;59(8): 491-495, oct. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104074</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias por sexo de la relación entre ejercicio de intensidad vigorosa vs. intensidad moderada y marcadores de riesgo de sobrepeso/obesidad en adultos saludables</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30732^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
