<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162030</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Benefits of music therapy on behaviour disorders in subjects diagnosed with dementia: a systematic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Dementia is characterised by cognitive deterioration and the manifestation of psychological and behavioural symptoms, especially changes in perception, thought content, mood, and conduct. In addition to drug therapy, non-pharmacological treatments are used to manage these symptoms, and one of these latter treatments is music therapy. Since this novel technique in non-verbal, it can be used to treat patients with dementia at any stage, even when cognitive deterioration is very severe. Patients&#146; responses to music are conserved even in the most advanced stages of the disease Development. A literature research was carried out using the following databases: Academic Search Complete, PubMed, Science Direct y Dialnet. The period of publication was 2003 to 2013 and the search keywords were «Music Therapy, Dementia, Behaviour, Behaviour Disorders y Behavioural Disturbances». Out of the 2188 studies that were identified, 11 studies met inclusion criteria for the systematic review. Conclusions. Music therapy is beneficial and improves behavior disorders, anxiety and agitation in subjects diagnosed with dementia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Palomares, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González López-Arza, MV</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Mansilla, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flores-Nieto, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido-Ardila, EM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Romero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La demencia se caracteriza por un deterioro cognitivo y por la aparición de síntomas psicológicos y conductuales, entre los que destacan las alteraciones de percepción, del contenido del pensamiento, estado de ánimo y de conducta. Para tratar estos síntomas, además del tratamiento farmacológico, se utilizan intervenciones no farmacológicas, entre ellas la musicoterapia. Esta técnica novedosa, por sus características no verbales, puede ser usada en todas las fases del tratamiento de las personas con demencia ya que, aunque haya un gran deterioro cognitivo, las respuestas ante la música se mantienen hasta los estadios más avanzados de la enfermedad. Desarrollo. Se realizó una búsqueda bibliográfica con un intervalo temporal entre 2003 y 2013 en las bases de datos Academic Search Complete, PubMed, Science Direct y Dialnet. Los términos de búsqueda incluyeron la combinación de las palabras claves «music therapy, dementia, behaviour, behavioural disorders y behavioural disturbances». Se seleccionaron 11 registros de los 2188 localizados tras aplicar los criterios de inclusión. Conclusiones. El tratamiento con musicoterapia es beneficioso para mejorar las alteraciones conductuales, la ansiedad y la agitación en pacientes con demencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;32(4): 253-263, mayo 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162030</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Beneficios de la musicoterapia en las alteraciones conductuales de la demencia. Revisión sistemática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33525^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33525^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9340^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9340^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
