<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037059</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neurodevelopmental (fragile X syndrome) and neurodegenerative (tremor/ataxia syndrome) disorders associated to the &#145;growth&#146;of a gene</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To present the latest findings on fragile X syndrome, the first genetic disorder identified to be caused by a new type of mutation called trinucleotide repeat expansion.     Development. Fragile X syndrome is the most common form of inherited mental retardation, is caused by hyperexpansion and hypermethylation of a CGG repeat tract in the FMR1 gene. In the first section we will discuss the various aspects of the gene mutation and the gene product, its phenotypic consequences in mutation carriers, diagnostic methodology, epidemiology, prevention, treatment and situation in Costa Rica. The second section deals with the recent findings in relation to the very recently described fragile X premutation tremor/ataxia syndrome, a neurodegenerative disorder affecting carriers of the mutation.     Conclusions. Screening for the gene premutation in aged individuals who have tremor and balance problems is important, especially when accompanied by other signs such as parkinsonism, short term memory loss and dementia. Family genetic counselling can help those affected as well as future generations which may inherit fragile X syndrome</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castro-Volio, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuenca-Berger, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Presentar los últimos hallazgos acerca del síndrome del cromosoma X frágil, el primer trastorno genético identificado causado por un nuevo tipo de mutación llamado expansión de trinucleótidos repetidos.     Desarrollo. El síndrome del cromosoma X frágil es la causa más común de retraso mental hereditario; lo causa el aumento de la expansión y de la metilación de un segmento de repeticiones CGG en el gen FMR1. En la primera sección discutiremos varios aspectos de la mutación y del producto génico, sus consecuencias fenotípicas en los afectados con la mutación, la metodología diagnóstica, la epidemiología, la prevención, el tratamiento y la situación en Costa Rica. En la segunda sección nos referiremos al recientemente descrito síndrome premutación X frágil con temblor/ataxia, un trastorno neurodegenerativo que afecta a los portadores de la mutación.     Conclusiones. Es importante hacer una criba de la premutación del gen en adultos mayores con temblor y problemas de equilibrio, especialmente cuando se acompaña de otros signos como parkinsonismo, pérdida de memoria y demencia. El asesoramiento genético a la familia puede ser útil para los afectados y para las generaciones futuras que pueden heredar el síndrome del cromosoma X frágil</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;40(7): 431-437, abr. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037059</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos del neurodesarrollo (síndrome X frágil) y neurodegenerativos (síndrome de temblor/ataxia) asociados al &#145;crecimiento&#146; de un gen</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29836^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9611^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10833</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33354^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30613^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32588^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5735^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14595^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14065^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5735^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33354^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14595^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5928^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1267^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1267^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
