<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038857</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Differences in the Use of Family Planning Methods by Adolescent Females According to the Education</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The objective was to compare the use of familyplanning methods during the immediate postpartum period and twoyears following childbirth among the adolescent females who hadfollowed two different intervention programs during their pregnancies.Methods: A quasi-experimental study was designed. A total of62 pregnant adolescents were selected to comprised two interventiongroups, the PRECEDE model and the Health Belief model (MCS)groups. Non-parametric statistical tests were employed and 95%confidence intervals estimated.Results: The average starting knowledge in the MCS groups was69.12 points (95% CI 63.27-74.97) and ending 89.71 points (95% CI86.24- 93.17), while the starting knowledge for the PRECEDE groupwas 49.39 points (95% CI 42.24- 56.54) and ending 75.25 points(95% CI 71.12- 79.38). IN the immediate postpartum, 93% (95% CI83.5-100) of the adolescents in the PRECED group accepted the useof a family planning method similar to that employed by the MCSgroup, of 94.2 (95% CI 86.3-100). As regards the continued use ofthe method, that is, two years later, the PRECEDE strategy had a greatereffect that the MCS strategy, respectively 92% (95% CI 82-100)and 72% (95% CI 56.9-87.1).Conclusions: A difference was found to exist between models asregards the use of family planning methods 2 years following childbirth.The PRECEDE program is proposed as the education strategyfor preventing a second pregnancy among adolescent females</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alanís Salazar, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salinas Martínez, Ana María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villarreal Ríos, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez Rocha, Georgina Mayela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garza Elizondo, M. Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alanís Alanís, María de Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: El objetivo fue comparar la utilización de métodosde planificación familiar durante el puerperio inmediato y dosaños después del parto en las mujeres adolescentes que habían seguidodos programas diferentes de intervención durante su embarazo.Métodos: Se diseñó un estudio cuasiexperimental. Se seleccionóa 62 adolescentes embarazadas que se integraron en dos grupos deintervención, el modelo PRECEDE y el de Creencias en Salud(MCS). Se aplicaron pruebas estadísticas no paramétricas y se estimaronintervalos de confianza de 95%.Resultados: El promedio de conocimiento inicial en el grupoMCS fue de 69,12 puntos (IC95% 63,27-74,97) y al final 89,71 puntos(IC95% 86,24- 93,17), mientras que el inicial del grupo PRECEDEfue de 49,39 puntos (IC 95% 42,24- 56,54) y al final de 75,25puntos (IC 95% 71,12- 79,38). En el puerperio inmediato el 93% (IC95% 83,5-100) de las adolescentes del grupo PRECEDE aceptaron eluso de un método de planificación familiar, similar al empleado porel grupo MCS, de 94,2 (IC 95% 86,3-100). En cuanto a la continuidaden el uso del método, es decir dos años después, el efecto de laestrategia PRECEDE fue superior al del MCS, 92% (IC 95% 82-100) y 72% (IC 95% 56,9-87,1) respectivamente.Conclusiones: Se encontró diferencia entre modelos en lo concernientea la utilización de métodos de planificación familiar a los 2años. Se propone el programa PRECEDE como estrategia educativapara prevenir un segundo embarazo en mujeres adolescentes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;79(1): 69-77, ene.-feb. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038857</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias en la utilización de métodos de planificación familiar por mujeres adolescentes en Monterrey, México, según el modelo de  educación utilizado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5297^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11695</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38861</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
