<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037458</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vagus nerve stimulation and psychosis. A single case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The appearance of behavioral disorders in the context of a decrease in the number of seizures in epileptic patients is a fact that was already described in Landolt's theory of forced normalization in the middle of the XX century. Through this clinical case, we propose several mechanisms that aim to give a general explanation to the physiopathology of this condition. Among them, the theory which suggests increased alertness as a result of inhibitory mechanisms secondary to a long lasting epileptic condition stands out. In addition, we consider the possibility that left vagus nerve stimulation (VNS), a procedure used as a second line treatment in epileptic patients refractary to multiple drug therapy, may cause an inhibitory reaction of similar characteristics as the previously described, and could therefore lead to different psychiatric disorders. Lastly, we bring up several alternatives that will try to throw some light on the physiopathological condition that leads to the chronification of this disease, the theory regarding a cognitive deterioration associated to the appearance of negative symptoms in patients with temporal lobe epilepsy standing out</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Adán, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayuso-Mateos, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escosa, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La aparición de alteraciones del comportamiento en el contexto de una disminución en el número de crisis en pacientes epilépticos es un hecho que ya fue descrito por Landolt a mediados del siglo XX en su teoría de la normalización forzada. Aquí proponemos, a través de un caso clínico, una serie de mecanismos que pretenden explicar a grandes rasgos la fisiopatología de este fenómeno. Entre ellos destaca la teoría del aumento en el estado de alerta provocado por los mecanismos inhibitorios secundarios a una epilepsia de varios años de evolución. Por otra parte, se plantea la posibilidad de que la estimulación intermitente del nervio vago izquierdo (ENV), procedimiento empleado como terapia coadyuvante en el manejo de pacientes epilépticos refractarios a politerapia farmacológica, pueda provocar una respuesta inhibitoria de características similares, que pudiese por sí misma originar una serie de cuadros psiquiátricos. Finalmente se barajan diversas alternativas en relación con el proceso fisiopatológico que conlleva la cronificación de dicha patología, entre las cuales destaca un deterioro cognitivo asociado al desarrollo de síntomas negativos en pacientes con epilepsia del lóbulo temporal</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;33(2): 130-134, mar.-abr. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037458</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estimulación del nervio vago y psicosis. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8018^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28247^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15033^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
