<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-AOT-2134</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-8831</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical description of a severe case of phytophotodermatitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Phytophotodermatitis is a skin reaction occurring after contact of the skin with a plant in conjunction with exposure to UV irradiation. The substances most frequently involved are furocoumarines, which are usually present in Rutaceae (lemon, orange, and lime), Moraceae (fig), and Umbelliferae (carrot, celery, and parsley), among others. Such reactions manifest by erythematous urticarial plaques that can develop vesicles and blisters, simulating a burn. Contact with the plants usually causes skin lesions with linear patterns. In this report we present a clinical characterization of this condition. Case report. A 9 years old boy presented to the Emergency Department with an erythematous plaque and blisters in a linear pattern in his left leg. Two days earlier he had been playing in a field wearing shorts and exposed to the sun. The patient was admitted, the large blisters were drained and treated with potassium permanganate soaks and silver sulfadiazine cream, and he received intravenous analgesics, corticosteroids, and antihystaminics. The outcome was good and topical treatments were continued as outpatient. Evaluation of the plants in the playing field revealed the presence of Umbelliferae. Comments. Phytophotodermatitis is not a common or severe disease, but bullous lesions can be striking and mimic a burn. Diagnosis is clinical, and a high level of suspicion is required (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Patos, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Peris, Sebastiá</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carsi-Durall, Ariadna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vila-Soler, Jorgina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguadé-Borrull, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las fitofotodermatitis son aquellas reacciones cutáneas inducidas por el contacto de ciertos vegetales con la piel sumadas a la radiación ultravioleta. Las sustancias más frecuentemente implicadas suelen ser furocumarinas, presentes en rutáceas (limonero, naranjo y lima), moráceas (higuera) y umbelíferas (zanahoria, apio y perejil), entre otras. Dichas reacciones se manifiestan con placas eritematosas urticariformes sobre las que pueden llegar a formarse vesículas y ampollas, simulando una quemadura. Típicamente, el contacto con las plantas ocasiona lesiones cutáneas con patrones lineales. Este trabajo permite desarrollar las características clínicas de la entidad partiendo de un caso particular. Caso clínico. Un niño de 9 años acudió a urgencias por una placa eritematosa en la pierna izquierda sobre la que habían aparecido ampollas, y en la que se intuía una disposición lineal. Dos días antes había estado jugando en el campo y, con pantalón corto, había estado también expuesto al sol. El paciente fue hospitalizado y se procedió a la flictenectomía de las ampollas tensas de mayor tamaño, a la administración de analgésicos, corticoides y antihistamínicos por vía endovenosa, y a curas con fomentos de permanganato potásico y crema de sulfadiazina argéntica. La evolución fue favorable y el niño pudo continuar con las curas de forma ambulatoria. Revisando las plantas presentes en el campo que visitó el paciente encontramos algún ejemplar de umbelífera. Comentarios. La fitofotodermatitis es una condición infrecuente que generalmente no supone gravedad, pero las lesiones ampollosas locales pueden ser muy llamativas simulando una quemadura. El diagnóstico es fundamentalmente clínico, siendo imprescindible mantener un alto grado de sospecha (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. catalan;77(3): 97-99, jul.-sept. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-AOT-2134</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fitodermatitis. Descripción clínica de un caso florido</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
