<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82853</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Knowledge and attitudes of population on influenza A (H1N1)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The influenza A (H1N1) outbreak has been a challenge for world health systems; it has provoked significant social alarm. We do not know if the health authorities advertisements have been understood by the population. Objective. To describe the knowledge and attitudes of the population on the prevention and treatment of influenza A (H1N1). Methods. Descriptive, cross-sectional study of a population who attended their Health Centre. A self-completed questionnaire was given. Results. There were 206 responses (60% women), with a mean age 49.8±17.4 years old, of which 33.5% thought they belonged to a risk group for A (H1N1)-flu. A total of 29.13% had been immunized against usual flu last season, and 27.8% this season (7.14% against A-flu). Proper knowledge about symptoms, treatment and the need of a prescription for antivirals were 61%, 32.7% and 70.3%, respectively. There was 40.1% who said they had little or no information, getting their information mainly from television (75.7%). A total of 37.81% were quite worried or very worried about the illness, and 37.24% thought it was severe or very severe. The attitudes relating to suffering the illness were similar to seasonal flu. Conclusions. Flu vaccination coverage (especially A-flu) is low. Knowledge of A (H1N1) flu symptoms and treatment was low, and a significant percentage of the population said they had little or no information. The information is mostly taken from unofficial channels (television). Concern about the illness is not great, but there is a perception of the severity. A-flu pandemic has not changed the attitudes of the population (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Braojos-Peñas, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Guerrero, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villarín-Castro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Martín, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcázar-García, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La pandemia de gripe A ha supuesto un reto para los sistemas sanitarios mundiales, conllevando una considerable alarma social. No tenemos la seguridad de que los mensajes de las autoridades sanitarias hayan llegado adecuadamente a la población. Objetivo: describir el grado de conocimiento y las actitudes de la población sobre prevención y tratamiento de la gripe A. Métodos. Estudio descriptivo transversal por reclutamiento de usuarios mayores de edad que acuden al Centro de Salud mediante encuesta autocumplimentada elaborada ad hoc. Resultados. Doscientas seis encuestas (60% mujeres), edad media 49,8±17,4 años. El 33,5% se consideraban pertenecientes a grupos de riesgo frente a la gripe A. El 29,13% se había vacunado el año anterior frente a la gripe, por 27,8% el año actual (7,14% frente a gripe A). Los conocimientos correctos sobre síntomas, tratamiento y necesidad de receta para conseguir antivirales fueron del 61%, 32,7% y 70,3%, respectivamente. El 40,1% se consideraba poco o nada informado, obteniendo la información fundamentalmente de la televisión (75,7%). El 37,81% se consideraba bastante o muy preocupado ante la enfermedad, y el 37,24% consideraba que esta era bastante o muy grave. Las actitudes ante el padecimiento de un cuadro catarral no cambiaron respecto a la pauta habitual. Conclusiones. La cobertura vacunal es baja, especialmente ante la gripe A. La población se considera poco informada sobre síntomas y tratamiento de la gripe A. La mayor parte de la información se obtiene de medios no oficiales (televisión). El grado de preocupación y la percepción de gravedad se encuentran en niveles medios. La pandemia no ha alterado las costumbres de la población (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);36(10): 547-553, dic. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82853</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conocimientos y actitudes de la población ante la gripe A (H1N1)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51282^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23109^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51282^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
