<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128096</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of the Spanish version of the attention deficit hyperactivity disorder adult screening scale (ASRV v. 1.1): A novel scoring strategy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) is a common neuropsychiatric disorder in the adulthood. It&#146;s diagnosis is a complex process in which a screening tool can be useful. Aim. To analyze the six-question Adult ADHD Self-Report Scale (ASRS v. 1.1) validity in an outpatient clinical context. Subjects and methods. We performed a casecontrol study, involving 90 patients with ADHD and 90 controls without ADHD. They were outpatient treated in a program for adults ADHD in a hospital. The clinical disorder diagnosis was measured by the Conners Adult ADHD Diagnostic Interview. We analyzed the test accuracy for different ways to score and cut-offs. Results. We found the best psychometric characteristics of ASRS v. 1.1 using a quantitative ranking between 0 and 24 points, setting as cut-off 12 points. We observed a sensitivity of 96.7%, specificity 91.1%, positive predictive value 91.6% negative predictive value 96.5%, kappa index 0.88 and area under the curve 0.94 (odds ratio = 297.3; 95% confidence interval = 76.2-1,159). Conclusion. The ASRS is a valid and useful tool for the adult ADHD screening in the clinical context (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Roncero, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bosch, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Daigre, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palomar, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nogueira, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Quiroga, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valero, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Barros, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El trastorno por déficit de atención/hiperactividad (TDAH) es un trastorno neuropsiquiátrico frecuente en la edad adulta. Su diagnóstico supone un proceso complejo en el que la aplicación de un instrumento de cribado puede ser de gran utilidad. Objetivo. Analizar la validez del cuestionario autoinformado de cribado del TDAH en adultos ASRS v. 1.1 de seis ítems, en un contexto clínico ambulatorio. Sujetos y métodos. Se realizó un estudio de casos y controles en el cual participaron 90 pacientes con TDAH y 90 controles sin él. Fueron seleccionados en las consultas ambulatorias hospitalarias de un programa especializado de adultos con TDAH. El diagnóstico clínico del trastorno fue realizado mediante la entrevista semiestructurada CAADID. Se analizó la exactitud de la prueba para diferentes formas de puntuación y puntos de corte. Resultados. Se encuentran óptimas características psicométricas considerando los ítems del ASRS v. 1.1 de manera cuantitativa, con un rango de puntuación entre 0 y 24, estableciendo como punto de corte 12 puntos. Se observaron una sensibilidad del 96,7%, una especificidad del 91,1%, un valor predictivo positivo del 91,6%, un valor predictivo negativo del 96,5%, un índice kappa de 0,78 y un área bajo la curva de 0,94 (odds ratio = 297,3; intervalo de confianza del 95% = 76,2- 1.159). Conclusión. El ASRS es un instrumento válido y útil para la detección de pacientes adultos con TDAH en el contexto clínico ambulatorio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;48(9): 449-452, mayo 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128096</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación al español de la escala de cribado del trastorno por déficit de atención/hiperactividad en adultos (ASRS v. 1.1): una nueva estrategia de puntuación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200905</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
