<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044245</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Back school. Our experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. This study aims to know the clinical and functional profile as well as the quality of life of patients attended in the back school, their evolution at six months, their opinion and degree of satisfaction. Patients and methods. An initial appraisal was carried out with 220 patients, which included, among others, the following variables: sociodemographic, clinical, visual analogue scale (VAS), functional state (Oswestry scale), and quality of life (SF-36 test). A satisfaction and opinion questionnaire was given to all of them. At six months a clinical, functional and quality of life prospective evaluation was carried out with the 116 patients who completed the program during the first year and a half after starting the back school activity. Results. 80 % of the patients had previous history of low back pain. Mean score in the VAS was 3.93 and 3.54 at six months. We did not obtain a significant change in the mean score of the Oswestry test at the sixth month, in relation to the initial score, but we obtained it in five categories of the SF-36 test. 96 % of the patients reported being satisfied after taking part in the back school. Forty patients gave their opinions and/or suggestions in the questionnaire. Conclusions. The patients attended in the back school report high level of satisfaction and a change in their attitude towards pain. After taking part in the back school, a significant improvement in the intensiveness of pain or in making their activities of daily living is not seen, but this improvement is shown in some facets of quality of life</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Erazo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Betolaza, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinedo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los objetivos del presente trabajo son conocer el perfil clínico, funcional y de calidad de vida de los pacientes atendidos en la escuela de espalda (EE), su evolución a los 6 meses, su opinión y grado de satisfacción. Pacientes y métodos. Se realizó una valoración inicial a 220 pacientes que incluyó las siguientes variables: sociodemográficas, clínicas, escala analógica visual (EAV), situación funcional (escala Oswestry), y calidad de vida (test SF-36). Además se les entregó un cuestionario de satisfacción y opinión. A los primeros 116 pacientes que completaron el programa se les realizó de forma prospectiva una valoración clínica, funcional y de calidad de vida a los 6 meses. Resultados. Un 80 % de los pacientes tenían antecedente de lumbalgia previa. La puntuación media en la EAV fue 3,93 y de 3,54 a los 6 meses. No se obtuvo una variación significativa en las medias del Oswestry al sexto mes respecto a las iniciales, y sí en 5 categorías del SF-36. El 96 % de los pacientes refiere estar satisfecho tras su paso por la EE. Cuarenta pacientes aportaron sus opiniones y/o sugerencias en la encuesta. Conclusiones. Los pacientes atendidos en la EE refieren un alto nivel de satisfacción y cambio de actitud ante el dolor. Tras pasar por la EE no se objetiva una mejoría significativa en la intensidad del dolor o en la realización de las actividades de la vida diaria, y sí en algunas facetas de la calidad de vida</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);40(2): 59-66, mar. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044245</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Escuela de espalda. Nuestra experiencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19283</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d212</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
