<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110876</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-2399</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Transcultural adaptation into Spanish of the Nursing Activities Score</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction Assessment of nursing workload is a common practice in the daily work of nursing care. This is usually done using scales that were not designed for Spanish-speaking countries, which may not take into account the characteristics of the environments that differ from one country to another. The Nursing Activities Score (NAS) has been described as being a useful tool for measuring nursing workload among the instruments used for this measurement in intensive care units. Objective It was aimed to adapt the NAS into Spanish for its use in Spanish intensive care units. Material and methods The NAS was adapted using translation-back translation method with the participation of both native English speakers who were bilingual in Spanish, and Spanish translators with a high level of English. All of the translators worked individually. A single Spanish version of the scale was obtained, after which a pilot test was made in an Intensive Care Major Burns Unit of the University Hospital of Getafe (Madrid, Spain) with 30 patients and 30 nurses during their regular work shift. We also consulted the primary author of the original description of the NAS regarding items that caused some kind of conflict. Results Between the original scale and the result of the back-translations to English, we obtained agreement ratings of good in 73%, and appropriate in the remaining 27%. No item was considered to have bad correspondence. Conclusion We have developed a Spanish translation of the NAS that appears well matched to the original English version (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Frutos-Vivar, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinto-Rodríguez, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias-Rivera, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conde-Alonso, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferguson, N. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Sánchez, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Patiño-Freire, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fraile-Gamo, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción La valoración de las cargas de enfermería es práctica habitual en el trabajo diario de los cuidados enfermeros, y normalmente se hace utilizando escalas ajenas al medio hispanoparlante, sin tener en cuenta las características de los distintos entornos que difieren de un país a otro. Entre los instrumentos utilizados para la valoración de las cargas de trabajo en enfermería en unidades de cuidados intensivos, Nursing Activities Score (NAS) ha sido descrito como un instrumento útil para medir dichas cargas en estas unidades. Objetivo Adaptar al castellano el NAS para su uso en unidades de cuidados intensivos. Material y métodos Adaptación por el método de traducción-retraducción del NAS mediante traductores de idioma materno inglés y bilingüe (castellano), y traductores con el castellano como idioma materno y alto nivel de inglés, trabajando los traductores por separado. Se obtuvo una versión única en castellano con la que se realizó una prueba piloto en la Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos y Grandes Quemados del Hospital Universitario de Getafe (Madrid, España) con 30 pacientes y 30 enfermeros durante su turno habitual de trabajo. Se consultó, también, con el autor principal del NAS los ítems que supusieron algún tipo de conflicto. Resultados Entre la escala original y la resultante de las retrotraducciones en inglés se obtuvo una buena correspondencia en el 73% de los ítems y una correspondencia apropiada en el restante 27%; ningún ítem fue considerado con correspondencia mala. Conclusión Se ha obtenido una versión adaptada en castellano del NAS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Intensiva;24(1): 12-22, ene.-Mar. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110876</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación transcultural al castellano del Nursing Activities Score</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29745</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9922^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
