<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72383</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">An Update on Scalp Psoriasis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Between 50 % and 80 % of patients with psoriasis have involvement of the scalp. The clinical presentation of scalp psoriasis can be very varied, with disease severity ranging from mild to extremely severe. The disease may have a major psychological impact. Treatment should be tailored to each individual in order to achieve a good clinical response or blanching that lasts for as long as possible, with a safe and convenient regimen. Many different treatments have been tried: phototherapy, pulsed magnetic fields, Grenz rays,keratolytics, coal tar, antifungals, dithranol, retinoids, vitamin D analogues, corticosteroids, and systemic treatment. Ideally, for scalp psoriasis, treatment should be effective; applied in the form of a lotion, foam, or emulsion; require few applications per week; and have proven long-term safety. One such treatment is potent corticosteroids and vitamin D3 analogues in combination, which has a fast onset of action and proven long-term safety (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Umbert-Millet, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sola-Ortigosa, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Regaña, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La psoriasis del cuero cabelludo afecta al 50-80 % de los pacientes psoriásicos. Su presentación clínica puede ser muy variable: desde una enfermedad leve hasta formas muy graves. Esta condición puede provocar un gran impacto psicológico. El principal objetivo del tratamiento es individualizar el mismo en cada paciente, conseguir una buena respuesta clínica o el blanqueo mediante un tratamiento seguro y cómodo, con una respuesta lo más duradera posible. Se han usado múltiples tratamientos: fototerapia, campos magnéticos pulsátiles, rayos Grenz, queratolíticos, alquitrán de hulla, antifúngicos, ditranol, retinoides, análogos de la vitamina D, corticoesteroides y tratamiento sistémico. El perfil farmacológico ideal para tratar la psoriasis del cuero cabelludo es aquel que sea efectivo, de aplicación intermitente pocas veces por semana en forma de loción, espuma o emulsión y seguro a largo plazo, como la combinación de corticoesteroides potentes y análogos de la vitamina D3, con efecto rápido inicial y seguridad a largo plazo demostrada respectivamente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;100(7): 536-543, sept. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72383</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Psoriasis del cuero cabelludo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7808^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3061^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12002^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31723^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12002^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d287</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10987^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12918^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12918^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
