<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110492</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Maintaining residual renal function in patients on haemodialysis: 5-year experience using a progressively increasing dialysis regimen</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: In contrast to patients treated with peritoneal dialysis, those on periodical haemodialysis (HD) do not receive programmed progressive increases in dialysis dosage, nor is residual renal function taken into account in the calculation of the total dialysis prescription; rather, only dialyser clearance is factored into the equation. In 2006, we decided to establish a progressively increasing dialysis regimen at the start of renal replacement therapy, evaluating the possibility of starting with 2 sessions of HD/week when renal clearance of urea was equal to or greater than 2.5ml/min. This study summarises our experience during the first 5 years of application of this progressively increasing HD prescription and its repercussions on residual renal function. Methods: We included all patients who started periodical HD between 1/1/2006 and 30/9/2010 and remained on dialysis for more than three months. The follow-up period ended on 31/12/2010 (study end date). When a patient started HD, urea and creatinine clearance levels were measured based on urea and creatinine concentrations in blood samples taken before dialysis and in urine samples taken 24 hours prior to starting the first dialysis session of the week. If urea clearance was equal to or greater than 2.5ml/min, 2 sessions of HD per week were applied, as long as the patient's clinical situation allowed for it (according to the criteria of the attending physician). Residual renal function was analysed every 2 months until diuresis was less than 100ml/day, which is considered to be basically null. We evaluated the decrease in residual renal function, calculating the rate of decrease in  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gomis-Couto, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villacorta-Pérez, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quereda-Rodríguez-Navarro, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Lucas, Milagros</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Teruel-Briones, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: A diferencia de los pacientes tratados con diálisis peritoneal, la programación de una dosis incremental de diálisis no se considera en el enfermo tratado con hemodiálisis (HD) periódica, ni tampoco es habitual tener en cuenta la función renal residual en el cálculo de la dosis total de diálisis, asumiéndose como tal la proporcionada exclusivamente por el aclaramiento del dializador. A partir del año 2006 decidimos establecer una pauta incremental de diálisis al inicio del tratamiento renal sustitutivo, valorando la posibilidad de comenzar con 2 HD/semana cuando el aclaramiento renal de urea fuera igual o superior a 2,5 ml/min. En el presente trabajo presentamos nuestra experiencia de los primeros 5 años de aplicación de esta pauta incremental de HD y su repercusión sobre la función renal residual. Metodología: Se han incluido a todos los enfermos que iniciaron tratamiento con HD periódica entre el 1/1/2006 y el 30/9/2010, y permanecieron en diálisis más de tres meses. El seguimiento de los enfermos finalizó el 31/12/2010 (fecha de cierre del estudio). Cuando un enfermo inicia HD se determina el aclaramiento de urea y creatinina con las concentraciones de urea y creatinina en una muestra de sangre obtenida antes de la diálisis y  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;32(6): 767-776, nov.-dic. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110492</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mantenimiento de la función renal residual en hemodiálisis: experiencia de 5 años de una pauta de diálisis incremental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14953</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
