<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157587</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-031X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Standardization of pretreatment and staining technique to perform automatic human sperm morphology with asma (assisted sperm morphometry analyses)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Standardization of pretreatment and staining technique to realize morphological semen evaluation with computer-assisted sperm morphometry analysis system, with semen system analyzer SCA 5.4 (Sperm Class Analyzer, Microptic). Material and methods. Morphological analysis was performed with semen system analyzer SCA 5.4 (Microptic SL, Barcelona, Spain). The staining method was a modification of Hemacolor kit (Merck). Between 60 and 125 semen samples were chosen randomly from our laboratory. Results. Pretreatment of semen samples was a centrifugation for 5minutes at 300g, seminal plasma was rejected and the pellet was homogenized with .2mL of the seminal plasma itself. Not change in sperm morphology have been found with this pretreatment. Staining was performed with Hemacolor kit (Merck) but with some modifications. Fixer has been buffered with phosphate buffer pH 7.2 at 10%, time recommended by the manufacturer has been reduced. Fixation for 5 seconds, 30 seconds with Eosin staining and 2 seconds with staining Azur. Finally it was washed for 30 seconds with pH 7.2 phosphate buffer, as indicated by the manufacturer. After the pretreatment and staining we have got reference values for our methodology. Conclusions. An automation methodology to perform sperm morphology reduces coefficient variations of determination thereby we can increase its technical reliability and remove the subjectivity of the manual analysis. This standardization can be the first step to study the diagnostic value of advanced morphology in infertility and urological diseases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Reyes, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gris, Josep Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramis, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez, Clara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aulesa, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Estandarización de la técnica de pretratamiento y tinción para la automatización de la morfología espermática con metodología tipo computer-assisted sperm morphometry analysis, con el analizador de sémenes SCA 5.4 (Sperm Class Analyzer, Microptic). Material y métodos. La automatización de la morfología se ha realizado con el analizador de semen SCA 5.4 (Microptic S.L., Barcelona, España). El método de tinción ha sido una modificación del equipo Hemacolor (Merck). Se procesan entre 69 y 125 sémenes, los cuales han sido muestras escogidas aleatoriamente de nuestro laboratorio. Resultados. El pretratamiento de la muestra de semen escogido, debido a los resultados obtenidos, fue una centrifugación suave durante 5 min a 300g, se descarta el plasma seminal y se homogeneiza suavemente el sedimento con 0,2ml del propio plasma seminal. Este pretratamiento ya se comprobó que no artefactaba los espermatozoides. La tinción que se ha escogido es el kit Hemacolor (Merck), pero con modificaciones. Se tampona el fijador con buffer fosfato pH 7,2 al 10%, se reduce los tiempos aconsejados por el fabricante a fijación durante 5seg, tinción con eosina 30 seg y tinción con azur 2 seg. Finalmente se lava 30 seg con tampón fosfato pH 7,2, como indica el fabricante. Tras dicho pretratamiento y tinción estandarizadas se hallan los coeficientes de variación del pretratamiento y valores de referencia para nuestra metodología. Conclusiones. La automatización de la morfología espermática reduce los coeficientes de variación de la determinación, aumentando su fiabilidad técnica y eliminando la subjetividad que conlleva un análisis manual. Esta estandarización constituye el primer paso para el estudio del valor diagnóstico de la morfología avanzada en la infertilidad y en enfermedades urológicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. int. androl. (Ed. impr.);14(4): 123-130, oct.-dic. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157587</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estandarización en la técnica de pretratamiento y tinción para la realización de la morfología espermática humana automatizada tipo asma (assisted sperm morphometry analysis)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13477^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13043^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13431^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13043^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13465^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13459^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53222^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13459^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7425^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7423^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7425^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
