<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058705</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mutations in the gene encoding bone morphogenetic protein receptor 2 in patients with idiopathic pulmonary arterial hypertension</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Pulmonary arterial hypertension (PAH) is a rare disease that can have a familial component. It has been shown that more than 50% of cases of familial PAH are associated with mutations in the gene encoding bone morphogenetic protein receptor 2 (BMPR2), which acts as a receptor for members of the transforming growth factor Beta superfamily. Some studies in patients with idiopathic PAH have also shown varying percentages of mutations in this gene. The aim of this study was to determine the frequency of these mutations in a group of patients with idiopathic PAH.         Patients and methods: The study population included patients with idiopathic PAH who were seen during 2006 in our unit specialized in this entity. Patients were excluded if they had relatives who had been diagnosed with PAH or who had symptoms that led to suspicion of the disease. Diagnosis was obtained according to the protocol used in our unit. A hemodynamic study was carried out in all cases and patients were included if they had a mean pulmonary arterial pressure of greater than 25 mm Hg. DNA was extracted from peripheral leukocytes and amplified by polymerase chain reaction. Seventeen primer pairs were used for the 13 exons that make up the gene. Using the single strand conformational polymorphism (SSCP) technique we detected anomalous DNA fragments for subsequent sequencing.                 Results: The study included 8 patients (4 women). In 5 patients, no abnormalities were observed, whereas in the remaining 3, anomalous electrophoresis patterns were obtained in the SSCP and sequencing revealed mutations. In 1 case, 2 different electrophoresis patterns were observed by SSCP, but it was only possible to sequence 1 of them due to the low concentration of DNA obtained.                 Conclusions: The presence of mutations in the gene encoding BMPR2 is not infrequent in patients with idiopathic PAH, suggesting that this family of growth factors may be important in the pathogenesis of the disease and could have therapeutic implications</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Baloira, Adolfo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilariño, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leiro, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valverde, Diana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: La hipertensión arterial pulmonar (HAP) es una enfermedad poco frecuente que puede tener un componente familiar. En este caso se ha comprobado que un porcentaje superior al 50% se asocia a mutaciones en el gen que codifica el receptor tipo 2 de las proteínas morfogenéticas del hueso (BMPR2), un receptor de la superfamilia del factor transformador del crecimiento beta. Algunos estudios en pacientes con HAP idiopática también muestran porcentajes variables de mutaciones en este gen. El objetivo de nuestro trabajo ha sido conocer la frecuencia de estas mutaciones en nuestros pacientes con HAP idiopática.                 Pacientes y métodos: Los pacientes con HAP idiopática seguidos en nuestra unidad de HAP durante el año 2006 constituyeron la población de estudio. Se excluyó la existencia de familiares con diagnóstico de esta enfermedad o síntomas que pudieran hacer pensar en ella. El diagnóstico de HAP fue acorde con el protocolo utilizado en la unidad. En todos los casos se realizó estudio hemodinámico y se incluyó a pacientes con presión arterial pulmonar media mayor de 25 mmHg. Se efectuó extracción del ADN de los leucocitos periféricos y se amplificó mediante la técnica de reacción en cadena de la polimerasa. Se utilizaron 17 parejas de cebadores para los 13 exones que componen el gen. Mediante técnica de conformación de hebra simple y electroforesis posterior se detectaron los fragmentos anómalos, para posteriormente proceder a la secuenciación del gen mediante un lector automático.                 Resultados: Se estudió a 8 pacientes (4 mujeres). En 5 de ellos no se encontraron alteraciones, pero 3 mostraron patrones anómalos en la electroforesis y en la secuenciación se observaron mutaciones. En uno de los casos se presentaron 2 patrones anómalos en la electroforesis, pero sólo fue posible secuenciar uno de ellos por la baja concentración del ADN recogido.                 Conclusiones: La presencia de mutaciones en el gen que codifica BMPR2 no es infrecuente en pacientes con HAP idiopática, lo que probablemente indique un papel importante de esta familia de factores de crecimiento en la patogenia de la enfermedad y, por tanto, podría tener implicaciones terapéuticas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;44(1): 29-34, ene. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058705</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mutaciones en el gen que codifica BMPR2 en pacientes con hipertensión arterial pulmonar esporádica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7155^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6297</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23644</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9346^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200801</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
