<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039561</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Potential benefits of living donor kidney transplantation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Living donor kidney transplantation is the best therapeutic option for endstage renal failure. In spite of being an underused option in our country, it acquires an important role reducing the waiting lists for transplantation because cadaver donation is not enough. Living donor kidney transplantation offers multiple advantages when compared with cadaver donor transplantation: longer graft and patient survival on the short, mid and long-term; the fact that a scheduled procedure allows us to optimize donor and receptor´s conditions; and ischemia time between nephrectomy and transplantation can be shortened to a minimum. A good initial function without need of dialysis (up to 90%) and lower incidence of rejection, which diminishes the need of antirejection drugs, should also be emphasized</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alcover García, Juan B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corral Molina, Juan M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luque Gálvez, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El trasplante renal de donante vivo es lamejor opción terapeútica en la insuficiencia renal terminal,y aunque en nuestro país ha sido una opcióninfrautilizada, adquiere un papel importante en lareducción de las listas de espera para trasplante, puestoque la donación de cadáver es insuficiente. El trasplanterenal de donante vivo ofrece múltiples ventajasrespecto al de cadáver: mayor supervivencia del injertoy receptor a corto, medio y largo plazo, el hecho deser un procedimiento programado permite optimizar lascondiciones del donante y receptor, así como disminuiral mínimo el tiempo de isquemia entre la nefrectomía yel implante. Además, destaca la buena función inicial (hasta un 90% ) sin necesidad de diálisis y la menorincidencia de rechazo, lo cual disminuye la necesidadde fármacos para prevenir el rechazo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;58(6): 485-489, jul.-ago. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039561</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Potenciales beneficios del trasplante renal de donante vivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
