<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124951</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Teh family sceno-test: toward a qualitative and quantitative coding system</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present work illustrates a way of administering a semi-standardized version of the Sceno-Test, together with a scoring system that was developed ad hoc within a family framework. The indices of which the coding is composed are both of qualitative and quantitative nature, and their goal is to guarantee the intersubjectivity of the scoring as well as to validate the use of the test itself. The two levels of scoring can be utilized separately or conjointly, or even some specific components can be employed. The final presentation of a clinical case exemplifies the scoring system with particular reference to its quantitative level, and it illustrates the use of the test in the context of family interventions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Margola, Davide</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perez Testor, Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo presenta una modalidad de administración semi-estandarizada del Esceno-test, junto con su codificación, para el grupo familiar. Los indicadores de que se compone la codificación son tanto cualitativos como cuantitativos, y tratan de asegurar la inter-subjetividad de la codificación y la validez de aplicación del mismo test. Los dos niveles de codificación pueden utilizarse por separado o conjuntamente, o simplemente pueden utilizarse algunos componentes específicos. La presentación final de un caso clínico muestra un ejemplo de la codificación con referencia particular al nivel cuantitativo e ilustra la utilización del test en el contexto de la intervención familiar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(23): 67-75, ene.-jun. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124951</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El esceno-Test familiar, una propuesta de sistema de codificación cuali-cuantitativa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52882^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
