<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152852</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cost analysis of biologic drugs in rheumatoid arthritis first line treatment after methotrexate failure according to patients&#146; body weight</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The objective was to assess the influence of patients&#146; weight in the cost of rheumatoid arthritis treatment with biologic drugs used in first line after non-adequate response to methotrexate. Patients and method. Pharmaceutical and administration costs were calculated in two scenarios: non-optimization and optimization of intravenous (IV) vials. The retrospective analysis of 66 patients from a Spanish 1,000 beds-hospital Rheumatology Clinic Service was used to obtain posology and weight data. The study time horizon was two years. Costs were expressed in 2013 euros. Results. For an average 69kg-weighted patient the lowest cost corresponded to abatacept subcutaneous (SC ABA) (&#128;21,028.09) in the scenario without IV vials optimization and infliximab (IFX) (&#128;20,779.29) with optimization. Considering patients&#146; weight in the scenario without IV vials optimization infliximab (IFX) was the least expensive drug in patients ranged 45-49kg, IV ABA in 50-59kg and SC ABA in patients over 60kg. With IV vials optimization IFX was the least expensive drug in patients under 69kg and SC ABA over 70kg. Conclusions. Assuming comparable effectiveness of biological drugs, patient's weight is a variable to consider, potentials savings could reach &#128;20,000 in two years (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Canal, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Román Ivorra, José Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oyagüez, Itziard</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Barrera, Manueld</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monte-Boquet, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ivorra, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Evaluar la influencia del peso de los pacientes en el coste de tratamiento de la artritis reumatoide con fármacos biológicos indicados en primera línea tras respuesta inadecuada a metotrexato. Pacientes y método. Se incluyeron costes farmacológicos y de administración considerando no optimización y optimización de viales de los fármacos intravenosos. Los datos de posologías y peso de pacientes se obtuvieron de forma retrospectiva de 66 pacientes atendidos en un servicio de Reumatología Clínica de un hospital terciario en España. El horizonte temporal del estudio fue de 2 años. Los costes se expresaron en euros de 2013. Resultados. En un paciente promedio de 69kg de peso, abatacept subcutáneo (ABA SC) fue el fármaco de menor coste (21.028,09 &#128;) sin optimización de viales, e infliximab (IFX) (20.779,29 &#128;) con optimización de viales. Considerando el peso de los pacientes, sin optimización de viales, IFX fue menos costoso en pacientes de 45-49kg, ABA intravenoso en pacientes de 50-60kg y ABA SC en pacientes &amp;#8805; 60kg. Con optimización de viales IFX sería menos costoso en pacientes &lt; 70kg y ABA SC pacientes &amp;#8805; 70kg. Conclusiones. Suponiendo efectividad comparable de fármacos biológicos, el peso de los pacientes es una variable relevante, pudiendo alcanzarse ahorros potenciales superiores a 20.000 &#128; en pacientes de más de 100kg de peso en 2 años de tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);12(3): 123-129, mayo-jun. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152852</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de costes de la utilización de fármacos biológicos para la artritis reumatoide en primera línea de tratamiento tras respuesta inadecuada a metotrexato en función del peso de los pacientes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54219^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30152^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55983^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54219^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55169^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1860^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55973^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1178^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1178^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55973^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16645</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28169^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55983^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1178^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
