<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148203</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The construct of cognitive reserve attempts to explain why some individuals with brain impairment, and some people during normal ageing, can solve cognitive tasks better than expected. This study aimed to estimate cognitive reserve in a healthy sample of people aged 65 years and over, with special attention to its influence on cognitive performance. For this purpose, it used the Cognitive Reserve Scale (CRS) and a neuropsychological battery that included tests of attention and memory. The results revealed that women obtained higher total CRS raw scores than men. Moreover, the CRS predicted the learning curve, short-term and long-term memory, but not attentional and working memory performance. Thus, the CRS offers a new proxy of cognitive reserve based on cognitively stimulating activities performed by healthy elderly people. Following an active lifestyle throughout life was associated with better intellectual performance and positive effects on relevant aspects of quality of life (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Roldán-Tapia, Lola</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-García, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El constructo de reserva cognitiva intenta explicar por qué algunos sujetos con patología cerebral o durante el proceso de envejecimiento normal pueden ejecutar tareas cognitivas a un nivel superior al esperado. Los objetivos del presente estudio abarcan la estimación de reserva cognitiva en sujetos sanos a partir de los 65 años y su repercusión a nivel cognitivo. Para ello, se empleó la Escala de Reserva Cognitiva (ERC) y una batería neuropsicológica que englobaba tareas mnésicas y atencionales. Los resultados revelaron que las mujeres obtuvieron mayor puntuación directa en la ERC. Además, la ERC predijo la ejecución en tareas de memoria (curva de aprendizaje y recuerdos a corto plazo y a largo plazo), pero no predijo las puntuaciones en memoria de trabajo ni en atención. Así, la ERC ofreció una estimación de reserva cognitiva, basada en el estilo de vida, en sujetos sanos mayores. Mantener un estilo de vida activo a lo largo de los años favorece la ejecución intelectual y repercute positivamente en facetas relevantes para la calidad de vida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;32(1): 218-223, ene. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148203</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55451</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
