<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130014</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Umbillical repositioning in TRAM flap</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A new method of umbilical repositioning by incising the anterior rectus sheath and rectus abdominis muscle is reported for cases of unilateral abdominal wall plication during the TRAM flap operation. This method does not weaken the contralateral abdominal muscles, keeps the umbilicus stable and nonstenotic, and it avoids hypertrophic scars. With this technique, patients have normal abdominal strength, performing abdominal strain and general exercise without areas of weakness in the abdominal wall (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Raveh, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuente del Campo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gordon, C. B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Describimos un método simple para reubicar el ombligo en los casos de plicatura abdominal unilateral consecutiva a la rotación de un colgajo TRAM. El ombligo se desplaza a lo largo de una incisión hecha en la aponeurosis anterior del músculo recto abdominal contralateral. Este procedimiento no debilita la musculatura abdominal contralateral, mantiene el ombligo estable, sin estenosis, y evita la formación de cicatrices hipertróficas a su alrededor. Tras este procedimiento los pacientes conservan una resistencia abdominal normal, pudiendo realizar esfuerzo y ejercicio sin manifestar áreas de debilidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;40(3): 295-298, jul.-sept. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130014</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reubicación del ombligo al realizar un colgajo TRAM</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30961^s22070</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14871^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55182^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55026^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
