<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122459</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Predictive risk factors for failure to induction therapy of lupus nephritis in a cohort of Colombian patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To determine the predictors of failure to obtain remission after induction therapy for proliferative lupus nephritis in a group of northwestern Colombian patients. Material and methods: A retrospective study was conducted. We included patients with systemic lupus erythematosus according to the American College of Rheumatology criteria who had nephritis confirmed by renal biopsy. Results: We followed 84 patients: 88.1% female, and 11.9% male. The mean age at diagnosis of systemic  lupus erythematosus was 27.5 ± 11.8 years (9-70). The average time between diagnosis of systemic lupus erythematosus and proliferative nephritis onset was 13.6 months (0-168). Histopathologic type: iv (78.57%), iii (15.47%), iii-iv/v (5.96%). Activity index: 6.7 ± 4.6. Chronicity index: 2 ± 2.7. 24-hour proteinuria (mg): 6,164 (130-18,100). Baseline creatinine: 1.14 mg/dL (0.43-7.4). Induction therapy: Steroids (100%), cyclophosphamide (76.2%) and mycophenolate mofetil (23.8%). At six months, 56% of individuals failed to   chieve partial or complete remission. Predictors of failure to induction therapy were, in accordance with the bivariate analysis (OR; 95% CI): creatinine level more than 1.2 mg/dL (10.8; 3.18-36.84; P &lt; .005), nephrotic range proteinuria (11.9; 3.09-45.8; P &lt; .001), and an activity index above 8 (5.04; 1.7-14.3; P &lt; .001). In the multivariate analysis, only baseline creatinine higher than 1.2 mg/dL (10.92; 2.65-45.02; P = .001), and nephrotic range proteinuria (9.81; 1.85-52.04; P = .007) were significant. Conclusions: A significant percentage of Colombian patients fail to achieve remission of proliferative lupus nephritis after six months of treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castro Mercado, Inis Lizeth</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez Hernández, Javier Darío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinto Peñaranda, Luis Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velásquez Franco, Carlos Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Duque Cabellero, Vladimir</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Determinar los predictores de falla a la inducción de remisión de la nefritis lúpica proliferativa en pacientes del noroccidente colombiano. Material y métodos: Estudio pragmático con análisis retrospectivo. Se incluyeron sujetos con lupus eritematoso sistémico por criterios del American College of Rheumatology con nefritis confirmada por biopsia renal.  Resultados: Se analizaron 84 pacientes (88,1% mujeres y 11,9% hombres). Edad al diagnóstico del lupus eritematoso sistémico: 27,5 ± 11,8 a&#152;nos (9-70). Tiempo entre el diagnóstico de lupus eritematoso y nefritis proliferativa: 13,6 meses (0-168). Clase histológica: iv (78,57%), iii (15,47%), iii-iv/v (5,96%). Índice de actividad: 6,7 ± 4,6. Índice de cronicidad: 2 ± 2,7. Proteinuria (mg/24 h): 6.164 (130-18.100). Creatinina basal: 1,14 mg/dl (0,43-7,4). Terapia de inducción: esteroides (100%), ciclofosfamida (76,2%) y micofenolato mofetil (23,8%). A los 6 meses fallaron en lograr remisión parcial o completa el 56% de los individuos. Los predictores  e falla a la terapia de inducción fueron, en el análisis bivariado (OR; IC 95%): creatinina mayor 1,2 mg/dl (10,8; 3,18-36,84; p &lt; 0,005), proteinuria en rango nefrótico (11,9; 3,09-45,8; p &lt; 0,001) e índice de actividad mayor de 8 (5,04; 1,7-14,3; p &lt; 0,001). En el análisis multivariado solo fueron significativos creatinina basal mayor de 1,2 mg/dl (OR: 10,92; IC 95%: 2,65-45,02; p = 0,001) y la proteinuria en rango nefrótico (OR: 9,81; IC 95%: 1,85-52,04; p = 0,007). Conclusiones: Un porcentaje significativo de pacientes colombianos con nefritis lúpica proliferativa fallanen lograr remisión a los 6 meses (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);10(3): 147-151, mayo-jun. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122459</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores de riesgo predictores de falla a la terapia de inducción de nefritis lúpica en una cohorte de pacientes colombianos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3421^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8356^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11946^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19333^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19233^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
