<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160748</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neurogenic ppendicopathy. A report of 8 cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Neurogenic appendicopathy is not a very well-known disease. Objective: To analyze the experience in the management of neurogenic appendicopathy in a tertiary hospital, assessing its clinical presentation, histological staging, the treatment carried out and its clinical evolution. Method: The study population included patients with histopathological criteria for neurogenic appendicopathy who did not present with MEN 2B syndrome, neurofibromatosis type I or Cowden syndrome. An analysis was carried out of tissue samples taken from a simple appendectomy after a diagnosis of neurogenic appendicopathy between 2000 and 2013, inclusive. The histopathological criteria were neurogenic hyperplasia with S-100 protein positivity and neuron-specific enolase in the immunohistochemical analysis. Results: Of the 4,969 samples from the appendectomies analyzed, 0.16% (n = 8) met histopathological criteria of neurogenic appendicopathy. The age at presentation was 27.8 ± 12 years. Four patients were male and four were female. All patients started with abdominal pain in the right iliac fossa (RIF), and were operated on due to a diagnosis of acute appendix, with a simple appendectomy being performed. In four cases, another associated disease accounted for the pain in the RIF. With regard to histopathological type, submucosal neurogenic hyperplasia was present in five patients and fibrous obliteration in three patients. No statistically significant differences were found between the histological types. After surgery, during a mean follow up of 73.2 ± 28 months (15-105), all the patients remained asymptomatic. Conclusion: Neurogenic appendicopathy is an uncommon entity that can evolve as abdominal pain which is similar to acute appendix. Simple appendectomy is curative (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Parrilla, Pascual</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ríos, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oviedo, María Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la apendicopatía neurogénica es una patología poco conocida. Objetivo: analizar la experiencia en el manejo de la apendicopatía neurogénica en un hospital de tercer nivel, valorando su presentación clínica, su estadio histológico, el tratamiento realizado y su evolución clínica. Método: la población a estudio estuvo formada por pacientes con criterios histopatológicos de apendicopatía neurogénica que no presentaran síndrome de MEN IIb, neurofibromatosis tipo I ni enfermedad de Cowden. Se realizó un análisis de las piezas de apendicectomía simple con el diagnóstico de apendicopatía neurogénica entre los años 2000 y 2013 inclusive. Los criterios histopatológicos fueron hiperplasia neurogénica con positividad en la inmunohistoquímica para la proteína S-100 y enolasa neuronal específica. Resultados: de las 4.969 piezas de apendicectomía analizadas, el 0,16% (n = 8) tenía criterios histopatológicos de apendicopatía neurogénica. La edad de presentación fue de 27,8 ± 12 años. Cuatro pacientes fueron varones y otros cuatro fueron mujeres. Todos debutaron con dolor abdominal en fosa iliaca derecha (FID) y se intervinieron con el diagnóstico de apendicitis aguda, realizando una apendicectomía simple. En cuatro casos se asoció otra patología que justificaba el dolor en FID. Respecto al tipo histopatológico, la hiperplasia neurogénica submucosa tuvo lugar en cinco pacientes y la obliteración fibrosa en tres pacientes. No se objetivaron diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre los tipos histológicos. Tras la cirugía, durante un seguimiento medio de 73,2 ± 28 meses (15-105) todos los pacientes permanecen asintomáticos. Conclusión: la apendicopatía neurogénica es una entidad infrecuente que puede cursar con dolor abdominal similar a una apendicitis aguda. La apendicectomía simple es curativa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;109(3): 180-184, mar. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160748</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Apendicopatía neurogénica. A propósito de 8 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1069^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1775^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7144^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1068^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1069^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1069^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7144^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1775^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1775^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1070^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1070^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
