<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78289</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hazard Analysis and Critical Control Point in pharmacies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to identify the hazards and critical control points in the operational processes of pharmacies with the aim of improving the quality of care. Material and methods: the pharmacies of Murcia were analysed and actions were defi ned in accordance with international standard UNE-EN-ISO 9001:2000. After defi ning the organisational structure of the pharmacy, the process map was created, and the Hazard Analysis and Critical Control Point tool was applied to identify the critical points of the operational processes and to establish preventive, control and corrective actions. Results: Dispensing: the most critical points (MCPs) identifi ed affect the initial communication with the patient (due to lack of time), the selection of the medicine and the information provided to the patient. The preventive measures include verifi cation with the patient to avoid hazards to his/her health. Pharmaceutical indication: there is a need for motivation and an improvement in the organisational structure of the pharmacy, in order to control most of the hazards identifi ed. Pharmacotherapeutic Follow-up: the most critical point (MCP) identifi ed is the pharmacist&#146;s lack of motivation to provide the service and, thereafter, the tiredness effect. The following are also MCPs: lack of time, not having the necessary resources, data collection errors (mainly during the fi rst interview), the patient&#146;s attitude towards the acceptance of the intervention, the doctor&#146;s failure to collaborate or mistakes by the pharmacist when drawing up the action plan. Management of magistral formulae and offi cial preparations: many of the critical control points concern hazards like the lack of technical and human resources, errors in the preparation and labelling, or in the information provided to the patient. Purchases: the critical points identifi ed are directed at the patient receiving the medication when required in optimum conditions of preservation. That thus translates into a correct: stock control; control of orders placed by patients; and the meticulous receipt of the order (quantity, preservation guidelines, missing items, charges, etc.). Storage: the critical points indentifi ed are the control of the stock, the expiry dates and the storage regulations. Conclusions: the custody and storage of medicines have since 1990 been governed by the Spanish Medicines Law, but today still there are certain ongoing points for improvement regarding the said regulation. That is also true of the Magistral Formulation governed by RD 175/2001. The dispensing processes, pharmaceutical indication and pharmacotherapeutic follow-up still require protocols, a fi nal standardisation and subsequent implementation, in accordance with the most recently published consensus on pharmaceutical care. It&#146;s also necessary the development of a complete plan of quality and pharmaceutical care(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sierra Alarcón, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Martínez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Jiménez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Identificar los peligros y puntos críticos de control en los procesos operativos de la ofi cina de farmacia para mejorar la calidad asistencial. Material y métodos: Se realizó un diagnóstico de las ofi cinas de farmacia de Murcia, y se defi nieron acciones de acuerdo con la norma internacional UNE-EN-ISO 9001:2000. Tras defi nir la estructura organizativa de la farmacia, se realizó el mapa de procesos, y se aplicó la herramienta de Análisis de Peligros y Puntos Críticos de Control para identifi car los puntos críticos de los procesos operativos y atribuirle acciones preventivas, de control y correctivas. Resultados: Dispensación: Los principales puntos críticos identifi cados afectan a la comunicación inicial con el paciente (por falta de tiempo), a la selección del medicamento y a la información proporcionada al paciente. Las medidas preventivas pasan por la verifi cación con el paciente, con el propósito de no obviar los peligros para su salud. Indicación farmacéutica: Necesitan motivación y mejora en la estructura organizativa de la farmacia, para controlar la mayoría de los peligros identifi cados. Seguimiento farmacoterapéutico: El principal punto crítico identifi cado es la falta de motivación del farmacéutico en ofrecer el servicio, seguido del efecto cansancio. Son también puntos críticos la falta de tiempo, no disponer de recursos necesarios, los errores en la toma de datos (primera entrevista sobre todo), la actitud del paciente para aceptar la intervención, la no colaboración del médico o la equivocación del farmacéutico al realizar el plan de actuación. Gestión de fórmulas magistrales y preparados ofi cinales: Han sido numerosos los puntos de control que atienden a peligros como la falta de recursos técnicos y humanos, los fallos en la elaboración y el etiquetado, o en la información aportada al paciente. Compras: Los puntos críticos identifi - cados se orientan a que el paciente disponga del medicamento cuando lo necesite en condiciones óptimas de conservación: control de stock, control de encargos realizados por pacientes y  recepción minuciosa del pedido (cantidad, normas de conservación, faltas, cargos&#133;). Almacenamiento: Los puntos críticos identifi cados son el control de stock, de las caducidades y de las normas de almacenamiento. Conclusiones: Desde la publicación de la Ley del Medicamento de 1990, que obligaba a la custodia y el almacenamiento de medicamentos, hoy día todavía se siguen encontrando puntos de mejora en el mantenimiento de los requisitos legales. En estas mismas circunstancias se encuentra la Formulación Magistral regulada por el RD 175/2001. En el caso de los procesos de dispensación, indicación farmacéutica y seguimiento farmacoterapéutico, aún está por establecer su protocolización, su estandarización defi nitiva y su posterior implantación, según los últimos consensos de atención farmacéutica publicados, haciéndose necesario el desarrollo de un plan integral de calidad y atención farmacéutica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;11(3): 102-113, sept. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78289</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de peligros y puntos críticos de control en la oficina de farmacia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10112^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10797^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10797^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6896^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
