<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118848</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8799</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quantification of caffeine from urine in Spanish triathletes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The ingestion of caffeine is also common in a specific group of people as are athletes, in order to improve athletic performance although from January 1st 2004, caffeine has been removed from the World Anti Doping Agency list of prohibited substances. The use of rapid and easy solid-phase extraction for caffeine extraction followed by liquid chromatography is useful to evaluate the presence in urine samples. Purpose: To investigate the presence of caffeine in urine samples from Spanish competitive triathletes using a new easy and fast caffeine extraction method followed HPLC-UV detection. Methods: Samples were extracted from urine in a reversed-phase C18 Sep-Pak Classic cartridge followed by HPLC coupled in the UV detector. &amp;#946;-hydroxyteofiline was used as internal standard. Twenty-six Spanish elite men triathletes with age 24.4&#150;25.9were studied. Urine samples were collected after competition. Results: The extraction method followed HPLC-UV detection has a limit of detection and recovery of 0.05 &amp;#956;g mL-1 and 92.8%, respectively. Twenty-six urine samples from triahtletes were analyzed after competitions detecting in 80.8% values of caffeine that ranged from 0.06 to 1.99 &amp;#956;g mL-1. The percentage of urine samples below the LOD (reflected as negative samples) was 19.2%.Conclusions: The optimized method is useful for the analysis of caffeine in human urine which provided an adequate cost-benefits ratio for routine analysis of this compound; its valuable features are sufficient sample throughput, robustness, precision and minimal sample handling. Its application in reals samples demonstrated the presence of caffeine in urine but any studied triathletes showed values above the former WADA cut-off (12 &amp;#956;g mL-1) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sebastià, Natividad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Daries, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escriva, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mañes, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soriano, José Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La ingesta de cafeína sigue siendo común entre los atletas con el objetivo de mejorar su rendimiento deportivo, aunque desde el 1 de enero de 2004, la cafeína ha sido eliminado de la lista de sustancias prohibidas de la Agencia Mundial Antidopaje, aunque está consensuado no sobrepasar ciertos límites (12 &amp;#956;g mL-1) por los efectos secundarios producidos por esta. El uso de una rápida y fácil extracción en fase sólida para la cafeína seguido de cromatografía líquida es útil para evaluarla presencia en muestras de orina. Propósito: Investigar la presencia de cafeína urinaria de triatletas españoles usando una nueva extracción en fase sólida rápida y fácil seguido de cromatografía líquida acoplada a detección de ultravioleta (CL-UV). Métodos: Las muestras urinarias se extrajeron con un cartucho Sep-Pak de fase extractiva C18 seguido por CL-UV siendo utilizada la &amp;#946;-hidroxiteofilina como estándar interno. Se estudió veintiséis triatletas españoles de nivel competitivo de edades comprendidas entre 24,4 y 25,9 años. Las muestras urinarias se recogieron después de la competición. Resultados: El método de extracción optimizado tiene un límite de detección una recuperación de 0,05 &amp;#956;g mL-1 y 92,8%, respectivamente. Se detectó la presencia de cafeína urinaria en un 80,8% de los triatletas estudiados con un rango de 0,06 a 1,99 &amp;#956;g mL-1. El porcentaje de muestras urinarias por debajo del LD (expresado como muestras negativas) fue de un 19,2%. Conclusiones: El método optimizado es útil para el análisis de cafeína urinaria proporcionando una adecuada relación coste beneficio para el análisis rutinario de este compuesto; las características del método son su adecuada robustez, precisión y manejo de la muestra mínima. Su aplicación en muestras reales ha demostrado la presencia de cafeína en orina, pero ninguno de los triatletas superaba el punto de corte establecido por la Agencia Mundial Antidopaje (12 &amp;#956;g mL-1) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. med. deporte;30(153): 21-24, ene.-feb. 2013. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118848</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuantificación de cafeína en orina de triatletas españoles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54180^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52435^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2902^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2143^s22050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4360</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
