<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056195</identifier>
<setSpec>0465-546X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There is evaluated the Protocol of Sanitary Specific    Alertness of Labour Asthma in six dimensions    of theoretical quality by means of the application of    the Instrument AGREE. For it there is established a    panel of four assessors by experience in different    areas of the Medicine of the Work.    Results: The Instrument AGREE was demonstrated    valid for the evaluation of this protocol existing    an agreement among assessors so much in the    strong like weak points of the protocol. The Aplicabilidad    of his recommendations and the Participation    of the implied ones appeared as the weakest points of    the protocol and very improvably in the scientific    Rigor. The publishing independence and the Scope    and Aims appeared as the strongest points of the protocol.    Conclusions: a review of the protocol Should be    realized on the basis of Guides or Guidelines of production    recommended by qualit institutions and    directed as a priority to improving the evidence and    aplicabilidad of his recommendations, likewise the    protocol must be the sufficiently documented to    allow his reproducibility</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Maqueda, Jerónimo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Buendía, M. Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roel, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se evalúa el Protocolo de Vigilancia Sanitaria    Específica de Asma Laboral en seis dimensiones de    calidad teórica mediante la aplicación del Instrumento    AGREE. Para ello se establece un panel de cuatro    evaluadores con experiencia en diferentes ámbitos de    la Medicina del Trabajo.    Resultados: El Instrumento AGREE se demostró    válido para la evaluación de este protocolo existiendo    un acuerdo entre evaluadores tanto en los puntos    fuertes como débiles del protocolo. La Aplicabilidad    de sus recomendaciones y la Participación de los    implicados se mostraron como los puntos más débiles    del protocolo y Muy mejorable en el Rigor    científico. La independencia editorial y el Alcance y    Objetivos se mostraron como los puntos más fuertes    del protocolo.    Conclusiones: Debería realizarse una revisión    del protocolo en base a Guías o Pautas de elaboración    recomendadas por instituciones de Calidad y    dirigida prioritariamente a mejorar la evidencia y    aplicabilidad de sus recomendaciones, así mismo el    protocolo debe estar lo suficientemente documentado    para permitir su reproducibilidad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;52(205): 13-21, dic. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056195</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de evaluación del protocolo de vigilancia sanitaria específica del asma laboral mediante el instrumento Agree</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28442</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
