<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163992</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Selective uterine artery embolization in the management of postpartum haemorrhage. Results at our centre</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To review the patients who presented to our hospital with postpartum haemorrhage and were treated with interventional radiology procedures since the introduction of this technique 6 years ago. Subjects and methods:  We collected data from all postpartum haemorrhages treated with arterial embolization at our hospital (n = 18) between 2009 and 2014. Results:  Our success rate was 88.24% and the overall rate of obstetric hysterectomy after embolization was 11.76%. Conclusions:  Approximately 5-15% of deliveries are complicated by postpartum haemorrhage, which is the most important isolated cause of maternal mortality. There are specific protocols in each centre, interventional radiology being an alternative treatment to hysterectomy. The number of emergency hysterectomies decreased in our hospital after the introduction of the technique. Although infrequent, the complications of this technique are not negligible, and long-term studies are needed to evaluate fertility and the obstetric impact in these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno López, Coral</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto Díaz, Aníbal</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Peñalver, Ana Iabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín Sánchez, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peces Rama, Almudena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Carnero, José Eliseo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Machado Linde, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Capel Alemán, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: revisión de la casuística de nuestro centro desde la introducción de la radiología intervencionista en el manejo de la hemorragia postparto hace 6 años. Sujetos y métodos:  estudio retrospectivo entre 2009 y 2014 en el que se recogen los datos de 18 pacientes. Resultados:  la tasa de éxitos en nuestra serie fue del 88,24% y la tasa global de histerectomía tras embolización fue del 11,76%. Conclusiones:  la hemorragia postparto complica el 5-15% de los partos y es la causa aislada más importante de mortalidad materna. Existen protocolos individualizados de manejo según el centro, siendo la radiología intervencionista un tratamiento de segunda línea, alternativo a la histerectomía. En nuestro hospital se ha evidenciado una influencia positiva en la disminución de la histerectomía obstétrica. Las complicaciones, aunque infrecuentes, no son despreciables y se precisan estudios a largo plazo que evalúen su impacto en la fertilidad y gestaciones posteriores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);59(6): 371-376, nov.-dic. 2016. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163992</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Embolización arterial selectiva en la hemorragia postparto. Experiencia en nuestro centro</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22596^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24850^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23248^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6625^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7225^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24848^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6625^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53231^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4695^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24848^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5367^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
