<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165973</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-7546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Drownings associated with swimming pools concerned in judicial cases from Spain, 2000-2015</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Drownings represent one of the main external causes of mortality worldwide. Our objective was to determine the characteristics of the process of drowning and its connection to the safety conditions of collective use swimming pools. Method. A descriptive observational study using data from judicial sources was conducted with setting in Spanish population during the period of 2000-2015. Socio-demographic data, types of facilities, previous activity held by the victim, risk factors and the main cause of the injurious event were investigated. Results. A total of 56 drowning in swimming pools, of which 49 died, were recorded. There were 76.8% males, 71.4% underage and children 5-10 years were the most vulnerable group (32.4%). 37.5% of victims didn&#146;t know how to swim and 60.7% were not alone. Critical events were commonly found in municipal swimming pools (46.4%). Among the most frequently causes of drowning were included: faults in lifeguards&#146; vigilance (19.64%), poor adult supervision for children (17.86%) and the reckless behavior of the victim (14.29%). There were identified risk factors related to deficiencies or absence of passive measures: pool fencing (7.1%), equipment of aquatic rescue (7.1%), visibility of bathing area (3.6%) and unprotected water drain suction (1.8%). Conclusions. The drownings remain an important cause of death in swimming pools for public use. To reduce drowning rates and to avoid a downgrading of safety standards that have a negative effect on preventive aims, the swimming pools code must be rigorously complied as well as to design specific intervention strategies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gámez de la Hoz, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padilla Fortes, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Los ahogamientos representan una de las principales causas de mortalidad externa a nivel mundial. El objetivo fue conocer las características del proceso de ahogamiento y su conexión con las condiciones de seguridad de las piscinas de uso colectivo. Método. Se realizó un estudio observacional descriptivo utilizando datos de fuentes judiciales con emplazamiento en la población española durante 2000-2015. Se investigaron datos sociodemográficos, tipos de instalaciones, actividad previa que realizaba la víctima, factores de riesgo y la causa principal del suceso lesivo. Resultados. Se registraron un total de 56 ahogamientos en piscinas, de los que 49 fallecieron. Un 76.8% eran varones, 71.4% menores de edad y el grupo más vulnerable (32.4%) fue el de 5-10 años. El 37.5% de las víctimas no sabía nadar y el 60.7% no estaban solas. Los sucesos se localizaron más habitualmente en piscinas municipales (46.4%). Entre las causas más frecuentes de ahogamiento destacaron la culpa in vigilando del socorrista (19.64%), deficiente supervisión del niño por un adulto (17.86%) y la conducta imprudente de la víctima (14.29%). Se identificaron factores de riesgo relacionados con deficiencias o ausencia de medidas pasivas: barrera de protección del vaso (7.1%), equipamiento de salvamento acuático (7.1%), visibilidad de zona de baño (3.6%) y toma de aspiración de agua desprotegida (1.8%). Conclusiones. Los ahogamientos continúan siendo una importante causa de mortalidad en piscinas de uso colectivo. Para reducir las tasas de ahogamiento y evitar una devaluación de las condiciones de seguridad que malogren los objetivos preventivos es preciso cumplir rigurosamente las normas reglamentarias de piscinas y diseñar estrategias de intervención específicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. andal. med. deporte;10(3): 106-111, sept. 2017. graf, mapa, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165973</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ahogamientos asociados con piscinas implicados en casos judiciales de España, 2000-2015</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34649</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4395^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4395^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28105^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13932^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25783^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
