<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87995</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Flu vaccination in the elderly</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Seasonal flu is a very serious public health problem in the elderly due to its morbidity and mortality and financial and social costs arising from this. The aim of this review is to describe the magnitude and importance of seasonal flu in this population group, and its prevention by means of vaccination. For this reason, an updated account of the composition of the vaccine, its dosage and administration route, vaccine safety and the evaluation of the immunogenicity and effectiveness of vaccination. There is variation between different countries and official organisations on the age at which flu vaccination must be established in the elderly. New flu vaccination strategies need to be introduced, to further improve flu vaccination cover in Spain(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alcudia Pérez, Florentina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mato Chaín, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mariano Lázaro, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Verdejo Bravo, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En las personas mayores, la gripe estacional es un importantísimo problema de salud pública por su morbimortalidad y los costes económicos y sociales que conlleva. El objetivo de esta revisión es describir la magnitud y la trascendencia de la gripe estacional en este grupo de población y su prevención mediante la vacunación. Para ello se realiza una exposición actualizada sobre la composición de la vacuna, su pauta y vía de administración, la seguridad vacunal y la evaluación de la inmunogenicidad y efectividad de la vacunación. Entre los diferentes países y organismos oficiales existe variabilidad en las recomendaciones sobre la edad a partir de la cual se debe establecer la vacunación antigripal en las personas mayores. Para mejorar la cobertura vacunal frente a la gripe en España es necesario implantar nuevas estrategias de vacunación antigripal(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);46(2): 89-95, mar.-abr.2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87995</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vacunación antigripal en personas mayores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23109^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23109^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16902^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23109^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28485^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23109^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28485^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23109^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23109^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28485^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23123^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23123^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
